<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 25,
<date when="1919-06-18">June 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Matter of Foreign Languages in Polish Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 25,
<date when="1919-06-18">June 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE MATTER OF FOREIGN LANGUAGES IN POLISH SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A law project is to be found in the legislature of the state of Illinois, aiming to exclude foreign languages from the parochial schools. Whereas this project was to come under deliberation during the past week, the Polish parishes, organizations, and societies sent out a protest against it. The general secretary, Mr. Ig. Wroblewski, has sent a telegram in the name of the Union from the State of Illinois to D. E. Shanahan, which reads as follows:</p>
   <p>To David E. Shanahan</p>
   <p>Speaker of House of Representatives</p>
   <p>Springfield, Illinois</p>
   <p>Honorable and Dear Sir: Today the House of Representatives is going to act upon the bill which will ultimately prevent the teaching of foreign languages in the elementary schools of this state. You will understand that religion is taught best in the mother language; therefore, any <pb facs="5423968_2_0350.jpg" n="2"/>attempt as the above is also an attempt against religion, which is the only safeguard against bolshevism. We want our children to know the English language well and we are for thorough instruction in that language, but the law, as proposed, will prevent the teaching of religion in the foreign language. This is un-American and contrary to the spirit of Washington and Lincoln. Oppression is a Prussian method and leads to discontent and disloyalty. For the above reasons, on behalf of 40,000 Poles belonging to our organization in this state, we ask you, Honorable and dear Sir, to speak and work against the bill and thus serve liberty.</p>
   <p>The Polish Roman-Catholic Union of America.</p>
   <p>By Ignacy Wroblewski, Secretary-General.</p>
   <p>A second telegram with the same contents was sent to Representative Joseph Petlak.</p>
   <p>Mr. D. E. Shanahan answered:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0351.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Springfield, Illinois</p>
   <p>June 11, 1919</p>
   <p>Mr. Ignacy Wroblewski, Secretary-General</p>
   <p>The Polish Roman-Catholic Union of America</p>
   <p>984 Milwaukee Avenue</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>Dear Sir: I am in receipt of your telegram of recent date and contents noted.</p>
   <p>I have objected on three different occasions to Senate Bill No. 10 being advanced. It is now on the calendar for second reading and I doubt if it will get a third reading.</p>
   <p>Thanking you for the same, I am</p>
   <p>Very truly,</p>
   <p>David E. Shanahan, Speaker.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0352.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>An answer has reached us also from Mr. Petlak, who informs that a second law project has been introduced in a modified form. We also found out that the second project, allowing lectures in foreign languages in parochial schools has already passed, by which the first loses the right of being. We judge, therefore, that the present danger has been forestalled.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
