<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIV, No. 25,
<date when="1920-06-23">June 23, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Defender of the Jews</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0891</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0891.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIV, No. 25,
<date when="1920-06-23">June 23, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">DEFENDER OF THE JEWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Arthur Brisbane, the journalistic clown who writes for Hearst's publications, defends the Jews against the alleged slanders in the article published by the Chicago Sunday Examiner. This was on account of an article that appeared in Ford's Weekly, in which the editor of that paper describes the Jews as parasites, reaping profits from other peoples' hard labor. We did not read the article which appeared in the Ford's Weekly, but referring to Mr. Brisbane's reply, we came to the conclusion that the Ford's article must contain must truth. The old proverb says that "Truth hurts." Evidently, in this particular case, the truth about the Jews did hurt the Jewish journalists, and especially Mr. Brisbane.</p>
   <p>The defender of the Jews rails at Mr. Ford very bitterly in the beginning of his article, and then he describes all great Jewish characters from the beginning of the world up to the present time, and shouts: "Look and see what the world owes to the Jews! They are making progress <pb facs="5423968_2_0892.jpg" n="2"/>in the world; they have abolished the throne of the tsars; they are remaking Russia, keep up her government, build railroads; they make the whole world tremble, therefore they are not cowards, not lazy. On the contrary, they constitute a chosen people, sent for the purpose of remaking the world.</p>
   <p>The Rothschilds built the railroads in France and Austria. Baron de Hirsch has established the railroad system in the Balkans. The Bischoffheims have built the railroads in Belgium, Mr. Pereires built the railroad in Southern Russia and Northern France, the German railroad system was kept up by  Meichreiders Bank. Almost all the cotton mills and the tailor shops in the United States are in the hands of the Jews.</p>
   <p>Mr. Trotsky (Braunstein) is the dictator of Russia, and Mr. Brisbane continues to point out the great Jews.</p>
   <p>It seems that in Trotsky, Mr. Brisbane found a great Jewish hero.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0893.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Trotsky is a Jew, every inch of him, and his heroism depends on the ability of skinning the poor Russian peasants.</p>
   <p>There is no question that there are noble individuals among the Jews, but the number is very small. We do not deny that the Jews possess business ability, that they are clever, but their cleverness depends in the biggest part on impudence and dishonesty. The Jew gets rich because he knows how to take an advantage of somebody else's labor. It is true that the Jews financed the European railroad systems, but the real work of constructing them was accomplished by the Christians. In almost every large enterprise we see a Christian idea but a Jewish capital. Did Trotsky or Lenin create any new social system or philosophy? No! Their whole wisdom is based on making money. They are not giving anything to the workers. They say the improved Russia; on the contrary, they tore down what the ages had built. They are the biggest criminals, placing bombs under the structure of civilization. Yet, such a journalistic clown as Mr. Brisbane dares to present them as heroes. There is <pb facs="5423968_2_0894.jpg" n="4"/>something wrong in America when the press points out Trotsky and Lenin as an example. However, Mr. Brisbane told a parcel of truth about the Jews when he said that "The Jews, numbering a small percentage of the earth's population, possess by conquest, enterprise, industry and intelligence, 50% of the world's commercial success," and "Jews and the printing press combined, have done a great deal to put the monarchs out of date. Jews have been leaders always in courageous radical thought."</p>
   <p>There is no doubt that 50% of the world's commerce is in the hands of the Jews, but they did not acquire it through "intelligence," as Mr. Brisbane maintains, but by impudence and exploitation.</p>
   <p>The second statement made by Mr. Brisbane can not be changed for it is true that the Jews, through their press, are abolishing thrones, destroying orders, demoralizing nations, depriving them of their faith and influencing radicals to murder. We give credit to Mr. Ford for telling the truth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
