<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-24">Nov. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Accidents on the Railroads</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-24">Nov. 24, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">ACCIDENTS ON THE RAILROADS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Interstate Commerce Commission has compiled a report of railroad accidents which occurred during the fiscal year that ended June 30. According to the Commission's statistics, 356 passengers were killed, of which number the railroads admit responsibility for the death of only 96. The rest were responsible for their own death--at least that is what the police and the courts have decided. The number of accidents this year was smaller than in previous years--especially last year, when 421 passengers were killed on the railroads.</p>
   <p>Of railroad employees, 3,602 were killed this year. The companies answer for the deaths of 1,201 of these people, while 2,401 are said to have been responsible for their own death. It is worth noting that most of the employees were killed by locomotives in the railroad yards, and at <pb facs="5423968_2_1425.jpg" n="2"/>crossings where there were no guards and no signals; nevertheless, it was not the greedy companies, but the unfortunate employees of the railroad Moloch who were blamed.</p>
   <p>In addition to the railroad employees and passengers, 5,284 pedestrians were killed at railroad crossings or in crossing the tracks in cities. This figure indicates just how much concerned the railroad companies are about the lives of human beings, who are exposed to danger because of the greediness of the railroad owners. There are no watchmen at the crossings, no gates which would block the crossing when a train is approaching. The tracks are laid along streets which are always crowded with people, and the trains speed by, crushing pedestrians under their wheels. That the companies in their greed are not concerned about the lives of employees, passengers, and pedestrians, is easy to understand; but that the law is blind to this destruction of human beings, and that it does not force the railroad trusts to install safety devices, is not easy to understand or to accept without indignation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
