<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-19">May 19, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A Voice from Saint Hedwig Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-19">May 19, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A VOICE FROM SAINT HEDWIG PARISH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have been requested to publish the following correspondence:</p>
   <p>"Being informed from reliable sources that my name has been libeled by members of the independent sect known by the sacrilegiously adopted name of "All Saints Parish" in Chicago--who claim that I had intentions to join this schism and had made a contribution of one hundred dollars, but that the officers of the sect had refused to accept me--I am forced to publicly and definitely announce that I was opposed to this independent schism from the very beginning and fought it in every possible manner.</p>
   <p>"I have endeavored to explain to those poor deluded people not to believe those who not only have discarded all honor and sold their own souls to the devil, but are also trying to dishonor all Poles in the eyes of other peoples.</p>
   <p>"I have been living in Saint Hedwig Parish for over ten years, and am well known <pb facs="5423968_2_1137.jpg" n="2"/>to all the Poles on the Northwest Side.</p>
   <p>"I am sorry to see what is happening there, and would never lift a hand to help such a cause. Still greater is my sorrow at the scandalous gossip which is being spread by certain maddened people.</p>
   <p>"I therefore wish to announce publicly once again that I have never talked to the leaders of this independent sect or to any of its followers or that I ever wanted to join them. I wish to announce, that I have always been and will remain faithful to the teachings of Jesus Christ and will never renounce my solidarity with the true Roman Catholic Church. I therefore warn everybody not to libel my name, because otherwise I will demand justice and satisfaction in the courts.</p>
   <p>"It is truly a shame that our neighborhood, which had a beautiful future before it, is now falling into such disrepute.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1138.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"People! Open your eyes and don't permit yourselves to be fooled any more....You will feel better and others will not laugh at the name "Pole" any more.</p>
   <p>Stanislaus Marcinkowski,</p>
   <p>1049 North Robey Street."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
