<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-10-15">Oct. 15, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Labor Favors Honest Temperance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0428</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0428.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-10-15">Oct. 15, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">LABOR FAVORS HONEST TEMPERANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In view of the fatal consequences of prohibition, and in an effort to end this illusion, the American Federation of Labor, at their convention in Los Angeles, passed a resolution demanding, of Congress, the modification of the prohibition law, in such a manner, as to permit the manufacture and sale of beer. Modification of this obnoxious law is receiving the full support of labor organizations. This law has been forced upon the people, without their consent, by protestant bigots and bootleggers under the disguise of patriotism.</p>
   <p>This resolution of the American Federation of Labor, is making many a legislator feel uneasy. Congressmen, who are in reality wet but politically dry and who are serving the Anti-Saloon League, cannot afford to disregard the demands of so large an organization. To the present time, these law makers have faithfully served this league. But the result of the votes cast on election day will ascertain their real standing in the eyes of their constituents. At the present time, they refuse to declare their attitude, whether dry or wet.</p>
   <p>Labor will be stubbornly opposed by the Anti-Saloon League; the league of moonshiners, smugglers, and peddlers of poison whiskey. Let us hope that the time will come, when the fulfillment of Labor'ssincere demands will be realized, and that our government will free itself of the flag waving bigots.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
