<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-20">Mar. 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Window Display Contest</title><title level="a" type="sub">Cieslak-Miedzianowski Gets First Prize; "Progress" Gets Second</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1490</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1490.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1917-03-20">Mar. 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">WINDOW DISPLAY CONTEST</title><title level="a" type="sub">Cieslak-Miedzianowski Gets First Prize; "Progress" Gets Second</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ekonomia (Economy), official organ of the Polish-American Businessmen's Association, edited by Mr. S. Jakel, sponsored a window display contest among Polish businessmen and offered two prizes, of ten and five dollars each, to those trimming their windows in the most practical and attractive manner.</p>
   <p>Four Polish firms entered the contest, namely: "The Progress," men's haberdashery owned by Ulanowski and Sobiecki; Cieslak-Miedzianowski, men's haberdashery; George Plucinski, men's haberdashery; and M. Idzikowski's, clothing store. All are located on Milwaukee Avenue.</p>
   <p>The judges were Mr. S. Koziolek, an expert on window trimming engaged by the firm of Klee Brothers, and representatives of the Polish press, namely:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1491.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. H. Lokanski, editor of Dziennik Narodowy; Mr. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Papara, editor of Dziennik Chicagoski; and J. Przyprawa, editor of Dziennik Zwiazkowy. The judges inspected the displays yesterday as a group and individually and met at the Polish Press Club in order to announce their decision and present the awards.</p>
   <p>The first prize was unanimously awarded to the firm of Cieslak-<gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>iedzianowski, 1145 <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>ilwaukee Avenue, which had the most artistic and attractive display. The second prize was also unanimously awarded to "The Progress," 1165 <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>ilwaukee, which had the most businesslike and practical display.</p>
   <p>Everyone had the highest praise for Mr. George Plucinski's window display, and had it not been that the illumination was deficient, this store might have won the first prize.</p>
   <p>Mr. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Idzikowski's window display was considered excellent and the best in St. John Cantius Parish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1492.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Everyone gathered at the Press Club, that is, the representatives of these stores and the editor of the official organ of the Polish-American Businessmen's Association, was satisfied with the decision of the judges.</p>
   <p>That contests of this sort can have a very beneficial effect on our merchants is shown by the fact that other businessmen, upon seeing the displays of the of the contestants, began at once to change their displays. Businessmen of other nationalities followed the example in an effort to attract the Poles. The Poles, however, should patronize only their own stores, because nowadays they can obtain all their needs at Polish stores, where they will no doubt get better and more courteous service. "Patronize your own stores" is a slogan to which everyone should adhere.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
