<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IV, No. 13,
<date when="1900-03-28">March 28, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Saloons, Sports, and the Pleasures of Our Youth</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0512</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0512.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IV, No. 13,
<date when="1900-03-28">March 28, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE SALOONS, SPORTS, AND THE PLEASURES OF OUR YOUTH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whoever watches intelligently the physical development of our youth must admit that the children born and reared here are on a much lower level physically than the children raised in "the old country."</p>
   <p>Our young people lack the sturdiness and hardiness of youth in "the old country" and they show neither the strength of body nor the happy expressions on their faces denoting the peace of their conscience.</p>
   <p>Your young people here show certain slowness, drowsiness, lack of energy, and show a considerable "doze" of indifference toward social matters. They also lack that freedom and hardihood of spirit that one finds only in those who stay away from sources of corruption and depravity.</p>
   <p>This distressing state of health of our youth is caused by the conditions of life, sports, and the destroying of even the strongest bodies by pleasures that our youth is given to.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0513.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The excessive use of alcohol and the long hours wasted in the saloons, degenerate a great part of our young people physically and morally. Our children drink too much, chew, and "have a good time" too often. They drink in saloons, at home, and in the homes of their friends and acquaintances.</p>
   <p>Some one may say that the young people of German or Irish descent drink also and it doesn't hurt them in their work nor prevent them from developing into practical people. The Polish writer, Sienkiewicz, gives a correct answer to this question - If a Slav tries to imitate a German in his drinking habits he will drink himself to death.</p>
   <p>We didn't get rid of our inclination for drinking and this is the reason that such a small percentage of our young acquire education even though there are so many opportunities here for education as in no other country in the world.</p>
   <p>Even moderate drinking dulls the critical faculties of man; weakens the memory and slows down all mental processes.</p>
   <p>The environment of our young people, the great number of the dens of <pb facs="5423968_2_0514.jpg" n="3"/>corruption in Polish neighborhoods are the cause that such a notable percentage of our youth lose their chastity between the ages of 14-18 years.</p>
   <p>It is extremely painful and detrimental to our community that a 25 year old boy is already unfit for marriage and if he does get married demands absolute chastity from his wife while he himself spends nights in saloons or in houses of disrepute. Such a life brings only surfeit and satiety and very often disease. Only the priests are able to stop this terrible epidemic by elevating the youth to higher ideals and making them stronger to resist and fight temptations.</p>
   <p>We are not degenerating numerically but we are disintegrating physically and morally and it will not help us any "if the flower of these millions," the children, are so effeminate that they are not fit for physical or mental labor. Only in healthy bodies are there healthy minds. For the nation to be strong, courageous, and great, the people must be temperate and morally strong. It is the parents' sacred duty to see that their children remain <pb facs="5423968_2_0515.jpg" n="4"/>chaste the longest time possible and abstain from alcoholic beverages.</p>
   <p>The assertion that our young people are indifferent and listless is based on their lack of interest in joining different groups or organizations. In case they are members of some organized group, their activity is generally limited to paying their monthly dues and occasionally showing themselves on the scene with some lecture or a poetical recitation.</p>
   <p>As a further proof of their indifference is the discontinuance of "The Alliance of Polish Youth," organized with so much pomp and shouting. Their "Alliance of Falcons" is also in the state of disintegration. This sad state of affairs is even more so because, being free to engage in any social work, our young people do not even realize that failing to perform their most sacred duty toward the country is a crime they so thoughtlessly commit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
