<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 2,
<date when="1913-01-08">January 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Women's Section. Fate of a Woman Drunkard.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0453</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0453.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 2,
<date when="1913-01-08">January 8, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH WOMEN'S SECTION. FATE OF A WOMAN DRUNKARD.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In one of the larger Polish colonies a Polish woman, with a few children, would frequently get drunk. The woman had been arrested several times for excessive use of alcohol; the sheriff even prohibited the saloon keepers to sell whiskey to this woman.</p>
   <p>But the saloon keepers have whiskey for sale, not for display, so the woman purchased the liquor without any objection.</p>
   <p>Once police officers broke into her house and witnessed this sad picture: The woman was unconscious, lying on the floor, and her three children, ages four, five, and six years, partially without clothing, running around in the house and trying to keep themselves warm, had built a fire on the floor.</p>
   <p>This picture touched the hearts of the police officers even though they are used to different dramatic episodes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0454.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Polish people in this country abuse themselves beyond limit - men are drunkards, women are drunkards, and innocent children looking at this get used to bad habits.</p>
   <p>Drunkards are not of any use to society but this type of people are raising the future murderers and bandits who end their lives in the prisons.</p>
   <p>Let us break the companionship with liquor, lock our doors and nor permit liquor in our homes because whiskey is the ruin of them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
