<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-10">Dec. 10, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The Germans Feel Offended</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1014</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1014.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I C (German)</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-10">Dec. 10, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMANS FEEL OFFENDED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish newspaper Dziennik Zwiazkowy wrote about the impression created upon the Germans residing in New York when they heard that the Chicago Board of Education was seriously contemplating the introduction of the Polish language in the high schools and was manifesting a definite desire to eliminate the German language from the public grammar schools. The readers will probably recall that referring to this matter New York's German newspaper Staats-Zeitung spoke rather unfavorably of German-Americans and charged them with lack of political influence. It also praised the activity of the Poles, who were able to develop their influence. The German newspaper at the same time referred to the Polish National Alliance and mentioned the celebration conducted at Washington through the efforts of the Alliance.</p>
   <p>In a moderate and calm tone the New York newspaper stated that although the success of Poles in Chicago hurts the Germans residing in New York, nevertheless they, as civilized people and citizens of a free nation, know how to <pb facs="5423968_2_1015.jpg" n="2"/>maintain a certain measure of restraint in the expression of their feelings.</p>
   <p>The same cannot be said, however, of Germans of the West, whose official organ is the St. Paul Volkszeitung. Judging from an article of this newspaper, which was kindly forwarded to the Dziennik Zwiezkowy by a member of the Polish National Alliance, we can see that this German newspaper suffers from an attack of some bad malady. It conducts itself in a purely fanatical manner toward the Poles.</p>
   <p>The St. Paul Volkszeitung is greatly perturbed over the news that the Polish language will be taught in the high schools of Chicago. In its uncontrolled anger, the Volkszeitung forgets that it is not permissible for a newspaper to divorce itself completely from truth, even in a political battle. After all, it should be prepared to expect that some more enlightened reader will notice the falsehood and will lose his faith in the paper.</p>
   <p>The Volkszeitung attempts to prove that the Polish language has no right to be included in the list of subjects to be taught at schools. Why?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1016.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Because, as the Volkszietung explains, it is a "dead language", because Poland, as a nation has not existed for more than a century. A wonderful argument is it not? Suppose Germany found herself suddenly at war, and attacked by Russia on one side and France on the other, would the German language suddenly become "dead" in the eyes of the St. Paul Volkszeitung? And so, according to you German gentlemen, a language which is spoken by twenty-five million people is dead today because these people do not have their country. Tomorrow, when they regain it, it will become alive; later, if they lose the country again, will the language also die again, and later again become alive, and so forth, ad infinitum?</p>
   <p>In the year 1806, when Napoleon sat in a castle in Berlin and held the whole of Prussia in his hand and was pondering whether to erase it from the list of nations or merely to slice off a large part of it the German language in Prussia, according to your theory, was dead. At that time there really was no Prussia; there were only people speaking German and reading the masterpieces of Goethe and Schiller.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1017.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>How is it possible to present such absurdities to the reader simply because of a political indifference toward a nation which in addition has done the Germans no harm, if one is to omit the almost forgotten Grunwald incident.</p>
   <p>[Translator's Note: The Battle at Grunwald, between the Polish and the Teutonic forces, in 1410, was most significant in the annals of history. The greatly superior forces of the Germans were decisively defeated by the smaller army of Poland. This defeat marked the end of the German drive toward the East.]</p>
   <p>The second argument of the Volkszeitung is even more silly than the first. The Polish language, says the editor of this newspaper, has no value, because it possesses no literature to which anyone could refer.</p>
   <p>So Poland has no literature? Will these gentlemen inform us from what language the works of Sienkiewicz and many others are translated into German and sold in the bookstores of Berlin? At the time of Sicnkiowicz the Germans were <pb facs="5423968_2_1018.jpg" n="5"/>buying more translations of Polish authors than the Poles were buying of German authors. German statistics--not the political type, but the honest, educational kind--show that Polish literature today occupies fourth place, after English, French, and German--that is, fourth place in regard to quantity, the number of works published in a given language. But if it were judged to quality, and if the decision were given by some impartial committee that knows all four languages, who knows if today Polish literature would not be giver second place, after the French, or even first place?</p>
   <p>In its actual, or perhaps in its pretended, ignorance, the German newspaper claims that the Polish language today is only a dialect of illiterate peasants in territories of former Poland.</p>
   <p>Naturally, the Polish language is spoken predominantly by farmers, because they compose nearly the whole of the Polish nation. Likewise the German language is spoken predominantly by farmers. The Volkszeitung, however, should know that the professors at the universities of Lwow and Cracow teach in the <pb facs="5423968_2_1019.jpg" n="6"/>Polish language as the professors in Berlin and Lipsk teach in the German language.</p>
   <p>But then, why talk with people who, in their bitter bigotry, prattle of impossible things? The German newspaper is right in one thing--that the present respect of Americans for the Polish language is due to the increasing political influence of the Poles.</p>
   <p>This influence, however, should not be exaggerated. It should not be maintained that it would be possible to force as worthless language into public schools merely by exerting political influence. That is the impression our enemies want to create. The main basis of the success of the Polish language in this campaign is its own value--its really great and rich literature, about which even Americans know something.</p>
   <p>But this value alone would not have gained a proper place for it if the American Poles had not begun to become a power, and a rather important power at that, in the political life of the United States. This fact should not be <pb facs="5423968_2_1020.jpg" n="7"/>kept a secret, it should not be denied. An American respects only strength and, if one wishes to command his respect, it is necessary to show him that there is a power. In this regard all friends and enemies of our people are correct when they point to the existence, growth, development, and activity of the Polish National Alliance, and manifestations and proofs of this power.</p>
   <p>But that strength is noble which does not harm another being, and yet can serve as an example for others to follow. Let the Americans learn that it is possible to become a good citizen of this country, care for its interests, serve it by one's work, and learn the language of the country, and yet not forget what every respectable man owes his motherland. Let them learn this, that a Polish citizen of the United States, speaking and writing English, not only does not renounce his native language, but, on the contrary, wishes to maintain it on an honorable level in schools. He will use all the resources of his strength to fulfill his wish. Such a lesson is beneficial to everyone.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
