<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-09">Jan. 9, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">To All the Polish Union Locals, Societies, and Organizations in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1619</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1619.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-09">Jan. 9, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">TO ALL THE POLISH UNION LOCALS, SOCIETIES, AND ORGANIZATIONS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Brothers and Sisters:</p>
   <p>A strike has been in existence since April 1, 1927 in the States of Pennsylvania, Ohio, and West Virginia. The organized coal miners did not want to accept the proposal reached by the mine owners which was another cut of the prevailing low wage scale. They demanded the continuation of the wage level as of April 1, 1927. The owners shut down all union mines. This resulted in throwing out of work hundreds of thousands of miners, depriving their families of a means of existence. The ten months of idleness has thrown thousands of families into a virtual state of poverty. This condition became more aggravated when the mining companies began vacating company-owned homes of the strikers. Hundreds of families are now living in makeshift wooden homes erected by the union. Sickness, due to malnutrition and inclement weather, is beginning to take effect on the miners and their families.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1620.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In Colorado, where workers have also received such low wages that they could not exist on them, a decision was reached to strike for higher wages. They also joined the <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>astern States in the strike. Among the miners in Colorado, Pennsylvania, West Virginia, and Ohio are found thousands of Polish people--our brothers. Already in many cities committees have been organized, which promote contributions and offer aid to the miners and their families. In Chicago, there are hundreds of societies and organizations and thousands of Poles. It is our duty to get together and decide upon a general plan of assistance to those miners and their families in dire need.</p>
   <p>This has been taken under full consideration by the Polish Machinists' Union, Warsaw Local 830, which is affiliated with the American Federation of Labor. According to a motion made in the meeting of January 4, it was decided to make an announcement in the Polish press, and call all the delegates of the various Polish organizations together at a meeting which is to be held January 19, at 8 P.M. in Stankiewicz's hall, corner of Noble and Emma Streets.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1621.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The societies and organizations which will not convene before this date can send their own officers instead of appointed delegates.</p>
   <p>Brothers and Sisters, let us fulfill our duty as citizens and attend this general meeting.</p>
   <p>Signed: Thaddeus Kotlowski, Secretary of Polish Machinists' Union, <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>arsaw Local 2830 of the International Association of Machinists.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
