<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-06-27">June 27, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Blessing of the Cornerstone at Saint Adelbert's School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0285</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0285.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-06-27">June 27, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">BLESSING OF THE CORNERSTONE AT SAINT ADELBERT'S SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The rainy spell which has been oppressing Chicago for some time threatened the failure of this ceremony, which took place yesterday as scheduled. Despite the rain, the ceremony was performed with considerable solemnity, with the extensive participation of the public and of various societies.</p>
   <p>Many of the venerable churchmen were also present in spite of the fact that it was Sunday. Thus respect and a good colleague's friendship was manifested toward the local pastor, Reverend John Radziejewski. The following priests were present: Reverend Vincent Barzynski; Reverend Domagalski; Neopresbyter Byrgier; George Kolesinski; pastor of the Lithuanian Church at Bridgeport; Joseph Malecki, assistant at St. Josephat's church; Paul Szulerecki; Adolph Nowicki; Theophilus Malkowski; and Deacon Stephen Nowakowski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0286.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A copper container, which was to be inserted into the cornerstone, was filled with several pieces of money dated from 1892, two editions of Wiara i Ojczyzna (Faith And The Fatherland), and one copy each of Dziennik Chicagoski, Gazeta Katolicka (The Catholic Gazette), and Dnia Swietego (The Holy Day), plus the Act of Institution of the school, and the names of the President of the United States, Harrison, and the Mayor of Chicago, Washburn.</p>
   <p>Members of the societies, garbed in many cases, in beautiful Polish uniforms, and the cadets of St. Stanislaus Kostka parish, twice circled St. Adelbert's Church to the accompaniment of music.</p>
   <p>The young ladies' sodality, dressed in white, congregated at this magnificent church and left with the venerable churchmen, led by the processional crucifix, for the newly constructed school. Here, Reverend V. Barzynski performed the ostentatious dedicating ceremony, following which he sang, in the company of <pb facs="5423968_2_0287.jpg" n="3"/>the other Reverend Fathers, the "Litany To All Saints," as a reminder that this school should be not only an edifice for education but that it should also develop the virtues leading to the sanctity of life which guarantees the heavenly crown. After the blessing of the cornerstone and the insertion of the container into it, the faithful, accompanied by the Reverend Fathers, returned to the church, which was filled to capacity.</p>
   <p>Reverend Domagalski rendered a splendid patriotic and religious oration appropriate to the ceremony. In it he aroused the religious and patriotic zeal of the Polish people in America, who, with a sincere heart and hard-earned money, erect here such magnificent Polish schools and churches, with a liberality which rivals that of the aristocrats and the kings in our fatherland and in the rest of Europe. Reverend Domagalski took this as proof that we are a people that has always stood in defense of the holy Catholic religion--that loves this religion and desires to safeguard its existence in America, for <pb facs="5423968_2_0288.jpg" n="4"/>which reasons the hearts of our brethren in Europe become elated when they hear of our Catholic and Polish zeal.</p>
   <p>A school, [the speaker then pointed out,] is a basic part of a good upbringing, and he who possesses an education holds the future in his hand. However, though it is education which makes one wise, an education will be of no avail to a corrupted heart. Education is useless without religion. The venerable speaker touched upon the history of other nations to show that the decline of religion in schools, and, hence, in the nation as well, had brought a horrible revolution upon France, and had led Poland to a fall. Finally, he talked about the duties of motherhood, about the tasks of the school, about the educational function of the priests, and about the necessity of uniting the school with the church. He advised his hearers to be cautious of socialistic conspiracies, and the poison spread by some of the supposedly liberal but, in reality, atheistic Polish writings in America. He spoke about basing Polish patriotism on the Catholic religion and on the Polish school. Finally, he thanked the parishioners for their generous contributions to the school, and those present for participating so actively in the day's festivities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0289.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>After this magnificent homily, which deeply touched all those present, a blessing with the Most Holy Sacrament was imparted to those congregated, several verses of that beautiful song "Nie Opuszczaj Nas" (Do Not Forsake Us) were rendered, and the pious parishioners left for their respective homes, with divine peace in their hearts and with joyful hope that their children would soon have a beautiful and comfortable school, where, under the zealous care of the Reverend Father Pastor, the blessings of a Polish Catholic education would be showered upon them, as the speaker had so impressively explained.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
