<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-09">Jan. 9, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">What Our Citizens Think of the Attacks by Dziennik Polski on St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1151</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1151.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-09">Jan. 9, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT OUR CITIZENS THINK OF THE ATTACKS BY DZIENNIK POLSKI ON ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA PARISH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Editor: It is impossible to listen any longer to the babblings and mad attacks on the St. Stanislaus Kostka Parish which appear daily in the Polish News, presumably Polish but actually published by Jews and unbelievers.</p>
   <p>These troublesome gentlemen must have their noses rubbed once....and well. I am asking you, therefore, to please publish my letter in your paper.</p>
   <p>The question I am asking everyone is: What business have such dregs of humanity with parochial reports? What good have they ever done for the parish? Did any one of them ever contribute one penny to the St. Stanislaus Kostka Church?</p>
   <p>Most likely they did not! And if this is a fact, then my dear sirs, do not <pb facs="5423968_2_1152.jpg" n="2"/>stick your noses where you have not contributed a penny or you may get them rubbed the wrong way.</p>
   <p>I am a simple person, but I can see what your aim is: you want to confuse the people of good will and muddle up the water in order to catch the fat fish. But you will not succeed. We will do without you and your wisecracks. You claim that you are Poles, yet you wish to destroy the Polish churches, exterminate the Polish priests, and step on that which is dearest and most holy to us. You are wolves in sheep's clothing. Your claws are all too evident. In every sentence you say, in spite of your assertion that you are acting in good faith, your hate and hostility to everything that is Polish and Catholic is so plain that you cannot fool even the feeble-minded.</p>
   <p>You are worse than the Jews. At least we know they are enemies of Christ, but you seemingly pray at the foot of a statue while the devil is hidden under your skin....</p>
   <p>Your mouth is full of honeyed words, but in these words there is poison. You <pb facs="5423968_2_1153.jpg" n="3"/>want to lead our people to anarchy and infernal insanity while taking advantage of them. We got along without you before....we will do without you now.</p>
   <p>Every day you repeat: "Teach Polish to the children," but this is your most monstrous lie. Of what use is the Polish tongue to them while you are trying to destroy everything that is Polish and Catholic? Why, it would be much simpler for you to advise teaching them the Russian tongue--you would then be believed!</p>
   <p>It would be better if you, yourselves, would study Polish for even the children laugh at your miserable writings, not to mention the older folks.</p>
   <p>But it is time I closed this letter.</p>
   <p>In the name of common sense and justice I appeal to all my Polish countrymen and to all people of good will not to read a paper so vile as Dziennik Polski (Polish News). After all, of what good is it to anybody? A person gets <pb facs="5423968_2_1154.jpg" n="4"/>smeared by it.....Perhaps it will convince a person who is inexperienced and confuse him so that he will not be able to tell the difference between good and bad--and then they will laugh at him as at the very devil himself, Oh, yes! I sincerely urge my fellow brethren: guard yourselves from this evil, and you can be sure of yourselves.....There is a Polish saying that "One on guard is guarded by God himself."</p>
   <p>These are my sincere wishes to my fellow Catholics and Poles.</p>
   <p>Your brother,</p>
   <p>Albert Melin</p>
   <p>658 Dickson Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
