<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XII, No. 50,
<date when="1918-12-12">December 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Anti-Polish Propaganda by the Jews</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0963</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0963.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XII, No. 50,
<date when="1918-12-12">December 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Anti-Polish Propaganda by the Jews</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jews have always been traitors of the Polish nation - either open or secret enemies of Poland. In our opinion it is not necessary to repeat all the falsehoods and calumnies that have been published in the American press controlled by the Jewish interests.</p>
   <p>Our countrymen who have any connection with the editors of American newspapers should not remain silent spectators to the anti-Polish campaign of intrigues, started in the Jewish press by our baptized or unbaptized "bosom" friends.</p>
   <p>It is necessary to take advantage of every opportunity in order to insure ourselves a fair presentation of the Polish-Jewish problem.</p>
   <p>We will also assist in this work and there will appear a long article in one of the leading American magazines, written in English, and giving a very accurate account of the Jewish problem in Poland, taken from historical statistics.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0964.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Living among the Americans and having connections with the editors of American newspapers, Poles, who are able to write English, should, in every locality, correct all false accusations and statements appearing in any newspaper, creating at the same time a contra-agitation in the American press.</p>
   <p>The anti-Polish propaganda in America was started more than three years ago by J. Brandes, who was the initiator of the anti-Polish propaganda in Denmark. It was continued by one Dr. S. Lewin and still later by a number of our "friends."</p>
   <p>And now, the closer the realization of our hopes, the stronger is the Jewish harmful action on many fronts. So, as soon as possible we must counteract this low intrigue and frustrate the work taken up by those who openly claim to be our friends and in reality are our worst enemies at heart, who, by adopting our Polish names, succeed in getting into the very midst of our society in order to exploit us shamefully and later do us harm.</p>
   <p>These remarks have been written because of the many facts which more than prove to us the wretched double game played by the Jews, whose low agitation <pb facs="5423968_2_0965.jpg" n="3"/>should not be under-estimated, if we do not wish to feel sorry for it when it is too late.</p>
   <p>We do not know of any Pole who would thrust himself into Jewish society; we do not know of any Pole who would play any role among the Jews. On the other hand there are in our national organizations Jews who hold high offices as leaders. What shall we call this? Is it naivete or a crime?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
