<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-05">July 5, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[Views on Organizing a Polish Printers' Union]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1593</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1593.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-05">July 5, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">[VIEWS ON ORGANIZING A POLISH PRINTERS' UNION]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The renewed idea of Messrs. Zagorski and Reichel for organizing a printers' union, furnished us with several observations. We are profiting by the hospitality of the Dziennik; we intend to become acquainted with the honorable colleagues of the trade. It is undeniable that the lack of a printers' union is being acutely felt by us. True, this question was not as yet discussed in the press as having any special importance, interesting only a small group of readers. This was discussed several times previously, however, in a private capacity. At his time, the author of this article had endeavored to form such a union; there were several followers, but when it came to the proper organization, so many obstructions were met that the idea had to be dropped.</p>
   <p>We believe that at present, in proportion to the enlargement of the number of the Polish printing establishments, this notion has a better possibility of realization, but not in the form of a union of the American type, but in the form of a Society of Polish Printers, whose aims would be mutual education in <pb facs="5423968_2_1594.jpg" n="2"/>the trade, fraternal aid in the event of illness, and some type of assistance to the family in the event of death of a member.</p>
   <p>A union similar to the ones Americans or Germans have, would not last long in our Polish communities because of many very important reasons. In the first place, we have an absolutely too small number of qualified compositors and pressmen; next, at least two-thirds of the employees in the Polish printing concerns are minors who are dependent upon the will of their parents or guardians; even if they were self-willed, it would be considered naive to allow them to institute laws which would obligate the qualified workers of many years of practice.</p>
   <p>We are not, however, in need of matured students who, through several months of employment in the printing shops, have learned a bit about the composition of the text for the press, but have no idea about any other type of work. These also consider themselves as compositors and demand the same pay as those who thoroughly understand their trade.</p>
   <p>It is known that the American unions have as their main purpose the possible <pb facs="5423968_2_1595.jpg" n="3"/>maintenance of a high [wage] scale for work performed and only after this are they concerned with sick benefits and aid during unemployment.</p>
   <p>We are also aware of this, that before these unions accept a member into their fold, they first examine and test his trade qualifications. On the basis of such an examination they then have the right to demand proper pay from the employer, equally concerning all the members. But how many could we find among our printers who could (pass) a similar examination? I doubt if there would be 50% of them. Even if so many were found it still would be at least 20% too few for our union to organize in a similar manner.</p>
   <p>As long as we have no capable and qualified workers, it is impossible to think of a union based on the English pattern, because every employer can justly say: "Give me capable people whom I can use in every type of work, then I will pay them the price demanded by you." On the other hand, again, no qualified compositor will disagree in receiving the same remuneration as the one who works for a duration of only a few months.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1596.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This, however, does not mean that we should abandon a printer's union; on the contrary, seeing such sad conditions, we should make every effort to correct them. This could be accomplished to a greater extent by the formation of a union that would have for its goal mutual education in our trade, a friendly solidarity, some assistance in the event of illness or death. Not much is needed for that. A bit of good will and the desire of these gentlemen and colleagues, who are well acquainted with the printed profession, will suffice.</p>
   <p>It is an undeniable fact that, in the greater part, the parents of our students send their children to the printing shops, not for the purpose of teaching them a trade but only for the purpose of having that child earn wages at the earliest time.</p>
   <p>Employers being often compelled to pay the students the same rate as is paid the accomplished compositor, do not even think of really teaching them something. They place him into a case and after a few years they create a machine-a man who composes rather rapidly. That is true, but without any basic principles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1597.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It is enough to examine the Chicago papers, which are still made in the best manner to become convinced of the truthfulness of the above statements.</p>
   <p>In any event, we are greatly pleased with the question that has been raised, and we do not doubt that if the meeting will be called according to schedule, without waiting for the personal appearance of individual members, many followers of the Gutenberg's invention will be present. That is their personal business.</p>
   <p>We would require one thing of the initiators, namely, that this meeting not be held in or near a saloon. Maybe some gentleman, who owns a printing shop, will permit the use of his place of business for the initial meetings; perhaps some gentleman colleague has an appropriately large apartment for this purpose. At any rate, either one or the other will be more appropriate than a saloon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
