<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1913-10-20">Oct. 20, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Jew an Eternal Wanderer</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0989</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0989.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1913-10-20">Oct. 20, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE JEW AN ETERNAL WANDERER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Perhaps there is no other nation more tolerant than Poles. The whole of our history is the reflection of our religious and nationalistic tolerance. In time of persecutions of non-Catholics throughout Europe, great numbers of the persecuted and exiled from their own countries found refuge in Poland. Especially the Jews, who were the most hated and persecuted race in the entire Europe, came to Poland in great numbers. Time passed and Poland became the promised land for them, and the Jews, the eternal wanderers, found rest at last. There was a hope that the Jews, sharing with Poles a good and ill fortune, will respect the land which was a real mother to them for centuries, will become good citizens, just like a great many Frenchmen and Germans, who, despite being of different faith, are good patriots, the names of many of whom are written in Polish history as those of heroic defenders of Poland's independence. Greed, underhand business tactics, and other undesirable racial characteristics of the Jews outweighed their gratitude for, and appreciation of the hospitality and the tolerance extended to them by the Polish nation</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0990.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In comparison with their actual productiveness, which is very small, the Jews obtained very much; they monopolized business and enriched themselves a great deal. But in other branches, especially in the most important one, that of agriculture, they are totally ignorant. They have never been attached to the soil, and that is why they will be the eternal wanderers. They always were inimical to the nations which granted them a refuge.</p>
   <p>When by change of destiny our nation lest its independence, very few of them participated in the battles for freedom. Now a member of their own race, Unschlicht, in a book published by him, throws in their face the accusation that they took advantage of our hospitality for exploiting us and that they never were interested in the welfare of our nation.</p>
   <p>The Jews were always idolizing power and sided with our oppressors against the vital interests of our people. Their financial status was growing steadily better, while our nations wealth was declining. They were buying property and dispossessing real estate owners by hook and crook. No wonder that the Polish people, losing their patience, are awakening and trying to adjust the wrongs done by the Jews.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0991.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is not a religious, not a racial, but strictly an economical self-defense movement. The motto "Down with the Jews!" is a general outcry of the exploited nation.</p>
   <p>At the present time the boycott of Jewish business is spreading throughout Poland, and many thousands of Jews are ready to emigrate; but so far the whole civilized world is against them, regarding them as an undesirable element, except America, where they are very strongly established and where another Palestine is in the making. Uncle Sam is a great friend of the Jews.</p>
   <p>About two years ago the entire U. S. Senate rose in protest against the accusation of ritual murder preferred against Mendel Beilis by the Russian government. The entire American press was condemning the Russian government for racial persecution. The result of this was breaking commercial relations with Russia, which caused tremendous loss of business. The Jewish mysterious religious rituals caused the ignorant Russian people to believe in ritual murder, and just verbal denying, and the yelling of the <pb facs="5423968_2_0992.jpg" n="4"/>American press will not stop the accusation. As long as the Jews will not adopt the cultural characteristics of the people among which they are living, the hate and scorn cannot be stopped. Ejected from their last haven, Poland, where for a few centuries they made their home, the Jews will always be an "eternal wanderer."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
