<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-10-24">Oct. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">In Defense of the Immigrants</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1385</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1385.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1916-10-24">Oct. 24, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">IN DEFENSE OF THE IMMIGRANTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American press has finally understood that, besides the chauvinistic aspirations of melting all immigrants into patented Americans in their pot of Americanization, it is necessary to adopt other means to protect their rights and property. The first American newspaper to strike an alarm was the Chicago Tribune. In a lengthy article, the Tribune points out that immigrants should be better protected by the law.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Tribune's article, entitled "A Duty to Immigrants," deals with the recent failures of many of the so-called "private banks." It is in these banks that most of the immigrants deposit their savings. They believe too much and too readily in the glib statements they hear and neglect to heed the good counsel of the newspapers. Indifferent to newspapers, either to save money or because they cannot read, many of the immigrants deposit their life savings in unreliable banks or send their money to Europe through firms that are irresponsible before the law. They transact their financial <pb facs="5423968_2_1386.jpg" n="2"/>matters through various private agencies which speculate with their money and profit from the gullibility of these simple folks in a manner usually worse than that employed by a pickpocket or an extortioner. In that way the immigrants here lose hundreds and even thousands of dollars.</p>
   <p>This state of affairs exists not only among Poles but among people of other nationalities as well. Many of our people, who are otherwise suspicious of everything, fall easy prey to the word "bank" on a window. The immigrants, however, persist in their obstinacy despite the frequent warnings of newspapers to deposit their money in the larger State banks and in Polish banks with Polish personnel and service.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Tribune is perfectly justified in its demand that, in accordance with Judge <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> recommendations, the State Legislature enact new laws intended to regulate the operations of "private banks" and other unsound financial institutions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1387.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Judge <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, for example, calls attention to the vast sums of money sent by immigrants to their families in Europe, and says that nearly all this money goes into the pockets of the dishonest owners of various express agencies. The sending of money to Europe is done through the so-called "private banks," which <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> are in agreement with the large express centers. These "private banks" issue receipts on the blank forms of large express companies, but the latter are not in the least responsible for the "private banks'" <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and as a result cannot be held <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> for damage.</p>
   <p>An investigation conducted in 1913 shows that at that time there were in Chicago alone one hundred and twenty-seven private banks dealing in foreign exchange. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> states that since then this number has increased to two hundred. In view of this, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> has ruled that no "private bank" shall <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in foreign exchange until it has received a State permit. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>ny private banker wishing to deal in foreign exchange must obtain first a special certificate, which means that he will have to submit to all State re<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>irements, such as having his books revised, and other regulations of</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1388.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="unk" reason="[blank]"/>
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
