<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-05">Jan. 5, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Protest on Protest</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1302</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1302.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-05">Jan. 5, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST ON PROTEST</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our dear brothers who watch the rising indignation of the people against the Russian Mongols from their own political standpoint, can readily see how untimely this is for Russia and how advantageous it can be for us. The Muscovite transgressions against our people, the worst inhuman acts the Tsar could ever permit, are untimely because Russia is going to display herself at the World's Fair Columbian Exposition in Chicago. Of course, she will don the finest garb and have her make-up artists work overtime so that she may be presented in a most holy state.</p>
   <p>We are emphasizing these points to our people and their political groups because we feel that with their cooperation we can influence the American public to favor our cause. This is the time to unmask the false Russian pretentions to the general public, so that they may no longer be deceived.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1303.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are emphasizing these points to our people and their political groups because we feel that with their cooperation we can influence the American public to favor our cause. This is the time to unmask the false Russian pretentions to the general public, so that they may no longer be deceived. First of all, it is necessary to bring to light that Russian civilization is in reality Greco-Mongolian. Internally, Russia is barbaric; her cruelty takes on a fanatic aspect and her fiendish wildness stamps out all feelings and efforts. Externally, she plays the role of an innocent lamb of angelic holiness, which enables her to make friends to support her most degenerate internal political schemes.</p>
   <p>If the people who are living under the banner of the Stars and Stripes want to burn the incense of praise and love, let them do this consciously and freely. No one will be able to say that the Poles remained silent, and in their silence admired the Russians. (Perhaps in astonishment, for in reality we consider Russia to be the most ignominious of all civilized countries.)</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1304.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Let us suppose that the first mass-meeting to protest against Muscovite oppression does not show any results, that it is a complete fiasco. This condition would be due primarily to blind Russian sympathizers who cannot understand the situation.</p>
   <p>The most important things the Poles are sorely in need of, are agreement and understanding. What they need is unity. Those who desire unity may as well give up for the Poles are going to be divided into two groups, Russian and Polish. Everyone of us knows that it is not the Russians who do not speak Polish who do us the more harm, but those who think like the Russians and know how to speak Polish, together with those Polish-speaking people who sell themselves to the Russian crown.</p>
   <p>It is high time for this vile comedy to come to an end and for these Polish hypocrites to be unmasked.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1305.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Finally, we are not bartering for any political or military favors, nor even a bit of political influence, but only for the pure influence (if anyone wishes, he may call it 'philanthropic') of the public at large against the Russian oppression. To state it in a Polish and Christian way: We desire to awaken the public opinion of the entire world in order that humanity may judge by itself these Russian acts of violence, acts which are going on in broad daylight, and above all in the nineteenth century. This policy is not only ungodly but insane, and it does not give civilization a very good outlook. If the people of the nineteenth century do not wipe this ghastly wound from their brows, then they will bear forever the shame of its scar.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, let us point out that it is important that we rise from this dormant stage to take active part in the politics of our adopted country. At the same time let us beware not to fall into the clutches of that type of business that hides behind the mask of higher diplomacy. We must recall the words of Jesus Christ to the Pharisees when they were offended because He was healing the sick on the Sabbath Day: "If one of your asses <pb facs="5423968_2_1306.jpg" n="5"/>or mules would fall into the well, you would get him out on Sabbath day."</p>
   <p>Therefore, while our own brothers are being murdered by the millions, we are to wait with our protests because this is the time of the Fair, Sabbath! Why, this is the time when the Muscovites pillage the Polish nation while gathering glory and triumph before the civilized world at the Columbian Exposition.</p>
   <p>This shall never be.!</p>
   <p>From plagues, hunger, fire, and war; from Russian oppression and false diplomatic policies, deliver us, O Lord!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
