<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-04-13">April 13, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Five - Day Work Week</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1352</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1352.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-04-13">April 13, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">FIVE - DAY WORK WEEK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The General Motors Corporations, the chairman of the Finance Committee, and J. J. Raskob, vice-president of E. J. Du Pont de Nemours, are of the opinion, that every employee in America should have a two - day holiday each week. Union leaders have been seeking a five - day work week for many years. In view of present circumstances there is sharing the opinion of the union leaders a well - known, employer, financier and official of the largest automobile manufacturing company in the United States.</p>
   <p>Mr. John J. Raskob, said: "Electricity and other new inventions make possible the short week." This is also the opinion of Mr. Henry Ford who, some time ago remarked, that his greatest ambition is to have his employees work but five days a week. Labor and capital, therefore, are united on this viewpoint.</p>
   <p>The automobile manufacturer predicts that with modern machinery and other new inventions it is possible to produce enough cars to satisfy the demand in a five - day work week. Union leaders too demand the short work week, to give work to those who have been unemployed because of the introduction of new machinery.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1353.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>William Green, president of the American Federation of Labor, declared, that the demands introduced in the five - day work week are based on the above findings, and require at this time, equal economic as well as human rights.</p>
   <p>Modern manufacturers have a tendency to produce more than the consumer can buy, which results in unemployment. Mr. Green, further stated: "Today, we feel the lack of balance between these two factors. The strength of the manufacturer in the past few years has grown to a size that in six months will be capable of producing more than we can consume throughout the year. Many of the large industries are closed for many weeks each year, because of the lack of purchasing power by the working man. This fact proves, that today we need less time for production than ever before. One of the methods for stablilizing employment, would be the short work week. We are, however, not so gullible that we cannot understand the five - day work week, and that it can be established universally, when industry, and those connected with it, are ready to accept it".</p>
   <p>Mr. Davis, Secretary of Labor, also recognizes the five - day work week, as a remedy for the unemployment problem.</p>
   <p>The Knickerbocker Press of Albany, New York, publishes with pride, the fact that the predicted short work week, was the idea of a laborer who worked very hard for <pb facs="5423968_2_1354.jpg" n="3"/>a small salary, but who is at present a high official in the world's greatest industry. Such people, however, usually stress the value of hard labor. The following statement was made in the aforementioned publication: "The average laborer does not look forward to becoming president of the corporation employing him; his greatest concern and objective is the security of steady employment."</p>
   <p>Members of society are now setting up plans, by which the average laborer will benefit, when the shorter hour week is in operation. The opinion of the South Bend Tribune, is that if the average laborer spends all his leisure time driving automobiles on the highways he would prove a dismal failure, because of the resulting fatigue." The Chicago Journal of Commerce, however, says: "It is foolish to set up any designed plan to be used by the laborer for utilizing his leisure time, because the five - day work week is far off."</p>
   <p>In reply to this question, the New Haven Journal Courier, reminds us of the time when it was the general belief that if the twelve - hour work - day were reduced to a ten - hour day it would bring a catastrophe to our form of government."</p>
   <p>Mr. Green, president of the American Federation of Labor, tells that practically an entire century was devoted to establishing an eight - hour work day. Whenever <pb facs="5423968_2_1355.jpg" n="4"/>the reduction of working hours became an issue, the industrialist too presented the same argument, which proof appears in the aforementioned opinions of the various newspapers. We must also remember that the steel industry very strenously objected to shorter hours. But today, with the establishment of the eight - hour work day, this same industry is paying greater dividends to its stockholders than it didi during the twelve - hour work day period.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
