<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1919-06-27">June 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">An Open Letter to Mr. Nathan Strauss.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Written by a Pole of Jewish origin, Dr. Vorzimer)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0902</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0902.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C (Jewish)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1919-06-27">June 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">AN OPEN LETTER TO MR. NATHAN STRAUSS.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Written by a Pole of Jewish origin, Dr. Vorzimer)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Nathan Strauss, Honorary Chairman, Committee for the Protection of Jewish Rights in Poland and Eastern European Countries.</p>
   <p>Sir:</p>
   <p>The American press of May 21, published an advertisement over your signature in which you state that Jews are being slaughtered in Poland, that pogroms are raging from Lemberg to Vilno and from Warsaw to Pinsk, and that the Jewish people never had been set upon by an enemy more merciless, more brutal, more determined, or more powerful.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0903.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On the same day, you opened a mass-meeting in <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Square Garden, and after having assured the large audience that Jews are massacred in Poland, you assumed the role of a prophet and said in regard to Poland the following: "I predict, as it has been in the past it will be in the future, that nations which permit persecution of the Jew will themselves come to an ignominious end, and the quicker that happens the better you and I will be pleased."</p>
   <p>These statements, combined with the amazing demonstrations held in this and other cities, constitute a most offensive provocation of the Polish people. It requires the full self-control of every Pole not to give vent to just indignation and to be able to view this matter calmly. I confess that I feel averse to discuss the merits of this issue or to attempt to disclaim the misrepresentations as contained in your charges against Poland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0904.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But I shall say that the data and proofs that were submitted by you and your followers, even if they possibly be correct in minor details, are, if taken as a whole and presented as you choose to do it, a rank distortion of the truth, a distortion more malicious, more dangerous and more liable to mislead than any overt libel or slander could possibly be. The American law requires in the pettiest of trials for dollars and cents, that witnesses speak "the truth, the whole truth and nothing but the truth." Are you sure to have lived up to this elementary requirement of law and equity in a case of such momentous importance as the matter at issue?</p>
   <p>Should it really not be known to you that Poland has received the Jews, and granted them protection at a time when the rest of Europe was revelling in an orgy of religious persecution; that the Jews have fared exceedingly well <pb facs="5423968_2_0905.jpg" n="4"/>in Poland ? Then does it not give you food for thought, that, if there was really spreading now in Poland an anti-Jewish sentiment, there must be some reasons for this change? Wouldn't you be willing to admit that there might be just a little tiny bit of guilt on the part of certain Jewish factions in Poland? Did your investigators never hear of the so-called Litvaks who when persecuted in Russia, came to Poland and took a most hostile attitude towards the Poles? While on Polish soil they acted as Russians, and in a provocative and most offensive manner declared loudly that "this is Russia not Poland?"</p>
   <p>Should you actually be ignorant of the fact that the Jews of Russia, Germany and America, waged, ever since the beginning of war, a campaign of slander against the Poles, accusing them of massacring the Jews at a time when there were absolutely no pogroms made by Poles, but there were on the contrary, <pb facs="5423968_2_0906.jpg" n="5"/>pogroms made by Russians? Should you have forgotten already the orgy of lies and calumnies against the Poles, indulged in by Jews, particularly in America, when the Jews attempted to show the world-at-large that Poland was not worthy of independence and that she should be kept chained like vicious dog? Would you really suppose that such good services rendered by the Jews to Poland at a time when the latter was breaking the chains of a prolonged bondage, could possibly enhance a feeling of special sympathy for the Jews on the part of the Poles? And did you ever hear of Jewish usurers in Poland or of Jewish speculators who clandestinely sold food supplies on hand in Poland to Austrians and Germans, thus stripping the country of the remnants of supplies?</p>
   <p>Has it altogether escaped your vigilant attention that anti-Jewish outbreaks have occurred repeatedly in nearly every European country during the last four years, and is your sense of fairness not shocked by the fact <pb facs="5423968_2_0907.jpg" n="6"/>that Poland especially constitutes the object of such vicious attacks, and that actual pogroms happening elsewhere are being passed over in silence or casually mentioned at best?</p>
   <p>Are you not aware of the fact that in almost all those localities, where acts of looting committed against Jews are being most carefully listed, these outrages affected often non-Jews as well, and that after the collapse of the Austrian and German authorities of occupation in Poland, there ensued a chaos permitting all kinds of lawless elements to ply their trade? And even now, the organization of the Polish state is not completed as yet and could not possibly be completed, the more so as Poland is compelled to wage a bitter war on nearly all fronts. Could there be, therefore, any surprise at abuses occurring at such time?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0908.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Are you not aware of the fact that Polish legislators and authorities have severely condemned and punished the perpetrators of all anti-Jewish outrages?</p>
   <p>And then again do you fail to realize that Jewish nationalists demand for the Jews in Poland, not only full civic and religious equality, but extra rights and privileges which the Jews nowhere else possess?</p>
   <p>On the other hand, they maintain an attitude of armed neutrality in Poland's war against her foes. And what do you think would happen to the Jews in America should they dare to act in a similar way towards the American nation?</p>
   <p>But certainly you want the Jews in America to be good and loyal Americans, while in Poland you want them to be Jewish <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, that is, a foreign element within the Polish body politic. Or should your humanitarian feeling <pb facs="5423968_2_0909.jpg" n="8"/>be offended by the stern measures of the Polish authorities against the Bolsheviks, who so often happen to be Jews?</p>
   <p>Let us, however, end it here. Truth is bound to come out sooner or later, and Poland can well await, with calm confidence, the verdict of mankind. It is an entirely different phase of this matter that I desire to lay emphasis on.</p>
   <p>As the honorary chairman of the Committee for the Protection of Jewish Rights in Poland, you pretend that the action undertaken by you and your followers, is in the interest of the Polish Jews. Against this assertion I must protest most vigorously. What you and your committee are doing is not at all in the interest of the Polish Jews but, on the contrary, it is likely to bring fatal results to them. If it were not for the self-control of the Poles, then, upon learning of these infamous assaults directed by the American-Jews against Poland, they would lose their patience and <pb facs="5423968_2_0910.jpg" n="9"/>serious anti-Jewish outbreaks would occur and Jewish blood would flow. Then the responsibility for these occurrences would rest with you and your followers, every drop of Jewish blood would fall upon your conscience. The most virulent anti-Semitic propagandists could not do greater injury to the Polish Jews than you have done. Only absolute blindness, stubborness or ill-will can at this moment try to accentuate the antagonism between the Christian and Jewish population in Poland. There are many reasons why the Poles look upon the Jews with difference. There are two groups of Jews in particular who are looked upon by the Poles with the greatest distrust: the Zionists, who aim to create Palestine not upon the banks of Jordan river but upon the banks of Vistula, and as mentioned before, try to impose upon Poland special privileges for Jews - privileges which they have nowhere, not even in America, and which if granted would create a Jewish state within a Polish state and Bolsheviks who want to turn Poland into a likeness of present day Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0911.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>The rest of the Jews in Poland are either good, loyal Polish citizens, many of whom fought bravely and bled freely for Polish independence, or comprise the unenlightened masses which, however, by no means are inimical to Poland. These Polish Jews in a common effort with the Polish people are striving hard toward the same goal: an independent Poland, where all will enjoy equal rights and equal privileges. But harmony among the Poles and Jews is not in the interest of the enemies of Poland, and all those who oppose this harmony and incite racial hatred, are either wilful or unwitting tools of the Germans, Bolsheviks and other enemies of Poland. Whether it was knowingly or unknowingly that you allowed yourself to be drawn into this infamous anti-Polish propaganda is not for me to decide, but there is no doubt, and I must repeat it with emphasis, that what you are doing is against the vital interests of the Jews whom you pretend to be defending.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0912.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>To all the reasons why the Poles mistrust the Jews you have added another one. To generations to come, the Polish people will keep on repeating to the Jews the words of Nathan Strauss, uttered at the very moment when the destiny of Poland was in the balance, that "the quicker Poland comes to an ignominious end, the better he and his followers would be pleased."</p>
   <p>You occupy one of the most prominent places in the Jewish world, a place attained by your philanthropy and especially by the distribution of milk to infants. Your philanthropy has been stained by your action of May 21, 1919. It was not a nutritious fluid but a poisonous virus, worse than all the murderous gases used in the war, that you injected into the souls of Jews and Poles.</p>
   <p>These frank but wholeheartedly meant remarks please accept from a plain and unassuming Pole of Jewish race and denomination, who is deeply affected by the ignominy of the attacks as made by the American-Jews against Poland.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0913.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
   <p>Dr. Vorzimer.</p>
   <p>Manager, Polish Book Importing Company.</p>
   <p>Several days after writing this letter, the newspapers published a summary of the report to the State Department prepared by the United States Minister to Poland, Hugh Gibson, on the basis of authoritative and impartial inquiry. This report fully demonstrates the injustice done to Poland by the vicious endeavor of certain Jewish elements to disseminate false information and thus to besmirch the good name of Poland. Official advices received by the State Department from Hugh Gibson were made public and seem to indicate that reports of massacres of Jews in Poland have in some instances at least been exaggerated. Mr. Gibson reports that his investigations indicate that the feeling against certain classes of Jews is due largely to economic <pb facs="5423968_2_0914.jpg" n="13"/>reasons, rather than to religious intolerance. The State Department announcement reads: "Mr. Gibson states that he has received no reports of atrocities against Jews in Poland, Lithuania and Galicia, with the exception of the affairs at Vilna and Pinsk. He states that his sources of information are the local newspapers, including the Jewish press, the American Relief Administration, whose representatives cover all Polish districts; the American Red Cross, the American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee, Allied Mission, representatives of Jewish organizations who have talked frankly with him concerning the situation, and miscellaneous sources.</p>
   <p>It is stated that information has been given that there is feeling against certain classes of Jews, largely due to economic reasons rather <pb facs="5423968_2_0915.jpg" n="14"/>than to religious intolerance, and that according to this information certain Jewish elements support the Government and are regarded with respect as an integral part of the nation of Poland, while another Jewish element is openly hostile to the government.</p>
   <p>The city of Vilna was captured by the Poles, on April 29, in a house-to-house fight, and some of the local population were killed during this fight. It is reported that the Polish forces had thirty-five casualties, and that thirty-eight civilians were killed. Persons who were known to be, or were even suspected of being Communists, it is stated, were deported as hostages as a set-off against Poles, deported by the Bolsheviks. These cases have been under investigation by a commission, and those found to be citizens of a good reputation are being returned to Vilna without delay.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0916.jpg" n="15"/>
   <p>Colonel Godson, attache of the American Legation at Berne, his assistant Lieutenant Dewald, and an American newspaper correspondent, were in Vilna on May 5, and talked with Jews and others regarding the situation. Later, representatives of the Relief Administration and also a General Staff officer attached to the mission in Lithuania, and a representative of the Jewish Joint Distribution Committee, were in Vilna. Information has been given that all of these persons are unanimous in the report that there was no Jewish massacre in Vilna, and that statements in Jewish newspapers, of Warsaw, confirm this view."</p>
   <p>Mr. Gibson further states in his preliminary report:</p>
   <p>"Violent agitation abroad based on unwarranted reports of conditions cannot help the Jews, but has exactly the opposite effect.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0917.jpg" n="16"/>
   <p>Such propaganda when it becomes generally known here, will rightly or wrongly, be attributed in some measure to the Jews, and resentment will be intensified."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
