<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-04">Dec. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Dishonest Leaders</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1544</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1544.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-04">Dec. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">DISHONEST LEADERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday a wire from Los Angeles, California, brought us the shameful news that two union leaders, the brothers John and James McNamara, confessed that they had used dynamite to settle their score with the employers.</p>
   <p>The older brother, James McNamara, confessed that he was the one who had set the bomb in the plant of the Times, in Los Angeles, California, on the night of October 1, 1910. The explosion of the bomb partially demolished the building, whose falling walls buried twenty-one workers who were in the plant, killing them instantly.</p>
   <p>This horrible deed was an act of revenge against the publisher of the Times, who had some misunderstanding with the workers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1545.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The other brother, John J. McNamara, secretary of the Iron Joint Constructors Union, admitted that it was at his direction that the Llewellyn Iron Works had been partially demolished by a bomb.</p>
   <p>The evidence against the accused must have been very clear and certain, for, in spite of the excellent attorneys who defended them and the money contributed by the workers for their defense, they confessed their crime with the knowledge and approbation of their counsel. They confessed in order to escape the death penalty, which they would have received had they continued to plead not guilty.</p>
   <p>We wrote about the accusation and trial of the McNamara brothers with reserve, not wishing to condemn or defend them until the investigation might disclose whether they were guilty or not. It was difficult to condemn these labor leaders without any evidence of guilt, and one could not defend them without knowing whether they were really innocent.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1546.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Now, after their confession, we can say openly that these dishonest men did a horrible wrong to the organized workers of whom they were leaders. No one can suppose, even for a moment, that the organized workers knew anything about the crimes perpetrated by these leaders. Indeed, they would have never permitted such a settlement of accounts with the employers. The workers, as a whole, cannot answer for the criminal impulses of a few individuals, just as one cannot condemn a nation for the disgraceful actions of its criminals.</p>
   <p>The organized workers are not grateful in the least to these leaders for protecting their interests in this manner. They themselves condemn the McNamara brothers, who have done them more harm than good.</p>
   <p>It was the duty of organized labor to defend the McNamaras, because it was supposed at first that they were the victims of the intrigue of the capitalists who try to discredit the labor unions. But now that they have confessed their horrible deeds, which bring no credit to organized labor, the workers must turn their backs upon them and condemn their action.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1547.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This is not the way to fight an adversary as ruthless and well organized as capitalism, nor does one gain in this manner the good will of the people at large. These madmen, concealing themselves under the cloak of organized labor, settled their personal accounts in a horrible manner and caused the death of many innocent workers.</p>
   <p>The blood of the twenty-one printers who died in the bombing of the Times' plant stains the hands of these conspirators, whose names will be cursed by the widows and orphans of the victims.</p>
   <p>Besides, such terroristic actions serve no purpose other than to harm the cause of labor. Not a single employer was killed in the explosion--in fact, with the money received from the insurance companies for damages, they were able to build a new plant more impressive than the one that was destroyed. Pure foolishness or some sort of wild instinct guided these dishonest labor leaders, whose action was that of ordinary criminals rather than of leaders of organized labor. Organized labor does not want the rights of its members to be established in this manner.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1548.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Leaving, then, the McNamara brothers to the fate which they have prepared for themselves, and letting the law settle with them, the honest workers organized into unions should look carefully over their ranks to see if there are any more dishonest leaders whose activities may be harmful to the cause of labor.</p>
   <p>In Chicago a gang of murderers was arrested and tried. This gang, in order to satisfy the personal ambitions of its leaders, caused a break in the unions. As a result of this break among different groups, several workers were killed and wounded. In Los Angeles, the recently disclosed activities of other murderers are so repulsive that they bring shame not only to organized labor but to society as a whole.</p>
   <p>Surely, there are men in the labor ranks who are honest, capable, and energetic--men who know how to represent the workers honorably and who would defend their rights intelligently. In spite of this, however, some unions are headed by dishonest leaders and repulsive politicians who wish to live <pb facs="5423968_2_1549.jpg" n="6"/>comfortably from the labor of honest workers, often committing extravagances which only injure the labor cause, thus turning away from it the sympathy of the people in general.</p>
   <p>Organized labor should rid itself of all such unworthy leaders at once and place at their heads intelligent and honest people, who will guide them toward victory in a legal manner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
