<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 22,
<date when="1919-05-28">May 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Agitation of Jews in the United States against Poland Jewish Massmeeting in New York</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0921</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0921.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 22,
<date when="1919-05-28">May 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">AGITATION OF JEWS IN THE UNITED STATES AGAINST POLAND JEWISH MASSMEETING IN NEW YORK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A gigantic Jewish protest massmeeting was held a week ago in New York at the Madison Square Garden, at which over 15,000 Jews protested against pogroms, about which news dispatches have been sent from various Slav countries. Nathan Straus was chairman.</p>
   <p>Charles Evans Hughes, former Republican candidate for President of the United States, declared in his talk that "America has always acknowledged the aspirations of the people in general and that presently she must speak."</p>
   <p>Other speakers were Abraham Elkus, former American ambassador to Turkey, and Rabbi Stephen S. Wise.</p>
   <p>The resolutions adopted express the protest of a million New York Jews against pogroms and ruthlessness, which were to have been perpetrated on <pb facs="5423968_2_0922.jpg" n="2"/>the Jews in Poland, Lithuania, Galicia, and other countries. Subsequently the resolutions call upon the Peace Conference in Paris, President Wilson, and the American delegates to take all possible steps to protect the Jewish national minority in Poland, Rumania, and other countries.</p>
   <p>Jewish Manifestation in Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>A similar Jewish meeting was held on the 21st inst. in the Auditorium, in Chicago. Before the meeting, parades of Jewish multitudes took place. Special weepers and professional mourners were hired, so as to attract attention with their loud cries and wolf-like howls. The rabble in greatest disorder and irregularity, constantly bawling and howling, marched from different parts of the city in the direction of the Auditorium. Jews and Jewesses took part in the parades, but most of the paraders were Jewish children.</p>
   <p>As a sign of solidarity, all Jewish merchants, owners of small stores, groceries, butcher shops, kosher shops, fruit stores, and the like, which have <pb facs="5423968_2_0923.jpg" n="3"/>made fortunes off the Poles, closed their doors. All of Division Street, Robey, Potomac, and neighboring streets; all of South Halsted, 12th street, and surrounding streets appeared dead, as far as business was concerned. Tailors and all clerks of the larger Jewish industrial and commercial establishments stayed away from work. That whole quarter, more Polish than some of the cities in Poland, took a holiday so as to prove to the world that Poland is a savage country in which the people do not know how to govern themselves, because they are killing others, and as a result of this the authority and control over Poland ought to pass into the same hands in which it is here in our Polish Chicago quarter; that is, to the Jews.</p>
   <p>So we saw, with utter disgust, how this vermin, how these parasites brought up on our bread, in the heart of the Polish quarter, were pouring upon us a torrent of slander and lies. Remember, brother, continue feeding and breeding this vermin; buy from them, and you will live to see the same results as in Russia!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0924.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Jewish Lamentations</p>
   <p>About 25,000 Jews and all kinds of leeches gathered in the Auditorium. The chairman was the Jew, Dr. Hyman Cohn, who also presented the resolution, naturally adopted, calling upon the Americans sitting in Congress and the Peace Conference in Paris to stop Jewish pogroms in Europe. The massmeeting in the Auditorium was really only a play on the nerves and emotions of the multitudes. There was not one sensible talk analyzing the facts realistically and coldly. There was only perfuming with flattery, abetment of hatred, and the spreading of venom and fire against other nationalities and other races. There were mournful songs, tragic speeches, moans, prolonged sighs, laments, and swoons, entirely the same as in the "Kahal" (assembly of the elders among Jews) on judgment day.</p>
   <p>Speeches</p>
   <p>Besides the Jews, speeches were made by the following: Bishop Fallows, Episcopalian; Clarence Darrow, Rev. Dr. J. P. Brushingham, Protestant; <pb facs="5423968_2_0925.jpg" n="5"/>City Prosecutor H. B. Miller, representing Mayor Thompson, and the Methodist pastor, Rev. J. Thompson.</p>
   <p>Clarence Darrow, the same one who in the past year made speeches sympathetic toward the Poles, demanded that Poland, before it becomes a nation, guarantee the Jews the right of freedom, because they are persecuted everywhere.</p>
   <p>We can assure Mr. Darrow that before he was born, Poland was a nation and the Jews always had in it their rights and complete freedom, and that is just what made them audacious. One does not have to be a lawyer to know that although Poland was not an independent state for one and one-half centuries, the Polish people, nevertheless, did not cease to be a nation which knows how to be self-supporting--not like the Jews who exist solely as parasites on the body of other nations.</p>
   <p>Pastor Brushingham protested against pogroms, like all the other speakers, and also expressed himself that the Jews demanded only justice.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0926.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Bishop Samuel Fallows showed himself immensely warlike, crying: "Do you think that I will agree to have our boys fighting for the freedom of Poland if Poland will not give freedom to others?"</p>
   <p>However, not one of the speakers mentioned about the Jewish treacheries in Poland, about extortions, about bribery, and rascally practices of Jews in business or politics. Similar protests and manifestations took place in many smaller Polish cities. They give to us Poles a proper lesson from which we ought to benefit immediately.</p>
   <p>Declaration of the President of the National Council</p>
   <p>Immediately after the first Jewish manifestation in New York, the president of the National Council, Mr. John F. Smulski, issued through the Polish information bureau in Washington, a declaration which in translation is as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0927.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"As an American citizen, in my own individual and in my official capacity as president of the National Council in America, an organization representing four million citizens of Polish descent in the United States, I cannot pass over in silence the provoking Jewish demonstrations against the new Republic of Poland, like those held in New York.</p>
   <p>"Appreciating for all times our duties as American citizens, as well as the fact that we have been in America and not in Europe during the past four years of the war we, in spite of numerous attacks from the side of the Jewish people, abstained from any declarations which would possible lead to some kind of misunderstanding between the Polish and Jewish population in America.</p>
   <p>"We were persuaded that because of our common citizenship with the Jewish population in America, a racial antagonism would be an act of disloyalty to the United States. Notwithstanding numerous provocations, I, as president of the National Council (Polish), loyally supported by the Polish population, suffered the disgraceful and false attacks of Polish aspirations to a united <pb facs="5423968_2_0928.jpg" n="8"/>and independent Poland.</p>
   <p>"Time and again, in the past ten years and particularly since the meeting of the Peace Conference, prominent Jewish leaders in the United States, people holding government positions, were sending by cablegram attacks on the Polish people and their national postulates (preliminary demands). Nevertheless, in spite of these attacks, in the course of a week we supplied the Jewish collective distributional committee with a thousand tons of supplies which were sent by the Polish National Council from New York to Gdansk (Danzig) on the relief ship "Westward Ho." That cargo, or the biggest part of it came from the non-Jewish population of the United States and was entrusted to Mr. Hoover with explicit instructions that it should be divided equally among the poor Jews and Christians, without any discrimination. Even when in the official Jewish organ and in daily newspapers we read that the relief ship which I, myself, procured from the Washington authorities, was proclaimed as a purely Jewish enterprise; even then we behaved peacefully, considering it improper and unimportant to argue about a welfare cause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0929.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>"The sacrifices which we have made, abstaining from arguing in the face of these continuous provocations, the consideration for our duties as Americans, seem to have been futile as these shameless warnings printed in yesterday's New York papers and the protest demonstrations simply prove. During all these years the Polish and Jewish population lived here side by side in friendship. The distinguished gentlemen who sounded the aforementioned warnings must realize that true unity and really sound reciprocal relations become impossible on account of such tactics.</p>
   <p>"As an American citizen I must stamp this warning as a threat to the welfare of the American nation, because inevitably it must lead to antagonism there, where, up to the present time, it never had been.</p>
   <p>"The Polish population in the United States gave 200,000 of her sons to the American army; it sustained ten percent of the losses in the general battles, and from among the men not recruited for the American service it gave 25,000 people to the Polish army in France. In the last Liberty Loan in the New York district, the Poles bought 100,000 Liberty Bonds. They are <pb facs="5423968_2_0930.jpg" n="10"/>Americans in their aspriations and are appealing to the American people against this campaign."</p>
   <p>Besides that, Mr. Smulski sent a cablegram to President Wilson in which he pleads with him to put an end, once and for all, to the scattered false reports about the pogroms of Jews in Poland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
