<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1913-01-15">JAN. 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Fate of a Polish Laborer</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0721</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0721.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>NAROD POLSKI</title>,
<date when="1913-01-15">JAN. 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">FATE OF A POLISH LABORER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>His name was N. N. He was a father of seven children. To feed them he worked sometimes day and night. It was hard work in the foundry, but he got used to this work and did not even complain.</p>
   <p>Early in the morning he left home for work, and came home late. He did not know what pleasure meant, he never went to any amusements, day in and day out his days were dark.</p>
   <p>Every Sunday morning he went to church, in the afternoon to the society meeting, and in the evening he played with the children at home.</p>
   <p>His wife took care of the children, trying to support the whole family on his small wages. Day after day it was of the same darkness for the Polish laborer after twenty-two years of residence in this country. Thus he passed this monotonous life.</p>
   <p>One of his small joys was the memory of his country life in the old country; he also hoped that soon, maybe in two or three years, he would be an owner of a small house, the one he bought with his savings with $300 mortgage on it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0722.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then an accident happened, from under the elevator they pulled out the broken body of the Polish laborer. He died just like many other Polish laborers in the United States.</p>
   <p>They took the body to the morgue and the coroner's jury did not find anything; they sent the body home, where the widow was crying and lamenting.</p>
   <p>On the third day there was a funeral, and a chronicle column in the newspaper was given him.</p>
   <p>The funeral was beautiful, the hearse and four white horses, casket for $120 covered with several high priced wreaths. After that,twenty-four carriages carrying the widow, children and friends to the cemetery.</p>
   <p>Then marched the members from his society, and a great throng of people displaying sadness.</p>
   <p>At the head of the funeral cortege a band was playing Chipin's funeral march. The church bells tolled funeral tones for the Polish wandering laborer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0723.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After a potation (drowning of sorrows) everybody went home. In a few days a couple of society representatives brought to the widow a $1,000 check.</p>
   <p>For this amount the deceased was insured; very often he told his wife that in case of his death, she could pay off the mortgage and use the balance for the support of the children. But the widow spent for her husband's funeral about $700, and with the $300 she paid off the mortgage, but for living expenses for herself and the children there was nothing left.</p>
   <p>In four weeks the widow got married again.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
