<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 13,
<date when="1924-03-27">March 27, 1924</date><title level="a">The Hundred-Per-Cent Patriots Should Be Reminded</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0838</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0838.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 13,
<date when="1924-03-27">March 27, 1924</date><title level="a">THE HUNDRED-PER-CENT PATRIOTS SHOULD BE REMINDED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Because some of the hundred-per-cent American patriots are getting to be a worse plague than some contagious disease and because they are trying to force their advice on American citizens of foreign descent, it would be advisable to remind them of that great personality, Abraham Lincoln.</p>
   <p>Abraham Lincoln is a great man, perhaps the greatest, for he has no equal in the history of nations. He was the type possessing the best of everything, best and truest that can be found in the American citizen. He knew and loved his fellow-citizen, he sympathized with him, for he was brought up with him and lived with him. That is the reason why Lincoln is so dear to the masses and that is why his person is so greatly outlined in the American history, and his memory is so pleasant. Lincoln ennobled work and he respected the working man. He could use authority with justice but he preferred mercy and praise. He had a tendency to replace sadness with happiness. He, while being highly placed and at the height of his glory, remained a simple and common man. The poor and forsaken had a friend in him, and his whole life, from the time when his mother caressed him in her arms till his martyrdom, was and is a best example of American citizen.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0839.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Citizenship is a great privilege, a most valuable heritage, begotten by sacrifice and suffering, struggle and blood. As it happens, American citizenship is our share through suffering of the revolution, through civil war and through the bravery of the World's War veterans. It is the most precious fruit of suffering and struggle through the ages. That dream of the ancients, the hope of medieval times has been realized.</p>
   <p>Those who are citizens now should be proud of it; those who are not yet citizens should try to become citizens. Those who were born here should fulfill their duties as citizens, not neglect them and, what is worse, not scoff at those who were not born here.</p>
   <p>Those who were not born here should all as one man, not only become citizens, but also profit from the privileges of citizenship.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
