<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-06">Sep. 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[The Greed of the American Wealthy Class]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1449</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1449.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-06">Sep. 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">[THE GREED OF THE AMERICAN WEALTHY CLASS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a time when many poor people are in abject poverty in this country and innumerable masses of laborers are being tortured by the high cost of living, the rich class enjoys itself....by importing diamonds and pearls from Europe. The customs department reported that in the month of August alone, jewelry whose value was appraised at $4,315,390.27 was imported into America, that is, over a million dollars more than in the same month of the previous year and three million dollars more than in [August of] the year 1908.</p>
   <p>But how many pieces of jewelry were brought into this country illegally, jewelry which has escaped the notice of the customs inspectors? One rich woman from Jersey City alone attempted to smuggle jewelry whose value exceeded one hundred thousand dollars. Of course she was unsuccessful in this, and the expensive baubles were confiscated by the officials. Nonetheless, there were <pb facs="5423968_2_1450.jpg" n="2"/>many women who were successful in bringing in valuables without paying duty. The greed, the vanity of the American rich surpass all bounds. They amass fortunes here with a wild and uncontrolled greediness, through the aid of dishonorable, illegal means--in other words, they rob their honest but less shrewd fellow citizens, and then take the millions gained from the hard work of the laboring masses and transfer them abroad. They spend this money for various unnecessary luxuries and bring many-colored gems into this country so that they might stand out in contrast to the rags and the misery of millions of needy people.</p>
   <p>The greediness of the American wealthy class has gained such proportions that its members not only endeavor to avoid paying legitimate taxes for general purposes, but even attempt to rob the treasury of their own nation, a country in which they have amassed millions. The tax burden usually falls upon the small real-estate owners and upon those who possess nothing, people who pay a tax on the purchase of each item, no matter how small, of every foodstuff.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1451.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The treasury of the nation is maintained by the poor citizens, and the rich pilfer it. the latter export billions of dollars abroad for articles of luxury, while misery bares its <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> in the gutters and hovels of their own country. The possessing class here will become degenerate, because it contributes nothing to the well-being of the nation; on the contrary, it robs the country <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> at every occasion. It is little <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, then, that dissatisfaction grows among the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> class, shamefully abused and robbed by the American upstarts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
