<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-02">Jan. 2, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Paderewski's Brilliance Unparalleled in Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1307</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1307.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-02">Jan. 2, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">PADEREWSKI'S BRILLIANCE UNPARALLELED IN CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon the Chicago Symphony Orchestra under the direction of Theodore Thomas, gave a concert in the Auditorium Theater. The outstanding feature of the concert was the brilliant performance of the noted Polish pianist I.J. Paderewski. Not many Poles attended the performance because of the mass-meeting of protest against Russian violence at the Polish hall; however, a good number came. Those who did were among the many who enthusiastically acclaimed the superb playing of the great Paderewski. The editors are sorry that the paper's representative could not be present because of the mass-meeting; however, we reprint the following excerpt from the Illinois Staats-Zeitung, a German paper which now calls him an outstanding Polish artist and not Russian, as it did before:</p>
   <p>"The first Sunday matinee concert of the New Year, held at the Auditorium <pb facs="5423968_2_1308.jpg" n="2"/>by the Chicago Symphony Orchestra, was practically sold out. Perhaps this was due to the holiday season. But it must be admitted that the great attendance was also due to the appearance of Paderewski, who made a triumphant appearance in Vienna, a like performance in Germany in 1888; the following year in France, and last season in London. All these nations have compared him with the renowned Anton Rubenstein. After yesterday's initial performance, several Chicago music critics place him above Rubenstein, particularly in one thing, that despite the complexity of interpreting classical music and despite the fine artistic touches, Paderewski performs throughout his concerts with great dignity and finesse. He goes about it like a dignified gentleman, not like some artists who try to imitate some wild animal with a grizzly mane, or a half mad person performing before a clavichord.</p>
   <p>"Paderewski has also an artistic set of heavy hair of a true golden blond tint. Yet, there is something about it that does not display the <pb facs="5423968_2_1309.jpg" n="3"/>greatness of a virtuoso nor produces an effect of desired conspicuousness. It is apparent that he performs his artistry as a true artist, for the benefit of the public, not as one whose only aim is personal prestige. With gratification and sincerety, Paderewski shook hands with director Theodore Thomas after playing his first number. He bowed with politeness to the men at the pit and received the applause of an audience of three thousand with polite gratitude.</p>
   <p>"The applause reached thunderous proportions after the piano performance of Mr. Paderewski. Only once before had it reached such magnitude and that was during the memorable performance of John Reszki in 'Aida,' which was produced here by the Abbey and Grau Opera Company. The audience that was present has never before heard such great applause, such great ovation.</p>
   <p>"And Mr. I. J. Paderewski has well earned this tribute. He is a piano virtuoso of the first order and something more. He is a true artist of <pb facs="5423968_2_1310.jpg" n="4"/>musical temperament, from head to toe. Astonishing was his musical technique and unmatched as his tall and slender figure. His matchless renditions gave an added impetus to the musical world. In his renditions he combines exquisite ability with ardent emotion and true deep poetical feeling. Various musical shades, from the soft fading pianissime to the thunderous fortissimo, serve his every command; each execution a true artistic expression. Throughout his playing, he never fell into pure sensual delight, but tried instead to get a diaphanous and plastic phraseology of every musical phase. The greatest triumph reached by the virtuoso and artist yesterday was Franz Liszt's 'Fantasia On Hungarian Airs.' It was as difficult as Rubenstein's piano concerto 'D Moll,' yet Paderewski knew how to inject into it livelier touches and strike finer accords, coupled with rhythmic precision and fine subtleness. Entirely new was the wonderful example of trilling, which blended well with the melody, especially delectable by the ears of the listeners. All this brought a distinct individual characterization of Liszt's composition, whose genius caught the spirit of the Hungarian <pb facs="5423968_2_1311.jpg" n="5"/>gypsy's life and music and personified them in his Hungarian airs.</p>
   <p>"As if this rendition was not impressive and imposing enough, Paderewski played Chopin's waltz 'Cis Moll,' showing again that he is capable of producing miraculous musical touches no matter how difficult the composition. He displayed his brilliance to a better advantage in 'Gampanelli,' by Paganini. Stating it briefly, Paderewski, with his overwhelming musical interpretations of world renowned classics, captured the hearts of Chicago's music lovers as if by storm. And the audience accepted this triumphant entrance with almost endless and enthusiastic applause and huzzahs."</p>
   <p>Mr. Ignac Paderewski arrived day before yesterday six hours late. This was due to one of the many American railroad mishaps. He was compelled to wait six hours without any food before traffic was restored. This delay made it impossible for him to rehearse with the Chicago Symphony Orchestra and his humor was not at its best. However, last night's reception restored his <pb facs="5423968_2_1312.jpg" n="6"/>dampened humor and his wrecked composure was completely renovated by the enthusiasm of the audience at the Auditorium Theater.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
