<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-06">Jan. 6, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">An Appropriate Project</title><title level="a" type="sub">Congress of Polish Teachers in America (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0265</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0265.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-06">Jan. 6, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPROPRIATE PROJECT</title><title level="a" type="sub">Congress Of Polish Teachers In America (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A very propitious and appropriate project has arisen among the teachers of Polish parochial schools in Chicago. It is a plan to call a Congress of all Polish teachers in America for this year. The object of the Congress, which could best meet in Chicago during this year's vacation period, is to create an understanding between our teachers as to forms and methods of teaching in Polish schools. During the Congress, lectures would be read on pedagogic questions, and experimental lessons performed, which would not be without substantial profit to the members of the Congress in general.</p>
   <p>One result could be the forming of an Association of Polish teachers. It is superfluous to demonstrate here the need for either the Congress or such an association. In the old country, more especially in the provinces of Galicia and Poznan, associations of this sort exist and bring about great gains in public education.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0266.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Congresses called together frequently in various places, are ever more useful; often they constitute a practical school for many teachers, simplify the exchange of views on pedagogic problems, and make for a uniform method of teaching.</p>
   <p>Similar congresses would be of still greater value here in America where we have only a few teachers who have studied pedagogic method, or who have the necessary professional experience. The project is therefore a pertinent one.</p>
   <p>As usual, financial difficulties may stand in the way of its fulfillment. We believe, however, that with honest effort, these barriers will not prove insurmountable. The exposition in Chicago will help to attract some of the teachers during the vacation months, especially those who possess the means and those who live in the vicinity of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0267.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>To the best of our knowledge, Mr. Sczesny Zahajkiewicz, one of the originators of the plan, intends to raise at least a small fund for this purpose; we have no doubt that his efforts will receive the sincere support of those to whom Polish education lies near to the heart.</p>
   <p>We wish the initiators of this project every success in its accomplishment, and we promise to return to this important matter not once, but many times.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
