<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-12">Dec. 12, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Expensive Trial</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-12">Dec. 12, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">EXPENSIVE TRIAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The most difficult and at the same time the most expensive battle that the Government of the United States is waging at present is the battle with the meat trust. This powerful organization which has millions of dollars at its disposal, which can command the cleverest lawyers, and which has been able to bribe witnesses and not infrequently judges, is defending itself with all its might; the Government has a real task on its hands if it really intends to behead this hydra. The battle is interesting--and expensive for all concerned!</p>
   <p>The Government knows well that if it succeeds in vanquishing the meat trust--the most powerful, financially, after the oil and steel trusts, and at the same time the best organized and the most influential--it will have an easier time handling the other trusts. But though the Government has been waging a battle with this monster for a long time, its efforts up to the present have <pb facs="5423968_2_1419.jpg" n="2"/>been ineffective in the face of the elaborate and clever defense put up by the trust.</p>
   <p>This trial is expensive for both the contending parties; it has made noticeable inroads into the Federal treasury, and the trust has sustained even greater losses. According to government statistics, this trial has thus far cost both sides a total of $716,000, and will certainly eat up still greater sums if it is continued. [Translator's note: Here follow the statistics relating to the expense of the trial.]</p>
   <p>The trial, therefore, has cost a tremendous sum, and there is so far no way of estimating how long the case will continue or how it will be concluded. For the battle with the trust hydra, therefore, the nation must make an outlay of tremendous sums, thanks to the inadequate legal statutes and the clumsiness of the judiciary.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1420.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>No other government in the world, when it wished to prosecute a wealthy corporation, would sanction such a tremendous outlay from its treasury; it would settle the matter with expedition and decisiveness. Here, however, the whole legal proceedings are beneath contempt, and are shot through with politics and selfish interests. The Federal treasury is full; why therefore should one not help himself by the handful? This is no mean opportunity for lawyers, agents, and witnesses of all sorts, nor can the judges be expected to lose by it.</p>
   <p>If the Government has expended such a large sum of money on the trial of but one corporation, with no decision in sight, one can then imagine how much money must be spent on the trial of the sugar, tobacco, steel, oil, and other trusts which the government is supposedly prosecuting. The nation, then, spends millions of dollars on this sham battle, while the trusts continue to strangle the people more vigorously than ever, since they must make up from our pockets the money which they spend on the trials. The people, therefore, lose in two ways at once, because on the one hand money goes out of the <pb facs="5423968_2_1421.jpg" n="4"/>Federal treasury, and on the other, the trusts make good their losses by raising the prices of all sorts of commodities. Naturally a number of attorneys and detectives are becoming wealthy in the process, but the people in general gain nothing by this battle.</p>
   <p>The trying of a case in America, even by the Federal Government, is a joke. Where else would the trial of some corporation last two years, after it had been established several times that the said corporation was breaking the anti-trust laws? Consider, for example, the famous trial of the oil trust, in which one judge decreed a large fine, which at least would have covered all the costs of the trials instituted by the Government against other trusts, and other judges then declared the sentence invalid and voided it, completely freeing the guilty party. Now this same trust is being tried again, so that again hundreds of thousands of dollars can be taken out of the treasury--for the benefit of the lawyers. All these trials for the dissolution of the trusts are a farce which no healthy-minded person can take seriously.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
