<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-03-26">Mar. 26, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Prayer</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0771</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0771.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-03-26">Mar. 26, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">PRAYER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the initial duties of parents is to teach the children prayer, and to train them to pray daily, so that they may go to bed with prayer and arise to greet each new day with prayer.</p>
   <p>Some unbelievers may ask what advantage the children can derive from prayer which they do not understand--nor comprehend the Being to whom it is being offered. True, the children will, from the beginning, repeat the prayer mechanically, not applying to it any thought. But, in the years to follow, when the mind will fully develop, more importance will be attached to prayer. It is then that they will always have in mind that God is present always and sees every act committed on earth by them; consequently, these children will think twice before they commit a wrong, and will consider whether or not it will be contrary to the principles of their religion. In the event they <pb facs="5423968_2_0772.jpg" n="2"/>commit an evil, their conscience will tell them that they have committed a wrong.</p>
   <p>Fervent prayer gives strength. How many times has it occured that an adult, in his later years, influenced by bad examples, forgot his prayers and considered the duties of the Roman Catholic Church exaggerated? Such a person has passed his years in disbelief, but if he had spent his youth among good friends, sooner or later he would be able to "collect" himself. Only one moment is necessary for this change. Under influence, be it at a moment of great joy or a time of pain and remorse, this person will recall the days of his childhood when he prayed on bended knees while his mother guided his words through the Lord's Prayer. A vivid image of his happy boyhood days pass in review; he sees the church in which he prayed, and the school he attended; the drone of the majestic church organ reverberates once again in his ears, while from the swirling clouds of incense legions of voices bowed before the Sanctissimum Sing out: "Holy God! Holy, Immortal God!"</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0773.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the meantime, words of prayer uttered during childhood will begin to flow from his lips, tears of remorse will sear his cheeks as he unconciously kneels before his forgotten God.</p>
   <p>Such moments have been experienced by simple persons, thieves, princes, and learned men who considered that there was no greater mind on this earth than theirs. Such individuals, when questioned, confessed that this change was not brought about through the influence of some book or urgings of others, but by the recollection of their childhood.</p>
   <p>It would also be necessary to ask wouldbe self-murderers how many or them cast away the instrument of murder, with which they desired to take their life, because of the mere recollection of the simple words of the Lord's Prayer: "Thy will be done on earth...."</p>
   <p>The great influence of daily prayer was attested by the late Ignatius Domejko.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0774.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>His narration contains many great passages of truth, for it was confided to one of our great priests.</p>
   <p>Being a rector at a university in Santiago, Spain, Domejko met a compatriot of his who did not forget his mother tongue, although he lived for several decades among strangers, where he did not hear one word of Polish uttered in conversation, out in the street, or in church. Domejko was dumbfounded to hear his friend speak in perfect Polish, and inquired of him how he was able to preserve his native language. The colleague replied, "I said my prayers daily in Polish."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
