<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-11-20">Nov. 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Practices of the Illinois Central Railroad</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1389</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1389.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1914-11-20">Nov. 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">PRACTICES OF THE ILLINOIS CENTRAL RAILROAD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday before noon, in a meeting held at the City Hall, City Engineer--Henry W. Lee, a man who calls things by their names, and that in a vigorous manner--exposed the management of the Illinois Central in its relation to the city.</p>
   <p>The contract of the Illinois Central Railroad with the South Park Commissioners was the topic of the day. We repeat Lee's assertions.</p>
   <p>"The contract by which the South Park Commissioners propose to give the Illinois Central Railroad a strip of five miles of land along Chicago's lake front will rob the public.</p>
   <p>"The so-called "opening" right on which the Illinois Central bases its claim is precisely one of those rights which it does not merit. The highest court had decreed in several cases that the Illinois Central Railroad Company has <pb facs="5423968_2_1390.jpg" n="2"/>no right other than the settler's right which it gained a long time ago in Chicago.</p>
   <p>"A committee from the legislature, after having examined the case, declared that the Illinois Central Railroad Company has no legal title to the property but nevertheless uses the land as though it owned it. The Company continues to cheat the public by keeping this land in its possession". So much for Lee.</p>
   <p>The committee did not settle this matter but postponed it until Wednesday. This proposal is the masterpiece of Alderman Littler, (Republican) of the Twenty-eighth Ward, who introduced it before the council in June. At that time the clerk read the proposal and Alderman Littler moved that the proposal be accepted unanimously. Nevertheless, since Jackson Park was mentioned in this proposal, Alderman Merriam, who it is said will not let anything slide by, stubbornly insisted that this proposal be sent to a committee, and he won. Since June this matter has been passed back and forth in the committee. Finally it was decided to settle the matter yesterday. Unfortunately for those who <pb facs="5423968_2_1391.jpg" n="3"/>wanted to push this measure through, Engineer Lee poured cold water on the proposal. After the adjournment of the committee, Henry Lee made the following statement:</p>
   <p>"The people of the city of Chicago should learn at last that the Illinois Central Railroad is in possession of a square mile of land situated north of Randolph Street, that this land is worth $1,200,000 an acre, and that the Company continues to hold it illegally".</p>
   <p>We brought this matter up in order to warn the citizens of a new trick prepared by the clever lawyers of the Illinois Central, a trick by which the company hopes to get another five-mile tract. We mention this now because when the contract is drawn up it will be too late to do anything about it.</p>
   <p>Therefore, go to your aldermen. Go to them repeatedly and tell them at every opportunity that you do not want the Illinois Central Railroad to rob the taxpayers again.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1392.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Begin this today. Go to your alderman today and ask him what he thinks about this matter--he whose duty it is to protect your interests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
