<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-07-02">July 2, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Graduation Exercises at St. Stanislaus Kostka College</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0222</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0222.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-07-02">July 2, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">GRADUATION EXERCISES AT ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA COLLEGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our young St. Stanislaus Kostka College held its public annual graduation exercises last night before an interested audience.</p>
   <p>The program began with "O Columbia," which was sung by the College choir, accompanied by the orchestra. T. Rekosiak, a student of the College, then delivered a beautiful address to the clergy, teachers, and parents, in which he thanked the teachers for the interest they take in the work of the pupils, and the parents for the hardships they bear for their sons. The recitations and songs were well received. Two students, Jarecki and Zender, recited with spirit, and were rewarded with great applause. Another student, A. Bocian, was also applauded when he played the role of "The Doctor" in a comedy which was next on the program. He was so comical that he made the audience laugh continually.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0223.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The solo rendered by E. Gordon was beautifully executed. This young artist charmed the audience with his melodious voice.</p>
   <p>Young J. Mucha gave an excellent recitation in English.</p>
   <p>The excerpt from "Dziady" (Beggers) by Mickiewicz, was splendidly rendered. The songs, of which some were difficult solos, were sung in a professional manner and pleased everyone.</p>
   <p>The gymnastics, though brief, because of the heat, proved that our brisk boys are fit for everything, or as we say in Polish, "Good for telling beads and for dancing".</p>
   <p>The audience listened to Reverend V. Barzynski's address with great attention and applauded him enthusiastically.</p>
   <p>The esteemed speaker complimented the students on their work and their diligence, <pb facs="5423968_2_0224.jpg" n="3"/>and encouraged the parents to give their children a good education, for, as he said, if our children do not receive proper education our American Poles will not make so good a showing as they should, considering their number. The money spent for children's education is like a treasure which will benefit fit not only the children and the parents but all society.</p>
   <p>The music rendered by the orchestra deserves praise in every respect. Piano playing by Reverend S. Cosimi and by Dlugowski, a student, was enthusiastically received by the audience, which rewarded them with thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>The occasion was ended with the awarding of diplomas to the graduating students. These exercises will be remembered for a long time by those who witnessed them.</p>
   <p>The following students received diplomas [names of students omitted in translation]....</p>
   <p>After singing "Boze Cos Polske" (God Save Poland), the public went home with a <pb facs="5423968_2_0225.jpg" n="4"/>feeling of satisfaction.</p>
   <p>We wish the young College success. It is the pride of our parish, and it does honor to the teachers as well as to the principal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
