<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 19,
<date when="1920-05-06">May 6, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Americanization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0895</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0895.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 d</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 19,
<date when="1920-05-06">May 6, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICANIZATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Learn English and study American ideals. Learn English so that you cannot often be deceived by the vices of your own race. Learn American ideals and know of the opportunities for advancement. American agitators are to be blamed for unrest.</p>
   <p>Two demoralizing forces have been working upon the foreign born in this country. They are subjective to the incendiary speeches of agitators of their own nationalities on the one side, and to the twaddle of parlor socialists on the other. Although they are supposed to be so much under domination of the Goldmans and the Berkmans, the fact is often ignored that some of the worst despoilers of the body politic are native born Americans. It is true that such have an alien slant in their minds, and that they are really foreigners in the country in which they have been reared.</p>
   <p>We have foreigners of the type of Martens, the Soviet apostle, but we also have William D. Haywood; American-born Foster, the firebrand of the steel strike, is a native of Pennsylvania; Eugene V. Debs was born in Terre Haute, <pb facs="5423968_2_0896.jpg" n="2"/>Indiana; Max Eastman in Canadagua, New York; and Louis Faraina, an organizer of the Communist Party, first saw the light in the United States although he is of Italian descent. Scott Nearing came into this world of strife at Morris Run, Pennsylvania. John Reed is an American-born journalist although he was once a delegate from the Bolsheviki.</p>
   <p>John Graham Brooks, in his book American Syndicalism and I. W. W., says that the first great fights of the Industrial Workers of the World took place at Cripple Creek, Colorado, and that foreigners neither led that organization nor were prominent in it.</p>
   <p>It is declared by another authority that of seventy-four men who were charged with first degree murder at Everett, Washington, in 1906, and were defended by the I. W. W., fifty-seven were native born Americans and the others were mostly of British birth.</p>
   <p>There are some foreign residents in this country who feel that the native born agitator has not been punished enough and that too much stress has been put upon bringing to justice the trouble-maker whose birthplace was Russia, <pb facs="5423968_2_0897.jpg" n="3"/>or Germany. Such as they, are likely to be exploited by the fomenters of unrest.</p>
   <p>We must do all we can to suppress any bolshevistic or anarchistic tendencies yet we believe that, at least, some regard should be shown the sensibilities of the foreign born.</p>
   <p>The average American is still ignorant of the fact that the vast majority of foreign born residents are loyal and that they are doing everything they can to understand America.</p>
   <p>"Of the foreign language newspaper," to quote from a recent statement of the Inter-Racial Council, "only five percent have at any time advocated the overthrow of the government and the substitution of communism for the present economic order. Fifteen percent are socialistic, while eighty percent are as conservative as the great majority of American publications."</p>
   <p>It is indeed a delicate question which involves drawing the line between harshness to the foreign born and coddling him. Many of the immigrants <pb facs="5423968_2_0898.jpg" n="4"/>maintain a love for their old customs and are driven thereby into their own communities. They wish to have everything as much like "home" as possible. Some of them who are going back when they have saved enough, and can find a place in Europe which is undisturbed enough to suit them, said that it will be a great pleasure to have wine with their meals. Others, however, like some Americans, are trying, though with not very good grace, to adjust themselves to the desert rather than the oasis.</p>
   <p>Comfortable as it is for so many of these to believe that they are bringing culture to this country, to take the place of the coarser Yankee hustle, they are not fully realizing the benefits of being American, as long as they take that attitude.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
