<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 140,
<date when="1906-06-20">June 20, 1906</date><title level="a">The Shortage of Polish Nuns</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0102</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0102.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XVII, No. 140,
<date when="1906-06-20">June 20, 1906</date><title level="a">THE SHORTAGE OF POLISH NUNS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Reverend Father H. Orlowski explains why he accepted two Irish teachers for his Polish institution. They are good Catholics, also diplomatic teachers; he says that in vain he sought for a long time to get Polish nuns as teachers.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Father H. Orlowski also states: "It is difficult to get nuns, and a hundred times more so to get the kind who would possess the adequate qualifications. From the time the parish of St. John Canthius was established, I have twice journeyed to different parts of the country seeking nuns, not to mention many letters I have written.</p>
   <p>"During one year I sent letters to a priest, the head of a certain group, and to the superiors of six convents. From all of them I received an answer. The priest informed me that besides the nuns he has, who teach in his school, there is no other group who possess adequate qualifications to teach. The five superiors who answered by letter claimed that they in no way could send me any teachers and one of them also added that she has to repossess some <pb facs="5423968_2_0103.jpg" n="2"/>nuns for her use from a certain parish.</p>
   <p>"The superior of the sixth convent consented to send me a nun. Delighted with this information I wrote a second letter stating that advanced mathematics was not being taught in my school and asking if the two nuns whom she had in mind to send to me knew the complete course of elementary arithmetic. This was her response:</p>
   <p>'After considering attentively your letter, Reverend Father, I arrived at the conclusion that I haven't any qualified teachers for you this year.' I underline the fact "this year."</p>
   <p>"These letters I still possess. I have not to this time destroyed them. One of the Polish priests told me he has nun teachers at his school. One of them is able and possesses a certain degree of education; she teaches other sisters, they then teach the children. Speaking in general, it is difficult to obtain nuns; a hundred times harder to secure nuns who have adequate teaching qualifications. Not only do Polish priests have this difficulty. One of the Irish pastors told me, 'Even though I have a nun, I likewise have lay teachers, because I cannot get nuns who meet the qualifications of a teacher.'"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
