<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 204,
<date when="1908-08-31">August 31, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Consecration of the School of the Apostles St. Peter and St. Paul</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0085</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-lithuanian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0085.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV (Lithuanian)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 204,
<date when="1908-08-31">August 31, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">CONSECRATION OF THE SCHOOL OF THE APOSTLES ST. PETER AND ST. PAUL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday was a day of great celebration at the parish of the Apostles St. Peter and St. Paul, in which the parishioners; their neighbors and friends took part. The organizer and the first pastor of this parish, now the first Polish bishop in America, consecrated this impressive and newly completed school building which will add beauty to this locality, and in which hundreds of Polish children will receive their schooling.</p>
   <p>From early morning the celebration was in progress in this beautifully decorated school; all Polish homes in the neighborhood between 37th and 38th streets and Ashland avenue and Paulina street, were decorated with Polish colors, red and white, and at the entrance to the school the following words were printed on a poster, "We Greet You, First Polish Bishop," and as our appreciation of his work in behalf of this parish we placed his picture above the entrance of the school, surrounded by Polish and American flags. At noon the various church societies, organizations, and priests, congregated at the front of the church to await the arrival of Bishop Rhode.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0086.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Guards on horseback, people from all sections of the city, even priests from out of town, made up the crowd awaiting the arrival of Bishop Rhode. This crowd reminded us all of Bishop Rhode's consecration on July 29.</p>
   <p>About 2 o'clock Bishop Rhode arrived by automobile accompanied by the pastor of this parish, Reverend Father Max Kotecki, with Reverend Father Frank Wojtalewicz and Reverend Father John Lange.</p>
   <p>About sixty young boys and girls from this parish, beautifully dressed and carrying Polish flags and flowers, escorted Bishop Rhode from the front of the church to the entrance of the school, where he blessed the structure before allowing people to enter.</p>
   <p>The various societies and organizations from more than forty parishes started the procession through this newly-blessed school in which a great number of priests took part.</p>
   <p>Four bands played at this consecration. They were composed of over 150 people. The bands played Polish songs and hymns, together with the choirs <pb facs="5423968_2_0087.jpg" n="3"/>from St. Peter and St. Paul, Holy Innocence, Holy Trinity, and St. Stanislaus churches. After the consecration, Bishop Rhode led the procession to the church where he bestowed his blessings upon the congregation and the various priests. He was assisted by Most Reverend Father Gronowski and Reverend Father Zwierchowski.</p>
   <p>The choirs under the direction of Mr. Walkiewicz sang during Bishop Rhode's blessings: Mr. Karczynski, accompanied by Mr. Walkiewicz, sang "In es Petrus," and "O Salutaris."</p>
   <p>After the blessings, Bishop Rhode told the congregation the value of the Polish Catholic schools, in which the children are taught Catholic religion and respect for their country and parents. With his final blessings the consecration ceremonies came to an end.</p>
   <p>At 6:30 a banquet was held in the new school hall at which all the priests and officers in charge of this great consecration were present; besides these, our well-known Polish political leaders, Mr. N. Budzban, Mr. Szajkowski, Mr. Smietanka, Mr. Pinderski, Mr. Szopinski, and Mr. Czarnecki <pb facs="5423968_2_0088.jpg" n="4"/>spoke of the undying love of the Polish people for the Catholic religion. The master of ceremonies for this great banquet was Mr. Czarnecki, who introduced the following speakers for the evening: Reverend Father Gronowski, Reverend Father Lange, Reverend Father Nawrocki, Mr. Jacob Gawczynski, Reverend Father Wojtalewicz, Reverend Father Sztuczko, Father Zwierzchowski, Reverend Father Furman, Stanley Szwajkart, editor of the Polish Daily News; Reverend Father Krawczunas, and Reverend Father Slominski. The evening speeches came to a close when Bishop Rhode told the people about the history of this parish. When he first organized and built it fourteen years ago, only twenty-seven families made up the congregation.</p>
   <p>The choirs sang "God, Who Through Ages Showered Love and Protection on Our Beloved Poland" for the concluding number on this program. Bishop Rhode departed from this parish amid the cheers, applause, and whistling of the happy throng of Polish people. This consecration will remain in the minds of all Polish people as the greatest remembrance of all because it was the first consecration performed by our first Polish bishop, Bishop Rhode.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
