<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-08-08">August 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Care of Children</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0662</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0662.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-08-08">August 8, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE CARE OF CHILDREN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It seems sometimes that it is useless to write about such a very important subject as "The Proper Care of Our Children," moral as well as parental, a general care. Occasionally, either on account of some special incident betraying lack of parental care as when a street car kills a child, or when one of our young generation"distinguishes himself" by committing a crime, and sometimes without any special reason, an article discussing the subject of bringing up children will appear in the pages of a newspaper.</p>
   <p>The opinion expressed in these articles is quite often reprinted in other journals and commented upon. Ultimately they are forgotten. Reality never changes, it remains intact, as bleak as it has been in the past.</p>
   <p>How then shall we explain this sad phenomenon?</p>
   <p>This sad condition is caused in the first place by the difference of opinions <pb facs="5423968_2_0663.jpg" n="2"/>on the matter, and in the second,by idle talk in the press and among the public about some kind of reform which is never carried out, because the public does not like action.</p>
   <p>This matter cannot be speeded by writing bombastic tirades. It requires action.</p>
   <p>In one of our journals there appeared an article in which the writer made a statement that a father and a mother must be more than just parents, if they wish to bring up their children properly. It is also necessary to know how to bring up children, to understand them, to know the soul of the child and the systems of developing its body and mind. It is not sufficient to have a deep affection for the child;  it is absolutely necessary to know how to guide and rear it.</p>
   <p>This is very important and it requires action.</p>
   <p>Here in America, we live in such circumstances that the burden of rearing children is forced on the mother. The father works long hours in the <pb facs="5423968_2_0664.jpg" n="3"/>factory and is not in a position to control the development of his children and to influence their bringing up. This very important duty must be performed by the mother who, having very little time and (still less) money, cannot perform this task properly. Besides, she does not realize the great importance and difficulty of the task. The school furnishes children with some knowledge during study hours, but cannot rear them.</p>
   <p>This most important duty is left to the mother, who is overworked and incompetent.</p>
   <p>The foregoing shortcomings should be removed by action. There should be playgrounds, nurseries, and other institutions to relieve overworked mothers. The children would have good care in such an institution, and mothers would be greatly relieved. There should be schools and courses for incompetent mothers, in which they could receive instructions on subjects necessary in bringing up children.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0665.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The members of our Polish Women's Alliance should take this matter up and the community will help.</p>
   <p>Let us act!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
