<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-07">Apr. 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Cigar-Makers' Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1586</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1586.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-07">Apr. 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">CIGAR-MAKERS' UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is with real pleasure that we publish the following letter sent to us by Theodore Gize:</p>
   <p>"I am a cigar-maker. I know many Polish workers, both men and women, of the same trade--that is, rollers and bunch-makers--who work in cigar factories at half pay. They roll a hundred cigars for thirty or thirty-five cents, and they make a hundred bunches for twenty cents each or less. The union scale is fifty-five cents a hundred for rolling and thirty-five cents a bunch on the cheapest grade of cigar. It is easy to determine how much extra profit the manufacturer makes and how many hours the worker puts in free at such pay. The workers earn themselves the ugly name of scabs.</p>
   <p>"As the only remedy for such a condition, I sincerely recommend that my countrymen join the newly organized Independent Cigar-Makers' Union. The entrance fee is twenty-five cents--the dues are twenty-five cents per month.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1587.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"By joining the union, our brethren will at last obtain a decent wage rate for their work. I am appealing to my countrymen and fellow-workers in behalf of the committee and almost a hundred members of our union. We ask that this matter be attended to without delay. Do not out off joining until later.</p>
   <p>"A meeting of the members of the new union will be held on Saturday, April 11, at eight o'clock in the evening, at 490 Union Street, corner Liberty Avenue..... New members will be accepted at this meeting. I appeal once more to all my fellow-workers for co-operation. Let us join hands."</p>
   <p>[Theodore Gize]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
