<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-13">Nov. 13, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Entertainment</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0520</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0520.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-11-13">Nov. 13, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH ENTERTAINMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the last issue of the Pittsburgh Przyjaciel Ludu (Friend of the People], the following item appeared:</p>
   <p>"Last Saturday there was a bit of music in the home of a certain F. Figiel..... At about midnight, the guests became so noisy and disorderly that the host asked them to leave. A few of them took offense and a brawl resulted, in which Figiel was wounded in the chest with a knife. The wound is deep but not fatal. The attacker, who hid under a bed in panic, was arrested by the police and held pending trial."</p>
   <p>Also, the latest issue of the Baltimore Polonia carries this item from Warren, Massachusetts:</p>
   <p>"A Polish wedding took place here, at which almost all of the local Polish <pb facs="5423968_2_0521.jpg" n="2"/>colony was present. Until midnight, six barrels of beer were consumed; then a brawl started. Knives and hatchets came into action and a near-riot ensued. The hand of Jacob Augustyn was almost hacked off, and Joseph Golen was wounded in the face. The chief offenders, Golen and Komiski, were arrested and will be duly punished."</p>
   <p>These two items are only samples of what can be regularly found in this or that Polish-American newspaper. It is deplorable news. It seems to prove that many of our countrymen who have come to this free land do not attempt to raise themselves to the level of true American civilization. That civilization depends, among other things, upon observance of laws, peaceableness, and temperance. Some of our countrymen cannot seem to enjoy themselves except by starting with liquor and ending with a brawl.</p>
   <p>The results of these incidents are very unpleasant to us. Disturbances caused by a few cast an unpleasant reflection on all of us and create a very unfavorable opinion of Poles in general, to say nothing of the sin <pb facs="5423968_2_0522.jpg" n="3"/>against God and the damage to health and property, for these are obvious to everybody.</p>
   <p>These violent methods of entertainment among the Poles in America must be brought to an end. Drunkenness, scandals, and brawls ought to cease. The Polish newspapers, priests, and societies ought to take a strong stand on this problem. Let us severely condemn all such outbreaks, let us never cease repeating that such outbreaks are scandalous and harmful and that they must stop. Let serious people teach the youth, wives their husbands, and parents their children the infamy of entertainment which leads to bestiality and crime, and surely there will be some results.</p>
   <p>No one denies anyone else the right to decent entertainment. One can dance and enjoy oneself and drink a glass of beer on occasion; but to drink like swine and to engage in subsequent brawls with knives and hatchets is a sin, a disgrace, and a crime.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
