<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-19">Dec. 19, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Enemies of Labor Unions</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1406</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1406.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-19">Dec. 19, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">ENEMIES OF LABOR UNIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American Association of Manufacturers recently held a convention in Chicago, at which the greatest potentates of the financial world, representing many millions of dollars in all sorts of investments, were present.</p>
   <p>Naturally, on this occasion the representatives of organized capital made many speeches, exhorting one another to become better organized against the enemy of capitalism, as organized labor is called. Of course, unions were subjected to a great deal of condemnation, just because, in defense of their just rights, they dare oppose capitalism. Among the speakers at the convention was John Kirby, Jr., president of the American Association of Manufacturers, who attacked the labor unions in an arrogant manner. He declared that such organizations as the American Federation of Labor, directed by such leaders as Gompers and Mitchell, are worse for the country and public peace than the <pb facs="5423968_2_1407.jpg" n="2"/>bands of Chinese Boxers or the criminal Italian secret societies "Mafia" and "Camorra".</p>
   <p>According to this furious enemy of organized labor, we should, for the good of society, pass a law definitely prohibiting workers from organizing.</p>
   <p>Several other millionaire industrialists spoke in the same vein and the rest applauded them enthusiastically.</p>
   <p>To strengthen their arguments against organized labor, the industrialists cited the case of the brothers McNamara, confessed terrorists, saying that such bombings are inspired and supported by labor unions; and that Gompers and Mitchell must have known about this plot, even if now when the crime has come to light, they pretend indignation against the criminals and deny having any connection with them.</p>
   <p>Such statements by the representatives of capitalism are an insult to all <pb facs="5423968_2_1408.jpg" n="3"/>organized workers--they are nothing else but malicious and impudent lies calculated to discredit the workers, who fearlessly and legally fight to improve the conditions of their existence.</p>
   <p>No sensible person will believe that the labor unions want to attain their rights by means of dynamiting plots, as he would have sense enough to realize that organized labor can never reach its goal by such tactics. To label several millions of organized workers as criminals because of the crimes of some individuals, is refined malice, worthy of the capitalistic leeches, who want to make the workers slaves, just as they did formerly with the negroes in the Southern States.</p>
   <p>Let the organization by the workers into one powerful and united mass be our reply to these attacks. The aim of the unions should be to incorporate into their ranks all unorganized workers, as herein alone lies their victory. By making admission into the unions or craft guilds difficult, the workers <pb facs="5423968_2_1409.jpg" n="4"/>already organized are bringing harm upon themselves, since they are creating strikebreakers, who are tools in the hands of capital. The blame for lost strikes can be laid upon the unorganized workers, who take the places of the union men when the latter strike, thus harming the labor cause and helping the capitalists to win.</p>
   <p>If all the workers of this country were organized, there would be no strikes, no unemployment, and capitalists such as Mr. Kirby would refrain from making unfounded charges against them. Capital wants to take advantage of the McNamara case to discredit the unions in the eyes of the public at large, thus arresting their further development.</p>
   <p>Capital is a relentless enemy, splendidly organized, and the struggle against it will not cease until the workers are strongly organized and unified.</p>
   <p>But experienced, energetic and, above all, honest people are needed to accomplish this great task. The workers should exercise great care in <pb facs="5423968_2_1410.jpg" n="5"/>choosing their leaders, avoiding such people as McManigal, McNamara, Shee, Enright, Gentleman, and similar scoundrels and politicians, who harm the great labor cause instead of helping it. Through such brawlers and even ordinary criminals, all workers suffer and their cause is set back rather than advanced.</p>
   <p>These are enemies of the unions, who help organized capital shatter the great labor cause.</p>
   <p>The battle between the two great powers, capitalism and labor, is furious and relentless and cannot end until organized workers reach a state of enlightenment in which, instead of quarreling among themselves and blocking the way for unorganized workers to join their unions, they will draw the latter towards themselves in order to teach them, thus creating a power before which almighty, relentless capital, the enemy or organized labor, will have to bend.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
