<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-07">Jan. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Disagreement in the Polish Press</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1296</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1296.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-07">Jan. 7, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">DISAGREEMENT IN THE POLISH PRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The last number of Zgoda was to be one of a peaceful nature. Various polemic articles and correspondence have been set aside, according to an agreement of the editors. It is apparent that harmony, unity, and cooperation are finally wanted.</p>
   <p>But what kind of articles? Those who have written them are going to shoulder heavy responsibilities. Every unprejudiced person, who desires unity and peace must suffer the consequences of these news stories. Such items should not be published if this union is to be attained, they should never reach the public eye, and true facts should never be misrepresented. For example, Mr. Karlokowski has asked for a vote, and had the motion affirmed relative to the protest against Russian and German oppression of Poland. Immediately following, Rev. Father Barzynski asked for a vote to oppose the proposed protest against Germany because this may change her attitude towards the <pb facs="5423968_2_1297.jpg" n="2"/>Polish minority. Not only that, but Germany has granted the demands of this group. Rev. Father D. Stablewski has been appointed bishop of the Posen province, and the Polish tongue has been permitted to be taught in the schools. Since Germany has become liberal-minded toward Poland, Father Barzynski pointed out, it would be wrong for this protest to be made, for everything that has been gained would be lost. As a result, the Poles abroad would not only suffer, but over 20,000 Poles in Chicago would probably have their jobs jeopardized. This caused a controversy, mostly because some of the questions and replies were misunderstood. The argument came to an end through the timely suggestion of the presiding chairman, Peter Kiolbassa, who called the meeting to an end, and lead the entire assemblage to church. Here prayers were offered for the success of the mass meeting.</p>
   <p>Why were these facts twisted, why were they so grossly misrepresented? Why is it that the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> which desires peace and unity, did not publish the copy of the minutes of the secretary of the mass meeting as was requested <pb facs="5423968_2_1298.jpg" n="3"/>by the Dziennik Chicagoski, and as was agreed upon? Why were the results of the meeting padded with different meaning? Is this the right road to understanding and cooperation? Is not this a deliberate attack? Let those officials and members of the Polish National Alliance that desire unity answer.</p>
   <p>The results of the article that appeared in the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> are summarized as follows: The protest plans of the committee of Fifteen were made in too much of a hurry. The Alliance is going to support this protest, but on different grounds, and after an understanding with our people abroad, along with the study of the situation has been made. Therefore, join the Alliance, and help this cause.</p>
   <p>It would be better for you, gentlemen, to take interest in these mass meetings and attend them. Your suggestions may become very helpful and useful. Instead, you are trying to create an independent stand. Then why are you asking for unity in this work? The mass gathering of January 1 <pb facs="5423968_2_1299.jpg" n="4"/>was just a beginning in our efforts to help our unfortunate people in Europe. Others are to follow, and the subject is <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> to be discussed more thoroughly. Open discussions will be held. why do you not make these gatherings more successful, why not have your ablest men represent the organization? They will see for themselves that many other minority groups participate. Why not follow the resolutions of the majority as we do? This step would be more favorable than the one which is being followed. Do not arouse the wrath of <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> by twisting the true <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> which have been proposed by the Committee. Do not depend on a solution of this problem on the action of the next Congress at Washington, D. C. This kind of attitude will not bring about a peaceful settlement of our differences.</p>
   <p>The mere statement made by you "that the government has already taken certain steps to solve the question of Poland in order to have this before Congress, that the government is going to use various means in voicing its protests against the violent offenses of the three conquering nations of Poland, and <pb facs="5423968_2_1300.jpg" n="5"/>then if we are convinced of favorable results shown by the next Congress, which is practically Republican, towards Poland, we will act." It is impossible to convince anyone through debates. This is hardly sufficient for such a grave problem. You want to be convinced first that this will bring results, and then agree upon it. Gentlemen, gentlemen, this is not the road to mutual agreement.</p>
   <p>Come to the next meeting if you have a desire. Familiarize yourselves with the procedure, but do not resort to the unpleasant road of distorting the news in the paper, for you will never be able to get the support of the press in general for many years to come. Let our papers serve us an instrument which will present our problem in an understanding manner. By enlightening the world at large with clear facts we will be able to elevate public opinion, and gain its assistance. Let our papers play this role, and public opinion will be with us. Let us not make it a battlefield for controversy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1301.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>This is the role we should play. This is the road we should take. There is no other way, no other route to solidarity. Drop any ideas of what Washington is going to do about the Polish question to the wayside, Let all of us strive to create better public opinion about our beloved country; let us become the guiding star for future betterment of our cause. Let us help those people who are trying to win a place in the world. Let Congress, as soon as it wishes, offer its help, but the freedom of making laws and resolutions should be left to the public.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
