<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-07-01">July 1, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Graduation Exercises of St. Stanislaus Kostka College</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0165</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0165.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-07-01">July 1, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">GRADUATION EXERCISES OF ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA COLLEGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The beautiful graduation exercises of the St. Stanislaus Kostka College were held Monday evening, in the large school hall on Bradley Street. The entire program was wonderful.</p>
   <p>Following the opening by the orchestra, Mr. Szezesny Zahajkiewicz spoke (in the absence of the rector, Reverend J. Kruszynski, who was indisposed).</p>
   <p>The program included music, recitations in different languages, singing, a monologue, and three plays--two Polish and one English.</p>
   <p>The students, Bocian, Sobieszczyk, W. Kwiatkowski, and F. Gums, recited well.</p>
   <p>The singing was fine, and the humorous monologue by K. Cylerski entitled "Anorzej Wytryszek" was given with freedom and understanding.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0166.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The high points of the program were the two plays given by the students.</p>
   <p>The first was a delightful paraphrase of Michiewicz's "Powrot Taty" (Father's Return), written by Szezesny Zahajkiewicz. The drama was very interesting and was well acted. The scenery, the costumes, and the entire ensemble was magical. The students acting as thieves, a merchant, and as children gave a creditable performance. The following deserve special mention: Sobieszczyk, Gastka, Bocian Nagornik, Mucha, and Lasecki.</p>
   <p>In the second play, "Nastancy, " (In a Boarding House), Kondziorski a student of the College, was outstanding in the role of Mikus. The play is very comical but at the same time moral. The other actors also played well. Konopa, as Szlubalski, was an excellent pedagogue and Pierucki, was a good second. Bloch, and Lasecki gave a good account of themselves as two students.</p>
   <p>The students also rendered a part of "The Merchant of Venice" in English.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0167.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Everything was flawless.</p>
   <p>This is a good proof of the ability and thoroughness of the students, and of the careful, patient labors of the rector of the College, Reverend J. Kruszynski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
