<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-07">Sept. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Defend the Polish National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1040</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1040.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-09-07">Sept. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">DEFEND THE POLISH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As often as Dziennik Zwiazkowy has requested the members of the Polish National Alliance to defend their organization vehemently against harmful articles, so often has a bevy of human wasps been aroused, reverberating in all camps antagonistic to the ideals of the Alliance. Some begin to complain that an injustice is being done them, similar to the fanatic Germans who preach about saving Germanism whenever they see a Pole making the sign of the cross in the Polish language. Others take the matter somewhat higher. By adding new calumnies to the old, they state that the people who work for the Alliance would prefer to do away with all criticism. Again the third group--these are the worst, write some new personal satires designed to bring the Alliance into a contemptuous light. This type denounces the Alliance in an easy but biting fashion, charging that it occupies itself in politics, giving one to understand that mutual aid societies are not permitted to do things of that type.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1041.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These enemies do not favor unity or patriotism, and are opposed to any organized effort made by the Alliance to defend itself. They would rather have the organization gag itself and surrender to their caprices. They are permitted to attack the Alliance, to besmirch people who give their utmost effort to serve the organization. They assume the right to fabricate the most hideous calumnies, to bring about dissension, to destroy every sincere endeavor. But, according to them, we are not allowed to warn our brethren to be wary, to step upon the necks of these reptiles and answer attacks with attacks. In what other way can useful type of work develop among the immigrants? How is the Alliance to grow and develop, how are we to have any peace if the people themselves fail to defend their own interests? This is impossible unless the right-thinking people repudiate this entire band of liars, conspirators and others of their ilk.</p>
   <p>These foes charge that we deny them the right of criticism. But did they ever attempt to criticize anything in a sincere and proper manner? Are calumnies, denunciations, lies, casting of the lowest form of insinuations, are these criticisms? Nothing with which they conduct battle is criticism but is common slander.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1042.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Could they classify the recent article about the Alliance Immigration Home as criticism? There were forty lies contained in only ten paragraphs, and all of them directed against the Alliance. And, again, can the articles about the feast of Washington, or the items spread in the personal satires be considered criticism? The Alliance has neither heard nor seen any sincere criticism for the post decade, criticism that might come from honest, sane and right-thinking people. Perhaps we have been fortunate to hear some constructive criticism from a few sensible delegates, who have taken a different viewpoint from ours on certain questions. These people would express their opinions with no malice, with no harmful intent, but, on the contrary, from their good will and for a definite purpose. But, unfortunately, criticisms of that type are not too frequent since they are voiced but once in every two years--at the biennial conventions of the Polish National Alliance.</p>
   <p>Make an honest criticism and the people will treat you with respect. The readers will gain some value from your articles. Do not fill your newspapers with people who breathe venomous hatred against their fellow brethren working in the Alliance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1043.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Do not drive away good people who at times find their way to you. Do not demoralize your co-workers with the unconditional command to kill the Alliance.</p>
   <p>As long as lies, attacks, calumnies are your sole pretext at criticism, we will defend the Alliance to our utmost ability. We will ask the members of our organization to pay no heed to your "criticism." By so doing we will compel you to criticize properly that which you consider deserving of criticism.</p>
   <p>Your greatest error lies in the fact that your hatred toward the institution is transferred to other people. This institution gives these people its confidence. The things these people plan, talk of, accomplish or write, is not considered by you as bad. You are indignant because they, and not you or your friends, do these things: If your people were at the head of the Alliance and worked in the same way as the present officials work, your praise for everything they did would reach beyond the heights of heaven.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1044.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We, as workers of the Alliance, are not harmed by your "criticism." The people of this organization are wise and know how to distinguish falsehood from truth, criticism from calumny. The people judge that when charges are made against someone by people who are capable of calumny, lies or insinuations, hence, by people who are decidedly evil, then that person whom they attack so vehemently must, most probably, possess some [good] quality.</p>
   <p>But, although you do not injure any of us personally, you do, however, harm the Alliance. You are unable to break it because it is too strong and too vast for you. You could, however, frighten away people who are as yet unacquainted with it; people who are unaware, suspicious, persons who are easily misled. A member of the Alliance, after reading your "criticism" of the Immigration Home, for example, where you have purposely enlarged the modest salaries which the Alliance is to pay the workers at this Home, we repeat, a member of the Alliance, after reading such lies will only look at them with contempt. A more vehement person will express his opinion of you. But a man newly arrived from Europe, who does <pb facs="5423968_2_1045.jpg" n="6"/>not as yet know you, after reading some of your calumnies might repudiate the Alliance and refuse to join it. And because your "criticism" harms the Alliance, we ask, and will not cease asking of all members of the Alliance: Defend the Polish National Alliance! Do not allow your workers to be insulted by any upstart. Prevent him from presenting the honest work in a false light and thus harming the organization. Cast out all papers that busy themselves with lies, and you will see how quickly these papers will reform and will find space for truthful criticism. When these attacks end and proper criticism begins, then will our members renew their support of private periodicals according to their tastes.</p>
   <p>The members of the Alliance are therefore implored to take an active part in uprooting these slanderous newspapers and articles, and they will see that a considerable reform will follow within a space of one month. The "critics" should lay stress on less hatred and more consideration for the general welfare. If they observe this they will then note that conditions will be better for them, because instead of the present contempt they will merit respect in the eyes of the people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
