<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-24">Jan. 24, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">In the Interest of Clerks Working in Dry Goods Stores</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1513</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1513.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-01-24">Jan. 24, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE INTEREST OF CLERKS WORKING IN DRY GOODS STORES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The unfortunate position of clerks employed in the large dry goods establishments is well known to everyone. In order to satisfy the needs of the public, more especially of the working classes, they work not only on week days but on Sundays as well. On Saturdays and Mondays their hours stretch far into the night.</p>
   <p>It is easy to understand how much they must suffer from this overwork. While the average working man is free to rest on Sunday, they must put in at least half a day's hard work. On ordinary week days, they are often at work until eleven or twelve o'clock, satisfying the demands of customers.</p>
   <p>It would be practically impossible to release the clerks in the stores, especially those stores patronized by Poles, from late evening or Sunday work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1514.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Poles are mostly poor working people, whose only leisure time for making purchases is often Sunday or a weekday evening--usually pay day, which generally falls on Saturday or Monday. To close the stores at such times would be to inflict a wrong upon them; moreover, it would harm the business interests of the store owners. Thus, when the large dry goods and clothing stores on the Northwest Side shut down completely on Sundays during summer and autumn of last year, the desired result was not attained. The small businessmen did not close their shops, and the people, instead of doing business with the large stores, patronized them. As a result, protection of their own business interests necessitated their resumption of Sunday hours. At present, however, a new step has been taken in this direction. In our opinion--providing the buying public co-operates--this plan could materially relieve the conditions under which the clerks, among whom are to be found so many Poles, work. Representatives of the largest stores or the Northwest Side, especially of those in the vicinity of Milwaukee Avenue, held a meeting on January 17 at Shoenhofen's Hall. They decided that they would all close their stores on Wednesday and Friday evenings at six o'clock. Thus their clerks, working usually from seven in the morning to <pb facs="5423968_2_1515.jpg" n="3"/>ten o'clock at night, or--taking off an hour for meals--fourteen hours per day, will have at least two free evenings per week, which they can devote either to their families or to amusement. Again, these free evenings will permit numerous small boys and girls (so-called "cash-boys" and "cash-girls") to attend evening school or to further their education in some other way.</p>
   <p>The advantages this decision will bring to a whole regiment of hard-pressed workers are obvious. In creating this respite, the employers have done their part. It remains for the public to co-operate. If the public desires this relief to be permanent, it should refrain from making purchases at stores open after six o'clock on Wednesday and Friday evenings. Otherwise, those stores which have given relief to their employees, will be forced to rescind their decision because of harmful competition. Such action would be a loss to the clerks, among whom are so many of our brothers and sisters. We present this matter to the Poles of Chicago, convinced that they will want to do something to help their countrymen and neighbors in the name of brotherly love.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
