<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VI, No. 50,
<date when="1902-12-10">December 10, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">What Is Drunkenness?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0509</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0509.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VI, No. 50,
<date when="1902-12-10">December 10, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS DRUNKENNESS?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is evil in this world beyond measure; undoubtedly no source provides more of it than drunkenness, and from no other cause do so many different and terrible results arise.</p>
   <p>Liquor brings along with it not only one evil but a long series of the most terrible misfortunes to which a human being is exposed, such as sickness, poverty, crime, insanity, and family quarrels. It is not only that drunkenness heaps upon a human being every degradation, not enough that those nearest to him suffer on account of him, but it even awakens in them the harshest kind of feelings because it brings contempt and dislike and something nasty and disrespectful to humankind.</p>
   <p>If a drunkard could realize what he was doing he probably would not get drunk a second time. A man has the feeling of power and superiority over all other creatures and things. He subjugates animals and puts them to his use. He gets minerals from the depths and plants from the surface of the earth. The very earth and water serve him in various ways. Man does not submit to them but controls them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0510.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As a whole, man does not like superiority and his natural tendency is to use to the utmost that precious gift of God - free will. Where conditions, distress, or some perversity are contradictory to man he puts up resistance and rebels. Wherever he feels a preponderance over himself, he yields involuntarily, but wherever he can, he puts through his own will. Let someone reflect now and say whether it is not ridiculous that man who occupies a ruling position over God's creations should allow himself to be deprived of this position by a glass of whiskey. He opposes all predominance and surely will not let any passerby seize him by the collar and allow himself to be led where he does not wish to go. This same man lets himself humbly be put under the power of the whiskey glass and allows liquor to rule him.</p>
   <p>Is it not so? It is certain that when you are drunk you have less willpower than a dog or a horse, because they at least have control over their legs and walk straight, and you have not even the power over your own legs and even if you would like to walk in the middle of the sidewalk, you step into the gutter or ditch.</p>
   <p>When you are drunk the will-power of man that you possess, which distinguishes you from an animal, does not even have control over your hand, which strikes <pb facs="5423968_2_0511.jpg" n="3"/>where you do not wish and you don't know why. You even have no control of your tongue then, and you say things that you would not say if you were sober. You tattle, wave your hands, holler on the street like a lunatic, and serve as an object of ridicule and a bad example to youth.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately this is not the end of the bad effects which are caused by whiskey; a hundred times worse is the destruction, so visible, that it leaves scars deep upon the body and changes the whole organism of the man. It brings upon him various diseases which may be carried over to his children and grand children. The miserable and pale child, his bad character and many faults, are only the continuation of the evil which before God is on the conscience of the drunkard.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
