<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-09">Dec. 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Rioting Increasing in Stockyards</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1712</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1712.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-09">Dec. 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">RIOTING INCREASING IN STOCKYARDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday afternoon riots again broke out in some of the districts where packing houses are located. Despite the order issued by Judge Sullivan that rioting and picketing was to be stopped, the workers continued to pelt the strikebreakers with bricks.</p>
   <p>Because yesterday was pay day all the strategic points in the area of the packing houses were filled with milling strikers. When the police tried to disperse the mobs they were showered with stones and bolts from the windows of the nearby homes. The women, with paper bags filled with paprika, flung the powder into the eyes of the police, rendering them temporarily blind.</p>
   <p>One of the major outbreaks of the afternoon occurred at 44th Street and Marshfield Avenue, where throngs of people had gathered since early morning.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1713.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was apparent that the strikers were awaiting the unfaithful workers. The police were on guard at all important points.</p>
   <p>About four o'clock, the vast mob commenced to become impatient, and began to dominate the entire street. As the police made an attempt to hold back the pushing crowd, a variety of missiles and several shots issued from the windows of the adjoining houses. The mounted police arrived in the midst of this tumult and they tried time and time again to disperse the maddening crowd, but the boisterous strikers would not budge. They held their ground with the yelling of "Down with the Cossacks." The police fired about three hundred shots in an effort to scare the tumultuous multitude. This rioting continued for over an hour, when droves of people finally began to leave. Hundreds were arrested.</p>
   <p>A second important street encounter took place at 48th Street and Racine Avenue. Here again a woman, Miss Sophia Horoska, threw herself at five <pb facs="5423968_2_1714.jpg" n="3"/>policemen who were patrolling the area. One of the officers fell to the ground as he was struck on the head with a club. Meanwhile Miss Horoska escaped with her colleagues. When the police made an attempt to extricate her from one of the homes, they were showered with paprika, but after a long while the officers succeeded in making the arrest.</p>
   <p>On Bishop Street, the police were vitually showered with revolver shots. When a search was made of the home from which the shots had issued, the guns were found empty. However, the tenant was located, and was arrested.</p>
   <p>John Jaraszunas was seized flinging bricks at the police, and was taken to the station in a squad car.</p>
   <p>On South May Street, a mob stoned the home of one of the strikebreakers. The police officers succeeded in dispersing the hundred odd persons, and they arrested one man named Omasta, who had assaulted an officer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1715.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A woman was arrested at 49th Street and Racine Avenue when she flung an empty bottle at a mounted policeman, striking him with such force that he dropped to the street.</p>
   <p>About two thousand persons attacked workers leaving for home from the Armour Glue Company, but police managed to scatter them.</p>
   <p>A freshly emptied whiskey barrel was found at a home numbered 48 at 48th Street and Racine Avenue (sic).</p>
   <p>The unsuccessful attempts of the strikers did not discourage them in the least, and when they were dispersed from one place they only congregated at another to continue their rioting.</p>
   <p>One of the important officials of the department for enforcing prohibition, Charles H. Gregory, revealed that prohibition officers are working quietly <pb facs="5423968_2_1716.jpg" n="5"/>and diligently in the area of the Stockyards and that all saloons selling illegal liquor will be closed and fined.</p>
   <p>"Victory for the strikers is certain," said the secretary - cashier of the Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workers (sic) yesterday. He added, "Over 22,500 persons are taking part in the strike." Statements from other cities where strikes are taking place show that the strike action is leaning in their favor. The union officials are demanding that the ten per cent cut in pay affecting all packing house workers be canceled. Stockyards' officials have stated that they will not negotiate with the workers on the principle of shop representation, which was recently adopted.</p>
   <p>W. B. Farris, general superintendent of Morris and Company, stated that meat production has reached its minimum. According to him, the plant is in a position to supply the public with meat with the additional <pb facs="5423968_2_1717.jpg" n="6"/>hiring of men from time to time.</p>
   <p>Judge Sullivan, who issued the order that the strike be stopped, admitted that the strikers have permission to mingle with others, but that a boundary line should exist, which would not infringe upon the rights of others. Stock should be taken of the situation and a line should be drawn which would be advantageous to those who have the right to be on that side, and yet would be disadvantageous to trespassers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
