<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IX, No. 52,
<date when="1905-12-27">December 27, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Marriage and Health</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0604</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0604.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IX, No. 52,
<date when="1905-12-27">December 27, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">MARRIAGE AND HEALTH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two people, until recently entirely strange to each other and reared under different conditions, suddenly get married and through a mutual relationship give to the world a new generation.</p>
   <p>We see, however, that each one of those new generations is a little weaker, despite the advance of hygiene and medicine. There must be involved in this, a fundamental reason.</p>
   <p>Society needs healthy and strong people - in no other way can it exist. It is necessary, therefore, to earnestly reflect on the cause of the degeneration of our future generations.</p>
   <p>It is beyond doubt that the main reason for this is the concluding of matrimony between persons the least, if not very little, capable to give to the world healthy offspring, because they are sick.</p>
   <p>The young men, by leading a gay life, destroy their life's strength, exhaust <pb facs="5423968_2_0605.jpg" n="2"/>their organism, ruin their health, and with the remaining strength go forth to the altar.</p>
   <p>The same can be said about the woman's thoughtless tribute to style, toilette; persons perpetually weak, sickly, constantly moaning, sometimes impatient, frequently unfit to be mothers and, at least, not capable of fulfilling all duties of motherhood.</p>
   <p>Compressed from early girlhood into a corset, dressed, in the summer with hoods and fiddle-daddles and in the winter as a grown lady, in tight patent leather shoes, she catches cold becomes pale, and next a whole series of illnesses which are slumbering within the young lady and wake up with all their might in a married woman, creating a hospital in the home of her husband.</p>
   <p>Naturally, a couple so matched gives fruit as good as the trunk; a cancerous tree does not give smooth and good looking fruit.</p>
   <p>The American people are entirely justified in trying to prevent marriages between people who are not healthy, and they are right even if only for the <pb facs="5423968_2_0606.jpg" n="3"/>fact that sickly children born from such marriages, sooner or later, become burdens to society, sucking up the sap of its very life.</p>
   <p>It would be well if young people could only enter wedlock after presenting to an official of a civil state a certificate of health, stating satisfactory health conditions of both parties. Then there would be a decrease of unfortunate marriages; youths will care for their health, mothers will not look so thoughtlessly upon extravagances of style and more oftener will reflect upon the requirements relative to the regulations of hygiene.</p>
   <p>Maybe the young men would gradually cease their fast life; more than one father would more forcibly keep his beloved son from smoking cigarettes and drinking liquor while still tied to a school desk, because he will think that this might be the very thing to prevent this son from a successful marriage.</p>
   <p>Today, this delicate subject does not allow two people, engaged to each other, to present such demands, but when the law will make such a thing compulsory, the order will be received by all with thanks, that as a result of this they <pb facs="5423968_2_0607.jpg" n="4"/>can all rest assured that there will be a decrease in persons placing the load of their fruitless lives on the shoulders of society.</p>
   <p>Finally, if a man without scruples inquires as to the amount of his sweetheart's dowry and the young lady as to the income of her fiance, it will also be natural for either one of them to inquire as to their health condition, which indeed is much more valuable that the total amount of all the dowries put together.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
