<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-26">July 26, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Printers Association</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Poles in Chicago)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1591</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1591.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-07-26">July 26, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH PRINTERS ASSOCIATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Poles in Chicago)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a result of the statement printed in our Chicago publications during the past week, an imposing number of Polish printers and compositors gathered at the office of Dziennik Chicagoski for the purpose of forming an association that would be adequate to their needs. The meeting was opened by Mr. Migdalski, who was also elected president at this meeting, and the undersigned was elected secretary.</p>
   <p>The entire meeting had the character of a personal chat, revealing mutual understanding, and a desire to build a firm foundation undor this new type of association in America. This worthy aim was achieved. All the delegates declared that an association of printers and compositors was necessary and good.</p>
   <p>At this meeting it was decided to organize also an association for the purpose of teaching the printer's art, and of sponsoring programs and lectures in all the ramifications of historical knowledge; further it was decided to try to bring about an improvement in the living standards of the members by seeking employment <pb facs="5423968_2_1592.jpg" n="2"/>for them, and giving them assistance in sickness and death. It was decided to charge one dollar as the initiation fee, and monthly dues of twenty-five cents. The other motions pertaining to sick and death benefits will depend upon the decision of all when the constitution has been formulated and accepted.</p>
   <p>After further discussion it was decided that our new association should take an active part in all matters essential to our Polish immigration, but it will be self-sustaining and independent and will not become combined with any Polish or American organization.</p>
   <p>At this meeting twenty-six members enrolled. The following members were chosen to formulate the constitution: Messrs. Migdalski, Olbinski, Zagorski, Sosnowski, Gorecki, Zloczewski, and Majchrzycki.</p>
   <p>The next meeting will be held at the same place, on Sunday, August 7, 1892, at two-thirty in the afternoon, to which we invite all colleagues.</p>
   <p>J. Olbinski, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
