<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-07-12">July 12, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Reflections after the Strike</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1615</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1615.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-07-12">July 12, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">REFLECTIONS AFTER THE STRIKE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Unfortunately, the strike is almost lost. The Poles did not commit any outrages or lawless acts during the strike. This is a fact. The Poles were only victims of those acts.</p>
   <p>Pullman, the hypocrite and exploiter of workingmen, is responsible for all that has happened. His name will be written with black letters in the history of the United States. His refusal to arbitrate is an act which is being condemned even by most capitalistic newspapers.</p>
   <p>Who plundered and burned the freight cars? Perhaps the deputies of the United States Marshal. At all events not the Poles.</p>
   <p>As far as the general strike was concerned, "There was a great storm but very <pb facs="5423968_2_1616.jpg" n="2"/>little rain" [a Polish proverb].</p>
   <p>One more question: Why was there no announcement that on Saturday the soldiers would "shoot to kill"? Why was no one warned before the shooting began?</p>
   <p>We were and still are with the workingmen--against the capitalists who exploit them. But we are always with the law and against outrages and violence.</p>
   <p>Debs fought like a man.</p>
   <p>Even the Tribune condemns Pullman for his stubbornness. Even the Tribune maintains that he should have submitted the grievances to arbitration. His failure to do so will prove very costly.</p>
   <p>The railroad companies have won, but let them not triumph. Above them there still is public opinion, which will not allow the working people to be crushed. The whole American nation condemns Pullman for his stand.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1617.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Catholic Gazette maintains that the railroad employees perhaps might have accomplished more by contributing a dollar a week for the strikers in Pullman than by starting a dangerous strike. This may be so, but no one should be discouraged by one failure.</p>
   <p>Anyhow, this great strike taught us something. The government should control the relations between capital and labor through an arbitration board. There is no doubt but that such a board for handling disputes between capital and labor must be established.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
