<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-01-31">Jan. 31, 1908</date><title level="a">Trusts</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1456</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1456.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-01-31">Jan. 31, 1908</date><title level="a">TRUSTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is a great change going on throughout the world today. It is an economical revolution and is causes by organized capital, which is controlled by international financiers. This is being accomplished by the consolidation of great industries into powerful corporations, called trusts; and is done for the purpose of removing competition, thereby paining control of market prices, which will, in turn assure them a high and steady income, and also give them power to carry on an effective fight with organized labor.</p>
   <p>They abolished competition, but did they accomplish anything by it? Of what benefit to man is the abolition of competition and steadier employment, if the capitalists make a slave of him? Of what benefit is productive energy? Of what use is that mysterious faculty, called initiative, if a man allows himself, and sometimes is compelled, to use it for exploiting his mentally weaker, fellowmen?</p>
   <p>Of what benefit to man are high wages, when the prices of the necessities of life are raised out of proportion. Some capitalists claim to be great arbitrators for working class, but simultaneously, they teach you by their own action, to loathe work, they teach greed, an easy way to make money, how to live in luxury, and to indulge in all kinds of pleasures.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1457.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Those who favor trusts, will not dare deny that the great luxuries enjoyed by the Morgans, Rockefellers, Vanderbilts, and other multimillionaires are causing sighs among the working classes.</p>
   <p>Any one who looks at the world with open eyes can see that trusts will not bring happiness to the world, they are spreaders of corruption.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
