<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-01">Apr. 1, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Coming Election</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1251</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1251.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-04-01">Apr. 1, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE COMING ELECTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a few days election day will be upon us. In tomorrow's and Monday's issues, we will publish a facsimile of the ballots to be used. We will point out to our readers the proper procedure to be followed when casting a vote for a candidate. Although the people have been instructed along this line at many political meetings and through the daily papers, it is our contention that there are still many persons who don't make out the ballot right, making it valueless. Therefore, in the next two issues we are going to give special attention to the proper method of making out the ballot.</p>
   <p>We wish to point out that it is the duty of every naturalized Pole to make use of his right to vote. Under no circumstances should he disregard this privilege, and those who are qualified to vote but do not, are unworthy of being called citizens of the United States.</p>
   <p>In the United States the people govern the country. From a political point of view, this form of government ranks higher than any other form <pb facs="5423968_2_1252.jpg" n="2"/>of government in other countries. Here the people make the laws and elect individuals to fill the various offices of the government. Because the people as a whole cannot agree upon certain issues, they elect persons to represent them. These representatives are given the instructions that they are to follow. Political factions represent the ideals of different groups, and the stronger a certain group gets in office, the more certain are its ideals or proposals to be adopted. But if the members of any party are indifferent and do not vote, it will be easier for the opposing side to win. It can rightfully be said that those who don't vote are the ones that neglect their privilege of governing the country.</p>
   <p>This is how we choose our city, county, and state officials, and finally our Federal officers.</p>
   <p>Next week we are to elect city and district officials.</p>
   <p>This day is of especial importance to the Poles because certain Polish candidates are running for office. Let there be no one that will shirk his duty as a citizen, for it is his privilege in this free country to pick the candidate he wants.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
