<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-29">Jan. 29, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Resolutions Attaching Mr. Wladyslaw Dyniewicz as Adopted by All the Polish Printers in Chicago, Illinois</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1573</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1573.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-29">Jan. 29, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTIONS ATTACHING MR. WLADYSLAW DYNIEWICZ AS ADOPTED BY ALL THE POLISH PRINTERS IN CHICAGO, ILLINOIS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Correspondence)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Friday evening, January 24, 1896, a meeting was held by all the Polish printers in Chicago at Mr. Lechert's hall, the corner of Division and Cleaver Streets, for the purpose of expressing indignation against the inhuman actions of Mr. Wladyslaw Dyniewicz, the owner of a printing shop.</p>
   <p>In the year 1894, during the general depression, a strike broke out in Mr. Dyniewicz's plant because the wages of all employees were cut in half (regardless of ability or many years of service), and the same conditions of labor were demanded as before.</p>
   <p>Mr. Dyniewicz then gathered his numerous family, even from distant points, <pb facs="5423968_2_1574.jpg" n="2"/>and decided to stick to his demands, meanwhile doing All the work with the help of his sons and daughters. It was therefore difficult for us to win. Some returned to work; others decided to find jobs elsewhere. The friends of these injured workers, deploring the conduct of Mr. Dyniewicz, decided to come to their aid. No sooner did Mr. Dyniewicz hear of the organization of the Polish Printers' Association of Chicago, than he immediately forbade his workers to join it under the threat of losing their jobs.</p>
   <p>A couple of months later, taking advantage of the cheap wages paid to his workers, he made an offer to the central administration of the Polish National Alliance to print the Egoda (Peace), the organ of the Alliance, a few dollars cheaper than the printing shop of Mr. Gladyslaw Smulski; but because the Polish Printers' Association protested and because of the well-known profiteering methods of Mr. Dyniswicz, the central administration of the Polish National Alliance rejected the offer.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1575.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In 1895, the Polish Printers' Association signed written agreements with practically all of the Polish print shops in regard to the scale of wages to be paid to the workers. They agreed without any difficulty on the terms submitted by the typesetters.</p>
   <p>However, it was different with Mr. Dyniewicz's firm. Receiving no answer to written inquiries, the executive committee decided to call on him in person. To a very polite and respectful question from a member of the committee as to whether he would not like to come to some agreement on the wages for his workers, Mr. Dyniewicz answered by feeling around in his back pockets (evidently looking for a revolver). When he did not find it, he grabbed a Polish flag and began to beat the committee members with it, not sparing epithets like "smarties, thugs, scoundrels, I'll give you a union; I'll give you terus; I'll show you, etc.!"</p>
   <p>In view of such a scandalous and unheard-of attack, we, the Polish Printers <pb facs="5423968_2_1576.jpg" n="4"/>of Chicago, Illinois, assembled this 24th day of January, 1896, do condemn the inhuman and highly improper conduct of Mr. Dyniewicz, and do adopt the following resolutions:</p>
   <p>Whereas, in this land of the free, these United States, all people are equal and should answer a polite question in a polite manner; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, Mr. Dyniewicz treats all of his workers like slaves;</p>
   <p>Whereas, Mr. Dyniewicz arrived here, as all of us did, seeking a livelihood in America, and has gained quite a fortune solely from the poor working Poles;</p>
   <p>Whereas, All of his publications find a market only among us Poles;</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1577.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Whereas, Mr. Dyniewicz has never done anything for the working people or the Polish cause, and instead reprints at will the costliest editions of books by Polish authors abroad, causing their publishers and the Polish European authors considerable loss;</p>
   <p>Whereas, All of this proves quite conclusively that Mr. Dyniewicz has grown rich from the workingman and from works of our Polish literature, that he does not respect the laws of the workers or of literature, but scandalously takes advantage of them; therefore, be it</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we, the Polish printers assembled in a meeting, do condemn the actions of Mr. Dyniewicz most severely and submit then for judgment to public opinion so that everybody may know whom he often supports with his hard-earned money and thus helps to spread profiteering among the Polish people.</p>
   <p>Signed: The Committee</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
