<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>, 
<date when="1908-06-11">June 11, 1908</date><title level="a">Polish People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1054</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1054.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>, 
<date when="1908-06-11">June 11, 1908</date><title level="a">POLISH PEOPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Kyle of Washington, D. C., a prominent marble and stone contractor, was a visitor for three days, at the Polish National Alliance home in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Because of his low bid, the committee on monument building, of the Polish National Alliance, appointed his concern to erect a granite pedestal for the Kosciuszko monument at Washington, D. C.</p>
   <p>My. Kyle, who comes from a family of pioneering Americans, was greatly impressed by our achievements in art, industry, and organization. The assimilation of the English language by the leading Poles received commendable praise from him. Mr. Kyle was overwhelmed by the Polish hospitality, typical of our people and matched only by some of the southern states.</p>
   <p>It was difficult for him to believe all the progress he saw at the Polish settlements. He admitted he had imagined the Poles were a backward race.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1055.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This visit revealed to him the actual facts, and changed his opinion.</p>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance building, with its richly decorated interior, the stately cathedral-like church, the library, the museum, and other establishments offered him conclusive evidence of the great progress and achievement of the Poles.</p>
   <p>In one of his conversations he remarked, "I never expected to find the Polish people enjoying such high financial standing in Chicago." He further stated, "The activities of the Poles in Washington are little known. The English papers seldom mention anything pertaining to them. With shame I must admit that the American newspapers devote very little space to foreign groups and their activities. The information is not only poor but at times misleading. No wonder that I, because of this false information, have been misled into forming an unjust opinion. My visit rights the wrong opinion I have formed <pb facs="5423968_2_1056.jpg" n="3"/>of the Polish race," he admitted with apology.</p>
   <p>"Of course most Americans know of the historical deeds rendered by Kosciuszko and Pulaski, the literary works of Sienkiewicz, the genius of the pianist, Paderewski, and other Poles of fame, but they are accepted as rare exceptions. A conclusion was drawn that the vast majority of them were just fit for tilling the soil or for hard labor, and some have considered them to be corrupt individuals.</p>
   <p>"My visit here has given me an entirely new and revealing aspect of the Polish people. It was almost unbelievable; yet my eyes have seen and my ears have heard. The high standard of living, the culture, and efficiency is amazing," he said.</p>
   <p>One of the delegates of the Polish National Alliance, inquired, "Have you ever tried to know the Poles a little better?"</p>
   <p>"Never," he replied emphatically. "Like most Americans I have judged these <pb facs="5423968_2_1057.jpg" n="4"/>immigrants by what the newspapers have written about them. I believe that the Americans, who do not know you and harbor false opinions, should observe you better through personal contact and observation. A comparison of living and working conditions would readily change their minds. I am certain that they would become your friends and think highly of you."</p>
   <p>My. Kyle mentioned the atrocities inflicted by the Prussian regime on the Poles, deploring this persecution. He lauded the Polish people for their undying fight for freedom and independence. He knew of this from the American newspapers but admitted that even this news was misrepresented and misleading, regarding the true facts of the struggle for liberty.</p>
   <p>After a comprehensive tour and an elaborate reception at the Polish National Alliance House, Mr. Kyle returned to his city with a new feeling and appreciation for the Polish people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
