<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1922-03-20">Mar. 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Our Local Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0848</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0848.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1922-03-20">Mar. 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">OUR LOCAL POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Irish make a holiday of St. Patrick's Day in honor of the patron Saint of Ireland. It is their custom on that day to wear some sort of green emblem which on the whole harmonizes with their faces. In their own way they succeed very well in celebrating their holiday. That is what happens in Ireland. Chicago is not really a part of Ireland; nevertheless the city council of Chicago, of course, not of Cork recently decreed that in the city hall St. Patrick's Day shall be a holiday. God rest you merry, gentleman! Naturally, to the functionaries of the city hall, or to use our customary American language, to the clerks and the other various irks found there, this pronouncement was exceedingly agreeable. Why not? After all, it is a holiday; pay without work. And besides it shows that you are a patriot, an Irish patriot, to be sure, but a patriot nevertheless.</p>
   <p>It means nothing that half these city hall functionaries are descendants of ancestors from Jericho, who take as much interest in an Irish holiday as <pb facs="5423968_2_0849.jpg" n="2"/>Pilsudski takes in the Himalaya mountains. It matters not that in the city hall there are some Germans, some Poles, a number of Italians, and a few Negroes (it is understood most of the latter are porters). All this means nothing. It is enough that the Irish constitute the remainder; this settles it.</p>
   <p>The majority want to celebrate, and the majority is Irish. Who knows? Perhaps next year the city hall will celebrate the Feast of the Tabernacles! Maybe it will be closed on the anniversary of the death of Savonarola. Anything is possible. The present state of affairs proves convincingly who promote, control, and manipulate politics in Chicago. Suffice it to say that the city hall celebrate an Irish national holiday, St. Patrick's Day, and that perhaps next year it will be closed for the Feast of the Tabernacles. This however, would be of little advantage to the city hall or to the city, since the Feast of the Tabernacles drags along about two weeks. This will suffice to clarify our outlook on local ward politics. And there are the politicians who institute this kind of holiday!</p>
   <p>They constitute seventy-five percent of the city hall employees and it is they <pb facs="5423968_2_0850.jpg" n="3"/>who proclaim: "Away with foreigners! We, the only one-hundred-per cent Americans, have the right to hold office and to enjoy special privileges!" And of this sort are the people who sneer at the Poles! It is enough to make a horse laugh.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
