<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-08">May 8, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Wiarus--A Denouncer</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-08">May 8, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">WIARUS--A DENOUNCER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Winona, Minnesota, Wairus, a Polish weekly, with its own "Marcypan" (Polish word, meaning one who eats Mars' bread"), has embraced a new profession worthy of itself. It has become a denouncer.</p>
   <p>We do not mean a denouncer of gossip or a newspaper denouncer striving to bring to light certain matters which it should not expose. No, it has become a denouncer in the broadest sense of the word, a denouncer before the authorities and the courts.</p>
   <p>And whom does it denounce? you ask. It denounces Polish organizations, Polish newspapers, Polish societies. It wishes to bring to them ruin and destruction, court sentences, and bankruptcy. It wishes to bring poverty to Polish widows and orphans.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1143.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This is not an exaggeration, but a fact.</p>
   <p>Let us take in hand (naturally, with the greatest disgust) the last issue of Wiarus.</p>
   <p>It informs us that the infamous chief of Wiarus, or his hideous assistant, Marcypan, wrote letters to the secretaries of various states formally accusing the Polish Roman Catholic Union and the Polish National Alliance, of carrying on a death benefit business illegally. Similar accusations were made or are to be made against the official organs of the Polish Roman Catholic Union (Wiara I Ojczyzna) and the Polish National Alliance (Zgoda), against the Committee to build the Kosciusko Monument, and finally, no doubt, against the entire Polish community.</p>
   <p>This is printed in black and white in the scandalous Wiarus for everybody to read.</p>
   <p>Of course, a dog's bark does not reach heaven. The accusations, even if <pb facs="5423968_2_1144.jpg" n="3"/>carried out on such an enormous scale, and no matter how terrible and cleverly planned, will not have the desired result. They will not undermine our Polish ideals....</p>
   <p>But how terrible is their action, what depths of depravity and moral turpitude they have disclosed to our eyes!</p>
   <p>For over thirty years we have been building our Polish communities here in America.</p>
   <p>We have established institutions, we have worked for them, we have taught our people to read the newspapers, we have been advancing and improving continuously.</p>
   <p>And now comes Wiarus with its Marcypan--and like Erostratus they wish, by misconstruing the laws of the country, to destroy all we have <pb facs="5423968_2_1145.jpg" n="4"/>accomplished. No! No despot oppressing Poland for over one hundred years could have desired better or more infamous servants, not even the czar of Russia. </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
