<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-03-15">Mar. 15, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">A Picture of the Polish Press in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1253</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1253.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-03-15">Mar. 15, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">A PICTURE OF THE POLISH PRESS IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Honorable Mr. Slisz, editor of Polaka W Americe (The Pole In America), has recently voiced bitter words in his paper because we did not comment devoutly enough about his publication. He has become angered on the grounds that other periodicals of lesser import received more publicity.</p>
   <p>If the editor of The Pole In America would only realize that it is essential to perform work of value in order to gain recognition in the field of journalism. As soon as Mr. Slisz will change his present policies and adopt the banner of righteousness, the sooner he will merit favorable comment. He must find the way to the road of truth and stay on it. The sooner he straightens the path of his entire paper, gets rid of the unpleasant articles of insinuation and suspicion, eliminates the insertion of attacks on honorable individuals and their worthy efforts; and the sooner he adopts a more fundamental platform, and finds, besides the polemic writings, original and <pb facs="5423968_2_1254.jpg" n="2"/>educational articles, the sooner will he win our praise. For the present, if Mr. Slisz is not content with our objective treatment, which is void of mud and gall, that is his lookout. Our taste is more persevering. To be stricken with sadness by someone's praise is a weakness of character.</p>
   <p>Reluctantly, we continue our true version of the Polish press in America. We have before us the stable of Augean, but we doubt that some kind of an American Hercules can be found who could cleanse the filth and corruption from the stables of some of our perverse journals.</p>
   <p>In the United States, there are many Polish journals that are called "Raeuber and Moerder Presse," a murderer's and robber's press, by the Europeans. It is true that they do not lurk in the woods, highways, and cities, with rod and stiletto in hand to committ physical murder and strip the victim of his belongings; yet, their attacks through the printed word on individuals, religion, patriotism, and worthy endeavor, serve the same purpose. Their moral attacks on Christianity, their subversive teachings <pb facs="5423968_2_1255.jpg" n="3"/>filled with filthy aphorisms, and overflowing anarchism are the rods, revolvers, and stilettos, by which the weaklings of our nationality became victims. They are the instruments that murder the heart, soul, and mind, of our brothers.</p>
   <p>Who prints these papers? Evil people. Persons who have been shorn of human feeling and virtue, persons of fallen character, derelicts, averse individuals who try to fill their hungry stomachs with their own literary succulence.</p>
   <p>We will not name the papers, nor their editors, or authors. Our entire immigrant group is familiar with them. We could point out all their faults, but by this we would proclaim their honor. Instead, we will treat them with silence. This will serve as ample criticism.</p>
   <p>Our first step in pointing out the nature, tendency, and literary stand, of the Polish press in this country has been completed. This has been a personal point of view. Perhaps we have erred in many respects. Mistakes that will be <pb facs="5423968_2_1256.jpg" n="4"/>pointed out to us will be gladly rectified.</p>
   <p>In the future, we will give short summaries of replies that have appeared in other papers relative to our comments on the Polish press. These reactions will appear each week.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
