<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 8
<date when="1922-01-11">Jan. 11, 1922</date>,
<title level="a"/><title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0562</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0562.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 8
<date when="1922-01-11">Jan. 11, 1922</date>,
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are people having <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> towards high learning and wisdom, having even in certain directions a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>education, who in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of all have to be <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> with as fools, if one is called a fool who willingly cause an injury or harm unto himselr.</p>
   <p>There are people who lack <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to such a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> which in bad or good for them, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> they <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to any sort of suicidal theory set from in the Christian world by the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> religion and become its <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. </p>
   <p>To such idiotic <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> spread at present among Christians, chiefly in American, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the se-called <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> for would-be <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>.</p>
   <p>This watch-world was thrown <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> world by the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of modern socialism, promising to fools a paradise on earth with the help <pb facs="5423968_2_0563.jpg" n="2"/>of doing away with private property, with the help of preparing a free love tie by nothing, a boundless freedom.</p>
   <p>Only fools allow themselves to be taken by this kind of talk, those not knowing how to distinguish laws of nature and not understanding the fundamentals of life and human happiness, generally the fundamentals of our entire Christian civilization.</p>
   <p>We have written many times about Socialism. Our attentive readers already understand perfectly the entire idiotism concluded in the Socialistic doctrine, relative to the make-up of the state. Up to this time we have not written extensively about the free-love proposed by the Socialists professors of universities, for would-be economic reasons. The Catholic church condemns this doctrine as incompatible with the principles of faith.</p>
   <p>We will try to enlighten it briefly from a purely <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and self-preserving viewpoint.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0564.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is not one human being with a sound mind that would not admit from a patriotic <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> purely <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> that the artificial <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of births is national <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> knows that the greater the population of a nation, the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the easier it is to uphold its culture and its political independence. It is a thin so clear that there is <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of having a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> over it. So then, the propagaters of "birth control" are <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> about this <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> and are raising only the economic question and saying that the uncontrolled number of births is bringing poverty not only upon the families individually, but also upon the entire country. Under the pretext, it would seem that they have a reason, when you take into consideration the fate of this or that numerically large and poor family.</p>
   <p>We are saying this under pretext only, because in reality the thing happens to be altogether different when we take into consideration the good of the entire country.</p>
   <p>Above all, the healthiest individuals, equally under the spiritual and <pb facs="5423968_2_0565.jpg" n="4"/>physical respect, are being born, in particular where the number of births is not bound by anything. This is happening particularly because they are conceived in natural manner from physically and spiritually healthy parents. Only the most morally and naturally conducted marriages can bear many children. A marriage, limiting by an artificial method the number of births, can never bring into the world healthy and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> children, because the artificial act of prevention ruins the health of both individuals, and above all the woman's.</p>
   <p>You cannot point our as one physically and spiritually healthy married woman who has conformed to artificial sterility. Such a married woman is almost always ill and usually comes to an untimely death. Generally, the women who live the longest and feel the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> fortunate, are those who have had a natural number of children.</p>
   <p>It is also a downright lie that an artificially lessened number of children, or sterility gives a woman satisfaction in life. Such beings are truly the most unfortunate, particularly when it comes to definition of one growing older.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0566.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>If it <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> the nourishing and the proper bringing up of the children of peer parents, that is remedied very essily by every city, every smallest community, and lactly the state. A <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> is also the claim that a greater number of people brings about a greater poverty, because every normal and industrious person can himself produce enough livelihood, that would be sufficient for six people.</p>
   <p>Further, the one who <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> "birth controls" is <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> who,briefly saying, performs suicide and corner number upon his posterity and nation. If the Jews propagate among Christians the principle of birth control, then one must ask them why is it that they do not adapt themselvess to it, but call every newly born child a treasure and blessing of Jehovah?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
