<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-21">May 21, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Middle Road Is the Best</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1474</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1474.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-05-21">May 21, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE MIDDLE ROAD IS THE BEST</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The people of America have seen in the past few months how harmful are the policies and politics of the so-called protective tariff, that is, high duties placed on imported products. This practice has brought profits principally to the capitalists. In England, on the other hand, we find that the [existing] conditions are in direct opposition to ours from the standpoint of tariff. The economists and political forces of Great Britain, although not as yet numerous, but nevertheless well-informed in their particular field, have come to the conclusion that the so-called free trade is unprofitable for the country. Lord Salisbury had the courage to oppose this opinion openly and to support his statements with proofs. A statement of that type could mean as much as the fall of the Salisburean cabinet. The English have learned to believe too strongly in the doctrine that free trade is the most beneficial to a <pb facs="5423968_2_1475.jpg" n="2"/>country and could not be convinced by any argument that the opposition might offer.</p>
   <p>Lord Salisbury was undoubtedly justified in his statement when he said that other nations would enact protective tariffs. Great Britain with her free trade, which has truly been the important factor in making her the greatest trade power in the world, today, in the face of actual warlike tariffs, finds herself disarmed. If some reform in this matter is not brought in, and in the very near future, then she is in danger of declining in power at the source which first gave her ascendancy. It is, beyond doubt, one of the most complicated economic questions that a civilized nation ever had to solve, namely, what is more beneficial to a nation: a protective tariff or free trade? The proper answer to this, as in many other similar questions, lies somewhere in the middle. The difficulty, however, lies in finding this medium.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1476.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Even if some one were successful in deciding this matter in a manner convincing all followers of every party in any nation, despite this, the application of such theories in practice would prove to be unsatisfactory unless and until every nation accepted the same principle. Only a final internationally co-operative decision could solve this; but a great deal of time will elapse before it will ever reach that point.</p>
   <p>The Democrats in America, in their bitter opposition to protective tariffs, are supported by the history of trade and commerce. They point to the success of England and its free trade, and on the other hand, to the failure of Russia with its high tariff. Nevertheless, despite the fact that England has begun to consider free trade as being insufficiently beneficial to the nation in face of the high tariffs of other countries, the Democrats of the United States are perfectly justified when they demand, not free trade, but a proper and moderate "reform of tariffs." This type <pb facs="5423968_2_1477.jpg" n="4"/>of reform is essentially the medium (via media) between the two detrimental extremes. Although it might be difficult to formulate the proposed reform in detail and in the most profitable way, nevertheless, it is undoubtedly better than a high tariff.</p>
   <p>In the near future the Dziennik Chicagoski will present a version of an excellently formulated work of the renowned economist, Henry George, entitled: "Protection or Free Trade?".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
