<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-23">Jan. 23, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Where There Is Fault, There Is Penalty</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1282</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1282.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-01-23">Jan. 23, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">WHERE THERE IS FAULT, THERE IS PENALTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>No one society of people can exist without proper and lawful authority. Respect and obedience of this power are also social necessities. Every individual, be he a believer of a monarchic or democratic from of government, must accept these two fundamental axioms. Although there may be some who place monarchic government above republican, one cannot call them fools or cowards because of this. History shows us that a Monarchy can benefit the people within its realm. The people felt safeguarded under the crown of the king or prince. The Jews in the Old Testament tried various forms of government. Finally they desired a king for a ruler, Jehovah granted this wish and the Israelites were given a monarchic government. Some of their kings ruled them in brilliant style; all <pb facs="5423968_2_1283.jpg" n="2"/>prospered. Dutiful obedience and respect paid the rulers was not harmful or degrading. All this was a result of earnest execution of duty.</p>
   <p>It often happened, and unfortunately it still occurs, that the kings who erroneously ruled their empires had power and still have this power. In their palaces they often imagined that their providence was not for the people, but that the people were created for them, by it. Their prejudices frequently betrayed them in their proceedings. They considered themselves a higher and better class, as if they did not belong to the common people. Because of their pride they looked down upon their subjects with disdain, as if all else was ended from their pedestals.</p>
   <p>The vanity of dominating heads often takes on great proportions from which <pb facs="5423968_2_1284.jpg" n="3"/>flows despotism that only drags the people into laggardness. It is difficult to explain to oneself how civilized peoples can endure this disregard, abasement, oppression, and persecution.</p>
   <p>It is worthwhile in this respect to look into some of these sad symptoms. It is not only necessary to worship with deep respect the present reigning lords and the older members of the family, but also the small kingly child. Certainly this child of the throne has not passed through any different stages than the average mortal. It has its three-cornered pants changed as often as any other child. Yet it has the right to have the people pay it homage. Beside its crib it sucks the nipple of rich appanages for which the poor subjects must contribute. And what about the approach of the <pb facs="5423968_2_1285.jpg" n="4"/>wedding day? It certainly would be a great day if these princely offsprings, whose blood has been weakened by marrying into the same strain, would marry a stronger and healthier person from another rank in order to revitalize their blood. However, court etiquette, pride, reason of state, and prejudice does not permit this unless all claim to the throne, etc., are relinquished. Everyone of such marriages, if they occur, is considered an insult to the royal family.</p>
   <p>Whom do the monarchs finally accept and tolerate on their regal steps? Does the ordinary individual from the rank and file have the privilege? No! One must have a certain birthright, hereditary family nobleness; at least a "de" or a "von" before his name. Who gets all the ranking army or civil appointments? Only a person from a count's or a baron's family. And no <pb facs="5423968_2_1286.jpg" n="5"/>matter how brilliant the avera e person may be he must always make way for the chosen. There is only one trouble with this and that is: the people are not treated "al pari" but "a la parias" (as equal but after the equal).</p>
   <p>If this were only an end to all this, now fortunate many peoples would be! But pride of the kings, ambition of the tsars, and godless state rights of monarchs go much further.</p>
   <p>Who carries out these bloody wars that ruin nations? Who drives the youth, the flower of the people, to horrible slaughter and death? These drives are carried out by kings, tsars, and monarchs. Is it for the good of the people? Rarely do these rulers demand the laurels of Mars. These killings, <pb facs="5423968_2_1287.jpg" n="6"/>this blind wasting of people is usually useless ambition - personal greed. For what did the soldier fight for at Woerth, Metz, Paris, etc.? For freedom and prosperity of the people? Oh, no! He fought in order to have a crown placed upon the Prussian resent, who is now nearing his grave, to make him a monarch and to fill his coffers with gold. He sacrificed his life so that generals could be decorated with medals for their valor, but this was not all. His force helped to take away from France two provinces, to pillage the churches, to take away the land of the bishops, like a Shylock taking away the last piece of life-giving bread. The bishops and priests were mistreated, the schools placed under non-religious tutorship, and the native tongue of the French, Danes, and Poles, were restricted. Representatives of the church shared the filthy cells and deathly dungeons <pb facs="5423968_2_1288.jpg" n="7"/>with thieves and murderers. The poor soldier was also used to destroy monasteries and to kill the inmates who had sacrificed their lives to serve God and the people. For all of this the Catholic soldier spilled his life-giving elixir upon the horrible frontiers of war and reward: To see the Prussian banner fly with its black eagle.</p>
   <p>Today a relatively new and young prince has begun a different policy in respect to the treatment of people. He has a nobler heart, his love for the people is more sincere, his concern is of their interests. The Polish people under his rule have been rid of the shackles placed upon them by the Prussian political reactionary Bismarck. This cruel executioner of our people is now living his predatory existence in seclusion. He has been <pb facs="5423968_2_1289.jpg" n="8"/>deserted by his clique and by his people.</p>
   <p>Dziennik Chicagoski, Jan. 25, 1892.</p>
   <p>Austria, as a Catholic nation, has never oppresed our people from a religious standpoint. Other benefits of which our people are proud to boast about under the Habsburg regime, although not a result of love and justice, were bestowed because of political necessity. The Austrian Empire, glued together from various nationalities, could not force all these peoples under the German strickle. Each nationality, entering into the <pb facs="5423968_2_1290.jpg" n="9"/>Habsburg realm, had its own past, history, religion, and native language. To amalgamate all these peoples into one was and is an impossibility, especially, since they have been knocking each other about for the rule of one another since the dawn of civilization. Therefore, Austria has chosen a different road. The many sections of this united country have been fused into a solid political bloc by giving each nationality the privilege of autonomic government, the right to continue the mother tongue, and the perpetuation of national tradition.</p>
   <p>There only remains one European country that does not foster this kind of treatment for other peoples under its rule. This one country is Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1291.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>This barbaric, this Tartar wild country, this godless nation filled with the upbringing of Byzantine vileness; today is wiping out alien peoples under its rule, and this is especially true of those of Poland.</p>
   <p>Our religion, our maternal language, our sprouting youth, etc., today is becoming the target of the Tsar's brutal murderers. There is no talk of justice, for the Muscovites have no knowledge of mercy. Righteousness cannot be found in the dictionary of the Tsar. Murder, robbery, falsity, treachery, imprisonment, and other barbaric words are on the tip of the Tartar, Mongol, Muscovite tongue. And what for? Only because these people happen to be Polish and Catholic. The clergy is abused, the churches are confiscated for loathsome Russian orthodoxism, and the schools <pb facs="5423968_2_1292.jpg" n="11"/>are filled with vile Muscovite teachings that deny the right of Polish thought. The Polish nobility is being materially wasted because of compelled contributions, taxation and especially by economic experimentation.</p>
   <p>What are free Poles in America going to do about this? Are we to kindle the fires of revolution and conspiracy? Never! What for? Today on a field of battle or revolt one can easily be lost - never victorious. St. Thomas Aquinas, the angelic doctor of the church, tells us in his writings that only rebellion against tyrants is just and excusable when there is hope of throwing off the ties of bondage. The present situation in Russia warrants no such action. It would be suicidal. It would also be futile <pb facs="5423968_2_1293.jpg" n="12"/>to become murderers. This would only bring us greater miseries, deathly burdens.</p>
   <p>There remains only one salvation for our people today: public protest. A protest that is general and loud enough to reach the ears of the entire civilized world. A protest in the name of heaven and earth to end this uncivilized and unmerciful attack on innocent people.</p>
   <p>We have a just right to protest against such savage treatment of people. We do not need the permission of any government to make this denunciation, for we do not acknowledge any of the present powers. There can only be one <pb facs="5423968_2_1294.jpg" n="13"/>national government for our people and that is the Polish government. Some day our people will triumph and have their own country, their own government, and our people will find a place in the European scheme of things. Until that day we will not recognize any of the ruling countries. We have always scorned and we will continue to scorn any imposters who try to get into our graces, be they English, French, Spanish, or American. Demagogues will never be recognized by us!</p>
   <p>There was a time when one nation would bear the tyrannical treatment of another nation but time has changed this; conditions have altered and the people have altered with them. Today the wind is blowing in another <pb facs="5423968_2_1295.jpg" n="14"/>direction everywhere. Kings and tears ought to sense this new trend and replace their old ideas about ruling people with ideas of catering to them. Nations in many parts of the world are turning to self-government-to republicanism. Old thrones are weakening, virtually tottering under this new movement. And if in the process of ruination the ruins spell oblivion for these tyrants and demagogues, it will be their own fault. They themselves have laid the foundations and the principles of their thrones. Wilhelm has as his slogan "Zerschmetern" and "Voluntas regis," while the Tsar's palace displays on its banner the words that were horrible to Nebuchadnezzer, "Mane, Tekel, Phares." They should take a hint from the words of the wise and remember the words of a former ruler of people, David. His profound words were: "Et nunc reges intelligite, qui judicatis terram."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
