<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XV, No. 217,
<date when="1904-09-15">September 15, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Doctor Kuflewski and the Germans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1077</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1077.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XV, No. 217,
<date when="1904-09-15">September 15, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">DOCTOR KUFLEWSKI AND THE GERMANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Kuflewski, a member of the school board, at a meeting held yesterday, brought the anger of Germans upon himself by shouting, "Why do the Germans want to express their feelings openly about the Poles by calling us show-off Poles?"</p>
   <p>Heinrich Heine, German-Jewish poet, when in Paris at a certain coffee shop, made remarks about the Poles to his friends. Seated at a table nearby, listening to his slander, was a Pole. At the end of his endurance the Pole rose and demanded that Heine take back his words. Heine was surprised at this outbreak, but instead of apologizing made another nasty remark.</p>
   <p>The enraged Pole struck Heine in the face. People in the shop anticipated a fight. Heine did not retaliate. The Pole paid his bill and left, unmolested. To get the score even, Mr. Heine wrote a verse about Mr. Krapulinski and Mr. Wraseklapski, called "Polen aus der Polskei, un die zwei Edlen Polen."</p>
   <p>Ever since then it seems as if in every little argument between a Pole <pb facs="5423968_2_1078.jpg" n="2"/>and a German "edlen Polen" comes into play. The Poles remember this episode. They are convinced a Jew will avenge an insult.</p>
   <p>The Illinois Staats Zeitung, in today's issue (September 15, 1904), called Dr. Kuflewski "der edle Dr. Kuflewski." Camillo Von Lueze, a professor at the Chicago University, persuaded Mr. Leon Wachsneren, owner of a theater, to allow school children and teachers to be present at daily matinees, to convince teachers and students that this was a good opportunity to learn German.</p>
   <p>Dr. Kuflewski greatly opposed this proposition and demanded that a proposition of this kind be given to the mayor (Harrison), and a special investigation be made before making any comment.</p>
   <p>The German newspapers promptly criticized Dr. Kuflewski and Mayor Harrison for their attitude, the papers being greatly in favor of having the German language taught in public schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
