<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-27">Apr. 27, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Kraj and the Poles of America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1178</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1178.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-04-27">Apr. 27, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">KRAJ AND THE POLES OF AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Polish weekly Kraj (Country), published by Erasmus Piltz in St. Petersburg and representing, fortunately, a small faction of Poles in Russian Poland, advocates Polish resignation to the fate of Poland under Czarist Russia. We do not intend to show here how, in the face of Russian persecution, such a political viewpoint is groundless and altogether, opposed to our policy. Everybody knows that, while a Polish party exists in Galicia [Austrian Partition] and even in Poznan [Prussian Partition], any sort of Polish political activity in Russian Poland is impossible. "Resignation to their fate" would mean to the Poles denial of all their national ideals and acceptance of the knout and czarism as the gospel. Such views can hardly be accepted by Poles beyond the small circle of Petersburg adherents. That Kraj has attained a certain popularity is possibly due to literary merit and probably due to the fact that, for one reason or another, it is looked upon with considerable favor by the Russian censorship. It is permitted to <pb facs="5423968_2_1179.jpg" n="2"/>write of many things which other Polish periodicals may not even touch upon. Thus, from time to time, there have appeared in Kraj news items concerning the activity of Poles in other countries, items which most of the other Polish papers are denied the right to mention. Such news has contributed to its popularity, for the people of Russian Poland, surrounded as it were by a Chinese wall of censorship, gladly read of their brethren in other parts of Europe and across the ocean.</p>
   <p>Since the news of American Polonia in Kraj has often been inaccurate or has followed a certain tendency, we have occasionally found it necessary to protest, remembering always the resultant value--information. In the March issue of Kraj, however, an article entitled "Poles in America," signed by Editor Piltz himself, has exceeded all bounds of decency. The article, which is an editorial on Polish-American conditions, was so unjust that it caused the resignation of Kraj's Chicago correspondent.</p>
   <p>Mr. Piltz, using as reference Dr. Dunikowski's brochure on his American travels, has seen fit to pass judgment upon us. The thoughtlessness with <pb facs="5423968_2_1180.jpg" n="3"/>which Mr. Piltz arrives at his opinion is astounding. His conclusions are based on neither more nor less than his conversations of a few years ago with a prominent Polish-American at one of Europe's famous spas. This Pole is, parenthetically speaking, one who for a number of years has been unfavorably disposed toward American Polonia, and who has withdrawn from its affairs completely. Using as a basis these private conversations, embellished by his own imagination, Mr. Piltz has decided that American Polonia has no future, that conditions here are deplorable, that our moral and intellectual standards are low, and that our community consists of two types of people--the uncultured masses and the intellectual scum. He claims that the second generation has already lost its Polish characteristics, and that it is idle to send us leaders from the old country (as if we asked them to), etc.</p>
   <p>We realize that we are not without faults. We ourselves point them out at every opportunity and strive to correct them. However, we can say truthfully that this judgment of Kraj is groundless and altogether unjust. We hesitate to say that Mr. Piltz's aim may be to weaken the growing effect of our community on the old country. The purpose of this editorial is simply <pb facs="5423968_2_1181.jpg" n="4"/>to call the attention of the public to this conscienceless judgment and to protest against it.</p>
   <p>We will permit ourselves to ask the editor of Kraj a few questions. How dare he forget that Polish-American intelligentsia is headed by two hundred odd Polish priests? Certainly, no one can call them "intellectual scum," especially since there is to be found among their number men who are capable of real sacrifice, men whose virtues are known and appreciated in Europe as well as here in America.</p>
   <p>Further--who built from one hundred and fifty to two hundred Polish churches in America? Does he realize that these are all buildings which will one day be acknowledged as noteworthy from an architectural viewpoint?</p>
   <p>Who established from one hundred to one hundred and fifty Polish schools, in which from forty to fifty thousand Polish children receive daily instruction and learn to praise God in Polish? Who taught thousands of illiterate Polish immigrants to read, write, and to understand political affairs in this country?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1182.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Who established the Immigrants' House, and who maintains innumerable charitable institutions? Who has established a competent organization which yearly provides for the existence of thousands of Polish widows and orphans? Who, by virtue of thrift, has accumulated millions of dollars in savings banks and building and loan associations? Who created thousands of Polish business enterprises? Who constructed Polish halls and taught the Polish masses, indifferent to national affairs in Europe, to gather in celebration of important national anniversaries?</p>
   <p>Who established from twenty to thirty newspapers, good, bad, and indifferent, we admit, but among which are journals of which Europe could well be proud? And, above all, who taught hundreds of thousands to read the printed word?</p>
   <p>Who has unfurled hundreds of banners with the Virgin Mary on one side and the Polish eagle on the other, from the Hudson River to the Pacific coast? And who taught peasant hearts to love these banners? Who, out of the crudest material, created a Polish stage and spread the fame of Polish music? Who established Polish libraries, reading rooms, Polish Falcons? Who accomplished <pb facs="5423968_2_1183.jpg" n="6"/>the election of many of our brethren to important political positions in this country? Who daily claims the attention of the American newspapers and through this medium reminds the world of Poland's past and present?</p>
   <p>Who sends thousands, perhaps millions, of dollars to Poland annually for the upkeep of families left behind? Who contributed thousands of dollars to flood relief in Galicia? Who collected money for the relief of Unite refugees? And who is contributing toward the erection of a Kosciusko memorial?</p>
   <p>Who sends great sums of money yearly for the purchase of Polish books and newspapers? Who? we ask Mr. Piltz, and the answer is simple. All of this has been done and is being done by two types of people: "uncultured masses and intellectual scum".</p>
   <p>Our questions, we believe, prove the unworthiness of Mr. Piltz's judgment of us. We doubt, however, that we will have convinced the Petersburg paper. We desired merely, since Kraj is circulated throughout Poland, to protest loudly in the hope that we can convince our brethren in Poland that our work <pb facs="5423968_2_1184.jpg" n="7"/>here is more profitable to the Polish cause than the destructive policy of Kraj, which has for its final aim the abandonment of Polish national hopes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
