<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VIII No. 16,
<date when="1904-04-20">Apr. 20, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Diligence Means More Than Talent</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0678</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0678.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VIII No. 16,
<date when="1904-04-20">Apr. 20, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">DILIGENCE MEANS MORE THAN TALENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are children, who at an early stage, perceive the awakening of the soul, grasp things easily, are of a brilliant mind, occupy front ranks in schools and possess good sense. In spite of all of this they are unable to carry anything into effect in life, because they are lacking industry, perseverance and effort in their undertakings. Here, involuntarily comes to our mind the fable about the hare and the snail, who were racing on a wager. The snail, although it dragged along slowly, but with perseverance, reached its goal; while to the contrary, the hare running quickly, leaping along the way cutting capers, always convinced that being the livelier, he will overcome the snail, arrived at the goal too late.</p>
   <p>Many, very talented youths, with splendid abilities, are last in this same manner, by their own thoughtlessness, carelessness, lack of diligence, accomplish very little in life; while on the other hand, those less capable, but diligent and persevering, leave them behind, and get a better position and fame.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0679.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It so happens that a few, who in their youth, miss their calling step forward at a more mature age, but they become prominent only through work, steady and unceasing work, and an iron will.</p>
   <p>Talent is a gift at birth which contains in itself no personal merit. Work comes from strong will, it is individuality created by activity, therefore, it should be valued more greatly than talent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
