<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-08">Feb. 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The So-Called "Morals Squad"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0530</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0530.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1915-02-08">Feb. 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE SO-CALLED "MORALS SQUAD"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The city of Chicago is fortunate in many aspects. It has things of which other cities have not even dreamed. It has capable police, truthful politicians, an excellent transportation system, a wonderful lighting system, and exemplary order on the streets. If any one doubts this, let him ask those who are in hospitals as the result of this exemplary order, suffering with broken limbs or fractured skulls. But the crowning glory of all these advantages possessed by Chicago is the so-called "morals squad". Its task is to arrest men and women leading an immoral life.</p>
   <p>The morally neglected members--our error, we should have said the moral members--of the morals squad are recruited mostly from people who have had relationships with the underworld. There is nothing surprising about this, after all--such people know best the secrets of hotel rooms and the relations of the world of crime with the women of a district.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0531.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What is more surprising and worthy of castigation is the fact that these gentlemen--we still refer to the morals squad--often break down the doors of houses at which they have previously called, but in which respectable people now reside. These new residents do not wish to have anything to do with the morality squad of Major Funkhouser. The epilogues of such visits are enacted in court, where the methods employed in obtaining evidence from supposedly immoral women by these guardians of morality are brought to light.</p>
   <p>A certain woman who had been arrested related the following story in Judge Goodnow's court. Some one rapped at her door, saying that his name was Smith. Everybody knows that in New York alone these are more than 84,000 Smiths, and in Chicago the number of Smiths is in excess of 45,000. Hence it is not difficult to understand that the woman opened the door, thinking that it was the [particular] Smith whom she knew. When she did so, Mr. Smith entered, followed by the police, who arrested her.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0532.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Another "moral" gentleman of the morality squad stands at a street corner and accosts every passing woman. When one of them answers him, he arrests her because she has talked with a stranger on the street. Such instances occur daily because the gentlemen from the "morality squad" must, after all, show that they are active, and the proof of their activities is the arrests. The whole difficulty in this lies in the fact that this activity of theirs does not bring any results where it should. Tramps and parasites living on disorder continue to conduct their trade because the "moral squadron" is less preoccupied with them than with people who do not deserve the least attention.</p>
   <p>But that is nothing! Mr. Funkhouser will eventually receive a medal of merit for his adequate management of the "morality squad" because the arrests are increasing every day. Those arrested are released, that is true, because there is no evidence against them, but the officials note the large numbers of arrests on the police calendars, and these are carefully <pb facs="5423968_2_0533.jpg" n="4"/>inspected whenever there is talk of promotion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
