<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIV, No. 33
<date when="1920-08-18">Aug. 18, 1920</date><title level="a">Loathsome Jewish Attacks on Poland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0886</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0886.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIV, No. 33
<date when="1920-08-18">Aug. 18, 1920</date><title level="a">LOATHSOME JEWISH ATTACKS ON POLAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is a rich Jew in American by the name of Hearst, who publishes many newspapers in the English language. One of his daily newspapers, Chicago Herald and Examiner, is edited in Chicago. This Jewish paper has been attacking Poles abominably for some time. It publishes man invented lies against Poland.</p>
   <p>The correspondents of this paper, who are Jews, born under the unlucky star, sling Bolshevistic mud at Poland, because they are Bolsheviks of the worst kind.</p>
   <p>One of the Bolsheviks who is employed by the Harald and Examiner in the Finance Department is hiding his identity under the pseudonym of "Boersnier." He has attacked Poland in regular bandit style. In his attacks he is trying to discourage Americans from giving any financial assistance to Poland. In order to acquaint our readers with his attacks on Poland, we quote from the following letter:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0887.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"To the Polish Ministry in Washington, D. C.</p>
   <p>"Prince Lubomirski</p>
   <p>"Your Excellency: We are informed that Your Excellency has negotiated with the United States Government for a loan to your country. In addition to the hundred million dollars which have been leaned to your nation by the United States Government, and also to the additional fifty million dollars which were loaned to your people by the private American investors, Your Excellency is asking for another and much larger sum."</p>
   <p>Then, after threatening the Polish ambassador that the financiers (read Jews) will look into the Polish internal matters and see whether the Polish government is mistreating the Jews, he continues: "There are in your country three million patriotic Poles (Jews who are betraying Poland. Editor) whose religion is different from that of the rest of the population. Those differences are not organic of cardinal; they are additional. Yet, in spite of the fact that these differences are <pb facs="5423968_2_0888.jpg" n="3"/>insignificant, they were used as an incentive or an excuse for murdering and robbing the minority. Children, women, old people and invalids were wantonly butchered and robbed, together with the strong, just because they were Jews.</p>
   <p>"In regards to cruelty and cowardice, those murders and plunders have no comparison with the old Russian pogroms, because under the old Russian stardom the government would make an attempt to present it. But in your country, your government planned it purposely and carried it out in Lemberg, Nolan and Pinsk. In the last city the terrible massacre was accomplished by the army; all the murders word Polish uniforms.</p>
   <p>"Thousands of innocent people have been killed and abused; their belonging have been stolen. This was accomplished by the Polish soldiers, the Polish fanatics and professional murderers and robbers who were incited by the Polish government. The victims were people who loved and had served Poland in peace and war, whose ancestors <pb facs="5423968_2_0889.jpg" n="4"/>lived in Poland for centuries. The majority of these are useful workers and the minority are able financiers and economists, whom Poland needs very much. They were murdered just because they were Jews.</p>
   <p>"Those crimes (at the sight of which the Russian Tsar would shudder) were committed in the young republic of Poland, in a free and independent Poland, for which the freedom-loving people of the whole world longed.</p>
   <p>"I admit that I was sorely disappointed when you chose for your first premier that pianist with the Lilliputian mind, Paderewski, who is prejudiced against the peasants. You cannot speak fifteen minutes with that incomparable musician but a brainless man, without hearing some silly remark about the Jews.</p>
   <p>"Electing him premier would have been humorously grotesque if the ruling class had no aversion towards those three million citizens, and if there had been no incompetence on the part of your government during the war with Russia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0890.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>That is enough! It makes your blood "boil." A base Jew, Bolshevik, a rogue who sells the most sacred thing for shekels, he dares to scoff at the Polish government and sling mud at one fo the best sons of Poland. THis is not only a slander but an open insult to the Polish nation, not by any "onion eater" by by a newspaper of a reptilian character which is read by the Americans and the Poles. Against such libel we should protest very vigorously.</p>
   <p>Enough of these calumnies!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
