<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. I, No. 130,
<date when="1907-08-17">August 17, 1907</date><title level="a">Unionists Don't Care to Read the Zgoda</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1561</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1561.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Ludowy</title>, Vol. I, No. 130,
<date when="1907-08-17">August 17, 1907</date><title level="a">UNIONISTS DON'T CARE TO READ THE ZGODA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We fortunately received the following request sent to the administration of the P. N. A. by a Union Committee:</p>
   <p>To The Polish National Alliance Administration, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>We, the members of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners, Polish Local No. 14 and 1805, consisting of ninety-five per cent of Alliance members, were very much amazed when the last two editions of the Zgoda was published without the Union stamp on it.</p>
   <p>The Polish National Alliance consists mostly of workers, and these workers have a right to demand the organ of this organization to be conducted from beginning to end by union workers, and not by scabs who violate our solidarity <pb facs="5423968_2_1562.jpg" n="2"/>We made it our business to find out why the Zgoda had dropped this union recognition. It was through the intrigue of two persons, who always wish to soak their dirty hands into everything. One of these men worked for nine years as a "scab" in a frame factory.</p>
   <p>We beseech the P. N. A. administration to select a committee of organized workers, - and then this affair shall be laid away peacefully.</p>
   <p>As you already know, dear Sirs, we, being union workers, aren't able to support a scab paper. And you can't expect us to drop the Union for Zgoda and become scabs because one or two gentlemen on the committee of the Zgoda hates unions. We expect that the administration will take action on these serious affairs.</p>
   <p>The Committee: A. Kulesza</p>
   <p>J. Papierski</p>
   <p>W. Janiszewski</p>
   <p>F. Mix</p>
   <p>E. Barandowski</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
