<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-07-02">July 2, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Employee's Part in Industry</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1928-07-02">July 2, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">EMPLOYEE'S PART IN INDUSTRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An article was published recently in the America press by W. C. Fisher, Professor of Economics at New York University, on the subject of encouraging employees to purchase stock in industries in which they are employed. Professor Fisher, after collecting data in the face of considerable difficulties, is very much opposed to these purchases, in defiance of those who argue that ownership of such stock can bring an employee a good profit.</p>
   <p>In the opinion of Professor Fisher, the purchase of stock by employees is a very undesirable practice. His survey reveals that, in a great many cases, an employee purchasing such stock gains no financial benefits. Professor Fisher quotes many examples. Employees who bought stock in the Nash Motor Car Company gained a good profit, but in the case of other companies which <pb facs="5423968_2_1350.jpg" n="2"/>were not so sound they lost every cent invested. Hydraulic Steel Company sold its employees stock at forty dollars a share; these shares dropped in a short time to fifty cents, and today are worthless. American Woolen Company sold shares to its employees at sixty-six dollars and fifty cents each; these shares dropped to sixteen dollars each, and today are worth about twenty dollars. Many similar cases can be cited.</p>
   <p>One of the purposes in selling stock to employees is to unite them with their industry. Therefore, such stock is sold on a installment basis over a long period. Some employers will not under any circumstances sell stock for ready cash. It takes five years for the employee to pay for and receive his stock. During this period of time various unforseen events often occur. Professor Fisher states that if an employee deposited the money in a bank, instead of buying stock with it, he would show a larger profit.</p>
   <p>Adherents of this plan argue that an employee owning stock in a firm has a voice in the management of it, and is in a position to know exactly how it <pb facs="5423968_2_1351.jpg" n="3"/>is progressing; this argument Professor Fisher describes as a great misrepresentation. There is not one fact, in Professor Fisher's judgment, which indicates that employees who own stock can at any time exercise influence on the management of their firm. A common laborer is not in a position to know the exact financial condition of his concern; thus, be cannot himself form a reasonable estimate of the value of his stock.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, Professor Fisher states that every experienced employer knows very well that the purchase of stock is a speculation. It is possible to make a profit, but more often an employee loses.</p>
   <p>If these philanthropical corporations are truly concerned with the welfare of their employees, instead of selling stock to them they should offer them bonds; then the prospect of profits for the employee would be far better.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
