<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VI, No. 33,
<date when="1902-08-13">August 13, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">English Manuals - - and the Poles</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1081</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1081.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VI, No. 33,
<date when="1902-08-13">August 13, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">ENGLISH MANUALS - - AND THE POLES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In almost all English manuals used in our schools there is no mention about Poland, and if here and there is to be found any, it is not distinct and short; better that it were not mentioned at all.</p>
   <p>Reading more about us in English newspapers and seeing the development of our schools, the publishers of school books, due more perhaps to good will than with a view of any material gain, are trying to fill the breach in the manuals and are already giving greater mention in regard to the historical and geographical study of Poland.</p>
   <p>The firm of Butler, Sheldon and Company has done very well in publishing the new geography, arranged by Eliza H. Morton. Worked out in an easy, accessible style for children, the geography has many illustrations of the different races of people, their ways of life, pictures of their countries, cities, historical buildings, and colored maps of the whole world. It also contains a quite extensive article about Poland in the time of John III Sobieski.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1082.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the outset is found a beautifully finished map of Poland, whose boundaries extend from the Black to the Baltic seas, being at that time one of the mightiest powers of Europe and comprising 282,000 square miles. Besides a map, correctly drawn, can be found engravings of the palace Wawel at Cracow, the oldest Polish cathedral in Gniezne, and portraits of Kosciuszke and Pulaski.</p>
   <p>A summary of Polish geography and history, written by Rev. F. M. Wejatalewiez is worked out very carefully and impartially. When a child learns this he will have a better outlook on Polish history and its historical mission.</p>
   <p>This matter is very encouraging to the Poles, because until now many of the residents here did not know of our past history and our fall, and if they did know, this knowledge came from a foreign and unfavorable source, where almost all historical facts are altered and do not coincide with the truth.</p>
   <p>At the present time, when the whole civilized world is more interested in us than at any time since the last insurrection, the setting aside of a place in English geography for Polish affairs is of great importance to us. The management in Polish schools where up to the present time there has been in use English geographies, beside the one on Poland, should try and procure the <pb facs="5423968_2_1083.jpg" n="3"/>Morton's Elementary Geography. Those interested, write to Butler, Sheldon and Company, Chicago, or Philadelphia. We owe the Reverend Wejtalewiez a sincere vote of thanks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
