<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 38,
<date when="1912-09-18">Sept. 18, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Fortune Tellers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0996</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0996.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVI, No. 38,
<date when="1912-09-18">Sept. 18, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">FORTUNE TELLERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The very plague of our society are the so called fortune tellers of many different kinds who benefit by ignorance of others by reading their future from the palm of their hand, from cards or the character of handwriting. They prey unmercifully on their fellow creatures, wheedling out of them at times considerable sums of money for their predictions.</p>
   <p>This industry is spread out far and wide, and here in Chicago there is no shortage of such "nimrods" hunting for human stupidity.</p>
   <p>All kinds of witch-doctors, fortune tellers, prophets and other charlatans are exploiting skillfully the ignorance of our people, who oftentimes believe more in a dirty raggedy, even illiterate old hag, than in the real knowledge possessed by doctors and physicians.</p>
   <p>In case of serious illness, in some sort of accident or injury, where shall one betake himself? To a witch-doctor. When misfortune pays a visit to your home or meets a member of the family - who will advise you? Who, if not the fortune teller!</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0997.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What important people are these witch-doctors and fortune tellers? With what remedies do they save the unfortunate ones?</p>
   <p>Undoing of charms, the burning of different herbs, the eating of fattened cats, the singeing of the hair on the tail of a mouse which had been trapped by a piece of fat, the burying of matted hair underneath the threshold of a home along with a certain amount of money (naturally, for the witch-doctor), the catching of bats and burying them during the night in unpolished pots, the swallowing of coal with pomade and almonds and hundreds of other foolish acts - here you have the "sure cures" remedies told over for the benefit of the inexperienced poor people, of whom more than one, sick or "bewitched" is dispatched into the great beyond sooner than he should have been.</p>
   <p>With such nonsense do they catch the simple-minded people. And that their business pays rich dividends, that there is no shortage of payers, in other words, foolish people - - is proven best by the flourishing business which is being done off human stupidity by these prophets, witch-doctors, fortune tellers and quacks. It is a well known fact that many of these <pb facs="5423968_2_0998.jpg" n="3"/>old witches own homes, bought with the money derived from fortune telling.</p>
   <p>These old hags do not scorn at any opportunity on giving advice. Whether a young man comes to them who has lost the love of his sweetheart or a young lady disappointed in love, even if it be some older person who has lost something or wishes to build up a fortune, for everybody, even for the sick, such an old hag will find positive advice, but it is a fact that she never does them any good.</p>
   <p>Many thousands of dollars are sunk in the pockets of these leeches, pretended saviors of the suffering people, giving good fortune and riches to all who seek their advice. The fortune tellers claim to possess all these infallible means of getting rich, nevertheless they do not use this means of making money for themselves but make a charge for using these means on others.</p>
   <p>Because if they should really possess this power of clairvoyance, if their advice could bring riches and happiness to others, why don't they first make themselves rich without fleecing and sucking the money from the trusting persons?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0999.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Guard yourselves against these parasites, charlatans and old hags. Everybody should know that God Himself is only able to determine a man's destiny and future. You have no doubt more than once heard the priest tell you that while he was preaching. Nevertheless this does not seem to have any effect on certain ignorant and foolish individuals who do not heed words of truth, but like moths to a flame they force themselves into dark holes and give up their own blood for a pile of predicted nonsense.</p>
   <p>Rarely is the deception of these fortune tellers disclosed,because many who have been deceived and afterwards convinced themselves of their stupidity, are ashamed to admit anything. However, there have been instances where such cases have been brought into courts and the deceptions revealed, showing how bottomless is human ignorance.</p>
   <p>Therefore one must guard himself like from fire against all these fortune tellers and prophets. Seek the truth in respectable papers and books and <pb facs="5423968_2_1000.jpg" n="5"/>not carry one's hard-earned money to these robbers who cannot help you and only laugh at you. The "charms" and stunts made by them should be of no wonder to anyone because they only "pull the wool" over your eyes and have no superhuman power.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
