<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VI, No. 22,
<date when="1902-05-28">May 28, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">A Word in Time</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VI, No. 22,
<date when="1902-05-28">May 28, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD IN TIME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Quite often one hears complaints about the shameful treatment we receive in politics; that we can never get anywhere. He who takes a closer look at our politics, must admit that we have no right to blame others for disregard in which we are held by others, because we ourselves are responsible for it.</p>
   <p>This alone proves that a great many of us let any political windbag lead us by the nose, lower us in the eyes of others. So why talk about our political maturity in regard to which we stand at a very low level. We do not go where we should, guided by common sense, but instead we are influenced by a glass of beer, our personal interests, the dollar, and quite often just by personal grudge.</p>
   <p>Other nationalities do not act that way and they choose sober persons, having some sort of education and those who have "clean" hands.</p>
   <p>Just take a look at our candidates for various jobs and you'll be convince that almost all of them lack the necessary intelligence that one should have in order to hold office, nor do they possess such qualities as a sensible person should have.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1091.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Part of them are recruited from people who know nothing and others who never worked hard for their living. A part of them, being unable to acquire a fortune by honest work, exert themselves strenuously for office just to make some "easy" money. That, subsequently, they are expelled from office, or are put on the "black list" after serving their terms, should be no wonder to anyone.</p>
   <p>If, finally, we were only concerned about these "gray wolves," this would not have much meaning to us, but here comes into consideration our whole Polish society, because other nationalities cannot allow the Poles to choose the most stupid and ignorant to act as their representatives.</p>
   <p>Judging, then, by the actions taken of our representatives, they must pass upon us a judgment of condemnation, and more so if our representatives "distinguish" themselves in office by their rudeness, lack of education, and national solidarity.</p>
   <p>It is common to refer to the chaff amid healthy grain, but in politics it would not be well to speak of chaff in which only occasionally you can find a healthy grain. When, in addition, you will find some newspaper, supposedly influential which for a hundred dollars will sell itself to this or that party against the Polish candidate, even if <pb facs="5423968_2_1092.jpg" n="3"/>is a most decent man, and begin to write the worst possible nonsense in an effort to blacken him in the eyes of the voters, it is no wonder that people express contempt for us. Our people sustain too many heavy sacrifices to be treated as stupid persons, so that those in whose hands rests the leadership in Polish politics, and those who on the other side have an influence on the great majority should not allow it to happen that our people be scorned because there was elected into office this or that person who missed his calling and is bringing disgrace to our good Polish name.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
