<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-16">Aug. 16, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">St. Hedwig Parish School Opened by New Pastor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1895-08-16">Aug. 16, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">ST. HEDWIG PARISH SCHOOL OPENED BY NEW PASTOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Reverend John Piechowski, new pastor of St. Hedwig Parish, opened the parish school last Wednesday, August 14. Over 350 children registered.</p>
   <p>Yesterday a special outing was arranged for them by the pastor. After attending Mass services, the children boarded streetcars at about 11 A.M. at Elston Avenue to go to the outing. Order was maintained by the pastor, members of the Young People's Choir and the elders of the parish.</p>
   <p>The outing was held in Irving Park. Games of all kinds were arranged for the children and grown ups. Books and school supplies were awarded the children who won first place in the various competitive games.</p>
   <p>The games were followed by declamations, singing by the parish choir and community singing. Applause greeted all performers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0200.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The picnic proved to be a total success. All were reluctant to leave for home when the outing came to an end at 6:30 P.M.</p>
   <p>On the way home all participants gathered before the church on Webster Avenue, where Mr. Tamillo made a speech in honor of the new pastor. At the close of his speech the air was filled with shouts, cheers and applause for Reverend Piechowski.</p>
   <p>Credit should be given the Reverend J. Piechowski, the Parish Committee and Mr. Tamillo for making this event possible. The cost and the time for getting up the outing was borne by them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
