<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-07-01">July 1, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">The Holy Family Academy</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Polish Secondary School Conducted by the Sisters of the Holy Family of Nazareth.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-07-01">July 1, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">THE HOLY FAMILY ACADEMY</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Polish Secondary School Conducted by The Sisters Of The Holy Family Of Nazareth.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On June 29, annual examinations were held at the Holy Family Academy on Division Street, in the presence of four clergymen and the parents of some of the pupils. The clergymen were Reverend S. K. Kobrzynski, Reverend Lange, Reverend W. Barzynski, and Reverend J. Barzynski. Twenty-two boys and eighty-seven girls attend this school.</p>
   <p>A table was covered with work of the pupils in English and Polish composition, arithmetical problems, also in both Polish and English, and drawings, many of which were commendable. There was every indication that the sisters had worked very zealously, and that they were capable of awakening in the pupils a desire for learning.</p>
   <p>The questions asked by the sisters and the clergymen were answered promptly <pb facs="5423968_2_0299.jpg" n="2"/>and correctly, especially those which referred to Polish grammar.</p>
   <p>The pupils showed a fair knowledge of simple and complex sentences, and of American and world history. In these subjects, the girls displayed a store of knowledge much greater than could be expected at their age.</p>
   <p>English, reading, and spelling tests were a great success, proving that Miss Moore, a secular teacher in this academy possesses great pedagogical experience and attachment to the subject.</p>
   <p>The needle work, made by the girls of the academy, was admired by the ladies for the skill and good taste displayed.</p>
   <p>Sophia Warszewski and Mary Barzynski distinguished themselves by their recitations. The poetical dialogue, in which seven-year-old Joseph Barzynski, Mary Szulc, and Sophia Warszewski took part, was a success.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0300.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Efficiency of the pupils in arithmetic, from simple addition up to the rule of three, and including commercial bills, assures us that the girls in time will become practical American women of Polish descent, for they are educated in a real Polish spirit. This was proven by Polish recitations and by answers to questions on Polish history.</p>
   <p>This is one more proof that the Catholic schools are of great benefit to our youth, especially to the girls. Polish Catholic schools surpass the public nonsectarian American schools.</p>
   <p>The following pupils distinguished themselves in music: Mary Barzynski, Martha Wleklinski, Sophia Warszewski, Mary Dyniewicz, K. Magnus, and A. Kochanowski. The pupils played a part of "Il Trovatore" accurately, under the direction of M. Barzynski. The pupils were presented with awards, after which a prayer was said, and a song sung to the Sacred Heart of Jesus.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0301.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This concluded the program, and the parents and children went home. The parents were pleased because of the progress of their offspring, and the pupils were happy because of a vacation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
