<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-04-26">Apr. 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Kosciusko or Bismarck?</title><title level="a" type="sub">Point of View of the Prussianized School Board</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0976</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0976.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-04-26">Apr. 26, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">KOSCIUSKO OR BISMARCK?</title><title level="a" type="sub">Point of View of the Prussianized School Board</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The School Board of the city of Chicago, thanks to the pro-German point of view of a few of its members, has raised against itself the indignation of the patriotic people of our city, especially after the proposal by Trustee Severinghaus that, if the name of the Bismarck School should be changed, the names of the Kosciusko, Komenski, and Kozminski schools should be changed, also. Severinghaus is, to a certain extent, the spokesman for the "solid six" who, from the time that the question of changing the name of Bismarck School was first raised, have been using all sorts of tricks to prevent the matter from coming to a vote. And if an ardent admirer of Prussian culture takes this stand, it can safely be said that his companions are also of the same mind. It is contrary to the wishes of these gentlemen that the loyal citizens of this country have taken a stand against the use of the name of <pb facs="5423968_2_0977.jpg" n="2"/>one of the greatest enemies of the freedom of nations, one of the greatest of all oppressors of vanquished peoples. Following the Prussian system, these men have opposed everything that the Poles, as the nationality that has suffered the most from the Germans, have said or proposed against German propaganda.</p>
   <p>It is not surprising that when Severinghaus dared to place the name of Kosciusko on a level with that of Bismarck, indignation among the Poles was raised to the highest degree. The proceedings of yesterday's meeting of the School Board, which appeared in our columns yesterday, have opened the eyes of many Polish citizens to the fact that Prussian intrigue has become so deeply rooted in American society that they cannot any longer remain silent, that they must rise to defend the ideals of this great republic, in defense of the virtue and honor of those who have given their blood for the freedom of this country.</p>
   <p>Voices of protest are being raised against this unprecedented infamy against <pb facs="5423968_2_0978.jpg" n="3"/>the name of Kosciusko, that greatest of all champions of the liberty of nations, that immortal hero of two worlds.</p>
   <p>Miss Emily Napieralski, secretary general of the Polish Women's Alliance, states that members of the School Board who dared to place the name of Thaddeus Kosciusko on a level with that of the greatest of despots, Bismarck, ought to resign from their positions immediately. "The School Board has for some time been acting as it pleases, and we are beginning to suspect that in defending the name of Bismarck, and in the attack on the name of the American general Kosciusko, there are other base motives. </p>
   <p>"Poles have shown their attachment to the United States from the times of George Washington to the present. There are no blots on the history of the Poles living in America. Shall we remain idle while Anthony Czarnecki fights alone for the honor of the city of Chicago?</p>
   <p>"I solemnly protest against the insult that has been paid to Kosciusko's name <pb facs="5423968_2_0979.jpg" n="4"/>and against the power wielded by the School Board. And when a loyal American has been basely insulted, the Polish women of Chicago will rise together to avenge him. It is high time that the people took the power into their own hands."</p>
   <p>Anthony Czarnecki said with respect to this matter: "All efforts of the School Board to discontinue the use of Kosciusko's name on public schools must arouse the indignation of the four hundred thousand Poles in Chicago. No one who is familiar with the history of Poland, and no one who has finished the sixth grade would dare compare the characters of Kosciusko and Bismarck. The attack against the name of Kosciusko should be regarded merely as camouflage, its purpose being to divert attention from the name of that monstrosity, Bismarck, and from the matter which the School Board has been seeking to avoid for months."</p>
   <p>J. Zawilinski, secretary general of the Polish National Alliance, expressed the highest indignation at the comparison of Kosciusko to Bismarck. "The first <pb facs="5423968_2_0980.jpg" n="5"/>was an American patriot, fighting for freedom, and the second was a Prussian tyrant, fighting for self-power," said Zawilinski.</p>
   <p>The statements of the above-mentioned individuals represent the opinion of nearly all of the Poles in Chicago. Yesterday, everyone we met had nothing but words of the highest indignation for certain members of the School Board, the "solid six," as they are called. It is high time that not only Poles, but all loyal citizens protested against the action of these Prussianized members of the School Board, and forced them to resign from their positions, for which they have proved themselves worse than incompetent, and which they have defiled by their action. Our organizations ought to take a voice in this matter and show the public that Prussian propaganda is being directed against our educational institutions. It is high time that we crushed the head of this Prussian hydra.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
