<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-05-12">May 12, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Poles as Seen by Americans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1051</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1051.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-05-12">May 12, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">POLES AS SEEN BY AMERICANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every day our mail brings us many letters from Poles of all sections of the United States.</p>
   <p>These letters are accompanied by newspaper clippings from English newspapers, containing articles expressing an opinion regarding the Polish Element in America. This, no doubt, is evidence that the Americans are becoming interested in the Polish element of America through the study of our national, political and social trend of life.</p>
   <p>The articles are not altogether of a favorable nature, and besides bringing to the surface the good points of our race many of these articles very emphatically show our faults or weaknesses. They are, however, not as treacherous in text as were articles written several years back. In a few instances the American press is nevertheless justified in its mild attacks upon our element, since we lay no claim to being a perfect race or group. Many of these unfavorable comments are the direct result of the conflicts now in full swing and which are not of a foreign origin, but <pb facs="5423968_2_1052.jpg" n="2"/>caused by the conduct of our own Polish-American Press, the columns of which are filled with attacks directed at our countrymen. Therefore, if such a condition prevails within our own ranks, we should not express amazement or discontent at articles not in our favor in other papers, since the source of such information is no doubt, built upon our personal conflicts.</p>
   <p>Conditions among the Poles in America are improving; from day to day we are becoming more powerful, self-governing citizens, and we are likewise, setting a remarkable pace of development in every field of endevour. Leading universities in America show a decided increase in the enrollment of Polish students. We are therefore attracting the attention of others in this country, as a race that in a short time, with a little more cultural and social development, will attain a high position in the scheme of the daily life in this foreign country.</p>
   <p>An article appearing in the Nolyoke Daily Transcript states: "The Poles in the Western part of the state of Massachusetts are going ahead full speed, amazing all with their progress. This is also true in Sunderland, <pb facs="5423968_2_1053.jpg" n="3"/>Mass. where they are showing rapid development, if we take into consideration the fact that they are members of an oppressed race abroad. The largest local hotel was purchased by a Pole, Anton <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>ysocki.</p>
   <p>"The reason for this progress is not a<gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>mystery: the typical Pole does not shirk hard work. In addition to this virtue the Poles are, as a rule, a thrifty race. On every occasion, whether it be joyous or one of sorrow, they share their responsibilities equally, because the average Pole takes pride in aiding his countrymen; he is not a believer in the "help yourself" slogan. In addition, the integrity of a Pole is very seldom questioned; he pays his bills on time and buys the best merchandise possible."</p>
   <p>These comments express the opinion of an American observer, who just recently came into contact with Poles, and to whom heretofore the Poles were but a strange nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
