<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-06-11">June 11, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Appeal</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1891-06-11">June 11, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH APPEAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An appeal, appearing in the Vienna press, has been made by the Russian Jews for financial aid to the oppressed Jews in Russia. In that appeal, the sad plight of the Jews in Russia is depicted. Perhaps in that appeal there is none of the exaggeration practiced by the Jews when they see that someone is after their skin. Indeed, on account of a little incident which occurred at Korfu, they made such an uproar that the fleets of all the European powers were almost mobilized. We are very sorry about the sad plight of the Russian Jews who are a prey of Russian officials, but we cannot help but see in that plight a historical nemesis. Up to 1848 Poland was loved by all of Europe. In that year [1848] liberal reforms were made, including the granting of equal rights of the Jews, and the latter, being naturally clever, quickly realized the great importance of the press, and either bought out or founded newspapers. They soon dominated the entire European press.</p>
   <p>From that time on they systematically slandered the Poles every day, at every opportunity and without occasion. They published about us and about our history all sorts of possible and impossible inventions. Simultaneously, these Jewish <pb facs="5423968_2_1320.jpg" n="2"/>journals exalted and idolized Russia. Let us recall the dithyrambs written in honor of Russia not long ago in all Berlin Jewish newspapers; how the latter abused us at the same time; how the Jewish press in France cringed before Russia; and, finally, how the Jewish liberal press in Italy loved Russia for her hatred of Catholicism.</p>
   <p>In other words, the Jews have devoted forty years to creating favorable world-opinion for Russia, at the same time destroying all sympathy for Poland. They have accomplished their purpose. Europe hates us, and we need not delude ourselves about this hate. Here and there, some noble person sympathizes with us, but the public is entirely indifferent to the Polish cause or else does not like it as a thing which might disturb the peace.</p>
   <p>Instead almost all of Europe cringes before Russia; admires her greatness, her power, her wealth; is charmed by her customs, her surroundings, and her literature.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1321.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It will be hard for the Jewish press, no matter how powerful it is, to undo what it has done in forty years. It has placed Russia on a pedestal. How can the Jewish press turn the heart of Europe against Russia and toward the Jews in one appeal?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
