<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-10">Dec. 10, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Disorderly Conduct</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0473</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0473.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-12-10">Dec. 10, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">DISORDERLY CONDUCT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The police of one of the Eastern towns have received orders from their superiors to prohibit Poles from conducting dances in small halls where intoxicating liquor is sold, on the grounds that debaucheries and orgies result. Rumor has it that indecent behavior in these places was so scandalous and fights were so frequent that the police was compelled to put an end to them. And so, a new shame befalls us Poles that some of our brother Poles conduct themselves in such manner that the police have to prohibit their recreation. Everyone knows that parties and moderate recreational activities are necessary for a hard-working person--they should even be frequent--but why must they necessarily be accompanied by fights, drunkenness, and other scandals? After all, it is possible for one to enjoy himself respectably without making a din or indulging in throaty arguments and head smashing. Generally speaking, our people are respectable and give officials little opportunity to proceed against them on <pb facs="5423968_2_0474.jpg" n="2"/>criminal charges. But, after Italians and Slovaks, the Poles are the nationality against which the greatest number of charges are brought of drunkenness and disorderly conduct at parties. And yet these people could enjoy themselves as respectable and cultured human beings.</p>
   <p>Similar things occur in some of the dance halls of Chicago, where intoxicated young Polish men, and even older people, have brawls and bring only shame to our nationality. Drunken arguments and noises last until late at night in these dens, which are usually located in saloons. A cry of despair can often be heard from a guest slashed with a knife or battered with beer bottles. Blood from the wounds of a fleeing reveler streaks the floor and the street. The police, if they are on good terms with the saloonkeeper, do not molest his "guests". If, on the other hand, the police are not on good terms with the saloonkeepers, they pack the killers into patrol wagons and transfer the entire group of "banqueters" to a police station, where a judge locks up the guilty and the innocent alike. People, consider what you are doing and do not bring shame to our people who must suffer a great deal because of your so-called "parties". We implore you to behave yourself respectably, as cultured people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0475.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>How can we ever hope to gain any respect among other nationalities when disorderly drunken conduct is permitted among Poles?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
