<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1901-12-19">Dec. 19, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">To the Z. N. P. Groups in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1094</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1094.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1901-12-19">Dec. 19, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE Z. N. P. GROUPS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Brothers:</p>
   <p>We are planning to protect the poles in Chicago from the barbaric attempts and lies of the German people against the Polish population here. The Central Board of the Z. N. P. has decided to hold a mass meeting in one of the biggest halls or auditorium, in the heart of our city. It has been decided to have all the Poles that have been insulted because of our ways of living, our religion and our Catholic school system, and have been degraded and cursed by the Germans before the eyes of all the other nationalities in Chicago.</p>
   <p>To talk over the plans and steps to be taken in this movement, the Central Z. N. P. Board has invited all the officials of the Z. N. P. groups in Chicago and vicinity for a mass meeting at the home of the Z. N. P., Monday, December 23, at 8 P.M.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1095.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Central Board does not have to go into details, dear brothers, to tell you the importance of this matter. Show them that we are still alive.</p>
   <p>We cannot give up! The Russians, Austrians and Germans said that we were not able to take care of ourselves and our country, and that is why Poland was under their rule. Now, that the Poles are working their way to the top in everything the Polish initiative undertakes in our city of Chicago, they are taking drastic steps to prevent us from accomplishing our aims and ambitions.</p>
   <p>Doesn't this prove to you, Polish men and women, that we are a fighting class of people? We must be, if the other nationalities, especially the Germans, are doing everything to degrade us.</p>
   <p>Do you, people, believe that we Poles have strength? If so, let us profit by it at this moment and show the world that the Polish nationality lives, that we work for the betterment of ourselves and most of all for the freedom in this land of the free. If we fight and continue fighting, and in the end lose (God forbid:), at least we Poles can be proud that we <pb facs="5423968_2_1096.jpg" n="3"/>went down to defeat fighting ourselves to the very last.</p>
   <p>Remember this, that the future of the Poles depends on us alone. Do not lock around for help from others, because this is mostly the cause of all our troubles.</p>
   <p>For the sake of our own good come to this meeting, so we can discuss our true feelings openly.</p>
   <p>This is a very important matter and should be of interest to all Z. N. P. members as well as all other Polish people. Do not be ashamed, come and speak your opinion and version in this great fight in behalf of all us Poles. Show them that we are living and do not intend giving up without all others knowing that we are a fighting group of people.</p>
   <p>With brotherly regards,</p>
   <p>The Central Board of Z. N. P.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
