<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-07">Dec. 7, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Illegal Trusts</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1422</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1422.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-07">Dec. 7, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">ILLEGAL TRUSTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Taft's message has disturbed the hornets' nest which the thieving trusts constitute. The sure and strong blows which the President dealt in his message foretell the downfall of the monopolistic extortionists, who have grown up into giants and keep a heavy foot on the chest of the nation. They have allowed themselves to be felt most by the poorer workers, who, although employed, are dying of starvation because their wages are not sufficient even for the most miserable existence.</p>
   <p>The criminal trusts, manipulating billions of dollars extorted from the workers, are responsible for the high cost of living and the general poverty that prevails in the country. It is high time to consign all the trusts to eternal damnation--with happy results for all of us in this country.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1423.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The President's declaration of open war against the trusts will call forth a battle between two powers--labor and capital--since a tremendous majority of the workers will come forward with renewed energy against the handful of capitalistic extortionists. This will be a terrific battle because capital has great strength in money, but let us hope that the people by their tremendous mass will defeat this ruthless colossus and make him powerless for all time. The patience of the exploited and robbed people seems boundless, but when it finally reaches its limit, the people will annihilate the trust hydra so that no trace of it will remain.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
