<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-29">May 29, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">More about Reverend Piechowski's Case</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1126</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1126.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-29">May 29, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">MORE ABOUT REVEREND PIECHOWSKI'S CASE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The report published by us yesterday about the audacious conduct of the Independents, who dared to swear out a complaint against Reverend John Piechowski, accusing him of libel and forcing this respected priest to appear in court at night, has created a furore in Saint Hedwig Parish.</p>
   <p>The members of the parish have been aroused to the highest degree. All are willing to defend their beloved pastor and to sacrifice all they possess so that the conscienceless accusers be punished. This will undoubtedly happen.</p>
   <p>Here are a few more particulars of the case in question:</p>
   <p>As a pretext for his complaint, the accuser has produced in evidence issue Number 15 of Przyjaciel Ludu (Friend of the People), dated April 12 of this year. This issue contains two interesting articles. One, entitled "From Saint Hedwig Parish," relates how the parishioners celebrated the Easter holidays; the <pb facs="5423968_2_1127.jpg" n="2"/>other, entitled "From The Goat Pastures," tells of the humbug practiced by the Independents.</p>
   <p>At the very beginning of the second article we read:</p>
   <p>"Through the streets of the goat pastures a carriage was being driven along on Holy Saturday. Every five or six blocks the drab woznica [tough driver] would step on a goat and look all around. 'Quiet!' he yelled loudly. The doors of the carriage would then open, and the guardian angel number two would step out and enter the yard."</p>
   <p>This particular paragraph was claimed, for no known reason, as meaning J. Kowarzyk, and that is why he swore out a warrant against Reverend J. Piechowski.</p>
   <p>Even if the [Polish] word drab, erroneously translated "thief" and "robber" by him, actually meant Kowarzyk, it would not constitute a libel. Linde's Dictionary will convince anybody of this. It says that [in Polish] drab means an <pb facs="5423968_2_1128.jpg" n="3"/>infantry soldier--a strong, clumsy man, and no more.</p>
   <p>Where then is the insult? Where is his honor libeled? Not even that brave lawyer, Rawnik, will be able to show us.</p>
   <p>Briefly, therefore, this entire affair is a scandalous trick. Nothing can come of such a case.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
