<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-14">Feb. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Case of the Stockyards Workers against Owners</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1378</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1378.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1918-02-14">Feb. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CASE OF THE STOCKYARDS WORKERS AGAINST OWNERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Stockyards workers continued to testify as to their working conditions at the hearing before Judge Alshuler in the Federal District Court yesterday. One of the witnesses was Mrs. Rozalie Bobak, a young widow with a baby in her arms, whose husband was buried Saturday. The young woman testified as to the miserable life she led while her husband was still working; when he became ill, however, their poor family, consisting of the parents and three very small children, really came to know poverty. At the question by Frank Walsh, attorney for the workers, as to whether she received any aid during her husband's illness from the welfare societies maintained by the stockyards owners, Mrs. Bobak said she had not. Mrs. Bobak further testified that she could never go to the park with her children, that she had never seen Michigan Avenue, and that she had never seen a motion picture, for while her husband was working for Wilson and Company they never had enough money to put aside anything.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1379.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The next witness was John Kennedy of New York, president of the Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workers of America, who answered all of the questions asked by Attorney C. Meyer, representing the packing house owners. The last witness to be called before noon was John Kikulski, well-known Alliance member and president and organizer of Local 554 of the labor union in the stockyards. Kikulski capably answered the cross-questioning of the millionaires' lawyers.</p>
   <p>The first witness to be called in the afternoon session of the hearing was Mrs. Anna L. McQuillen, 6512 Dorchester Avenue, the wife of one of the union officials. She demonstrated that a family of five people, three children and the parents, buying everything at the prices existing two years ago and not spending a penny for anything but absolute essentials, needs an annual income of $1,288.84, while the average stockyards worker earns $2.75 daily, or $825.50 yearly. In her detailed testimony, Mrs. McQuillen proved that, because of high costs and low wages, the worker suffers a yearly deficit (sic) of $463.34.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1380.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>One of the last witnesses of the day was Reverend Ludwig Grudzinski, pastor of St. John of God Parish (52nd and South Throop Streets), who is intimately acquainted with conditions existing among the stockyards workers' families. Among other things, the pastor described the poverty existing among the workers living in his parish. He said that his parish consists of 1800 families, ninety per cent of whom are employed in the local packing houses. In order to relieve slightly the conditions among these victims of capitalism, Father Grudzinski established a home at 46th and Gross Streets, where girls who have no parents can live at very small cost. In addition to this, the priest-friend of labor testified that his parish school is attended by 1200 to 1300 children of both sexes. Many mothers, Father Grudzinski testified further, who are forced to go to work, can leave their children at the parish shelter, where they are cared for by the nuns. The priest answered the cross-questioning of the lawyers and the judge clearly, and the catch-questions put by the shrewd Meyer, attorney for the stockyards barons, served no purpose.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1381.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>By appearing as a witness in this labor case, Reverend Grudzinski proved that he is a real friend of the workers and of labor's cause, for which he deserves acknowledgment.</p>
   <p>The last witness in yesterday's session was Miss Agnes Nestor, president of the women's union, who also answered all of Attorney Meyer's questions clearly.</p>
   <p>The hearing of witnesses from the labor union will be continued today and soon the meat barons and their representatives will be called to the stand to testify.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
