<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-05">Dec. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Don't Waste Time and Money!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1366</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1366.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-05">Dec. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">DON'T WASTE TIME AND MONEY!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The warnings and comments below are called forth by a communication compiled by Edgar Wheelock and sent to us by the American Press League in November, 1921.</p>
   <p>In 1916, a certain American, who practiced a profitable profession, purchased a thousand dollars block of stock in a concern that dealt in the reclamation of patented inventions. He <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>as informed that within the immediate future the automobile industry would use these discoveries in the manufacture of vehicles.</p>
   <p>The stockholders would thereupon receive large dividends. Five years have elapsed since the purchase of the stock and no dividends have been paid.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1367.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This example is cited in order to produce evidence in black and white that fortunes are rarely made over night, or in a month, or in a year for that matter, as a result of the introduction of new mechanical inventions, even when these show great promise and eventually find <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>eneral use.</p>
   <p>People who invest their life-savings in the stock of these newly discovered mechanical wonders should take into consideration the above statement, Let them not be deceived by stock <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>esmen who claim that manufacturers of mechanical devices have amassed fortunes in a short time.</p>
   <p>The truth is that the cost of equipment runs into vast sums of money before the products are perfected and made practical, after which great sums of money are required to market them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1368.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The telegraph, the telephone, the electric <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, the reaper and other agricultural implements, the screwmachine, the steam engine, the automobile - these and many of their accessories belong to this category. A long period of time and <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> capital are necessary before any profit is realized.</p>
   <p>Let us take, for example, the discovery of the automatic telephone. This invention, devised over thirty years ago, was to rev<gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>lutionize the use of the telephone within a short time. An organization was founded to introduce the new telephone for practical and popular use. This developmental work lasted a number of years. The organization and the stockholders did not stint any money, for they sincerely believed that this type of telephone would replace the old.</p>
   <p>However, as a result of misunderstandings, suits, conflicts and court procedures <pb facs="5423968_2_1369.jpg" n="4"/>developed, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> six years. In 1906 a decision was reached by the courts. The <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Telephone Company was awarded the patent rights. Not one of the former stockholders made a fortune. Indeed, many received a severe financial <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> and a less <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> lifetime. At present, the owners of the new patents are preparing to replace the automatic telephone by a new <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> cities and small towns.</p>
   <p>Large volumes could be written about such experiences, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>ut it still would be practically impossible to convince the people that the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> fortunes realized from the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> in patented machinery are fictitious. As a result, vast <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> of invested capital <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> dwindled to a few paltry dollars.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1370.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Hundreds of patents are purchased by various interested concerns, but these concerns plan "fiascos" and are not interested in introducing these patents into industrial use. They are more interested in profit than in public benefit.</p>
   <p>In order not to fall into the hands of such stock companies, it is wise to turn to a reputable bank or some similar institution for aid and advice. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>hen such blocks of stock are purchased, the buye<gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> must realize that this purchase is merely a speculative and unsound investment. People with small incomes should avoid such speculative offerings and not invest their meager life-savings in stock with which they are not familiar. To risk one's savings in such enterprises is an unwise practice. Beware of a get-rich-quick schemes!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
