<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-02">July 2, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">St. Stanislaus Kostka College Terminates School Year with Exercises</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0149</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0149.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-07-02">July 2, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA COLLEGE TERMINATES SCHOOL YEAR WITH EXERCISES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Exercises and a contest for gold medals and other prizes were staged by the St. Stanislaus Kostka College last night before special guests in the school auditorium. The school year and the examinations came to an end a few days ago, and many students left for a long-awaited vacation. Consequently not all the most capable took part in the contest. Those who participated, however, were worth seeing and hearing, for their answers and discussions gave concrete evidence of the training which they have received at the only Polish College in Chicago. This demonstration was also a credit to the instructors.</p>
   <p>Besides a number of students and teachers, members of the Board of Education's examining board were on hand, as well as a few special guests.</p>
   <p>The program was divided into two parts. The first took place from 9:30 A.M. to 12:30 P.M. and primarily concerned the taking of a series of tests by the <pb facs="5423968_2_0150.jpg" n="2"/>students. At 2 P.M. the second half, the awarding of prizes began.</p>
   <p>The most impressive part of the second half of the program was the delivery of addresses by four members of the student body. All the speeches were delivered in English and were full of warmth and patriotism. John Sobieszczyk was awarded a gold medal as first prize for his stirring delivery of a talk on Thaddeus Kosciusko. Some beautifully bound books were awarded to Edmund Gordon, who spoke on the theme of "The Cross," to Anthony Bocian, who talked on "Pulaski," and to W. Kwiatkowski, who discussed "The Influence of the Catholic Church on Civilization".</p>
   <p>Walter Kwiatkowski received a gold medal for correctly answering the largest number of questions in a quiz on various subjects.</p>
   <p>Awards in advanced algebra went to W. Kwiatkowski and John Nagorznik; T.Laseecki, Konopka, and Jankowski took honors in elementary algebra.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0151.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Stanislaus Wisniewski took first prize for his German composition based on the theme "Die Wiese," while Paul Donek received a prize for making the best translation of sentences from English into German.</p>
   <p>First and second prizes for the best written papers on "Our Government" were taken by Simon Pierucki and S. Wisniewski respectively.</p>
   <p>For the best Latin paper on Kosciusko prizes went to W. Kwiatkowski and Anthony Bocian.</p>
   <p>Prizes for the best Polish paper written on "Why We Should Study Polish Literature" were given to John Sobieszczyk, W. Kwiatkowski, and F. Repinski. From these compositions one could readily infer the knowledge which the students posses of Polish poetry and poets.</p>
   <p>The awards were given by the Reverend Vincent Barzynski, C.R., pastor of St. Stanislaus Kostka's parish, as the examiners announced them. He also <pb facs="5423968_2_0152.jpg" n="4"/>gave an address that was filled with appreciation and thanks to the student body, teachers and guests. He especially commended the Reverend John Kruszynski, rector of the St. Stanislaus Kostka College. Before he concluded,the pastor called upon the students to say a few words.</p>
   <p>On the tables were displayed sketches made in the art classes and samples of other fields of the College's work. Notes on geometry, bookkeeping, physics, Greek, etc., gave evidence of the type of work which the students are doing. The art work was of especial interest to the visitors.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Fathers John Obyrtacz and Barzynski contributed two gold medals, and John Kasprzycki gave one of the books; the other prizes were offered by the college.</p>
   <p>Pauses between the speeches were filled with piano solos, songs, and violin music. These musical interludes proved to be so entertaining and skillful that Andrew Kwasigroch, choirmaster of St. Stanislaus Kostka's parish, <pb facs="5423968_2_0153.jpg" n="5"/>offered a special award, and Stanslaus Szwajkart, editor of the Dziennik Chicagoski, gave another. Francis Kondziorski received the first award mentioned for his outstanding violin solo, and the other went to Joseph Klass for his piano solo.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
