<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-21">Nov. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Polish Language in Parochial School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0358</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0358.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-11-21">Nov. 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLISH LANGUAGE IN PAROCHIAL SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"These children use Polish in their ordinary speech as little as possible," writes "Felka" in an article entitled "Some Observations on the Subject of Parochial Schools in America." Unfortunately, this is the bitter truth. It is also true that not only the parents, but the nuns and even the priests are often to blame for this.</p>
   <p>I have in mind, particularly, those nuns who were educated in the convents of other nationalities. I speak from my own painful experience. The Franciscan sisters of Milwaukee taught in my parish school at one time. Not once, but often. I heard the mother superior speak English in her ordinary conversations with the children and growing girls. Naturally I scolded her for this, but to no avail, because just as soon as I left, the English chatter began again. Having become convinved that children under care of such nuns would very soon become completely Americanized. I dismissed these nuns and engaged the Felican sisters. I did not have to scold anymore because these nuns, true Poles, from the beginning <pb facs="5423968_2_0359.jpg" n="2"/>inculcated the Polish spitit in the children in their charge.</p>
   <p>Yes,a great deal depends upon the nuns in this matter. But many priests are also not without fault. Again I speak from personal experience. Time after time my neighboring priests have visited me, and I have taken them all over the premises, showing them the recently completed church, school, nuns' home, etc. Sometimes, during these tours, the children would be having recess. They would run over in groups to greet us. They never heard an English word from me; on the contrary, they knew how severely I had forbidden the use of this language wherever it was not absolutely necessary. But the visiting priest himself would address them in English! I was horrified. Out of courtesy to my guest. I would not say a word, but many thoughts passed through my mind. This happened on several occasions.</p>
   <p>If some Polish priests themselves speak to Polish children in English, if some Polish priests themselves feel a repugnance toward their mother tongue, how can one be surprised at the children, hearing Polish nuns and Polish priests speaking <pb facs="5423968_2_0360.jpg" n="3"/>to them in English, for feeling a distaste for the Polish language, and for scorning it?</p>
   <p>Gor forbid that I should relegate all Polish priests to this category. No, indeed! There are brave, patriotic Polish priests here, the true pride of our nation, but there are, unfortunately, also priests who, upon every occasion, speak English with obvious pleasure even among themselves. Again, I speak from experience. This very thing happened during the forty-hour services. I had but recently arrived in this country. In the city in which I was employed, there were two Polish parishes. The ceremony was taking place at my neighbor's parish, to which I was invited. In the rectory there were five or six of us, all Polish priests. But what was my surprise and at the same time indignation, when these priests began conversing with each other in English! At first I observed this quietly, thinking that this conversation could not last very long, that they were probably relating some anecdote which they had read in an English paper, and which could not be told so well in the mother tongue, but finally, seeing that this English conversation was lasting <pb facs="5423968_2_0361.jpg" n="4"/>a bit too long, and seeing my person utterly ignored, I spoke with indignation: "I did not expect to find that priests have valued their mother tongue so little that even in speaking among themselves they were ashamed of using it. It is also very tactless to use a foreign language, since you know very well that I do not understand this language." With these words, I left the rectory. If, however, there are Polish priests in this country who are even ashamed of their Polish names, like the one, for example, who instead of "Wazlowski" signs himself "Laslow, clergyman from New England." One can certainly assume that school children, with such an example, before them will scorn the Polish language, and it is even possible that such a renegade will plant in the hearts of innocent children contempt and hatred for everything Polish.</p>
   <p>As for the unusual work and sacrifice of the entire Polish clergy for Polish people here, I, too, fail to see this unusual work, because, every one of the priests here, besides his work connected with the parish, should really have plenty of time for social work. The priests, for example, in the county of Poznan, as "Felka" justly observed, have an entirely different attitude. There they follow <pb facs="5423968_2_0362.jpg" n="5"/>the teachings of Archbishop Stablewski, who, in one of his addresses, spoke thus to his priests: "Go among the people, and work with the people and for the people," and the priests went and continue to go among the people, and they organize industrial and agricultural societies, loan associations, food co-operatives, public reading rooms, etc., and they are not sorry for the work and sacrifice which this entails. Therefore, a priest, there, is a true benefactor of the masses, and the people there look upon a clergyman differently than they do here.</p>
   <p>And what do the priests here do for the masses? With few exceptions, absolutely nothing. The most they do is to go among the people to beg for contributions, or to fill their pockets with dollars during carols! This just about constitues their entire contact with the masses, their entire work for the people. These people make sacrifices, but do the priests do anything for them in return? Even in the mother country, the priests are partially supported by the people, but then we often hear of the great social work that the clergy there does for its people. In this connection, I will but mention the Marchlewski Students' Aid <pb facs="5423968_2_0363.jpg" n="6"/>Society. Just read the annual reports of this society and you will see how many thousands flow out of the pockets of the clergy in the county of Poznan for the education of young people, and for enlightenment. How many men now holding important posts in our communities owe these posts to the clergy, who, having recognized the abilities of a boy, took him in and had him educated, without exerting any pressure on him to join the ranks of the clergy.</p>
   <p>Much is being written about the harmful effects of a bad press. Why do not the priests do something to remedy this evil? Why do they allow this evil to keep on spreading? Certainly, they could do a lot of good in this field, since they have the means for it. Once a great deal was said among the priests about the evil which was spreading among the people as a result of bad Polish publications. I too joined the discussion: I dared to call the attention of my confreres to the fact that there is a need in this country for a good paper for the masses, such a paper as everyone would read with interest. I was answered that not everyone would subscribe to such a paper.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0364.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>How much the priests in the mother country do for the country girls who leave their villages to take employment in the cities! They organize special societies for them; they try to have them take the Holy Sacrament regularly, with the help of ladies, they organize employment offices where the girls can apply for work, and even organize houses where the girls without jobs can receive free room and board. It is true that the priests alone do no bear all the costs entailed by this, but they always stand at the head of all of these and other welfare societies, bountifully lending their support.</p>
   <p>Do we have here any such institutions for the care of girls who have no parents, relatives, or friends and who are, therefore, often exposed to horrible temptations? There are probably more than three million of us here, and how many of these institutions do we actually have? Could not then the clergy here do a great deal of good in this direction?</p>
   <p>There is time for everything, except, unfortunately, the thing which is most necessary, work for the masses, the old and the young. There also is money for everything--there is money for expensive automobiles and carriages, for houses <pb facs="5423968_2_0365.jpg" n="8"/>and land, for gold mines, for the establishment of newspapers in which our confreres can be criticized; there is money for frequent and expensive trips to Europe, where one can brag and throw easily-earned money about: there is money for satisfying all sorts of whims, but there is not enough for welfare work among the masses from whom this money comes.</p>
   <p>When a priest in the old country dies, he leaves not only a part of his estate as a permanent legacy for the peace of his soul, and for the church, but almost always he remembers the poor, too, and therefore leaves money to St.Vincent De Paul Society, to homes for the aged, and to poor widows. He also leaves money to educational institutions public reading rooms, student aid societies, etc.</p>
   <p>What priest here has ever left a penny in his will for a Polish institution? All the churches, schools, and convents that we have, the people erect for us. It is the people who pay, and we ourselves--oh, let us blush!--do nothing, or else very little, for these people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0366.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>The field for work among the people is very large, but there are very few workers.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Clergyman from New England</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
