<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol.15. No.29.
<date when="1921-07-21">July 21, 1921</date><title level="a">Americanization and Civilization.</title><title level="a" type="sub">By A.F.Bloch (the Editor).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0879</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0879.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol.15. No.29.
<date when="1921-07-21">July 21, 1921</date><title level="a">Americanization and Civilization.</title><title level="a" type="sub">By A.F.Bloch (the Editor).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Arthur Brisbane, the noted writer for Hearst's papers has this to say on the Americanization of New York's immigrant women:</p>
   <p>"New York City had been 'Americanizing' fifteen hundred immigrant women. The work is abandoned for lack of funds.</p>
   <p>Why not persuade the fifteen hundred immigrant women to turn around and civilize a few thousand American housekeepers? These immigrant women keep house, and not with a can opener or a trip to the delicatessen store. They don't stupefy their children with soggy, fresh or hot biscuits, or make their husbands crave whiskey by filling them with stuff that an ostrich couldn't digest."</p>
   <p>Well, well, ---- look at what Brisbane writes. This is probably the first good thing he said about immigrants. Just a few days ago Brisbane said that the "small nations have no right to independence" because of this or that, but he always does say good things about the Jewish people and at the same time he casts <pb facs="5423968_2_0880.jpg" n="2"/>aspersions upon the Polish people. He was glad whenever the German aggressors in Silesia made advances and he devoted the heroic Polish "insurgents" for the stand they have taken in defense of this ancient Polish territory. Of course we don't blame Brisbane for his stand, he is paid for his work. What astounds us is the good things he now says about the immigrant women of New York. The same thing can be said about all foreign-speaking immigrant women in the entire country. The trouble with many of our eager leaders in Americanization work seems to be that they do not understand the real Americanization, which in their opinion consists of flowery speech-making, singing and a great deal of flag waving. Bear in mind the fact that the fine words of the speakers are least understood by those to whom they are addressed. We fail to understand why the work, of "Americanizing fifteen hundred immigrant women" should be abandoned. Lack of funds should be no reason. You don't need any money for that kind of work. All you need is a good American heart and ability to speak the language of those whom you want to Americanize. For that matter the great number of immigrant are good American, although they cannot tell you this in the English language. It is true, however, that many of our Americans need a little more Americanizing.- Brisbane tells us, "Why not persuade the fifteen hundred immigrant women to turn around and civilize a few thousand American housekeepers? Oh! come on now Artie, don't kick on the American <pb facs="5423968_2_0881.jpg" n="3"/>housekeepers; we pay tribute to the millions of our good American mothers, who are the exact prototype of our foreign speaking mothers; our American mothers in all instances have helped the immigrant-mothers. The American women have kept the scent of the upper air and the love of liberty in the hearts of our American boys, who laid down their lives for the freedom of mankind. America turned the scales of liberty to victory and Poland is finishing in Europe the work begun by America. The American women here in the United States have taught the same lesson to their Polish-American boys who have fought in the ranks of the American army against the hosts of tyranny and it was not because they were bred as soldiers, but because with their mother's milk they drank the pure and unduluted American patriotism. So Arthur Brisbane, don't blame the women of any nationality for lack of civilization here in America; look for the source of corruption in another direction and you will find it in our touted American upper millionaire classes, in our American crooked politicians and in our American radical circles bred by corruption, graft and lack of religious education.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
