<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-06">Dec. 6, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Washing Our Domestic Troubles in the Courts</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Letter from One of Our Readers, Francis Peska, Assistant State's Attorney)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0567</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0567.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-06">Dec. 6, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">WASHING OUR DOMESTIC TROUBLES IN THE COURTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Letter from One of Our Readers, Francis Peska, Assistant State's Attorney)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Why are there more cases in court dealing with the domestic troubles of our own people than with those of any other national group?</p>
   <p>This is the question that is formulated by many who visit the court of domestic relations. In this court family misunderstandings are unraveled and straightened out. The tribulations of young and old married couples and the troubles arising among the youth of both sexes are dealt with. This tribunal is considered an authority on the problems of the home. Its efficient method of handling the cases has won the respect of students and teachers of sociology and of many civic organizations which are interested in keeping the home and morals in high esteem and at a high standard for both sexes. This applies to married people as well as to single individuals.</p>
   <p>The court of domestic relations takes down all data concerning persons who come <pb facs="5423968_2_0568.jpg" n="2"/>here for assistance in marital or domestic troubles. The name, age, nationality, employment, etc., are taken down, including the complaint. Statistics are kept of all cases and are sent to all points of the country to be used for reference by persons interested in domestic problems.</p>
   <p>A check upon the cases reveals that Polish people are the principals in the majority of them. Their high mark outstrips even that of the Negroes. The latter hold second place. By these statistics it is apparent that other national groups pay more attention to family relations. That the Polish people treat their domestic problems with negligence is revealed by the fact that sometimes twenty Polish cases are tried to one Jewish case. The court is always filled with people of many nationalities who come to be entertained at the expense of others; therefore these people are amused principally at the expense of the Poles.</p>
   <p>I should not like to be classed among those Polish persons who do not understand the duties and the obligations of matrimony. There are many of these who admit before the court their unfamiliarity with the laws governing the home. The <pb facs="5423968_2_0569.jpg" n="3"/>number is greater in proportion than that of any other nationality.</p>
   <p>This in reality may not be true. Other nationalities may rate even worse in this respect; however, they maintain organizations that deal with marital and home problems and offer advice to those in need. Such organizations are instrumental in getting such problems settled before they reach the courts.</p>
   <p>As a result, these national groups rejoice over the fact that their people are more peaceable than those of other groups. Many people are not aware of this fact. Many do not have any comprehension of the load of work carried by these organizations which try their best to instill the American way of living into their people. It is a great burden, but they have succeeded in showing that their people are upright citizens.</p>
   <p>It is high time for our people to take under careful consideration their own problems and rectify them before they get out of control and require the courts to settle them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0570.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The court of domestic relations at times has twenty-five to forty cases on the docket to be heard in one day. A majority of them deal with marital troubles. It is impossible for the court to try each case in detail, for very few would be heard in a day. Therefore the judge has no alternative except to review hurriedly the case before him and render a decision. Many times it is impossible to give a proper verdict because of the complications in which the matter is involved. At times the confused cases that come up before the judge are treated in such a way by the tribunal that it results in a family split instead of encouraging the persons to a better understanding of their problems which would result in a better family life.</p>
   <p>Social organizations that are sponsored by other nationalities send their representatives to court in order to give a better interpretation of the problems, thereby giving to the judge a better opportunity to appraise the situation. Continuations are asked in order that the cases may be better reviewed, and suggestions are offered for their solution. These representatives have a full understanding of the marital problem or problems, and many times the court takes <pb facs="5423968_2_0571.jpg" n="5"/>their suggestions, for they shoulder full responsibility for the outcome. Many times such cases are tried in the judge's chambers at the representatives' request and are settled. The married couple to which a solution is offered by them accepts it with the greatest respect. The organization and the solution are held in high esteem. Such capable assistance lightens the burden of the courts and prevents many a family tragedy, averts court costs, and eliminates unwanted publicity. But it is not so with our people.</p>
   <p>The time has come for some of our outstanding Polish organizations that have the interest and the betterment of our people at heart to take the matter into their own hands and follow the example of other nationalities. The large number of Polish cases before the court of domestic relations is a blot on the honor of our people, for others deem us the greatest violaters of the code of morals pertaining to the home. Poles are considered not only incorrigible but undesirable. Many of these cases can easily be solved outside the courts. The other cases, after careful investigation, could be brought before the court, if necessary, and presented in so clear a manner that the court could give a fair <pb facs="5423968_2_0572.jpg" n="6"/>decision. In this respect a just remedy would be rendered to the unfortunate couple.</p>
   <p>There are other cases that could easily be undertaken by our own societies; namely, those that come before the juvenile court. Records reveal that in the number of petty crimes committed by them our juveniles exceed all others. These transgressions and their causes could as easily be taken into consideration by our Polish organizations. They could render a great service to our children and our parents. They could take measures to prevent many of these sins and show to our youth the better road to manhood and to citizenship.</p>
   <p>A few weeks ago such a committee was formed by some of our outstanding citizens. They are to call on various city officials to get a few pointers in the methods used in curbing wayward youth, so that our people may benefit by them.</p>
   <p>I sincerely hope that our organizations will listen to my plea and understand these words that have flowed from the depths of my heart. Let our societies <pb facs="5423968_2_0573.jpg" n="7"/>proudly respond to this appeal and give their moral and financial support to this humane program. We must work with ardor to better the reputation of our people to such an extent that we shall be considered exampled of law-abiding and peace-loving citizens.</p>
   <p>The eyes of all the world are turned on Poland. Let us show to the world that we are worthy citizens of this free and worthy country. Let us be proud of the fact that we are Polish, and above all, let us not soil our good name.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
