<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-01-08">Jan. 8, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Behavior of Parents Toward Children and Vice Versa</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0635</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0635.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>,
<date when="1927-01-08">Jan. 8, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">BEHAVIOR OF PARENTS TOWARD CHILDREN AND VICE VERSA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Communications from the Polish Welfare Association, tell us that many volumes can be written on the aforementioned subject, outlining the causes, of discordant situations of parents. In many homes, parents resort to very strict disciplinary measures, which have often been inherited; and which, however, basically correct are not practical, and cannot be adapted to conditions and children of today.</p>
   <p>Times and conditions have changed, therefore,obsolete ideas of strict discipline which were adopted in the average home, with effective results now produce confusion, chaos and lack of understanding in our growing children. This misunderstanding is often the cause of permanent delinquency. In the course of daily events we note that parents do not have sufficient will power to adequately govern their own children. Therefore, in a temperamental rage, and a desire to punish, they take the problems of their own children to the police station, or Juvenile Court.</p>
   <p>It is pathetic to see newspapers with headlines, or articles, relating the fact that Polish children were brought before the court at the request of their own parents; emphasizing to other nationalities, the lack of domestic management among Poles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0636.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Example: 1 -</p>
   <p>A father came to the Juvenile Court and requested that his 10 year-old son be arrested, because he had stolen money from him, and ran away from home. After an investigation it was proved that the boy asked his father for a few pennies, on Sunday, to attend a movie, the father, however, refused because financial circumstances would not permit. Thus, in his desire to be near his chums, who were going to the movies, he resorted to petty larceny. Money was left carelessly lying, on the table, in full view of the child, creating a natural temptation. Because of a false fear for the safety of the boy, the father rushed to the police station to report this incident. Who is at fault? We shall not underline it; but it is good material for serious thought.</p>
   <p>Example: 2 -</p>
   <p>A mother brought a charge against an 18 year-old son in the Boys' Court. Fortunately, an investigator of Polish origin, and connected with the Polish Welfare Association happened to be at the hearing and inquired of the mother the reason, for the action. It was apparent that her son Stephen, who worked nights in a bakery earning $30.00 per week, had been reading literature of a questionable text which brought about <pb facs="5423968_2_0637.jpg" n="3"/>misunderstanding and quarrels, and finally caused him to leave home, and live with his friends. It justly angered the mother, who, instead of dealing in the matter sensibly, or seeking advice of confidential friends, sought satisfaction in the Juvenile Court, with the definite intention of having him committed to a reformatory.</p>
   <p>What would have been the fate of this boy, had not the Polish Welfare Association taken an interest in his case. Without a doubt he would be compelled to serve a sentence in a reformatory for an unjust reason, thereby destroying forever his love and respect for his parents. In a series of conferences with the boy and his mother, through skilful investigation, he returned to his home, and amended his behavior: and we believe that he will become a law abiding citizen. Thanks to the effort of the Polish Welfare Association.</p>
   <p>The excellent accomplishments, which were the result of hard labor of the Polish Welfare Association are vividly portrayed in the above examples. The field of the settlements is vast, therefore, we need financial strength, to create a strong association, and to enlighten the Poles in regard to domestic problems. Let us not hesitate in securing membership to the Association for the low sum of $3.00 per year; we may salvage some poor Polish child from a bitter fate.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
