<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. 9, No. 20,
<date when="1905-05-17">May 17, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Chewing Gum - the Fault!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0503</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0503.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. 9, No. 20,
<date when="1905-05-17">May 17, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">CHEWING GUM - THE FAULT!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have recently read "Pole In America":</p>
   <p>We Poles have this to ourselves, that in many things we love to imitate others. If we would imitate them in something worthwhile, it would be a good thing, but we do not pay any attention to the good motives and qualities, but get accustomed to what is evil, nasty and absurd. So, as an example, a large number of our girls get accustomed to chewing gum, and this nasty habit is learned from girls of another nationality. Now, we quite often meet Polish girls, even beautiful and blooming, on the street, who while walking, keep moving their lips? They are chewing gum with enjoyment as if they were eating something very appetizing. As many times as we have met Polish girls chewing gum, so many times we have experienced an unsavory and uncomfortable feeling, and involuntarily have been reminded of the chewing by calves and heifers. If a Polish girl could see herself in a mirror, and how unbecoming the chewing of gum is to her face, she certainly would never take gum into her mouth again.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0504.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Not long ago, in Buffalo, an attractive Polish girl received a painful penalty, for chewing gum, which she will not forget so easily. A certain handsome and industrious young man met her, became acquainted, and had asked for her hand in marriage. He was well-mannered, had a good job, and quite a bit of money saved up, and therefore had all the requirements of a husband. The young lady received his proposal with delight and other girls envied her because of her affianced. Though the young man was in love, he had noticed that his betrothed chewed gum; so in a nice way, but with decision, he asked her to break the habit because he imagined that he would not have a wife at home, but a "young beast". The young lady promised but did not keep her word, because her sweetheart caught her chewing gum on several occasions.</p>
   <p>One evening on coming into her home, he again noticed, that not only she, but her two companions were working their jaws. Then, not saying much, he took up his hat and started for the door. His surprised sweetheart asked him if he was really going home and why, so suddenly. To this her betrother replied: "I am going away and I'm not coming back any more. You gave me your word that you <pb facs="5423968_2_0505.jpg" n="3"/>would not chew any more gum, but you did not keep your word. If you do not keep your word as one engaged to me, you will not keep it as my wife."</p>
   <p>Saying this, he walked quickly from the room. There rose screaming and lamenting, the young lady went into hysterics, but this did not gain her anything, because her lover did not return. The young lady to this day is unhappy, and the fault of all this, is the chewing of gum. If a certain amount of abomination is caused by young ladies chewing gum, no better an impression is made by young men chewing tobacco, so called a "chew" or "scrap".</p>
   <p>Out of their mouths they have formed various "mills", to transform the loathsome "scraps" of tobacco into some sort of stinky pap and pungent smelling liquid. More than once a pedestrian gets a stickly feeling, when such a chewer squirts under his feet a chewed up plug or a foul sputum.</p>
   <p>From the mouth of such chewer comes a foul odor, and more than one person standing in close proximity, has to move away, when such a chewer opens his mouth. So the chewing of gum, as well as that of tobacco, is a very disgusting <pb facs="5423968_2_0506.jpg" n="4"/>habit and our young people should break off the custom without any compromising.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
