<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XV. No. 15,
<date when="1904-01-19">Jan. 19, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Poles in Steel Factories</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1458</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1458.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XV. No. 15,
<date when="1904-01-19">Jan. 19, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">POLES IN STEEL FACTORIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was said outright to the workers of the Illinois Steel Company in South Chicago that their pay will be cut. The workers marched upon the office in so great a number, that the doors had to be barred to avoid trouble. After the police quieted the workers, an office employee said, "there is enough work for all those willing to work at the new scale."</p>
   <p>The workers were paying to some agents as much as 1 to 3 dollars who promised the workers, that they would receive better jobs and more pay; they claimed they were company agents. The police had all they could do to restore peace and order after this new outbreak.</p>
   <p>The police were stationed in the repair shops, the supply rooms, and near the furnaces to guard the angered men from damaging these and at the same time protect the new workers.</p>
   <p>Delegates from some of the locals were sent to the Federation of Labor, to try and settle this wage dispute. In some of the locals the Socialists started uprisings. One local, with headquarters at Madison and Sangamon, took steps to have all its members present to thrash out this strike movement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1459.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Meyer, the leader of the Socialist movement was attacked, and narrowly escaped with his life.</p>
   <p>On the corner of Madison and Peoria street, the angered workers attacked the president of the Federation of Labor, John J. Ryan, also John Stevens and James Sullivan, they were beaten with clubs and were so badly injured, they had to be sent to a hospital for treatment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
