<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VI, No. 14,
<date when="1902-04-02">Apr. 2, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">Our Respect for Our Parents</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0680</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0680.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. VI, No. 14,
<date when="1902-04-02">Apr. 2, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">OUR RESPECT FOR OUR PARENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It can not be denied that our children among other faults, have no respect for their parents. The cause is improper bringing up, misunderstanding of freedom and sometimes the influence of environment. Very often a daughter, whose mother allowed her everything, when grown and dressed in the latest style, is ashamed of her mother dressed in simple style. Ashamed of her simple talk and her simple ways. In company she answers her mother gruffly or forbids her to speak because she thinks mother is "too ignorant" for the great lady. The son, whom his father praised so much, because as a four year old "kid" he began to smoke, as soon as he grows up is ashamed to cross the street with his father, will not kiss his hand, and in his talk with his father makes your hair stand. After work the son dress up in prince Albert suit, leans against the fence and the father chops the wood, brings the coal, runs to the store for the groceries.</p>
   <p>The fourth commandment exists only in a theory for the young generation. They <pb facs="5423968_2_0681.jpg" n="2"/>have neither courage nor ambition, and adhere to the principles of the devil; because the elders come first, they can also be the first to "chop wood."</p>
   <p>The much occupied youth forget how much hardship it required to rear them; the tears and sacrifices their poor parents had to bear before "the fine moss beg an to sprout" under "sonny's" nose and the daughter donned a long skirt.</p>
   <p>After God, the parents should be most highly respected, because they are our best benefactors on this earth, and he who does not admit that and does not respect his parents, him even God abandons. Even if your daughter dressed in silks and satins and your son was the prime minister, it is their duty to respect their parents even if they are only common and poor folks, because only then you can count on the blessings of God.</p>
   <p>A fine example of honoring parents, even among those whom we class as uncivilized, is related by a certain missionary from the mouth of the Congo River.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0682.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>When this certain missionary, with his company, arrived in his first negro village, the seat of the tribe leader, the leader had asked to be escorted to his ship. He happened to be an eighty year old man with hair as white as snow. In the retinue of the missionary there happened to be one of the sons of the tribal chieftain, a very comely and intelligent man, who had been given a position in a French business house in order to learn the European languages. When his father came forth the young man bowed his head to the ground, then after rising he began to clap his hands. This being the native form of children greeting their parents. The father laid his hand upon the son's head and with his index finger made the sign of the cross on his forehead, meanwhile saying a few words; this most likely was a prayer in which he had begged the Lord for a blessing on his son.</p>
   <p>This is a beautiful example worth following.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
