<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-06">Dec. 6, 1921</date><title level="a">A Discussion about Marriage</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Women's Section)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0574</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0574.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-06">Dec. 6, 1921</date><title level="a">A DISCUSSION ABOUT MARRIAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Women's Section)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Does marriage always lead to disappointment and disillusionment? If marriage is not successful, what are the causes? What is the foundation for a successful marriage?</p>
   <p>The problem of marriage,which has always been an interesting one, requires new interpretations as times change. The following is a discussion of the problem: Why is it that some people can see nothing but failure in marriage? Why is it that marital failure gets publicity in the papers while nothing is ever said about successful marriages? Is it because accounts of marital bliss are not considered as interesting as accounts of marital failure?</p>
   <p>It is not on account of the little interest they create that successful marriages receive little publicity. The reason why they are made public is that they stir up envy and jealousy among the people. This envy is sometimes <pb facs="5423968_2_0575.jpg" n="2"/>so strong that it leads many people, through some Satanic urge, to break up the most blissful married couple. Is marriage always a deception and does it always result in failure? This is a question that can be also applied to life in general. Life and marriage are just exactly what we make them. The future depends upon the foundations we build in the beginning. There are as many successful marriages as there are old couples.</p>
   <p>"My parents," writes E.B., "were as happy in their later years as they were on the day they took the nuptial vows before the altar. They lived happily for over fifty years. When my mother died, my father became despondent over her death and as a result became gravely ill; he passed away a few weeks after her funeral." The writer goes on to say that he knows several other old couples who are happy in marriage.</p>
   <p>There is no gainsaying the fact that the cause of marital failure lies in that modern married couples do not stick to their vows, as did their parents. In the good old days,the husbands understood the nature of the responsibilities they were taking upon themselves; the wives, on the other hand, understood <pb facs="5423968_2_0576.jpg" n="3"/>that sincere love for their husbands would pay them many dividends. Wives, therefore, were industrious and thrifty, and the thought of leaving home on some escapade or getting a divorce never entered their minds. To them the until-death-do-us-part vow was law.</p>
   <p>The young married couples of a few decades ago realized that in life you pay for everything--that marriage must be paid for with virtue without which it cannot exist. Such was their conception of married life, and that is why they are able to smile today. Both husbands and wives sacrificed themselves and were patient and willing to co-operate in order to keep their vows. They knew that quick marriages were risky, that time was needed to select a suitable companion for life. As a result, the period of courtship was rather long. When they married, after considering the step from all angles, they were very considerate, understanding, co-operative and patient, even making sacrifices to keep their marriage vows. The old-timers, both men and women, took their time in choosing their mates, not overlooking the smallest detail....</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0577.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>There are people who take a long time before they decide to marry, but when they marry they find nothing to regret. Some people fall in love at first sight; others fall in love only after a long period of friendship with a woman.</p>
   <p>As a rule, marriages which follow quick courtships are bound for trouble later on. Love at first sight is an infatuation, good while it lasts but destined to assume a different aspect soon after marriage. The love that evolves from friendship, taking shape gradually, is in the long run the one that leads to happiness.</p>
   <p>There are no ready-made gardens of paradise in this world--those who want a life of bliss must work for it.</p>
   <p>The reward for our struggles is the feeling of happiness that comes to us when, after fulfilling our daily tasks, we come home to find that agreeable and understanding soul who reigns over our fireplace. This mutual understanding <pb facs="5423968_2_0578.jpg" n="5"/>and devotion is what makes life so different. The woman of the house resigns herself to her duties, knowing that she is not being neglected by her husband. Both are happy because they are not selfish; both are content because their sacrifices are bringing them many dividends.</p>
   <p>Information has reached the editorial department about a couple who has been married for eight years. Their life is one that is to be envied by many people. It is doubtful whether there is another like it. Both are happy in spite of the fact that hardship is a constant visitor at their door. The husband is an individual who learned his obligations many years before be contemplated to take a wife. His young wife was brought up like a favorite child by her parents, but this did not spoil her in any respect. After six years of marriage,conditions in the home were not as good as they had anticipated. Hard times pressed, but this did not discourage the young wife, who, putting away her kitchen apron decided to find a job. Her determination to help her husband enabled her to get a suitable position. Both were happy in their meager circumstances; both were happy in work and play.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0579.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>It is these unselfish decisions and sacrifices that make life worth while and marriage a success. There are many happy married couples today. Although their names never appear in the paper, they are happy just the same, living quietly and avoiding publicity. Perhaps this is so in order not to have the world break up the glowing fireplace in their homes, which is their happiness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
