<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-02-01">Feb. 1, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Polish Merchants Will Boycott German Goods</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1061</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1061.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-02-01">Feb. 1, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">POLISH MERCHANTS WILL BOYCOTT GERMAN GOODS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Polish merchants in Chicago are planning a very energetic boycott on all goods bearing that hated mark "Made in Germany." This information was communicated to us by several Polish drug store proprietors, who are promoting an energetic agitation, not only among the druggists but also among other merchants who handle German merchandise. The number of merchants who sell German merchandise is very large; in fact, it is much larger than most of us suspect. Polish merchants in America sell millions of dollars of German goods every year. Many Polish merchants do not even know that on most articles imported from Germany there is the small stamp "Made in Germany." Our readers can easily prove this for themselves by taking a good look at some of the post cards showing views of Chicago; they will find, on one of the corners, in small print, "Made in Germany." Not only post cards but also pocket knives, brushes, combs, pins, pencils, notebooks, religious pictures, musical instruments, and hundreds of other articles manufactured in Germany are sold by German agents in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1062.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>So far, our merchants did not pay much attention to that but now is war time, and war is war. American firms are in favor of this boycott, because, if it proves successful, it will force out all cheap German goods, representing millions of American dollars, and will furnish work for thousands of American working men. Well organized agitation may spread this boycott throughout the whole United States. If Belgium, through her sympathy, did as much for Poland, why can't the United States do the same? We are informed that all Polish commercial organizations are interested in this movement. The Polish Druggist Association and the White Eagle Commercial Association in Chicago promise their cooperation. Our merchants can take it for granted that the whole Polish community in America will give its whole-hearted support. Not only the merchants but also every one of us should help to boycott German goods, not only by refusing to buy these goods but also by persuading all merchants not to handle them.</p>
   <p>Two and one-half million American Poles who are well organized may very easily prevent millions of dollars from flowing into Prussian pockets; the impudent <pb facs="5423968_2_1063.jpg" n="3"/>Prussian H. K. T. or the Pole haters will then realize that we are not so feeble as to allow them to mistreat us with impunity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
