<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-18">Jan. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">From the Strike Front</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1654</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1654.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1922-01-18">Jan. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE STRIKE FRONT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A mass meeting was held in Slowacki's Hall Monday afternoon by the Stockyards' strikers. This rally was more or less a demonstration of labor to show the citizens of Chicago the strength of their forces, which for the past six weeks has adhered to its original demands.</p>
   <p>The large crowd of strikers that gathered filed orderly into position and started out into the streets. At the head of this marching group of demonstrators were a number of men bearing large American flags. Marching in unison behind the red, white, and blue flags, the stockyards' strikers did not let the police interfere with their purpose. Although several shots were fired by the police in an effort to scatter the demonstrators, the grim determination of the strikers to show their strength to the public continued onward peacefully, despite the fact that several of our innocent people were wounded.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1655.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As the marchers reached 43rd Street at Marshfield Avenue, several strong-arm men, apparently hired by the stockyards' officials, made an attempt to break up the parade by attacking the men with clubs. The marchers, consisting of thousands of packing house strikers, continued onward. One of the henchmen, or policemen, fired into the moving mass when resistance was offered. Anthony Marczak, 28, of 4836 So. Marshfield Avenue, was critically wounded in the back. This cold-blooded attack did not stir the ire of the strikers, they marched forward in peace.</p>
   <p>It has been rumored that a Polish police officer shot Mr. Marczak; however, the New City Police Station denies this. The wounded man was taken to the Cook County Hospital; his fate is uncertain. Several others were also nursing bruises that were dealt by the clubbing henchmen.</p>
   <p>The parade ended at 4:30 P. M. The interference that occurred the day <pb facs="5423968_2_1656.jpg" n="3"/>before yesterday will be long remembered by the strikers.</p>
   <p>Officials of the Stockyards, because of the strike conditions existing in their plants, have their residences guarded by the police day and night.</p>
   <p>Last Saturday, over one thousand dollars worth of food was given out by the unions to the needy strikers. The American Federation of Labor is supporting their cause and is asking the support of organized labor to send whatever help possible.</p>
   <p>Those who have not yet made any contributions for the poor strikers are urged to do so immediately. The unfortunate strikers have been without work for six continuous weeks. Their children are constantly begging for bread, for the fathers have no money to purchase the bare necessities of life. Donations should be sent to Walter Bakowski in care of Slowacki's Hall, 1700 W. 48th Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
