<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-02">Dec. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Parochial Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Challenge by B. Promyk, Member of the Polish National Alliance and the Falcons</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0042</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0042.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1911-12-02">Dec. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">PAROCHIAL SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Challenge by B. Promyk, Member of the Polish National Alliance and the Falcons</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This heading, although promising much, is not as threatening as it seems.</p>
   <p>In reality, this is not a challenge but a continuation of a subject already begun. The subject is a very important one, as it concerns one of the most important problems confronting us in a strange land.</p>
   <p>In his most recent remarks on this subject, the reverend correspondent from New England asked the members of the Polish National Alliance clearly to define their stand on the school question. I believe that all the members of the Alliance who have taken an active interest in this problem have already clearly defined their position, for which they were bitterly assailed by uninvited critics. I take the liberty of voicing my opinion on this <pb facs="5423968_2_0043.jpg" n="2"/>matter and declare that we members of the Alliance desire, with all our hearts, to co-operate in the development of Polish schools here in America, regardless of who began them. But we demand certain prerequisites. According to our demands, the schools should be for everyone and should be based on purely national precepts. They should not be controlled by any faction--religious or otherwise. By this we do not mean that the teaching of religion should be eliminated.</p>
   <p>Those who suspect the members of the Alliance of extreme attempts to suppress the teaching of religion in our parochial schools, are gravely mistaken. We know, or at least a great majority of us know, that religion elevates the people of a nation. Religion is so strongly connected with the history of certain nations that it is impossible to find a definite line of demarcation between their religious and political pasts. Why, then, should we be continually showered by the so-called "preserving" party, or what has already become to be known as the "clerical" party, with such pretty nick-names as "atheists," "nondenominationalists," "enemies of the Catholic <pb facs="5423968_2_0044.jpg" n="3"/>Church," and many similar ones, the meaning of which probably our opponents themselves would be unable to define, let alone ascribe them justly to the members of the Alliance?</p>
   <p>We members of the Alliance desire the separation of the so-called materialism from spiritualism, that is, the separation of worldly matters from those of the soul. The people pay for the building of churches and rectories, they pay for their upkeep, for the interest on their debts, and for their mortgages. Therefore, in accordance with the basic principle of the American revolution--"no taxation without representation"--they should have a voice in the management of the parish, and a decisive voice at that. Do they have it? No. The present imitations of supposed parochial boards of directors are at best poor parodies. Who does the electing and who elects whom?</p>
   <p>The matter of the churches is of lesser importance--they are buildings dedicated to God's service. But why have we been deprived of the schools built and supported by our hard labor? Why is it that here, too, we have nothing to say?</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0045.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Why should these havens of our national existence become someone else's property? Why should we pay with our hard-earned money so that our Polish language be thrown out of our parochial schools or merely tolerated there by an order of foreign bishops unfavorably disposed toward us? And the writer has proof of this.</p>
   <p>I request an answer to these questions! I agree absolutely with the Reverend from New England that the Polish clergy encounters many difficulties in conducting parochial schools, but I decidedly maintain that these difficulties would disappear entirely if all of us were summoned--but summoned sincerely--to do this work together. Our people, if properly approached, would not refuse to make any sacrifices for this purpose, and among them many would be found who would lend a hand in the good cause. But we are pushed aside only because we demand certain conditions and because we do not want to accept blindly the dictates of our "lawmakers".</p>
   <p>We are eager to live in concord--we want to co-operate, but this must be <pb facs="5423968_2_0046.jpg" n="5"/>on the basis of the free with the free, the equal with the equal.</p>
   <p>The method we follow in discussing a matter of such grave importance interests me greatly, and I hope that further polemics on this subject, if conducted without rancor and anger, will lead us toward a better understanding and perhaps to a so-called "Ankieta" [Translator's note: An investigation of a problem through discussion], as is often the case in the homeland, with benefit for both sides.</p>
   <p>I have put forward these suggestions in order to enliven the discussion of this great problem. I invite to it not only the deeply respected Reverend from New England, but everyone who wishes to discuss this matter with me intelligently, for everybody's benefit.</p>
   <p>I have as my aim only the good of all--not a simple match of words.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
