<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. V, No. 11,
<date when="1901-03-13">Mar. 13, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Teach Our Youth Love of Work and Respect for Others Who Work</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0692</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0692.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. V, No. 11,
<date when="1901-03-13">Mar. 13, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">TEACH OUR YOUTH LOVE OF WORK AND RESPECT FOR OTHERS WHO WORK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>God did not endow all equally, that is, some less, others were more endowed with good deeds and judgment or brilliancy.</p>
   <p>We have no millionaires among our wanderers. We do not imitate a learned group, there are few of us who could command high office, because we are a people of toilers and must, therefore, in order to exist fight for this existence.</p>
   <p>Our entire future lies in our own young offsprings upon whom we should impress from early childhood that the future depends upon the consolidation and unity of work, be it physical or mental.</p>
   <p>Those who can must educate their young, because what the parents do for them will pay personal dividends in the future and become national wealth.</p>
   <p>Work gives us heart, teaches us our duties and obligations, and although under <pb facs="5423968_2_0693.jpg" n="2"/>trying conditions, we do not allow ourselves to believe about better fortunes that perhaps God may bless us with.</p>
   <p>Aside from work, teach our young to respect people who work.</p>
   <p>Educate our children from the time they begin to reason, that it is worth more to be an honorable toiler in the lowest category than to be a lazy gentleman who may have his position and name handed down from princes and nobles, with a golden crown, who boasts of his ancestors as being really great, but he himself hasn't any desire to work.</p>
   <p>Teach our young to be able to distinguish the good grain from the hull, just like the difference between a good man's work and that of a lazy one, to be ashamed of the latter kind and avoid them, and join forces with those who work for the family, recognition and fame.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
