<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-07">Apr. 7, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">Students of St. Stanislaus Kostka College Present a Review in Honor of Father Barzynski</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0228</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0228.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-04-07">Apr. 7, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">STUDENTS OF ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA COLLEGE PRESENT A REVIEW IN HONOR OF FATHER BARZYNSKI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We received the following report about the review presented by the students of St. Stanislaus Kostka College the day before yesterday:</p>
   <p>"On Reverend Vincent Barzynski's birthday, St. Stanislaus College held a review which surpassed all our expectations. The program consisted of twenty four numbers.</p>
   <p>"A group of priests from outside of Chicago, as well as a number of laymen, listened with great interest to the exercises of the boys. There were speeches in Polish, English, and Latin; recitations and violin solos, varied by beautiful singing, testified to the dean's energy and the diligence of the students.</p>
   <p>"Among others, student A. Kalinowski distinguished himself by [delivering a] <pb facs="5423968_2_0229.jpg" n="2"/>speech in Latin and [by his] beautiful drawings. Jaworski's recitation about the battlefield of Raclawice brought tears to his listeners, and M. Czajkowski thrilled [the audience] with his violin music.</p>
   <p>"It would be almost impossible to ignore A. Kwiatkowski's drawings, which deserve special attention. If Kwiatkowski would only pay more attention to this subject, he could win great success.</p>
   <p>"Every number of the program was executed with great precision, and for this reason all performers were greatly applauded.</p>
   <p>"The results obtained by our youth, and which we witnessed the other day, bring credit to the whole American Polonia.</p>
   <p>"The children of well-to-do parents should benefit by this college, for it is just as good as any American institution. Polonia is growing, and so does the number of the students every month. We wish this institution success.</p>
   <p>"One who was present"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
