<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-03-04">Mar. 4, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">Against Cigarettes</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0547</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0547.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1897-03-04">Mar. 4, 1897</date>.
<title level="a">AGAINST CIGARETTES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The local City Council has recognized that the smoking of cigarettes is detrimental to the health, especially to minors. Whether the smoking of cigarettes on the whole is injurious to the health we will not argue with the City Council. We only wish to call attention to the habits of the Slavic peoples, among whom the smoking habit is widespread, and no one among them calls attention to the harmful effects of this habit.</p>
   <p>No doubt is expressed either in America or in Europe that the minors who smoke become dwarfed, wasted, and short-lived. This is accepted as a fact.</p>
   <p>What kind of cure is there for this? In Europe it has been a long practice to forbid children to smoke cigarettes, cigars, and pipes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0548.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The retailer selling tobacco to minors, and parents who permit their children to smoke, are subject to a fine by the authorities. The schools, the folks at home, and society in general constantly warn the children against the evils of smoking.</p>
   <p>In Chicago, however, the City Council has a different practice. It takes advantage of this injurious habit in order to increase the city funds. A one-hundred-dollar tax is placed upon retailers selling cigarettes, thereby taking away a means of livelihood from the poor businessmen who cannot pay such an exorbitant tax. He who can pay this high tax is permitted to sell cigarettes, poison children, and undermine the health of our future citizens.</p>
   <p>In the event a teacher or any responsible citizen sees a child smoking a cigarette in an alley or elsewhere and gives that child not only a sound thrashing but a severe verbal reprimand, that individual can be arrested for cruelty to minors. But the man who pays one hundred dollars receives a permit <pb facs="5423968_2_0549.jpg" n="3"/>to poison the children, the standard bearers of posterity.</p>
   <p>Despite this absurdity, our city officials consider themselves the representatives of this great country, which is supposed to be one of the civilized nations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
