<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-07">Jan. 7, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Many Polish Families Suffer Great Privations in Town of Lake</title><title level="a" type="sub">Shortage of Coal, Milk and Other Commodities Forces Poor Mothers to Beg</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0702</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0702.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1928-01-07">Jan. 7, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">MANY POLISH FAMILIES SUFFER GREAT PRIVATIONS IN TOWN OF LAKE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Shortage of Coal, Milk and Other Commodities Forces Poor Mothers to Beg</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, another visit to several Polish families, suffering great hardships, was made.</p>
   <p>Provisions furnished by individuals or welfare societies in the form of Christmas baskets have long disappeared. Gifts of money have been spent during the holidays, while the force of poverty is increasing with each passing day under the roofs of many Polish families.</p>
   <p>Who will provide for these destitute people and dry the tears of the mothers? Who will come with a kind heart and help these people who have been left <pb facs="5423968_2_0703.jpg" n="2"/>stranded as preys of want in the whirlpool of American life? Will we permit gradual death through starvation to our people, especially the children, who look upon the world with pleasant eyes and upon their sad existence.</p>
   <p>"Mister," said one of the neighbors of Mrs. Hedwig K., 4937 So. Loomis Street, "I fear that this grieved mother will not return to her home today. She said to me several times that she will take away her life, for she will not be able to endure such misery any longer."</p>
   <p>"And the husband?"</p>
   <p>"Ah what a husband this unfortunate woman has. As yet, he never brought his 'pay' (salary) home--always coming home drunk."</p>
   <p>"How much does he earn?" was asked.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0704.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Ah, what kind of earning do you call that. He brings home about sixteen dollars a week and from it three children must be fed and clothed, besides the husband and wife. This would not be so bad if he brought this regularly, but he makes demands on his wife who is forced to go out and beg in order to keep her children alive. In addition, her husband has been out of work for sometime."</p>
   <p>When a visit to the home was made the mother was out--out, begging. Out in the yard three children were playing amidst the melting, dirty snow. Two of the children, both girls, belonged to the unfortunate family. It was evident that they were hardened to their misery, for they were bareheaded and dressed in thin clothing.</p>
   <p>"Is your mother at home?"</p>
   <p>"No, mother is not at home."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0705.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"But if you will visit us," said the other seven year old girl, "my mother will tell you about her."</p>
   <p>The second floor was visited.</p>
   <p>"Good morning, madam, I have several dollars for Mrs. K. I understand that the family is in dire straits."</p>
   <p>"Oh, there is great poverty," replied the woman, who was a picture of health.</p>
   <p>A conversation about the stricken family took place.</p>
   <p>"Sir," said the woman, "I have a second husband but I never knew such poverty."</p>
   <p>"Which are her children?"</p>
   <p>"O, those two girls outside. The oldest is almost seven. The youngest is not able to walk as yet. This makes three children in all--all girls."</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0706.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The floor, rather dark looking, was scanned for the infant. Two dirty dogs were warming themselves under the stove. In the corners lay some wood and broken toys. On the left side a cupboard stood. The lower doors were open and behind them the small child was sitting. The stockings on the child's feet were black with dirt. The child was very thin. Both hands were filled with flour, which was taken from the bottom of the cupboard. Just then the child began to cover her face with the flour.</p>
   <p>"Ah, this child gives me more trouble than all the other children put together," replied the woman. "The baby is forever getting into something; after getting a handful of something it goes into the mouth. Apparently this is done because of hunger," she added after a pause.</p>
   <p>The guardian of the child rose and wiped its face with a soiled cloth and placed it among the dogs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0707.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"Stay here by the 'pups', it will be warmer," remarked the woman as she placed it before the small dogs, which felt annoyed by the intrusion and left towards the door.</p>
   <p>The unfortunate woman in question had her husband arrested because she could no longer stand his treatment. She charged that he beat her cruelly when he was intoxicated and demanded money from her.</p>
   <p>Another incident similar to the above was met at 1224 West 50th Street.</p>
   <p>The husband is in jail for beating his wife and for non-support of four children. The poor wife recently returned from a hospital where she underwent a serious operation. The mother is residing with her brother, who is also poor. He can barely provide for his large family.</p>
   <p>An inquiry was made at the first floor about Mrs. B.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0708.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"Yes," came the reply, "only she is not at home, she went out to get some things left by her husband."</p>
   <p>The case history was the same. The husband constantly came home under the influence of liquor, penniless, beat his wife to such an extent that she had to flee to her neighbors or relatives for help. Finding no help among her friends, she had her husband arrested and put in jail.</p>
   <p>After a few minutes the sick and poor woman entered.</p>
   <p>Her appearance was pitiful. The face was tinged with a yellowish hue and very thin looking, the eyes were sunken and she had a difficult time breathing after her long walk along Bishop and Throop Streets.</p>
   <p>"Here are a few dollars for you, madam."</p>
   <p>"I heartily thank you for your kindness. Now, if only temporarily, I will <pb facs="5423968_2_0709.jpg" n="8"/>have something to pay my debts with. I have debts outstanding in all the neighborhood grocery stores. No longer can I get food on credit."</p>
   <p>The same conditions are prevalent at 4736 South Ada and 4815 South Ada Street. In these two homes although the husbands are not drinkers they are not able to find work. Both stay at home and only leave in the morning to search for employment. Each day at noon they are back with the same story:</p>
   <p>"There is no work."</p>
   <p>Hunger, cold and dreadful misery is gradually forcing its way into the homes. From day to day the scene is the same; the worry is the same; and the struggle is the same.</p>
   <p>It must be said that the Guardian Angel shelter is making a great effort to assist the poor in this locality. Aid is given in various ways. Coal, food <pb facs="5423968_2_0710.jpg" n="9"/>and clothing is given out. But all this is not enough. The aid of the unfortunate poor must reach the deeper strata. The bare necessities of life are not enough. We have in this neighborhood many Polish organizations. But these, it seems, are only concerned with the general affairs of the organization and nothing else.</p>
   <p>During the time of the great war these same societies made contributions to the newly formed homeland, to the Polish army in France, which to this day is remembered and lauded. At this time, however, money is no longer needed for these causes. How wonderful it would be if these clubs banded together and made an effort to drive the existing conditions of misery out of the homes of the poor families. There are a out two hundred Polish Societies in the township of Town of Lake. If each contributed five dollars per month, two thousand dollars [sic] could be had to combat the ever increasing misery. What is needed is getting these groups together to discuss the problem and make <pb facs="5423968_2_0711.jpg" n="10"/>plans for action. For Hunger, misery and death from starvation are awaiting the poor.</p>
   <p>Give them succor, friends!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
