<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-07-01">July 1, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Nazarene Sisters' Elementary School for Girls</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0250</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0250.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-07-01">July 1, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">NAZARENE SISTERS' ELEMENTARY SCHOOL FOR GIRLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Examinations were held at the Nazarene Sisters' Elementary School yesterday for the third, fourth, fifth, and sixth grades, under the direction of Father Simon Kobrzynski, in the presence of numerous visitors. The school is conducted on the eight-grade plan and is exclusively for girls. Besides other subjects, four languages are taught, namely: English, Polish, French, and German. During the examinations, the girls answered questions on all subjects clearly and confidently, giving proof of the wonderful progress they are making. It is difficult to praise them, for they seemed more lucid in each subject. We must mention, however, that the Sisters give special emphasis to Polish history and literature and train their pupils properly in the Polish patriotic spirit. For this we must pay them homage.</p>
   <p>Drawings and writing exercises on exhibit were very carefully done, with a complete understanding of the subjects treated. We glanced through a few fairly large albums in which were written thoughts and verses from the best known <pb facs="5423968_2_0251.jpg" n="2"/>English poetical works. What a good idea! If only our children could be as well acquainted with the gems of Polish literature!</p>
   <p>We do not have space enough to describe in detail the work done in every subject. We merely say that everyone present could express nothing but the sincerest acknowledgement and the highest praise for the school.</p>
   <p>During the past year, one hundred and thirty pupils attended the Nazarene Sisters' School. It is expected, however, that after such gratifying results as were achieved this term, the number of pupils will be doubled.</p>
   <p>The girls presented a floral wreath to their teacher, Sister Felicyta, whose experienced and tactful handling of the examinations evoked the admiration of all those present. To the wreath, the pupils added the pearly tears of sincere love.</p>
   <p>Everyone who understands the importance of a girls' elementary school, and <pb facs="5423968_2_0252.jpg" n="3"/>everyone who has recognized the sincere, conscientious work of the Nazarene Sisters, will join us when we say, by way of acknowledgment and encouragement to even greater effort, the ancient Polish words:Szczesc Boze (Godspeed).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
