<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-05">Oct. 5, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Our Rejuvenation Lies in Co-Operation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1028</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1028.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-05">Oct. 5, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">OUR REJUVENATION LIES IN CO-OPERATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Just as fresh air contributes to bodily health, spiritual morality, acquired through true education, strengthens and ennobles the soul. During the present era all nations turn their attention to the study of matters that have the utmost importance. They make innumerable discoveries and various inventions. In a word, they make progress at every step, in order to ease the existence of future generations. Many efforts have been expended to make dreams a reality. Nevertheless it is far from the time when any nation can say: This is enough of striving; what we have thus far acquired will suffice. Any sane nation will not remain stationary, but will plod forward unceasingly, when it has once selected a path. The reason for its refusal to remain stagnant is that it possesses enlightenment, it knows that this life is a beautiful thing, that it is worthwhile to bear the hardships to prolong this life. Only the unenlightened nation <pb facs="5423968_2_1029.jpg" n="2"/>fails to understand the true value of life, and hence makes no effort, nor does it care, to elevate itself by education and really live, in the full sense of the term.</p>
   <p>We feel fully the influence of environment and the power it possesses over our morality in life and the benefits we have from it. Nothing of any importance can be found among a completely uneducated and totally neglected people. Education is necessary to the achievement of everything in that category. Every nation, as every individual, though it only wishes to be fully alive and to compete with its bordering neighbor, must be ever alert, must continually strive toward a higher level, and must strengthen itself spiritually.</p>
   <p>Our Polish people are thus far, generally speaking, very unenlightened. Very few can be found among us to whom this world is really of interest. Nearly all of our Polish people possess no enlightenment and adhere to age-old traditions which could be greatly modified. The educational level which we have reached <pb facs="5423968_2_1030.jpg" n="3"/>is in no way <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> for a truly good life. This knowledge we now possess in no way heralds a bright future for us. If we fail really to strengthen our selves and definitely to uproot drunkenness, discord, and other shortcomings from our midst, then the future of our people is very beclouded.</p>
   <p>Perhaps some of our readers may ask what good it is to spread enlightenment among us as long as the theory of morality has no influence upon our life. Should someone be under such an impression, he would be in grave error. Knowledge is the main basis of morality, and everyone should know it. What we are concerned with here is that more acquaintance with the fact is insufficient; practice in a given sphere of activity is necessary as well as knowledge.</p>
   <p>A person, although he possesses knowledge of some general principle, will rarely be able to apply it in his life if he lacks the proper culture and moral qualifications.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1031.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Hence the purpose of our spiritual rejuvenation should be to create love of freedom in ourselves and to arouse moral convictions which will guide our actions. We should know that our actions are the best proof of morality, and that everyone judges us according to them. The motives and the deed must always be in perfect harmony with each other; otherwise there cannot be even the slightest thought of true morality. The developing of moral concepts should be the first step in creating an atmosphere among people which will be a foundation for our spiritual life. With time, all this must exert a vast influence upon our feelings and, therefore, upon our progress.</p>
   <p>Even if there were no other motives for worming in the cause of spiritual regeneration, the mere fact that there is an increase in the trend among people to have no respect for <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> should suffice. Wherever knowledge, feeling, and progress become subject to culture, we shall see results in moral progress. We must feel not only the need but the absolute necessity to understand human nature thoroughly and to apply ourselves to it intelligently.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1032.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Educating not only the younger generation, but also nature people who are not as yet properly enlightened, is part of the process of moralizing humanity. The feeling of harmony is the most beautifull moral attitude and one which humanity should develop. Instead of inciting hatred, which we now see among various parties, we should develop a feeling of brotherly love and should educate the entire generation in that direction. It is unnecessary to force one's views upon another; others should be allowed to express their feelings, discuss them, and thus arrive at a mutual understanding.</p>
   <p>At the present time nearly all social conditions are made on the basis of the most dense egotism. Today we find that individuals, as well as the various societies, manifest by their action a tendency that is completely egoistic, entirely contrary to the general social welfare. Nearly everywhere we find that people strive only for personal gain. The greater part of the people, who have a very low level of knowledge, are unable to understand that everyone--both individuals and groups--could gain huge benefits, not only ideal but also <pb facs="5423968_2_1033.jpg" n="6"/>real, if they only limited their hatred toward each other. Harmony is needed among us. I repeat, harmony!</p>
   <p>Whoever feels the dignity of man should exert every effort to bring about a union of dissenters. By so doing, he would render a great service for our national ideals. A person of that type could really be called a true son of our motherland--one who truly desires rejuvenation and liberation from the chains of enslavement.</p>
   <p>(Signed) St. J. Michalczyk</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
