<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 23,
<date when="1919-06-04">June 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Defense of Poles against Attack by Jews</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0918</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0918.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XXIII, No. 23,
<date when="1919-06-04">June 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">DEFENSE OF POLES AGAINST ATTACK BY JEWS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. N. L. Piotrowski, president of the Polish Roman-Catholic Union and cashier of the National Department, sent a cable ram to President Woodrow Wilson on May <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> 1919, which reads as follows:</p>
   <p><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Woodrow Wilson</p>
   <p>President of the United States</p>
   <p>Paris, France</p>
   <p>The Jews in America are making a nationwide campaign against Poles and the new Polish Republic, chargin them with pogroms against Jews. The eminent Chicago Jews, Julius Rosenwald and Adolph Krause have cabled you that reliable reports have reached them about hundreds of Jews killed and buried alive in Poland, also thousands wounded and hundreds of thousands of their homes pillaged or ruined. During the war the undersigned visited Poland, making a special study of the Jewish situation, and can truthfully state there were no pogroms in Poland, but that there were bread riots.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0919.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Jews hoarded food supplies and demanded exorbitant prices from starving population and thus provoking riots against speculators, who were mostly Jews, but neither race nor religion of speculators was considered by victims of profiteering whose only thought was to punish the guilty. This anti-Polish <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> has been instigated by powerful interests seeking commercial domination in Poland, failing in which they now intrigue to deprive Poland of just rights by slanderin the good name of the Poles.</p>
   <p>The undersigned knows this to be true.</p>
   <p>K. L. Piotrowski.</p>
   <p>I, the undersigned, Dr. B. L. Smykowski of <gap unit="words" extent="2" reason="illegible"/>, Conn., declare that during my visit to Poland in February and March of this year, as representatives of the Polish Relief Committee of America, I covered practically the entire country, and after exhaustive investigations can confirm the foregoing statement of <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. L. Piotrowski in every particular. Furthermore, I know from personal observation that in <pb facs="5423968_2_0920.jpg" n="3"/>several localities starving inhabitants attacked establishments where dishonest speculators stored foodstuffs and demanded prohibitive prices. These speculators were mostly Jews. Furthermore, nearly all Jews I observed fostered bolshevic tendencies, as for example in Kielce, where a crowd of Jews made a street demonstration during which they shouted: "Long live Lenin," and "Long live Trotzky," and "Down with Poland." Naturally, this angered loyal Poles and a skirmish resulted in which a number of Jews were killed, not because they were Jews, but because they had offended the national sentiment of the Poles by acclaiming bolshevism. Such outbreaks have occurred in certain localities because so many Jews are profiteering and sowing the seed of bolshevism and anarchy. No self-respecting nation would tolerate such pernicious activities.</p>
   <p>Dr. Bronislaw Smykowski.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
