<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abstynent</title>,
<date when="1911-11">Nov. 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[New Type of Public Enemy]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0463</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0463.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abstynent</title>,
<date when="1911-11">Nov. 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[NEW TYPE OF PUBLIC ENEMY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Notwithstanding the absolute dishonesty of the saloon businesses, our saloon keepers in America always have the necessary influence and the position in society to give them respect.</p>
   <p>In this case the money of saloon keepers is in play; we know that to everybody the dollar is everything, especially in America.</p>
   <p>Beside this, most of the saloon keepers are Polish Catholics, bringing disgrace and shame for themselves and Polish society.</p>
   <p>In Poland most of saloons are operated by Jews, because a real Pole and Catholic think himself too respected and too honorable to operate such a vile business. And this is the reason why saloon keepers and saloons in Poland are insulted and become mean to the Polish people. And for that reason the Poles are filled with antipathy and antisemitic aversion. In America it is the opposite. Polish Catholics are operating saloons because it is simpler and more profitable than any other business.</p>
   <p>To be a saloon keeper every ordinary man with the ambition of good drunkard <pb facs="5423968_2_0464.jpg" n="2"/>or plenty of "gab" will do. Even the brewery helps them financially when it comes to rent, fixtures, merchandise and furniture; they give them these for credit.</p>
   <p>Poles willingly give their support to their countrymen, go to the saloon and support them in the name of patriotism, and saloon keepers good heartedly serve them drinks of any kind, domestic or imported.</p>
   <p>Business is going good. Support your fellow countrymen with the aim of solidarity.</p>
   <p>Saloon keepers are public enemies, transgressors who ruin whole families and the whole nation.</p>
   <p>Any respectable man or woman should not even shake hands with them, also everybody should ignore and be disgusted with them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
