<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-01">May 1, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Our Polish Clerks</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1509</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1509.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-05-01">May 1, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">OUR POLISH CLERKS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The spring season has arrived and soon summer will be here.</p>
   <p>Practically everybody must provide himself with summer clothing, and there are many other things to buy. One person needs this, another that. The stores and shops are all very busy. Everybody is visiting them and buying various things.</p>
   <p>So at this time it is proper for us to make certain observations.</p>
   <p>We Poles do not own any large clothing stores, shoe stores, dry goods stores, men's and ladies' furnishings stores--we must therefore make our purchases in stores owned by those of other nationalities. When we buy anything from them, they make a profit. We must make sure, then, that those who are favored with <pb facs="5423968_2_1510.jpg" n="2"/>our trade are worthy of it--and that they also give our Poles an opportunity to earn some money, also.</p>
   <p>Let us support only those stores and businesses that respect the Poles and who also support us. So, first we should support those stores that advertise in the Polish papers. Those businessmen who seek Polish trade by advertising, and pay for that advertising, deserve our support. We should support them as a good business proposition. Only respectable and honest stores advertise. You can buy what you need at low prices. The prices in these stores are stable.</p>
   <p>The stores that cheat usually do not like to advertise.</p>
   <p>In the stores owned by people of other nationalities, we should insist on being waited on by Polish clerks. It is our right--even our duty. First of all, we are the buyers, and allow the merchants to make a profit. They should, therefore, serve us in a manner that will please us. Why should we "break our tongue" <pb facs="5423968_2_1511.jpg" n="3"/>trying to speak a foreign language, entirely strange to us, and why should we torture ourselves (and, at that, be misunderstood), when we can have a Polish clerk who will understand us at once and serve us to our complete satisfaction?</p>
   <p>There is no reason why we should be ashamed of being Poles--and we don't have to be!</p>
   <p>On the contrary, we should, as soon as we enter a store, demand the services of a Polish clerk. He will give us better and speedier service. The Swedes, Germans, and Dutch do this, and are satisfied. Why shouldn't we imitate them?</p>
   <p>We should consider it our duty to ask for Polish clerks, in order to help the many young Polish clerks. Store owners enjoying a Polish trade, when faced with the demand for the services of Polish clerks regularly, will be forced to employ our own brethren. They cannot lose by doing so. The Poles will earnestly support those stores which do not scorn our brethren; such stores will benefit a <pb facs="5423968_2_1512.jpg" n="4"/>hundred fold for going to the expense of hiring Polish clerks. Both sides will benefit by this arrangement. But it is necessary for all Poles to patronize those stores that are willing to advertise in the Polish papers and pay Polish clerks good wages--and that we should never be ashamed to say that we are Polish and that we wish to be served by Polish clerks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
