<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-07">Dec. 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Strike Is Growing</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1730</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1730.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-07">Dec. 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE STRIKE IS GROWING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The strike yesterday did not have as many sympathizers as was claimed. According to stockyard officials, many workers returned to the employment offices and asked to be taken back. It is apparent that the announcement about the loss of work alarmed many people. This is a marked indication that the union, and the strike in general is weakening, despite the fact that the union leaders are demanding that the workers support their cause.</p>
   <p>As a result of the strike, the price of pork has increased from four to five cents per pound in the local markets. This is an indication that the strike curtailed production to some extent in the plants of the "Big Five."</p>
   <p>Cornelius Hayes, one of the leaders of the strike, revealed yesterday <pb facs="5423968_2_1731.jpg" n="2"/>that over twelve thousand strikers will take part today. They will be supported by a better organized picket line. Over ninety per cent of the workers are taking part in the strike outside of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The gravity of the strike grew to such proportions in St. Paul that it was necessary to call out the State militia. The police are guarding the packing houses in St. Joseph. All the slaughter houses were closed in Oklahoma City. Mr. Hayes declared that there would be no decided change in the number of strikers this week. In the meantime, the inexperienced workers will prove to be unproductive. As a result, the meat will begin to spoil and prices will reach unprecedented heights. "Naturally the public will pay for all this." (This statement appeared in bold type). It is not surprising that the workers, receiving eighteen dollars per week at the present time, revert to desperate measures.</p>
   <p>Several meetings were held by the strikers when reports from other cities <pb facs="5423968_2_1732.jpg" n="3"/>were read. The plan for strengthening the picket lines was approved.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, packing house officials, after estimating the number of strikers at eleven hundred, expressed hopes that the strike will end shortly.</p>
   <p>A dispatch from St. Paul reveals that the state police had to be called when the strikers attacked a train of strikebreakers. The workers in Denver are out on strike one hundred per cent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
