<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-01">Dec. 1, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Forty Hours Devotion</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0746</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0746.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-01">Dec. 1, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">FORTY HOURS DEVOTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Forty Hours Devotion services were held at the Immaculate Heart of Mary's Church November 27, 28, and 29. At no time was the church empty. From early morning to late evening both young and old kept coming in.</p>
   <p>The balustrade before the altars was filled with devout people who offered their prayers before the throne of God. After a short prayer, they returned to the pews for the ceremonials.</p>
   <p>A procession of the Blessed Sacrament officially started the opening of the Forty Hours Devotion ceremony. Rev. Raymond Appelt, pastor, officiated during the procession. He was assisted by Fr. S. Derwinski, who served <pb facs="5423968_2_0747.jpg" n="2"/>as deacon, and Rev. S. Szwakowski, C. S. V., who was the sub-beacon.</p>
   <p>The latter priest celebrated with High Mass. The Benedictus was officiated by Rev. B. Nowakowski. The deacon was Fr. Francis Rusch and the sub deacon was Fr. John Kendziora.</p>
   <p>All the sermons were given by Fr. Stephan Dzialdowski, O.F.M., from Pulaski, Wisconsin. Many local and visiting priests assisted in the three day services.</p>
   <p>The alter was decorated with fresh flowers and many deceorative candlesticks. The decoration were done by the nuns of the parish school. The church choir, under the direction of Stanislaus Mrozinski, local organist, sang many beautiful religious hymns. At regular intervals, groups of children of would come to the church to pray and sing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
