<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1902-03-12">Mar. 12, 1902</date>, Vol. VI, No. 11.
<title level="a">"On Marriage"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0614</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0614.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1902-03-12">Mar. 12, 1902</date>, Vol. VI, No. 11.
<title level="a">"ON MARRIAGE"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great number of suicides, murders and divorces noted especially by American Newspapers, indicate that either our legislation is worthless, or what seems most probable, the principles of bringing up and educating our generation does not answer the purpose. Something is wrong for facts prove that the number of victims and number of those, who, with their own hands, prematurely cut their span of life, is increasing daily, especially among the young. The person and revolver play the most important part. English, German and even Polish papers devote whole columns every day about murders, suicides, divorces, etc. To one who is not acquainted with the conditions, our newspapers appear as criminal records; A suitor shot a young lady because she did not return his love; or went to a ball with some one else. Another young lady poisoned herself because mother opposed her marriage with "Frank" or "Frank" was caught flirting with another girl. Young couples married sometimes only two or three months get their divorces for a very trifling reason. Let Hubby stay a little longer after the meeting or if he fails to buy her a hat or dress she likes, <pb facs="5423968_2_0615.jpg" n="2"/>she runs directly to court for a divorce.</p>
   <p>If a hard working husband, after a hard days work, is unwilling to beat the carpets, clean the stove, turn the washingmachine, wash the dishes, take care of the baby until midnight, immediately the loving spouse has a cause for a divorce, on the grounds of mistreatment. The other side is not any better. A seventeen or eighteen year old youngster (stripling) noticing only a hem of "Josies" white underskirt, after exchanging a few words with her on Saturday night and Sunday afternoon, gets married in a few weeks. But after the wedding an amorous husbands find out that his beautiful and cooing "Josephine" does not even know how to make coffee. He realizes, too late, that his wife beside the white hem of her underskirt has nothing else that is white. That she has no ability to mend clothes, sew on her husbands buttons or wash his soiled shirts. All she knows about house management is that there should be a stove in the kitchen, sofa and chairs in the parlor and bed in the bed room.</p>
   <p>Suddenly the eyes of the married couple are opened. She envies "Eve", that she <pb facs="5423968_2_0616.jpg" n="3"/>did not have to cook, scrub, mend and wash, and he envies Adam for not having trouble with buttons, carrying coal to the 3rd floor or looking for a new dress or gloves.</p>
   <p>After a week or so, perhaps a few months later they start to aggravate each other. They disfigure their faces with pots and plates, and then divorce follows. Frank looks for another and so does Josie. This appears really funny but it is the truth, and you don't have to look very far in order to verify it.</p>
   <p>It cannot be denied that marriages in America are contracted like by telephone. Sometimes the parents do not even suspect that their daughter gave her heart to the chose one, and who usually does not appear until the banns are to be announced. Such marriages usually have a sad ending. We have to counteract this evil and the best remedy is to keep the young lady home. She sould spend her time home studying domestic art, cooking, sewing for herself and family, so when she get married she will know how to manage the <pb facs="5423968_2_0617.jpg" n="4"/>household. Unfortunately our parents care little for this. The sigh of a beautiful daughter, doll like, blinds them, fills them with joy. In order not to soil her daughters nice silk dress, mother does all the work and the nice daughter likes it. Later on this mother will complain that her son-in-law threw her daughter out, not realizing that her daughter outside of dressing up, powdering and rolling her black eyes does not know anything about keeping house, necessary for future life. Hence frequent divorces and scandals in marriages for which mothers are to blame. Blinded by their daughters they forget to bring them up properly. Mothers! remember that a beautiful dress or a hat shall not bring your daughter happiness, but cleanliness, economy and proper knowledge of domestic art, and what is more important, religious training. A young lade seeking only adornment and pleasure, who does not care for home and church, and indifferent in the matters of faith, will not, and cannot be a good wife, because the sacrament of matrimony is not sacred to her. She considers nuptial bonds as some kind of a sport, and for that reason it is not hard for her to break with the first or second man and unite with a third or fourth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
