<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Związkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-02-19">Feb. 19, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Two Sides of the Medal</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0494</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0494.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1908-02-19">Feb. 19, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">TWO SIDES OF THE MEDAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fight conducted in the United States by temperance societies against the selling of liquor has attracted the attention of the whole public, which suddenly divided itself into two opposing camps, each one of which is trying to prove its point by statistical records. Mass meetings are conducted throughout the country, and speakers of each camp are trying in a jocular manner to convince the public that whiskey is either the cause of all misfortunes, with which humanity is afflicted or that it is an absolute necessity; and that the country depends upon the revenue collected from its sales. So that we can present this unique fight against alcoholism without partiality, we will confine ourselves to plain figures, obtained for the benefit of arguments of either side.</p>
   <p>The enemies of alcoholic drinks maintain that the money spent for liquor, in the United States, every year, could be used for the moral and material benefit of the public. Mr.A. B. Farwell, leader of the Temperance League disclosed the fact that the people of Chicago spent about $52,000,000.- or a million dollars a week- for liquor. For this great sum of money, a large supply of food, clothing, fuel, furniture and other necessities of life could be purchased. The men who produce these commodities would earn about $1,000,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0495.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The working class would have about $15,000,000 more for which they could live in better homes which have modern conveniences. There would also be an additional $15,000,000, a year with which to increase the police force. The Fire Department too, could receive $3,125,000 a year more, as could the Health Department, about $4,000,000. There would still be a surplus of over $4,000,000, which could be used for building new schools, for parks, and for street repairs. This condition exists not only in Chicago, but proportionately, in other centers of the American Union. The foregoing figures and argumentations are very convincing, and can very easily, deceive the average citizen who sees only one side of the medal.</p>
   <p>Let us turn to the other side of the medal, that is, to the farmers, brewers, distillers, saloonkeepers, barrel makers, icemen, bottle men and others, who supply such articles as are used in connection with the liquor business; and who also presents very interesting figures; perhaps not in statistical order but very convincing and contradictory. We, also wish to call your attention to the annual revenue of a billion and a half dollars, which the government receives from the sale of liquor; which would otherwise be added to our taxes, a burden, which would affect even the supporters of temperance; and the farmers, who now raise large crops of potatoes, rye, barley etc. and receive large sums of money for these products would be without employment which would result in further loss. Besides this, the closing of saloons would deprive millions of men of their means of employment.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0496.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The bigots are absolutely wrong in maintaining that the money now spent for liquor would be used only for a good purpose. Hard-working people will always seek enjoyment; therefore, the money now spent for liquor, would then be spent gambling, for tobacco and other luxuries. We do not deny that drunkenness is very repulsive, and should be discouraged; but on the other hard forbidding a glass of been or whiskey, is the absurdity of narrow minded hypocrites, posing as saints. We know very well that gluttony is also detrimental to health; there are people, however who are not drunkards, but who, nevertheless,maintain a gluttony that has reached a pinnacle of perfection. A moderate person will not abuse himself, either by drinking or eating too much. There is no reason why a handful of bigots should dictate to the millions of people telling them what to eat or drink; thereby robbing them of their personal liberty. This should be resented by all of us.</p>
   <p>Let us cure the habit of drunkenness with educational lectures that point out the great harm resulting from the excessive use of alcoholic drinks; but let us not try to prohibit the use of drink or food by law, which, besides having the apparition of a farce, causes dissention among the people. In conclusion, to deprive a few million people of employment, just because a few Puritans desire to do so - would certainly be an unforgivable blunder. Here is the best advice: "Let every one mind his own business and not peep into his neighbors pot." Indeed, the fight of Puritans against alcoholism in the United States, is very characteristic, even interesting, but it is difficult to prophesy its outcome.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
