<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 25,
<date when="1914-06-24">June 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Men and Women Boarders</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XVIII, No. 25,
<date when="1914-06-24">June 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">MEN AND WOMEN BOARDERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The thing is happening in any of the Polish colonies, on a Sunday.</p>
   <p>In a certain home the housekeeper keeps in quarters several young men and young ladies. But as it happens in most cases, the housekeeper allows the boarders all kinds of extravagances, and even carefully watches that under the bed of each boarder there is a gallon of whiskey and a keg of beer. If perhaps the boarder should not have these articles it would not be merry in her home.</p>
   <p>On a certain Saturday, when the boarders returned home in the evening, they immediately drew out boxes of beverages from underneath the bed and began to drink unto insensibility. Oh! they drank and drank, played cards and sang in hoarse voices.</p>
   <p>The more decent neighbors, Poles, wondered at the drunken orgies of their neighbors. The Americans on the other hand cursed the "Polanders" because they would not let them sleep at night. In the quarters of this housekeeper were staying also several decent girls who during these drinking <pb facs="5423968_2_0451.jpg" n="2"/>bouts, locked themselves in their rooms and only heard through the walls how the drunkards emitted inhuman tones. It is known that the excessive use of fiery beverages awakens also the immoral and shameless instincts. So then, when the drunks were well "soused" they began to try to break their way into the girls' rooms. One of them with his "bear like" shoulders leaned up against the door and began to break it in. The weak American doors crashed and the drunk broke into the room. But the poor hapless fellow terribly over-reckoned himself. The resolute girl was already waiting for the drunk with a dull instrument and began to pound him over his hard "dome," and when this did not bring results, because he had a skull as if of stone, she began to scratch him with her finger nails, so the drunk was "doused" with blood and his eyes were in great danger. Willy-nilly the poor body had to ignominiously step aside from the resolute girl, who in addition threatened to kill him like a dog.</p>
   <p>When the drunk got out of the room of the girl, he did not look at all like a gallant bold knight, fighting in defense of the fatherland. His <pb facs="5423968_2_0452.jpg" n="3"/>red face indicated that he got sweated up alongside the whiskey glass; the scratched nose indicated that some nocturnal adventure befell him. The next day the girl began to abuse the housekeeper, because she keeps in her home such loathsome sots and moved away from the house.</p>
   <p>Well, and what happened after that?</p>
   <p>And well! The young man came to next day to see the young lady, kindly apologized to her, that upon the instigation of his drunken colleagues he arranged the attack on her and that from this time on he will reform.</p>
   <p>In such a way do our pious and respectable girls protect their maiden honor and such a lesson they give those godless ones. Oh! If there were only more of such kind!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
