<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 8
<date when="1922-01-11">Jan. 11, 1922</date>,
<title level="a">Murderous Propaganda</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0562</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0562.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zjednoczenia</title>, Vol. XXVI, No. 8
<date when="1922-01-11">Jan. 11, 1922</date>,
<title level="a">MURDEROUS PROPAGANDA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are people with pretentions to high learning and wisdom, having even, in certain directions, a high enough education, who, in spite of all, have to be reckoned with as fools, if one may be a fool who willingly causes an injury or harm unto himself.</p>
   <p>There are people who lack orientation to such a degree in that which in bad or good for them, that they adgere thoughtlessly to any sort of suicidal theory set from in the Christian world by the confessors of the Mosaic religion and become its ardent propagators.</p>
   <p>To such idiotic propaganda being spread at present among Christians, chiefly in American, belong to the so-called "birth-control" for would-be economic reasons.</p>
   <p>This watch word was thrown to the Christian world by the founders of modern socialism, promising to fools a paradise on earth with the help of doing away with private property, with the help of preparing a "free love" without <pb facs="5423968_2_0563.jpg" n="2"/>any obligation - a boundless freedom.</p>
   <p>Only fools allow themselves to be taken by this kind of talk, those not knowing how to distinguish laws of nature and not understanding the fundamentals of life and human happiness, generally the fundamentals of our entire Christian civilization.</p>
   <p>We have written many times about Socialism. Our attentive readers already understand perfectly the entire idiotism concluded in the Socialistic doctrine, relative to the nature of the state. Up to this time we have not written extensively about the "free-love" proposed by the Socialists, and about proposed "birth control," even by some of our non-Socialistic professors of universities, for would-be economic reasons. The Catholic church condemns this doctrine as incompatible with the principles of faith.</p>
   <p>We will try to enlighten it briefly from a purely rational and self-preserving viewpoint. There is not one human being with a sound mind that would not admit from a patriotic viewpoint, purely nationalistic, that the <pb facs="5423968_2_0564.jpg" n="3"/>artificial limitation of births is national suicide. Everyone knows that the greater the population of a nation, the stronger, the easier it is to uphold its culture and its political independence. It is a thing so clear that there is no need of having a dispute over it. So then, the propagaters of "birth control" are discretionally silent about this question and are raising only the economic question and saying that the uncontrolled number of births is bringing poverty not only upon the families individually, but also upon the entire country. Under the pretext, it would seem that they have a reason, when you take into consideration the fate of this or that numerically large and poor family.</p>
   <p>We are saying "under this pretext" because in reality the thing happens to be altogether different when we take into consideration the good of the entire country.</p>
   <p>Above all, the healthiest individuals, spiritually as well as physically, are found particularly where the number of births is not controlled. This happens because they are conceived in natural manner from physically and spiritually healthy parents. Only the most morally and naturally conducted <pb facs="5423968_2_0565.jpg" n="4"/>marriages can bear many children. A marriage, limiting by an artificial method the number of births can never bring into the world healthy and strong children because the artificial act of prevention ruins the health of both individuals, and above all the woman's.</p>
   <p>You cannot point out to us one physically and spiritually healthy married woman who has conformed to artificial sterility. Such a married woman is almost always ill and usually comes to an untimely death. Generally, the women who live the longest and are happiest are those who have had a natural number of children.</p>
   <p>It is also a downright lie that an artificially lessened number of children, or sterility, gives a woman satisfaction in life. Such beings are truly the most unfortunate, particularly when they come to realize that they are growing older.</p>
   <p>If it concerns the economy, the nourishing and the proper rearing of the children of poor parents, that is remedied very essily by every city, every smallest community, and lastly the state. A lie and nonsense is also the claim <pb facs="5423968_2_0566.jpg" n="5"/>that a greater number of people brings about a greater poverty, because every normal and industrious person can himself produce enough livelihood, that would be sufficient for six people.</p>
   <p>Further, the one who cultivates "birth controls" is the one who, to say briefly, performs suicide and corner number upon his posterity and nation.</p>
   <p>If the Jews propagate among Christians the principle of "birth control," then one must ask them why is it that they do not adapt themselvess to it, but call every newly born child a treasure and blessing of Jehovah.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
