<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1892-02-17">Feb. 17, 1892</date><title level="a">The Affair of Polish Churches in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0811</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0811.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Zgoda</title>,
<date when="1892-02-17">Feb. 17, 1892</date><title level="a">THE AFFAIR OF POLISH CHURCHES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>1. The priest receives a suitable lodging and board for his services, with a pension of $800 yearly, and in case the parish grows bigger, the pastor endeavors to procure a priest or priests to aid him, Every one of these priests also receives a pension and lodging.</p>
   <p>2. The parish financial committee must inform the tutelar of various changes made and consult with the pastor about its needs.</p>
   <p>3. The priests, organist, teacher or teachers and the church servants, receive also a pension from the treasury of the parish, consisting of funds received in the parish.</p>
   <p>4. All of the money collected in the church and parish for the use of the pews and schools belongs to the treasury of the parish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0812.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>5. The parish treasury should be in care of the cashier of the parish, but under the guidance of its committee and pastor. The cashier must receive and safely retain in his possession the money.</p>
   <p>6. The secretary of the parish should have a book and the pastor another; these books should show the income and the expense of the parish. The financial statement in the parish should be revealed at least tqice a year, that being the duty of the committee and the pastor.</p>
   <p>7. The priest who directs his parish and his church cannot depend on or be concerned with any other parishes or priests but his own.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
