<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-08-17">Aug. 17, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">St. Stanislaus Kostka College</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0215</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0215.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1894-08-17">Aug. 17, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">ST. STANISLAUS KOSTKA COLLEGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the past few years, when Polish immigration reached large proportions, and the number of Poles in Chicago passed the one hundred thousand mark, we have felt a great need for a Polish high school.</p>
   <p>Toward this end, the Resurrection Fathers decided to establish a Polish high school which would supply our youth with knowledge necessary for holding small public offices and clerical positions. Lack of material support on the part of the Poles hindered the development of the school and did not promise much hope for the future. After three years of endeavor, the Resurrection Fathers enlarged the institution to such extend that its continued existence is now assured. The number of students has increased considerably, and the conscientious work of the teachers, together with the perseverance of the rector, has raised the standard of this school to the level of regular high schools, and has gained the confidence of the public.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0216.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>People of good will and parents who are interested in the welfare of their children have come to the conclusion that education is the only guarantee of our future.</p>
   <p>Lack of proper education is responsible for the fact that the Poles hold so few public offices in proportion to their number. They get rid of us by throwing us some crumbs, and even these crumbs are snatched from us as soon as opportunity presents itself--snatched away on all kinds of pretexts. If we had a suitable number of capable and educated young men, they surely would not have difficulty in finding profitable employment. Quite often there is an opportunity to secure a fairly good position, here and there, but lack of qualifications frustrates all endeavors, even on the part of a third party.</p>
   <p>Could any one conceive a better thought than that of helping our young men <pb facs="5423968_2_0217.jpg" n="3"/>(to prepare themselves for public office) by building a high school for them in a locality inhabited by more than one hundred thousand Poles? Every thinking person must admit that this school may bring us incalculable benefits. But let us look at its accomplishments without prejudice, let us appreciate that which we can see and not that which we hear from those who are prejudiced against it--then we will surely see it in a different light, and not as presented by those who, for personal reasons, desire its fall.</p>
   <p>Our college is supervised by the Resurrection Fathers, and its purpose is to prepare the Polish Roman Catholic youth for priesthood and to teach regular college courses.</p>
   <p>Two languages, English and Polish,are used in this school; English and Polish literature and history are taught by competent professors who have university degrees.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0218.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As there is no thorough education without religious training, the management scrupulously observes that the young men entrusted to their care receive such training.</p>
   <p>The students of this college are obliged to attend a holy mass daily and to receive holy sacraments at times prescribed by the rector.</p>
   <p>As the management of the college is interested in physical development of our youth, the students are obliged to take gymnastic exercises regularly.</p>
   <p>Strict obedience is demanded from the students, not only to professors but also to elders and parents. Stubborn and disobedient students are expelled from the institution. Students must be well mannered and properly dressed. Disregard of this rule is met with punishment.</p>
   <p>The curriculum of the college consists of three courses:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0219.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>classical, scientific, and commercial. (When better times come, a fourth course, philosophical, will be added.)</p>
   <p>The classical course prepares pupils for theology, law, and medicine. It embraces Latin, Greek, Polish, German, English and French languages, hysiology, chemistry, physics, and mathematics. In this course, more than half of the time is devoted to English and Polish history and literature.</p>
   <p>The science course prepares students for engineering, surveying, architecture, and pharmacy, and embraces the languages mentioned in classical course.</p>
   <p>The commercial course prepares students for business, and embraces, besides the studies in the science course, bookkeeping, higher mathematics, commercial law, legal instruments, lettering, and penmanship.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0220.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The foregoing list of subjects proves that the standard of our college is not lower than that of regular American colleges, but that it stands higher in many respects.</p>
   <p>Religion, Polish language, and the history of our nation are taught in our college; many other colleges do not teach these subjects. Besides, our school has a special teacher of drawing, painting, singing, and music.</p>
   <p>Singing, drawing, and painting lessons are free, but there is a charge for instrumental music lessons.</p>
   <p>The tuition is only two dollars a month, a fee which gives even moderately situated parents an opportunity to educate their children at low cost, and thus insure their future.</p>
   <p>We wish to mention that, by special arrangement between the management <pb facs="5423968_2_0221.jpg" n="7"/>the school and certain big firms, graduates of St. Stanislaus College will be offered a position suitable to their training.</p>
   <p>The faculty consists of the following persons:</p>
   <p>Reverend John Piechowski, rector;</p>
   <p>Reverend John Gieburowski,</p>
   <p>Reverend Seraphim Cosimi,</p>
   <p>B. McEvoy,</p>
   <p>Ignatius Kowalski,</p>
   <p>P. A. Schaedler.</p>
   <p>For further information, please apply to Reverend John Piechowski, C. R., rector of the college.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
