<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IX, No. 6,
<date when="1908-02-08">February 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">American Girls and Polish Girls</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0598</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0598.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IX, No. 6,
<date when="1908-02-08">February 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN GIRLS AND POLISH GIRLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>American maidens present themselves as intelligent and business-like; making a business out of the sensation of love. When an American girl has a fiance she carries on a flirtation with others, to be assured that she can catch a husband if the present bethrothed one does not keep his promise to marry her.</p>
   <p>Sometimes she remains engaged for a long time, not wanting to marry, so she can partake of freedom and other similar things, most likely the desire for entertainments, dances, theaters, and finally - God knows what - perhaps coquetry and idle talk. When she marries, these pleasures become curtailed and then she is a model woman, caring for the home and guarding the cleanliness of her family hearth.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile the European girls, I am here considering the Polish girls, as maidens, do not know how to flirt as a business, that is, to catch their man. They are bashful, modest, they lower their lovely eyes even if they <pb facs="5423968_2_0599.jpg" n="2"/>have the little "devil" behind their backs, because when they get married they are free and do not bind themselves, and take part in social entertainments, etc.</p>
   <p>Let us see who is right. Whether the maiden accustomed to flirtation, who possesses that qyality, or defect - take it as you prefer - which is a part of her nature can be reformed after she is married. Most likely not! (The author thinks the flirtation lasts). Cleanliness in the home amid such a marriage, what an irony! That is why later we see among American marriages so many divorces. That is the best answer to the adherents of the American system.</p>
   <p>Or, the Polish girl who is modest, industrious, knows how to manage a house-hold, cook, wash clothes, render life more agreeable for the husband so that his life and his stay at home are to him lovlier and more pleasant than a saloon or club; she amuses herself later and is free, and the husband is assured of her virtue because she has been virtuous from a child. He looks <pb facs="5423968_2_0600.jpg" n="3"/>at her with pleased eyes, not like the American man who has to watch his wife and not allow her to dance with another man or let him entertain her with his ingenuity (witty sayings). The fact that the Polish girl is free after marriage justly indicates the customs and virtues of Polish women, which accounts for so few divorces among the Poles.</p>
   <p>Love is not a ward and you cannot do business with it; and where they make a business of love the nations disappear. Modesty, home virtues, health and respect - those are what bring good fortune to families so flirtations and making a business of love not only make families unfortunate but brings about the fall of the nation.</p>
   <p>Polish girls! Go the old way, the way of your mothers, the way of modesty, bashfulness, industry, guardianship of the home, nourishing within the heart that flame of love on the hearth of the home, and what is sacred to the Pole-the love of God and Poland, and you will be successful.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
