<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-20">Oct. 20, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The High Cost of Meat</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1447</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1447.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1910-10-20">Oct. 20, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE HIGH COST OF MEAT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The retail meat packers, in their report given to officials, enumerate the following reasons for the high cost of meat: high tariff; exorbitant expenses of meat packers for state and federal inspectors; and lack of manual labor on farms and the high price of corn necessary to feed the cattle and hogs.</p>
   <p>In order to have lower prices on meat, the meat packers offer a suggestion that the tax on cattle and hogs be abolished. Secondly, they propose that pastures be maintained upon a co-operative system. Thirdly, they urge the enactment of a law whereby the killing of cattle, sheep, and hogs during the spring season would be unlawful. Finally, they want workers directed from the cities to the farms, that is, start a "back to the land" movement.</p>
   <p>The meat packers, however, make no mention of the trusts, which withhold enormous supplies of meat in cold storage for several months until prices rise.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1448.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They act as if they knew nothing of the trusts' existence and the fact that it is such trusts that cause the high cost of living. It is possible that the proposals of the meat packers may increase the supply of cattle and hogs in this country, but they would not prevent the meat trusts from buying them out and packing the meat in storage houses, where it would remain until higher prices could be asked.</p>
   <p>After all, there is no shortage of cattle or hogs even today. Meat in great quantities is being exported to other countries, where it is sold at a lower price than here in America. Meat sold on the markets of London or Liverpool, in England, is far lower in price than in Chicago, San Francisco, Buffalo, or New York. The meat barons of America rob their fellow citizens of their hard-earned money in a more shameless manner than those of foreign nations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
