<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. IV No.5.
<date when="1900-01-31">Jan. 31, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Editorial I. "About the School Children Taking Part in School Theatricals from the Moral and Pedagogical Viewpoint."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>NAROD POLSKI</title>, Vol. IV No.5.
<date when="1900-01-31">Jan. 31, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">EDITORIAL I. "ABOUT THE SCHOOL CHILDREN TAKING PART IN SCHOOL THEATRICALS FROM THE MORAL AND PEDAGOGICAL VIEWPOINT."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In response to a letter written by Rev. P.M.Abbelen of Milwaukee, Wis. protesting against stage productions given in parochial schools and played by children under the direction of their teachers. (Sisters-Nuns) The letter was prompted by tragedy in Quincy, Illinois, where children were badly burned when the stage caught fire and one nun had to have both hands amputated as the result of burning.</p>
   <p>Whoever knows well and understands the purpose of Polish schools in America must admit that a terrible evil has crept into these schools, affecting not only the bodies but even the morals of the children. The children are used for a magnet to draw the public to these stage productions contrary to the laws of pedagogy. The stage productions have nothing in their favor because they don't benefit anybody, neither materially nor morally and pedagogically they are only a detriment to children and impose hardships on their teachers making it difficult to maintain the necessary discipline in schools.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0134.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Although the plays are given for the benefit of the school or the church, the profits derived from them in comparison with the expenses and hardships connected with it are insignificant. If every child was given the amount that its mother spent for buying the dresses, suits, flowers, decorations, etc. connected with their taking part in the play, the clear profit would remain very small.</p>
   <p>The sacrifices made by the parents swallow up sometimes whole two weeks pay of the father in order to see thir son or daughter "blowing the horn or taking a part as some king or princess." As the result the rest of the family must suffer privations. Even the priests of poor parishes would not care for the donations for their schools or church when the sacrifices are comparatively so great. But from the moral point of view the whole matter looks even worse than from the material. For instead of teaching children meekness their taking part in theatricals causes some of them to be vain and conceited and others jealous. Those not chosen for any part in the play feel humiliated, dislike their teachers and hate their fellow students. One may often hear the actors bragging among themselves on what a fine <pb facs="5423968_2_0135.jpg" n="3"/>"role" they had to play, and what a huge success they were on the stage evoking great applause from the audience. Very often those that were not chosen for the play were reminded by their fellow pupils that they were not called because they were either too stupid or that their parents were too poor and uninfluential.</p>
   <p>And how detrimental to the moral development of the children is the selling of the tickets for the play from door to door. It is a sort of beggary which in many cases was a cause of complete moral ruin of the child. There are cases of children peddling the tickets who kept the money for themselves and used it for improper purposes. Although these are exceptions one must always bear in mind the influence of bad example set by the depraved and corrupted children on the morally healthy children. The peddling of the tickets from door to door exposes the children to what "their innocent ears should never hear and their eyes should never see." It is better not to mention how many times the children are forced to listen to obscene language in regard to their "Nuns, teachers or priests."</p>
   <p>The children suffer these humilations with great patience in order either to gain favor with "sisters" or earn a free admission ticket. Fear of their superiors in schools also prods the children in their efforts to sell their alloted number <pb facs="5423968_2_0136.jpg" n="4"/>of tickets whose price is often too high causing a great deal of hardship to parents of the children whose attendance at the school theatre is expected. One cannot accuse the "sisters" of exerting pressure but one must admit the existence of moral compulsion.</p>
   <p>After mature consideration one wonders if from pedagogical and logical point of view is there any gain in teaching the children to "hop and skip" on the stage in front of the public. The science of pedagogy is against it &amp;,as far as logic is concerned one sees no sense in dressing "a kid" up in royal or princely robes or as some other dignitary or diplomat and play the role of which he cannot have even the slightest idea. One may even witness little girls bedecked as patriarchs, arch-priests or prophets singing the prophecies about the coming of the Saviour.</p>
   <p>Remembering the amount of work and patient labor on the part of "sisters" coaching the children in their respective parts one is sorry to admit that aesthetically the plays are not successes, but rather failures. And though occasionally the plays are not deprived of some charm and beauty, it is a pity that one cannot <pb facs="5423968_2_0137.jpg" n="5"/>refrain from shouting - "it is a loss of time and effort!</p>
   <p>Talking about logic one must mention the widely spread among the Poles Christmas plays. It is absolutely against all logic to make the children take part in the play as Jesus Christ or Holy Mary, or some other saint. After the play the children are apt to brag about their roles and belittle roles of children who played a part of some minor saint or even the murderer Herod. One must look upon it as a sort of profanity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
