<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XII, No. 27,
<date when="1917-07-05">July 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Advise to Mothers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0650</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0650.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XII, No. 27,
<date when="1917-07-05">July 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ADVISE TO MOTHERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Right now we have a very dangerous time for the young girls, and we feel that it is our duty to give a few words of good advice to those mothers who have grown up daughters. Every good mother should see that her daughter receives a good bringing up and education because our future depends on a good bringing up of our daughters. We shall not discuss here the ways of bringing up, because our priests preach that from the pulpits many times, but we like to mention something which appears very innocent and harmless, and yet the effect is very harmful to marriageable girls.</p>
   <p>This article is a contribution from a certain mother. She writes, "My daughter Josie who has just finished her 18th year told me that one night while coming home late from the theatre all alone, she met, on the corner of a certain street, a large automobile with a few jolly young men. The automobile stopped by the curb and one of the young men invited my Josie for a ride. The girl did not know any of the young men, but when he told her that he would take her home, she <pb facs="5423968_2_0651.jpg" n="2"/>accepted the ride. The automobile started and in a few minutes she found herself outside of the city limits. This frightened her and she told them to take her back to the city, otherwise she would call for help or jump out. At first the young men started to laught at her, but later when she started to cry they turned back and brought her home. Josephine's mother states that she will never allow her to go out alone at night because she might meet with a misfortune.</p>
   <p>Yet how many girls take automobile rides outside of the city with strange men, and how much misfortune is there on account of that. Therefore, dear mothers think of this and do not allow your daughters to keep company with strangers. That your daughter avoid those automobile rides, because on account of these "joy rides" there is much misfortune. Let not your daughters become "flyers." Let them take care of the house and stay home nights. The girls who spend their free time outside on the streets generally do not get good husbands. Get them used to housework, to accuracy, and to read good literature, and then you will be sure that you have fulfilled your duty towards your daughters, who will bless you in the future, but now the times are very dangerous, and mothers should watch their daughter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
