<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-06-13">June 13, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Poles in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1892-06-13">June 13, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">POLES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Annual examinations were held on Friday and Saturday of last week in the school conducted by the Venerable Sisters of Nazareth at 120 West Division Street. Public exercises will be conducted at the end of this month.</p>
   <p>The successful results of the examinations manifested the excellent teaching methods of the Venerable Sisters who have graduated in Austria and proved that their toil and wholehearted sacrifices are so necessary in an educational position. The students answered rather rapidly and accurately to the comparatively difficult questions on religion, arithmetic, Polish language--reading, grammar, partition, and orthography (writing). Equally successful were the answers in geography in the Polish and English languages, from Polish history, from arithmetic in the English language, from the history and geography of the United States, from the history of English literature, which is a great merit to the lay teacher born in Chicago. The students of the highest grades have shown great rapidity in practical arithmetic, in geometrical and physical calculations, as well as in natural history and Polish literature. In publicly <pb facs="5423968_2_0291.jpg" n="2"/>thanking the Venerable Sisters for their efforts, undertaken so successfully for our youth, that embryo of our national future in America, we can readily recommend this school to the parents interested in good breeding and a thorough education. This priceless wealth, is what they can give their children.</p>
   <p>The Venerable Sisters complain that they cannot complete the education of their students because the parents remove them too soon to enroll them into the English schools. For this reason they are ready, upon request of the parents, to create a higher class in their school with an English lecture, and at the same time, not neglecting the Polish language and Polish history.</p>
   <p>We here add that, due to the construction of our school, the Venerable Sisters have moved to their own home, at 258 West Division, and that the school term will be continued until the end of the academic year in the former press building of Zgoda, at 112 West Division Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
