<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-13">Dec. 13, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Stockyards' Strike Situation Unchanged</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1688</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1688.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1921-12-13">Dec. 13, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE STOCKYARDS' STRIKE SITUATION UNCHANGED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The present situation of the strike in the Stockyards has remained unchanged. Chief of Police Fitzmorris informed Captain Roosevelt of the Stockyards Station that a large part of the police on duty in the strike area will be called back. Packing house employers have said that the strike prevalent throughout the country has been a mistake, while union leaders have announced that 6,000 workers in New York City have joined their ranks in sympathy. The Court for Industrial Relations, in Kansas City, will issue a plan of factory representation, which has been adopted since the expiration of Judge Alschuler's term as arbitrator. The factory representation plan, which confirmed the ten per cent reduction in pay, is to affect both factory workers and officials as well. The unions are opposed to this plan, as well as the wage reduction, and are demanding Judge Alschuler as arbitrator. The employers do not wish to concede to these demands.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1689.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On the other hand, the union has turned to other unions for help in the strike. It has been rumored that it is true that the machinists and firemen have joined the strikers.</p>
   <p>A negro was lynched in Fort Worth for shooting two strikers who have been participating in the demonstration. At the time of the shooting the Negro was hurt and taken to a hospital. The enraged strikers stormed the hospital doors, overcame the resisting guards, and dragged the wounded Negro out into the street. Twenty minutes later, the body was found riddled with bullets suspended from a tree.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
