<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-23">Jan. 23, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A Polish Teachers' Seminary in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0186</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0186.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1896-01-23">Jan. 23, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">A POLISH TEACHERS' SEMINARY IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A matter of necessity and importance for the Poles in America, perhaps an absolute necessity, is the project of organizing a Polish teachers' seminary in America. Everybody must agree that this is a necessary undertaking.</p>
   <p>The schools depend on sincere and understanding teachers who know the conditions surrounding our people, and, alas, we lack such teachers. Only a Polish-American teachers' seminary can prepare a sufficient number of teachers who are thoroughly qualified for such work.</p>
   <p>We have spoken and written about such a seminary time and again. The project was discussed at assemblies of priests, and at the conventions of organizations (including the convention of the Polish Roman Catholic Union at South Bend) and various proposals were submitted, but no definite results were obtained.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0187.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From present indications, this problem is on the way to a solution, judging by an article in the last issue of Wiarai Ojczyzna (Faith and Fatherland). This article, which was included in the report of the last meeting of the central administration of the Polish Roman Catholic Union, reported as follows:</p>
   <p>".....There followed a discussion, as to how the administration should proceed to fulfill the duty imposed upon it by the last convention; namely, to undertake to organize and open a Polish seminary for teachers.</p>
   <p>"The administration has no funds with which to build such a school, to employ and pay teachers or for the upkeep of such a seminary. There can, therefore, be no good reason for a discussion of such a project at the present time.</p>
   <p>"Still, the administration ought to do something about it, inasmuch as the convention ordered the administration to take this matter up, and a report will have to be submitted of its actions at the next convention. Moreover, <pb facs="5423968_2_0188.jpg" n="3"/>the Catholic Congress will, no doubt, become interested in this matter, and mention will then be made of the fact that the administration of the Polish Roman Catholic Union was ordered to see what it could do in this matter by its last convention, and the Congress will demand some information, as to what has been done about it.</p>
   <p>"The matter was therefore considered very seriously. Finally Mr. Boleslaus Klarkowski made a proposal requiring deep consideration and his proposal at once gained the support of all present.</p>
   <p>"Since this proposal has just been submitted, and must be elaborated by the president of the Polish Union in collaboration with Mr. Klarkowski, we will not discuss it further until it has reached some definite form."</p>
   <p>It is evident that the administration of the Polish Union intends energetically to carry out the proposed plan to organize a Polish teachers' seminary in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0189.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We are assured that the project submitted by Mr. Klarkowski is very practical and economical, and will probably be easy to put into execution.</p>
   <p>We are glad that something is finally being done about this matter, and await further particulars with impatience. In any event we wish the Polish Roman Catholic Union the earliest and most successful conclusion to its most honorable efforts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
