<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. 16, No. 157,
<date when="1905-07-07">July 7, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting to Organize a "Society to Aid Schooling."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0110</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0110.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. 16, No. 157,
<date when="1905-07-07">July 7, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING TO ORGANIZE A "SOCIETY TO AID SCHOOLING."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The administration of the Polish Roman-Catholic Federation held a meeting at St. Adalbert's Hall yesterday, where a number of Polish priests and a group of laymen, invited by mail, were present. Archbishop Symon honored this meeting by his presence.</p>
   <p>He told of the vast importance of such an organization - to help the people realize that the greatest duty of all Polish parents is to give their children an education. After the choir sang a few Polish national songs, Reverend Father Gronkowski opened the meeting by asking Archbishop Symon to say a prayer before the regular procedure of this meeting got under way. He then asked Reverend Father Truszynski, president of this federation, to speak on the importance of this meeting. He also appointed Mr. John F. Smulski, our city attorney, as chairman and Mr. Stanley Swajkart, an editor of the Polish Daily News, as secretary. He explained our task here, our aims abroad, and our obligation to help this Polish Roman-Catholic Federation to continue its wonderful work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0111.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. K. H. Watchel, an editor of the paper Narod Polski, read the memoir; this was followed by a wide and hearty discussion in which the following people spoke their respective views: Dr. Adam Swajkart, Most Reverend Father John Kosinski, Most Reverend Father Wm. Zapala, rector of St. Stanislaus; Wm. Dyniewicz, assistant rector of Polish National Alliance; Reverend Father Gronowski, Kazimir Neuman, an editor of the Polish Daily News.</p>
   <p>Mr. Neuman stressed his points to advantage, in regard to organizing this society and the importance of schooling. He made a motion that the organization of this society should not be postponed for later voting or approval but to vote on it immediately. It was passed unanimously. In the name of the church and the Catholic people, Archbishop Symon thanked Mr. Neuman for his splendid speech and for the congregation's unanimous vote on this motion.</p>
   <p>The people must realize the importance of schooling - not to send their children to work at an early age. This will be the society's most important task.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
