<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. V. No. 27,
<date when="1901-07-03">July 3, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The End of the School Year at St. Stanislaus College.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0123</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0123.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. V. No. 27,
<date when="1901-07-03">July 3, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE END OF THE SCHOOL YEAR AT ST. STANISLAUS COLLEGE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the parochial hall of St. Mary's was held on Sunday a formal ceremony celebrating the end of the school year of St. Stanislaus College.</p>
   <p>A large number of priests, Sisters of Notre Dame, Sisters of Nazareth, parents, students, and citizens interested in the education of young people in Chicago in a Polish institution of higher education took part in the ceremony whose program was very interesting.</p>
   <p>The poem "Greeting" was read in clear Polish and with emotion by a young student H. Czekata. Two students leaving the institution gave speeches suitable to the occasion, P. F. Ligman in Polish and P. J. Gryczka in English. Two other graduating debaters. T. Lasecki and J. Konopa debated on the subject: "Should Cities Own and Manage Public Utilities?" The first took the affirmative and the other the negative side.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0124.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There was also a three-act drama "St. Stanislaus" translated from Italian by one of the students. The young amateurs gave a splendid performance, especially the role of the old servant.</p>
   <p>The orchestra played during the intermissions, giving evidence of progress in music in the college under the direction of Mr. N. Nowicki. The most interesting part of the program was the awarding of diplomas, medals, and rewards. The first diplomas were for completing the course, giving the degree of "Bachelor of Arts" the same as in first-class American universities; these were received by Adam Bloch, Thomas Bona, Stanislaus Bubacz, Jacob Gryczska, John Konopa, Thomas Lasecki, Thaddeus Ligman, and Valentine Swientek.</p>
   <p>Diplomas were awarded by Rev. F. Gordon. Everyone of the "Bachelors" received also a beautiful bouquet of flowers from girls dressed in white. A student of the fourth course, Steven Kolanowski, received a gold medal donated by Alderman Stanley Kunz; Theodor Czastka from the same course received second <pb facs="5423968_2_0125.jpg" n="3"/>reward.</p>
   <p>Michael Kruczas from the second course received a gold medal donated by Mr. Peter Kielbassa. Other students receiving rewards were Adalbert Soska and Bernard Pstrong. A student of the first course, Stanislaus Zywicki, received a gold medal donated by Mr. N. Piotrowske, while Stanislaus Shaeffer and John Bielawa received other rewards. Norbert Goreczka, a student of the preparatory course also received a reward.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
