<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1921-01-19">Jan. 19, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Let's Get a Couple of "Pollack-Girls" Tonight</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0645</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0645.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>,
<date when="1921-01-19">Jan. 19, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">LET'S GET A COUPLE OF "POLLACK-GIRLS" TONIGHT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Nowiny Polskie (Polish News) we read: When one of our reporters heard this remark uttered by a young Jewish sport loitering near a downtown hotel, his blood commenced to boil in his veins and his fist itched with a desire to shut the mouth of that loiterer. We have written many times before about our girls strolling around the city, lingering at hotels of a questionable character, and their frequenting all kinds of Venetian gardens in company of the worst type, young Jews, Greeks and other underworld scum. Whether or not, our warning did bring about results is hard to say.</p>
   <p>The object of this article is not to convert the already fallen girls-although it is never too late to reform-but to warn and save other young girls from the same fate; and to warn mothers, who do not realize the dangers to which their daughters are exposed by going out with strangers. Therefore, we appeal to mothers, especially to those who are fascinated by their daughters' beautiful faces, and who dress their daughters beyond their means, but never critisize their behavior, permitting them to go out with all kinds of "fine beaux," regardless of whether that beau is a young Jew from underworld sporting dens, a Greek, an Italian or any other disreputable character, provided he is from downtown.</p>
   <p>Mothers who think that such "beaux" will be the husbands of their gracious daughters are greatly mistaken. The idea of marriage never enters their mind.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0646.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then what is their motive for going about with our beautiful and healthy Polish girls?-- You can judge that for yourselves. If such rascals dared seduce a girl of some other nationality they would be tracked down even in hell, to have their bones broken, but our ignorant, as the snuff in the snuff box, nation, allows such rogues to do with our children as they please, using the excuse later on, that they can-not find the scoundrels to punish them.</p>
   <p>When the writer of this article heard this sentence: "Let's get a couple of"Pollack" girls tonight," he must have involuntarily blushed with shame, and anger at the fact that our girls are foolish enough to allow demoralized loafers to take such advantage. No wonder then, that among the people of that caliber there is a slogan "Let's get a couple of "Pollack" girls tonight." Who is to blame -- these naive girls who chase the glittering trifles of life? No! a hundred times, No! The whole fault lies with those parents who suffer with delusion of grandeur and to whom a Pole means nothing but a downtown sport, who knows how to bow to mother when, or if, presented to her. and whose picture is placed on the girl's dresser or hung on her breast. O! yes, that is a great honor. Mother will tell her neighbors how her daughter went out with a swell, downtown, rich sport, who kept her out till early in the morning! Most often such a rich sport doesn't have the price of a dinner the next day; but he tells his friends what a good time he had with a "Pollack" girl.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0647.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And you girls! Do you know that your names are placed on the lists of all such sports as "desirable girls," that your addresses are known, indecent remarks are being passed, about you? Perhaps you are too stupid to know that, therefore, we wish to open your eyes. Do you think that people do not see you in the automobile with a stranger, or coming home at early hours of the morning? Do you know that after a few incidents of that kind people will "keep you on the lip of their tongues and no one will respect you? No self respecting person, either of Polish or any other nationality admires a girl of that type. Do not wonder then, that the Polish boys pass you up. You yourselves have closed the doors to those young men who had serious intentions.</p>
   <p>The condition about which we write, existsnot only among the poor, but also among the so called "cream of Polish society." We could point out the names of families where preference was given an Italian, Greek or Jew because he had a diamond on his finger, a swell car,which was probably bought on the payment plan, or about which neither parents nor the girl have any information. Such beaux do not marry the girl but discard them like they would a used broom, to be replaced with fresh game.</p>
   <p>Parents! For Gods sake, do not make fools of yourselves and monkeys of your daughters.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
