<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 205,
<date when="1908-09-01">September 1, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Blessing of the Corner Stone at the School of the "Good Shepherd"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0081</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0081.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>, Vol. XIX, No. 205,
<date when="1908-09-01">September 1, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">BLESSING OF THE CORNER STONE AT THE SCHOOL OF THE "GOOD SHEPHERD"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The only reguge for preserving the consciousness of Polish origin among our children are Polish parochial schools. Let us look at the new addition to our knowledge, the new stronghold, and new watch-tower of our Polish spirit, showing us menaced Poles the horrible example of American children, who can thank the public school for their instruction, their lack of respect for their parents, and insufficient knowledge of the English language. The children in our parochial schools can learn more respect for their parents and acquire more knowledge of the English as well as the Polish language, in three or four years, than the average public school student can in six or seven years.</p>
   <p>A new Polish school is being erected in the territory inhabited mostly by Poles. At the present as in the past, the children are being taught in the old frame church of the "Good Shepherd." In the past year the children were taught by Mr. Walter Mogilicki, who during the coming year will be aided <pb facs="5423968_2_0082.jpg" n="2"/>by a woman teacher; they will teach until the Sisters arrive and take over full control of all school activities.</p>
   <p>The constant increase in attendance which at the present time is over the 100 mark, compelled Reverend Father Junga to consider building a small inexpensive school building, because the church is not large enough to accommodate all the students.</p>
   <p>The plans for this building were under the direction of a well known architect, Mr. John Steinback; the contractor, Mr. F. Ostrowski, claims that the building will be complete by the end of October. Although a small brick structure, it will be the most modern of the present schools.</p>
   <p>The fromt of the school will face 43rd street and the school will measure 64 x 74 feet. The building will be a two-story structure consisting of three large rooms and an apartment for the pastor. The building will be of dark red brick, with a beautiful large brick doorway with large columns <pb facs="5423968_2_0083.jpg" n="3"/>on each side of the doorwar. Four empty lots in the rear of this building were also purchased so that in case the school has to be enlarged they will have enough room to add at least 16 more classes, also build a larger church. The cost of erecting this small school is $13,000.</p>
   <p>Four weeks after work was started, the fifteen Polish workers, the contractor, and the cashier of the Polish National Union, Mr. Ostrowski, openly stated that according to the progress shown to date the structure should be complete by next Sunday. Bishop Rhode will officiate at the blessing of the cornerstone. We should offer our thanks to Reverend Father Junga, pastor of the "Good Shepherd" parish for making this move to help our children receive a Polish education, also the parishioners and the Polish workers, who worked to make this dream come true.</p>
   <p>Sunday afternoon at 3 o'clock a parade will start to celebrate the good fortune of the "Good Shepherd" parish. All the societies of this parish will participate, as well as societies from the following parishes:</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0084.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Immaculate Conception of St. Mary, St. Ann, St. Joseph, St. Salemea, and The Sacred Heart of Mary.</p>
   <p>Bishop Rhode will be assisted by Reverend Father Junga, Reverend Father Czajkowski, Reverend Father Jagielski, and Father Grudzinski.</p>
   <p>At the close of this great celebration, Bishop Rhode praised Father Junga and his parishioners for their splendid work in behalf of Christianity.</p>
   <p>He expressed his belief that the Polish priests and Polish Catholics are doing more to preserve Polish nationality and the Roman-Catholic religion than any other nationality. He also hoped that the Poles will continue their work for the good of their native tongue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
