<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. 24, No. 35,
<date when="1920-09-01">Sept. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Politics in the Ranks of Labor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1600</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1600.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. 24, No. 35,
<date when="1920-09-01">Sept. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICS IN THE RANKS OF LABOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is something wrong in the ranks of organized labor. The workman is entering a slippery path of international politics for purely economic reasons. Organized labor desires to dictate laws, first to its own government and later on to other governments and countries.</p>
   <p>To what does this lead? Recently we witnessed a few very important incidents. A certain English labor group sided with the Russian Soviets against Poland's just demands. The Italian laborers did the same. In Danzig, Czechoslovakia and Germany, labor stopped the ammunition supplies to Poland. In the United States a certain labor group threatened a strike if the United States government helps Poland.</p>
   <p>Naturally, not all English, Italian and American workers are behind these decisions and threats. Furthermore, the regular worker has nothing to do with this matter. This is done by the leaders themselves, in most <pb facs="5423968_2_1601.jpg" n="2"/>cases without the knowledge of the workers and without their consent. The Chicago Federation of Labor is an example. The leaders of this organization made a resolution to disadvantage Poland, against which the workers had to protest later on.</p>
   <p>What is the result? Dissatisfaction, indignation and ill-will of one toward another. THe worker finds out that his leader, who not long ago preached about the "better working conditions" of his fellow men, today is playing "pay-off politics" and is controlled by the money belt of the Jew or the German, selling the national, sacred feelings of the workman.</p>
   <p>Some American or English Jew, standing at the head of the labor union, desires to control the destiny of Poland. Out with such leaders of the labor unions. The labor organizations do not exist for political purposes. Whoever desires to bring politics into the ranks of the labor union, consciously or unconsciously is endangering it. Politics should be removed from the labor unions as soon as possible. If the union leaders desire to play politics, we Poles cannot cooperate with them <pb facs="5423968_2_1602.jpg" n="3"/>lest we betray Poland, our nation.</p>
   <p>Let us remember that among the union members belonging to the international labor organizations, there are many Jewish and German paid agents, enemies of Poland. Therefore, be on your guard, brothers!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
