<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-12">Dec. 12, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">A Bit of Polemics</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1166</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1166.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Chicagoski</title>,
<date when="1893-12-12">Dec. 12, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">A BIT OF POLEMICS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our readers know full well how unwilling we are to enter into controversies, especially if they deal more over personalities than over matters of general import. There are times, however, when polemics are necessary, when matters of great importance demand an exchange of opinions in order to clarify the issues, when a newspaper must make known its stand regarding a certain important question, when it is compulsory for a large newspaper to publish its opinions, contradict false assertions made by its adversaries and explain matters under controversy.</p>
   <p>We are obliged to devote some space to one of these controversies now.</p>
   <p>We wish to answer as briefly as possible a few assertions published in the last issue of Polak w Ameryce (Buffalo).</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1167.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This newspaper is published on a conservative basis and has passed through various phases regarding its policy, especially its manner of dealing with Polish matters. From the excess of controversial material which characterized the Polak w Ameryce formerly, and which caused several Buffalo citizens some time ago to demand satisfaction in a manner truly regrettable--a personal attack on the editor--this newspaper changed a year or two ago to a more objective policy and until recently looked at our affairs in a more respectful way.</p>
   <p>We even remarked about this change sometime ago and have gladly given publicity to whatever they did that was worth while, as the newspaper possessed a certain degree of influence all its own. We judged that it would not be necessary for us to fight a Pole and that the Polish-American press had gained a new organ whose purpose was to build, not to destroy.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, the last few issues of Polak w Ameryce seem to contradict our fond hopes. The political stand the Buffalo newspaper has taken in regard to the pamphlet published by Dr. Dunikowski, the Polish Central Committee <pb facs="5423968_2_1168.jpg" n="3"/>organized to help the Lwow Exposition, the Committee to build the Kosciusko monument, and other important matters initiated in the city of Chicago has become so unwholesome and so out of accord with the spirit of true citizenship that our duty as newspapermen demands that we call this to the attention not only of the public but of the editors of the publication referred to as well.</p>
   <p>In everything written lately by Polak w Ameryce about our activities, one can detect a certain personal grudge, if not direct animosity. The activities themselves are not condemned, probably because the newspaper has already commended them in previous articles. The attacks are aimed at the promoters of these activities, whose actions are criticized. In general, Polak w Ameryce endeavors to complain as much as it possibly can. One would think that these attacks are the result of jealousy and envy--jealousy over the activities of our community and envy over matters of leadership. We do not wish, of course, to entertain such an improbable suspicion, for such attitude would run counter to the aims of the editors of this publication--aims which we have always hoped are above such feelings. We would much prefer to attribute this sad <pb facs="5423968_2_1169.jpg" n="4"/>condition to the temporary mental aberrations of the editors, aberrations which, if God permits, will pass.</p>
   <p>Lack of space and time does not permit us to criticize or contradict all personal invectives published by Polak w Ameryce during the last few weeks. We have mentioned some briefly; others, such as the question of the Polish Committee for the Lwow Exposition, we shall take up at another time. Here we wish only to protest against the unwarranted accusations hurled by Polak w Ameryce against our newspaper, accusations which, although false, damage us greatly. We refer to an item in the April 7 issue of Polak w Ameryce.</p>
   <p>The editor of Polak w Ameryce, piqued at a five-line news item of ours about his conversion from a fervent admirer to a severe critic of Professor Dunikowski, published a two-column editorial, in one full column of which he explains the meaning of our five-line news item and places in our mouth a number of assertions that we never made, if only because of the briefness of the article. He accuses us of animosity toward the St. Stanislaus School in Buffalo, and the Seminary and Felician Sisters' institution in Detroit.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1170.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Furthermore, he insinuates that he obtained the information from secret sources.</p>
   <p>We regret that our short article has been interpreted as a tirade against others. Against whom? We certainly don't know. Anybody can read the article in question and convince himself that it contains none of the evil presumably found in it by the Polak w Ameryce. We are mainly interested in the accusation made so carelessly, if not with ill will, toward our newspaper. We protest against this accusation with the greatest energy.</p>
   <p>Polak w Ameryce writes as follows: "....surely, whenever anyone wants to discredit and belittle the Polish school of St. Stanislaus Parish in Buffalo, the Seminary in Detroit, or the Felician Sisters, all he has to do is to get a copy of Dziennik Chicagoski, which is always ready with a supply of dishonest assertions and suggestions."</p>
   <p>In view of such statement, we feel it is our duty to state that such assertion is untrue and constitutes a brazen falsehood without any foundation at all.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1171.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Our readers are witnesses that we have never attacked said institutions.</p>
   <p>We earnestly and energetically protest against this untruth. For over one year it has been under the present management, Dziennik Chicagoski has never attacked, either directly or indirectly, any of these institutions. In fact, this newspaper has never made any disparaging remarks about any Polish institution. Our files which contain copies of all our issues, are sufficient proof of this.</p>
   <p>The stand taken by our newspaper has been entirely misjudged by the Polak w Ameryce. We have been grievously wronged.</p>
   <p>Our aim during one year of activity in the newspaper field has been to stand as much as possible above parties and conventions, above sympathy or personal enmity, whenever the welfare of the general public has been at stake.</p>
   <p>We have always lent assistance to anything Polish, to anything worth while. We are interested, not in personalities, but in matters of general interest.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1172.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>A good idea, regardless of the camp from which it may come, will be always welcome and praised; an evil idea, regardless of its origin, will be always condemned. For this reason, whatever our opinion of the editor of the Polak w Ameryce, we have praised all his good and worthwhile articles. Because of this, and because it is published in conjunction with the organ of one of the greatest Polish organizations in America, Dziennik Chicagoski has never felt, or feels now, any dislike toward any Polish organization. On the contrary, this newspaper looks objectively and even sympathetically on the affairs of these organizations, for, since they are Polish, they are part of us. This same truism does not permit us to be envious of, or unwilling toward, the institutions mentioned by the Polak w Ameryce: institutions whose aim is the growth of religious, moral, and educational ideals, and, therefore, the welfare of our people.</p>
   <p>The Polak w Ameryce cannot point to any instance of such envy or jealousy on the part of our newspaper--not even in the five-line article whose meaning it has so diabolically distorted.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1173.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>This is not the first time that Polak w Ameryce has done this. On several occasions it has accused us of enmity toward Unia Polska [Translator's note: Polish organization in Buffalo] and the Poles living in the Buffalo archdiocese--all because of our article, based on Hoffman's Directory, about the Polish churches in America. In every instance, however, we have been able to convince these people that Polak w Ameryce's accusations were groundless, that we wished only the best for everything that was Polish.</p>
   <p>With this accusation hurled at us again today, we feel it is our duty to distinctly and positively declare our position and to protest against this accusation, on the ground that it is baseless, if not dishonest.</p>
   <p>Concluding this explanation, we return to the Polak w Ameryce to call them to order.</p>
   <p>Polak w Ameryce should decide once and for all in which direction it wants to travel--whom it wants to serve? If it--understanding the public good and wishing to strive for it even at the expense of personal insults--decides <pb facs="5423968_2_1174.jpg" n="9"/>to go along the road of Christian brotherly love, we will sincerely and gladly enroll it among those whose aim and purpose in life are truth and goodness. If for selfish reasons it wishes to condemn public undertakings and to sow hatred and dissension, it will fall, even without any effort on our part, to the level of a newsmonger, whose aim it is to destroy everything, thus harming itself and our own brethren.</p>
   <p>The choice we leave to Polak w Ameryce.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
