<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. II, No. 34,
<date when="1898-08-24">August 24, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">St. Stanislaus College. under Management of Resurrectionist Fathers in Chicago. History of its Establishment.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0138</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0138.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. II, No. 34,
<date when="1898-08-24">August 24, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">ST. STANISLAUS COLLEGE. UNDER MANAGEMENT OF RESURRECTIONIST FATHERS IN CHICAGO. HISTORY OF ITS ESTABLISHMENT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the past decade, during which our Polish immigration has taken on larger proportions, and the number of Poles, especially in Chicago, increased to 150,000, the natural concurrence of circumstances had brought about the feeling of the lack of an institution of higher education for our youth. The reports of the individual parochial schools show that they have a total attendance of about 10,000 pupils. It is no wonder that there is an urgent need of establishing a high school, where the youth can receive further education, on the same basis as that of the American high schools, with special emphasis on the subjects of morals and the teaching of the language of their fathers.</p>
   <p>In the year 1889, under the advisory aid of the Very Reverend Waleryan Przewlocki, at that time the head of the assembly of Resurrectionists, the father of the assembly in Chicago began to take action.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0139.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As always and everywhere, where anything pertains to a good cause, the Poles are always in "doubt." It is not surprising that from the start until the present time the directors have had to compete with this difficulty, not mentioning the lack of material means, which are so necessary in bringing about such an institution. Is there anything that cannot be accomplished by unceasing labors? Is there anything that cannot be accomplished by sacrifices and an iron will?</p>
   <p>The first three years we had to put up with a shortage of materials and the unavoidable consequences due to a general lack of confidence. In spite of these obstacles we did not lose hope. Today it can be said it was not a disappointment to those who had hopes of a brighter future, to those who with utmost effort have made sacrifices for the cause, for the good of our immigration, and for the sake of knowledge, because the establishment stands now on a firm foundation and, when it comes to interior decoration and equipment, takes second place to none.</p>
   <p>The nine year old "ant-like" labor is beginning to bear fruit. The people <pb facs="5423968_2_0140.jpg" n="3"/>of good will, and parents who were interested in their children's welfare, finally became convinced that in these days education and wisdom are the only means of a better existence; the lack of which has obstructed the way to intelligence for our youth and has constantly balked the efforts of the third parties toward this aspect, regardless of how influential they might have been.</p>
   <p>Even today institutions are being criticized by the prejudiced and unappreciative. They are opposed to them because they are Polish institutions and we know that whatever is ours is "no good" - only what belongs to others impresses them and receives their praise.</p>
   <p>We are sure that these criticisms will gradually cease; when our people will go to the trouble to find out the true fact - that even today this institution is already bearing fruit.</p>
   <p>These courses are in the Polish and English languages. The teaching of the fundamentals of Polish and English literature and history is conducted by teachers who are well informed on these subjects.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0141.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Because a thorough education must rely on a fundamental religious feeling, therefore the management of the college gives special care to the youth entrusted in its care to see that they receive the best of education concerning religion and morals. This conscientious work has today, already brought results to students, who, after leaving this institution are receiving further education in still higher institutions of learning, with glory to all Poles who have already successfully passed their examinations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
