<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XV, No. 25,
<date when="1911-06-21">June 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A Useful Institution</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_1011</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1011.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III G (Jewish)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f (Jewish)</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Narod Polski</title>, Vol. XV, No. 25,
<date when="1911-06-21">June 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">A USEFUL INSTITUTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lately our press has been filled with all kinds of plans and projects. The number of those projects is so great and everyone of them is so important and so lofty that it would take at least twenty-five years to complete one properly.</p>
   <p>We have a great habit of creating plans, large and small, but when it comes to carrying them out, we are either short of men or of good will. This would hinder any plan.</p>
   <p>Other nationalities do differently. They do not make so much noise about it but carry out their plans with complete success. With them action follows the words; with us there is a boundless gap between the words and the action. In the Winter we build our castles on ice and in Summer on sand; that is why the first are destroyed by the action of the sun and the others are scattered by the wind.</p>
   <p>Of all the projects discussed by the press, we wish to call your attention to one recently taken up, and that is, the protection of our immigrants.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1012.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is a known fact that the majority of Poles have no citizenship papers, and because they don't know the English language they cannot get either citizenship papers or employment. In order to remedy this evil it was decided to form clubs and classes for learning English.</p>
   <p>But alas! the whole affair ended in nothing, or rather in a project of sending a protest to the government against the sharp restrictions against our countrymen who are illiterate.</p>
   <p>The Jews did differently. They did not call mass meetings, but engaged an able lawyer, sent him to Washington and in a short time the case was settled successfully. That is not all. The Jews, without making any noise, established in every large city a school for their immigrants. In Chicago this was taken care of by the Jewish Educational Association which, at the cost of $100,000, converted an old orphanage into a Jewish immigrant school.</p>
   <p>According to the information given in the English papers, those schools will teach not only the English language but also other subjects necessary in life.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_1013.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The practical methods of the Jews should serve as an example worthy of following. Others also supply us with such examples, but we do not make use of them. We think of them after misfortune, when it is too late to remedy it. Then we call mass meetings and send protests which are useless. They do not mean any more than the shaking of the big toe in the shoe. That ends our action in the good cause and our future good.</p>
   <p>Our political clubs are active only before election - after election they are dead.</p>
   <p>Our people need such schools more than any other nation on account of their lack of English. Having the knowledge of the English language we would gain politically, but in order to obtain our objective we should make less noise and have more action.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
