<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-05-27">May 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The Education of Mothers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0410</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0410.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dziennik Zwiazkowy</title>,
<date when="1909-05-27">May 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE EDUCATION OF MOTHERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the most important problems of Polish Society is the uplifting of mental horizons. This can be made possible through proper education of the younger generation and by organizing them in the "New Poland."</p>
   <p>Certain aspects of this are being carried out at the present time. The work is progressing in a slow, gradual way, and there is a great deal more to be done.</p>
   <p>The influence of a mother upon her child is of great importance, more important than schools and other institutions of learning, but this influence is comparatively small.</p>
   <p>The schools educate and cater to the masses and therefore cannot give individual instruction to each person. The teachers and instructors cannot satisfy the wants of each child and quality must be sacrificed for quantity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0411.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Although the children obtain worldly knowledge, it is known that the moral aspect of education is neglected. One [bad] child has more influence in degrading another than a good school in improving him. It is a difficult problem to cope with among such great numbers.</p>
   <p>Children that are brought up in a negligent way bring to the school their assimilated ill manners, which do more harm than the teachers can do good. The child thus mixed becomes a problem to good mothers, who are found in comparative small numbers, especially among the poor working class.</p>
   <p>No wonder! How can a working mother, filled with worries, look properly after her children? How can she show them the right from the wrong, see to it that they are taught and enlightened so that they can follow the path to a good religious and righteous living?</p>
   <p>Who looks after the instruction of the mothers? Although small articles appear <pb facs="5423968_2_0412.jpg" n="3"/>from day to day on the bringing up of children, yet this is only a drop of water in the ocean when compared to the problems and needs of the mothers.</p>
   <p>Since long ago, there should have been a movement in this direction in the way of a well organized plan to aid and fill the needs of the mothers, a plan that would be a guardian for the children and for posterity. Liberally speaking, in every parochial school, library, and reading room, lectures should be given every week for the mothers, this lecture to be held between the hours of 5 and 6 in the late afternoon, to be managed by intelligent mothers for the betterment of the children and parents, and intended to bring out points lacking in the present educational system.</p>
   <p>These sessions would be particularly intended to bring out suggestions where they are needed, later to be brought before the proper authorities for consideration. Suggestions for proper reading matter and its supervision as <pb facs="5423968_2_0413.jpg" n="4"/>regards both children and mothers, should be an important function so that the two can benefit. This kind of meetings and round table discussions would bring closer to the mothers, especially those of the working class, their children's problems and educational progress.</p>
   <p>Among our Polish women, none of these things exists. There are many good will societies that aid the poorer children. They hold affairs to raise funds for clothing. However, these organizations do not help the weary hearts of the mothers whose children have become problems, both for them and the school. There is no club or group that would assist her in correcting her wrongs, the child's wrongs, where guidance could be found both for the soul and mind. The uneducated mother will not spoil her children morally, but people of loose morals can easily corrupt them, and these children, despite their good intentions, are easily led to the road of sin.</p>
   <p>Unless the mothers of the poor take it upon themselves to get a better outlook on life from intelligent mothers, there will be no maternal gain for <pb facs="5423968_2_0414.jpg" n="5"/>themselves or for their children. Until both groups of mothers organize, there cannot be any moral and intellectual improvement for neither parents nor children.</p>
   <p>In England the Christian Mothers Association has been organized and operated successfully for thirty years. This organization is increasing every year. Classes are sponsored for mothers where the most advanced knowledge of the world is presented, including the best motherhood advice. This association has over 4,500 members, has two doctors, two obstetricians, three medical centers, and drug stores.</p>
   <p>This ought to be a model for our Polish mothers to follow. Although it would be difficult to pattern one after that style, one could be started that would embody the major principles.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
