<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 37,
<date when="1919-09-11">Sept. 11, 1919</date><title level="a">What Prohibition Has Done for Many Families</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423968_2_0440</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-01-11">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0440.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>POLISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Polonia</title>, Vol. XIII, No. 37,
<date when="1919-09-11">Sept. 11, 1919</date><title level="a">WHAT PROHIBITION HAS DONE FOR MANY FAMILIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If there is anything that makes us glad, on account of prohibition, it is the circumstance that father is coming home straight from work, and that was very hard for him to do when the saloons were open. Furthermore, he is getting interested in his family's affairs. For the first time in his life, he is getting"satisfaction and pleasure from a walk through the park with us," so a young girl of 25 told me. She was the oldest of five children and the main support of the family, because her earnings balanced the deficit caused by her father's squandering of his earnings.</p>
   <p>However, these words were only a sample of the important facts which I have learned just after an investigation lasting a whole day and a whole night, considering some of the consequences caused by prohibition in an average family. In the daytime and late after midnight I have spent weary hours, riding and walking through the parks, visiting places of amusements, in a crowded American city.</p>
   <p>There I used to see hundreds of men drinking at the bar, staggering and cursing; there I saw painted beauties intimately embracing their partners, dancing on the dazzling floor of the cabaret, all that crowd around them devoted to such low orgies. There once I saw long lines of fallen women, stopping men and offering for sale their withered charms. In all of those places I met a kind of peace and quiet.</p>
   <pb facs="5423968_2_0441.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But where are all those people, those patrons, who crowded those places? I asked when the lonesome hours of the night were passing slowly one after the other, and the empty saloons and cabarets seemed to fill my mind with mysterious dreams of the past.</p>
   <p>But in my ears rang the words of that girl: "Father is coming home straight from work." And because I am convinced that her statement could be applied in thousands of such cases. I am only placing this statement before every working man and woman in our community.</p>
   <p>Home, back home, to the mutual home which is the best substitute for the saloon. Not only should you spread that slogan, but also propagate it and plan its realization.</p>
   <p>Home is not only a place but also a family unit.</p>
   <p>When father and mother and all the children spend the evening pleasantly in the park or at the seashore, in the theater; when father enjoys such liberties that he would in the presence of his family, when father comes straight home and stays evenings with his family, then we see the regenerated family life that appears to replace the degradation of the saloon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
