<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The History of the Jews of Chicago</title>, Page 151.
<title level="a">(Edited by Hyman L. Meites)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_11_0110</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_11_0110.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The History of the Jews of Chicago</title>, Page 151.
<title level="a">(Edited by Hyman L. Meites)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Bernard Horwich was born in Ponieman, Suwalk, Russia, May 10, 1863, where he lived with his parents until he was 13 years old. After working in Koenigsberg, East Prussia, for two years, he went into business for himself, as a grain broker.</p>
   <p>At the age of 17, he came to the United States, and made his way to Chicago. Here, he rose from his first humble occupation, that of selling stationery on the streets, to the presidency of two banks and of important commercial enterprises, and a position of trust and honor in the community.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_11_0111.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He started to work for the improvement of his co-religionists on the West Side, and in practically every movement toward that end his name is to be found among the organizers and officers.</p>
   <p>The Hebrew Literary Society, the Order B'rith Abraham, the Jewish parade during the World's Fair, the Kishsneff Relief Committee of Chicago, the Ezrath N'Odchim ( for relief of Russian refugees), and the Chicago Hebrew Institute, have all known his aid in some leading capacity, as organizer, president, or as an official.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_11_0112.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>One of his earliest pieces of work was the formation of the Chicago Zion Society, the first Zionist organization in the United States. Later, together with Leon Zolotkoff, he founded the Order Knights of Zion, of which Horwich was the first grand-master. He was elected several times to the International Zionist Congress, and has served in numerous executive positions. In raising money for Zionist purposes, as well as in giving of his own, he stands preeminent.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_11_0113.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>His supervision of the sale of 20,000 shares in the Jewish Colonial Bank, at $5 a share, his activities in the "Bread for Palestine" campaign during the World War, and his chairmanship of the local People's Relief Committee for War Sufferers, which raised $2,000,000, are a few instances of the many occasions on which he has demonstrated his qualities of leadership.</p>
   <p>In 1919, he went to Europe as one of a commission of three, sent by the Joint Distribution Committee, which in its five months' stay, distributed two shiploads of food and millions of dollars to the war victims of Poland and Lithuania. In personal donations, Horwich has long set a mark, being one of the earliest on the West Side to give on a large scale and thus influencing others to follow his example.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_11_0114.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>What was undoubtedly his greatest single achievement was the Federated Jewish Charities, to the firm establishment of which he devoted two years' exclusive effort. He has been a member of the American Jewish Committee since its inception, and has held various public positions, among them, election commissioner of Cook County.</p>
   <p>This position, to which he was appointed by the late Judge Scully in 1915, had never been held by a Jew before. Besides being president of the Public and Superior State Banks, on several occasions he has been called upon to safeguard the depositors of other institutions, when these were threatened. The Ashland, Twelfth and Sixteenth Street Banks, are two cases in point, in which he devoted months of labor, gratis, and saved thousands for the depositors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
