<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Daily Tribune</title>,
<date when="1901-04-04">April 4, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Beg for "Mother" Cohen Children's Friend Dies and They Seek to Save Her Body from Potter's Field</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_11_0190</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.B"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_11_0190.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>V B</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Daily Tribune</title>,
<date when="1901-04-04">April 4, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">BEG FOR "MOTHER" COHEN CHILDREN'S FRIEND DIES AND THEY SEEK TO SAVE HER BODY FROM POTTER'S FIELD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Mother" Cohen was buried yesterday. All morning the children about her late dwelling, 106 Bunker Street, went from store to store and begged for money to save the remains of their friend from "Potter's Field." This they could not do, but they raised enough to deck the rough coffin with flowers and robe the figure with a gown of a quality such as it had not worn for many a day. One boy, who had received pennies from her shrunken hands since he was old enough to toddle, bought violets with all the cash he had in his bank, amounting to $2.80. The others succeeded in getting $5 together, which was given to the undertaker to use for flowers and clothing.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Cohen was eighty eight years old. She was born in Russia, and came to New York when a child. Her husband, Eli Rosenbloom, was a merchant, and for a time wealthy. When his fortune melted in speculations he died of a broken heart. From that time until her death, Mrs. Cohen worked for her living. When whe came to Chicago no one knows. Three years ago she appeared on Bunker Street, and roomed with Mrs. Baum at $2 a month. A week ago she was taken ill with pneumonia, and yesterday <pb facs="5423972_11_0191.jpg" n="2"/>the Health Department ordered her moved to the County Hospital. On the way she died. Just before she entered the ambulance she called a little girl to her and gave the child the last twenty-five cents she had. In her room nothing but an old dress and a Yiddish Bible was found.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
