<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
wk. of <date when="1892-04-16">April 16, 1892</date>. p. 212.
<title level="a">[Godfrey Snydacker Dead]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_11_0063</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_11_0063.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
wk. of <date when="1892-04-16">April 16, 1892</date>. p. 212.
<title level="a">[GODFREY SNYDACKER DEAD]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Godfrey Snydacker died suddenly on Tuesday night of heart failure, at his residence, 2522 Michigan Ave. He was born 66 years ago in Westphalia, Germany, where he received an excellent education in the national schools. After graduating, he followed the profession of a teacher for a time and filled an important position in a leading German institute of learning.</p>
   <p>In 1853,he emigrated to New York, and after a residence there for a few months, he came to Chicago. For three years he was preacher of the Kehilath Anshai Moarab Congregation of the Men of the West, and also taught the day school in connection with the Congregation. When the Sinai Congregation was formed in 1858, Mr. Snydacker became a member, and, on several occasions, has been its presiding officer.</p>
   <p>He was one of the business pioneers of Chicago, having established a banking and real-estate business in this city as early as 1858. The firm's name <pb facs="5423972_11_0064.jpg" n="2"/>was first known as Eisendrath and Co., and it was composed of Nathan Eisendrath, Conrad L. Niehoff, and Godfrey Snydacker. In 1861 his partners retired, and Mr. Snydacker and his brother, Moses Snydacker carried on the business under the firm's name of Snydacker and Co.</p>
   <p>He was a member of the Hebrew Relief Association for twenty-five years, and for many years was a member of the executive committee. Mr. Snydacker was also German Consul in Chicago for several years subsequent to 1858.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
