<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>American Jewish Year Book</title>,
5663. <date when="1903-09-21">October 2, 1902, to September 21, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Edited by Cyrus Adler</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_11_0168</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_11_0168.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The American Jewish Year Book</title>,
5663. <date when="1903-09-21">October 2, 1902, to September 21, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Edited by Cyrus Adler</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>NATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS. THE JEWISH AGRICULTURISTS' AID SOCIETY OF AMERICA. (pp.116 - 118.)</p>
   <p>The Biennial Meeting of the Jewish Agirculturists' Aid Society of America was held January 6, 1902, at Chicago, Illinois. The object of the society is to make loans to prospective Jewish farmers. Since 1888, when it was organized, the society realized its object without means of its own. The money loaned by the society had been advanced by Jewish citizens of Chicago, who invested and reinvested sums varying from $150 to $1,000, to the proteges of the society. As individuals willing to make such loans cannot always be found readily, it was decided to create a "Loan Fund." With this end in view the society now issues "Certificates of Credit," in denominations of ten dollars and upwards. The certificates are redeemable after ten years from the date of issue, or before, at the option of the society, and bear interest at the rate of three percent per annum, payable January 1. It was also decided that persons who had made loans to Jewish farmers through the society, be permitted to exchange the papers they hold for such loans for the Loan Certificates of the society. Up to July 1, 1902, Loan Certificates to the amount of $8,095 were subscribed for. Membership fees and donations <pb facs="5423972_11_0169.jpg" n="2"/>are used to carry on the work of the society. As an additional revenue for this purpose it was decided to place "Mite Boxes" in Jewish households; the scheme to be operated through the Sabbath School children and teachers.</p>
   <p>The following data are taken from the reports of the Corresponding Secretary, for 1901, and the first six months of 1902: Since 1888, when the society was organized, the society has settled 105 farmers, of whom 89 are at present still on their farms. The cost of settling a family on a farm varied from $300 to $1,000. In every case, assistance was rendered in the shape of a loan, secured at the rate of four percent. The 89 families work on an aggregate of 10,617 acres of land, situated in Minnesota, North Dakota, South Dakota, Michigan, Iowa, Illinois, Indiana, and Florida. Thirty-six families have taken homesteads on government lands, 5,760 acres, valued at $28,000. On these homesteads have been built 29 dwellings, 22 barns, 15 granaries, 10 stables, 6 sheds and corn cribs. The buildings represent a value of $14,500. Forty-one families have purchased 3,617 acres for $48,630, valued, in their present improved condition, at $65,000. Twelve farmers work 1,230 acres of <pb facs="5423972_11_0170.jpg" n="3"/>rented land, paying annually $1,460 in rent. The 89 families own 257 horses, 277 cows, and 195 calves. The aggregate amount loaned to the society is $35,525, of which sum $22,495 have been repaid; 38 persons still owing $14,030. The total encumbrance on the farms, including liens held by others as well as by the society, is $26,200. The cost of carrying on the work of the society since 1888, setting aside the loans made to farmers, has been less than $3,000, or an average of about $230 a year, for printing, postage, legal fees, records, etc.</p>
   <p>During 1901, the society assisted 28 parties - 20 heads of families, and 8 single men, or 57 adults over sixteen years, and <gap unit="chars" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>0 children under that age - all more or less depending upon the Jewish Charities of Chicago, to take up farming as an occupation. Five have rented 330 acres, 11 have purchased 640 acres, and 12 have filed homestead claims upon 1,920 acres of government lands. The farms are located in Illinois, Michigan, Indiana, Wisconsin, Florida, North Dakota, South Dakota, and Oklahoma. Of these assisted farmers, 17 had about $6,500 of their own. During the year, 23 loans were granted by the society, aggregating $9,800. Twelve of these loans were made to farmers who took up the work during the year, 11 to farmers of longer standing.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_11_0171.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Three of these loans were advanced by the Jewish Agricultural and Industrial Aid Society of New York, the rest of the money was advanced by Jewish citizens of Chicago. The repaying of loans proceeded promptly during the year.</p>
   <p>The report of the first six months of 1902, is as follows: Loans made by the society on its own account, $7,983.14; expenditures $496.95;  balance $153.19. Total balance in treasury, $569.21. Thirty-six parties have been assisted to take up farming in Colorado, Iowa, Michigan, Wisconsin, Illinois, and Dakota. The society has taken stock in the "Wilton Creamery Association," in Burleigh County, North Dakota, which will begin operations by August 10, 1902, by which 25 Jewish farmers in Burleigh and McLean counties will be greatly benefited.</p>
   <p>The officers and directors of the society are: President, Adolph Loeb; Vice-President, Dr. Emil G. Hirsch; Treasurer, Edward Rose; Recording Secretary, Leopold Gans; Corresponding Secretary, Rabbi A. B. Levy, 15 York St., Chicago, Illinois. Directors: Israel Cowen, Henry N. Hart, Adolph Moses, Julius Rappaport, Julius Rosenwald and Emanuel I. Selz.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
