<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sinai Congregation Correspondence</title>.
<date when="1897-09-06">September 6, 1897</date></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_11_0192</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.B"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-17">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_11_0192.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>V B</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sinai Congregation Correspondence</title>.
<date when="1897-09-06">September 6, 1897</date></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Superintendent, Chicago City R. R. Co.,</p>
   <p>2020 State Street,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>I beg to advise you of the commencement of our church services, and request additional car service on the following dates: Our regular Sunday services begin next Sunday the 12th inst., and terminate at 12:30, at which time, at least seven or eight cars ought to be at 21st street and Indiana avenue, without any delay. Our arrangements this year will be such that the services will be over promptly at that time, and the cars will not have to wait any length of time, and I shall be obliged if you will have this arrangement made for the entire season as to Sunday services.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_11_0193.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On Sunday the 26th inst., there will be no morning service, but it being the eve of the Jewish New Year's Day, extra service will be required by cars going north at 7:30 and south at 9 o'clock P. M. An extraordinary large crowd is then in attendance, and from the fact that all other Jewish churches on that evening have services it will be very desirable that at least eight or nine cars be at 21st street and Indiana avenue, at 9:00 P. M.</p>
   <p>On Monday the 27th inst. This day our services begin at 10:00 in the morning and terminate at 12:45 at which time we need the same number of extra cars, say about seven or eight.</p>
   <p>Wednesday, October 5, on the eve of the Day of Atonement, extra cars will be required from 7:30 going north and 9:30, about eight or nine cars going south. Wednesday, October 6, at 10 o'clock going north, and an extra number of cars at 1 o'clock at the Temple, going south. On this same day at 3 P. M. going north and at 5:45 going south, about seven or eight cars at 21st and Indiana avenue. During these holidays the attendance is unusually large.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
