<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-25">June 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Committee for Fourth of July Celebration Meets</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0042</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0042.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-06-25">June 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">COMMITTEE FOR FOURTH OF JULY CELEBRATION MEETS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night a meeting was held in the offices of the Czech branch of the American Red Cross, 3342 West 26th Street, Mr. F. O. Layer presiding. Almost every member of the Czech Arrangement Committee for the Fourth of July celebration was present. The question of supplying the necessary band was soon settled when it became known that a number of our organizations have already procured their own music and others plan to do the same. The latter will be urged to hire their band as soon as possible, since many musicians were engaged by other nationalities weeks ago.</p>
   <p>Several new members have been added to the present Arrangement Committee. The finance committee asked for suggestions on how to provide money. The answer was that in an enterprise of such magnitude as this contributions and gifts should be solicited.</p>
   <p>Mr. Oldrich Farsky, representing the Czech Artists Club, proposed the outfitting <pb facs="5418478_7_0043.jpg" n="2"/>of three carriages, one symbolizing the arrival of immigrants, one showing Columbia as protectress of the smaller nations, and the third representing the Slavonic peoples paying homage to Columbia.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anton J. Cermak introduced Mr. Brousek, band leader, who warned the Committee of the incidental dearth of musicians for the parade. All Slovak bands have been contracted--all by the Czechoslovak organizations.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. J. Salat suggested that our singing societies should sing patriotic songs while marching. We regret that the idea was rejected....</p>
   <p>The costs of one carriage was put at $160. Mr. Petrtyl stated that the Czech Artists Club is ready to do the purely artistic work on the carriages without charge; he submitted sketches of the proposed decorations.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anton J. Cermak proposed that the collection of contributions be started immediately, and announced that the firm Cermak and Serhant donated $25.00. Mr. Salat informed the committee that the Lawndale National Bank and the <pb facs="5418478_7_0044.jpg" n="3"/>Lawndale State Bank have contributed $100 together. Our theatrical associations will be asked to assist the various groups. Czech breweries are going to place their wagons and horses at the disposal of the parade. Mr. F. G. Hajicek's motion to leave the artistic arrangement of the carriages in the care of the Czech Artists' Club was accepted. Mr. Cermak's proposal also was greeted with loud consent: Ten thousand buttons for paraders will be sold and the proceeds donated to the tobacco fund for soldiers of the Czechoslovak Army. The year 1776, the year of the proclamation of American independence, will be seen on the upper part of the button, the year 1918 on the lower, while the words "Czechoslovaks for America" will be in the center. The "Vcelky" (Little Bees) women's auxiliary for the Czechoslovak Army, will sell the buttons.</p>
   <p>Mr. Veverka, director of the Czech Free-Thought schools in Chicago, declared that the participation of pupils is feasible, notwithstanding certain difficulties in supervising them. The colorful aspect of the parade is to be enhanced by the Banderium, i.e., mounted Sokols.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
