<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-01-06">Jan. 6, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Annual Meeting of the Board of Delegates to the Bohemian National Cemetery Association</title><title level="a" type="sub">Five Hundred Dollars Appropriated for the Benefit of Hoover's Relief Fund</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0947</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0947.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-01-06">Jan. 6, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE ANNUAL MEETING OF THE BOARD OF DELEGATES TO THE BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY ASSOCIATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Five Hundred Dollars Appropriated for the Benefit of Hoover's Relief Fund</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual meeting of the Sbor Zastupcu Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova (Board of Delegates to the Bohemian National Cemetery Association), held at the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies' hall, was called to order by Mr. Jan Pecha, chairman, promptly at 8 P. M. The minutes of the last meeting were read by Mr. Victor H. Filip and were approved as read.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Smejkal then called the attention of the delegates to the need for increasing the surety of the treasurer for the coming year. It was then resolved to raise the surety from twenty thousand to fifty thousand dollars. The sureties of other officers will remain the same. Many of the delegates recommended that salaries of the officers be raised, especially that of the treasurer, who is forced to spend much of his time every day in the interest <pb facs="5418478_7_0948.jpg" n="2"/>of the Cemetery. A motion to raise the salary of the new treasurer for this coming year to five hundred dollars was presented by Mr. Zrust. Mr. Kopecky recommended that the salary of the chairman and members of the board of directors also be raised one hundred dollars each. Both motions were carried by a two-thirds majority. Salaries of other officers were also raised as follows: Vice-chairman, $50 a year; secretary, $200 a year. The board of directors recommended that the salary of the Cemetery superintendent be raised to $2,400 a year; the salary of the financial secretary to $150 a month; the salary of the conservatory superintendent to $150 a month. All these recommendations were approved.</p>
   <p>After that the nominations began. The following delegates were elected: Mr. Jan Pecha, chairman; Mr. Ringl, vice-chairman; Mr. Victor H. Filip, secretary; Mr. Jurka, treasurer. The following delegates were elected to the board of directors: Messrs. Siman, David, and Lang for a two-year term, and Mr. Frank Boucek, for a one-year term.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0949.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The communication of the Czechoslovak committee of Hoover's Relief Action was again taken into consideration, and following the recommendation of Mr. Frank Boucek, the sum of five hundred dollars was appropriated for this purpose.</p>
   <p>Receipts for the month of December were $24,338.73; expenses, $18,565.91. There were 103 burials and 4 cremations during the month of December. After the reading of the financial report, this important meeting ended.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
