<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-03">July 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Let's All Participate!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0360</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0360.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-03">July 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LET'S ALL PARTICIPATE!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In order that the John Huss anniversary celebrations may achieve the fullest success, that they may become a magnificent manifestation of Chicago Bohemians, that they may leave a permanent impression on all, and arouse the interest of the Chicago public, it is necessary that all of us do all we can to make them memorable. Already the physical appearance of our settlements in Chicago should tell everybody that the Bohemians are celebrating a great holiday. Therefore, it is necessary that all houses belonging to our countrymen be decorated with flags, and pictures of John Huss or scenes relating to his teachings and work should be displayed in all windows Monday and Tuesday.</p>
   <p>The Monday parade of our Free Thought associations should be an enormous one. Every member should be on the spot, and prove in that way, not only that he understands the significance of John Huss, that he is proud of being of the same nationality, and determined to continue following his teachings and <pb facs="5418478_7_0361.jpg" n="2"/>principles, but also that he is interested in the proper representation of his own association. This occasion will show which association has a wide-awake, keen, and interested membership, a membership capable of good work. A large attendance of its membership will be the best publicity any association can get, it will be its most effective propaganda, and the most subtle campaign for new members.</p>
   <p>It is of great importance also to make the festivities of Tuesday night in the Auditorium a complete success and thus show the American public that the Bohemians honor their great men and know how to do honor to their memories. The Auditorium must be filled to the last place. Only in that way will we receive recognition and favorable mention in our English newspapers, which just like to keep quiet about everything that concerns the Bohemians. Bohemian businessmen should close their doors early Tuesday evening in order to make it possible for them and their employees to be at the Auditorium in time.</p>
   <p>Only if all Bohemians get together and do their duty can the John Huss <pb facs="5418478_7_0362.jpg" n="3"/>celebrations become such as they should be, and stimulate our action-generating enthusiasm. Only thus will it show the general American public that the Bohemians are a mature, well-developed nation, that we have great men of whom we are justly proud, that we have a glorious history and fully deserve an honorable place among the nations of the world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
