<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-14">Oct. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">News of the Free Thought Movement</title><title level="a" type="sub">Minutes of the Meeting of the State Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0695</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0695.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-14">Oct. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS OF THE FREE THOUGHT MOVEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">Minutes of the Meeting of the State Committee</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Statni Vybor Svazu Svobodomyslnych v Illinois (State Committee of the Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers of Illinois) took place in the Husuv Dum (Jan Huss Memorial Building) in Chicago, on October 9, 1922.</p>
   <p>The following delegates were present: Messrs. J. Musil, F. Strunc, K. Kamis, F. Remta, B. Ploss; Mesdames M. Zeman, J. Rohles. Other delegates were: Brother J. H. Filip, representing the Grand Lodge of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies); O. Rajtora, representing the Cesko-Slovanska Bratrska Podporujici Jednota (Czecho-Slavonic Fraternal and Benevolent Union); K. Studnicka of the Mistni Svaz (Local Federation) of Town of Lake; Frantisek Krupar of the Local Federation [of Bohemian Freethinkers] of Cicero, Illinois. [The article includes a list of <pb facs="5418478_7_0696.jpg" n="2"/>those members who were absent from this meeting and had not excused themselves.] The following bodies were not represented by their delegates: Cesko-Slovanska Jednota (Czecho-Slavonic Union); Cesko-Americka Jednota (Bohemian-American Union); Jednota Taboritu (Taborites); Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Bohemian Sisterhood); Mistni Svaz Svazu Svobodomyslnych v Chicagu (Chicago Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers).</p>
   <p>The minutes of the previous meeting were approved as read, as were the minutes of the last meetings of the organization committees. The reading of correspondence followed. A letter was read from the Local Federation of Town of Lake in which the complete roster of all their members was given, together with the correct names of their officers. This local organization also suggested in its letter that news concerning the American free thought movement be sent to the periodical Volna Myslenka (Free Thought) in Czechoslovakia. The news should be sent by the State Federation or by the Supreme <pb facs="5418478_7_0697.jpg" n="3"/>Council of the Federation. After a brief debate it was agreed that such news be sent to preclude any possibility of the home country receiving erroneous information about our movement here. This often happens when individuals posing as freethinkers send information to the homeland without being in any way identified with our organization. The secretary was entrusted with this duty of sending news to the homeland and ordering periodicals there-from which would throw more light upon the movement there, particularly as regards the anticlerical movement.</p>
   <p>An invoice presented by the [Chicago] periodical, Spravedlnost (Justice), was ordered paid. A letter from Frantisek Kovar and Frantisek Svoboda of Cleveland was, after an exchange of views, declared to be contrary to the principles of free thought. Since the letter deals with the president of the Velko-Vybor (Supreme Council [of the Federation]) it was decided to refer it to that body.</p>
   <p>The reading of reports followed. The secretary reported on the activities in <pb facs="5418478_7_0698.jpg" n="4"/>Cicero, Illinois. He attended the meeting of the [local] organization there, and believes that the activities of that body will improve in the future because the propaganda in the last protest meeting was rather active. He was of the opinion that activities always improve when a member of the national body pays a visit to local federations and speaks a few encouraging words to the members of such federations. He made some detailed reports on the work of the organization committees which refer their work to the members of the state committee due to the fact that the members of the Supreme Council never attend any such meetings. He touched upon the importance of propaganda work in all public protest meetings, claiming that whenever and wherever such propaganda takes place, people immediately start actions to sever their church memberships.</p>
   <p>The secretary's report and his views led to a lively debate, and this, in turn, led to a decision to start the most effective propaganda work in the next general protest meeting, that propaganda to be made both by means of press publicity and by announcements in club and society meetings. The <pb facs="5418478_7_0699.jpg" n="5"/>program of the [next general protest] meeting is to be most carefully worked out. The secretary is to take charge of this work and the rest of the members are to help him as much as possible. The Supreme Council is to be advised by letter about attending the meetings of the organization committee.</p>
   <p>The president reported on the last lecture which was given in [the crematory assembly hall] of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery). According to his report the attendance at that lecture was good. He also presented the lecturer's and the organist's bills which were approved and ordered paid. He expressed his opinion as to these lectures, suggesting that they be discontinued this year because there is other work confronting us. His suggestion is to be followed. The management of the cemetery will be sent a letter of thanks for their kind co-operation.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Zeman, who was present in the meeting, also received the thanks [of the <pb facs="5418478_7_0700.jpg" n="6"/>organization] for the trouble she took in drilling the children on the various occasions of our public functions. Two of the pupils who gave recitations on the last occasion of this sort are to be given souvenir gifts.</p>
   <p>The delegate of the Local Federation of Cicero reported that due to the indifference of certain officers no meetings were held; conditions improved, however, by the Local Federation's gaining two good workers recently--the vice-president, who was on a visit to Bohemia, and the teacher, Mr. Vasku. The reporting delegate also expressed the hope that some aid would be given the Cicero organization by the Ceskoslovensky Poplatnicky Spolek (Czechoslovak Taxpayers Association [of Cicero, Illinois]) which is one of the strongest organizations in that community, and which will surely not permit the danger which threatens Cicero, there is, the erection of a Bohemian Catholic school, to become a reality.</p>
   <p>The delegate from Town of Lake reported that besides a protest meeting, for which the members are doing extensive propaganda work, the Delnicka Dramaticka <pb facs="5418478_7_0701.jpg" n="7"/>Jednota ([Bohemian] Workingmen's Dramatic Association) will give a play on November 5, 1922. The Town of Lake local is also organizing classes in public speaking. Financially they are well off, and the whole sum of their activities is satisfactory.</p>
   <p>The report of the absent Chicago delegate was delivered by the secretary. The report stated that besides preparing for a protest meeting, a series of lectures is being prepared and will be delivered in various halls. The voting on motions made at the conference was favorable with the exception of three votes which opposed the publication of a weekly periodical.</p>
   <p>The delegate of the Supreme Council reported that in its last meeting the Council discussed the convention of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky and our views concerning the selection of delegates [to that convention]. A lively debate followed this report, and it was finally agreed that the Supreme Council be asked to call a joint meeting of both committees.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0702.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>[Translator's note: The committees are not specified but I suspect that the committee of the Supreme Council and another of the State Federation would be the natural groups in this instance.] The high-ranking officers of our movement are to be invited to this joint meeting to deal with the whole situation [of the movement] as it affects our public life.</p>
   <p>The meeting adjourned.</p>
   <p>Frantisek Strunc, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
