<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-08-04">Aug. 4, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Meeting of the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0888</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0888.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-08-04">Aug. 4, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE MEETING OF THE SBOR CESKEHO NARODNIHO HRBITOVA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular monthly meeting of the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova (Bohemian National Cemetery Association of Chicago) was called to order by the vice-chairman, Mr. J. Ringl, last night at eight o'clock, at the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies' Hall. The chairman arrived later. The secretary, Mr. Victor H. Filip, read the minutes of the previous meeting which were approved without correction. The reading of bills received during the month of July followed, and all the bills were ordered paid.</p>
   <p>The reading of communications by the secretary then followed. The Svobodna Obec (Bohemian Free Thought Community) in its communication asks the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova for co-operation and for the outline of a program which would be presented at the unveiling of a memorial plaque at a celebration in honor of the late free thought lecturer and orator, Frantisek B. Zdrubek--the first to advocate the establishment of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery). The celebration is to be held Sunday, <pb facs="5418478_7_0889.jpg" n="2"/>September 11, at two o'clock in the afternoon, in the main hall of the crematorium. In this letter the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova is also requested to lend the hall for that purpose.</p>
   <p>The George Washington Lodge No.66 of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies of America sends invitations and admission tickets to its forty-first anniversary celebration which will be held in connection with the unveiling of the picture of the first president of the United States. It was accepted and taken into consideration.</p>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Placek, president of the Americka Obec Sokolska (American Sokol Union) acknowledges the receipt of valuable papers amounting to eleven thousand dollars and which were deposited and held by the treasurer of the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova as collateral for a loan made by the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova to the Americka Obes Sokolska. The loan was recently repaid.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0890.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Smejkal announced the maturity of bonds amounting to $14,782.50 and further asked permission for the laying of new water pipe extensions in a new section which is being prepared for use. It was approved.</p>
   <p>The chairman called the attention of the delegates to the annual inspection of the cemetery which is to be held this Sunday. At the same time he did not forget the reporters of the Bohemian daily newspapers and invited them to attend. They all promised to be there.</p>
   <p>The delegate, Mr. Masek, then took the floor and called attention to the significant celebration of the unveiling of the memorial plaque of Frantised B. Zdrubek and requested that a speaker be selected for this occasion. The chairman replied that the orator of the Svobodna Obec, Mr. Vaclav Petrzelka, is above all others qualified to be a speaker at this celebration. The delegate, Mr. Zrust, having only the best of intentions, brought up the matter of buying a piece of land from the Ceska Utulna a <pb facs="5418478_7_0891.jpg" n="4"/>Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage) and asked if any letter regarding this matter was received. Replying to the question of the chairman, the secretary and the superintendent of the cemetery stated that they had not received anything. The delegate, Mr. Vaclav Cipra, moved that the debate regarding this matter be ended. The delegate, Mr. Spousta, then asked if it was true that the wages of the men who are employed by the cemetery had been reduced by ten cents an hour. Mr. Smejkal denied that it was so, but at the same time admitted that the men who were recently hired cannot expect the same rate of pay as the men who are experienced. Mr. Spousta was satisfied with this explanation.....</p>
   <p>Receipts for the month of July amounted to $39,926.08; cash on hand from last month, $24,767.86; total receipts, $64,693.94. Expenditures for the month totaled $36,694.72. cash on hand, $27,999.22.</p>
   <p>During the month of July there were one hundred and nineteen burials and twelve cremations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0892.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Inasmuch as there was no other business on hand the meeting was adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
