<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-09-16">Sept. 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Protestants and the Czech National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary from the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1050</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1050.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-09-16">Sept. 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH PROTESTANTS AND THE CZECH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary from the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Czech Evangelical Union in its last conference resolved to form a body within its own organization which is to devote its time exclusively to the aim of liberating the old homeland......Its activities will in no way interfere with the work done by the Czech National Alliance, since no one can become a member without simultaneously belonging to the Czech National Alliance.....</p>
   <p>A proclamation to this effect was issued: "Because the Czech National Alliance with which we have been co-operating since its beginnings needs help at this serious time from every possible agency, we are about to found the Straz Svobody Ceskoslovenskych Americkych Protestantu, to which we give the English name Liberty Guard of the American Czecho-Slovak <pb facs="5418478_7_1051.jpg" n="2"/>Protestants. This is a merger of all Protestant churches to which Bohemians and Slovaks belong. This new group is to induce all the adherents of their creeds, American or foreign, to take an active part in the movement for the liberation of the old homeland. At the same time request that two members of our new organization be accepted in the executive committee of the Czech National Alliance. The provisional executive committee, which is to introduce the Liberty Guard into its new sphere of activity, is composed of four of our brethren, elected to that office in the twelfth conference of the Evangelical Union. They are: Reverend Joseph Bren, D. D., Reverend Vaclav Vanek, D. D., V. Cejnar, and Joseph Krenek."....The original proclamation issued at the Evangelical conference was signed by Reverend Bren, Reverend Vanek, and M. Votava.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
