<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-05">Oct. 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Regular Meeting of the Board of Delegates to the Bohemian National Cemetery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0715</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0715.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-05">Oct. 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">REGULAR MEETING OF THE BOARD OF DELEGATES TO THE BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting of the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova (board of delegates to the Bohemian National Cemetery) was opened at the usual hour by the president, Mr. Jan Pecha. The secretary, Mr. V. H. Filip, read the minutes of the previous meeting which were approved as read. The receipts and disbursements for the month of September were as follows: Receipts, $13,187.72; disbursements, $12,981,91; balance, $205.81. Fourteen cemetery lots were sold for a total of $3,436.50. One urn was sold for $58. There were seventy-seven burials and one cremation. The sum of $953.95 was turned over to the reserve fund. The payroll for the month of September was $7,733.11. The secretary then read the minutes of the last annual inspection tour of the Hrbitov; these, were approved as read. The minutes were a sort of survey of the activities for the year of our national enterprise, of which our Free Thought countrymen may justly be proud. The delegates who were absent on the day <pb facs="5418478_7_0716.jpg" n="2"/>the inspection was made could get any information relating to the Hrbitov from these minutes. Since this newspaper reported on the inspection in great detail, it will not be necessary to make any further mention of it here.</p>
   <p>The financial secretary, Mr. Kozak, submitted the bills for the month of September; all of these were found correct and ordered paid.</p>
   <p>Then followed the reading of correspondence. The most important letter was from the Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani (Council on Higher Education). The letter enclosed a circular in which support is asked by the Council. It was decided to make a contribution to the Council when the Sbor sends out gifts probably at the beginning of the new year. The next communication was a letter of thanks from the Narodni Jednota Posumavska; (National Union of the Bohemian Forest). The 10,000 Czechoslovak crowns sent by the Sbor to the Jednota were received on May 16, 1922. The Jednota, in recognition of this gift, sent a receipt to the Sbor. The business manager of the Utulna a Sirotcinec</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0717.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>(Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage) asked the Sbor for a gift of flowers for the graves of two inmates of the Utulna. This was done previously.....</p>
   <p>The Utulna will give a concert on November 1, 1922, in the Pilsen Park pavilion. Since the concert is to be given for the benefit of the institution itself, the Sbor was requested to donate some fresh cut flowers. The request was granted. The Druzina Ceskoslovenskych Legionaru (local group of Czechoslovak Legionnaires) sent a letter of thanks for the erection of two tombstones on the graves of two Legionnaires who had no relatives or friends to perform that last service for them.....The Moravska Utulna Zenska v Brne (Moravian Old Women's Home at Brno, [Czechoslovakia]) sent a letter of thanks for a gift of 4,000 Czechoslovak crowns to be used for the building of their new home. This letter, although addressed to the board of directors of Ceskoslovenska Americka Obchodni Komora (Czechoslovak-American Chamber of Commerce), really belonged to tbe Sbor, since it was that organization that made the gift.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0718.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>There was a discussion concerning the authority of the board of directors of the Hrbitov; someone made a motion to the effect that that board sanction the gifts of flowers made by the board of delegates. It was decided that it is the latter board and not the board of directors that has the authority to make such gifts.....The general public is to be informed about this, and no organization or individual is to feel disappointed if requests for gifts of flowers are not granted by the board of directors. Delegate J. Smejkal pointed out that according to present practice the treasurer makes out all checks. He insisted that this should be changed as follows: All future checks are to be made out by the financial secretary, signed by the president, and endorsed by the accountant. This does not imply distrust but is only to be regarded as the modern way of conducting business. The modern way is more reliable than the old. It was decided, consequently, that all checks be signed by the three mentioned officials, and the new system will go into effect on January 1, 1923.</p>
   <p>The president, Mr. Pecha, made a report on his trip to Bohemia which was made <pb facs="5418478_7_0719.jpg" n="5"/>under the auspices of the Czechoslovak-American commercial expedition. Although he had made some mention of his work on the occasion of the annual inspection of the cemetery, he stated again that the $500, which the board granted him for any charitable work which he might wish to do while in Czechoslovakia, was divided among certain deserving institutions.....He also reported that he could not accede to the wishes of the board in dividing the money among the Free Thought organizations only, since there are very few of such organizations in Czechoslovakia. He gave 4,000 Czechoslovak crowns to the Slovak library, his argument for doing so being that there are many Slovaks here in Chicago who support the Bohemian National Cemetery. To the Brnenska Utulna (Old People's Home at Brno) he gave 1,500 Czechoslovak crowns. (The secretary read a clipping from the Prague newspaper, Narodni Politika (National Politics), in which mention was made of this last gift, and the clipping served also as a receipt.) The same Narodni Politika article mentioned all the other institutions which received gifts from the Hrbitov through Mr. Pecha; no receipts were needed therefore. The delegates unanimously approved Mr. Pecha's distribution of the sum.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0720.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Delegate J. Jelinek asked the Sbor to approve the perpetual care of the grave of the unfortunate journalist, Avenarius. This matter was referred to the board of directors. [Translator's note: See article titled "A Promenade Through the City of the Dead" in a September, 1922, issue of this newspaper.]</p>
   <p>The following persons and organizations paid for the perpetual care of graves: Mrs. Emilie Zuska $200; Mrs. Rose Sacha $200; Mr. Josef Zub $100. For the temporary care of the grave of Frantiska Soldat, the Karlin Lodge No. 111 of the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Bohemian Ladies' Union) paid $50.</p>
   <p>Delegate Kroc recommended that steps be taken to prevent certain unseemly conduct of some individuals whose expressions are highly censurable. Thus, for instance, at a recent burial of a Bohemian woman, a certain Baptist minister said that "he who does not believe in God is a scoundrel".....The delegates were of the opinion that such and similar statements should not be tolerated. A recommendation made by a member of the Sbor was endorsed by <pb facs="5418478_7_0721.jpg" n="7"/>the rest of the delegates. All funeral orators and others assisting at burial rites will be warned that this being a Free Thought cemetery, certain forms must be respected.</p>
   <p>The meeting adjourned at about 10 P. M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
