<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-11-14">Nov. 14, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A Special Meeting of Representatives of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1219</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1219.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-11-14">Nov. 14, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A SPECIAL MEETING OF REPRESENTATIVES OF THE CESKY NARODNI HRBITOV</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A special meeting of the board of representatives of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) was held in the hall of the Cesko-Anglicka Svobodomyslna Skola (Bohemian-English Free Thought School) at 18th and May Streets last night. The meeting was called to discuss a report submitted by the crematorium committee some time ago. The report is of sufficient interest to warrant publication in full. The committee makes the following recommendations:</p>
   <p>1. Build the crematorium so that it would be connected with the present chapel. This would be in compliance with the wishes of some of the representatives and of the public, and would make it possible to conduct funerals in accordance with the methods in use at the present time.</p>
   <p>2. The cost of the crematorium should not exceed $35,000, which sum is to <pb facs="5418478_7_1220.jpg" n="2"/>include the cost of building three incinerators and reshaping, lowering, and landscaping the terrace in front of the chapel.</p>
   <p>3. Appoint a committee consisting of Messrs. Ringl, Smejkal, and Dobias to investigate the question of gas, a fuel which should be used because of its purity and cleanliness. The committee should particularly inquire about the most efficient way to bring gas to the cemetery and contact the gas company for any useful information the board should have in this respect.</p>
   <p>4. In order to avoid any possible trouble, a contest of plans should be held with the following prizes: First prize, awarding of the contract; second prize, $100; third prize, $75.</p>
   <p>5. Explain to our expert, Mr. Rusy, the wishes and ideas of the board and have him prepare a simple sketch of the whole project which could be submitted as a guide to architects who enter the contest. Indicate the company which will supply the incinerators. Pay Mr. Rusy for the work he has done so far <pb facs="5418478_7_1221.jpg" n="3"/>for the board.</p>
   <p>6. Install chimes in the crematorium, somewhat on the order of those used by the neighboring cemetery.</p>
   <p>A lively debate about each proposal ensued and showed a wide divergence of opinion among the representatives.....</p>
   <p>Definite decisions will be made when the board has all necessary information concerning each point in question.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
