<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-23">May 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Convention of Bohemian-Slavonic Evangelical Faiths</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1150</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1150.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-23">May 23, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">CONVENTION OF BOHEMIAN-SLAVONIC EVANGELICAL FAITHS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The proceedings of the Second Interdenominational Convention of all Cesko-Slovanske Evangelicke Cirkve ve Spojenych Statech (Bohemian-Slavonic Evangelical Faiths in the United States) were opened with a prayer led by the Reverend F. T. Bastel. At 9:30 in the morning, the convention was called to order by the temporary chairman, Reverend Vaclav Vanek, and the following gentlemen were elected to office: Chairman, Vaclav Vanek; first vice-chairman, Reverend E. Vrbitsky from Silver Lake, Minnesota; second vice-chairman, Reverend V. Kralicek from Chicago; secretary, Reverend V. Dudycha from Chicago; and recording secretaries, Reverend K. J. Sladek, Crete, Nebraska; and the Reverend A. J. Moncol, Holdingford, Minnesota.</p>
   <p>The following visitors were introduced to the participants in this convention: Dr. Chas. I. Edwards and wife of Iowa City, Iowa; Professor O. C. Graner, <pb facs="5418478_7_1151.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago; Dr. Anderson and Dr. C. J. McConnell, both of Chicago.</p>
   <p>As to the need of an official organ representative of the Bohemian Evangelical faiths, the following gentlemen presented their personal views: Vaclav Hlavatv, Cedar Rapids, Iowa; Jan Prucha, Cleveland, Ohio; and K. J. Sladek, Crete, Nebraska.</p>
   <p>After a debate on this question,....a committee was chosen to take further action in reference to the official organ and bookselling business, and the following gentlemen were named: Reverend Jan Prucha, Mr. Alois Vokoun, Reverend K. J. Sladek, Reverend Josef Bren, Reverend Pisek, Reverend Vaclav Vanek, and the Reverend Kralicek. By next Saturday this committee is to have ready a detailed report on the proposals for an official organ and a book-selling establishment.</p>
   <p>The secretary read a letter sent by the chairman of the general assembly of <pb facs="5418478_7_1152.jpg" n="3"/>the Presbyterian faith, now in session in Chicago, in which the chairman stated that the convention adopted the following resolution, which we present in translation:</p>
   <p>"Being informed of the convention of our Bohemian and Slovak brothers now in session in Chicago from May 21 to May 25, inclusive, our general assembly of all Preshyterian faiths in the United States hereby expresses its interest and concern in your Slavonic convention and in the work of our dear Slavonic fellow citizens. We, too, want to take an active part with you in the celebrations commemorating your great countryman and religious leader, John Huss, on July 6, 1915.</p>
   <p>"We hope that your meeting will be a great event for all of you and also for us, because we want to go along with you in your work for a higher and purer life and a true brotherly love.</p>
   <p>"Yours in brotherly love,</p>
   <p>"A. J. Shrever."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1153.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This resolution of our American brothers was accepted with great applause, and the resolutions committee was ordered to send a reply thanking the general assembly of the Presbyterian faith.</p>
   <p>Brother F. Horalek delivered an address about the proposed establishment of the Evangelical Slavonic Publishing Company, and he cited from his rich experiences how such an organization could be formed. After a debate in which many of the brothers took part, it was agreed to send Brother Horalek's recommendations to the resolutions committee. It was also agreed by the assembly that the resolutions committee thank the Denni Hlasatel for the interest it has shown in our convention. The session was then adjourned with a prayer.</p>
   <p>The afternoon meeting was called to order at 2 o'clock, again with song and prayer, led by the Reverend V. Kralicek. The members agreed to ask the <pb facs="5418478_7_1154.jpg" n="5"/>brother delegate, Reverend Miller of New York, who is an American, and who out of sympathy with us has learned the Bohemian language, to speak to us; and Miss Elizabeth Davis was also requested to address the assembly. Miss Davis is an American, and is the manager of the Slavonic Mission School for Girls at Uniontown, Pennsylvania. She was introduced and spoke very well in Bohemian.</p>
   <p>The convention members were really astonished by the accomplishments of Reverend Miller and Miss Davis and value their friendship deeply. These two respected members of ours, in their intercourse with their many American friends, can create a feeling of respect for the Slav foreigner. When these two spoke, many delegates cried with joy--such is the power of love for one another when applied with the help of God.</p>
   <p>The following gentlemen were elected to serve on the resolutions committee:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1155.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Messrs. Krenek, Hlad, Musil, Dudycha, and Zavodsky.....</p>
   <p>How the Slovak Protestants should celebrate the five-hundredth anniversary of John Huss was explained by the Reverend Pisek of New York. The speaker with his customary pithy delivery, grouped his address address around the following points: 1. Work more energetically for Christ and our nation. 2. Let us being to prepare for the celebration this year to the best of our abilities. 3. Arrange outdoor encampments in the country and in the cities, and thus reach everyone to whom our Huss is dear. 4. Invite the best men of each state to work along with us--those who would lay stress upon freedom of thought, which was defended by our Huss. 5. At our lectures use stereopticon views or moving pictures depicting the life of Huss. 6. Sing! We are a nation of singers, and the song "Kdo Jste Bozi Bojovnici" (You Who Are God's Warriors), or Huss's own song, "Jezu Kriste Stredry Kneze" (Jesus Christ, Bountiful Priest), will prove to all listeners just what Huss was. 7. Support all countrymen who honor Huss at their celebrations. Everyone evaluates <pb facs="5418478_7_1156.jpg" n="7"/>Huss from his own standpoint and honors him accordingly, and we in turn as Hussites follow him in his teachings, and so inform the public. 8. Distribute literature relating to the life of Huss. 9. Let us not be afraid of pictures! The great teacher, Jan Amos Komensky, whom in all justice we call our own, recommends the use of pictures from life for life! 10. Boldly proclaim that Huss is all ours! Work among our denominations now, and do not wait until the last minute. 11. Arrange a trip to Bohemia in the year 1915, and go in a body.</p>
   <p>"Let us not forget," said Dr. Pisek, "that every pilgrim from America will testify his love for the old country. The last and the most weighty point of how to commemorate the life of Huss is to build up a great Huss Evangelical central unit in this congress since the one Christ, by his love, brings us closer to one another and to our master, John Huss. Let us get together to commemorate his life! Let us make Huss's work our work.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1157.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>"I see," said Dr. Pisek in conclusion, "a new era of our Slavonic Zion in America, and it is not far away if each of us becomes a ray of light emanating from the character and moral purity of Huss."</p>
   <p>The oration of Dr. Pisek was received with great applause, after which a ten-minute recess was announced.</p>
   <p>After the recess, Reverend Vaclav Vanek spoke of the immigration and colonization questions, and proposed that a list of all Slavonic denominations be given to immigrants when they arrive at the various ports of entry.</p>
   <p>After a debate, it was agreed to have such a list published.</p>
   <p>With a prayer by the Reverend Sladek, the afternoon meeting was brought to a close.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
