<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-16">July 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czechs at Bastille Day Celebration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0065</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0065.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-16">July 16, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHS AT BASTILLE DAY CELEBRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In recent years, the celebration of the anniversary of the storming of the Bastille has been the occasion for a large gathering of friends of the French people, in the Pilsen Brewery Park, each July 14. This park is located between the preponderantly Czech districts called "California" and "Plzen" (Pilsen).....</p>
   <p>A group of Sokols stood in the rear of a platform. They were headed by Mr. Paskovsky, and they had expected to be called on to perform....."They were not asked to give an exhibition, but we think they themselves should have offered their contribution to the entertainment.....The Sokols want to co-operate; they never forget their friends who are fighting for the independence of their country....."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0066.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The arrangements committee, the representatives of the Czech National Alliance and of the Czech newspapers, and their guests had dinner together. There were about five hundred persons in the dining room; a second dinner had to be served for the rest of the crowd.....</p>
   <p>"We Czechs had a very pleasant conversation with our allies; at our table there were four Czechs, three Frenchmen, two Italians, one Belgian, two Americans, and one Swiss. The World War was the chief topic; French and Italian were chiefly spoken. The instant introductions were over, and our friends learned that we were Czechs, their eyes filled with tears and they grasped our hands--Czechs? Why, you were the first to come to our aid!' one of them exclaimed in English. One of the Czechs said a few words of thanks in the French language. This evoked an outburst of enthusiastic questioning. Our representative was compelled to give all sorts of detailed information about the Czechs. This animated conversation was carried on, even after we moved to make room for other diners; <pb facs="5418478_7_0067.jpg" n="3"/>our representatives were then introduced to Mr. Barthelmy, French consul in Chicago, and to other members of the local French colony.</p>
   <p>"Night was drawing near when we Czechs, numbering about fifty, sat in the garden, eagerly awaiting the columns of Sokols, who were to assemble at the hall of the Havlicek Tyrs Sokol Gymnastic Society, at Lawndale Avenue and 26th Street, and who were expected to appear here in an impressive parade. We were, alas, disappointed.--Did our people forget? They failed to heed the appeal issued in our daily papers. They did not arrive!</p>
   <p>We had anticipated that there would be more of our countrymen than there were last year, when three hundred participated; we thought there would be at least six hundred. On the contrary, there was just a handful."</p>
   <p>Those who had assembled at the Sokol Hall joined the others, who were <pb facs="5418478_7_0068.jpg" n="4"/>sitting in the garden, and they marched into the pavilion where the invited guests, led by the French and the Belgian consuls, had occupied the platform, and where also Mr. R. Jaroslav Psenka appeared as official representative and speaker for the Czech National Alliance and the Czech-Americans in general. He was introduced by the chairman as follows:</p>
   <p>"The Czechs are among the small nations who have suffered most from unjust treatment by the Prussians; their nation has a glorious history, and their volunteers were the first to fight for France, trusting that she would help them win independence for their old homeland." These words drew thunderous applause, and shouts of praise and enthusiasm for the Czechs.</p>
   <p>Mr. Psenka, in a short address, which he delivered in the French language, <pb facs="5418478_7_0069.jpg" n="5"/>defined the political attitude of the Czechs, declaring that the place of the Czechs is on the Allies' side, and that his nation has formed an army which is fighting on the battlefields in Russia. He solicited the good will of France, entreating her to intercede in behalf of Czech liberty....and closed by acclaiming France with a mighty 'Vive La France!'" These words were reverberated by hundreds of voices throughout the hall.</p>
   <p>After several other speeches had been given, the Czechs present rallied, and proceeded to take part as a body in a parade through the dance hall. About two hundred gathered; they hastily procured a red and white flag, the Czech colors, and then succeeded in executing a demonstrative parade which wound up before the French and the Belgian consuls, to the tune of French music, followed by the Czech national anthem "Hej Slovane" (Hail, All Ye Slavonic Peoples!). By this manifestation the Czechs were able to testify to their sympathies for the Allies.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0070.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The success of the dignified celebration will materially contribute to funds for the relief of wounded French soldiers.</p>
   <p>"We admit having been guilty of an omission which will be marked by France. We should have begun to agitate for a manifestation one month previous to the event, for, just as we do not forget the Fourth of July, we should feel duty-bound to remember the observance of the Fourteenth of July--the Bastille celebration. Let us hope that on the next Fourteenth of July we shall celebrate the defeat of Germany, for it will bring liberty to the Czechs. In that way we shall make amends for our failing."</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: This item is an ordinary report interspersed with editorial comment--a "semi-editorial", frequently met with in Bohemian papers.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
