<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-12-08">Dec. 8, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">New Years Gifts Granted for Welfare Purposes by the Delegates of the Bohemian National Cemetery Association Amounted to $2,575</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1236</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1236.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-12-08">Dec. 8, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">NEW YEARS GIFTS GRANTED FOR WELFARE PURPOSES BY THE DELEGATES OF THE BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY ASSOCIATION AMOUNTED TO $2,575</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1, Col.5--The regular meeting which was held last night was brought to order by the chairman Mr. Pech. Mr. Halik, the secretary, then read the minutes of the previous meeting, which were accepted without correction. After the reading of bills against the organization, which were ordered paid, communications were read, from the Bohemian Liberal School Association of Irving Park which asks that it be remembered with a gift in order to lessen the expenditure on the building of a new school-building. In a further communication this organization expressed thanks for the gift of flowers. The National Slovak School Board also asks for a contribution for it's school. The Association of Delegates for the Saturday and Sunday schools requests that the Cemetery Association remember the schools with a gift.</p>
   <p>Vek Rozumu, a liberal-minded Bohemian monthly, announces it's organization and asks for a contribution. After communications had been read, newly elected delegates were inducted. Reports of committees were then heard Mr. Smejkal announced before the management committee, that the expense <pb facs="5418478_7_1237.jpg" n="2"/>sheet was large owing to the installation of ditches and many other special jobs. Further he announced that the Recorders Office requests the recording of individual lots. As a result, new plans will have to be prepared, requiring the expenditure of about $300.</p>
   <p>Chairman Mr. Pech, reports from the meeting of the directors of their recommendation for a new year's gift of $2,000 to the schools and $500 to the Old Peoples Home. For other welfare purposes according to the decision of the delegates. According to these recommendations $2,000 was granted for the schools and $500 for the "Home." The Bohemian Charitable Association and the Central School Association were given $25 each. In the case of the school board of the Slovak Schools a like sum was granted.</p>
   <p>Receipts were $5,776.19, disbursements $5,748.32. The meeting then adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
