<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-09-27">Sept. 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Big Rally of Roman Catholics</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1041</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1041.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-09-27">Sept. 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">BIG RALLY OF ROMAN CATHOLICS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night's session of the twenty-fourth general conference of the Czech Roman Catholic First Central Union was opened by a holy mass chanted by Reverend P. M. Cerveny. Debates on changing the statutes took up the first hours.</p>
   <p>A communication from the National Alliance of Czech Catholics was the next subject on the program. It was received at a previous session and contained an invitation to the First Central Union to join in the movement for the liberation of Czech lands. A respective resolution was passed:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, We live in a time which in its magnitude and immense importance has not been equalled in history--a time which makes us witness to a most terrible struggle; on one side there are the free nations striving to secure <pb facs="5418478_7_1042.jpg" n="2"/>liberty for their present and future generations and also for the small nations, helpless and oppressed for many centuries; on the other side of the struggle are nations ruled by autocrats who are bent on expanding their power in order to subjugate the free nations and subject those whom they overwhelm by violence to cruel treatment; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, The protagonists of liberty have been joined by the United States, our new homeland where we have been received with kindness and accorded freedom and the same rights enjoyed by those whose forebears helped to make this country free;</p>
   <p>Whereas, These United States have proclaimed through Wilson, their great President, that they entered the war not only because of the danger threatening their own liberty but also to win independence for the small nations who are now ruled against their will; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, The Czechs, whose liberation from three hundred years of thralldom <pb facs="5418478_7_1043.jpg" n="3"/>is our most cherished hope, are also among them; and further,</p>
   <p>Whereas, We American Czechs have, in this moment which is so crucial for our people, joined hands to help them win their fondest wish--freedom; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, We have placed this task into the hands of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America, an organization which is discharging its duties in the most honorable manner; therefore be it</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we who are assembled here in the twenty-fourth conference and celebrating the fortieth anniversary of the Czech Roman Catholic First Central Union in the United States of America, solemnly proclaim our loyalty to our new homeland, the United States. We further declare that we are ready to give our lives for the protection of our new homeland; and be it further</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we proclaim that we are in favor of establishing an independent Czechoslovak state. We commend the work done in this direction by the National <pb facs="5418478_7_1044.jpg" n="4"/>Alliance of Czech Catholics.....</p>
   <p>In closing, we are addressing ourselves to the Holy Father, Pope Benedict XV, praying that he may use his great influence in favor of our distressed old homeland.</p>
   <p>Chicago, September 26, 1917. Signed: Peter M. Cerveny, Jan [John] Straka, Joseph W. Bartunek, John Kahoun, Frank J. Sebek. We represent the committee on resolutions."</p>
   <p>The question of death benefits of members enlisted for service in the Army was another problem for discussion. It was resolved by seventy-eight against eight votes to grant only one fifth of the regular death benefit to soldiers for the duration of their military service. After discharge from the Army or Navy, members will have to submit to a doctor's examination and, if found to be in acceptably good health, they will be reinstated with their initial death benefits without any additional dues. Those who do not pass the examination <pb facs="5418478_7_1045.jpg" n="5"/>will have to pay the proportional dues on one fifth of the death benefit.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Thomas J. Bobal succeeded in having a motion passed to the effect that the flag of Svaty Vaclav [St. Venceslas] which had been presented to the First Central Union by the First St. John Czech Catholic Society of Chicago was to be brought to St. Prokopius College where a history of that flag would be written. The Reverend Bobal then announced that the archiepiscopal consistory of Chicago had granted permission to the only Czech Roman Catholic bishop in the United States, the Very Reverend P. Koudelka of Superior, Wisconsin, to accept an invitation to chant Holy Mass and hold a sermon next Friday, St. Venceslas day, in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Last night's session was followed by a banquet arranged and provided for by the Cyril and Methodius community in its headquarters on Robey and 52nd Streets.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
