<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-13">Feb. 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Sokols at Disposal of the United States</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0559</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0559.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-13">Feb. 13, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SOKOLS AT DISPOSAL OF THE UNITED STATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The unified Sokol societies, whose official name is now "Ceska Sokolska Obec" (Czech Sokol Community), held its first constitutional meeting in the Pilsen Sokol hall last night. Jan Simon was elected head of the community. His election, as well as that of the other officials, was performed with unanimity.</p>
   <p>The community consists of five groups: the eastern, with New York as headquarters, the Chicago group, the western, with Omaha as the seat; the Pacific, with San Francisco as the seat; and the southern, with Dallas, Texas, as headquarters. Their legal incorporation will be enacted through Mr. Simon.</p>
   <p>One important resolution was passed which aims at rousing the Czech-American Sokols into an enthusiastic support of the United States in <pb facs="5418478_7_0560.jpg" n="2"/>case of war. An appeal to all members in the United States will be sent out, admonishing every able-bodied individual to hold himself in readiness for taking up arms, and help in the forming of Czech regiments at the disposal of the United States, and so serve the new homeland and the Czech nation abroad, as well.</p>
   <p>Representatives of the Pilsen district Sokols made the motion to name Mr. Frothingham, the generous New York sponsor of the Sokols, an honorary member of the Czech Sokol Community. The motion will be voted on by the entire membership of the Sokol organizations. A donation of $1,000 will be bestowed on the Narodni Sdruzeni, (Czech National Association) the amount may be raised to $2,000, if the respective motion by the Sokol Pilsen should carry. The Chicago group intends to hold a festival for the benefit of the Czech National Association.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
