<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-21">Apr. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Slim Change for a Czecho-Slovak Regiment</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Press Bureau Czech National Alliance)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1444</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1444.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-21">Apr. 21, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SLIM CHANGE FOR A CZECHO-SLOVAK REGIMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Press Bureau Czech National Alliance)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The highly promising movement, initiated in Chicago, which aimed at the formation of a Czecho-Slovak regiment at the disposal of the United Sates Army has been meeting with obstacles. Captain Franklin R. Kenney, United States Army, chief recruiting officer for the district comprising Chicago, after having repeatedly communicated with his superiors in Washington, received a telegram, Tuesday, in which he was informed of a change in the regulations of the War Department to the effect that no volunteers are to be accepted for service in the United States Army as a large group. The recruiting officers will be permitted to accept volunteers as a unit up to the number of one hundred; these may be assigned to one larger body, <pb facs="5418478_7_1445.jpg" n="2"/>but no guarantee is given that two kindred volunteer units will be incorporated in one and the same larger body.</p>
   <p>Captain Kenney elucidated the purport of this order to the Military Committee of the Ceske Narodni Sdruzeni [Czech National Alliance] as follows: Various civic organizations promised to furnish contingents, true enough, but recruiting progressed at an unduly slow pace. The War Department, therefore, accepts in principle individual volunteers only, and transfers them to units where needed.</p>
   <p>The representative of the Czech-Americans voiced his disappointment over the new order, and the fear that it might have a detrimental effect on the patriotic fervor of the Czechs in cooling off their enthusiasm for war activities. He simultaneously asked whether the Captain thought it <pb facs="5418478_7_1446.jpg" n="3"/>expedient to submit a request to the Department for excepting the Czechs from this order; he pointed to one hundred and twenty Czech volunteers who enlisted in Chicago within two days after the declaration of War. Captain Kenney readily recommended the proposed action. A respective petition was sent by the officers of the joint Committee on Military Affairs, all of whom are members of the Czech National Alliance or the Czech Sokol Community. The document was addressed to the Secretary of War and contained an additional item, that is, an offer by the Committee to open up and equip recruiting offices at no costs to the Department, similar to those in Chicago, New York, Baltimore, Cleveland, Cedar Rapids, Omaha, Dallas, St. Paul, San Francisco, and Portland. The Committee furthermore promises to do all in its power to create sentiment for enlistment among the Czech-Americans by lectures and newspaper publicity. All they ask is <pb facs="5418478_7_1447.jpg" n="4"/>the transfer of Czech-American volunteers to the one Czecho-Slovak regiment.</p>
   <p>Up to the moment when the War Department has decided upon the petition we are able to answer the manifold inquiries by counseling our boys, eager to fight for the just cause of the United States, to wait a few days. Meantime, the Committee for Military Affairs will lay out a program for united action. The fact remains, however, that instructions from Washington are subject to constant change, that the War Department has not arrived at fixed methods as yet, primarily because the President is not sure of the approval of his program by the Congress. We do not, however, want to dampen the patriotic spirit. We urge our men to enlist wherever circumstances favor these steps, and to combine into groups of one hundred, so that one Czech company is formed; others are to follow.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1448.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The committee on Military Affairs, will inform the public of all stages of this issue so important for us.</p>
   <p>For the joint Committee on Military Affairs, Adolph Vlk, president, J. F. Smetanka, corresponding secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
