<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-31">May 31, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Decoration Day Ceremonies at the Bohemian National Cemetery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0234</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0234.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-31">May 31, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">DECORATION DAY CEREMONIES AT THE BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thousands of people, young and old, were attracted to the beautiful Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) yesterday. Perhaps never before was the celebration so charming as yesterday, when the weather was so pleasantly cool, so ideal for awakening spring. The massive crowd of people could hear the speakers and the entire program of this phenomenal celebration without fatigue. Surely no other nationality could hold such a wonderful celebration. People began to gather at the cemetery early in the morning, and before the time set for the beginning of the ceremonies the spacious grounds of the cemetery were packed with people. They came to pay tribute to those lying there in perpetual sleep; to dedicate a grateful memory to those who laid down their lives for the abolition of slavery and the preservation of the Union.</p>
   <p>When the flower-laden parade arrived at the cemetery, Mr. John Pecha, president of the cemetery association, greeted the gathering with a sincere talk, <pb facs="5418478_7_0235.jpg" n="2"/>explaining the purpose of the celebration.</p>
   <p>Mr. Brousek's band then played a medley of Bohemian and American national airs, after which the first of the speakers, Judge A. Petit, was introduced. Judge Petit spoke as follows:....</p>
   <p>Mr. Pecha then introduced the next speaker, Dr. Frantisek Iska.</p>
   <p>The speeches were received with great enthusiasm.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Pecha thanked the gathering for its participation, and the celebration was concluded.</p>
   <p>The managing committee then entertained the speakers and press representatives at dinner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
