<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-05-30">May 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Unveiling Ceremonies at the Bohemian National Cemetery. Grand Bohemian-American Manifestation.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0310</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0310.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-05-30">May 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">UNVEILING CEREMONIES AT THE BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY. GRAND BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN MANIFESTATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 29th of May, 1892 will remain inscribed in golden letters in the history of Chicago Bohemians.</p>
   <p>On that day we were all united in one common thought and the enthusiasm for an accomplished work filled each one in whose bosom a Bohemian heart beat, whether a believer or free-thinker. It was a manifestation on the part of Chicago Bohemians, the effects of which must be felt even beyond the boundaries of our city. It proved that Bohemians do not come to this land merely to enjoy its freedom, - but that whenever the occasion requires it, they are willing to defend this freedom with their lives.</p>
   <p>An enormous crowd of people were present at yesterday's dedication, and the Bohemian people gave a practical answer to the American press for all the maligning which we have endured in recent years.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0311.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Even if we are not as strong numerically as other nationalities, still the American people must realize that the Bohemian element is one of the strongest pillars in the foundation of this republic.</p>
   <p>We shall not waste words as to why this monument to Bohemian veterans was erected at the National Cemetery. This was all clearly explained by the official speakers at yesterday's dedication. We will only remark that we performed our duty and carried it out honorably and with glory.</p>
   <p>To honor the memory of those who fought for the destruction of slavery, who fought for humanity is the duty of everyone, therefore, we honor the memory of those Bohemians who left their families and all that was dear to them and hastened to battle for the integrity of the union.</p>
   <p>Chicagoans understood the full meaning of yesterday's dedication and attended in large numbers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0312.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Whoever even feels himself a Bohemian hastened to the National Cemetery, to be present when the veil covering the monument was removed. The enthusiasm with which the speakers were greeted proved that they were not brought to the cemetery by mere curiosity, but truly by the love and respect for the memory of those for whom the monument was built.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
