<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-09-26">Sept. 26, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Last Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Festive Days of the Fuegner-Tyrs Group End with a Farewell Party</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0602</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0602.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-09-26">Sept. 26, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE LAST DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Festive Days of the Fuegner-Tyrs Group End with a Farewell Party</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A resolution was adopted by the convention, according to which fraternal contacts are to be established with all local units of the National Sokol Union, and likewise with the Sokols of other Slavonic nationalities. </p>
   <p>Because the festive program had been exhausted on Sunday, yesterday was dedicated to a tour of inspection of our city. Some of the guests moved about on their own, whereas others in the company of president of the Group, Sokol Dolezal, paid a visit to the Plzensky Sokol (Pilsen Sokol) at its headquarters at Ashland Avenue and Eighteenth Street, from whence they came directly to our establishment, where we enjoyed a pleasant visit with our guests. After inspecting our establishment, the guests went to the Cesko-Slovanska Podporujici Spolecnost (Czech-Slavonic Benevolent Society) hall, where the convention discussions were continued, <pb facs="5418478_7_0603.jpg" n="2"/>Brother Dolezal presiding. The planned publication of the organization journal received first attention. It was resolved to fix the assessment per member at five cents monthly, and a quarterly group assessment at ten cents per member, so that the total assessment per member will amount to one dollar per year. It was further resolved to pay the assessments due to the Ceska Obec Skolska (Czech Sokol Community) from the treasury of the Group. Sokol (brother) Cermak voiced the opinion that it would not be to the detriment of the Group if its members undertook steps for co-operation with the Narodni Jednota Sokolska (National Sokol Union). In the lengthy debate ensuing on this proposal, it was Sokol (brother) Zeman who protested most vigorously against acceptance of anything of this kind. The issue was finally cleared up by Sokol Kosar, who stood ardently for fraternal associations among sokol organizations, pointing out the many advantages resulting from such friendly approaches. Brother Kosar finally proposed a resolution whereby all sokol organizations are urged to get into closer contact. A respective resolution was passed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0604.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The independent administration by women Sokols was the next object of discussion, broached by the women's section of the Sokol Havlicek of Cleveland, Ohio. The motion could not be debated, as it was not presented in writing as required by the constitution of the Group. Sister Loula, of Sokol Pokrok, declared that the women do not insist upon independent administration, and the proposal was set aside. The convention was then adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
