<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-20">Apr. 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Sokol Girls Follow Example of the Men</title><title level="a" type="sub">Create New Red Cross Unit</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1449</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1449.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-20">Apr. 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SOKOL GIRLS FOLLOW EXAMPLE OF THE MEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">Create New Red Cross Unit</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Hardly had the vanguard of the Czech Legion left for Jefferson Barracks, in St. Louis, Mo., to be gradually supplemented by others of our Sokol brethren, than the Sokol Girls began taking up work to prove that they have grasped the importance of the War. Women can help materially. They can perform wonders, while the furies of war are raging everywhere.</p>
   <p>Sokol Girls met in the hall of the Havlicek-Tyrs Sokol [gymnastic society] last Wednesday to organize their own branch of the American Red Cross. A great number signed up for service as nurses, and pledged themselves to take up the medical course required by the Army regulations. Physicians, also members of Sokol societies, will act as instructors. The next meeting will <pb facs="5418478_7_1450.jpg" n="2"/>be held in the hall of the Sokol Chicago on April 25. The main program will be laid out by a Sokol leader and physician and submitted to the committee on military affairs with the consent of the Czech National Alliance. The nurses' course will conform with those conducted by the American Red Cross.</p>
   <p>The physician [name not given] who will be in charge of training the nurses had had wide experience as an organizer, teacher, hospital interne, and field surgeon as well. There will be several physicians assisting, and a number of trained nurses in addition. It is, therefore, to be expected that the new Red Cross Unit will accomplish very much, in fact more, than various clubs and societies who think that in this time of War, help can be extended by dances and entertainments only. The courses will comprise every detail of nursing from bandaging to hygiene, physiology, etc. Special attention will be given to the teaching of behavior in emergencies, such as explosions, air raids, etc., when cold-blooded action and reason count more than screaming and crying.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1451.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>All honor to our Sokol Girls for their noble intention. There is an initiation fee of two dollars; the tuition in the course is free. The work to be performed is absolutely up to the individual's good will. There will be no compulsion. As the task has been taken on voluntarily, it is a matter of course that the members will also gladly submit to a certain necessary discipline.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
