<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-20">May 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Minutes of the Plenary Meeting of the Bohemian Liberal School, Vojta Naprstek</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0625</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0625.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-20">May 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">MINUTES OF THE PLENARY MEETING OF THE BOHEMIAN LIBERAL SCHOOL, VOJTA NAPRSTEK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting of the Bohemian Liberal School was called to order by the chairman, Mr. Richard Dvsil. The minutes of the previous meeting were accepted as read. Messrs. Veprek and Loula, sent a communication in which they offered to donate effervescent beverages for the picnic. It was referred to the committee.</p>
   <p>The report of the committee on the concert cannot be made until the next meeting. The committee turned in one additional dollar as receipts of the theatrical of March 26. There is still due seventy-five cents. The school premises are to be rented without heat, in the month of May, unless conditions require it.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0626.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A bill of twenty-one dollars for rent, and five dollars for janitor service, was allowed. It was resolved that the ceremonial dedication of the new school building be held on July 9, and that all liberal societies be invited to participate in the ceremonies, and also take part in the parade. The conditions for the building manager were approved according to the committee's original recommendations, with the addition that the building manager be appointed each year. An advertisement is to be placed in the newspapers, seeking bids for the job, and the election of the successful applicant is to take place in the meeting on May 30. Notices of the meeting are to be mailed to the members.</p>
   <p>The matter of borrowing money from a Building and Loan society, or from a bank, for the building, is to be decided at that meeting. A loan of about $12,000 will be needed. The school committee is to pick up some school supplies from Mrs. Lukes, who is donating them to the school. Mrs. Hrych <pb facs="5418478_7_0627.jpg" n="3"/>announced that tuition received from the children is not to be remitted to the central body of the Associated Liberal Schools, according to a resolution of that body, but is to be kept by the various schools.</p>
   <p>It was also announced that the California Theatre, Trumball avenue and 26th Street, would give two performances, the proceeds of which will go toward the benefit of the school building fund.</p>
   <p>The receipts of this meeting were $127.00, and disbursements were $140.00. The meeting was then adjourned.</p>
   <p>Marie Stepanek,</p>
   <p>Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
