<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-15">Sept. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Graduation Exercises of 106 Bohemian Candidates for Citizenship</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1532</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1532.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-15">Sept. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">GRADUATION EXERCISES OF 106 BOHEMIAN CANDIDATES FOR CITIZENSHIP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night graduation exercises were held for 106 Bohemian candidates for citizenship. The event took place in the J. Sterling Morton High School assembly hall at 8 P. M., under the sponsorship of the active Poplatnik Czechoslovak Taxpayers' Association. This organization was instrumental in providing the necessary training for the candidates, without which it would be impossible for them to obtain the desired citizenship certificate. It is noteworthy that the instructors in this course were Professor Otto Duda and Miss Josefa Duda who with unwonted zeal and industry endeavored to convey the necessary information to the candidates. In this they were eminently successful according to the naturalization officer who praised the Bohemian people in general and the Bohemian candidates in particular, saying that they all deserved high grades [in the examination given by the naturalization department].</p>
   <p>The graduation committee in charge of the soiree consisted of Messrs. Frantisek Svoboda, a notary public of 5544 West 25th Street; H. Liberacky, Bohumil Walek, <pb facs="5418478_7_1533.jpg" n="2"/>P. Nudera, and J. Schneider. These gentlemen also provided an excellent entertainment which consisted of....music and speeches. There was an opening speech by Mr. M. Raab, superintendent of night schools, who explained the advantages of citizenship and complimented the candidates for their wishing to become citizens. Speeches were also made by Mr. Josef Z. Klenha, president of the Cicero community, and Mr. F. Righeimer, county judge. The Bohemian virtuoso, Mr. Jiri Hrusa, then played a solo and arias from Bedrich Smetana's "Prodana Nevesta" (Bartered Bride). The main item on the program of course was the awarding of diplomas to the graduates, and Mr. H. Church, the superintendent of schools, assisted by the instructors, presented them to the graduates....music followed, and the ceremony was ended. [List of persons receiving diplomas is omitted in translation.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
