<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-01">June 1, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Excerpt from Judge Cavanagh's Oration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0296</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0296.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-01">June 1, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">EXCERPT FROM JUDGE CAVANAGH'S ORATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1--"It is an uplifting and beautiful experience to see the representatives of so great a people congregated under these boughs and surrounded by these splendid flowers in the presence of the shades of our beloved dead, assembled to honor them in the name of this country of ours. It seems to me that this huge gathering has at least a two-fold significance. You are honoring this country of ours, and you are honoring the old country.</p>
   <p>"Do not think for a moment, my friends, that you are standing here alone. Do not think that our dead do not hear us. No; out of this multitude of graves rise the spirits of those who are dear to us, and they stand by your sides participating in your memorial ceremony. I say that you are honoring your country. What a beautiful heritage for us on this day, my friends! Remember the history of your own country, of your own people, and you will have a picture of this country, of the mightiest nation on earth.</p>
   <p>"Let us consider for a moment the reasons which gave rise to this commemoration. It is known to you how the armies of the North met the armies of <pb facs="5418478_7_0297.jpg" n="2"/>the South for the preservation of the Union. This great war war fought about forty years ago, and the men who took part in it are daily departing from this world; but the memory of their deeds will never die. It is hard to understand that this country was in great danger so short a time ago, that liberty was in danger of being lost to its ardent supporters, that the great battle of Gettysburg had just been fought, and that a terrible war was still going on.</p>
   <p>"We have among us a mighty race which has always stood at the head of the Slavonic nations, which has a great task before it, and of which I am glad to report that it is fulfilling its promises. The Czech gives ample return for what he receives from his new country. He is independent."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
