<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-13">Feb. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Conference of the Czech National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-13">Feb. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CONFERENCE OF THE CZECH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The conference of the Czech National Alliance, of which it may be fairly said that it drew the attention of all Slav-America and of all responsible workers for Czech independence in the old country, passed into history last night. Most of the American delegates are already on their way to their homes, to the sunny South, the far West or the Eastern States. They are surely leaving our Garden City with the proud feeling of having accomplished work that is going to be a steppingstone in the history of the Slav element in the United States.</p>
   <p>The last day's session was crowned with far-reaching and beautiful successes that excelled all expectations. The unification of the movement for Czechoslovak independence into one mighty action was realized. Three <pb facs="5418478_7_0471.jpg" n="2"/>bodies that had up to the present worked independently, were cemented into one. They are the Czech National Alliance, the National Alliance of Czech Catholics, and the Slovak League. According to carefully laid plans, these three organizations will from now on work under the directions of a single executive committee, and their financial action shall be placed on a common basis. There will be no difference between them any more. The lofty words of Svatopluk Cech, the poet, shall henceforth be their slogan: "For one sacred idea, for the sole idea...."</p>
   <p>The last meeting was a plenary session in the fullest sense of the word, for representatives of all three bodies, now combined, took part in it. This fact is of particular significance, since the main object of this meeting was the reorganization of these bodies. The Catholics were represented by Reverend J. Kestl, Reverend F. Jedlicka, Tomas Filas, Jan Straka, and others. For our brothers, the Slovaks, the representatives were Messrs. Mamatej, Jan Pankuch and others.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0472.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The question of the merging of the three bodies occupied the assembly all forenoon. It must be admitted that the discussion was a heated one. For the purpose of working out definite plans for the reorganization, a committee of sixteen had been formed. On this committee for the Czech National Alliance: were Professor Bohumil Simek, Messrs. E. V. Voska, F. J. Kubec, Dr. Ludwig Fisher, president of the Czech National Alliance, and Vojta Benes, the school teacher and organizer of the body. Dr. Fisher and Mr. Benes were present as ex officio members. The Catholic members of this committee were Hynek Dostal, newspaper editor, Reverend Zlamal, and Reverend Kestl. The Slovaks were represented by Albert Mamatej, Jan Pankuch, and six others.</p>
   <p>This committee faced the not too easy task of effecting the combination to the satisfaction of the elements they represented. The result had, at the same time, to be practical, based on amity and justice. Six main propositions were laid before it, of which one, that had been worked out by Mr. Jancek, <pb facs="5418478_7_0473.jpg" n="4"/>newspaper editor, was finally accepted by all members except Vojta Benes, who withheld his vote and motivated his action later. The motion passed by the committee reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Report of the organization committee for the creation of a common political organization of Czechs and Slovaks, submitted by Mr. Jancek.</p>
   <p>"1. The new organization is to be known by the name of 'American Branch of the Czechoslovak National Council'.</p>
   <p>"2. The president should be some member of the Czechoslovak National Council sojourning in America. Vice-presidents are to be (a) the president of the Slovak League and (b) the president of the Bohemian National Alliance.</p>
   <p>"3. Secretaries are to include one Czech, and one Slovak.</p>
   <p>"4. Departments: (a) Finance, (b) Political and consular, (c) Military, (d) <pb facs="5418478_7_0474.jpg" n="5"/>Auxiliary, (Aid) (e) Agitation and organization, (f) Information and propaganda. Each department is headed by two referees, always one Czech and one Slovak. These referees form the executive body and will call meetings of trustees of Czech and Slovak district committees at which they will make reports and arrange for the next work period. These meetings will be called every six months or less, if necessary. The executive body and the trustees shall form a "branch".....</p>
   <p>"The seats of the various departments will be: Political and Consular, Washington, D. C; Military and Auxiliary, New York; Propaganda and Information, consisting of the Slav Press Bureau and the Slovanska Tiskova Kancelar, New York, with branches in places to be designated by the executive body; Agitation and Finance, to be decided on by the executive body. The executive body will select its seat in a location best suitable for its purposes. The Auxiliary (aid) Department is to be directed by Czechoslovak women. A monthly paper will be issued under the name of Organ Cesko-Slovenske Narodni Rady v <pb facs="5418478_7_0475.jpg" n="6"/>Americe (Organ of the Czechoslovak National Council in America). Further details will be passed on by the executive body."</p>
   <p>Although this proposition had been worked out and accepted by the committee of sixteen, composed of both Czechs and Slovaks, it nevertheless became the object of a discussion which took up all the forenoon, and which, actually, was the most tempestuous discussion experienced during the four days of the conference.</p>
   <p>It was advanced against this proposition that its style is patterned too closely after the statutes of the organization in Russia, where conditions are essentially different from those in America. It was argued that, if this proposition were put into service in this country, it would stultify the entire work performed here during the last three and a half years. It was pointed out that the proposition calls for too many referential functions which have, it is true, proved valuable in parts, but which can never make up for the <pb facs="5418478_7_0476.jpg" n="7"/>detailed work performed by the organizations as they existed up to the present.</p>
   <p>The true aim of the proposition seems to be nothing else but the creation of an American branch of the Czechoslovak National Council. This would mean something brand new, not only for Czechoslovak-America, but for the large American public as well. The bodies, as they existed up to the present, have a good name, and have done much valuable work. If these bodies had to vanish and be replaced by something novel, chaos, possibly accompanied by distrust, might result.</p>
   <p>Almost every delegate joined in the debate, and when it became obvious that the motion would not carry, Reverend Jedlicka came out with a proposal which was a sort of compromise. It called for the creation of a Czechoslovak executive body composed of the Czech National Alliance and the Slovak League, each of whom are branches of the Czechoslovak National Council. This executive <pb facs="5418478_7_0477.jpg" n="8"/>body is to have an equal number of Czechs and Slovaks, and govern the Czech National Alliance and the Slovak League......</p>
   <p>After this compromising proposal Delegate Hrbek pleaded for the former proposition as offered by Mr. Jancek. A new debate ensued in which Reverend Vanek pointed out the work done by Czech Protestants in regard to propaganda for the movement of liberation by making valuable contacts with influential American circles. It would help the cause materially if the public were shown that a new organization has taken the place of the old one. Mr. Milan Getting called for equal representation of Slovaks with the Czechs, contending that, as long as the Czechoslovak state is still non-existent, the Slovaks are still in Hungary, and have, therefore, to speak for themselves. He denied Mr. Pergler the right to speak in the name of the Slovaks, because he is a Czech. Pergler, on the other hand, defended his actions by saying that he is a Czechoslovak. This statement did not satisfy Mr. Getting. He retorted that "Mr. Pergler only recently had termed the word Czechoslovak a <pb facs="5418478_7_0478.jpg" n="9"/>monstrosity....."</p>
   <p>Reverend Zlamal declared that if any satisfactory solution of the question is to be gained, the Slovaks must be represented in the executive [department] on par with the Czechs.....The Slovak delegates seconded him enthusiastically. Mr. Vojta Benes then moved that the committee work out a final proposal in which equal representation is to be the guiding point. The committee retired and appeared after the noon recess with a new proposal which will enable all parties to engage in concerted action.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovak reorganization committee composed of sixteen members put the following final proposal before the delegates:</p>
   <p>"1. An executive body, composed of Czech and Slovak-American delegates of the Czech National Alliance and the Slovak League, shall be formed under the name 'American Branch of the Czechoslovak National Council'.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0479.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>"2. This executive body will consist of four departments headed by the most competent persons from its midst.</p>
   <p>"3. These bodies shall be: (a) political and consular, (b) for propaganda and information, (c) for military affairs, and (d) auxiliary.</p>
   <p>"4. The executive body reserves the right to propose to the organization amendments and additions to the rules. All the departments are responsible to the executive body. The executive body shall call a meeting of the branches and representatives of the Bohemian National Alliance and the Slovak League, to report about its activities. It also shall select the location of its own and the seats of the branches. It shall publish a monthly, representing the organization. The Czech members of the executive body shall be elected at this conference, and the Slovak members at the meeting of the central committee of the Slovak League to be held in New York this month."</p>
   <p>The satisfaction with which this proposal was received became obvious from the <pb facs="5418478_7_0480.jpg" n="11"/>fact that it passed without debate of any sort. Only Mr. Joseph Tvrzicky raised a question about the failure in the proposal to mention a committee on finance. He was satisfied, however, when informed that the new executive body shall elect a treasurer, through whose hands shall go all the contributions for the action of liberation, regardless of whether from Czech or Slovak sources. The various branches shall keep only funds large enough to meet administrative and other current expenses; all other monies shall flow through the channels directed by Professor Masaryk in the pursuit of the great action for the establishment of an independent Czechoslovak state.</p>
   <p>After this question was disposed of, the election of members for the executive body took place. Here again, the Catholics showed tolerance, and enthusiasm for the great cause. Reverend Zlamal, to whom unquestionably belongs the credit of having brought about the co-operation between the National Alliance of Czech Catholics and the Czech National Alliance, declared that the Catholics <pb facs="5418478_7_0481.jpg" n="12"/>will be perfectly satisfied with having on the executive board three seats only, leaving five seats to members of the Czech National Alliance. This announcement evoked stormy applause from the gathering.</p>
   <p>The Catholics elected the Reverend Zlamal, Mr. H. Dostal, editor, and Mr. Jan Straka. The election of candidates from the Czech National Alliance brought the following result: K. Pergler, 31 votes, Dr. L. Fisher 27, Professor Simek 25, Dr. Motakova 23, and Reverend Koukol, 22. These five were elected. Two other candidates, Messrs. Martinek and Vojta Benes received only 21 and 18 votes respectively, out of a total of 34 votes.</p>
   <p>It is to be noted that the Slovaks have agreed to join the Czechs only if the delegates of the Slovak rally, which is to be held in a week, shall give the final approval. Mr. Mamatej, president of the Slovak League, however, assured the conference of his vigorous efforts to bring the Slovaks into the merger, <pb facs="5418478_7_0482.jpg" n="13"/>provided that they are given equal representation with the Czechs. The aim to liberate the old homeland is common to us, and the Slovaks will surely join us where the purpose is so noble.</p>
   <p>Captain Z. Firlinger [a Czech] was put in sole command of all Czechoslovak military affairs. This was greeted with loud consent, for it will do away with the question of proportional representation.....The Slovaks will elect their representatives for the executive body at their rally in New York.</p>
   <p>In this way one of the most burning questions before the conference was solved, and the joyful expression on the faces of all those present showed the great satisfaction over the successes achieved in the debates. Both Czechs and Slovaks were contented. This was voiced by Mr. Mamatej, spokesman for the Slovaks, who expressed the hope that what will be done at the Slovak rally will agree with the decisions of this conference. He stated that more money for the revolutionary movement was collected among the Czechs than the Slovaks.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0483.jpg" n="14"/>
   <p>This, he declared, has to be explained by the different political conditions under which the Slovaks of Europe live. They have not only the Austrian government to contend with, but the Magyar as well. In the final analysis, he declared, liberty cannot be bought with money alone, but demands other sacrifices also, namely, of blood--and this the Slovaks are ready to shed. The Slovaks have given the Czechs the best from their midst: Kolar, the first Slavist, and Safarik the scientist. Thomas G. Masaryk, president, and Dr. Milan Stefanik, vice president, of the Czechoslovak National Council, are of Slovak blood. The moment these timely remarks had been spoken, a thunder of applause reverberated through the hall.....</p>
   <p>After Mr. Mamatej's uplifting address, the Slovak delegates parted, being given the most cordial farewell by the Czechs. Telegrams and other communications were read.....As an attest to Slav solidarity a resolution was presented by Professor Simek and unanimously passed. It reads as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0484.jpg" n="15"/>
   <p>"We have joined hands with our brothers, the Slovaks, for mutual activities in the movement of liberation of the Czechoslovak nation. May our people be directed by sincerity and good will, now, but also in the future happy time when the united Czechoslovak nation will work on the basis of complete, honest equality.</p>
   <p>"We are expressing the hope that beside the independent Czechoslovak state there will stand an independent Polish and an independent Jugoslav state. We are voicing our wholehearted wishes for our brothers, the Poles and Jugoslavs, that these three Slav states shall constitute a fortress against German lust for expansion, and thus insuring a permanent peace for Europe.</p>
   <p>"For the committee on resolutions:</p>
   <p>(Signed) "B. Simek, B. Ludvikova,</p>
   <p>Tony Novotny."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0485.jpg" n="16"/>
   <p>An address expressive of loyalty and confidence was sent to Professor T. G. Masaryk. The Slav Press Bureau will be requested to convey thanks to Mr. Jusserand, French Ambassador in Washington D. C. Similar letters will be sent to Congressman Sabath and other prominent Czechoslovak people. A general appeal will be sent to the Czechoslovak public in America.....An address is to be sent to our workingmen's organizations which are pillars of our liberation movement.....Another address of encouragement will be sent to our volunteers in the Czechoslovak Army, and one of thanks to the Vcelky, a Czech-American women's auxiliary.</p>
   <p>President Wilson was sent an address reading as follows:</p>
   <p>"The Bohemian National Alliance in convention assembled in Chicago, pledges anew to you and through you to America the allegiance of all the Czechoslovaks. The delegates assembled received enthusiastically your last message to Congress declaring that all well-defined national aspirations must be satisfied if <pb facs="5418478_7_0486.jpg" n="17"/>permanent peace is to prevail. We realize this necessarily leads to an independent Czechoslovak state. America through you has again given a noble message to the world.</p>
   <p>"Dr. Fisher, president."</p>
   <p>The conference gratefully acknowledged the valuable service of Congressman A. J. Sabath who interceded in Washington, D. C., and also established contacts with various influential persons in behalf of our movement. In order to give full recognition to the service given by many workers, a resolution to that effect was passed.....The officers of the central committee have dutifully discharged themselves of their task.....Dr. L. J. Fisher, president, Joseph Tvrzicky, secretary, and Vojta Benes, organizer, of the Czech National Alliance, were specially mentioned, and so were Karel Pergler, director, and A. G. Mik, secretary of the Slav Press Bureau.....</p>
   <p>There were many propositions before the conference. A number of these however <pb facs="5418478_7_0487.jpg" n="18"/>lost their significance as a result of the successful completion of the merger. The remaining business was conducted mostly in the manner of colloquial debates, a survey of which follows:</p>
   <p>Mr. E. V. Voska's motion, calling for an All-Slav rally, was referred to the executive body. Another motion, made by the same delegate, calling for preliminary work for a "revolutionary bond issue" was treated similarly. Mrs. Novak demanded the co-operation of all women here in the work of the women's auxiliary "Vcelky". The executive body will take care of the corresponding work. Mr. Hynek Dostal called attention to the fact that the Poles have already been recognized by Allied governments. He urged that something be done in Washington to give the Czechs an equally legal standing. This issue was referred to the executive body.....Dr. Fisher and Mr. Voska informed the delegates that Professor Masaryk will be invited to America, and that the prospect is in sight of welcoming the leader in this country this spring. Mr. Serpan moved that proper contacts be established with influential persons <pb facs="5418478_7_0488.jpg" n="19"/>in America to win their support for our cause. The propaganda committee was directed to take the necessary steps.</p>
   <p>The debates lasted until 7:30 P. M. when the conference was officially declared closed by Mr. Pazdra, chairman. The manner in which he gave the finishing touch to this memorable meeting will certainly never vanish from the memory of the participants. Mr. Pazdera, a man of the typical Czech-American intelligence, represents the Czechs of the state of Texas. This farewell address brought tears to the eyes of every one of the delegates. "Hej Slovane", the Czech national anthem, and the "Star-Spangled Banner" were sung, whereupon the delegates joined in an ovation for Mr. Pazdera in appreciation of the masterful arrangements he had made for the conference. The women delegates and other workers gave him a delightful surprise by presenting him with a chairman's gavel adorned with colors. Mrs. Ludvik, who directs the Ludvikovci [Czech-Chicago theatrical group], headed the ladies, and spoke words befitting the occasion....Mr. Pazdera paid homage to the patriotic work <pb facs="5418478_7_0489.jpg" n="20"/>of the Czech women, declaring that they deserved a monument high enough to reach to the sky.....</p>
   <p>Thus ended the conference in which were laid the foundations for future events of downright monumental significance. May the hopes that rest upon its daring plans come true!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
