<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-07-07">July 7, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">Hus Celebration the Memory of the Charnel-House Martyr Was Celebrated with Dignity Throughout the Entire Bohemian Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0300</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0300.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1902-07-07">July 7, 1902</date>.
<title level="a">HUS CELEBRATION THE MEMORY OF THE CHARNEL-HOUSE MARTYR WAS CELEBRATED WITH DIGNITY THROUGHOUT THE ENTIRE BOHEMIAN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2 - Saturday evening showed that liberal-minded Bohemians are not asleep, and that they are working industriously to introduce the principles for which they stand to our public. Also, it was shown that the public recognizes their efforts.</p>
   <p>The celebrations which were arranged for the anniversary of the burning of the Master Jan Hus, were successful in every respect, in spite of the dreadful heat which prevailed and made remaining in closed halls unbearable.</p>
   <p>Hus celebrations were held Saturday in the following places: The Bohemian English Liberal School on 18th Street; Sokol Chicago Hall on Kedzie Avenue; Loula's Hall at 48th and Paulina Streets; in the Town of Lake; Atlas Hall, on Emma Street, on the North Side. The celebration held in the school on 18th Street was notably successful. The hall was entirely filled and all present followed the program so arranged as to afford the audience a great deal of <pb facs="5418478_7_0301.jpg" n="2"/>refined entertainment and education - with interest and enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>The address by R. Bittner, editor of Sotek, was brilliant, and the applause with which it was received was proof of its quality.</p>
   <p>Remarkably good speakers appeared at the other halls. In Sokol Chicago Hall the speaker for the occasion was Jos. J. Kral; Vil. Krouzilka also spoke. In the Town of Lake, J. Stybr of Coal City, proved that he had lost none of his eloquence, wit and satire. In Atlas hall, on the Northwest side, Alois M. Zahorik, proved to be an excellent speaker.</p>
   <p>Sokol Slavsky, together with Straz Osvojenych (Guard of the Masters) arranged a Hus celebration in Grand Crossing yesterday. This celebration was well attended and its program satisfied in full all who attended.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
