<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-22">Mar. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Bulletin from the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku</title><title level="a" type="sub">To All Bohemian Catholic Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0842</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0842.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-22">Mar. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A BULLETIN FROM THE NARODNI SVAZ CESKYCH KATOLIKU</title><title level="a" type="sub">To All Bohemian Catholic Societies</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We beg to call the attention of all the Bohemian Catholic societies associated with the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America) to the fact that membership fees for 1922 are now due. We also ask those Bohemian Catholic societies which are not yet associated with us to join us this year in order that we may all work together toward our common goal. We ask all our associated organizations to send us twenty-four cents per member annually, and not to send us just $5 or $10 as many societies, having more than one hundred members, are wont to do.</p>
   <p>Every society associated with us should regularly receive our monthly bulletin Hlidka (Sentinel). Copies of the bulletin are mailed to the secretaries of all the associated organizations, or to the district offices of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku which latter bodies transmit them to individual societies. Wherever copies of the Hlidka are not available, the respective society should <pb facs="5418478_7_0843.jpg" n="2"/>inform us by postal card so that we may correct our mailing list. By this means all our societies are [fully] informed about the activities of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku, and may, on the basis of these activities, develop their own in co-operation with the main body and thus work for the good of all our people.</p>
   <p>Since some societies have been invited to join the National Catholic Welfare Council, we must advise them that the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku is a member of that organization to which it also contributes by large sums from its districts and societies; whenever such invitations to join are directed to you, all you need to say is that you are a member of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku, which fact per se will satisfactorily answer such a question. Of course we cannot prevent you if you wish otherwise to contribute to the National Catholic Welfare Council in some special way.....</p>
   <p>Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku,</p>
   <p>3207 West 22nd Street,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
