<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1899-05-04">May 4, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">In Honor of Bohemian Soldiers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1487</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1487.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1899-05-04">May 4, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">IN HONOR OF BOHEMIAN SOLDIERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Reception and welcome to our boys in Pilsen Falcon. Yesterday at 7 P. M. Pilsen Hall was overflowing with both old and young generations to welcome our brave Bohemian soldiers, who returned, healthy, from the last Spanish-American war to enjoy life among their beloved ones. The music greeted the boys and all neighbors were out on the streets to look at them. Everyone read in the newspapers about the hardships and the bloody battles and sometimes hungry days experienced by the soldiers, and now seeing them marching, our hearts were filled with national pride. Many had among the boys their sons, or brothers, and maybe sweethearts, and many eyes were wet.</p>
   <p>The parade started from 624 Centre Ave., home of the Bohemian-American Veterans from 1898 to 1899, and was led by Capt. Frank A. Yaska to the Pilsen Falcon, where it was heartily greeted by the Bohemian ladies, sponsors, and arrangers, of the celebration. Then the brave boys were introduced by their fathers or relatives to their friends and treated with tasty dishes and cigarettes. Then followed many speeches made by the Bohemian ladies accenting the bravery of the boys and thanking them for their achievements, which raised the name of Bohemian-Americans to a high point in the eyes of the whole population of the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1488.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Gen. Theodore F. Brown in a brief speech praised the boys and finished the allocation by expressing the hope that the veterans will not be in need to look for jobs, because the government will offer the best jobs and positions to the ex-soldiers, who have risked their young lives for their adopted fatherland. Then followed different patriotic songs, as "America", "The Old Folks at Home," "Break the News to Mother".</p>
   <p>The moving pictures, demonstrated by the "vitascope" finished the celebration. We have seen the destruction of the Spanish fleet at Manila and Santiago, the battle by El Cancy, and many others. - The celebration ended late in the night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
