<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-08">Oct. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Meeting of the Board of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-08">Oct. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A MEETING OF THE BOARD OF THE CESKY NARODNI HRBITOV</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A regular meeting of the board of representatives of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) was held in the hall of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) last night.....</p>
   <p>Among the incoming letters was one from the Ceska Utulna A Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage), inviting the board to the annual inspection of the institutions to be held Saturday, October 25. The inspection will include an exhibit of the inmates' handwork.....</p>
   <p>The board of representatives of the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice (Bohemian-American Hospital) inquired by letter whether the board of the Narodni Hrbitov would be interested in buying the $15,000 worth of bonds the board of the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice expects to issue, and if so, under what conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1137.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The bonds will be secured by a real-estate mortgage on the Hospital's property. They will be issued to facilitate an early start in building an addition to the present home of the Hospital. The board of representatives of the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice mentioned in the letter that the board of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov frequently invests in bonds, and that there is no reason why it should not invest in Bohemian bonds with as good security as any other bonds may offer under favorable conditions. Only two representatives offered their opinions concerning this deal. One advocated the purchase of the bonds; the other was against it and moved that the secretary be instructed to reply in the negative to the letter. His motion was carried, and the secretary will inform the Nemocnice that the board has no cash on hand because of expenses connected with the building of the crematorium.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Mencl reported for the building committee on the progress being made with the crematorium.....The stucco work is nearly completed, floors are being <pb facs="5418478_7_1138.jpg" n="3"/>laid, and the incinerators are almost ready.....</p>
   <p>....The treasurer reported an income of $7,064.79; balance at the last meeting, $22,511.58; expenses, $13,476.23; $15,000 deposited with 3 per cent interest. Cash on hand is $1,100.11.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
