<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-17">Apr. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Our National and Auxiliary Activity</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1063</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1063.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-17">Apr. 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">OUR NATIONAL AND AUXILIARY ACTIVITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting on April 10 of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics was one of the most remarkable ever held by the organization. It proved that our activities have increased in intensity and extent, notwithstanding the many difficulties that presented themselves to us, but were overcome or removed gradually.</p>
   <p>The news was received with high gratification that a branch of the Cyrill and Methodius Auxiliary Fund and also a branch of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics have been created in St. Paul, Minn., largely through the efforts of that patriotic priest, the Reverend John Rynda.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1064.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>News no less encouraging has been received from Cleveland, Ohio, and New York. Another item which demonstrates co-operation is an article published in the Slovak Jednota where the Catholic Slovaks declare that they are making our cause their own.</p>
   <p>The executive committee of our organization is preparing to take steps of immense importance towards the liberation of the old homeland. The public will be acquainted with all the details as soon as the preliminary plans are carried out.</p>
   <p>We feel happy over another proof of co-operation for a number of newspapers have opened their columns to us. They are: Natrod, Katolik, Denni Hlasatel, Svornost and Slavia of Chicago, and others from Czech and Slovak settlements all over the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1065.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The break between the United States and Austria has greatly facilitated our operations as we can step forth more definitely, and pursue more energetically, the aims which we have set as our goal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
