<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-07-11">July 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">John Huss Memorial and the Five-Hundredth Anniversary of His Death</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0374</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0374.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-07-11">July 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN HUSS MEMORIAL AND THE FIVE-HUNDREDTH ANNIVERSARY OF HIS DEATH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>July 6, 1915, marks the five-hundredth anniversary of the day when John Huss, having been declared a heretic by the Church Council, was burned at the stake near Constance. No doubt this anniversary will be commemorated throughout the whole civilized world, particularly, however, by the Bohemian nation. In the old country, people are already busy making elaborate preparations. There the ceremonies will culminate in the unveiling of a monument--which will be finished by that time--at the Staromestske Namesti (Old Town Square) in Prague.</p>
   <p>Nor will the Free-thinking Bohemians in America permit such an important occasion to pass without a dignified, serious commemoration. Upon the <pb facs="5418478_7_0375.jpg" n="2"/>initiative of the grand lodge of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies), the Svaz Podpurnych Jednot A Spolku (Federation of Benevolent Societies and Associations) is calling the representatives of all local Free Thought bodies to a conference at which ways and means for the arrangement of a joint, unified John Huss celebration in Chicago will be discussed.</p>
   <p>Aside from this,for quite some time now the idea has been circulated for the building of a Jubilejni Husuv Dum (John Huss Memorial Building) in Chicago by the combined efforts of all Bohemians in America. This building would become a center for all Free-thinking Bohemians in America. In addition to a large, formal hall for important meetings, the building would contain several smaller meeting rooms and offices for central bodies. There would also be a Bohemian-American Museum where all documents concerning Bohemian life in America would be kept. Also courses for teachers would be held in the building, and it would house a model school for practical training.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0376.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A publication issued by the committee on advance preparations for Husuv Dum states that some two hundred organizations have already signified their willingness to co-operate, and that more than one hundred Bohemian settlements throughout the United States have set aside funds for the John Huss Memorial Building. Thus, the amount now available exceeds $10,000. The committee has sent a request to all Free Thought lodges, societies, associations, and other such units in America to arrange fitting John Huss celebrations during the month of July at which contributions for the Huss Memorial would be solicited. According to articles in the publication, the enthusiasm for the Memorial is pronounced and general. The committee has set August 15 as the deadline for reports on collections. After this date, particulars will be published concerning the election of a legal Stavebni Druzstvo (Building Committee), which will be incorporated in September.</p>
   <p>The Druzstov will be composed of delegates of co-operating bodies.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0377.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Organizations contributing twenty-five dollars with a down payment of ten dollars and a pledge to remit the balance by July 6, 1914, will be entitled to one delegate with one vote. Each additional one hundred dollars entitles an organization to one more delegate or vote. Out-of-town delegates may vote by mail. Individuals contributing one hundred dollars are also entitled to one vote, and contributions of five hundred dollars entitle them to two votes. Newspaper representatives may also become delegates. However, they will be appointed by the Druzstvo at its own discretion in accordance with the amount of contributions sent through their respective papers and the effectiveness of their paper's co-operative efforts.</p>
   <p>Immediately after its constitution is written, the Stavebni Druzstvo will select a site and publish the conditions of a competition for plans of the building. The committee on advance preparations now has available helpful material for the work of local bodies, such as blanks for entering contributions, "bricks," picture post cards, stamps, etc., which may be had by sending <pb facs="5418478_7_0378.jpg" n="5"/>a request to the financial secretary, Mr. Karel Kavalle, 2723 South Avers Avenue, Chicago, Illinois. The press and publicity committee, whose chairman is Dr. Fr. Iska, has such program material for Huss celebrations as addresses, speeches, declamations, and songs, which is available free of charge. Requests should be addressed to the Press Committee, J. H. D., 1510 West 18th Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
