<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-31">Jan. 31, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Call to Join the Expedition of the National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America and the Catholic Sokol Union to Czechoslovakia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0859</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0859.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-31">Jan. 31, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A CALL TO JOIN THE EXPEDITION OF THE NATIONAL ALLIANCE OF BOHEMIAN CATHOLICS OF AMERICA AND THE CATHOLIC SOKOL UNION TO CZECHOSLOVAKIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p> </p>
   <p>Many of our countrymen are making preparations to visit their old homeland this year. It would be desirable if they would take advantage of the projected expedition of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics) and the Katolicky Sokol (Catholic Sokol Union) and thus participate in a happy adventure with the other members of the expedition when they set foot upon their native soil. The trip will not be expensive, so that many people will be able to afford it. The cabin cost on one of the finest steamships of the Holland-American Line will be $130 or $132.50 for a second class cabin if one joins the expedition. This would then be a decided advantage. The meals served on this steamship will suit our Bohemian tastes. From Rotterdam there will be special express trains to Prague, and the fare will amount to eight or nine dollars. The trip from Chicago to Prague will consume about thirteen days.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0860.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>First-class cabins on this boat are not available anymore, except in two cases where the remaining cabins, fully equipped, will accommodate only two persons each....Our participants in the expedition will for the best part engage cabins in the second class. These cabins are well appointed and their comforts are well known to regular travelers who use the services of this steamship company.</p>
   <p>The dead line for applications has been deferred until the end of February. It is therefore necessary that everyone who intends to join the expedition file his application on time! Do not wait until the last moment to reserve your cabin and to secure desirable accomodations.</p>
   <p>During our stay in the homeland, there will be an information bureau for the members of the expedition, who will thus be enabled to obtain any necessary information, and the bureau will also serve as a meeting place for any members who desire to join various trips to the provinces.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0861.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Narodni Rada Ceskoslovenska V Americe (Czechoslovak National Council in America) has already informed the Narodni Rada (National Council) in Prague of our proposed expedition, and we were promised extensive facilities. Other information reaching us from the Amerika Korespondence (American Correspondence) of Prague [Translator's note: The Americka Korespondence of Prague was a news-gathering and news-distributing organization for all matters concerning an interchange of activities between the United States and Czechoslovekia] has offered its services to the members of the expedition. Thus, there seems to be a great deal of interest in our welfare. We are being invited by many different organizations abroad, so it is now up to us to make applications to join the expedition. We shall secure a cabin for you as soon as we receive your deposit of $30. Send in your application!</p>
   <p>The Narodni Svaz Ceskych Kateliku, </p>
   <p>3207 West 22nd Street, Chicago, Illinois. </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
