<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-18">July 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">To Reorganize Army Aid</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1386</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1386.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-18">July 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">TO REORGANIZE ARMY AID</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night a reorganization meeting was held by the Narodni Armadni Pomocny Vybor (National Army Aid Association), at the offices of the Czech Bureau, 3342 West 26th Street. Mr. Louis Solar presided. The discussions centered on the question of increasing the membership.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jos. J. Salat stated that the Aid Association is under the direct sponsorship of the State Defence Council, and as such is part of the Government. Its authority, up to the present, is confined to the 27th and 28th Recruiting Districts, both within the Twelfth Ward.</p>
   <p>The National Army Aid Association is at present divided into two bodies. One for the 27th District, presided over by Mr. Louis Soula, and the other, for the 28th District, under Alderman Otto Kerner.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anton J. Cermak is chairman of the combined bodies, Mr. Jos. J. Salat is secretary, Mr. Fr. G. Hajicek, treasurer. Alderman Jos. I. Novak is secretary <pb facs="5418478_7_1387.jpg" n="2"/>for the 27th District.</p>
   <p>Mr. Salat explained that the primary purpose of the Aid Association is the maintenance of the Czech Bureau, and the provision for payment of expenses for the War Bond, War Savings Stamp, and Red Cross campaigns. In addition there are other business matters in which the Czechs are to exert themselves as much as possible, to demonstrate their loyalty to the Government.</p>
   <p>In the Czech Bureau, headed by Mr. Salat, War Bonds and War Savings Stamps are sold, and contributions for the Red Cross accepted. The Czech Bureau played a large part in the arrangements for the Independence Day celebration by the Czechs, an event which created a general sensation.</p>
   <p>Mr. Solar urged the members to launch a vigorous drive for an increased membership. The dues are five dollars per year, but each individual member is bound to perform some work. Businessmen in the two recruiting districts are among the first expected to join and co-operate. It was deemed necessary <pb facs="5418478_7_1388.jpg" n="3"/>to create an expense fund to cover the necessary expenses, as for instance the debt for the recent Fourth of July celebration, a considerable amount of which is still unpaid.</p>
   <p>Mr.Solar stated that the Aid Association contributes funds for the relief of our boys on the battlefront, in the camps, and wherever necessary. The Association also supplies information on the whereabouts and welfare of soldiers.</p>
   <p>Valuable and sincere patriotic work is being done, for example, "The Salat &amp; Crystal Concertina" society will hold a picnic at Pilsen Brewery Park, August 24, the proceeds of which will be donated to the Aid Association. Tickets cost thirty-five cents. Mr. Frank Kaspar succeeded in gaining thirty new members in a single day. It is to be hoped that Czechs in other districts will also extend their help.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
