<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-07-11">July 11, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">To All Bohemian Freethinkers in the State of Illinois</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0989</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0989.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-07-11">July 11, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">TO ALL BOHEMIAN FREETHINKERS IN THE STATE OF ILLINOIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The August edition of the Vek Rozumu (Age of Reason), which, according to the resolution of the last Freethinkers' convention, will be published in Chicago by the executive committee of the Svaz Svobodomyslnych (Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers), will be the first one to be received by every member of the federation and will be edited by Dr. Jaroslav E. S. Vojan. A generous one-thousand-dollar contribution by the Bohemian National Cemetery enabled the executive committee to start the organization work at once. Therefore, the executive committee sincerely asks Freethinkers of every Bohemian colony in the State of Illinois to call meetings immediately for the purpose of starting new branches of the Svaz Svobodomyslnych, and to report their activities to the secretary of the executive committee, Mr. V. K. Soukup, 2000 South Ashland Avenue, Chicago, Illinois, or to the editor of the Vek Rozumu, Dr. Jaroslav E. S. Vojan, 2004 South Albany Avenue, Chicago, Illinois. It would be most <pb facs="5418478_7_0990.jpg" n="2"/>gratifying if we could report such news in the first issue of the Vek Rosumu, either from the State of Illinois or from any other state of our great Union, and prove by it that the Free Thought movement of Bohemian-America is awakening to a new and better life. The contribution of the Bohemian National Cemetery convincingly demonstrates that the interest in the invigoration of the Bohemian Free Thought movement in America is serious and deep. It is only necessary to awake and work energetically in all of our colonies, in order that the interest which was aroused by the last convention may be fully utilized. Let the flag of the Bohemian-American Free Thought movement proudly wave in every one of our Bohemian colonies in the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
