<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-13">Jan. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">An Introduction to the Sokol Chicago Athletic Tournament</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1398</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1398.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-13">Jan. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AN INTRODUCTION TO THE SOKOL CHICAGO ATHLETIC TOURNAMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Narodni Armadni Pomocny Vybor (National Army Auxiliary Committee) has undertaken the task of caring for the needs of our boys who eagerly volunteered for service in the United States Army and plunged into the fight for the lofty principles of universal democracy. Anton J. Cermak, chief bailiff of the municipal court, is president, Frank J. Hajicek is treasurer of the branch of the organization for the Twelfth Ward ["Czech California" district]. Most of our volunteers serve in the Twenty-seventh and Twenty-eighth divisions, which are quartered at Camp Grant, Rockford, Illinois. The Auxiliary Committee was instrumental in procuring many articles, necessities or luxuries, which are being sent as gifts to the soldiers.</p>
   <p>This gives us a good reputation, for in the camp it is well known that the <pb facs="5418478_7_1399.jpg" n="2"/>Czech soldiers are not forgotten by their fellow countrymen. It is a well-known fact that whatever gifts the soldiers have received, whether they be phonographs, tobacco, pipes, or money, they were provided by the Czechs of the Twelfth ward. These same Czechs will again testify to their love and generosity at a great athletic tournament for the benefit of our brave young men.</p>
   <p>This affair is going to take place in the auditorium of Sokol Chicago, South Kedzie Avenue and 24th Street, on Sunday, January 20. An immense attendance is expected, for the cause is noble and the tournament is expected to be the most impressive ever held in our community. The complete program has not yet been made known to us. What we could learn up to this moment is enough to make every lover of athletic sports anticipate the event with eagerness.</p>
   <p>Bill Hokuff and Paul Martenson, great wrestling stars, will meet there.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1400.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Hokuff will offer a stake of two hundred dollars to anyone who wants to tackle him. There will also be other gladiators. The referee will be our countryman, Joe Stecher, champion, who will function in this capacity before Czech spectators for the first time. He is looking forward to the occasion with great anticipation. Mr. Henry Sonnenschein is in charge of the arrangements for the wrestling. He informs us that the demand for tickets is keen. It will be advisable for those interested to secure a place early. Tickets are on sale at the following addresses: Mattas, 26th Street and Trumbull Avenue; Honsik's drugstore, Turner Avenue and 26th Street; Placet's restaurant on Kedzie Avenue; Kuflewski's drugstore; Bezner's drugstore, 26th Street and Kedzie Avenue; Rys' restaurant, Kedzie Avenue and 22nd Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
