<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-27">Sept. 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Arouse Enthusiasm for the Narodni Dan Svobodomyslnych!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0972</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0972.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-27">Sept. 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">AROUSE ENTHUSIASM FOR THE NARODNI DAN SVOBODOMYSLNYCH!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Let the Sokol's motto "Tan svet se hne, kam sila se napre" (In that direction the world will move in which power is exerted) be a guide for all those who are really interested in the Bohemian-American Free Thought movement.</p>
   <p>Beginning October 1, all the preliminary work for the Narodni Dan Svobodomyslnych (National Tax of Freethinkers) must be at its peak. For this purpose only, the Chicago branch of the Svaz Svobodomyslnych (Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers of America) will hold a special meeting on Thursday, September 30; and in all the other Bohemian-American colonies, it will be necessary to arouse interest in this tax to the best of our ability. As a result of inadequate organization, we cannot compare ourselves this year with the Bohemian Catholics, who have natural collection places in their churches for their St. Wenceslaus National Tax. Those societies who have "free thought" not only on their emblems and in their mouths, but really in their hearts, must voluntarily extend the best of their honest <pb facs="5418478_7_0973.jpg" n="2"/>efforts and help where none of the local branches of the Svaz Svobodomyslnych exist, as well as at places where they already exist.</p>
   <p>In order that the Svaz Svobodomyslnych may be informed that in individual communities the preliminary work has started already, we are asking our Free Thought societies all over the United States to let the central office know about all that has been accomplished so far. (V. K. Soukup, 2000 South Ashland Avenue, Chicago, Illinois).</p>
   <p>Here in Chicago we again repeat our request that secretaries or financial secretaries of Free Thought organizations, with the approval of their presidents, send us a list of their members in order that we may establish a list of Bohemian Freethinkers and organize collection districts. This list of members should be sent to Mrs. Marie Stepanek, 2232 South Kedzie Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Therefore, away with all slackness and despondency! Just as five years ago <pb facs="5418478_7_0974.jpg" n="3"/>there were many who doubted that Bohemian-America would be able to undertake any liberation action on a large scale, today there are many fainthearted Free-thinkers who repeat despondently again and again that our people are absolutely indolent, that all the efforts to invigorate the Free Thought movement are futile. Do not believe them! The Bohemian-American Freethinkers were able to accomplish a great deal for our old homeland, and now it must be proved by them that they are able to do the same for themselves--for the Free Thought movement here in America--which, without energetic help, might find itself upon the verge of a decline. We must not permit it to go that far. We have existed and we shall exist, and if the Zivot (Life), a Protestant journal of Oklahoma, today proclaims that the Bohemian-American Free Thought movement is a dead body, then let us prove that he whom they tried to bury alive will live for a long, long time! But it is necessary to work, work, and work again and not to throw up our hands helplessly. Besides the work, financial means are also needed, and the national tax is the only possibility for providing this aid. Since Bohemian Catholics collect the <pb facs="5418478_7_0975.jpg" n="4"/>St. Wenceslaus National Tax for their purposes, it would be a shame for us to stay behind and devote ourselves to laziness.</p>
   <p>The anniversary day of Karel Havlicek-Borovsky [Bohemian patriot] is nearing. Do not forget what he once said--that it is about time that Free Thought be moved from our mouths into our hands and into our pockets. (Of course Havlicek spoke about patriotism, but the same may be applied to the Free Thought movement.) Sincerity of conviction is judged properly not according to beautiful words, but according to deeds and generosity!</p>
   <p>For the Svaz Svobodomyslnych,</p>
   <p>V. Cada, President:</p>
   <p>Dr. Jaroslav E. Salaba Vojan, </p>
   <p>Chairman of the press committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
