<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-16">May 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Through Foreign Countries to Our Own Country's Heart</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0177</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0177.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-16">May 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THROUGH FOREIGN COUNTRIES TO OUR OWN COUNTRY'S HEART</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have been waiting for a very long time to give our readers and the whole Bohemian public the good news that Bohemian-America, and in particular our Bohemian-American metropolis on the shores of Lake Michigan, our own Chicago, will be the recipient of an unusual honor. It is all the more significant that this honor will be ours this year, the year which should be a year of special significance to all Bohemians no matter in what part of the world--this year marks the quincentenary of John Huss' martyrdom. During the year we shall be the first to hear the introductory performance of a great, beautiful Bohemian composition, a three-part oratorio entitled "Huss". It originated in the severely persecuted Bohemian minority of Imperial Vienna; it came to America, and here it has penetrated into the hearts of our people. We have been waiting a long time to make this announcement, and at last we are free to do so. We did not publish it earlier out of consideration for the <pb facs="5418478_7_0178.jpg" n="2"/>Cesky Pevecky Spolek Bedrich Smetana (Bedrich Smetana Singing Society) which had devotedly undertaken to honor the memory of the great martyr by the presentation of an oratorio which, while beautiful, and depicting some of the phases of John Huss' life.... is and will remain a German composition.....</p>
   <p>Now, once Loewe's oratorio has been performed, we can inform our public that it will hear an extremely artistic composition, one which fully evaluates the life work of John Huss and by which his memory will be honored in a most appropriate way. It is Rudolf Vohanka's oratorio "Huss," the words of which were also written by a Bohemian, Ferdinand Havelka..... Our Ustredni Pevecka Jednota (Federation of [Bohemian] Singing Societies) was first to take cognizance of the existence of this work and....got in touch with the author who....has given the Federation permission to perform it.....</p>
   <p>The Ceska Ustredni Pevecka Jednota is already working on preparations for the oratorio's rehearsals.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
