<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-06-02">June 2, 1904</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Meeting of Representatives of Bohemian National Cemetery.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1283</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1283.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-06-02">June 2, 1904</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">MEETING OF REPRESENTATIVES OF BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The representatives of the Bohemian National Cemetery held a meeting last night in the lower hall of the Bohemian American Liberal School. Mr. Jan Pech the chairman, brought the meeting to order at 8 o'clock sharp, there was however only a meager attendance.</p>
   <p>The secretary, Mr. Jos. Filip, read the carefully written minutes of the previous meeting, which were approved without debate.</p>
   <p>The financial secretary, Mr. Husak presented a large batch of bills payable, all were accepted and approved for payment. The managing committee purchased $4,000 of Brainard Minn., school bonds and $1,000 of C. Hadron, Nebr., school bonds. The Minnesota bonds return 4 per cent and the Nebraska bonds five per cent interest.</p>
   <p>The association received only one communication, that of representative Havlik, in which he requests pardon owing to his inability to attend the meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1284.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The association received only one communication, that of representative Havlik, in which he requests pardon owing to his ability to attend the meeting. The report of the managing committee in regards to the Decoration Day ceremonies was then read. The report and likewise the bills were accepted.</p>
   <p>Mr. Smejkal announced that various bids had been received for furnishing the posts to build a fence around the new section of the cemetery. Since the lowest bid was made by the California Sash and Door Company, that is fifty cents a piece, the job was turned over to that firm. The furnishing of the necessary wire was turned over to Mr. Kapsa, his bid being the most advantageous.</p>
   <p>Some drainage tile is needed on the cemetery and it was decided to purchase a carload of it.</p>
   <p>A Cemetery Association has been organized in Illinois, having for its purpose the betterment of conditions of all cemeteries in Illinois.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1285.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They sent a letter to the National Cemetery Association urging it to become a member, and remit the annual fee of two dollars. It was decided by vote to join this Association.</p>
   <p>A 50th anniversary jubilee committee of the C. S. P. S. (Czechoslavak Benevolent Society) requests that the National Cemetery place an advertisement and a brief outline of the history of the cemetery in their souvenir book. It was decided that the managing committee do so, using at least three pages. A debate followed regarding the heating of the premises in the winter. The committee announced that a new boiler will be needed and when that has been provided, the heating question will very easily be taken care of. The committee will attend to the matter. The bonds of the newly elected representatives were then read and accepted.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pech, the chairman announced the loss of a member of the association, Vaclav Kolar, representing Lodge Jiri Podebradsky #24 C. S. P. S.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1286.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A committee was appointed to draw up a letter of condolence. The chairman named the following for that purpose: Ed. Hole and David Koziska.</p>
   <p>An informal discussion followed during which several suggestions were made to improve the cemetery. Mr. Smejkal brought up the surprising idea of erecting a building on the grounds in which would be located a room sufficiently large to hold the association's meetings. At first it seems somewhat audacious, but when it is more carefully analyzed it becomes evident that it would be a highly desirable improvement. The urgent need of providing toilet facilities was discussed, because the present facilities are insufficient, and very unhandy. On the motion of representative Matejka, it was decided that the managing committee consult a competent architect on the subject.</p>
   <p>The financial secretary Mr. Husak, then read the report for the month of May, from which we extract the following.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1287.jpg" n="5"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Receipts for past month</cell>
     <cell>$11,900.34</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance from previous month</cell>
     <cell>6,366.60</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Disbursements</cell>
     <cell>7.697.22</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance on hand</cell>
     <cell>10,599.72</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>The managing committee was instructed buy additional bonds as it is undesirable to have this money lying idle.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
