<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-31">May 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">In Memoriam</title><title level="a" type="sub">Inspiring Celebrations on Decoration Day (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0071</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0071.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-31">May 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">IN MEMORIAM</title><title level="a" type="sub">Inspiring Celebrations on Decoration Day (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A downpour in the morning and an unpleasant autumnal atmosphere throughout the rest of the day could not mar the programs set for the Memorial Day celebrations which were held on various Czech cemeteries yesterday, nor could the chilly breeze which fanned the drizzling water dampen the patriotic spirit that filled the bosom of every participant. The attendance, however, was visibly affected by the inclement weather, for it could not compare with the multitudes of other years.....</p>
   <p>In the Bohemian National Cemetery</p>
   <p>The celebration began with the customary parade from the Cesko Americka Svobodna Skola (Czech American Liberal School) at 8 A. M. Mr. Frank Stejskal <pb facs="5418478_7_0072.jpg" n="2"/>was the marshal. After a rearrangement before the Bohemian Orphanage and the Old People's home, the parade arrived at the Bohemian National Cemetery, where flowers were laid upon the monument of the Civil War veterans. Mr. Albert Machacek was the speaker.</p>
   <p>He first remembered our recently departed fellow-countryman, the patriot and marshal, Frank Schultz, and other veterans whose ranks are thinning rapidly. Czech-American fathers and mothers were reminded by the speaker of the crucial time in which the liberation of the oppressed nations is being fought, and that young men are necessary to strengthen Uncle Sam's Army..... The speaker emphasized: "Remember my dear fellow-countrymen that those sons of our nation who lend an ear to its voice will be fighting not only for the Allies, but also for the liberation of our poor, oppressed people in the old homeland and for the independence of our dear country. Every nation struggling for freedom must be ready for sacrifices!.... You are today a part of this great country, and under a severe obligation to show your gratitude for the friendly reception <pb facs="5418478_7_0073.jpg" n="3"/>given you upon your arrival from the old country. Show your patriotism by buying Liberty Bonds, which are absolutely safe. Use the money which you may have placed in doubtful investments. That money will be used for your own good, and for a speedy ending of the War.</p>
   <p>"It is mainly up to those who stay at home to contribute to the funds for the alleviation of the untold sufferings which are awaiting our Army in action. Everyone of you, to the last man and woman, should become a member of the Red Cross...."</p>
   <p>During the speech, a heavy rain began to pour down, and the greater part of the attendance retired to the Crematory where the celebration was continued, although there was hardly any standing room left. After a piece of incidental music rendered by Mr. Rubringer's band, Mr. Pecha introduced Harry Olson, Chief Justice of the Municipal Court.</p>
   <p>Judge Olson's address contained much praise for the Czech people, and, as <pb facs="5418478_7_0074.jpg" n="4"/>a matter of course, reflected the spirit of the time of war, which raises the significance of this year's Decoration Day. After a brief review of the incidents which led to the proclamation of Memorial Day, the speaker pointed out that in the Civil War it was a Czech regiment which offered its services first. "At this time, it is again the Czech and Slovak boys who formed the largest contingent for enlistment in the service of "The Star-Spangled Banner." This corresponds with the tradition of the Czechs and other Slavonic peoples, who have always believed in humanitarianism, justice, and liberty, and who have always been ready for great sacrifices. We Americans are not an aggressive nation, and this is the reason why President Wilson hesitated so long before issuing his manifesto, which will be a profoundly significant document in history. We did not want War. Even after 232 American lives had been sacrificed, we still did not want War. But there was no way of evading the issue. Hostility was forced upon us, and we had to take to arms to protect our dignity and the freedom of the seas.....This War has united all strata of the population, the <pb facs="5418478_7_0075.jpg" n="5"/>poor and the rich. The Czechs and the other Slavonic nations of America have contributed, and in doing so, they are helping to liberate their oppressed countries."</p>
   <p>The wards of the Bohemian Orphanage then sang a chorus, and Miss Mary Neboska recited a poem by A. J. Havranek. The American anthem sung by the girls of the Orphanage, under the direction of Mrs. Augustine Dusek, concluded one part of the program.</p>
   <p>Bohumil Simek, professor of botany at the State University of Iowa, took the platform. Although born in this country, he speaks the Czech language impeccably, so that he might very well lecture at a Czech University. He is the prototype of the Czech-American intelligentsia, and we are proud of him. He is a speaker for the people. He has not a trace of the poser on him, he uses no flowery language, he speaks plainly, to the heart. His words breathed simplicity and American patriotism at the same time.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0076.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The professor dwelt upon the history of America's great men who had laid down their lives for the Flag. "There is not one war in American history which has not been justified, none for which we have to be ashamed before the civilized world. The War of Independence for our freedom, the Mexican War to liberate the oppressed people of Texas from the yoke of the blood-thirsty hordes of General Santa Anna, the Civil War for the abolition of slavery, and the Spanish-American War was fought so that the rays of freedom might shine upon the unfortunate people of Cuba, who had been moaning for centuries under Spanish terrorism. America is, however, entering the holiest of all the wars, for the liberation of a large group of subjugated nations, and for the removal of the domineering classes, who looked down upon their subjects as the means for the satisfaction of their greed and lust for power....."</p>
   <p>"Mobilization in the old country is different from ours.....Over there the path to the front is beset by moaning women shedding bloody tears. The soldiers are heading toward slaughter not knowing why. How different <pb facs="5418478_7_0077.jpg" n="7"/>would it be if the Czech soldiers in Austria were to fight for the liberation of the Czech people! There surely could not be found in Czech lands one mother, wife, or sweetheart, who would see her boy off with a grief-stricken look in her eyes. Only encouragement and enthusiasm would shine in them. We can part now with our boys under these same circumstances exactly. Today, we have a beautiful opportunity to combine our Czech emotions with the patriotic American sentiment; our directions do not diverge, they point to one and the same goal. If we succumb now, it will mean the funeral of all hopes for freedom; a tyranny will gain the upper hand such as this world has never seen, and the worst sufferers will be our fellowcountrymen in the old homeland." Prof. Simek concluded in a ringing voice that he, himself, would rather see his son dead than see him dodge his duty, thereby branded a coward.</p>
   <p>After this address, which left a visibly deep impression upon the audience, little Emma Kunt of the Orphanage recited in English "Unforgotten." The <pb facs="5418478_7_0078.jpg" n="8"/>multitude followed with the singing of "Kde Domov Muj" (Where Is My Homeland), and the band played "American Patrol."</p>
   <p>In St. Adalbert's Cemetery</p>
   <p>About six hundred persons took part in the celebration, part of them having gathered at 8 A. M. Among these were members of the Knights of St. Vence-lslaus and of the Veterans of Baron Filipovic. The parade started out from the Bohemian-American Hall. After a rearrangement of the parade, they took street cars reserved for them, and then boarded the Northwestern train to the cemetery. Because of rain, the participants had to file into an annex of the Cemetery administration building.</p>
   <p>The celebration was opened with the singing of the American anthem, played by the Filipovic Veterans' band, under the direction of Mr. Volenec. The Very Reverend Kohlbeck and Reverend F. W. Jedlicka delivered appropriate addresses.....The latter invited everyone in the gathering to contribute <pb facs="5418478_7_0079.jpg" n="9"/>to the Catholic auxiliary, the Cyril and Methudius Fund, for relief in the old country. "We are Czech Catholics," he said. "We can see how our creed and our maternal language prosper under the government of our new homeland. We wish the same for our old homeland." The speaker assured the gathering that the Czech Catholics have always been sincere Czechs, and law-abiding, loyal American citizens at the same time..... Two great Czech organizations have combined their powers in the work for the liberation of the old homeland. They are: The Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics. These two, the Reverend Jedlicka urged, deserve the most liberal support.....</p>
   <p>Leo J. Doyle, Judge of the Municipal Court, was introduced....."You Czechs who have come to these shores have mustered many of those who have given their blood for their adopted homeland," the speaker said, "and you are proving yourloyalty to this country now."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0080.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Most of the participants in the celebration came from the Town of Lake district. They gathered at 7 A. M. in the Cyril and Methudius settlement, on 50th Street and Hermitage Avenue. Two companies of the Baron Filipovic Veterans, the Sokol Borivoj gymnastic society, and many other organizations were represented. The parade, led by John R. Vojtech, moved over Lincoln Avenue [now Wolcott Avenue] to Leavitt Street.</p>
   <p>The celebration was opened with the playing of "The Star-Spangled Banner," "America," and the Czech national song, "Hej Slovane" [Forward, Slavs!].</p>
   <p>Judge Denis E. Sullivan, of the Superior Court of Cook County, was the first speaker..... He assured the gathering that in his opinion the sweet thoughts of the old homeland do not disturb the loyalty toward the adopted country. "The man who loses the love for his native land the minute he steps upon foreign soil is liable to forget his adopted country <pb facs="5418478_7_0081.jpg" n="11"/>as well.....You Czechs have every reason to be proud. Your country surrounded by the enemy lands has resisted for centuries; it has preserved its strength and its language;.....You stand before the world today as a small nation which has the right to independence from any other nation..... Numbering only six million souls, you have but two percent analphabets, a percentage smaller than that of any other European country. With your great universities, cloisters, churches, and schools, your educational institutions outrival in ratio the rest of the European countries. America ought to welcome with joy a people so good, devoted, and loyal, such as are the sons and daughters of Bohemia, and appreciate the achievements of the Czechs, which also benefit this country. You have newspapers, colleges, churches, and schools, and you have injected all these progressive elements into American life. You have brought with you assiduousness and loyalty, and incorporated these virtues into our national traits. The United States is now at War with Huns and Vandals, ever enemies of the Czechs, the same race with which the Czechs had to contend during all <pb facs="5418478_7_0082.jpg" n="12"/>the time of their national life, the Prussian aristocracy, which stakes its future upon one single item--might....."</p>
   <p>The address delivered by Mr. Jan Straka is given on page 3 of this issue.</p>
   <p>The celebration was concluded by a sermon and prayer. The participants then dispersed to visit individual graves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
