<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-10-10">Oct. 10, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">For Our Children's Better Future</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0871</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0871.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-10-10">Oct. 10, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">FOR OUR CHILDREN'S BETTER FUTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If our present social life were based upon charity, justice, love, and good will, instead of tears and sorrow we should be seeing only contentment and pleasure of living. The Svaz Svobodomyslnych (Free Thought Community) of America has made it its aim to bring about an improvement in the life of Czech America. Its purpose is to make our social life better and healthier, to awaken our people to the recognition of their humane and cultural mission, and, at the same time, to see to it that our youth be not only saved for our Czech Free Thought organizations in America, but that it be educated in the truly Free Thought spirit, that it may become saturated with the lofty principles of our spiritual giants Klacel, Zdrubek, Schnajdr [all are Czecho-Americans] and others, all those who are in our eternal memory as intrepid leaders and pioneers of liberty in thought and speech.</p>
   <p>If this great aim is to be reached, it is necessary that our Czech Free <pb facs="5418478_7_0872.jpg" n="2"/>Thought school receive the active support,both moral and material, of our public.</p>
   <p>It is for this reason that the Svaz Svobodomyslnych has decided to devote one full half of this year's Narodni Dan (National Tax) to Czech Free Thought schools in America.</p>
   <p>This mere fact should be a sufficient reason that there be not one person among us who would fail to make his contribution to that Dan. If you have not yet done so, do so now and send your contribution to the undersigned collector or give to an authorized solicitor.</p>
   <p>Get from us a collection booklet yourself! Collect contributions among your friends and acquaintances! All correspondence as well as monetary contributions <pb facs="5418478_7_0873.jpg" n="3"/>should be addressed to Fr. Haut, 4236 West 22nd Street (John Huss Memorial), Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
