<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-06-09">June 9, 1904</date>, p. 4
<title level="a">[Meeting of Bohemian National Cemetery Association]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1280</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1280.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-06-09">June 9, 1904</date>, p. 4
<title level="a">[MEETING OF BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY ASSOCIATION]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An opinion was expressed, by one of the representatives at the last meeting of the Bohemian National Cemetery Association, which is deserving of more consideration than it was given. This representative mentioned how desirable it would be if a building were erected on the cemetery grounds which would include a spacious hall, where the association could hold its meetings, and where during unfavorable weather various ceremonies could be held. At first it may seem to many that such a suggestion really an opinion because as yet it has not been put in the form of a motion is somewhat untenable. Why build a hall in the cemetery? That probably is what many will say.</p>
   <p>However in reality it would not only be practical but would bring the organization a decided profit. We mean, of course, in the manner which the afore mentioned representative indicated.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1281.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Cemetery Association holds monthly meetings. The meetings are held in the evening in a rented hall. Then once each year an inspection of the cemetery is conducted, which is participated in by all the representatives. Some of the representatives may go to the cemetery several times during the year, because of personal matters, but on such occasions do not seem to have time to notice what is going on at the cemetery, hense the managing committee must take care of everything, render reports at the meetings of what has been accomplished, and what should be done for the prosperity of the cemetery. True the managing committee is acting honorably and it's efforts are the best, but it would improve conditions if the representatives took more interest and made suggestions from their viewpoint. This however cannot be accomplished through an annual or casual inspection of the cemetery. So we approach the gist of the matter. If the meetings of the association were held at the cemetery, if it were possible for the representatives to at least partially acquaint themselves with the most important things, surely it would be much easier for them to decide on the many and often important questions that arise. A man can always form a better opinion about the thing he sees than he can when the details are related to him.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1282.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If they had their own hall, meetings could be held on Sunday afternoons, which would be much more convenient, for many of the representatives, than to go to a meeting at night, after returning home weary and tired from a hard days work.</p>
   <p>The rich Association of the National Cemetery should have no worry regarding finances. There is plenty of money on hand, and the Association is remarkably successful. Of course it depends upon the representatives; if they would serve the cemetery well, they will seriously consider this undertaking. In fact it belongs to all Bohemians of Chicago, and the Association has no right to think or hesitate; it is their duty to act immediately. The Association can finance a project of this character and still have sufficient money to support our other national undertakings- the "Bohemian School" and the "Old Peoples Home,"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
