<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-03">Dec. 3, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Bountiful Donations of the Bohemian National Cemetery to Free Thought Organizations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0958</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0958.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-03">Dec. 3, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">BOUNTIFUL DONATIONS OF THE BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY TO FREE THOUGHT ORGANIZATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular meeting of the delegates to the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery), held at the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies' hall yesterday, was called to order by Mr. John Pecha, president, at 8 P. M. sharp. The attendance was very small. The secretary, Mr. Victor H. Filip, presented the minutes of the last meeting, which were approved as read.</p>
   <p>Among other communications received since the last meeting were those from the grand lodge of the Bohemian Slavonic Society, of which Dr. K. Newman is president, and from the Vernost Lodge No. 8 of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies. Both of these respective bodies, in their communications, asked that the bylaws of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov concerning the nomination and election of officers be changed in such a manner that the nomination and election of officers be executed in one and the same meeting, as it is being <pb facs="5418478_7_0959.jpg" n="2"/>done in many other societies. In the discussion which followed, Mr. Smejkal urged Mr. Friedl, a representative of the grand lodge of the Bohemian Slavonic Society, to explain why this change is asked. Mr. Friedl then made the following statement:</p>
   <p>"Although the management of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov, which is purely a national and people's project, is excellent, this does not mean that it could not be improved. By this proposed change, an opportunity would probably be given many able representatives to hold an office, and this would be to the advantage of this organization."</p>
   <p>Both communications were accepted and filed, and Mr. Kopecky then presented a motion that both of these organizations present their proposals in writing at the next meeting in regard to this change of the bylaws.</p>
   <p>Mr. Filip then read the minutes of the consultatory meeting of the officers of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov held November 27, 1920, in which donations for <pb facs="5418478_7_0960.jpg" n="3"/>various purposes were discussed and approved. The meeting was attended by the following officers: Mr. Jan Pecha, president; Mr. Josef Ringl, vice-president; Mr. Victor H. Filip, secretary; Mr. Josef Jurka, treasurer; and members of the auditing committee. Their report reads:</p>
   <p>"This year, as usual, the officers are taking the liberty of recommending to the representatives of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov the following New Year's donations to the following organizations and institutions: To the Bohemian Free Thought Schools of Chicago, the sum of three thousand dollars; to the Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage, one thousand dollars; to the Jan Huss Memorial Association, five hundred dollars; to the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies' hall on 18th Street, five hundred dollars; to the F. B. Zdrubek School, one hundred dollars; to the Council on Higher Education, fifty dollars. The officers recommend the above-mentioned donations, and the representatives may rest assured that these donations have been recommended by them only after due consideration."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0961.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The donations were then approved by the representatives without change, and it was recommended that checks for the above-mentioned sums be made out and sent to the respective organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
