<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-08">Mar. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">An Important Matter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1390</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1390.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-03-08">Mar. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AN IMPORTANT MATTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The moment that the United States declared war on Germany, many of our fellow countrymen joined the Army and Navy as volunteers, while later on, others hastened to the recruiting stations when compulsory service was introduced for the fight against our age-old enemy. Soon after, the declaration of war against Austria followed. According to an international agreement, the United States cannot call Czechs to arms while they are still counted among Austrian subjects. It is also, for technical reasons, not feasible to accept Austro-Hungarian subjects into the American Army for service at the front. The United States Army headquarters decided, therefore, to put before all Austro-Hungarian subjects the alternatives of either staying with that part of the United States Army which remains in America, or leaving this country.</p>
   <p>A large number of our fellow countrymen are eager to meet the enemy in the field. They are, however, compelled to wait until a new law is passed, <pb facs="5418478_7_1391.jpg" n="2"/>allowing them to go to the front, if such a law is passed. It just happened that some of our young men forgot that they are sons of Czech or Slovak parents, and that they are under a twofold obligation to defend the country which has entered a terrible war to fight for a just cause. They are dodging their duty, using either the perfidious excuse that they are Austro-Hungarian subjects, or they lie by contending that they do not want to fight against their own brothers in the old country. And so they stay at home, cowards. Cases such as these are, heaven to be thanked, only exceptional, yet they serve to besmirch the name of our Czechoslovak element in America. Shame and scorn upon him who would cloak his cowardice with such excuses!</p>
   <p>It is now easy to clear the way for Austro-Hungarian subjects of Czech or Slovak descent to join our Czechoslovak Army. He who does not want to stay at home may address himself to one of our trustees, one who is already in the American Army, but, for reasons mentioned above, is not permitted to fight <pb facs="5418478_7_1392.jpg" n="3"/>across the Ocean. These trustees are at liberty to explain to the military authorities who surely will not make it difficult for anyone to join our Czechoslovak Army. If, however, he has given his promise to join, he is duty bound to keep his word.</p>
   <p>Fellow countrymen! The main issue is to uphold the honor of the Czechoslovak people in America! When this country will have felt the full burden of the war, when the Star-Spangled Banner will have been drenched with the red, precious blood of our American boys, when thousands and thousands of American soldiers will have returned home, then America will spit upon us as Austro-Hungarians who enjoy its hospitality in a boundless measure, but who would not defend this country. America will look down upon us as rats who, in cowardice, are ready to betray anyone.</p>
   <p>The United States is mobilizing new contingents apace,and we must do likewise; we must keep abreast with the American Army.</p>
   <p>Hence, those who cannot help the Allies within their own ranks should rally <pb facs="5418478_7_1393.jpg" n="4"/>under our own banner of liberty! The Czechoslovak Army is the best guarantee for our future independence, and everyone of us should, therefore, feel duty bound to join it.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovak Army is made up of Czechs and Slovaks who happen to be beyond the German and Austro-Hungarian borders. This is done with the full consent of the Allies and the United States. It is especially sponsored by the French Government and its head.</p>
   <p>The permission to keep up our own Czechoslovak Army is tantamount with the recognition of an independent Czechoslovak state....Volunteers! Report at your district office of the Military Committee of the Czechoslovak National Council.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
