<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-29">Sept. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's Meeting of Bohemian Catholics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0969</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0969.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-29">Sept. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">YESTERDAY'S MEETING OF BOHEMIAN CATHOLICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A select group of local Bohemian Catholics met in the newly decorated auditorium of the Bohemian-American Hall yesterday and filled the great auditorium and galleries to capacity long before the stipulated time. The Bohemian Catholics met in the auditorium on the holiday of St. Wenceslaus in order to demonstrate again that, notwithstanding the circumstances, they still love their old homeland with the same fervor, that they are willing to undergo the greatest sacrifices with the same enthusiasm as they showed in the recent struggle for liberation. They also demonstrated that they are ready to defend the heritage of their fathers, the faith St. Wenceslaus, which cannot be taken away from them.</p>
   <p>All the speakers expressed themselves in that manner, and they were often applauded loudly by the audience. All the speakers unanimously voiced a firm belief in the brilliant future of our nation and expressed the hope that someday <pb facs="5418478_7_0970.jpg" n="2"/>all the Slavs will unite, invigorated again, and will witness the unexpected growth of the faith of the Slavonic apostles, Cyril and Methodius.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order by Mr. Vaclav Radous, chairman of the Chicago district executive committee of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku (Federation of Bohemian Catholics) who in his brief speech greeted the audience and introduced Reverend Frantisek Bozenek. His appearance aroused such continuous applause that this popular speaker had to beg the audience to give him a chance to say something. In his beautiful speech he first mentioned that he firmly believes in the brilliant future of our nation. It is true that conditions in our old homeland are not as the Bohemian Catholics would like to have them. But it is necessary to take into consideration the fact that a real chaos of opinions and ideas reigns there, and of course it will require a longer period of time before everything is crystallized and stabilized, and then conditions, even in regard to the spiritual life, will be altogether different. There is no reason to be despondent and discouraged, but it is necessary to work diligently and hope for the best. Such is the duty of every Bohemian Catholic.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0971.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He then explained the purpose of the National St. Wenceslaus Tax and urged everybody to contribute toward this noble cause according to the best of his ability. Reverend Bozenek reaped long applause for his hearty and patriotic speech.</p>
   <p>Then Mr. Hynek Dostal, an editor, took the floor. He said that the Slavs who are just awakening from their sleep are heading toward a great future. "Just let them hammer into us, let them oppress and whip us. We, the Slavs, are just like a willow--the more the willow is trimmed, the more it grows, and the more we luxuriate and grow powerful."....</p>
   <p>Toward the end of this memorable meeting, the St. Prokopius Parish Choir, under the leadership of its conductor, Mr. Quido Petru, Sr., sang the magnificent St. Wenceslaus choral, and the audience soon joined in the majestic refrains, so that even the conclusion of this meeting was most dignified.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
