<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-03">Mar. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Meeting of the Bohemian National Cemetery Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0933</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0933.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-03">Mar. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE MEETING OF THE BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting of the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova (Bohemian National Cemetery Association) was held yesterday in the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies hall, at 18th and May Streets, with a meagre attendance of the delegates. The meeting was called to order by Mr. Jan Pecha, chairman, at 8 P.M. sharp. Mr. Victor H. Filip, secretary, then read the minutes of the previous meeting, which were adopted as read. Inasmuch as there were no letters received by the Association last month, the manager of the cemetery, Mr. Longin Tuma, began the reading of bills for the month of February. All the bills were approved and referred for payment.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Tuma then announced that recently, he and Mr. Smejkal attended the meeting of managers of all the Chicago cemeteries, where the present cost of cemetery equipment and prevailing conditions were discussed. Mr. Smejkal then reported that all the cemetery associations intend to cut down the wages of their employees, because the cemetery business, taken from a purely political point <pb facs="5418478_7_0934.jpg" n="2"/>of view, is not a profitable proposition.</p>
   <p>He also compared the prices charged for flowers at other cemeteries with ours, and said that at our cemetery it is possible to buy any decorations for graves, including flowers, much cheaper than anywhere else. At other cemeteries, for instance, there is a special charge for watering the flowers and mowing the grass. If our cemetery followed this example and made charges for this work, which at present is being done free, then a sum ranging between fifteen and twenty thousand dollars could be obtained annually.....</p>
   <p>Receipts for the month of February amounted to $14,631.75. Expenses amounted  to $9,249.07. Twenty-two lots worth $5,781.50 were sold during the month of February. There were twenty-two burials and ten cremations. The sum of $4,998.30 was paid out to forty-nine employees. Following the roll call of delegates, the meeting was adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
