<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-05-31">May 31, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Decoration Day Celebration at the Bohemian National Cemetery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-05-31">May 31, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">DECORATION DAY CELEBRATION AT THE BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1--Yesterday's grave decorating celebration at the Bohemian National Cemetery was one of those events which touches the heart-strings of human feelings. For that reason there was not a single participant, who did not show signs of sadness, enthusiasm, indeed, even exultation. The speakers, who addressed the thousands of Czech people gathered there, were able to arouse memories, that echoed the sentiments of the hearers. A great mass of people gathered around a flower covered mount, where stands the dignified monument to a Civil War soldier, to listen to the words of the speakers who spoke of the history of our new country, describing the merits of the soldiers whose memories were being observed. The Bohemian speaker remarked that the Bohemian people could also celebrate on this 30th day of May an important happening in their own history, the battle of Lipan not far from "Ceskeho Brodu." This was a battle for humanity, freedom, and equality. Our nation fought for liberty and justice almost 500 years ago, when other nationalities were still suffering in the fetters of serfdom.</p>
   <p>The celebration was attended, in addition to the veterans of the Civil War, by the Bohemian Sharpshooters Society, which has eighty members, who stood <pb facs="5418478_7_0299.jpg" n="2"/>guard at the monument to the fallen soldiers of the Civil War; they were joined by about thirty Bohemian veterans of the Spanish-American war.</p>
   <p>The parade which took place before the celebration formed at half past ten in the morning in front of the property of the "Old People's Home and Orphanage," from where it moved toward the cemetery with Governor Deneen and Judge McEwen in the lead. In the parade were trumpeters and musician veterans of the Civil and Spanish-American wars, sharpshooters and the public.</p>
   <p>The attendance was very large, the parade extending beyond the "Old Peoples Home." The celebration was attended by over 5,000 persons, however, the entire attendance may readily be estimated at 15,000. Honor belongs to our heroes whom we shall always remember sincerely.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
