<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-09-01">Sept. 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Yearly Inspection of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1198</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1198.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-09-01">Sept. 1, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A YEARLY INSPECTION OF THE CESKY NARODNI HRBITOV</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday morning brought together fifty representatives of various Bohemian organizations who compose the board of trustees of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery). They met at the Cemetery in order to undertake the regular annual inspection under the guidance of the executive committee, composed of Messrs. Smejkal, Kralovec, and Kopcky. Manager Tuma was on hand to point out all improvements, additions, and changes that took place during the past year.....</p>
   <p>The inspection tour started in the basement of the administration building, which just recently received a new outer wall replacing the old wooden one, which had to be removed because of its poor condition.....</p>
   <p>The next stop was the boiler room, which has now been separated from the hothouse by a new wall.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1199.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The pumping station, where things are as they were last year with the exception of a few minor details was visited only for the benefit of new representatives who were not yet familiar with all of the equipment of the Cemetery.....</p>
   <p>From the pumping station the group was conducted through the Cemetery proper and had occasion to express satisfaction on the excellent condition of the walks and lanes, and to inspectthe newly opened section of the grounds.....</p>
   <p>Someone remarked on the American flags with which a number of graves were decorated....and received the explanation that the graves thus marked are the graves of the deceased members of the Cemetery board of trustees.....</p>
   <p>The principal point of interest, however, was the burial vaults where the proposed crematorium is to be built.....The explanation as to how the crematorium will fit into the present picture, where it will be placed, where the new chapel will stand, and what part of the proposed building will be <pb facs="5418478_7_1200.jpg" n="3"/>devoted to use as a columbariun was given by Mr. Randak, the architect whose plans have been adopted by the board of trustees.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
