<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-26">Sept. 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Associational</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1522</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1522.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-26">Sept. 26, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ASSOCIATIONAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of our junior clubs founded by the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) recently put on an amateur theatrical performance, the principal significance of which is that it indicates the Club's interest in national work. This does not mean that all that our junior clubs do is to put on shows; in fact, they are finding many other fields for their activities, but the main thing is that they do work, that they are active, which is of particular importance just now when all our fraternal organizations have to turn to our young people for new membership. There is no relying upon new immigration, since so very few people are coming to America these days, and it is easy to imagine that there will not be many young and healthy men left in Europe after the war. Therefore our junior clubs are now more important than ever before and should be organized and encouraged whenever there is an opportunity. This activity has not been quite satisfactory among the young people of our Chicago, although there is a rich and fertile field for it here that should be fully taken advantage of.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1523.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Soon the cold weather will set in, a time when club meetings and other gatherings should be showing a greater attendance than in summer. As a rule they do, but even so, the attendance is not so good as it should be. No doubt it would be well if the membership would pledge an improvement in that respect, promising to one another regular attendance at the meetings of their organizations and showing in that way their interest in the work.</p>
   <p>George Washington Lodge Number Sixty-six of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky celebrated yesterday its thirty-fifth anniversary with a party in the Ceskoanglicka Svobodomyslna Skola (Bohemian-English Free Thought School).....</p>
   <p>A new branch was added in Morton Park to the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Bohemian Ladies' Union) last Sunday. It has the name of Mir Cechie (Cechia, Peace) and has almost seventy members.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
