<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-14">June 14, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Fourth of July Parade to Be Lead by Bohemians They Will Probably Be Accompanied by the Slovaks</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0251</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0251.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-14">June 14, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE FOURTH OF JULY PARADE TO BE LEAD BY BOHEMIANS THEY WILL PROBABLY BE ACCOMPANIED BY THE SLOVAKS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Karel Vopicka, the chairman of the central committee of the Association for a sane Fourth of July celebration, announced at yesterday's meeting that it had been decided that the nationalities participating in the parade would march in alphabetical order. Because in the English alphabet Bohemians come before British, we Bohemians find ourselves in first position in the order of the parade. The Arabs and Austrians who, under this order, would come ahead of the Bohemians are not participating. However, even if it were only through circumstance that this honor is bestowed upon us, we can still be proud of it. We should make every effert to use this excellent opportunity to make the best showing possible before the public.</p>
   <p>The meeting was brought to order by the chairman of the Association, Mr. John A. Cervenka, <pb facs="5418478_7_0252.jpg" n="2"/>who briefly explained the situation. The committees then reported on what had been accomplished. Since success is dependant primarily on the financial means, the treasurer of the finance committee, Mr. Hajicek, took the floor and brought the reassuring report that a total of $577 already had been raised for the celebration. To be sure, this is far from enough, so in order that we might represent ourselves in the manner that we would wish, and as would be proper as we have been allotted first place, it is expected that at least twice the amount already in hand will be raised before the next meeting. There is no doubt that our leaders will not be miserly when our dignified representation is concerned.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vopicka announced that the central organization would furnish music for all parks, so that local branches will have no expenses in that respect. For the parade, each nationality will provide its own band.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0253.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Anton Dolezal announced that several Sokol drill exhibitions would be given in various parks, also that folk dances would be given. It was left to Mr. Dolezal to make the necessary arrangements.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cervenka announced that bids had been received from three firms which engage in the construction of allegorical wagons, for the construction of a Bohemian allegorical wagon. The Industrial and Historical Pageant Corporation made the most satisfactory bid for the building of a representative Bohemian wagon, according to the specifications of the artists, Korbel and Kosar. They will build the wagon for $380, whereas the other firms ask $500 or more. In addition, the firm gives the delegates the opportunity to oversee the work, and agree to heed their wishes, even if it should be necessary to make changes. This is surely an advantageous proposal, and it was accepted.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vopicka then brought up for discussion the question of Slovak <pb facs="5418478_7_0254.jpg" n="4"/>participation. He expressed fear that perhaps many of them would go into the parade with the Hungarians, and asked that agitation be started among them to ascertain if they wish to take part in the celebration, to either march with the Bohemians, or independantly. There is no doubt that brother Slovaks will give preference to the company of Bohemians over that of the Hungarians. It would not be dignified for any Slovak to be seen in the company of his greatest enemy, the Hungarian. We would be sincerely joyful if the Slovak societies and newspapers took this matter up, and began to work as quickly as possible. Mr. Vopicka will see to it, although it is somewhat late, that a place is provided for them in the parade.</p>
   <p>The parade will be made up of uniformed societies only. No one will be allowed to parade in civilian clothes.</p>
   <p>Dr. Jaroslav Vojan complained that the Chicago Tribune did not mention <pb facs="5418478_7_0255.jpg" n="5"/>that Bohemians are to take part in the parade, and that he will start agitation to induce all English newspapers to write about Bohemian participation.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ort reports that he has circularized all sokol and singing societies, asking them to take part in the celebration, but thus far has not received any replies, because the societies have not held meetings. The matter of speakers for the various parks was left up to Mr. Vopicka.</p>
   <p>The main Bohemian celebration will be held in Douglas Park. A celebration will also be held in Svatopluk Cech Park, and a suitable program will be given in the playground at Twenty-eight Street, and Sawyer Avenue, where Mr. Dibelka will speak for the Bohemians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
