<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-08-06">Aug. 6, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Bohemians Honor the Memory of Karel Havlicek</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0277</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0277.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-08-06">Aug. 6, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO BOHEMIANS HONOR THE MEMORY OF KAREL HAVLICEK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At last the day came when Bohemian-American people were able to pay homage to the great Brixen martyr, and commemorate the fiftieth anniversary of the death of Karel Havlicek Borovsky. Even nature was kind to this celebration, and although the early morning did not indicate that the day would be clear, it turned out to be very suitable for the occasion, and instilled a festive mood into the hearts of sincere Bohemian inhabitants of our district.</p>
   <p>From early morning on, there was unusual activity on the streets of our Bohemian "Pilsen," which indicated that something out of the ordinary was taking place, something which was beyond humdrum life. The Bohemians, stimulated by some mysterious elixir, showed more life, more enthusiasm, no longer appearing to be the people of whom it could be said that they could not become interested or enthusiastic about anything.</p>
   <p>Our Bohemian settlement was elaborately decorated with national emblems, <pb facs="5418478_7_0278.jpg" n="2"/>especially in places through which the festive parade was to proceed. Those who had not decorated their places of business or their windows on Saturday did so hurriedly today.</p>
   <p>Our people awakened yesterday feeling that it was their duty to pay homage to the memory of their fearless fighter, Karel Havlicek Borovsky, for otherwise they would have been shamed by our countrymen in the old country, where the memory of Havlicek is celebrated by a great national holiday.</p>
   <p>It was a feeling of sincere enthusiasm which governed everyone yesterday, for the participants in the celebration gathered, not by force of any command, but out of reverence for a great man, to show their respect and at the same time express their joy over the fact that from the midst of our people there came a man so energetic and of such a distinguished character, who in the righteous battle for the national heritage of his people was scornful not only of his own liberty but of the happiness of his family, being concerned only to preparing a better future for his people.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0279.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At 2:00 o'clock sharp the ringing strains of the band were heard, and the picturesque procession moved from the starting point down 18th Street. At the Bohemian-American School the parade was joined by the Sokol groups associated with the Miroslav Tyrs circuit; at the Sokol Pilsen Hall the rest of the Sokol societies fell in line.</p>
   <p>The parade, which was made especially picturesque by the varicolored uniforms of the Sokols, arrived at the ceremonial grounds at 4:00 P.M. Hundreds of people greeted the parade along the line of march, and such a great throng accompanied the marchers to the Pilsen Brewing Company's grove that the place was almost immediately filled to capacity.</p>
   <p>An atmosphere of reverence seemed to reign over one at the time. A feeling of inexpressible pride filled the hearts of all those present, when the masses of our Bohemian people were seen, for truly it was the flower of our Bohemian-American nation, which was not ashamed of its language, which sincerely felt Bohemian. Many were absent whose duty it was to attend the <pb facs="5418478_7_0280.jpg" n="4"/>celebration, but let them settle that with their own conscience.</p>
   <p>The flag-bearers grouped themselves around the statue of Havlicek, and the rest of the participants gathered about the speakers' platform. The chairman of the arrangements committee welcomed those present and declared that the celebration had begun. The Central Singing Society then sang a festive hymn by Kalas. Professor Zmrhal then appeared on the speakers' platform and addressed the public with a characteristic speech, which, although unaffected, was ornamanted with new ideas and impressed itself indelibly upon the minds of the listeners. The festive mood was greatly enhanced by the rendition of the song "Spi Havlicku!" by the Daughters of the Czechoslovak Benevolent Society. Enthusiasm was at its height when the Pilsen Sokol band, under the direction of bandmaster Rubringer, played our national hymn, "Kde Domov Muj?". After Professor J. J. Kral's speech the band played Mach's overture "Karel Havlicek Borovsky," and then Miss Ella Jesenska recited Muzik's poem "Za Havlickem" delightfully. The multitude listened to the young lady's words so attentively that we believe not a single word was <pb facs="5418478_7_0281.jpg" n="5"/>missed by anyone, Miss Jesenska proved in this instance that not only is she a true and sincere Bohemian, who feels in her heart every word of this patriotic poem, but that she is a remarkable artist as well. Mrs. Karolina Janecek addressed the audience on behalf of Czech women. After the conclusion of Mrs. Janecek's speech, the band played selections from "The Bartered Bride." Dr. L. Wistein, well known for her activities in Czech circles, was then presented to the public. She spoke in English on the significance of Havliceks influence.</p>
   <p>The evening program consisted of a concert, and recitations by several wellknown actors. An informal dance was held at the conclusion of the ceremonies.</p>
   <p>Those were impressive moments that we spent amid that mass of enthusiastic countrymen of ours. We felt ourselves to be one powerful family, of one Czech mother. A smoldering feeling of love for a sacred national cause was awakened within us. This feeling burst into great enthusiasm, it overwhelmed the great multitude, it inspired us to noble effort, and acquainted us to a <pb facs="5418478_7_0282.jpg" n="6"/>considerable measure with the spiritual life of one of our great leaders, who sacrificed for the Czech people his life and everything that was dear to him.</p>
   <p>Let the near future bless the results of our united efforts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
