<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-07-09">July 9, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">In Memory of Jan Hus.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0323</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0323.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-07-09">July 9, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">IN MEMORY OF JAN HUS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Saturday, July 7, the memory of Jan Hus was solemnly celebrated in the Pilzen Sokol Hall. As a start there was shown a dramatic play by J. Kaj. Tyl, entitled "Jan Hus" presented very successfully. The main characters were in the hands of experienced ameteurs: Sophie, wife of King Vaclav IV, was played by Mrs. H. Stejskal; the part of Marketa, Hus' mother, was presented by Mrs. M. Vaskova; Jan Hus by F. B. Zdrubek; Jan Zizka by A. Pregler; Petro Angelo, Cardinal and Pope's delegate, was played by Jos. Zak. All these amateurs were well-known as dramatically experienced.</p>
   <p>Strange as it may seem, the editors of Svornost were partaking in the play and each was very busy with the interpretation of his part in the drama - as Zikmund, the German Emperor; the Roman Catholic Pope, Jan XXIII, the Archbishop of Praha, and consequently, all our editors condemned Jan Hus, portrayed by the chief editor, F. B. Zdrubek.</p>
   <p>It is so impossible for us to give the correct details or the real criticism of the play because every one of the editors was so absorbed with his own <pb facs="5418478_7_0324.jpg" n="2"/>part that is was simply impossible for him to observe critically the interpretation of other actors and it is not our wish to praise ourselves. The hall was over-filled. All intelligent Bohemians were present; we don't know what had attracted the public more - the drama or the editors of Svornost.</p>
   <p>The second part of the celebration, the dance, finished late in the night, will be remembered for a long time by the countrymen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
