<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-10">Feb. 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A Czech's Military Career</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1395</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1395.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-10">Feb. 10, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A CZECH'S MILITARY CAREER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are several officers in Camp Grant, Rockford, Illinois, who come from Czech-American stock. One is a Chicagoan, Captain John F. Zajicek, one of the instructors who is considered an expert in gunnery. This was recognized by the authorities, for he was awarded no less than four distinctions.</p>
   <p>He had been in Camp Grant even before the first contingents from Chicago arrived there. He acted in the capacity of engineer, directing the construction of the water system, canalization, and other work in the building line carried on by the United States Government. Considering the magnitude of this enterprise, it is evident that Captain Zajicek's position was a highly responsible one. After the work was done, Captain Zajicek was appointed an instructor, and as such proved himself to be not only an efficient, but also a popular officer. Our Czech-American soldiers there found him friendly toward the people from which he descended. Though he has spent most of his time outside of Czech circles, he has not forgotten the land of his forebears.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1396.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Numerous letters from our boys mention the Czech-American captain who is ready to explain things in the Czech language when our soldiers know Czech better than English.</p>
   <p>Captain Zajicek is twenty-eight years of age. He was born in Chicago, and in his early years he embarked upon a soldier's career by joining the United States Navy. In those times the Denni Hlasatel used to receive and publish his letters sent from all corners of the world, particularly South America. He was a sailor on the "Tennessee" when this man-of-war brought President Taft to Panama.</p>
   <p>After he had served his term in the Navy, he studied engineering. When the United States declared war on Germany, he enlisted as an instructor and later studied in the military schools at Fort Leavenworth and Fort Sheridan. After this he was sent to a regiment of engineers in Texas. There he was promoted to the rank of captain and later placed in charge of the work at Camp Grant. He wears the highest decoration bestowed in the Army for achievements in gunnery.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1397.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Captain Zajicek's parents live at 2329 West 18th Place, Chicago, and are surely justified in rejoicing over the successes of their son.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
