<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-03">May 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Model Labor Organization</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1429</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1429.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-03">May 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A MODEL LABOR ORGANIZATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Press Bureau of the Czech National Alliance)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the entrance of the United States into the war a duty has been laid upon Czech-Americans--the duty of proving our loyalty to this Republic, which has revived the tradition of its early struggle for independence by its participation in the fight for the liberation of mankind from military despotism. Our enlightened Czech-American workingmen are following the shining example of their brethren across the ocean, especially those of Paris, France. These men responded to the roar of the first cannon-shots. Czech Sokols (members of gymnastic societies) and socialists alike enlisted for service in the French Army. Our Czech-American workingmen are doing their duty to their own race and to mankind. They are setting an excellent example for others. Hundreds of young workmen have joined the United States Army; they have heeded the call sent out by Mr. Kupka, commander of the Czech Legion in France.</p>
   <p>These hundreds of volunteers who come from Chicago and from various other <pb facs="5418478_7_1430.jpg" n="2"/>Czech-American communities deserve the fullest recognition and sympathy of our commonwealth.</p>
   <p>This sympathy, let us hope, will not be purely of a platonic nature but will be accompanied by practical gestures, as exemplified by the action of Pekarska Unie (Bakers' Union) Number 13 in Chicago, from which seven Czechs and one Slovak enlisted. The following resolution was passed by this Union:</p>
   <p>"All those who enlist shall receive a withdrawal card, and the Czech Bakers' Union will pay for them their dues to the International Union so that they shall be insured against sickness, and their dependents against the event of their decease. Those who are wounded or are taken sick on the battlefield shall receive $7 weekly for the duration of sixteen weeks; only the certification of the military medical authorities will be required. In case of death the heirs shall receive a lump sum of $75 to $400, according to the number of years of membership. In case a soldier shall not return within a year, the <pb facs="5418478_7_1431.jpg" n="3"/>Union shall renew his withdrawal card from its own funds."</p>
   <p>This resolution by the Bakers' Union will be written in golden letters into the annals of the movement for the liberation of the Czech people. We sincerely hope that this example will be [extensively] emulated in one form or another.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Czech Sokol gymnastic societies were politically active for the liberation of the Czechs.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
