<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-03-29">March 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Komensky Celebration.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0313</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0313.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-03-29">March 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">KOMENSKY CELEBRATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Arranging a celebration honoring J. A. Komensky, in strange premises and inviting as the principal speaker a distinguished American, as the National Committee recommended, was a very fortunate thought and its actual carrying out, brought Bohemians a much greater moral success than a whole row of such entertainments as had been customary with us on like occasions. It was a celebration such as we should have had - it was a celebration the like of which we should arrange at least once each year; and then we surely would be able to silence slanderous mouths which often harm us more because of ignorance, rather than from hatred.</p>
   <p>Our Bohemian public attended in considerable numbers, although we candidly admit, that we expected many more. We understand that there were about fourteen hundred Bohemians and some Americans at the Musicians Hall, though <pb facs="5418478_7_0314.jpg" n="2"/>only a few of the latter. Since there was also held a Komensky celebration in the Methodist Church Block, with the well-known Rev. Bristol as speaker, which also was attended largely by Bohemians, the cause for the Musicians Hall not being filled to capacity can readily be seen.</p>
   <p>The celebration began with an organ recital by Mr. Falk. Immediately there-after, the chairman, Mr. Matousek, introduced Mr. Jos. Cermak, who delivered a short prologue in the Bohemian language. Following Mr. Cermak, Mr. Vickers was introduced and he spoke briefly on the rise and fall of Bohemian and the causes that brought it about. The chairman then introduced the principal speaker, Mr. Donnelly, who spoke mostly of the life and accomplishments of J. A. Komensky. The celebration was concluded with an organ selection by Mr. Falk. As we mentioned previously the moral results were excellent and the financial result is likewise satisfactory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
