<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-14">Sept. 14, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Ninth Convention of the Jednota Ceskych Dam</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0388</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0388.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-14">Sept. 14, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">NINTH CONVENTION OF THE JEDNOTA CESKYCH DAM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's session of the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Bohemian Ladies Unity) was not called to order until 3 P. M., on account of the excursion to the Stock Yards. The ladies returned from the Stock Yards exhausted but, nevertheless, at once commenced to work, in order to finish as soon as possible. The work of amending the constitution having been accomplished, there remained to be considered only various proposals for the good of the organization, donations to various purposes, resolutions and similar matters. The next seat of the central committee will be New York, which won over the State of Ohio. Only these two states were proposed, and 794 votes were cast for New York and 337 votes for the State of Ohio.....</p>
   <p>The next convention of the Jednota Ceskych Dam will be held in New York <pb facs="5418478_7_0389.jpg" n="2"/>six years from now.</p>
   <p>The afternoon session was adjourned at 5:30 P. M.</p>
   <p>After supper the delegates commenced to work again, and the election of officers for the central committee came up. Those elected were: Sister Marie Havranek, chairman; Sister Bozena Stolfa, vice-chairman; Sister Marie Zeman, secretary; Sister Marie Vojtisek, financial secretary; Sister Antonie Safarik, treasurer; Sister Barbora Lankas, sergeant at arms; Sisters Marie Machovsky and Josefa Zoudlik, members of the board of trustees.</p>
   <p>The session then adjourned unitl the following morning at nine o'clock.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
