<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-31">May 31, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Decoration Day Ceremonies at Ressurection Cemetery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0266</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0266.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-31">May 31, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">DECORATION DAY CEREMONIES AT RESSURECTION CEMETERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A dignified Memorial Day celebration was held yesterday at the newest Bohemian cemetery, the Resurrection Catholic Cemetery, near Summit. Enormous crowds of Bohemians, Slovaks, and Poles, gathered there to do homage to the soldiers buried there, and to decorate the graves of their departed loved ones. Although this was only the fifth time that Decoration Day has been observed at this cemetery, still, according to the words of the Rev. Thomas F. Bobal, almost nine hundred bodies have been buried there in the short period of the existence of the cemetery. Bohemian lodges participated in the ceremonies, and numerous individuals met at about 8 A.M. at 50th Street and Hermitage Avenue, from whence they marched to 47th &amp; Damen Avenue to board street cars, which carried them to the city limits. There inter-urban cars were boarded, and the trip to the cemetery was continued.</p>
   <p>Arriving at the cemetery, the participants rested a while. They formed a column, and to the tune of a funeral march, proceeded to the Speakers' platform, around <pb facs="5418478_7_0267.jpg" n="2"/>which they grouped themselves. Mr. Joseph R. Vojtech welcomed those who were present, and expressed his pleasure over the large attendance of countrymen, and brother Slovaks. He thanked the lodges for their participation, and introduced the other speakers. Mr. Frank Jilek gave a short talk, comparing the American holiday with the Bohemian holiday, during which children decorate the graves of their parents and parents decorate the graves of children from whom they have been separated by death. At present, there rests in the Resurrection cemetery six comrades, who were buried there in a short period of time, and it is possible that in a year's time their ranks will be increased by several of us.</p>
   <p>Mr. Frank B. Brom, commander of Sokol Borivoj, recollected the immeasurable sacrifices soldiers make to their country, in leaving their families and occupations to go to battle. Then followed the speech of the Rev. Thomas F. Bobal of Saints Cyril and Methodius church, in Town of Lake. The Rev. Bobal, after the conclusion of his talk, said a prayer, such as is used on All Soul's Day in the old country. The parade then moved on to the grave of veteran Vaclav Kolar. This grave was decorated with many flags, and the Societies returned to the place of assembly, in order to disband. With that the program was ended.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
