<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-03-28">March 28, 1892</date><title level="a">J. A. Komensky Memorial Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0315</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0315.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1892-03-28">March 28, 1892</date><title level="a">J. A. Komensky Memorial Celebration</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today it is three hundred years since the birth of Jan Amos Komensky. Who was Komensky? What did he do, that all civilized nations celebrate his memory, that with great respect they speak his name? Komensky was the teacher of all teachers. He knew that the foundation of happiness of all people began in the good upbringing of youth, and all his efforts were concentrated on this objective. Chicago Bohemians are celebrating his distinguished memory at the Music Hall, today. We take it for granted that it is not necessary to remind Bohemians as to their duty. Whoever claims to be a sincere Bohemian will overcome all obstacles which may stand in his way, in order to be present at today's celebration.</p>
   <p>Let no one use as an excuse, that everything spoken about Komensky is already generally known, a large attendance of Bohemians will have a very important meaning. We continually pride ourselves on our liberality, we continually pride ourselves on our Bohemianism, every little while we are showing to Americans of what meritorious masters the Bohemian nation can boast. So today we are to prove that we not only boast of these masters but that we know how to respect their memory with dignity.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0316.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Tonight we will find out all the Bohemians who are ready to prove these facts, and who they are who only talk.</p>
   <p>We expect that our entire intelligentsia will make a rendezvous of Music Hall, and that what strangers have to say about the Bohemian people and the great sons will be carefully followed.</p>
   <p>The celebration will commence at eight o'clock sharp, and it would be quite proper for the public to be in the respective seats earlier that there will be no interruptions made by late comers after the program has started.</p>
   <p>The celebration will be opened by the Chairman of the Committee, Mr. Matousek, after which the eminent organist, Mr. Falk, will render a ceremonial choral.Mr. Jos. Cermak will deliver the prologue and following him Mr. Vickers will appear, and describe the period of the decline of the Bohemian nation.</p>
   <p>Following Mr. Vickers will be the principal speaker of the evening, Mr. Donnelly, <pb facs="5418478_7_0317.jpg" n="3"/>who will speak on the influence of Komensky. Mr. Donnelly is known as a highly educated man and an extraordinary speaker and we are certain that the Committee's choice will prove to be a good one.</p>
   <p>All necessary arrangements have been made and it now depends only on the Bohemian public to likewise attend in full number, and we believe it will do so.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
