<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-27">Dec. 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">December Issue of Hlidka</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0950</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0950.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-27">Dec. 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">DECEMBER ISSUE OF HLIDKA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America) published its fifth number of the Hlidka (Sentinel), an organ which has been very sympathetically accepted by all classes of our Bohemian-American people. Many of our prominent countrymen and various institutions have requested that this organ be sent to them. A large number of copies of the Hlidka are sent every month to our old homeland. Parish and district alliances continuously ask that more copies be sent to them, and it is apparent that the instructions and programs published in the Hlidka are very useful.</p>
   <p>This December number has a very timely article, "Na Sklonku Roku" (Toward the End of the Year), in which the editor and members of the executive board give a resume of the work accomplished during the year. Another very important article is, "Americanization Does Not Mean a Denial of One's Birth and a Repudiation of One's Mother Tongue". In this article the author analyzes right and wrong Americanization. The article is very important and should be read at <pb facs="5418478_7_0951.jpg" n="2"/>our organizations' meetings, because it is very informative. Also, there is an article called, "The Private Schools Shall Not Be Restricted by the States". The article appeared in the Government bulletin on schools and was translated into the Bohemian language. The article deals with our parish schools and concerns all Bohemian Catholics of America. The translator won the favor of our district and parish alliances by his translation and also by his other article, "From Czechoslovakia," in which he presents the latest information on conditions in our old homeland. Another article, "What We Have Accomplished," brings attention to the gifts given by the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku to various institutions. Read only the letters of thanks from those who received the gifts and then you will understand why the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku is growing. In the article, "Our Organization," instructions are given to our district and parish alliances for the winter period. Every one of our workers should read these instructions in order that wide-awake activity may be evidenced in our alliances during the winter.</p>
   <p>There is plenty of material to work on. All that is necessary is a good will.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0952.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Anyone who understands and comprehends the importance of this organization cannot stop his activity; on the contrary, he will always try to invigorate and broaden his work.. Our organization is a good guide.</p>
   <p>From the contents of this issue of Hlidka, it is also apparent that a temporary employment department has been established. The secretaries of our district and parish alliances should read the contents of the Hlidka at the monthly meetings of their alliances, and any important article should be discussed. The Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku is such an important organization for our Bohemian Catholic life that there should not be a meeting in which the name of this organization is not mentioned. Each parish should then see to it that an alliance is established in every parish, so that next year there will not be a single Bohemian Catholic parish in America which is not a member of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku. There is nothing difficult about it, because in every one of our parishes there is an enlightened countryman who is able to explain the importance of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
