<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-03-26">Mar. 26, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Proclamation to Bohemian Free Thought Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1005</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1005.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-03-26">Mar. 26, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">PROCLAMATION TO BOHEMIAN FREE THOUGHT SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In their sessions, the delegates to the Constitutional Convention, in Springfield, Illinois, are preparing a new constitution for the State of Illinois. A delegation of preachers and parsons is waiting in Springfield for the purpose of achieving the legalization and introduction of the study of the Bible in public schools. Not much exertion on their part will be needed, and the Convention delegates will restrict the Free Thought movement in the State of Illinois. It is necessary to take energetic action now! Therefore, a resolution is being prepared and representatives of our Free Thought societies will be sent to Springfield to check the attempt of the rash and underhanded churchmen. We request all secretaries and presidents of our Bohemian societies to be present, on Sunday, March 28, between the hours of 9 A.M. and 3 P.M., at any of the places mentioned below, to sign and seal the resolution protesting against the restriction of the Free Thought movement in this state. Then the societies that are holding their meetings this month are requested to elect one or two <pb facs="5418478_7_1006.jpg" n="2"/>representatives. These representatives will accompany the other delegates to Springfield, and by their presence will protest against the bold activities of the churchmen. Members of the Executive Committee of the Freethinkers Alliance will be present with the resolution at the following places: In the Vojta Naprstek School, at Homan and 26th Streets; the Czechoslavonic Benevolent Societies Hall, at 18th and May Streets; the Jan Hus Memorial Hall, at 4240 West 22nd Street; the Czechoslavonic Benevolent Societies Hall, at 48th and Honore Streets; the Sokol Karel Jonas Hall in Cicero. It is absolutely necessary for the president and secretary to appear together with the seal of their society, because otherwise the resolution cannot be signed. The signed resolution will be presented to the Constitutional Convention in Springfield by the Secretary of the Executive Committee, Mr. V. K. Soukup, who will represent the Freethinkers' Alliance of America.</p>
   <p>For the Freethinkers' Alliance of America, the Executive Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
