<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-22">Apr. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Defending His Country</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1438</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1438.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-04-22">Apr. 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">DEFENDING HIS COUNTRY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the officers of the U. S. Navy there is one Czech-American Nicholas Vytlacil now doing duty on a torpedo boat destroyer somewhere on the coast of Florida. We do not know if at this moment another Czech-American is serving as a naval officer, which may, in the final analysis, be possible. Vytlacil was born in Reading, Pa., twenty-two years ago; he was brought to Chicago by his parents Mr. and Mrs. Vaclav Vytlacil, 2239 S. Clifton Park Ave. He studied in the public schools and in the Czech afternoon school in the C. S. B. S. (Czech-Slavonic Benevolent Society), Hall, the Crane High School, where he studied under Mr. Fucik, present assistant principal of Carter Harrison Technical High School, who at that time taught mechanical drawing. After graduating, Mr. Vytlacil was sponsored by Congressman Mc Andrew, of the sixth congressional district, for the Naval Academy in Annapolis. After graduating from there, with the rest of his classmates, three months before regular time, he was commissioned as an ensign.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1439.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is fitting to mention that the family of our fellow-countryman Vaclav Vytlacil has distinguished itself by particular endeavor. Vaclav, the oldest son, is an artist whose paintings won one of the first prizes of the Art Institute four years ago. He now lives in New York as an artist whose creations hold out high hope for his future; he is not ashamed of his name Vaclav which figures on all his paintings. Two daughters have devoted themselves to general studies, and both have taken up the study of the Czech language also.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
