<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-14">Aug. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">To the Bohemian-American Catholics!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0764</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0764.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-14">Aug. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN CATHOLICS!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America) is calling its third general convention, which is to be held in Chicago, October 3, 4, and 5, 1922, as was decided during the last convention of the Svaz. Two years have gone by since our last convention, and during that time there has been much organizational, religious, social, and nationalistic activity. The tasks already accomplished are the best proof of the good leadership of our organization; they show that it followed its aims and that its name is unsullied. Today, everybody regards the Svaz with respect; this respect, however, was gained by unceasing activity of our organization, with the result that, today, the Svaz is known in every Bohemian Catholic community, and wherever a branch of the Svaz exists one may encounter lively activity in both the national and the religious fields. It is obvious, therefore, why everybody looks forward with pleasure to the third convention; it is expected to lead to still greater activity which will ultimately establish branches in every locality inhabited by our people. We have grown, our ranks have expanded, <pb facs="5418478_7_0765.jpg" n="2"/>and so has our work. With this, new workers are needed, such as lecturers and organizers who would be ready at all times to work for the good cause! Grave times are ahead of us and we must be prepared for them. There are a great many unsolved problems which bid us to orientate ourselves, and to become fully aware of our duties to the Narodni Svaz.</p>
   <p>The third general convention will afford opportunities to us to become more intimately acquainted and that in itself will be a measure of success. The Bohemian Catholics of America must unite into a single, peaceable but invincible body, which would defend the truth of God and our national rights against all possible attacks....</p>
   <p>All the district and parish branches of the Svaz have already received information and counsel about the preliminary work of the convention, and this will be augmented from time to time as necessary. Our clergy is kindly asked to fill out the questionnaire sent to it by the executive committee of the Svaz; this is essential for the meeting of the planning committee which <pb facs="5418478_7_0766.jpg" n="3"/>will be guided in its work by the returned questionnaires. Our Bohemian Catholic organizations are requested to send us the names of their delegates; the same should be done by the district and parochial branches of the Svaz. The convention will try to solve a great number of problems which have an intimate bearing upon the life of our Bohemian-American Catholics. Motions, suggestions, resolutions, complaints, etc...should be sent to the planning committee of the Svaz which is located in its central office, 3207 West 22nd Street, Chicago, Illinois. This must be done on or before September 15, 1922. All later communications will be disregarded.</p>
   <p>Every delegate, be he a member of the Svaz, the local union, the parish, or any other body [affiliated with the Svaz], must have credentials from his organization.</p>
   <p>Friends! Begin, all of you, to work today for the success of our third convention! Let us demonstrate our development. Our past activity was great, and will not be forgotten; but our future must be beautiful, promising, and elevating. Be untiring in your work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
