<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-23">June 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Masons</title><title level="a" type="sub">The First Bohemian Masonic Lodge Was Organized in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1234</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1234.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-23">June 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN MASONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">The First Bohemian Masonic Lodge Was Organized in Chicago</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first Bohemian Masonic Lodge on earth will be inducted in a festive manner tonight into the powerful society of Free Masons. This lodge is the Bohemia Lodge A. F. and A. M.</p>
   <p>When we say that it is the first Bohemian Masonic Lodge on earth, we mean the first that was officially authorized by the Grand Lodge. This new lodge numbers 100 charter members and its officers are the following: Karel B. Pavlicek, master; Karel J. Novak, Jr., senior warden; Joseph A. Holpuch, junior warden ; Frank E. Novak, treasurer; Otto Polanek, secretary; Harry Chochol, senior deacon; Otto J. Pelikan, junior deacon; Frank J. Pecival, senior steward; Frank Srachta, junior steward; Rev. Vaclav Vanek, chaplain; William Kolacek, marshall; Karel Novak, tyler; A. Erst, organist.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1235.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is worthy of mention that the members of this new lodge worked hard for three months before they received permission from the Grand Lodge of the State to take the name "Bohemia." Before the new lodge could be organized it was necessary to secure the permission of three prominent lodges of the neighborhood and this was granted the new lodge unanimously in each case. So far as regalia and the like are concerned, this was donated to the lodge by members and that this indicates a sizable offering, it is sufficient to say that the articles cost $900.</p>
   <p>Today's induction, which will be carried out in the West Side Masonic Temple on Oakley Avenue and Madison Street, and which will be attended by the highest dignitaries of the Free Masons, will be in conjunction with a grand banquet. The founders of this lodge confidently expect that all Bohemian Masons will become it's members.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
