<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-11">Feb. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Conference of the Czech National Alliance</title><title level="a" type="sub">Second Day (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0513</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0513.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-11">Feb. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CONFERENCE OF THE CZECH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Second Day (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The conference of the Czech National Alliance which is being held in the hall of Sokol Chicago is making rapid progress, in spite of the fact that barely one-half of the program has been disposed of. It may be said, even at this early stage, that the conference is highly important and will have far-reaching consequences. The delegates let it be known that they have come to build up, not to destroy. True enough, there is considerable fighting spirit in evidence, and many reform ideas are being given expression. But the changes demanded spring from the purest motives and from the longing to gain excellent results and to remove everything that has been obstructing progress in the past.</p>
   <p>The conference is furnishing proof that very much has been accomplished by Czech-America during the past two and one-half years, and that the beautiful <pb facs="5418478_7_0514.jpg" n="2"/>concept of Czechoslovak independence is taking root among our people in all walks of life. Just as our people in Czechoslovak lands reject any party strife, and stand in a united front for the independent state idea, in the same way our people here have come to recognize that success can be had in unity alone. Very much is expected from the outcome of the conference, and it surely will fulfill our hopes.</p>
   <p>A review of the reports on work so far accomplished shows a mighty development in the organization and a political maturity which we never even dreamed of a short time ago. Within the short period of three and one-half years, a soil has been tilled which had been mere barren land for years. The political significance of the Czechs and Czechoslovaks in general has grown by fully ninety per cent. This was possible under the stress and strain of these ominous times, but it was also the result of ceaseless propaganda, of prudently established contacts, and, above all, of organization which performed in masterly fashion deeds never before accomplished among us.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0515.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These gigantic successes lay before the delegates like an open book. They were gained by very small sacrifices--at least so far as the financial angle is concerned--which will, by comparison with the results, win the unstinted praise of the public. When times are more stable an open accounting may be rendered.</p>
   <p>And, therefore, in whatever mood the delegates may have come to the conference, one dominating idea is conspicuous: To guard conscientiously what has been accomplished at the cost of such effort, and what is today the property of Czech and Slovak America. With this in view, a harmonious course in the sessions seems guaranteed, and the words uttered by Dr. Kramar in the Prague paper, Narodni Listy (National Newspaper), after his release from prison may be recalled: "When Klofac, Dyk, Preis, and I stepped out of the door of the penitentiary, free again, we looked into one another's eyes and clasped one another's hands."</p>
   <p>Thus the common suffering of our people in Bohemia has united those who not long ago engaged in passionate party struggle. A similar picture of unification <pb facs="5418478_7_0516.jpg" n="4"/>is shown in the movement for Czechoslovak independence crystallizing out of the conference. We feel convinced that, in spite of all the early indications of an unfortunate outcome, the delegates will return from the conference fortified for the struggle, holding up as their slogan: "Now or never!"</p>
   <p>The first session, held last Saturday, was delayed until 10:30 P. M. The most weighty part of its program was the report made by Mr. Karel Pergler, director of the Slav Press Bureau. We mentioned in yesterday's issue that it evoked profound interest. We herewith present it in detail:.....</p>
   <p>We also present part of the report made by E. V. Voska on his activity in America and Russia in behalf of our cause, although certain parts cannot be published now.....One voice of criticism was heard concerning Mr. Voska's departure from America to Russia without first consulting with New York's Czech Socialist members of the Czech National Alliance.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0517.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The second session of the conference was opened yesterday, Sunday, at 10 A. M. Almost the entire forenoon was reserved for the report made by Mr. Vojta [Adalbert] Benes, organizer of the Czech National Alliance. Mr. Benes's report secured the close attention of the delegates, for in his capacity he had traveled through a large part of the United States and delivered over four hundred lectures. He reported in plain figures how much has been collected for the movement of Czechoslovak independence by the central organization up to the present time. The exact amounts are known to the central offices only. This was interpreted by some as undue secrecy. Voices were heard which advanced the opinion that the Czech public should have the right to know about the money the faithful contributing of which had entailed such sacrifices on their part. Nobody accused the officers of the organization of selfishness or dishonesty. Such things do not--Heaven be thanked!--happen among our people.</p>
   <p>And yet it was pointed out that now, when the United States is at war with both Germany and Austria, such secrecy and such an air of conspiracy is out of place. At the evening session figures were revealed upon private inquiry, but the <pb facs="5418478_7_0518.jpg" n="6"/>general public will not be informed. The leaders of the Czech National Alliance will adhere to the policy practiced up to the present and will refrain from making reports public as far as finances are concerned. The reasons for this will be given later.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vojta Benes's report follows: "I am to give an account of the work done in the year 1917. My statement will be simple. We had 178 branches in 1917, against 242 at present. The financial returns of the past year indicate an increase in the number of branches. I do not say that we are satisfied, but we may claim that in this respect we have fulfilled our duty to the old country as well as to our Alliance. Our organizational work has been given wholehearted support by our Czech press, which deserves our sincere gratitude.</p>
   <p>"We have accomplished a great deal by the lectures we held throughout the United States. During the past three years the organizer has delivered more than four hundred lectures wherever a Czech heart beats. In this work he was supported by Mr. Joseph Tvrzicky, secretary, and a goodly number of excellent speakers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0519.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Among these were Dr. [Ludwig J.] Fisher, Mr. Voska, Professor [J. J.] Zmrhal, Mr. Cimler, Mr. Pergler, the director of the Slav Bureau, and many others whose ranks are steadily increasing. Some are ordinary people, some teachers from the schools of higher learning. Professor Pisecky's work even reached into the strata of Slovak life. We had two aims, to stimulate enterprise in patriotic work, and to protect our interests.</p>
   <p>"Many obstacles presented themselves in the beginning of our work. Every organization grows if its tactics are sound, but declines in strength if they are not. I am stating my firm belief with respect to the manner in which we should conduct our campaign. We should never follow aggressive tactics. When we attack the enemy, we place him upon our own level. This means that we accord him an importance which he does not deserve. Our counter to the enemy's attack should consist of refuting false statements. We must never lower the quality of our blades by crossing them with those of an unfair foe.</p>
   <p>"True enough, we were attacked by those who did not know our work and did not <pb facs="5418478_7_0520.jpg" n="8"/>take their proper places when we began this arduous and difficult struggle. Today, after three years, our cause has been strengthened by virtue of the merits of our people. It is now being taken seriously. We have gained recognition. Nevertheless, today voices are raised against us in places from which no recognition for us will ever be forthcoming. A bad conscience is one which would like to shift the guilt from its own shoulders."</p>
   <p>Mr. Benes then presented a review, in figures and percentages, of the work done by the various districts of the organization. St. Louis heads the list of accomplishments, and Cedar Rapids, Iowa, is second. It is a pleasure to look over this record of work done by the people for the people. Mr. Benes continued: "It will, however, arrest the attention of all America when I reveal which Czech settlement excelled all others in this country. It may be a sign that our undertaking is under favorable auspices; it may be something which will warm the cockles of your hearts when I tell you--and it is the solemn truth--that it is a small Czech colony in Nebraska which contributed with heart and soul. That settlement, a shining example, friends and brothers--Proclaim this all over <pb facs="5418478_7_0521.jpg" n="9"/>America!--is Praha (Prague) in the State of Nebraska!</p>
   <p>"Every organization lives as long as its existence is justified. We have to assign enough serious work to our people to make them see in this organization a part of their own work--the work which results in callouses on their hands. This work will have to be of a democratic nature. This rally will create an impetus for making our organization one of work and of love.</p>
   <p>"We have always been striving in this direction, always keeping in mind the fact that a dearth of serious work is the beginning of decadence. We have shaped our statutes so that they will contain information on how to work. Our branches disseminated English literature, which informed the country of our demands.</p>
   <p>"It was through our efforts that The Bohemian Review was introduced into our branches and from there into American libraries, so that it might successfully fulfill its purpose. We are publishing the Poselstvi (The Message). This is our organ. Its keynote is to stimulate patriotic enterprise by nonaggressive <pb facs="5418478_7_0522.jpg" n="10"/>methods. It offers suggestions for this kind of work. It bestows praise where praise is due, and keeps silent in cases that must be viewed with regret, and where it is best to be silent.</p>
   <p>"The Message will surely attract the attention of our public. It will give directions along which our organization will be conducted in the future.</p>
   <p>"We want our people to be wholeheartedly with us in our struggle. In this we shall succeed by making this struggle the people's own precious possession. Everyone who has contributed to this work by the sweat of his brow will consider it an attack upon his own person if the work so dear to him is assailed. He will then join the ranks of those who build but do not destroy."</p>
   <p>Mr. Benes then spoke of how the Czech National Alliance is to be reorganized. He warned the conference not to base their hopes upon any plans or schemes. He is not a friend of the German speculative methods. Our organization should be supported by good men, able district organizers, who will implant vigor in places <pb facs="5418478_7_0523.jpg" n="11"/>where there has been no life up to the present time.</p>
   <p>The reorganization, the speaker declared, will have to be twofold. It must reach into the administrative department, but it must also touch the moral issue.....Mr. Benes proceeded: "A word was uttered that should never have been spoken by Czechs. It was said even publicly that we are not fit for independence .....[Translator's note: Five lines are illegible.]</p>
   <p>"The people in the old country, as well as the Czech peasant in the State of Texas, answered with deeds. We created an organization of free people. We did it voluntarily. It is a large, impressive body of Czechs and Slovaks. The work performed by it speaks proudly and solemnly in its own behalf.....</p>
   <p>"I am addressing myself to the Czech press. It is a mighty pillar of our work. It will count its contributions to our cause sometime, just as we shall give an accounting of our actions....."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0524.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>The speaker closed with an ardent appeal to his people to keep united: "I sincerely hope that our people in the old homeland will never have to hear the horrible outcry: 'The Czechs of America are fighting among themselves!' We have only one longing and one duty: To stand in our places honorably; to persist in the struggle for the sacred cause of our nation until victory has come to us."</p>
   <p>Motions concerning Mr. Benes's report were made in the afternoon session, and a lively exchange of opinions developed, which became passionate at times. The initiative was given by a motion made by Mr. F. J. Kubec, a member of the Chicago district committee of the Alliance. He demanded that the figures quoted in the Benes report be placed on record as an "official," or rather "diplomatic" secret, and be barred from public print. This was most seriously opposed by Mr. E. V. Voska, a New York delegate, who declared that Czechs of that town are already sated with all sorts of secrecy and want to see things in black and white. Two opposing elements clashed here in one single moment, for there ensued among the delegates an obstinate debate about the way in which the <pb facs="5418478_7_0525.jpg" n="13"/>conference was to be carried on.</p>
   <p>It behooves us to mention that the Chicago headquarters had anticipated such an emergency and inquired at the Czechoslovak National Council in Europe about the attitude it should assume in this matter. Dr. Edouard Benes, general secretary of the National Council, in a cablegram sent to the conference, declared that the figures may be published if this should be insisted upon, but he counseled at the same time that, for reasons of expediency and strategy, he considers such a step unfavorable to the cause. This viewpoint was also taken by Professor Thomas G. Masaryk from the very beginning of the liberation movement. All Czech leaders in Europe are of the opinion that publishing this material would be of little value to our cause, for it would only play into the hands of our enemies who could otherwise only guess at our strength without obtaining any precise information.</p>
   <p>This was the turning point of the whole debate. Should the public in America learn about the amounts collected for our revolutionary movement, which would <pb facs="5418478_7_0526.jpg" n="14"/>mean showing our cards to those who are most eager to get an insight? There was hardly a delegate who failed to take part in the controversy. The argument was, as a matter of course, a rather violent one. It must be admitted, however, to do the delegates justice, that each defended his viewpoint in the spirit of honest conviction and with the certainty that he was acting in good faith.</p>
   <p>A large number of delegates declared that they share Professor Masaryk's opinion, that they trust in him, and that secrecy was advisable.....</p>
   <p>An opposing view was taken by Mr. K. Bernreiter of Cleveland, Ohio, who said that people want to know where they stand; that the conference should conform with the agreement reached at the Cleveland conference, which provides that monthly statements should be sent at least to the executive committees of the various district branches of the Alliance. He added that Cleveland would not like to appear in the role of a mere collecting substation. It was finally decided not to publish the figures, but to send monthly statements to the <pb facs="5418478_7_0527.jpg" n="15"/>district branches.</p>
   <p>After this ticklish question, which threatened to become a stumbling block for the smooth course of the conference, had been disposed of, another tempest arose when a cablegram sent by the New York Workmen's Central Union was read. It demanded that Mr. Voska be barred from taking part in the conference, and also that he not be elected to any official office. It stated further that the senders could not, true enough, by their own authority, coerce the conference, but that they will cease to contribute financially if their demands are not heeded. Their case with Voska, they added, will be settled with him in their own way in New York.</p>
   <p>This communication evoked a long debate. Mr. Voska gave an explanation of the affair.....In spite of this, the debate continued. Some delegates proposed to shelve the case. Some wished action against Voska. Others again declared that he could not be barred from the meeting, since he was fully accredited by the New York branch. This opinion won out. Voska was permitted to remain as a <pb facs="5418478_7_0528.jpg" n="16"/>delegate. The complaint of the New Yorkers was, however, referred to the Chicago main offices of the Czech National Alliance for further consideration.</p>
   <p>The conference ended at 6 P. M. with a discussion of the means which would be employed and the action to be taken in the pursuit of the aims of the organization. It was more or less a friendly discussion. Among those who took part were Professor B. Simek, Professor Pisecky, Dr. Breuer, and Mrs. B. Ludvik.</p>
   <p>The meeting was adjourned until tomorrow morning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
