<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-06">July 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Report from a Regular Monthly Meeting of the Board of Delegates to the Bohemian National Cemetery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0789</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0789.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-06">July 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT FROM A REGULAR MONTHLY MEETING OF THE BOARD OF DELEGATES TO THE BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular monthly meeting of the Sbor (board of delegates) to the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) was held last night in the lower hall of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Czechoslovakian Benevolent Societies) on May and 18th Streets. The president [Mr. Jan Pecha] being absent on a trip to Czechoslovakia, the meeting was opened by the vice-president, Mr. Stanislav Simecek. The minutes of the previous meeting were approved as read. All the bills presented for payment by the financial secretary, were also approved. During the preceding month only two letters had been received by the Sbor.....In one of them, the Dejluv Ustav Pro Slepce v Praze (Deyl's Institute for the Blind in Prague) thanked the Sbor for its generous gift of $50 to be used for the print shop of the institute. The other communication was from the president of the Sbor, Mr. Jan Pecha, who, at the present time is visiting Czechoslovakia and sends his greetings <pb facs="5418478_7_0790.jpg" n="2"/>to all the delegates.....</p>
   <p>Reporting for the executive committee, Mr. Smejkal announced the purchase of a Ford sedan, at a cost of $700. This purchase was approved by the executive committee at its last meeting, and the car is to be used by the cemetery....Additional bonds worth $15,000 were also purchased. These bear an interest of four and one-half per cent. During the course of the month [of June], $897.50 was received as interest on matured bonds. Among other things it was also reported that a purchase of a new pump for the cemetery is necessary. This item was referred to the executive committee....as was also the item of repainting the water pipes. Since the Sbor is obliged to pay such high taxes on a parcel of land consisting of eight acres which formerly belonged to Mrs. Scheiner, the executive committee was asked to try to have these taxes reduced. The same committee was also requested to furnish estimates on the proposed enlargement of the columbarium, the present size of which will, in the near future, be found inadequate.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0791.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The next item was to set a date on which the Sbor was to make its annual tour of inspection of the cemetery grounds. This tour is considered sort of a climax to the annual activity of the Sbor.....After some discussion, it was decided to make this tour on the second Sunday in September. All the delegates will be informed by letter where to meet on that occasion....A motion was made by Delegate Smejkal to ask the management of the cemetery to continue watering the lawns and graves and not to economize on water. The present dry weather requires that all [grass] be watered constantly..... [A list follows of the names of owners of cemetery lots who effected the transfer of ownership of such lots to other persons.] The following persons paid for the perpetual care of graves. [A list follows of the names of such persons and the amounts paid by each during the month of June. The total was $1,900.] The cemetery employed ninety-two persons during the month of June and the pay roll was $9,387.37. The income during that month was $2,727.07 and the disbursements amounted to $36,862.77. Twenty-three cemetery lots were sold for $5,108 and two urns for $180. There were <pb facs="5418478_7_0792.jpg" n="4"/>ninety-six burials and six cremations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
