<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-10-09">Oct. 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Farewell Banquet for Ambassador Vopicka</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1468</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1468.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-10-09">Oct. 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A FAREWELL BANQUET FOR AMBASSADOR VOPICKA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The beautiful ballroom of the Congress Hotel on Michigan Avenue where the Ceska Beseda (Bohemian Club) held a farewell banquet for one of our most prominent and deserving leaders, Mr. Karel J. Vopicka, was filled to capacity last night. The wall behind the places where the officers of Ceska Beseda were seated with the official guests of the evening was decorated with an American, a Serbian, a Bulgarian, and a Rumanian flag. Among the guests were representatives of all these nations, in addition to Slovaks, Slovenes, and Croatians.</p>
   <p>After the excellent dinner was finished, Mr. W. Kolacek, Ceska Beseda's president, welcomed those assembled and introduced the toastmaster, Mr. O. J. Hruby, who in turn presented Congressman Adolph J. Sabath as one of the men whose influence is responsible for Mr. Vopicka's appointment. Mr. Sabath, in his brief address, stressed the fact that it was the Democratic party which fully recognized the merits of Bohemians settled in the <pb facs="5418478_7_1469.jpg" n="2"/>United States and showed this recognition by nominating a Bohemian for the important, responsible, and highly distinguished position of a United States ambassador. He said that Mr. Vopicka was quite undecided as to whether he should or should not accept this honor. Only after it had been pointed out to him that it is a duty not only toward himself, but also toward the Bohemian nation, did Mr. Vopicka agree to seek this nomination.....</p>
   <p>After Congressman Sabath's speech, the toastmaster read messages of congratulation which reached the hotel from Secretary of State W. J. Bryan, . Governor Dunne, and Senator James H. Lewis, the last two of whom also expressed their regrets that unforeseen obstacles had prevented them from being present at the celebration.</p>
   <p>Mr. John R. Palaudec, the editor of the Srbske Listy [a Serbian newspaper], assured Mr. Vopicka in his remarks that he (Mr. Vopicka) will be cordially welcomed by the eight million Jugoslavs who will be glad to have among them <pb facs="5418478_7_1470.jpg" n="3"/>a son of the Bohemian nation as the representative of the great American Republic.....</p>
   <p>Mr. E. St. Vraz recalled Mr. Vopicka's merits for his part in the foundation of the Ceska Beseda.....He also expressed his appreciation for the work of the Democratic party and its impartiality in matters concerning the national origin of those in whom it puts its trust. He stressed the Democratic party's courage in making a precedent by nominating a naturalized citizen for the office of ambassador, this being the very first case in the history of the United States.....</p>
   <p>Mayor Harrison spoke briefly but with sincere cordiality. He congratulated Mr. Vopicka on the great honor of representing the United States in the Balkans, wished him a great deal of success, and bade him farewell.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1471.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Vopicka thanked all those who came.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
