<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-01-20">Jan. 20, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's Session</title><title level="a" type="sub">Bohemian American Foresters working tirelessly. the committee on by-laws is more than half through with its work.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0637</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0637.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-01-20">Jan. 20, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">YESTERDAY'S SESSION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Bohemian American Foresters working tirelessly. The committee on by-laws is more than half through with its work.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1--The chief-forester, Mr. John Budilovsky, brought the session to order shortly after 9 o'clock. The minutes of the first day's session were read and accepted as read. The secretary, Mrs. Smrcek, read the communications received.</p>
   <p>The reports of the committees being in order, the audit committee reported, that it had not yet completed its work and would report later.</p>
   <p>The grievance-committee made a report in which it recommended, that the death-certificate remain as it is, because the committee found the certificate to be just. A motion made to that effect was adopted.</p>
   <p>The resolutions committee recommended that an assessment of five cents be levied, for the benefit of brother Sky. This was adopted. Further, the resolutions committee recognized the liberal work of the Grand-lodge officers <pb facs="5418478_7_0638.jpg" n="2"/>and gave thanks to them. The same held for the officers of all lodges. The resolutions committee also recommended the support of Bohemian schools with a one cent per-month assessment. The committee further recommended, that all printing work be given to union-shops and important reports to be published at least twice each year in Bohemian newspapers.</p>
   <p>The rituals committee recommended and offered a motion, that there be no change made in the rituals. Delegate Pech, protested against this, pointing out that certain parts of the rituals should be dropped. He objected to the use of passwords, claiming that such things are not suitable for a civilized people. Delegates Hajek, Marek, Smejkal and others were opposed to this kind of change, claiming that if the rituals were dropped, the society would be considered an insurance company and would be taxed accordingly. Finally, a motion was made to accept the recommendation of the committee. This was adopted by a large majority.</p>
   <p>The committee on by-laws made a report, that it had progressed so far with its work, that the recommended changes could be read to the assembly. On the motion of delegate Bouse, the paragraphs, which the committee recommended be changed, were read.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0639.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The afternoon session was brought to order at 2 P.M. The secretary read the minutes of the morning session and these were accepted as read, Reading of correspondence was next on the program.</p>
   <p>The Finance committee made its report. It conformed to the request of the convention, examined the books and bonds of the organization, and found everything in order.</p>
   <p>The committee on by-laws continued its work.</p>
   <p>Delegate Pech, of the resolutions committee asked permission to make an oral presentation of a resolution which was omitted at the morning session. The assembly resolved, that the resolution be presented in writing.</p>
   <p>Secretary Hajek introduced the question, to the convention, as to whether members should continue to receive remuneration for securing new members. Delegate Zahrobsky moved, that the organization should continue to pay for <pb facs="5418478_7_0640.jpg" n="4"/>securing of new members. The motion was approved.</p>
   <p>With that, the business of the afternoon session having been completed, the chief-forester adjourned the meeting till to-day at 9 A.M. </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
