<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-12">Aug. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Organize Recruiting Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1378</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1378.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-12">Aug. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ORGANIZE RECRUITING COMMITTEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Citizens' Committee for the 83rd Recruiting District, under the auspices of the National Defense Council, organized as a permanent body in a recent meeting. The following officers were elected: John A. Cervenka, chairman; Joseph Bolek, vice-chairman; Bohumil A. Mudra, secretary; Reverend Vaclav Vanek, financial secretary and treasurer. The permanent Executive Committee will be constituted of officers of the various subdivisions.</p>
   <p>One of these subdivisions will provide preliminary instruction for our recruits, who will profit from it when in the regular camps. Mr. Pecival, former instructor of the Pilsen Sokol, is captain of this preliminary training division, and Mr. F. J. Kohout is chairman. Another subdivision will take care of hospitality and entertainment for soldiers leaving for the camps. Other subdivisions are to investigate situations of soldiers' families and their title to support; they will provide the funds. There will be also a subdivision for obtaining members for the organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1379.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The dues for members will range from $2 to $25 per year. In the first meeting $322 was collected in dues.</p>
   <p>The next meeting will be held at Hubbard Memorial Church, 2520 South Lawndale Avenue. Numerous citizens from the 83rd District will be invited to attend. The District is bordered by 22nd Street, the Canal, Central Park Avenue, and the western city limits. This committee was formed upon request from the U. S. War Department. Every Czech citizen resident in the District should take a lively interest in this body.</p>
   <p>The office of the local recruiting board is located at Ridgeway Avenue and 26th Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
