<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-11-28">Nov. 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Social of the Ceska Ustredni Pevecka Jednota</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0206</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0206.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-11-28">Nov. 28, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A SOCIAL OF THE CESKA USTREDNI PEVECKA JEDNOTA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our singers, now united in the Ceska Ustredni Pevecka Jednota (Federation of Bohemian Singing Societie) again made a public appearance, after a period of comparative inactivity. The occasion was the celebration of the Posviceni [a fall festival in Bohemian lands comparable to the celebration of Thanks-giving Day in America] held in the hall of Sokol Plzen, yesterday afternoon.</p>
   <p>The Jednota prepared for this celebration a rich, we may say a splendid and very ambitious program, whose artistic value alone should have been enough of an attraction to fill the largest of our halls, to say nothing of such attendance as should have gathered to show appreciation due our singing societies for their unselfish cultural and artistic work. However, our singers did not get that satisfaction.....The gallery was almost empty, and the main floor could have accommodated at least twice as many people. Those who were present were mostly singers or members of various singing societies. The complaint voiced some time ago and directed at the general public seems to <pb facs="5418478_7_0207.jpg" n="2"/>be justified. Our public is indifferent, and there is no use to try to cover up this fact.....</p>
   <p>Those, however, who by their presence showed appreciation for the conductor and choir masters, came in for an afternoon of keen enjoyment.</p>
   <p>The first number on the program, Karel Bendl's "Bohemian Folk Songs," put the audience in a most agreeable mood.</p>
   <p>The afternoon was most successful--morally. What a pity that the singers best intentions had to meet with such an indifferent reception. The evening was devoted to dancing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
