<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-30">May 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A School Recital Arranged by the Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0806</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0806.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-05-30">May 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A SCHOOL RECITAL ARRANGED BY THE FEDERATION OF BOHEMIAN FREE THOUGHT SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the auspices of the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol (Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools), a recital was held last Sunday afternoon, May 28, 1922. During this recital many of the pupils of the Free Thought schools were able to demonstrate their progress with the exception of the Oak Park and south side schools, all of the schools of our Federation were represented. The large and beautiful assembly hall of the Carter H. Harrison High School, in which the recital was held, was filled to capacity by our Czech people who followed the program with interest, an interest shown by the enthusiastic applause for the various items on the program....</p>
   <p>The program was long and very well arranged, doing honor to its committee. By its variety it surprised all... There were prologues, poems, dances, songs, and music; the young actors excellently performed their individual rolls. It was a beautiful and exalted spectacle! It was borne out that with the full <pb facs="5418478_7_0807.jpg" n="2"/>understanding of our aims, and by remembering the work our schools are doing, by supporting this work financially and morally, we need not have fear for the future of our nationality in this country.</p>
   <p>The program ended with a beautiful tableau and an epilogue by Miss M. Vacula. In this many of our great national [Bohemian] figures, especially the person of the great teacher of western nations, Jan Amos Comenius, were dramatically represented.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
