<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-03">May 3, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemians Will Again Take Part in the Fourth of July Parade</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0272</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0272.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-03">May 3, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIANS WILL AGAIN TAKE PART IN THE FOURTH OF JULY PARADE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The anniversary of the Declaration of Independence of the United States of North America will be celebrated again this year, though in a quiet manner.</p>
   <p>Once again, there will be held a grand parade in Michigan Avenue, and once more will the various nationalities living in Chicago be represented in the parade. The parade will be held in the forenoon, and celebrations will be held in the afternoon in parks, and in all places suitable to the free gathering of people. The arrangement of these celebrations will be left to the representatives of the largest nationalities living in the neighborhood of the gathering place. For instance, the Bohemians will hold celebrations in Douglas Park, Svatopluk Czech Park, Grant Park, and other places. These celebrations will be characteristic of our own nationality. There will be Bohemian speakers, our national dances, and plays will be performed, and there will be a grand fireworks display in the evening. Naturally, the speakers will speak of the meaning and significance of the day being celebrated.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0273.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That is the way Mr. John A. Cervenka explained it at the meeting of the Bohemian Association for a sane Fourth of July celebration.</p>
   <p>The meeting was held in the office of the Pilsen Brewing Company on Albany and 26th Streets, and was participated in by many prominent countrymen. Messrs. Cervenka, Hajicek, Vopicka, and Cermak, who are members of the central committee of all nationalities took part in yesterday's meeting, and for them Mr. Cervenka explained what had been done, and could yet be done for a quiet celebration. This year, there is no concern over a big parade, insofar as the number of participants is concerned, but it is to be all the more picturesque. It will again be a parade of all nationalities, and each nationality is to prepare one allegorical float having historical significance to it. After Mr. Cervenka's explanation, the body proceeded to elect officers. The following were elected: J. A. Cervenka, chairman; J. Ort, secretary; and F. G. Hajicek, treasurer.</p>
   <p>The next point discussed was whether the action was to be carried out by the body just organized, or whether it should be left up to our lodges. After a <pb facs="5418478_7_0274.jpg" n="3"/>lengthy debate, it was finally resolved to leave it in the hands of the new organization, because of the shortness of time.</p>
   <p>Various committees were then selected, and the chairmen of these committees were authorized to name further committees as necessity dictated. The next meeting will also be held in the same place one week from last Tuesday. Those present yesterday took up a collection which netted $120. In that way the financial foundation was laid for the participation of Bohemians in the celebration of the Fourth of July.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
