<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-20">Aug. 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Notice to All the Sincere Freethinkers of Chicago and Vicinity!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0760</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0760.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-20">Aug. 20, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NOTICE TO ALL THE SINCERE FREETHINKERS OF CHICAGO AND VICINITY!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In view of the forthcoming holidays, the Statni Svaz Svobodomyslnych (State Federation of [Bohemian] Freethinkers) has decided to arrange for a trip to Milwaukee, Wisconsin....on September 3 and 4. This proposal has been joyfully received by our Milwaukee brothers and sisters, who will do their utmost to make our stay among them as comfortable as possible. According to information already received, they will meet us with a band upon our arrival at the Milwaukee depot. We, on the other hand, should endeavor to have our young and old Freethinkers turn out in truly representative numbers.</p>
   <p>The program for the trip is as follows: We shall leave Chicago from the Northwestern depot on Sunday at about 9 A.M. In the afternoon, we shall take part in a jubilee celebration arranged by the Milwaukee lodge of the Zapadni Ceska Bratrska Jednota (Western Bohemian Fraternal Union), during which speeches will be heard on the Free Thought movement. On Monday, September 4 (Labor Day), we shall make a trip through the city by means of automobiles; in the afternoon, <pb facs="5418478_7_0761.jpg" n="2"/>there will be a public meeting. We return to Chicago that same evening, that is, Monday night.</p>
   <p>Arrangements have already been made for the housing of all the Chicago members. The reduced railroad fare to Milwaukee will be about $2 per person. All applications must be made by August 29 at the latest; they must be addressed to the secretary of the State Federation: Frantisek Strunc, 2600 South Ashland Avenue, Chicago, Illinois. The exact time of our departure from Chicago, as well as all other particulars, will be announced later.</p>
   <p>Brothers and sisters, you who have joined the group carrying the banner of Free Thought--it rests upon you to make this trip a success. Endeavor, therefore, to make it possible for the Bohemian Freethinkers of Chicago to be well represented, and thus bring courage to our Milwaukee brothers and sisters in their....work for the success of the Free Thought movement!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
