<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-25">Aug. 25, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America Prepares for its Third General Convention</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0756</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0756.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-25">Aug. 25, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE NATIONAL ALLIANCE OF BOHEMIAN CATHOLICS OF AMERICA PREPARES FOR ITS THIRD GENERAL CONVENTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The third general convention of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America) will be held October 3, 4, and 5, 1922, in the Cesko-Americka Sin (Bohemian-American Hall) on West 18th Street, Chicago. The convention will open with a pontifical mass which will be celebrated in Saint Procopius Church, [northeast] corner of Allport and west 18th Streets. The formal opening of the convention will take place at 2 P. M. with the chairman of the executive committee officiating. For the second day of the convention the district Svaz of Chicago is preparing a friendly soiree in which the president of the district Svaz, Mr. Karel Radous, will be the master of ceremonies. In the course of the evening various <pb facs="5418478_7_0757.jpg" n="2"/>workers of our Svaz will make reports of their work.</p>
   <p>The right to be represented in the general (national) convention belongs to men's and women's organizations and unions (Catholics), the Jednota Katolocky Sokol (Catholic Sokol Union), the Sdruzeni Ceskych Katolickych Spolku (Federation of Bohemian Catholic Societies) belonging to foreign-language Catholic unions, the district and the parish organizations of the Svaz, the clergy, institutions, publishing companies of Catholic periodicals, and parishes and societies from those parts of the country in which there are no district or parochial branches of the Svaz.</p>
   <p>The executive committee of the Svaz has already invited our Bohemian Catholic organizations as well as all district and parochial branches of the Svaz; these organizations were asked to elect their delegates and send us their names so that we could issue the proper credentials and mail them out to each organization.</p>
   <p>The representation is as follows: For the organizations and district branches of the Svaz, one delegate for every 2,000 or more members; for institutions <pb facs="5418478_7_0758.jpg" n="3"/>and publishing companies, one delegate for each; for the clergy, one delegate for each district branch of the Svaz.</p>
   <p>September 15, 1922, serves as a deadline at which time all resolutions, requests, information, and complaints to be presented before the convention must be on file. Do not procrastinate, therefore, and mail all your convention material in as early as possible, so that it may be referred to the appropriate committees. Besides the duly elected delegates, any priest and any Catholic layman may attend the convention as a guest. Particularly welcome are those nuns and women who hail from localities not having any branches of the Svaz; they should come to convince themselves of the work which the Svaz accomplished, and to become its pioneers in their own vicinity. The National Alliance must be represented in every Bohemian Catholic parish, and every Bohemian Catholic, priest or layman, man or woman, must become members. The work already done by the Svaz bids us fair to cherish the best hopes for the future. New tasks will be set at this convention, and the Svaz will tackle <pb facs="5418478_7_0759.jpg" n="4"/>one in particular, namely, the problem of our youth. A special report is being prepared in this regard. Detailed information relating to the program of the convention will be announced later.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anton V. Tesar,</p>
   <p>office manager of the Narodni Svaz</p>
   <p>Ceskych Katoliku v Americe 1440 West</p>
   <p>18th Street, Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
