<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-25">Aug. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Citizens' Defense Committee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1373</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1373.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-08-25">Aug. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CITIZENS' DEFENSE COMMITTEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We reported in an earlier issue that citizens of the Thirty-fourth Ward have formed the "Eighty-third Exempted Citizens' Committee of the State Council of Defense". Its aims are so noble and praiseworthy that there is probably no patriotic citizen who would not like to become a member.</p>
   <p>After the first appeal for membership many who came from political circles or religious societies signed and sent in dues in larger or smaller amounts. They know that the Committee will be helpful in the struggle for a decisive victory of democracy over autocracy. This victory will bring liberty and independence to small oppressed nations, and among them to the Czechoslovaks.</p>
   <p>The work of the Committee will also include providing material help and moral comfort for those whose dear ones are in the war. The results of these activities will surely demonstrate that the Thirty-fourth Ward, the most thoroughly Czech ward in Chicago, knows what the duties of its inhabitants are. This <pb facs="5418478_7_1374.jpg" n="2"/>ward will prove by its accomplishments that its people are ready for all the sacrifices which this country is asking of them in order to insure victory over the Huns.</p>
   <p>Many are the tasks which the Committee has undertaken to perform. We are going to refer to a few only, just to let our fellow citizens know that the Committee intends to work with vigor and zeal so that all Chicago will justly be proud of the Thirty-fourth Ward.</p>
   <p>This Committee will take care of the following agenda. It will see to it that hospitality is extended to our soldiers leaving for the camps, and that they are provided with articles which they need, and which give them comfort, such as tobacco and cigarettes. The boys are to be brought to the railroad station in automobiles, and a parade will be formed in their honor. The soldiers' families are, if in need, to be regularly provided with means that will keep them out of want.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1375.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Committee will also promote [Liberty] Bond and War Stamp sales and do everything to prove that the inhabitants of the Thirty-fourth Ward are inspired with genuine patriotism, particularly now when the salvation of democracy is the issue, and liberty is at stake. A gorgeous Service Flag is to be bought, bearing a star for each boy of the Thirty-fourth Ward in service. The flag will be raised amid festivities and a grand parade.</p>
   <p>The work of the Committee is divided into several departments. Mr. John A. Cervenka is chairman, Joseph Bolek is secretary, B. B. Mudra is auditor, and the Reverend Vaclav (Wenceslaus) Vanek is treasurer.</p>
   <p>The Committee has various departments, namely, of investigation, of finance, of entertainment, of the press, of instruction, of membership promotion, and of Liberty Bond sales. Offices are at the southeast corner of Ridgeway Avenue and 26th Street, where the recruiting office also is located. Meetings are held every first and third Thursday of the month in the chambers of the church on Lawndale Avenue between 25th and 26th Streets.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
