<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-01-06">Jan. 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Meeting of the Representatives of the Bohemian-National Cemetery Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-01-06">Jan. 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL MEETING OF THE REPRESENTATIVES OF THE BOHEMIAN-NATIONAL CEMETERY ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual meeting of the representatives of the Bohemian-National Cemetery Association was held last night in the lower hall of the Bohemian-English Liberal School, on 18th Street. The meeting was called to order and conducted by the Chairman, Mr. T. Pech. The first order of business was the election of a substitute for the absent secretary, St. Halik, and Mr. Kopecky was elected. By direction of the chairman, the minutes of the previous regular meeting were read, and unanimously accepted. Then followed a long list of bills, all were approved. Next in order were the communications. The first, over which ensued a heated debate, was sent by Secretary St. Halik. It contained his resignation. The secretary of the Bohemian-National Cemetery Association is elected for one year and Mr. Halik's term of office has not yet expired. As is readily admitted by all, Mr. Halik, performed the duties of his office with admirable accuracy. Being a lawyer, he was particularly well qualified.</p>
   <p>The proposal of the majority, that the management committee make known to Mr. Halik, that he should continue his duties as secretary, in accordance with the by-laws, until the end of his term, was adopted. Communications from individual organizations were read, in which the re-election of delegates or the election of new delegates were announced. A letter from Mr. Ed. Longa, <pb facs="5418478_7_1250.jpg" n="2"/>requesting that his 19 year old son be given the opportunity to learn gardening in the Bohemian-National Cemetery was discussed and turned over to the managing committee for a decision. All those present arose to honor the memory of the deceased Representative Karel Spirka. Three transfers of lots were announced; a summary of gifts to the schools was also read.</p>
   <p>The chairman introduced Mr. Cejka, of St. Louis who, in a short, but commendable speech expressed his admiration for the Bohemian-National Cemetery---which he called, correctly, the most beautiful cemetery, not only in Chicago, but in the entire United States. After reading a letter of thanks from Judge Kersten, for the flowers sent to him by Superintendent Tuma, for his speech on Decoration Day, the total receipts of the past year were announced. They amounted to $5151,00; disbursements were $7671,00. The meeting was then adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
