<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-22">Feb. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Prague Weekly Cesky Svet Dedicates its Latest Issue to the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliky V Americe (The National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0852</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0852.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-22">Feb. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE PRAGUE WEEKLY CESKY SVET DEDICATES ITS LATEST ISSUE TO THE NARODNI SVAZ CESKYCH KATOLIKY V AMERICE (THE NATIONAL ALLIANCE OF BOHEMIAN CATHOLICS OF AMERICA)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Washington, Feb. 14. (From the Czechoslovak press bureau.) The latest issue of the Prague illustrated weekly Cesky Svet is dedicated to the Bohemian Catholics and their active participation in liberating [Czechoslovakia]. The cover is adorned by a successfully executed reproduction of the well-known Polasek medal. In the textual part of the magazine there is a concise history of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku, its activities during and after the war. The text is appropriately and richly illustrated by the following half-tones: The diploma of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku V Americe, the first executive committee; the executive committee of 1920-1921; the first general convention at Chicago, Illinois; a portrait of the Reverend A. Biskup; Reverend Biskup officiating at the Holy Eucharist; the first mission of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku, its second mission;....the allegorical float in the Chicago festivities of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku; its office [in Chicago]; its branch offices in <pb facs="5418478_7_0853.jpg" n="2"/>Detroit, Michigan....the high schools, college and Theological seminary at Lisle, Illinois, and finally....the Saint Joseph's orphanage at Lisle, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
