<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-09">July 9, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Hus Memorial Service</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0380</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0380.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-09">July 9, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">HUS MEMORIAL SERVICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A memorial service which met with great success was held in Svatopluk Cech Park, May and Fisk Streets, on July 6, the 496th anniversary of the death by torture of Jan Hus. The attendance was so large that about two hundred people had to be turned away, due to lack of space.</p>
   <p>The program consisted of fifteen numbers, and was carried through faultlessly. Following the singing of "Rovnou Cestou" (Straight Road) and a prayer by Reverend F. Pelikan, Mr. V. T. Prchal played a violin solo. The mixed choir of Emmanuel Church sang two numbers. Dr. G. B. Lafford spoke in English. His subject was: "Hus, How He is Looked upon by the American People". It was a masterly oration, which made a powerful impression upon everyone. Next, there appeared a twelve-year-old Bohemian girl, Anezka Blafka, who was introduced by the sponsor of the service, the Reverend Vanek, as a Bohemian child genius. The girl, although only twelve years of age, has graduated from grammar school, and for three years has won first <pb facs="5418478_7_0381.jpg" n="2"/>prize at the Chicago Musical College. Recently, she received a diamond medal from that institution for her extraordinary musical talent. Her playing filled all those present with admiration.</p>
   <p>Another talk: "The Significance of the Memory of Hus" was delivered by Mr. Jaroslav Smetanka, who several years ago graduated from Columbia University in New York with a degree of Master of Science, and later received from Union Theological Seminary the degree of Bachelor of Theology. Mr. Smetanka is now located in Chicago as a government official, and his talk was received with great applause.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Vanek's theme was: "Hus, and the Approach of His Five Hundredth Jubilee". He called attention to the approaching five hundredth jubilee which will be celebrated by a joint excursion of Evangelical Bohemians to the Bohemian homeland, in 1915. Reverend Duha, minister of the Hus church at Sawyer Avenue and 24th Street, thanked all those who participated in the <pb facs="5418478_7_0382.jpg" n="3"/>service, and the sponsor of the memorial, the Reverend Vanek. After another song, joined in by the entire audience, and an appropriate poem, "A Prayer for the Homeland", which was delivered by L. Burian, the services were ended with the singing of our national hymn, "Kde Domov Muj?" (Where Is My Home?).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
