<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-06">Feb. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian-Americans to Answer Call</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1463</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1463.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-06">Feb. 6, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN-AMERICANS TO ANSWER CALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian National Association has issued a call for Czech men to be ready to do their duty with arms in hand when necessary. All of our people are conscious of the fact that the United States would go to side of the Allies, if they enter the War. Together, they have promised to help the small nations win their liberty. President wilson, who looks upon the rights of the citizens of this country and upon the rights of the small nations alike, has written upon his banner a slogan which is the slogan of every Czech, conscious of his obligations. In this case, the fight of the United States will be our fight, and it shall be the duty of every Czech to take up arms: a principle established for us by our leader, Professor Masartk.</p>
   <p>For this reason, the Bohemian National Association has taken preliminary <pb facs="5418478_7_1464.jpg" n="2"/>steps to create a military committee which shall compile lists of all able-bodied Czechs, and on the strength of the authority given to it by all our Czech associations, begin to organize. Jarka Kosar, F. J. Kubec, and A. D. Vlk are the representatives of Sokol gymnastic societies who have been named on the committee. All of our fellow countrymen who wish to be informed about matters of military nature, or on questions touching upon the ideals of the Allied Nations,may apply in the offices of the Bohemian National Association.</p>
   <p>All fellow countrymen should take out their first papers, if they had not already done so, and everyone should procure an identification card from the Bohemian National Association, so that our members will feel more secure in case of a conflict.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
