<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-08">Sept. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Preparatory Work for the Third General Conventin of the National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0746</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0746.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-08">Sept. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">PREPARATORY WORK FOR THE THIRD GENERAL CONVENTIN OF THE NATIONAL ALLIANCE OF BOHEMIAN CATHOLICS OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following is a report from the offices of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku, 1440 West 18th Street, Chicago, Illinois:</p>
   <p>On October 3, 4, and 5, 1922, the third general convention of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics) will be held in Chicago. It is therefore necessary that all Bohemian Catholic societies and all parochial and district branches of the Alliance send their delegates to this convention and announce the names of their delegates on the official duplicates of accreditation papers. Every society and organization has already been invited to attend, and all the organized bodies have been asked to forward their resolutions, recommendations, and complaints which are to be presented before this convention. A high pontifical mass will be celebrated on October 3, 1922, at 10 A. M. in the Saint Vitus Church, 18th and South Paulina <pb facs="5418478_7_0747.jpg" n="2"/>Streets, by the Very Reverend Abbot Valentin Kohlbeck, O. S. B. A festive sermon will be preached on this occasion by the chaplain of the Svaz, Reverend Frank W. Jedlicka, who is the parish priest in the Parish of the Panna Marie Dobre Rady (Our Lady of Good Counsel).</p>
   <p>The convention will be formally opened at 2 P. M. by the president of the Svaz, Mr. Jan Straka, in the Ceskoslovanska Americka Sin (Czechoslavonic-American Hall). Mr. Straka is on his way home from a visit to Czechoslovakia and will arrive this week. On the second day of the convention a banquet in honor of the delegates will be given by the central office of the Svaz. After this convivial affair, the Chicago district Svaz will hold a soiree for the delegates, but this will be open to the general public. There will be no admission charged. On this occasion the Reverend Father Siegenberger, who is an excellent orator, will speak on the theme, "The New Citizenship".</p>
   <p>All of the convention days will be charged with activity; several very important programs are being prepared; significant questions that touch our <pb facs="5418478_7_0748.jpg" n="3"/>lives intimately are being formulated. For example, the problem of our youth will be the most important subject facing the convention, and the assemblage will have to decide how we may preserve our young people for our faith and our nationality. The programs of the convention are being printed and will be available shortly; in them you will learn about the exact time of each subject to be discussed. It is certain that this year's convention is a very important one which will surpass by its deliberations the two previous conventions.</p>
   <p>Besides the duly accredited delegates who have the right to vote, other persons may attend, and are sincerely invited to this convention. Such other persons are priests and laymen who are asked to attend as guests. Your attendance will prove that you are committed to the cause of this most necessary organizaton of the Bohemian Catholics in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
