<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-03">July 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Festival and Mass-Meeting of the Bohemian Freethinkers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0793</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0793.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-03">July 3, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FESTIVAL AND MASS-MEETING OF THE BOHEMIAN FREETHINKERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In spite of the unusually fine weather which tempted a great many thousands of our people to make trips into the country, the mass-meeting called by the local branch of the Sdruzeni Svobodomyslnych (Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers) at the Pilsen Park pavilion was rather well attended. When, at 3:45 P. M., the band....started to play, the spacious hall of the pavilion began to fill. The chairman of the local branch of Federation, Mr. Ploss, in his opening speech, stressed the duties which devolved upon every freethinker to defend whatever still remained of our freedom. Prohibition, together with other blue laws, and the introduction of the Bible into the schools, threaten us and fall heavily upon our shoulders. The daily press of the Hearst chain of newspapers, in reporting about the spiritistic seances, reaps havoc with the general public, William J. Bryan, writing in the <pb facs="5418478_7_0794.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago Daily News, mentions the Gospels, but not a word is said about freedom and progressive thinking. The University of Illinois spent one million dollars for the support of religious education which has been seriously discredited by the advances of science. This is the first time that an American [state] university has introduced such a course in its curriculum; elsewhere similar steps are being supported by the united efforts of the churches. The Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers is trying, therefore, to counteract all these forces by uniting with other American Free Thought organizations whether they are English speaking or foreign-language groups. The Constitution of the United States was conceived and written by very wise men who insisted that the church be separated from the state, but it seems that forces are now afoot which threaten that wise provision. To prevent such a threat, a strong organization is needed which would declare its colors through the active work of its members.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0795.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The next speaker was the secretary of the American Secular Union, Mr. McClaskey. He mentioned first the new constitutional amendment proposed in the Illinois legislature which would permit the reading of certain passages and parts of the Bible in public schools. He severely critized this "innovation," and said that the American people are astonishingly negligent, calmly observing the lopping off of parts of their hard won freedom. If our people do not wake up as soon as possible, this country is going to have the most ecclesiastical government in the world.</p>
   <p>The children of the Bohemian Free Thought Schools, under the guidance of their teacher, Miss Zeman, recited a number of fine poems, and ended by singing "Kde Domov Muj?" (Where Is My Home?), "Slava Ti Vlasti Ma!" (Glory Be Thee, My Fatherland!), and "Hej Slovane!" (Hey Ye Slavs!). Miss Miluse Splichal then recited a long epic poem by Svatopluk Cech, "Svetlo V Temnotach" (Light Shineth in the Darkness"). She recited with a faultless enunciation and a full comprehension of the import of that poetic creation. Stormy applause rewarded her efforts. Miss Anexka Pechous, with equally great success, declaimed another one of Cech's poems, "Ctyri Bohatyri"</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0796.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>(Four Heroes). A humorous vocal duet wound up the program....The singers were Misses Bozena Fencl and Miluse Splichal. Miss Zeman deserves much credit for her work in preparing this program. Mr. J. J. Jelinek the editor [of Spravedlnost], then spoke concerning our Free Thought and how it fares today. Chairman Ploss declared the meeting ended at 6:30 P. M. Free entertainment followed and continued until late in the evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
