<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-12-07">Dec. 7, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">The Donation of Cesky Narodni Hrbitov</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1217</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1217.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-12-07">Dec. 7, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">THE DONATION OF CESKY NARODNI HRBITOV</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The board of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) remembered our Free Thought schools with a very large gift, $2,500, in its last meeting. Of course, it is not much, if we consider the wide development of our Free Thought school system; but, on the other hand, it is certainly a substantial contribution. Naturally, we realize that the board of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov has very definite obligations toward our public and national institutions which it must not neglect.</p>
   <p>But at the same time, it must be borne in mind that every one of us, not only corporations, has a similar obligation. This applies to all individual citizens. Let us be frank and admit that the Bohemian colony in Chicago does not consist exclusively of poor folk. There are many men among us already with whom the epithet "rich" or "capitalist" is neither satirical nor inappropriate. How <pb facs="5418478_7_1218.jpg" n="2"/>much support do our Free Thought schools get from this side every year? Is it that our well-to-do countrymen believe that they have no real obligation to our Free Thought school system? It would be very sad indeed if this opinion would take permanent root among them.</p>
   <p>The men who are responsible for the well-being of our Free Thought schools should approach everybody without hesitation, knock on every door, not only on the door of our National Cemetery. Such an analysis of the pulse of our public opinion would do absolutely no harm. If rich Jews can fulfill their national obligations, there is no reason whatever why rich Bohemians should shun theirs. And a rich man ceased to be a rare exception among us a long time ago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
