<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-08-17">Aug. 17, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">New Religious Sect.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1324</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1324.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1901-08-17">Aug. 17, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">NEW RELIGIOUS SECT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Liberal Society, (Jan A. Komensky), was incorporated as a religious society under the laws of the State of Illinois on June 5th, 1901, and has the right to elect a speaker who is legally empowered to perform the marriage ceremony according to the methods of the society. Joe J. Burita was chosen to act as the speaker. The Society, which was formerly known as the Jan A. Komensky Educational Society, does not intend to allow it's educational activities to slow down. It intends to increase and expand them.</p>
   <p>Since money is required to do this and since the Society is composed mostly of people of small means, the speaker has elected to perform his duties without pay.</p>
   <p>All money collected by the Society will go into the Society's treasury, to be used for the maintainence of the educational class, which will be arranged for evenings, in the Society's building. Beginning next month the Society will also hold regular lecture meetings, before the Sunday school meetings every Sunday afternoon.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1325.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Twice each week, on Monday and Thursday, the speaker, Jos. J. Burita, will teach English. Other educational projects will be started as soon as financial conditions permit. All decent Bohemians, irrespective of religious beliefs, will be allowed to attend the English school, all other educational classes, and all lectures. For the privilege of attending the school and other educational projects a small fee will be charged. Admission to the Sunday lectures will be free; however, a voluntary contribution will be taken for the building fund, which now amounts to over $50. According to the speaker, Mr. Burita, the purpose of the Society is for the members to strive for a moral and dignified life and to further this ideal, by example and teaching in order to gain and convert their friends. He does not think that for this purpose it is necessary to resort to abuse and scoffing. What is necessary is continuous positive work, governed at all times by the rules of decency. The Society must proclaim at the very beginning that no barbarous attack will be made upon any religious sect nor against the liberal camp.</p>
   <p>The Society's hall, where meetings are held every Saturday is located at 774 So. Ashland Ave., near 17th Street. The Board of Trustees is composed of <pb facs="5418478_7_1326.jpg" n="3"/>the following named persons: J.J.Burita, V. Chochola, Ruzena Fivek, Richard Hlina, Jos. Herout, Jos. Richter, Marie Hasek.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
