<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-25">Dec. 25, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Best Way for a Freethinker to Celebrate Christmas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0953</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0953.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-25">Dec. 25, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE BEST WAY FOR A FREETHINKER TO CELEBRATE CHRISTMAS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a known fact that Christmas, as it is celebrated by the churches today, was borrowed and taken over from pagan nations who at this time of the year celebrated the winter solstice, the repeated birth of the sun, which is a symbol of light and life. For us, the enlightened people of the twentieth century, Free Thought is a light which is illuminating the road of life, and therefore each Freethinker who has not yet contributed toward the first Narodni Dan Svobodomyslnych (National Tax of Freethinkers) should do so this Christmas time.</p>
   <p>The problem is to bring the collection of the Narodni Dan Svobodomyslnych to a conclusion in order to avoid interference with the collection of contributions for the benefit of Mr. Hoover's relief fund for suffering people in Europe. We are well aware of the fact that prevailing conditions are pretty bad. But if we should lag behind the proceeds of the Catholic Saint Wenceslaus Tax now being collected by the Bohemian-American Catholics whom <pb facs="5418478_7_0954.jpg" n="2"/>we outnumber, it would be proof that the indifference and weariness which now prevails among the Bohemians of America is a very grave phenomenon, that it is actually a catastrophe.</p>
   <p>Each spiritual movement needs financial means for its propagation. In order that we may have good Free Thought literature, a good organ, and good schools, everybody who claims to be a Bohemian Freethinker of America must do something for his convictions at once. In case of a new failure it will be useless to say: "I did not know it was so bad. If I had only known it was so bad I would have contributed something." Yes, it is an absolute necessity, and nobody will have the excuse that he did not know about it, because for three months, once a week at least, he has read about it in all of our Bohemian newspapers.</p>
   <p>All contributions should be sent to the office of the Narodni Dan Svobodomyslnych, 2232 South Kedzie Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Secure for yourself during this holiday season the inner satisfaction of <pb facs="5418478_7_0955.jpg" n="3"/>knowing that you have fulfilled your obligation toward your convictions!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
