<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-24">May 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Second Convention of the Cesko-Slovanske Evangelicke Cirkve Ve Spojenych Statech</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1146</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1146.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-24">May 24, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE SECOND CONVENTION OF THE CESKO-SLOVANSKE EVANGELICKE CIRKVE VE SPOJENYCH STATECH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A mass meeting of members of the Cesko-Slovanske Cirkve Ve Spojenych Statech (Bohemian-Slavonic Evangelical Churches in the United States) was held at the Baptist Church on Throop Street Friday evening. The speakers were the following gentlemen: Reverend Miloslav Filipi, Reverend E. Urbitsky, Reverend Pavel Slaby and Reverend Jan Blum. The Church was filled to overflowing and the participants evidently enjoyed the program. The convention was called to order by Reverend Pisek of New York Saturday morning. The chairman, Reverend Vaclav Vanek, opened the meeting and appointed a colonization committee consisting of Reverend A. J. Mancol, chairman, and Brothers K. Brazda, J. Becicka, J. Vavra, and Louis Vokoun.</p>
   <p>Letters of greetings were read from the following preachers: Dusek, Rybar, Bicht, Kovar, Cada, Link, Hegar, and Stevcek. Brother Horak, a visitor from Texas, presented greetings of the congregation of which he is a member and said <pb facs="5418478_7_1147.jpg" n="2"/>that his congregation is in sympathy with all that would lighten the hearts of those present. Mrs. and Mr. Sixta also sent greetings.</p>
   <p>The interdenominational organ committee and the book store committee submitted their reports. They urged all Slavonic Evangelical churches to become stockholders of these two enterprises.</p>
   <p>Reverend Josef Bren, representative of the Federated Slavonic Protestant Churches, moved that an association of Protestant Federated Churches be formed. His motion brought on a debate in which almost all of the delegates took part, and a committee of sixteen members was appointed to start the preliminary work.</p>
   <p>The resolutions committee presented the following resolution of thanks to the Denni Hlasatel:</p>
   <p>"To the editorial staff and publishers of the Denni Hlasatel: The Second Interdenominational Convention of Bohemian-Slavonic Evangelical Churches hereby offers <pb facs="5418478_7_1148.jpg" n="3"/>public thanks to the editors and publishers of the Denni Hlasatel for their offer of space for advertising and articles referring to our convention during its course. For the resolutions committee, Josef Krenkek."</p>
   <p>Sincere thanks were offered to the members of Protestant churches in Chicago for hospitality shown to out-of-town delegates.</p>
   <p>The convention adopted a resolution concerning the celebration of the John Huss anniversary in the year 1915, recommending: (1) work with increased energy on preparations for the John Huss jubilee celebration; (2) commemoration of the anniversary in every community; (3) the arranging of open-air meetings with good speakers. (4) the arranging of demonstrations; (5) the holding of lectures with slides; (6) that the celebrations be imbued with the enthusiasm and spirit of John Huss and characterized by lusty singing; (7) that those celebrating the day be urged to support all decent nondenominational celebrations; (8) that the literature be distributed freely; (9) that pictures of John Huss and scenes referring to that period be shown; (10) that the celebration be started early <pb facs="5418478_7_1149.jpg" n="4"/>this fall (11) the installation in each church of an appropriate memorial of the occasion; (12) the organizing of a large pilgrimage to Bohemia under the direction of Reverend Pisek as its chairman; (13) the formation of a federation of Evangelical churches; (14) the formation of denominational unions in America for the purpose of arranging a John Huss day.</p>
   <p>The meeting was adjourned at two o'clock in the afternoon and all those in attendance assembled before the First Methodist Church where a group photograph was taken.</p>
   <p>In all Bohemian Evangelical churches meetings are called for today, both in the afternoon and in the evening, at which the convention delegates will speak.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
