<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-22">May 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Sixth Annual Convention of the United Societies of Chicago the Bohemians Played Leading Role in a Stormy Session</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0620</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0620.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-22">May 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">SIXTH ANNUAL CONVENTION OF THE UNITED SOCIETIES OF CHICAGO THE BOHEMIANS PLAYED LEADING ROLE IN A STORMY SESSION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The sixth annual gathering of the United Societies of Chicago, furthering the defense of personal rights of the citizenry, was held yesterday afternoon. The meeting took place in the South Side Turner Hall at 31st and State Streets, and was largely attended by delegates of all nationalities.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order by the chairman, Mr. Charles Kellerman. He greeted the assembled delegates warmly, and called attention to the beneficient activities of the organization during the past five years. The secretary, Mr. Anton J. Cermak, read the minutes of the executive committee's meeting. A motion was made and passed that the minutes be accepted without being read. A motion then followed that the chairman appoint a credentials committee. The motion passed, and the following named Bohemians were appointed members of the committee: Messrs. Rud.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0621.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Svoboda, Jos. Stastny, and Leo Marek.</p>
   <p>The credentials committee reported that 735 organizations are represented in the convention. The report was accepted. The proceedings continued, and three vice-chairmen were appointed, one of whom was Mr. J. Cervenka; as secretaries, Messrs. Banebas and Jandus. A committee for the amendment of the by-laws was elected and the following were named: Messrs. Jandus, Denemark, Sedlak, Vojan, and Judge Uhlir.</p>
   <p>Otto Bettman called to the attention of the gathering the fact that we have two laws to which he is opposed. One of these laws states that only a respectable citizen of good morals can secure a license to keep a saloon. The other states that a saloonkeeper who is caught keeping open on election day absolutely cannot become a citizen. The organization should endeavor to have these laws removed. If these laws were enforced, then no one who worked on that day could acquire citizenship.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0622.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>One of the delegates, D. Sateman, somewhat angered, inquired as to just what did the convention have to do with the liquor question. The meeting recessed for ten minutes. The band playing all kinds of national airs.</p>
   <p>When the resolutions and amendments committees returned, the secretary Mr. Cermak, announced that he wished to explain a certain supplement concerning the delegates from the public press. Then he introduced a resolution the representatives of the newspapers should not have the right to serve on the executive committee, and that the committee be composed of seventy-five delegates from individual organizations, and fifteen delegates at large. These are to be composed of representatives of the press, but not having any voting privileges. This motion raised a veritable storm of protest. Mr. Cervenka spoke in opposition to the motion. He called attention to the merits of the press, and decidedly protested against any such discrimination. Mr. Jandus also made vigorous protest against the adoption of the motion. After a lengthy debate, it was finally decided <pb facs="5418478_7_0623.jpg" n="4"/>not to make any change in the matter.</p>
   <p>A nominations committee of eleven members was them elected, with Mr. Cervenka as chairman. Other Bohemians elected to this committee were: Messrs. Cermak and Smejkal.</p>
   <p>Several speakers addressed the convention, among whom were: Mr. Prilow, delegate of the Schwaben Ferein; Dr. Kersher; <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Lebrin, who travelled in Bohemian and Germany, and in all Europe stated that he did not see so many drunkards as he saw in a single prohibition town in America. Finally, Judge Uhlir was called, and his cheerful talk was enthusiastically received. At last, the committee returned and made its report about the nominations for the executive committee. The following named Bohemians were among the nominees: John Cervenka, Anton J. Cermak, C. R. Jandus, John Rezabek, Jos. Ringl, Jos. Smejkal, J. Stastny, Ferd. Svoboda, Anton Zahrobsky, Jos. Z. Uhlir, Anton Denemark, Jos. E. Marek, Wm. Blaha, Anton Lupinek, Joseph D.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0624.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Marek, Jos. Houska and J. P. Javorsky. Delegates at large from the newspapers: Otto Fuerst for Hlasatel; Mr. Lorenz for Narod; Mr. Sedlak for Spravedlnost; Mr. Krasny for Svornost.</p>
   <p>The Italian delegation protested against discrimination being shown them. The protest was heard and the matter adjusted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
