<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-22">Apr. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Meeting of the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0830</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0830.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-22">Apr. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A MEETING OF THE SDRUZENI CESKYCH SVOBODOMYSLNYCH SKOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol (Federation of the Bohemian Free Thought Schools) took place yesterday. The meeting was opened by the president, Mr. Josef Tichava. All other officials and many delegates were present. The minutes of the previous meeting were approved as read. The minutes of the subcommittee were also approved. A letter was received from the board of directors of the Ustredni Jednota Cesko-Americkych Zen (Central Union of Bohemian-American Women). In it the Sdruzeni was informed about the death of a former delegate to the Sdruzeni, Mrs. Karolina Zika, and the Jednota enclosed a check of $25 as a contribution to the Sdruzeni. This sum was bequeathed by the said deceased delegate to the cause of the Sdruzeni. It was decided to send a letter of thanks to the Jednota. A letter was received from the Vcelky (Ladies Auxiliary of the Czechoslovak National Alliance). It informed the Sdruzeni of the appointment of a delegate and enclosed a contribution of $25 for the benefit <pb facs="5418478_7_0831.jpg" n="2"/>of the schools. A letter was received from the board of directors of the T. G. Masaryk School informing the Sdruzeni of the appointment of its delegates....A letter was received from the Narodni Tiskarna (national printing house) in which an offer was made to print the periodical Svobodna Skola (Free Thought School). The delegate Mr. Masek asked that this matter be deferred, and that the printing committee be asked to investigate it and report at the next meeting. Mrs. Radesinsky gave a report of the F. B. Zdrubek School. In it she claimed that on the days the Sokols hold gymnastic exercises, the attendance of the school falls off. The teacher, Mrs. Reacky, announced that in a meeting held by the Sokol Rozvoj a committee was appointed which was to come to the meeting of Sdruzeni and give an account of the situation as reported by Mrs. Radesinsky, and to seek an adjustment of it....Mrs. Dobias claimed that an adjustment is possible, and it all depends how matters are handled by the Sokol trainer Mr. Kocka. Hours devoted to the training of the Sokols could be changed in order to eliminate the conflict with the hours devoted to school instruction. Mrs. Soucek suggested that day classes be changed only on Saturdays and Sundays.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0832.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A motion was made to organize a school for the Utulna A Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage), and Mr. Hrisny will submit this proposition in the next meeting of the Utulna and report back to the Sdruzeni when it meets again. Mr. Krafcik reported on the condition of textbooks which, he asserted, were found to be in good order.</p>
   <p>The Sdruzeni was informed that it is free to use the hall of the Carter H. Harrison High School on the fourth Sunday in May for the purpose of giving a school concert and entertainment, but the principal of the school stipulated that no admission may be charged, or, if the Sdruzeni wishes to charge admission, it would have to make an application to the Chicago Board of Education and obtain a permit to do so. It was also announced in this meeting that the Svaz Svobodomyslnych (Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers) proposes to have a school picnic at Willow Springs, Illinois on the third Sunday in June, and desires to know if the Sdruzeni will agree to ask the various schools to arrange the picnic and care for the comfort of the children. The refreshments for the children would be free, only the fares would have to <pb facs="5418478_7_0833.jpg" n="4"/>be paid. The proposed picnic was approved.</p>
   <p>Since one of the delegates of the Svaz, Mrs. V. K. Soukup, is to act as a teacher in the schools of the Sdruzeni, the Svaz was asked to appoint another delegate for it is not permitted that a teacher represent any other organization but the Sdruzeni.</p>
   <p>The last item on the program was a report on income and disbursements after which the meeting adjourned.</p>
   <p>Mr. Josef Tichava, president,</p>
   <p>Mr. Karel Soukup, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
