<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-19">Sept. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">An Invitation to the Third General Convention of the National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0734</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0734.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-19">Sept. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">AN INVITATION TO THE THIRD GENERAL CONVENTION OF THE NATIONAL ALLIANCE OF BOHEMIAN CATHOLICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On October 3, 4, and 5, 1922, the third general convention of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics [of America]) will be held in Chicago.....The convention proper will begin at 2 P.M. on October 3, 1922, in the Ceskoslovenska-Americka Sin (Czechoslovak-American Hall), 1436 West 18th Street, Chicago.</p>
   <p>All of you who stood at the cradle of the Svaz and witnessed its growth to this day may reminisce with pride and hopefully look forward into the future. Twice before we have made a survey of our ranks and our common work. Today we stand at the threshold of the third of these [periodic] events to express our wishes and to listen to the reports of our delegates and officers, <pb facs="5418478_7_0735.jpg" n="2"/>thus receiving a new impetus for further work. We have invited to this third convention the entire Bohemian clergy and Catholic laity, both men and women, and today we issue a call to all who have the permanence of a representative body of Bohemian-American Catholics close to their hearts. It goes without saying that the convention will be remarkable and highly interesting. Every Czech priest and every Czech Catholic layman should attend this convention if conditions permit him to do so. All may be certain of a hearty welcome.</p>
   <p>Anticipating that we shall meet our foremost Bohemian-Americans during the days of October 3, 4, and 5, we call to all of you:"Come, you are expected!"</p>
   <p>Members of the central office of the Svaz: Nota bene--all telegrams and letters concerning the convention should be addressed to National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics, 3207 West 22nd Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
