<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-13">Oct. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From the St. Agnes Czech Community</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1363</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1363.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-10-13">Oct. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE ST. AGNES CZECH COMMUNITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The St. Agnes Czech community will participate today in the raising of a service flag in honor of the soldiers and sailors from the 83rd recruiting division. This event was arranged by the citizens' auxiliary committee, under the sponsorship of the State council of defence. It will be held on the playground of Corkery school, 25th Street and Kildare Avenue.</p>
   <p>More than 200 boys from our community belong to the 83rd division. The celebration will help to promote the Fourth Liberty War Loan. All members of our community will gather at the community center, Central Park Avenue and 27th Street, at 1 P. M. The parade to Corkery school will begin at 1:30 P. M., headed by bands and flag bearers. Mothers of soldiers from our community will form a group of their own. All pupils, from the third grade up, of our community school will march along, each bearing a small flag. Some of them will be in Sokol garb. Two hundred girls from our school will march in the parade. They will be in white uniform dresses and will represent the 200 soldiers <pb facs="5418478_7_1364.jpg" n="2"/>from our community. Three groups of scouts and cadets will be guard of honor for our church flag.</p>
   <p>A large American flag will be borne by older girls. The Vcelky (Little Bees) women's auxiliary, and workers for the Liberty Loan Campaign, will be there in large numbers.</p>
   <p>We expect that our community will be represented in an impressive manner, and that our group will be the most colorful in the entire parade. Don't fail to take part!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
