<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-12-04">Dec. 4, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Meeting of the Board of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-12-04">Dec. 4, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A MEETING OF THE BOARD OF THE CESKY NARODNI HRBITOV</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular monthly meeting of the board of representatives of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) was held last night in the hall of the Cesko-Anglicka Svobodomyslna Skola (Bohemian-English Free-Thought School.....</p>
   <p>The payment of all bills, mostly for building work done during the month--including the building of the crematorium--was approved. President [Jan] Pech cautioned the secretary to make a separate record of the latter bills, in order to determine the exact cost of the crematorium as easily and as accurately as possible.....</p>
   <p>The pay roll for the past month shows fifty-six employees whose combined salaries totaled $2,830.74....</p>
   <p>The Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Society) has sent in <pb facs="5418478_7_1186.jpg" n="2"/>a letter protesting against the remark of one of the representatives who charged that the Society was supporting people who do not deserve it. After a debate concerning this letter, it was agreed to reply to the effect that no charge of this kind has been brought to the official knowledge of the board of representatives.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Mencl presented the report of the buildings committee, and announced that the laying of the cornerstone of the Crematorium will be celebrated in a festive manner next Sunday. The ceremonies will start exactly at 1:00 P.M. The architect, Mr. [Frontisek] Randak, reported that the work on the basement has been finished, and should the weather be favorable, all work with the exception of the roof may be completed in six weeks. Next Sunday, just before it is torn down, the old chapel will be photographed.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Hladovec expressed the wish that a priest, or a Protestant minister, might be tolerated in the Cemetery as a private person, provided he did not use any ceremonial clothing, i. e., that he appear in civilian attire. He complained <pb facs="5418478_7_1187.jpg" n="3"/>that the board had been intolerant and narrow minded at times, and that such attitudes should be avoided. As long as neither Freethinkers nor the Cemetery are offended, we should keep hands off.....If a president of a Free-Thought society is permitted to conduct a funeral service, regardless of his inexperience or lack of knowledge, and to behave as clumsily and shamefully as you please, there should be no objection to letting a sectarian present a decent sermon, providing he does not offend anybody. The board agreed with this interpretation.....</p>
   <p>The board agreed to grant the following contributions: Free-Thought schools, $2,500; Ceska Utulna A Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage), $500; Matice Vyssiho Vzdelani (Council for Higher Education), $50; Delnicky Pevecky Sbor (Workingmen's Singing Society), $25.</p>
   <p>Income reported last meeting, $6,848.66; balance carried from last month, $29,703.13; total, $31,751.79 (sic). Expenses, $11,502.60; in treasurer's hands, $20,249.19.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
