<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-26">Sept. 26, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">To Free Thought Czechoslovaks in the United States!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0876</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0876.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-26">Sept. 26, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">TO FREE THOUGHT CZECHOSLOVAKS IN THE UNITED STATES!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In accordance with the decision of the fourth convention of the Ceska Svobodomyslna Obec (Czech Free Thought Congregation) and the conference of the State of Illinois group held in May of this year, we are starting to collect the Druha Narodni Dan (Second National Tax) of Free Thought Czechs, the purpose of which is not only to build a powerful organization of Free Thought people of Czech America, but to promote and support Czech Free Thought schools in this country--half of the money collected is to be devoted to this purpose.</p>
   <p>These two lofty purposes alone should induce every Free Thought man and woman to observe the tax. If we look at opposite camps we see that frequently hundreds of thousands of dollars are spent on reactionary causes, and enterprises hostile to the liberty of the people. We are hoping, therefore, that our people will try to avoid any possible blame at least as to generosity, that <pb facs="5418478_7_0877.jpg" n="2"/>they will not be outdone by the enemies of liberty and progress, particularly when it is a question not only of building a strong organization but also of saving our youth, our Czech youth, which is our only hope for the future in these times.</p>
   <p>For these reasons we appeal to you, Czech men and women, to help us in the collecting of the Druha Narodni Dan of the Free Thought people. Give as much as your personal conditions permit, and see to it that there is not a single individual among us who has not been approached in this matter, so that there may be nobody who can made the excuse that he or she had not been approached and had not known anything about the tax. Put your names on the list of collectors, and get your collection books! Call on or address Mr. Frant. Haut, 4236 West 22nd Street, (John Huss Memorial), Chicago, Illinois. Success to the Druha Narodni Dan of the Freethinkers!</p>
   <p>The tax committee of the Ceska Svobodna Obec</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
