<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-22">May 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Bohemian-American Cremation Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0617</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0617.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-22">May 22, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN CREMATION SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian-American Cremation Society celebrated the tenth anniversary of its existence with a fine celebration recently. The purpose and significance of the society was explained to the listeners by capable speakers, in both the Bohemian and English language. The chairman of the arrangements committee, Mr. John Hejno, welcomed the visitors, and turned the supervision of the celebration over to the president of the society, Mr. Joseph W. Egermayer.</p>
   <p>Following a beautiful rendition of two musical numbers by Miss A. Cada, Mr. Egermayer gave a brief summary of the history of the society.</p>
   <p>In a private home more than ten years ago, four men and a woman met to give an impulse to the founding of a society for the advancement of a more rationalistic method of burying human bodies than had been, until <pb facs="5418478_7_0618.jpg" n="2"/>then, generally customary among Bohemians. From this insignificant number of founders, the number of members grew to the present 464, and the hope is warranted that it will now grow much faster then heretofore. The society has a fund, amounting to $619.84, devoted exclusively to covering the expenses in connection with the burial of members. The fund for current expenses amounts to $181.91.</p>
   <p>After the discourse by the president, the Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society rendered the song"O vlasti Ma" (O! My Fatherland). Dr. J. F. Pecival, who spoke in English, gave the reason for the cremation of bodies, and called attention to the trifling objections raised against it. He explained that from a scientific standpoint the same process occurs during both methods of interment. The body, composed of a few gases, three-fourths of the weight of the body being water, composed of oxygen and hydrogen, <pb facs="5418478_7_0619.jpg" n="3"/>disintegrates into its constituent parts during cremation, quickly and cleanly, but while mouldering in the ground, it requires a long period of time. From the standpoint of ethics and health, it is impossible to do otherwise than condemn the practice of burying bodies in the ground, and take up the practice of cremation as is being done by the more enlightened people. In the same sense, Dr. Fr. Iska spoke, and disproved the objections to cremation which are raised chiefly by the Catholic Church.</p>
   <p>This significant celebration was brought to a close by Mr. Egermayer, thanking everybody who aided in its success by their attendance. The society was deserving of a much greater visitation, even if we take into consideration the uncertain weather conditions of yesterday.</p>
   <p>The society gave beautiful souvenirs of the occasion, which contained among other things, the names of all members.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
