<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-06">May 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Cesky Narodni Hrbitov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1114</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1114.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-06">May 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE CESKY NARODNI HRBITOV</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The board of representatives of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) held one of its regular meetings. The meeting dealt with the letter from the Ceska Utulna a Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old Peoples' Home and Orphanage) asking whether the Hrbitov is planning to insert a document into the cornerstone, which will be laid May 30, of the orphanage's new building; in the event that the organization is planning to do so, the letter asks that the document be prepared.....The preparation of that document was agreed upon....and one hundred dollars was apportioned for the Utulna a Sirotcinec, which will be donated to the institution on that occasion.</p>
   <p>Mr. Smejkal reported that the executive committee had received a letter advising the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov of the plan to pave Crawford Avenue over a distance of 2,719 feet from Argyle Avenue, at an approximate cost of $29,000. Since that part of the street is rarely used, and is still in a fairly good <pb facs="5418478_7_1115.jpg" n="2"/>condition, the executive committee, together with the other two cemetery associations and owners of adjacent real estate filed a protest against this plan. With the help of the Bohemian commissioners, Mr. Sima and Mr. Novak, the protest was successful, and this question will not come up for the next five or ten years.</p>
   <p>President Pecha reported that Decoration Day falls on a Sunday and asked for an expression of opinion as to whether or not the celebration at the cemetery should not be postponed until the following Monday.....The delegates decided to hold the celebration Sunday, even though the Utulna a Sirotcinec will hold its ceremony of laying the cornerstone on the same day. The celebration at the cemetery will take place in the morning and the Utulna's affair in the afternoon.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1116.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The treasurer, Mr. Jurka, reported an income of $16,111.40 and expenses of $13,919.38, which, added to last month's balance, leaves a balance on hand of $8,405.20. The meeting agreed finally to pay the new year's donations, there now being sufficient cash on hand.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
