<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-08-04">Aug. 4, 1904</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Meeting of Representatives of the Bohemian National Cemetery Association.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1275</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1275.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-08-04">Aug. 4, 1904</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">MEETING OF REPRESENTATIVES OF THE BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY ASSOCIATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the representatives of the Bohemian National Cemetery Association was held yesterday in the lower hall of the Bohemian American Liberal School on 18th. St. The attendance at the meeting was very small, apparently the result of the convention of the C. S. P. S. (Czechoslovak Benevolent Society) being held in St. Louis, which is being attended by many members of the Association. The meeting was called to order at 8 p. m. by the vice-chairman Mr. Mencl. The secretary Mr. Josef Filip read the minutes of the previous meeting, which were accepted as read. The financial secretary, Mr. Husak, read the bills payable of the Association, they were all ordered paid, though there was some discussion about several of them. Finally everything was explained and the meeting proceeded to further business. The secretary, Mr. Filip, brought before the meeting two Bohemian Women who requested free graves for their children. They were Mrs. Marie Kunrad, requesting a grave for her fifteen year old daughter Marie and Mrs. Braun, who asked for a grave for her two and one-half year old child. These requests were unanimously granted, whereupon, after thanking the members of the Association the women withdrew from the meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1276.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Communications were then read. J. Meduna requested that he be taken back to work as he has been unable to find anything else since he was discharged. In his letter he complained that he had been discharged because of pressure by certain individuals. A prolonged debate on the matter ensued. The Gardner, Mr. Ine, explained that there were too many people employed on the Cemetery and that it was necessary to dismiss someone. That was the reason for the discharge of J. Meduna. Representative Rehak interceded, and explained that Meduna should be re-employed, because he is a member of the Liberal Community, and of the Knights and Ladies, and that should be given consideration. Also Representative Pospisk in speaking of the matter expressed his surprise, that there were several persons employed by the Cemetery who do not belong to any of the lodges. He knows that several lodge members applied for employment but it was not given to them. The Gardner explained the matter from his viewpoint, and convinced the representatives, that it is necessary to employ only capable people whether or not they belong to any lodge. In that respect Representative Masak agrees with him and requests that such matters be turned over to the managing committee, Finally a motion was adopted that such matters be left to the managing committee for consideration.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1277.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Bozovsky, the treasurer of the Old Peoples Home, sent to the National Cemetery Association a check for $1,000. This is the eighth thousand and it would be desirable it it were the eightieth for the Home's money is well taken care of by the Cemetery Association. Bids were received for furnishing coal to the Cemetery. Four bids were received namely from V. Roubal George Lill Company, Wilston Coal Company and Scully and Kostner Company. A lengthy and lively debate followed regarding the bids, but all of the representatives wereunanimous that the contract be given to a Bohemian firm. Gardener Ine was asked for his recommendation as to the quality of the coal, proposed, that nine carloads be ordered, half and half of the so called Indiana block and new river Pocahontas. Representative Rehak, proposed that the lowest bid be accepted, that of Scully and Kostner, which was protested against by treasurer Jurka, who maintained that it is not always smart to buy that which is offered cheapest, without investigating the quality offered.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1278.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Finally the low bid of Scully and Kostner of $3.35 per ton for New River Pocahontas was accepted. Reports of the auditing committee were made. The committee examined the books and the entries of Bonds, everything was found in order. Also the accounting committee announced that the bequest of $300 by the deceased Mrs. Barta will be paid over to the Association as soon as possible after the matter is settled by the Probate Court. The treasurers report for the past six months was then read. It is interesting that the wealth of the National Cemetery increased about $20,000 during the past six months.</p>
   <p>The following report for the month of July was then read. Receipts:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Payments on lots</cell>
     <cell>$1,070.35</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Flowers for Graves</cell>
     <cell>291.25</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Raising of Graves</cell>
     <cell>13.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>History</cell>
     <cell>3.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Floral pieces</cell>
     <cell>296.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Foundations</cell>
     <cell>671.90</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Graves in rows (small)</cell>
     <cell>110.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Graves in rows (large)</cell>
     <cell>48.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Lots small</cell>
     <cell>20.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Lots large</cell>
     <cell>93.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1279.jpg" n="5"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Telephone</cell>
     <cell>.60</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Misc.</cell>
     <cell>.50</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>$2,618.10</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance on hand from previous</cell>
     <cell>2,355.24</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>4,973.34</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Disbursements</cell>
     <cell>2,233.57</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Balance in treasury</cell>
     <cell>$2,739.77</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>During July, eight lots valued at $1,060 were sold. Sixty-eight corpses were buried- one free of charge. Two hundred fourteen dollars and seven cents was deposited in the reserve fund. After several less important decisions the meeting was adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
