<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-08-01">Aug. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">St. Wenceslaus Tax of 1920</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0982</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0982.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-08-01">Aug. 1, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">ST. WENCESLAUS TAX OF 1920</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We take the liberty of calling the attention of all our district and parish alliances and the Bohemian Catholic people to a new project of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics in America).</p>
   <p>The executive committee, together with the consultation committee of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe, decided, after due consideration, to collect the Svatovaclavska Dan 1920 (St. Wenceslaus Tax of 1920) throughout the entire United States. The collection of the tax will begin on or about September 28, 1920, and will continue until October 15, 1920. The purpose of this collection is to support the extension of the Bohemian Catholic press in the United States and across the ocean, and to support our poor students and all of our cultural-religious interests.</p>
   <p>Our district and parish alliances, and individuals who will go from house <pb facs="5418478_7_0983.jpg" n="2"/>to house, will collect the Svatovaclavska Dan from every Czechoslovak Catholic in every one of our Bohemian Catholic parishes in the United States. The tax will be a voluntary one, but the smallest contribution should amount to at least one dollar. Every contributor will receive as a souvenir a picture of St. Wenceslaus. This picture should be displayed in the home of every contributor to prove that he has fulfilled his patriotic and religious duty. Contributions will be entered in the collection books, which will be sent to every district and parish alliance and to all spiritual leaders of the Bohemian Catholic parishes by the headquarters of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe during the course of this month. Every collector of the Svatovaclavska Dan will receive a collection book with double receipt slips, one of which will be given to the contributor and the other will stay in the book, which will then be sent by the officers of the respective district or parish alliance to the headquarters of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe. The contributions will be audited by a special committee and a report will then be published in our Catholic organ, the Hlidka (Sentinel), together with a statement showing the total number of <pb facs="5418478_7_0984.jpg" n="3"/>contributions collected by each individual district or parish alliance. The district and parish alliances are entitled to keep ten per cent of the amount collected to be used for publicity purposes and local needs. All expenses incurred in the collection of the Svatovaclavska Dan will be paid by the headquarters of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe, which entrusted the whole project to the undersigned special committee.</p>
   <p>The collection of the Svatovaclavska Dan will require the co-operation of everyone. It will be necessary to raise an army of self-sacrificing collectors--men and women--and therefore we urge all the district and parish alliances to prepare themselves for the collection ahead of time. Besides that, we recommend that the Svatovaclavska Dan be discussed at every opportunity in order that an interest may be aroused in our project. We are fully convinced that our endeavor will be generally comprehended by our people; and with the help and harmonious co-operation of all the Bohemian Catholics of the United States, the Svatovaclavska Dan will meet with success, and that by this deed our Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe <pb facs="5418478_7_0985.jpg" n="4"/>will accomplish another meritorious cultural-religious and patriotic deed. Zdar Buh! (May God Give You Success!)</p>
   <p>For the special committee for the collection of the Svatovaclavska Dan of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe:</p>
   <p>(Signed): Reverend Frantisek Bozenek,</p>
   <p>Vaclav Kadlec, Joseph J. Janda,</p>
   <p>Marie Novotny, Rozalie Nedved,</p>
   <p>Anna Zdarsky.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
