<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-05-19">May 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Consecration of New Church in Brookfield</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1214</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1214.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-05-19">May 19, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">CONSECRATION OF NEW CHURCH IN BROOKFIELD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The settlement in Brookfield neighbors on the very popular outing resorts of Lyons and Riverside, where thousands of our countrymen like to spend their week ends. It is an independent Chicago suburb which holds promise of developing into a purely Bohemian community, due to the efforts of our well-known real-estate dealer, Mr. Konrad Ricker.</p>
   <p>Yesterday this settlement in Brookfield celebrated the consecration of its new, small but attractive St. Barbara church.</p>
   <p>The beautiful weather, just ideal for such an occasion, lured many hundreds of our countrymen out in the open. During the whole forenoon practically all of the streetcars bound for Lyons or La Grange, as well as the special train of the Chicago, Burlington, and Quincy Railway were crowded.</p>
   <p>All those who got off the train in Brookfield were personally welcomed by Mr. Ricker who, after the arrival of the main body of the visitors, led the <pb facs="5418478_7_1215.jpg" n="2"/>guests to the not-far-distant corner of Prairie Avenue and Windemore Street where the church is located.</p>
   <p>The church itself is a neat and handsome building with an imposing tower under which the main entrance is located. The entrance is flanked by two large windows and leads directly into the main hall, which has only one altar at the present time. The church pews can accommodate more than 250 worshippers. Above the portico is a stately choir and a medium-size organ. The church cost $6,400, of which $3,000 was contributed by Brookfield residents, and the balance donated by Mr. Ricker himself, who also donated the land. He did all this to make sure that the community which he founded and to whose full development he continues giving all possible care may have a centrally located place of worship. The church stands on a 150 by 125 foot lot.</p>
   <p>The festivity proper started with an official Bohemian sermon by the Reverend Innocent Kestl of the Bohemian parish of Blessed Agnes. The church was consecrated by H. E. E. J. Quigley, Archbishop of Chicago, who was assisted by a large number of clergymen in celebrating the first High Mass. Although <pb facs="5418478_7_1216.jpg" n="3"/>spacious, the little church could not accommodate all those who came to take part in the consecration ceremonies, and many of them had to listen from the outside. Shortly after noon, the benediction was pronounced.</p>
   <p>The visitors then made a round of inspection of the new Bohemian settlement. Mr. Ricker personally answered all requests for information and promised to do all in his power to secure a Bohemian priest for the parish and to see that a Bohemian school is also built in Brookfield. He told us that there are now 123 Bohemian families living in Brookfield, most of whom have bought lots in one of his two subdivisions in Brookfield and in Lyons.....</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The last two paragraphs of the article are nothing but advertising for Ricker's real-estate business.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
