<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-11-03">Nov. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Ellis Island</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1534</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1534.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-11-03">Nov. 3, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">ELLIS ISLAND</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was not until the local newspaper The Chicago Tribune and its associate papers in other cities called attention to the terrible conditions prevailing in Ellis Island that the Government saw fit to take disciplinary measures with the employees on that island and do something in the way of improvement in this immigration station which must be passed through by almost all immigrants. The Tribune, no matter what may have been the motives for its action, deserves an experession of recognition and sincere thanks. But then thanks are due to the paper not only from the immigrants but also from native Americans who desire a rapid Americanization of all immigrants. The first impression one receives in a new country is always the most permanent and decisive one. Therefore it takes many years before the immigrants forget the suffering and humiliation meted out to them in Ellis Island. When such an immigrant, just fresh after these experiences, falls a victim to <pb facs="5418478_7_1535.jpg" n="2"/>exploiters, it is small wonder that he comes to hate the country to which he came with so many high hopes, and that Americanization progresses so slowly.</p>
   <p>Therefore it will be necessary not only to improve conditions in Ellis Island but also do something in regard to advice and friendly counsel to newly arrived immigrants, thus causing them to love this country right from the start. They will also love all our institutions, artificial [sic] Americanization will become unnecessary, and the results of natural ways of making good American citizens will be immeasurably greater.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
