<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-28">Mar. 28, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Svaz Ceskych Svobodmyslnych Skol V Chicagu</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0916</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0916.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-28">Mar. 28, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE SVAZ CESKYCH SVOBODMYSLNYCH SKOL V CHICAGU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Following are the minutes of the regular meeting of the Svaz Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol v Chicagu (Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools of Chicago) held March 19, 1921:</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order by the chairman, Mr. Joseph Tichava, in the presence of all the officers and many delegates. After the delegates were greeted by the chairman, the reading of the minutes of the previous meeting followed. With one exception, the minutes were approved as read. The minutes of the executive committee meeting were also approved as read. The financial secretary, Mrs. Cepelak, then presented her annual report which was approved and ordered printed.</p>
   <p>The reading of communications followed. In a communication received from the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Bohemian Sisterhood), regarding the teachers salaries, the said organization protests against paying the teachers salaries <pb facs="5418478_7_0917.jpg" n="2"/>during vacations when the schools are closed. By not paying the salaries during vacations, the communication reads, the school expenses might be cut down. In a discussion which followed, Mrs. Radesinsky and Mrs. Frantiska Soucek explained this matter and told the delegates that such a misunderstanding would not have arisen if the delegates of the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota had protested when the matter of the teachers' salaries was discussed. It was resolved to send a letter to the above-mentioned organization explaining why some of the teachers received salaries during vacations. In the future all societies and organizations will be asked for their opinion on any financial question which may arise in order to avoid similar misunderstandings.</p>
   <p>The delegate of the Patronat Skoly Jan Amos Komensky (Board of Trustees of the Jan Amos Komensky School) complained that the tuition fee which the children are required to pay hardly covers the rental and cleaning expenses incurred by the school. Inasmuch as almost every one of the societies and organizations represented in the Svaz Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol were under the impression that the money collected from the school children go to the treasury of the <pb facs="5418478_7_0918.jpg" n="3"/>Svaz Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol, it was explained that these monies are kept by the respective boards of trustees to be used by them to pay the rental and cleaning bills, and in many cases this fee is not sufficient to cover even these expenses. This explanation was accepted by the delegates. The treasurer, Dr. Antonin Mueller, received a communication in which the Slovenska Svobodomyslna Skola (Slovak Free Thought School) asks for a contribution of twenty-five dollars, which sum is annually paid out to it by the Federation from a gift made by the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova (Bohemian National Cemetery Association). It was resolved to send the contribution of twenty-five dollars to the said school.</p>
   <p>The report of the business manager of the Svobodna Skola (Free School) for the month of February, 1921 was approved. Mr. Karel Jirak, the business manager, resigned from his office, but, according to the minutes of the meeting of the executive committee, he accepted the office again for the year of 1921. Mrs. Frantiska Soucek praised Mr. Jirak for his fine articles appearing in the Svobodna Skola, and for his businesslike handling of that organ. She appealed <pb facs="5418478_7_0919.jpg" n="4"/>to the delegates to report and explain in the meetings of their respective organizations that Mr. Jirak does not work on a commission basis, that he receives only a small compensation, and that, for his hard and responsible work, he deserves a larger salary. The delegates were requested to ask their respective organizations for an approval so that it will be possible to increase Mr. Jirak's compensation from fifteen to twenty-five dollars a month.</p>
   <p>Inasmuch as all of the old officers, with the exception of the secretary, were re-elected, the chairman, Mr. Joseph Tichava, in a brief speech reminded the new secretary, Mr. Karel Soukup, of his duties, expressing the hope that the new secretary would always willingly perform his duty in behalf of Bohemian Free Thought Schools. The new secretary was then asked to take office. The surety of the stock room clerk for textbooks, Mr. Frank Vlach, was approved.</p>
   <p>Because of the critical financial conditions in which the Svaz Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol found itself, a resolution was prepared by the resolution committee, in which Bohemian Free Thought organizations are requested to help <pb facs="5418478_7_0920.jpg" n="5"/>the Federation in some way, either by increasing their head taxes or by providing a monetary gift. This must be done in order that the schools may continue to operate. It was resolved that copies of this resolution be printed and sent to all Bohemian Free Thought organizations. A motion was carried that asked the delegates to appeal to their respective organizations to increase their head tax in behalf of the schools from five to seven cents. Many of our organizations are under the impression that the Federation receives plenty of money which should be sufficient revenue. But if we consider the fact that the Federation now receives the same amount of money as it did in the past when there were fewer pupils, fewer teachers, and the school necessities were not so expensive, then we come to the conclusion that the Federation has been spending its money very reasonably. At the present time, and contrary to former practices, there is no school superintendent, and therefore this appeal to our Bohemian Free Thought organizations is just and urgent.</p>
   <p>The treasurer, Dr. Antonin Mueller, explained the financial conditions of the Federation which, at the present time, are very critical; he stated that if <pb facs="5418478_7_0921.jpg" n="6"/>some help is not immediately forthcoming, the schools would have to be closed. But at the same time he expressed a hope that the Bohemian people and organizations would not permit this to happen. He also requested that a letter be sent to the Central District of the Americka Obec Sokolska (American Sokol Union), and that Sokoldom be asked to support by levying a head tax on its members. The motion was carried. Another motion--that the Sbor Ceskeho Narodniho Hrbitova be asked to help our schools in this financial crisis--was carried, and the secretary was instructed to send a letter to that association. Another motion suggested that the Dorostovy Klub (Juniors Club), which is arranging a theatrical performance, be asked to donate part of the proceeds of the performance to the Svaz Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol. The Vcelky (Ladies' Auxiliary of the Czechoslovak National Alliance of America) donated one hundred and ninety dollars for the benefit of the Svobodna Skola, for which they deserve thanks.</p>
   <p>For the coming anniversary celebration of our first creator of institutional education, Jan Amos Komensky (Johannes Amos Comenius), it was resolved that <pb facs="5418478_7_0922.jpg" n="7"/>the teachers of our Bohemian Free Thought schools prepare some lectures about Jan Amos Komensky to celebrate the occasion and thus acquaint the student body with the importance of his educational work. After a report on receipts and expenditures, the meeting adjourned.</p>
   <p>Joseph Tichava, chairman,</p>
   <p>Karel Soukup, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
