<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-30">May 30, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Preparations for John Huss Anniversary Celebrations</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Fr. Strunc</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0366</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0366.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-30">May 30, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">PREPARATIONS FOR JOHN HUSS ANNIVERSARY CELEBRATIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Fr. Strunc</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The significance of the year 1915 as the five hundredth anniversary of the martyr death of John Huss was to have found its expression all over the world. It was to furnish a new impulse for efforts toward liberty, equality, humaneness. It was to mark a new era in the twentieth century. All this, and more, should have happened in the year of 1915. Instead, however, there is heard throughout Europe the thunder of cannon, the beating of war drums, the rattle of guns, the swishing of shrapnel, the trembling of the ground--all these terrible things that go to make up a war, a war which has hit the center from which the humanizing influences were to emanate, a war which is doing such a great deal of evil just now in the Bohemian lands.</p>
   <p>This war has succeeded in putting down and stifling all this, but it has not succeeded in doing so everywhere. If Bohemia is checked now, she is thus being given time and opportunity to gather new inner strength for more valiant efforts in the future, but there is every indication that the Bohemians in <pb facs="5418478_7_0367.jpg" n="2"/>America are far from being stifled. What is being done now in Bohemian America, and, more specifically, in Chicago?</p>
   <p>Ever since February 12, 1914, the representatives of the Grand Lodge of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies), the Grand Lodge of the Cesko-Slovanska Jednota (Bohemian-Slavonic Union), the Grand Court of the Cesko-Americti Lesnici a Lesnice (Bohemian American [men and women] Foresters) the Grand Lodge of the Cesko-Americka Jednota (Bohemian-American Union), the Grand Lodge of the Taborites, of the Cesko-Slovanska Braterska Podporujici Jednota (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Brother-hood), the Svaz Podpurnych Jednot (Federation of Benevolent Associations), the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery), the Narodni Jednota Sokolska (National Sokol Union) with all its component bodies, the Sokolska Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs (Sokol Unit called Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs), the Straz Osvojenych (Guard of the Liberated), the Svobodna OBec (Congregation of [Bohemian] Freethinkers), and the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol (Association of Bohemian Free Thought Schools) have been holding meetings and have deliberated <pb facs="5418478_7_0368.jpg" n="3"/>as to how best to observe the five hundredth anniversary of the burning at the stake of John Huss. The work they have done so far proves definitely that they are fully appreciative of the purpose of John Huss celebrations. There is but one regrettable circumstance to be recorded. All efforts to secure the co-operation of women's organizations have been in vain. It is not my purpose to analyse the causes of that failure, and I shall limit myself to the statement that it was a duty of our women's organizations to give a helping hand to the men. Thus they would have given proof that they know the meaning of the words, "Free Thought, Liberality, Independence of Thinking". It is my belief, however, that our women's organizations may still do what they have so far neglected to do: They should do all they can to give the widest distribution to the pamphlet published by the Sdruzeni Pro Oslavy Husovy (Association for John Huss Anniversary Celebrations), and to participate in large numbers in the parade and in the celebration in Pilsen Park, especially, however, in the festivities on the day of the anniversary itself, which will be held in the Auditorium downtown.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0369.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>One important thing the Sdruzeni has not neglected. It has not forgotten our Youth.</p>
   <p>The children's day is set for the afternoon of July 5, and the affair proper will be preceded by a children's parade which will start, at the Vojta Naprstek School. The program of the celebration is being worked out by the teachers of the Sdruzeni Svobodnych Skol (Free-Thought Schools Association), and the Sdruzeni, in order to help in making a success of the celebration, has prolonged the school year to the festive days. The participating children will receive a copy each of the pamphlet "Hus, Kacir" (John Huss, the Heretic) by the teacher, Vojta Benes, published by the Socialist-Democratic Party in Bohemia. The perusal of this pamphlet will show the children the difference between truth as taught and lived by the priests, and the genuine truth of John Huss. To bring about the recognition of that difference is the best tribute to his memory.</p>
   <p>The Sdruzeni has done other work also. It has published beautiful picture <pb facs="5418478_7_0370.jpg" n="5"/>post cards, twenty thousand of them, which will be sold at five cents apiece. An enlargement of the picture on the cards is being sold for framing. This will be a decoration which should be in the home of every freethinking men. The price is fifteen cents. In addition to the cards and the large-sized pictures, the Sdruzeni has had a pamphlet printed, the Bohemian edition of which is ready for distribution, and the English edition is on the presses.</p>
   <p>The pamphlets, both the English and the Bohemian editions are by Professor Josef Jiri Kral, of Washington, D. C. His name guarantees that the pamphlets will be a wonderful asset in the Huss celebrations. They are sure to find a place, and to be read, in every liberal-minded, progressive household. Wherever Huss celebrations are to be held this year, the committee on arrangements should order the necessary quantity of these pamphlets for the participants. The principal celebration will be here in Chicago July 5 and 6, in addition to the youth's celebration in the afternoon and a popular celebration in the evening of July 5, which will have a particularly rich program. There will be four tableaux by the Sokolska Zupa Fuegner-Tyrs: (1) The Period of <pb facs="5418478_7_0371.jpg" n="6"/>Bohemian Power and Glory; (2) The Collapse of the Nation; (3) The Exile; (4) The Nation's Awakening. The tableaux will be accompanied by singing in Bohemian by the Ceska Pevecka Jednot (Federation of Bohemian Singing Societies). The tableaux will be followed by a Bohemian speech and music. The program will be preceded by a parade contemplated as a public manifestation against darkness and superstition.</p>
   <p>On the day of the anniversary, July 6, an evening celebration commemorating John Huss will be held downtown, in the Auditorium, the largest and most suitable place in Chicago. This will be the culmination of the festivities. The speakers will be Professor J. J. Kral, who will give a talk in English, and Dr. Frantisek Iska, who will speak in Bohemian. The Pevecky Spolek Bedrich Smetana (Bedrich Smetana Singing Society) will present the Oratorio "John Huss". A fifty-man orchestra under the leadership of Mr. J. Capek will play the Overture to Smetana's "Libuse," and a tableau will be arranged depicting the burning at the stake of John Huss.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0372.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>It is up to our public to give wide distribution to the pamphlets published by the Sdruzeni, and to participate in really large numbers in the parade and in both celebrations, thus demonstrating that there is a great, strong freethinking movement for the abandonment of superstitution and the dissipation of darkness amongst us that no one can stop.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
