<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-08">July 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Cesky Narodni Hrbitov</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1104</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1104.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-07-08">July 8, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE CESKY NARODNI HRBITOV</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A regular meeting of the Board of Representatives of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) was held yesterday at the usual place under the chairmanship of Mr. J. Hladovec.....</p>
   <p>The pay roll for the last month, which included seventy-five workingmen, amounted to $5,017.31.....</p>
   <p>Among the letters that were read was one from the Patronat of the Cesko-Anglicka Svobodomyslna Skola (Bohemian-English Freethinking School), in forming the Board of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov of their intention to build a new Bohemian school for the Bohemian Polsen District, for which the site had already been bought. The Patronat asked the Board whether it would be willing to purchase ten thousand dollars' worth of three-and-a-half per cent bonds to be issued by the Patronat. Naturally, this very interesting proposal caused a most lively debate....resulting in the <pb facs="5418478_7_1105.jpg" n="2"/>adoption of a motion to pass the request back to the executive committee for an investigation, on which they are to make a report to the Board at its next meeting. The request of the Board of the Ceska Utulna a Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage) for a loan of between twenty and twenty-five thousand dollars needed for the erection of the new building was disposed of in a similar manner.</p>
   <p>Mr. Dobias reported for the building committee, his report dealing mostly with bids submitted for the installation of containers for ashes, socalled columbaria. The committee has bids from four firms, to wit: Strnad &amp; Son for 260 containers, or urns, for $4,292; the Polsen Foundry Company, one for 236 urns for $3,350, and another for 290 urns for $4,200 with an additional $300 for special urns lined with white enamel. The Garden City Iron Works submitted a bid for 280 urns for $3,898, and the firm of Cerny &amp; Pikas, one for 290 urns for $4,225.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1106.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The committee recommended the bid of the Pilsen Foundry Company as the one most suitable for the crematorium, and the Board instructed the executive and the legal committees to accept that bid and to see to it that the work on the containers is started and completed as soon as possible.</p>
   <p>The treasurer reported the income of $10,214.54 and expenses of $6,921.47. Balance from last month was $24,598.84. Thus there was on hand $27,891.93.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
