<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Czechoslovak Review</title>, Vol. III, No. 12, pp. 395-396,
<date when="1919-12">Dec., 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Conference of National Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0432</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0432.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Czechoslovak Review</title>, Vol. III, No. 12, pp. 395-396,
<date when="1919-12">Dec., 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CONFERENCE OF NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian National Alliance of America held a conference in Chicago, Nov. 15th and 16th, at which the main problem was changing the activities of the organization from a war to a peace basis. There were fifty-five delegates present representing all the district branches of the Alliance from New York to Oklahoma and Winnipeg, as well as delegates representing the important local branches, and delegates from fraternal and gymnastic societies affiliated with the Bohemian National Alliance.</p>
   <p>The committee on reorganization recast the constitution completely. The Alliance was established in 1914 for the purpose of supporting the movement for Czechoslovak independence and the original Constitution was framed accordingly. For four years all activity was centered on collecting money to finance the campaign of Prof. Masaryk. Later, emphasis was placed on recruiting members, who were not naturalized in the United States, for service with the Czechoslovak army in France. During the last year the Alliance was engaged in relief work for the needy of the Czechoslovak Republic.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0433.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The new Constitution, adopted unanimously by the Chicago Conference, omits all reference to the country from which the members of the Alliance came, except for one paragraph which provides that one of the aims of the organization will be acquainting America with the life of the Czechoslovak people and the development of the free Czechoslovak Republic. The main object of the Alliance has now become the good of its own members and of Americans of Czechoslovak descent in general, and special emphasis is laid on educational and cultural work in the interest of sound Americanism. New arrivals from Bohemia will be looked after and introduced to the sprit of American institutions. As reconstructed, the organization will be the representative body of American citizens, including Canadians of Czechoslovak blood and will take the lead in all matters affecting them.</p>
   <p>The name of the organization was changed from Bohemian to Czechoslovak National Alliance. In 1914, the people from which the members sprang, were known as Bohemians. Today they are known as Czechoslovaks - hence the change.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0434.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>From the first days of the Alliance the central committee was located in Chicago. The Chicago workers asked that it be transferred to Cleveland or New York, but the conference insisted on maintaining headquarters in Chicago as the logical center.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
