<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-13">Sept. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Narodni Dan Svobodomyslnych Is Utmost Necessity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0976</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0976.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-13">Sept. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE NARODNI DAN SVOBODOMYSLNYCH IS UTMOST NECESSITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If the present tireless efforts of the Svaz Svobodomyslnych (Federation of Bohemian Freethinkers) leading to the invigoration of the Free Thought movement in Bohemian-America is to be successful, the Narodni Dan Svobodomyslnych (National Tax of Freethinkers), the collection of which will begin October 28, must give the movement a financial foundation which will put an end to its present state of stagnation. To keep on under the present circumstances is simply impossible. Just today, when, with the death of Mr. Vaclav Snajdr,the epoch of pioneers of the Bohemian-American Free Thought movement has closed completely, the Svaz Svobodomyslnych calls to all the Bohemian Freethinkers:</p>
   <p>Shall we be tortured by the thought that those forty years which Vaclav Snajdr dedicated to the Free Thought movement were wasted, that he worked in vain? At Vaclav Snajdr's bier, the Bohemian-American Freethinkers should make a <pb facs="5418478_7_0977.jpg" n="2"/>pledge that his legacy will be brought to new life again. Will it happen? The Chicago Archbishop, George Mundelein, in his special communication, proclaimed the Svatovaclavska Dan (St. Wenceslaus Tax) of Bohemian Catholics as most desirable and approved the campaign for it in churches, organizations, and newspapers. His action befitted a church leader, and we give him full credit for it. We, the Bohemian Freethinkers, have no such dignitaries among us. But we have our ladies' and men's benevolent organizations. It is expected that their grand committees, national lodges, central and executive committees, will act just as Archbishop Mundelein did, that they will recommend the tax to all lodges and units as most necessary and thus help toward its success.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the Svaz Svobodomyslnych calls upon these representative bodies of our Bohemian Free Thought organizations and asks them to demonstrate their sympathy and support for this tax. If we do not succeed in creating enthusiasm <pb facs="5418478_7_0978.jpg" n="3"/>for our cause and in making the national tax a great success, then it will be better to stop all the work for the Free Thought Movement and leave it to some other, better generations. But we firmly hope that we will not live to see such a sad end, that our Freethinkers will awaken and bestir themselves into action!</p>
   <p>For further information concerning the Nardoni Dan Svobodomyslnych, kindly communicate with the secretary of the executive committee of the Svaz Svobodomyslnych, V. K. Soukup,2000 South Ashland Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
