<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-12">Feb. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Conference of the Czech National Alliance--Third Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0490</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0490.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-12">Feb. 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CONFERENCE OF THE CZECH NATIONAL ALLIANCE--THIRD DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The third session of the conference of the Czech National Alliance, which is being held in the auditorium of the Sokol Chicago, was opened yesterday morning. The National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America and the Slovak League of America were also represented. From morning until night the conference presented the picture of a veritable beehive. Besides delegates of the district branches, representing almost every state of the Union, there were numerous visitors, many prominent in public life, and all of whom were evidently absorbed in what was being said and done.....Many questions of current public interest were dealt with, the problem of the Czechoslovak Army taking first place.</p>
   <p>The question of a merger of the Czech National Alliance, the National <pb facs="5418478_7_0491.jpg" n="2"/>Alliance of Czech Catholics, and the Slovak League was discussed. They are to be combined into the Ceskoslovenska Jednota (Czechoslovak Union). This plan is meeting with general and enthusiastic approval.</p>
   <p>Since the scheduled program had not been exhausted, Professor Pisecky moved that the meeting continue its regular work while a committee, representing the three bodies, works out plans for the merger. This committee's proposals were to be brought before the plenary meeting. It was decided, after some discussion, to give the Czechs and Slovaks eight votes each on this committee. The following were elected to the committee: For the Czechs: Professor [Bohumil] Simek, E. V. Voska, and F. J. Kubec, representing the Czech National Alliance; Hynek Dostal, Reverend Zlamal, and Reverend Kestl, representing the National Alliance of Czech Catholics. The president of the Czech National Alliance, Dr. Ludwig J. Fisher and its organizer, Vojta Benes, will sit ex-officio. Our brothers, the Slovaks, will appoint their men in the course of the day. This committee of <pb facs="5418478_7_0492.jpg" n="3"/>sixteen is expected to submit proposals this evening.</p>
   <p>Mr. Rada, representing the Cesko-Slovanska Podporujici Spolecnost (Czecho-Slav Benevolent Association), was granted the privilege of attending the conference so as to be able to report on the proceedings to the various brotherhoods which are composed of members or friends of the Czech National Alliance.</p>
   <p>Mesdames Anna Novak, and Milada Tetrev appeared, representing the Vcelky (Little Bees). They reported that this women's organization has produced 1,700 various articles, gifts for our boys, volunteers in the Czechoslovak Army. From October 24, 1917 to February 11, 1918, they collected $3,784.53 from various sources, and expended $3,709.53, leaving a balance of $75 in the treasury. They pleaded for support for the founding of new branches of their organization, particularly in rural districts. In their department, however, some centralization will be needed, and so it was decided <pb facs="5418478_7_0493.jpg" n="4"/>to let the committee on organization take care of their problems. They belong to the auxiliary, organizations whose activities will have to be systematically conducted by a central office. The ladies were congratulated for their efforts, Mr. Voska remembering the excellent work done by the New York branch of the Little Bees.</p>
   <p>Sundry motions were made, Mr. Voska being the first to take the floor. He pointed out the meritorious work performed by the New York Artists' Club in behalf of the movement for the liberation of Czechoslovakia.....He proposed that this Club be granted $1,000, and the Czech Chicago Artists' Club $500 for the further pursuit of their patriotic aims. The money should be paid in installments as a subvention. The speaker emphasized the value of the artists' co-operation in the movement. This motion brought on vigorous debate in the course of which the Chicago Artists' Club was reproached for not giving the movement of liberation due attention, so that it appears that the Club does not care very much <pb facs="5418478_7_0494.jpg" n="5"/>about the Czech National Alliance. Mr. Vojta Benes rose in defense of the Chicago artists, reminding the meeting of the splendid exhibition they had arranged on the occasion of Czech Day at the University of Chicago, and of their contribution to the booklet, Bohemia. Mrs. Ludvik suggested that the New York artists be sent merely an address expressing recognition of their aid. Finally, however, Mr. Voska's motion carried, and the respective appropriations were voted for the artists' clubs as a means of encouragement.</p>
   <p>The publishing of a book, Bohemia Under Habsburg Misrule, by Thomas Capek, of New York, was brought up. The Alliance was asked to take care of the printing of the first 1,500 copies at an expenditure of $1,060. This request came from the New York branch of the Alliance which had charged itself with the publication of the book without consulting the Chicago central offices. After a somewhat heated debate, it was decided to admonish the New York branch to always consult the Chicago central office before acting. On second thought, however, it was admitted that the time <pb facs="5418478_7_0495.jpg" n="6"/>was pressing, and that a book of real merit as that by Mr. Capek would enhance our cause very much and should be published as soon as possible instead of waiting until the war is over. Mr. Pergler declared that he had found the book to be of biographical and historical value which would give strong impetus to the Czechoslovak movement for independence.....</p>
   <p>The afternoon session was surprised by the unexpected appearance of Mr. Martinek, of Cleveland, Ohio, who had returned from Russia where he had traveled as a member of a delegation which included Messrs. E. V. Voska, Koukol, and Svarc. He gave a description of conditions there as no one has done before...."No matter how sad the plight of that country is, we have to keep good friendship with the Russians," he said....The speaker's narration made a deep impression, and he was urged to deliver another lecture as soon as possible, preferably about the Czechoslovak Army in Russia.....</p>
   <p>Routine business was then taken up. Mr. Adolph Lonka gave a report of <pb facs="5418478_7_0496.jpg" n="7"/>receipts and expenditures which we cannot publish because a publication of figures was found in the last session to be not only impractical, but, for diplomatic reasons, downright dangerous; it meant giving information to our enemies.....The figures had been checked by trustworthy men and found to be based on perfectly honest management. This conclusively refutes the contentions of certain elements who accuse the leaders of the Alliance of indulging in secrecy.</p>
   <p>Mr. Svoboda read the following report on the business of the Alliance:</p>
   <p>"Report of the finance committee of the Czech National Alliance in Chicago, February 11, 1918: The finance committee elected by your conference, well aware of the responsibility involved in the audit of the books of the central office of the Czech National Alliance which has been so often attacked recently, approached its business with the utmost conscientiousness and without the slightest bias.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0497.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>"This committee began by comparing the items of expense with the original checks and vouchers, and found them to tally perfectly. The vouchers were, as a rule, issued by three officers--president, bookkeeper, and treasurer. From this, and from the records, it is evident that they were authorized for payment.....The money sent to banks in Europe is duly receipted by them and also by letters in Professor Masaryk's own handwriting. Our district executive committees have recorded all amounts received by the central offices. These amounts appear also in the journals, the books in which current transactions are recorded.</p>
   <p>"The books are kept by Mr. Adolph Lonek. We are obliged to him for his accurate, painstaking work, and also for the explanations which he was always ready to give to our committee. The minutes and the journal give ample evidence of the constant supervision by the chairman of the central committee. Besides this, the books were audited by an accounting committee <pb facs="5418478_7_0498.jpg" n="9"/>three times each year. This committee was appointed according to directions given by the Cleveland, Ohio, conference. The books were found to be in perfect order, and the respective information was submitted to us. The first two audits were performed by Messrs. John Cervenka, Vaclav (Venceslas) Vanek, and Joseph Klicka; the third by Mr. Stana (Stanislas) Simecek and Dr. Pecival. All considered, we can testify with full satisfaction that the finance accounting was carried out with scrupulous accuracy, conscientiousness, and sterling honesty.</p>
   <p>"Of the total outlay, .28% went for the office, 1.23% for wages, 1.47% for printing, and 1.07% for traveling expenses. This ratio demonstrates best that no money was wasted, and that charges against the central committee are unjust. Conforming with the decision of this conference, monthly financial reports are to be sent to the district committees. We recommend that they be in such form that one glance will show whether the expenses refer to the office, organization, propaganda, the military committee, the <pb facs="5418478_7_0499.jpg" n="10"/>Vcelky (Little Bees), the Czechoslav Press Bureau, or action taken in Europe for the movement of liberation. A journal for daily, current transactions and a main ledger will have to be used. The latter will serve for accounts between the central committee and the various district committees. To this end it will be absolutely necessary to pass all receipts and expenditures through the hands of the bookkeeper before they are given over to the treasurer who is responsible for proper disbursement. The central committee has often asked the district committees, the branches, and the Czech public to send all money to the Bohemian National Alliance of America, and not to individual officers. We lay emphasis on this point. The committee on finance is willing to make suggestions on the kind of books to be used.</p>
   <p>"To enable the central office to cope with the ever-growing demands on the organization, we recommend that all help be hired, and that places be rented, which are not primarily necessary for an efficient conduct of business, but for a dignified, representative appearance of the entire <pb facs="5418478_7_0500.jpg" n="11"/>organization. We consider skimping in this respect not only out of place, but even detrimental to the development and general standing of the organization.</p>
   <p>"J. J. Franka, New Ulm, Texas,</p>
   <p>"C. B. Svoboda, Cedar Rapids, Iowa."</p>
   <p>The report was accepted with general satisfaction. Each delegate was able to see that the charges of lack of economy in management raised against the central committee of the Czech National Alliance were based either on ignorance of conditions, or sheer maliciousness. Whatever the cause, it surely tends to damage a purpose which merits the enthusiastic support of every one of us Czechs.</p>
   <p>Professor Simek, chairman of the committee on resolutions, took the floor enumerating the propositions now before his committee. Proposals concerning organization are:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0501.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>1. The abolition of district branches, and substitution of bodies composed of members of a whole state.</p>
   <p>2. Combination of the various branches with the central organization. </p>
   <p>3. The creation of a Czechoslovak executive body of fifteen members from six branches.</p>
   <p>4. The organization of a Czechoslovak, Polish, and Jugoslav political block.</p>
   <p>5. Complete union of all organizations now existing.</p>
   <p>6. The appointment of a committee of six members representing the Czechoslovak National Council in America, with its seat in Washington, D. C.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0502.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>7. The creation of a body of nine members, each from the Czech National Alliance, the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America, and the Slovak League. The members will be "trustees" and will represent the state.</p>
   <p>Proposals regarding names and purposes demand an American League for Czechoslovak Independence, and The Friends of Bohemian Independence. The latter shall also accept native Americans.</p>
   <p>Proposals on internal agenda are:</p>
   <p>1. To establish a commercial staff with regular pay in the central and other offices.</p>
   <p>2. To impose a "national head tax".</p>
   <p>3. A conciliatory attempt to attract circles that are now remote to our <pb facs="5418478_7_0503.jpg" n="14"/>cause.</p>
   <p>4. To reduce administrative and representative expenses.</p>
   <p>5. An annual general collection to last a full week along the lines of the Red Cross campaigns.</p>
   <p>6. To pay our representatives $5 per day plus transportation.</p>
   <p>7. To take a census of the Czechs in America.</p>
   <p>8. To invite prominent Czechs not only from outlying districts, but also from the central offices.</p>
   <p>Proposals regarding activities of the Czech and the Slav Bureau, with headquarters at the offices of the Czechoslovak branch for political action are:</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0504.jpg" n="15"/>
   <p>1. To establish a press bureau in every state with men and women who have a command of the English language.</p>
   <p>2. To mail our organ, The Message, to all members so as to make it the organ of the Slovaks also.</p>
   <p>Proposals on military action are:</p>
   <p>1. To recruit men after the pattern of United States compulsory methods.</p>
   <p>2. To single out from leading circles men able to do military service.</p>
   <p>3. To generously support our volunteers and their families.</p>
   <p>4. To gain permission from the United States Government for the unhampered return of disabled soldiers from the Czechoslovak Army.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0505.jpg" n="16"/>
   <p>5. To transport that part of the Czechoslovak Army which is now in Russia either to France or the United States.</p>
   <p>A proposal was offered to transfer the management of the work done for our soldiers by the Vcelky (Little Bees) to the Union of Czech Ladies, a ladies auxiliary, and to place it under the supervision of our central office and our committee on military affairs.</p>
   <p>Proposals on diplomatic action are:</p>
   <p>1. To secure recognition of our representatives as political consuls at Allied headquarters.</p>
   <p>2. To change our attitude, for political and diplomatic reasons, toward President Wilson's proclamation in regard to the preservation of Austria-Hungary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0506.jpg" n="17"/>
   <p>There is proposed an All-Slav rally in Washington, D. C.--a rally and manifestation to be held on July 4, 1918, in which all Slavs in the United States will participate. The present conference shall be a preparation for the rally of Czechs and Poles only.</p>
   <p>Proposals to exert influence upon America are:</p>
   <p>1. To desist from exacting any influence upon the President.</p>
   <p>2. To protect our movement from American party influence.</p>
   <p>3. To protest against irresponsible and unauthorized representation of Czech-Americans before the American public.</p>
   <p>4. To extend an invitation to Professor Masaryk to submit the question of Czechoslovak independence to authorized circles in Washington.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0507.jpg" n="18"/>
   <p>5. To win the support of influential Americans by contact with professors and students from the schools of higher learning, priests, and others of Czechoslovak descent.</p>
   <p>6. To present a memorandum to the American Government and to the American people, the Czechoslovak National Council acting for us.</p>
   <p>7. To create a Czechoslovak department for political action with its seat in Washington.</p>
   <p>8. To establish a bureau of statistics.</p>
   <p>9. To create Czech branches of the American Red Cross to avoid the appearance of our being neglectful in our duties toward America.</p>
   <p>10. To let Americans become members of the Czechoslovak organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0508.jpg" n="19"/>
   <p>It is evident that the conference has taken on an immense task, and also that the majority of the propositions are good and practical. It is to be hoped that their realization will place the action for independence on a still sounder and firmer basis. The discussion of these propositions had to be postponed because there was before the conference the report of the committee on military affairs. The military committee consists of Captain Z. Firlinger and Mr. E. Kopecky, both of whom were to hurriedly depart from Chicago, wherefore their report was given preference before other questions. Mr. Kopecky declared the Czechoslovak Army as the medium which will make it possible for the Czechoslovaks to sit at the peace conference. This army is attracting wide attention in the Allied press.....He appealed to the Czechoslovak brotherhoods, entreating them to allow their enlisted members to remain in the organizations even if they be unable to pay the dues.....Mr. Kopecky's report sounded enthusiastic, true enough, but it brought disappointment, nevertheless. It was superficial, and suffered from too many gaps; it could not have been accepted as a finished <pb facs="5418478_7_0509.jpg" n="20"/>product.</p>
   <p>Delegate Mr. Cimler scrutinized its weak points and stated that much more detailed information should have been given on our military affairs which rank as the most important before all others. On what foundation has our Czechoslovak Army been really placed? Our boys in that army are not satisfied to the degree we think they are. One of our volunteers was, indeed, so embittered that he wrote that he would instantly desert were it not for the shame of such a step.</p>
   <p>"Much is yet to be explained," the speaker declared. "Are our boys insured against all eventualities as are the soldiers in the American Army? Will they be permitted to return to the United States in case they become disabled or crippled? These questions will have to be answered without high-sounding phrases. Many of our volunteers left wives and children. They did their duty. It is we who should bear the responsibility.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0510.jpg" n="21"/>
   <p>These facts remained untouched in Mr. Kopecky's report....."</p>
   <p>A debate on these points ended after Captain Firlinger had offered some enlightening remarks and finally read a manifesto addressed to the Czechoslovak people in America, which he solemnly admonished to do its duty.....</p>
   <p>Letters from our boys showed that tobacco is one of the most appreciated articles at the front. A collection will be started to send ample supplies to the soldiers. Mr. John A. Cervenka, clerk of the Probate Court, was one of the first to contribute by donating $50.</p>
   <p>A discussion of the many propositions enumerated above followed. Among the latter it was Mr. Voska's motion to pay $5 per day and travel expenses to delegates that evoked much controversy. Those seconding the motion declared that efficient workers who happen to be poor should not be made to shoulder the burden of expenses, but should be reimbursed. Those against it said <pb facs="5418478_7_0511.jpg" n="22"/>that there are prosperous men who would represent us without pay. This was opposed by delegates who sneered at rich men "who come to the rallies only to exhibit their dear women folk shining with adornment". It was finally left to the district branches to finance their delegates according to their own judgment.</p>
   <p>Another interesting issue came up when Mr. Serpan moved that prominent men from our communities, who have, up to the present, not appeared in the service of the Czech National Alliance, be invited to place their efforts at the disposal of our cause. He volunteered some names. This threw the meeting into a chaos. Delegates vehemently protested against begging "some big-whigs" who but a short time ago had only sneers and even disgust for the movement. When a specific name was mentioned, Dr. Fisher, president of the Alliance, declared downright that he would decline to sit in the same office with that person. He had invited the man several times to give support to the Alliance by his influence, but was brushed aside, the <pb facs="5418478_7_0512.jpg" n="23"/>man declaring that he did not believe in Czechoslovak independence. Reverend Vanek sided with Dr. Fisher, saying that he could not comprehend how the name of such a "would-be patriot" was mentioned, "a man who has not come near the movement for Czechoslovak liberation". Mr. Serpan's motion met with such an exhibition of general displeasure that he withdrew it. The persons mentioned and rejected in this discussion are well known in the community. In order to avoid further dissention and possible complications, these names were kept from the general reading public in this report.</p>
   <p>During the afternoon session a number of congratulatory telegrams sent to the conference from various parts of the United States were read.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
