<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-30">Mar. 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Lecture by the Reverend Krenek</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1070</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1070.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-30">Mar. 30, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">LECTURE BY THE REVEREND KRENEK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hubbard Memorial Church on Lawndale Street was the scene of the ceremonies held by the Czech Presbyterian community of Chicago to commemorate the 325th birthday of Jan Amos Komensky on March 29. The Rev. Joseph Krenek, of Silver Lake, Minn., delivered the oration in the Czech language.</p>
   <p>"We celebrate the three hundred and twenty-fifth birthday of Komensky in an ominous moment. The existence of the Czech nation is at stake. This condition calls on us, the Protestants especially, to come to the rescue. It is imperative to act before 'the last avalanche sweeps our hope away.'"</p>
   <p>After these introductory words, the speaker, in striving to inspire enthusiasm for work in behalf of the nation, pointed to and enumerated the treasures of Czech aspirations, and held forth our just demands in the <pb facs="5418478_7_1071.jpg" n="2"/>light of humanity.</p>
   <p>Reverend Krenek began by defining the essence of our demands and expounding the spiritual basis upon which all exertions of the Czech nation are founded. But he declined to lift the nation upon the pedestal of an idol by concealing its faults and exaggerating its virtues. He endeavored, as Neruda once sang, to "Look the nation into its eyes." The orator led on his audience, indeed, to look into the eyes of the nation, to sound its soul that speaks from it. The Czech soul, it is said, speaks with its gaze when viewing the soil upon which its people live. The Reverend Mr. Krenek related a precious incident in quoting an Englishman, a friend of the Czech nation, who stood with him on the crest of the Mount Rip, which dominates the heart of the Czech lands,: "Here one can fathom the soul of the Czech nation."</p>
   <p>A second gaze into the Czech eye reveals the Hussite times, and shows that <pb facs="5418478_7_1072.jpg" n="3"/>the longing for genuine humanity moved the nation, but that no craving for material goods and worldly power ever motivated its actions. While knightly contests and pomp ruled Europe, plain Czech citizenry turned to spheres purely humane and spiritual. "Let us preserve a good heart!," that is the call of Stitny to his nation.</p>
   <p>And Zizka? He is no incendiary bent on destruction. If he is driven into battle, he fights to defend the purest inheritance of mankind, humanity. The Husitic tenets represented the Magna Carta of spiritual rights, they showed that the ideal of the Czechs meant fraternity and equality for all. The Czechs hankered for a kingdom of God right here on earth.</p>
   <p>The speaker held up as great leaders, Chelcicky, and particularly, Komensky. In the former, the Czechs see the repentant spirit that atones for whatever imperfections found their way into Husitism. Atonement and auto-criticism are the elements of humanity. And Komensky? Who can penetrate the depths <pb facs="5418478_7_1073.jpg" n="4"/>of his soul? There dwells something eternal in his ponderings. The elixir of his creed lies in his words: "I say unto you that to right all ills there is no way but by good conduct of youth." Komensky himself, deprived of the most primitive rights due to mankind, thus becomes one of the outstanding servants of the nations. His religion meant to serve the Lord for the good of his nation and mankind.</p>
   <p>The oration finally leads us into the history of the Czech people from the time of its national awakening with its leaders, Kolar, Dobrovsky, and especially Havlicek and Palacky, up to the present time. The Czech soul is reflected in the undaunted spirit with which these men resisted oppression. </p>
   <p>The second part of the oration dealt with the relation of the Czech aspirations to the present mode of life of the nation. If the Czech people want to exist today, it is because of historical rights to do so, and not because of some insane daylight dreaming of a dying people. In spite of oppression, <pb facs="5418478_7_1074.jpg" n="5"/>the people are standing up with marvelous determination.</p>
   <p>The last part of the oration treats with the relation of the endeavor of the Czech nation to the aims of humanity, which adorned the entire civilized world, though outraged now, yet more powerful than ever, steps forth as the aim of human life. This present time teaches that if culture is to survive, the nations must live according to principles taught by culture. The Czech Protestant cannot better follow the teachings of Komensky than by working wholeheartedly for the liberation of the Czech people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
