<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-24">Dec. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Amateurs' Cabaret</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1401</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1401.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-24">Dec. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AMATEURS' CABARET</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night members of the theatrical section of Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs changed their usual performance. Instead of drama they gave a cabaret. It was intended to be a welcome to soldiers on furlough from Camp Grant. It was sponsored by the Czech members of the commission of the 83rd Recruiting Division. About fifty soldiers attended and the audience was fairly large.</p>
   <p>Mr. Adolph Mach, chairman of the auxiliary committee, opened the evening. He explained why the soldiers who are enjoying their first longer furlough should be treated in the most friendly manner. He said they are about to risk their lives in the struggle against the enemy of democracy and liberty. Therefore, to us who are disqualified from the army falls the duty of encouraging our soldiers in every possible way. The short address was received with wholehearted applause.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1402.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The performance began with a recitation by Mrs. Cervenka. Mr. Krejci sang light songs, and Mrs. Krejci assisted by four other ladies, danced a veil dance. Mr. Zima also gave an act.</p>
   <p>Mr. William K. Pflaum, who is secretary of the auxiliary committee, regretted that the program was not so large as the committee would have liked it to be. The question of a furlough for the soldiers was in abeyance. Therefore, more elaborate preparations could not be made for this event. The "Causes and Significance of the War" was the main subject of his address. After his address he distributed among the soldiers presents from the auxiliary committee. These gifts were not luxuries. They were useful articles.</p>
   <p>Little Miss Janacek in a charming way and with the voice and manner of a child surpised the audience by telling the soldiers "how to lick the Kaiser". The effect of this little scene was evident from the stormy applause it drew.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1403.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This reporter regrets only that he could not tell whether the acclaim was due to the prospective "licking the Kaiser" or to the histrionic manner of the little girl.</p>
   <p>Miss [or Mrs.] Stoces gave an exhibition that was unexcelled........</p>
   <p>To prove that the soldiers also can boast of talent, Sergeant Putta appeared and danced a genuine jig. The remainder of the program was taken care of by the amateurs, and directed by Mr. Krejci.</p>
   <p>Mr. Anton J. Cermak, John Toman, Dr. Zabokrtsky, Bolek and other members of the auxiliary committee were present. Ladies from the Thirty-fourth Ward brought knitted articles, such as sweaters and gloves, to some of the soldiers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
