<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-10">Dec. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Charles J. Vopicka Resigns</title><title level="a" type="sub">The American Ambassador to the Balkan States Sent His Resignation to President Woodrow Wilson Yesterday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1348</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1348.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-10">Dec. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">CHARLES J. VOPICKA RESIGNS</title><title level="a" type="sub">The American Ambassador to the Balkan States Sent His Resignation to President Woodrow Wilson Yesterday</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our Chicago countryman, Mr. Charles J. Vopicka, who so successfully filled the post of Ambassador to the Balkan States for a long number of years, to the honor not only of the United States but especially of us Czechoslovaks, sent a message to President Woodrow Wilson yesterday, asking that he be relieved of his duties as Ambassador. In other words, he resigned. There is not the least doubt that Ambassador Vopicka acted according to his convictions and sentiments in regard to the prevailing circumstances, and in regard to the approaching change in the government administration. We do not doubt a bit that President Wilson, who admired Mr. Vopicka so much for his achievements, accomplished in such a difficult situation, will accept his resignation and will be thankful to Mr. Vopicka for his tactful manifestation of loyalty.</p>
   <p>Not only once but on various occasions have we reported on the work <pb facs="5418478_7_1349.jpg" n="2"/>accomplished by Mr. Vopicka in his responsible position as the United States Ambassador to the Balkan States, and especially Rumania. It is not necessary, therefore, to report on it again today. Many episodes of interest will be written by Mr. Vopicka himself who, as we are told, is working on a book in which he will give a detailed account of all his experiences. Although he is resigning from a government position he wishes to be active. He will be active not only here in Chicago, where he occupies a prominent place in our business and industrial life, but on a much larger scale. He has already become a member of a great importing and exporting company; but his greatest desire is to devote most of his time to his family which, during recent years, because of his duties in connection with the office, he somehow neglected.</p>
   <p>Now with his family at his home, 3251 West Washington Boulevard, he can peacefully recollect all the successful accomplishments achieved in a position which redounds not only to his honor but to the honor of all Czechoslovaks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
