<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-01-04">Jan. 4, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the Bohemian National Cemetery Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1232</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1232.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-01-04">Jan. 4, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting was held yesterday of the Bohemian National Cemetery Association under the chairmanship of Mr. [Eugene] Frydl. The minutes of the previous meeting were accepted as read. The payroll for the month of December was $2,075.23. [Translator's note: List of delegates follows.]</p>
   <p>Fifty dollars was appropriated for a donation to the Cesko-Americky Tiskovy Kancelar (Bohemian-American Press Bureau), and Mr. R. Kapsa was elected as the Association's representative to that body. Twenty-five dollars was appropriated for a donation to the Cesky Delnicky Pevecky Sbor (Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society).</p>
   <p>Indiana bonds held by the Association rose fifteen per cent because the company is now offering the National Cemetery Association forty per cent for bonds held by it, as against a previous offer of twenty-five per cent. These so-called Indiana Bonds are the bonds of a gas company in Indiana, <pb facs="5418478_7_1233.jpg" n="2"/>and it seems that this company is not faring so badly if in a year's time it can raise its bid by fifteen per cent. Mr. Kralovec moved that the offer be accepted, and Mr. Cerny seconded the motion because the National Bank accepted thirty per cent for the same bonds. The Association holds a total of five thousand dollars of these bonds. After a lengthy debate it was resolved, on a motion by Mr. Smejkal, that the managing committee take the necessary steps to transfer the bonds and accept payment of the two thousand dollars offered.</p>
   <p>Marie Srajba, 1828 South May Street, deposited the sum of two hundred dollars for the decoration of five graves. Mrs. Marie Hejmalik deposited two hundred dollars for the decoration of four graves. Mrs. Karolina Jambora deposited one hundred dollars for the decoration of graves. John and Marie Novak transferred their lot to James Novak.</p>
   <p>Disbursements for the month of December amounted to $5,468.55; receipts, $4,776.75; balance in the treasury, $6,016.85; thirteen lots sold for $1,100.91; burials, 93. The meeting was adjourned. </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
