<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-23">May 23, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Cesko-Americky Spolek Pro Spalovani Mrtvych</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1225</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1225.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-05-23">May 23, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">CESKO-AMERICKY SPOLEK PRO SPALOVANI MRTVYCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday the Cesko-Americky Spolek Pro Spalovani Mrtvych (Bohemian-American Cremation Society) held an organization meeting in Town of Lake. The Meeting was held in the Cesko-Slovanska Podporujici Spolecnost (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Society) hall at 48th and Honore Streets, and Dr. Antonin Mueller was the lecturer. He explained the advantages of cremation over the customary placing of bodies in graves from the point of view of health, common sense, and enlightened sentiment.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. W. Egermayer, president of the society, also spoke about the progress of the idea of cremation among American-Bohemians and called attention to the fact that the Cesko-Americky Spolek Pro Spalovani Mrtvych already numbers over five hundred members and has members all over Bohemian-America. He also mentioned that the idea of building a crematorium at the Cesko-Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) is nearing realization, that the committee authorized by the Bohemian National Cemetery Association is diligently investigating various systems of cremation, and that it intends to present <pb facs="5418478_7_1226.jpg" n="2"/>its final proposals to the Cemetery Association during the course of the present year.</p>
   <p>The advisability of founding a branch of the society in Town of Lake was also discussed. The matter was set aside for a later date. During the meeting and immediately afterward, a large number of new members applied, which is evidence of the advancement of our countrymen who live in this community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
