<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-25">July 25, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Meeting of the Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0776</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0776.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-25">July 25, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A MEETING OF THE FEDERATION OF BOHEMIAN FREE THOUGHT SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol (Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools) was held on July 15. It was opened by the president, Mr. Josef Tichava. All other officers, with the exception of Mrs. Radesinsky, were present. The minutes of the previous meeting were approved as read. The minutes of the executive committee were likewise.... approved, with the exception that all reports sent in were to be received only by the responsible officers of the Federation and nobody else. Dr. Mueller then proposed that the teaching in all of the Free Thought schools be made more uniform. The religious sects are endeavoring to gain more children for their schools, enticing them by various gifts such as books, pictures etc., at the same time they try to introduce the Bible into the public schools. To prevent this, a more systematic teaching of Free Thought is necessary. Although Mr. Zajeda pointed to the practice of holding Free Thought classes only once a week, it will be better if a unified system of teaching be introduced which will regulate the instruction methods of individual teachers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0777.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A letter from the Cechie Lodge No. 15 of the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Bohemian Sisterhood), accrediting its new delegate, Mrs. Anastazie Schiguta, was read and the new delegate was greeted by Mr. Tichava....A letter from the Sdruzeni of Cleveland, Ohio was read. It contained a proposition to unite all of the Bohemian Free Thought schools in America, and to introduce a unified teaching plan for all of them. To accomplish this, they ask for a conference to be called which would consist of officers of all the main offices. They also wish to know where such a conference should be held, whether in Chicago, Cleveland, or New York....After a lengthy debate the following decision was reached: The Sdruzeni is convinced that the present time is not ripe for the unification of all the Bohemian Free Though schools in America. Although the Sdruzeni is aware of the importance of the proposed step, and the desirability of grouping all such Free Thought schools under one central office, the expense which would be incurred by such a conference <pb facs="5418478_7_0778.jpg" n="3"/>could hardly warrant holding it [at the present time]. The money, which would thus be spent, should rather be employed for propaganda, and the proposed unification should be postponed till some later and more auspicious time.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Stary made a report on the entertainment given [for the benefit of the Free Thought schools] in the Carter H. Harrison High School. It netted $111.25. Mrs. Dobias made a report of a school picnic of the Free Thought school of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Scoieties) which is located on West 18th and May Streets. The picnic, which was held on June 28, was entirely successful, and Mrs. Dobias thanked all the ladies who helped to make it so. She also mentioned that Mr. Zdenek, of Stickney, Illinois, permitted the free use of his park on that occasion.</p>
   <p>The delegate Mr. Dufek reporting for the entertainment committee, announced that letters have been mailed to all the societies and lodges asking them <pb facs="5418478_7_0779.jpg" n="4"/>to purchase tickets for a festival which the Sdruzeni will hold in the Pilsen Park pavilion on September 17. Mrs. Dobias reported that the management of the benevolent societies' school in the Town of Lake has not yet paid its tuition fee. Although the principal of that school, Mr. Frantisek Kajer, pointed out that the management of his school receive no school salaries, its duty is to pay one third of the money received as tuition into the treasury of the Sdruzeni. This is in accord with the scale laid down by the Sdruzeni. Therefore the management of the Town of Lake Free Thought school shall be notified by letter to abide by the ruling. The receipts of the Sdruzeni were: From the Pavla Cechova Club, a gift of $25; membership fees from the Grand Lodge of the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Bohemian Ladies Union), $544.35; from the Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs, $14.00; tuition from the Jan Neruda Free Thought School $6.65; from the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota, $536.90 in membership fees; from the Grand Lodge of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky [in membership fees], $450.00; from the Mikulas <pb facs="5418478_7_0780.jpg" n="5"/>Ales Free Thought School, $8.50 in tuitions; supplementary receipts from an entertainment given at the Carter H. Harrison High School, $12.75. The total was $1,598.15. Disbursements: Salaries of teachers, $1,073.76.</p>
   <p>Josef Tichava, president;</p>
   <p>Karel Soukup, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
