<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-17">July 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Stand Forth!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summarized editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-17">July 17, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">LET US STAND FORTH!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summarized editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 128th anniversary of the storming of the Bastille was commemorated in the pavilion of the Pilsen Brewery Park last Saturday, under the auspices of the French-American colony of Chicago, effectively aided by the local Belgian colony. The celebration is held annually, and the Czechs have always participated in it in impressive numbers to show their sympathies, which have always been, and are particularly this year, very pronounced. But we were quite startled by the meager participation on the part of the Czech Chicagoans this year.</p>
   <p>We want to be frank, and, therefore, say that the Czechs of this city form a class of people who take to showy celebrations like a duck takes to water.....We like to appear in impressive numbers.....but only on occasions of a Czech nature, where we appear only before ourselves without being noticed <pb facs="5418478_7_0063.jpg" n="2"/>by outsiders, by people of other nationalities whose attention we could well draw to our activities.</p>
   <p>The fact that last Saturday's celebration was not arranged by us, but by the French colony, supported by Chicago Belgians and Italians, may account for the lack of interest exhibited by us, and, it must be admitted, to our disadvantage. If we know how to arrange social and political affairs for ourselves, we should be able to turn our appearances before strangers to our advantage just as well. This is necessary, not only for the sake of representation itself, but because this same representation often becomes weighty in places where one would least expect it.</p>
   <p>The French are a people who have always, and everywhere, demonstrated their highly sympathetic feelings for the Czechs, even before the World War.....</p>
   <p>We had a celebration on the Fourth of July to commemorate the Declaration of Independence. This affair was held in the Pilsen Brewery Park; it was <pb facs="5418478_7_0064.jpg" n="3"/>arranged exclusively by us, and for us. There was a parade which may be called magnificent. Why did we not appear in a parade of our own on July 14, when a nation so sympathetic to us was concerned?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
