<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-04-03">Apr. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Oslava Komenskeho V Sini Cesko-Slovanskych Podporujicich Spolku</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0087</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0087.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-04-03">Apr. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">OSLAVA KOMENSKEHO V SINI CESKO-SLOVANSKYCH PODPORUJICICH SPOLKU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The three hundred and twenty-fourth anniversary of the great Moravian--teacher of nations--Jan Amos Komensky was remembered by a dignified celebration under the leadership of sokol Komensky with the co-operation of Moravian and Slovak organizations at the hall of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies), Eighteenth and May Streets on Sunday afternoon at three o'clock.</p>
   <p>There was a capacity attendance. The meeting was called to order by the chairman, Brother Horky who, in a short address, welcomed the audience. He then informed them why this celebration was arranged, and introduced, the speaker of the day, Professor J. J. Zmrhal, who spoke on the theme, "Poselstvi J. A. Komenskeho Pro Nas a Nasi Dobu" (The Message of J. A. Komensky for Us and Our Times).</p>
   <p>The second prominent speaker was the Slovak, Dr. Stanislav Osusky, who <pb facs="5418478_7_0088.jpg" n="2"/>spoke on the theme "Zivot J. A. Komenskeho," and discussed the time of Komensky's activity and the relations which caused him to take up the profession of teaching.</p>
   <p>The addresses of both speakers were interesting and entertaining, but nevertheless we desire to call attention to the fact that the Komensky celebration was given primarily to inform the public who he was, how he lived, where he was born, and where he died.</p>
   <p>The rest of the rich program was filled with the recitation of a long poem entitled: "Pamatce Komenskeho" (To the Memory of Komensky) by a pupil of the Saturday Bohemian school, Miss Wittner, and then editor Bittner's poem of the same name by little Miss Cepelak.</p>
   <p>There were then songs by the three singing societies: Slovensky Pevecky Sbor (Slovak Singing Society), Pevecky Sbor Lumir (Lumir Singing Society), and Pevecky Odbor Zupy Fuegner-Tyrs (Singing Circuit Fuegner-Tyrs), the <pb facs="5418478_7_0089.jpg" n="3"/>last of which has a chance of becoming the best singing society in Chicago.</p>
   <p>There were two still pictures shown; one with the caption, "Komensky, Ucitel, Vychovatel" (Komensky, the Teacher, Educator), and the very impressive, Komensky Loucise s Vlasti, which was accompanied by a singing quartet composed of Miss Zizka, Mrs. Hess, Mr. Hess, and Mr. Krajcovic.</p>
   <p>The rest of the numbers were given by Mr. Kratochvil's twenty piece orchestra, and as this celebration was given for a good cause--for the benefit of [Ceske] Narodni Sdruzeni (Bohemian National Alliance)--Brother Kratochvil and the members of his orchestra donated their services.</p>
   <p>After a two-hour intermission, there was dancing in the evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
