<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-30">June 30, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Preparations for the Fourth of July Celebration Almost Completed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0245</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0245.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-30">June 30, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">PREPARATIONS FOR THE FOURTH OF JULY CELEBRATION ALMOST COMPLETED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Bohemian committee for the safe and sane celebration of Independence Day was held Tuesday evening in the office of the Pilsen Brewing Company. Mr. Cervenka presided at the meeting, and Mr. Ort acted as secretary.</p>
   <p>It was announced in committee reports that the management of Svatopluk Cech Park hire a band other than the one which had been agreed upon with the Sokols. The sokols of the Fuegner-Tyrs group expected to have the band with which they had rehearsed their program. For a while, this change threatened the whole program, because the sokols thought that they would have to withdraw certain numbers from the program. The matter was finally adjusted by deciding that the numbers which could not be performed in this park, because of the change in arrangements, would <pb facs="5418478_7_0246.jpg" n="2"/>be taken to Douglas Park.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cervenka announced the names of the men and women selected to portray the various personages and figures on the Bohemian allegorical float. The chairman reported that the horses for the mounted sokol company would probably be secured free, but he could not say so definitely, because the commander of the State Militia, whose permission is necessary, is out of town at present.</p>
   <p>In regard to the question whether the float should be held over for the unveilling of the Havlicek monument, Mr. Cervenka was informed it would cost seventy-five dollars. It was, therefore, left to the Arts committee to decide after an inspection of the float whether this sum should be expended on it.</p>
   <p>Alderman Anton J. Cermak, who was present, was asked to make arrangements for street cars to transport the sokol youth from Svatopluk Cech Park to <pb facs="5418478_7_0247.jpg" n="3"/>Twenty-sixth Street and Wabash Avenue, the point of assembly for the parade. All preparatory work has been completed, and there only remains that the various activities outlined by the committees be carried out, so that this year's participation by the Bohemians may be most dignified. </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
