<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-09-24">September 24, 1883</date><title level="a">The Catholic Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-09-24">September 24, 1883</date><title level="a">THE CATHOLIC CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian Roman Catholics yesterday held a celebration at the consecration of the new Catholic Church, corner 18th and Allport Streets. At 7 A:M there was already a big crowd of people around the church. Many scouts and members of the church societies came. Early in the morning there arrived the delegates from St. Louis, and the St. Vaclav Knights went with the band to the railroad station to meet them. At 8 A:M the procession started from the church on Center Avenue, then from 19th to Halsted Street, where the societies of St. John from 25th Street joined the march, which then proceeded on Halsted Street to 12th Street. Here the societies of St. Valclav Church from De Koven Street and the Knights from St. Louis and Milwaukee, joined the crowd of celebrants.</p>
   <p>The parade formed this way was splendid, because besides all Catholic Societies, which arrived even from the country, and Polish Knights, twenty-three Bohemian Clubs and Societies participated in the celebration. The procession proceeded on Halsted Street, and Blue Island Avenue, to the new church, which was consecrated by the Archbishop. Father Suchy from Milwaukee preached a sermon outside the church, and, inside, Father Hestoun from St. Louis preached. After 1 P.M all marched again to 19th and Halsted Streets and back again.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1335.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This celebration can really be called a splendid one, and our Catholic countrymen should be proud of it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
