<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-25">Jan. 25, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Third Convention of National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_0862</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_0862.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-01-25">Jan. 25, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THIRD CONVENTION OF NATIONAL ALLIANCE OF BOHEMIAN CATHOLICS OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to a decision reached in the first regular meeting this year held on January 13, 1922, in the presence of the advisory council, the third general convention of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics) is to held on May 7, 8, and 9 of this year in the city of Chicago in the Bohemian-American Hall on 18th Street. Thus, the convention will take place before the proposed expedition of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku and the Katolicky Sokol (Catholic Sokol) to Czechoslovakia. The reason for selecting these particular dates is that many of our workers and delegates will leave in order to visit their native, liberated homeland.</p>
   <p>The convention will commence on Sunday, May 7, with a Pontifical High Mass which will be celebrated at ten o'clock in the morning. This will be the third time in our history that we shall convene to survey our work, to learn about our progress, to attain a certain self-appraisal, to outline new <pb facs="5418478_7_0863.jpg" n="2"/>directions for our work, and to carry out the program of our organization by deepening and enlarging its objectives. It is therefore necessary that we begin our preparations today! Remember that a national convention of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku has full legislative power and is the highest judicial authority in all matters concerning it. Elect your delegates to this convention. Work on the proposed plans of the convention in such a way as to secure the greatest possible benefits for it among the Bohemian Catholics of America. The exact program will be announced later and will be mailed to all branch organizations.....Chicago, Illinois, January 15, 1922.</p>
   <p>For the executive committee of the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku:</p>
   <p>Reverend Frank W. Jedlicka, chaplain;</p>
   <p>Reverend F. Bozenek, secretary;</p>
   <p>Josef Kopecky, treasurer;</p>
   <p>Mrs. Rosalie Nedved, Mrs. Marie Novotny, Josef J. Janda, Jan F. </p>
   <p>Novotny, Vaclav Kadlec, trustees.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
