<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-15">Feb. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Let There Be Light!</title><title level="a" type="sub">From the Headquarters of the National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_7_1007</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1007.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-02-15">Feb. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">LET THERE BE LIGHT!</title><title level="a" type="sub">From the Headquarters of the National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A wish was manifested in one of our Bohemian newspapers that certain questions with reference to the National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics should be answered, and more light thrown on this national institution of ours. To satisfy the Reverend Father Joseph Klobouk, author of "More Light," published in the newspaper, we pass over his questions, and explain here briefly the constitution and the systematic and effective work of this Alliance. We hope that this explanation answers all those questions, and that there will be more light thrown on the Alliance.</p>
   <p>The Membership</p>
   <p>The National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics has among its members the clergy, men's and ladies' societies, editors of Catholic newspapers, Catholic institutions, <pb facs="5418478_7_1008.jpg" n="2"/>and also individuals not belonging to any organization at all. The Alliance organization is a federation. In the same manner as we are citizens of the United States, so every Bohemian Catholic man and woman is a member of this National Alliance, either through the societies, or by a personal application. However, like the United States, which is composed of several states, so it is with the National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics.</p>
   <p>District and Parish Alliances</p>
   <p>Our people, united in this National Alliance, are divided into District or Parish Alliances, according to the diocese in which they live. The District Alliance is divided again territorially. District Alliances were founded in the following cities: In New York, New York; Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania; Detroit, Michigan; Cleveland, Ohio; Chicago, Illinois; Lankin and Pisek, North Dakota; Omaha, Nebraska; Tabor, South Dakota; La Grange and West, Texas. All these mentioned cities are the centers of our people, suitable <pb facs="5418478_7_1009.jpg" n="3"/>for the District Alliances, with its parishes and societies many miles away, which is the case in the District Alliance of Omaha, Nebraska, and which includes parishes and societies seventy-five miles away from Omaha, Nebraska. In cases because of distance or other reasons, it is impossible to unite parishes and societies into a District Alliance, a Parish Alliance should be founded. This happened in Baltimore, Maryland; New Bohemia, Virginia; Toledo, Ohio; Saint Paul, Minnesota, and Lytomysl, Minnesota, where the Parish Alliances were founded. For instance: If some parish and societies are remote from the District Alliance centers, then, according to the constitution, the minister of that parish, as a parish representative of all the local societies, should create a Parish Alliance, such Parish Alliance having the power of the District Alliance. This applies to scattered parishes and societies in all of the states. District and Parish Alliances are governed by the same by-laws, but also are entitled to accept such regulations as they see fit, according to conditions and habits. These by-laws shall not contradict the by-laws of the National Alliance. They are self-governed just as are the territories of <pb facs="5418478_7_1010.jpg" n="4"/>our United States. They choose their own spiritual adviser, president, vice-president, secretary, treasurer, and executive committee. They act on local matters within the by-laws or inform the National Alliance headquarters on various problems, but they receive and follow the instructions of the National Alliance headquarters. Parishes, societies, and individuals shall assist with voluntary contributions to meet the running expenses of the District or Parish Alliance.</p>
   <p>National Alliance Headquarters</p>
   <p>At the head of the National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics is the National Alliance headquarters, located in Chicago, Illinois, as determined by the national convention, having full power to act within the by-laws, with the assistance of the consultation committee, consisting of clergy and associate ladies and gentlemen. It has an office and visitors' room to accommodate the many people living here, and also those from our old country. There is a manager employed there. Every day it is necessary to answer <pb facs="5418478_7_1011.jpg" n="5"/>many letters, and to carry on the office work necessary in connection with this great body of the National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics. There also are other expenditures, such as postage, telegrams, cablegrams, and often traveling expenses. The administration disbursements, although economically conducted, alone amount to thousands of dollars a year, and, therefore, every member of our societies is required to pay a small assessment of two cents a month to cover the expenditure of our sacred cause. It is also proposed that the societies themselves, should collect this assessment, but in consideration of the fact that none of these societies can apply this assessment without having a general meeting, the only thing left to do is to leave this matter of collecting this assessment to be thrashed out by the societies and the National Alliance headquarters themselves. There will be one great advantage: every member will feel that he is not a member on the books only, but will consider him or herself a real contributing and active member.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1012.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Systematic, Effective Work and</p>
   <p>Committees of National Alliance</p>
   <p>To accomplish all of the aims stipulated in our constitution, not only the National, District, and Parish Alliances are active, but also the Committees, appointed by the National Alliance officers and the executive committee, are assisting. Taking in consideration that the reorganized National Alliance is only about a year old, much has been done in the national, religious, charitable, and cultural life of the Bohemian people in the United States, and also in Czechoslovakia. When our committees are fully prepared, more affective work is expected. In the course of the existence of the Alliance, the consultation and religious, school and education, public affairs, foreign, and publicity committees have handled various matters already, or have important matters on their program. We call attention to the following information about these committees.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1013.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The consultation and religious committee consists of the ministers of Cleveland, Ohio. It also seeks missionaries for Czech America. According to the news, there is hope that the Jesuits of Czechoslovakia will be secured, and an attempt was also made to secure Reverend Father Jan Ruzicka, doctor of philology and theology from Siberia.</p>
   <p>The school and education committee consists of clergy and laymen of Omaha, Nebraska, who work together with the National Alliance headquarters, against the proposals of different State Legislatures aimed against the parochial schools. In the State of Illinois, it succeeded in defeating a similar proposal in the Committee on Education in the State Legislature.</p>
   <p>The public affairs committee consists of our foremost men in Chicago, Illinois, and follows public questions. If one appears which falls within the scope of our National Alliance, this committee either notifies the proper committee, or the National Alliance headquarters takes action itself.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1014.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>The foreign committee, located in Chicago, Illinois, is still represented by the men retained from our old political Alliance, and still is active as in the past. It has been a factor in our relief work for the suffering people in the Czechoslovak republic, and sent a mission abroad, composed of seven members, to propagate our most holy cause.</p>
   <p>The publicity committee consists of the clergy and laymen of Saint Louis, Missouri, and is preparing to publish the history of the National Alliance. It is also considering the publication of brochures dealing with social problems of the world.</p>
   <p>At the head of all these committees stands the National Alliance headquarters, a centre of the National Alliance, its officers, executive, and consultation committees, meeting every Friday, sometimes more often. Any of our local or out of town visitors, who has attended one of our meetings, recognized and admitted that this is a pulse and focus of the National Alliance from <pb facs="5418478_7_1015.jpg" n="9"/>which come all the directions for the District and Parish Alliances and committees, working systematically and effectively toward our goal. Surely much more could have been done, but in consideration that our National Alliance was reorganized not quite a year ago, and that the task of uniting in it all the Bohemian Catholics in the United States, living under different conditions and circumstances a thousand miles apart, but reaching all the classes of our people, it has been a gigantic task in itself. In consideration that our National Alliance is performing its mission impartially, it is desirable that in places where there is not a District or Parish Alliance one should be started immediately in order to finish our organization work. With full strength and understanding, we could work together toward the beautiful and noble cause which we resolved upon in our last convention. To this end, let everybody work according to the best of his ability as is required by the necessity of the present times, and by our progress in the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_7_1016.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>For the National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics (Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku):</p>
   <p>Signed: Jan Straka, president.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
