<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-07-10">July 10, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Propaganda Question Again</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0900</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0900.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-07-10">July 10, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROPAGANDA QUESTION AGAIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Bishop" Papadopoulos and printer Kastritsis have named the room at Monroe Street and Grant Avenue, where a few Greeks gather to listen to the sermons of "pastor" Papadopoulos every Sunday, "The First Greek Evangelical Church". This is this same man who preaches that our Holy Virgin is not the Mother of God; that the saints are ordinary men; and that the holy icons or images are merely pieces of wood and paint.</p>
   <p>Among those who listen to Papadopoulos are a few Greek laborers who go there because they are promised that they will be given work.</p>
   <p>Certainly, these people have no desire to listen to all these fantastic and "enlightening" ideas of Papadopoulos, but they are forced, because of their great need, to listen to the "inspired pastor's" sermons. In addition to these good people, there are a few young men who attend the sermons. They say that they have been promised a high school or a college education.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0901.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Thus, all these unemployed men and supposed lovers of wisdom gather in this place without knowing the real purpose of Papadopoulos. Lately, he has had the insolence to elevate himself to the rank of bishop. As yet, we are unable to discover who ordained Papadopoulos and who promoted him to the bishop's chair.</p>
   <p>Now, this person owns a printing shop and is printing the notorious book of the still more notorious renegade and deserter of the church, Cyril Georgiades. Together with "pastor" Kastritsis, Papadopoulos operates the Hermes printing shop and publishes a pamphlet called Hope, which gives free publicity to a few people with whom we shall deal in a later issue.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the activities of "Bishop" Papadopoulos is the continuance of Georgiades in the post of principal of the Greek school and the retention of the former's sister-in-law as a teacher in the same school. The Holy Synod of Greece, the supreme authority in the Greek church, has forbidden these two so-called educators to continue their teaching. Under their guidance, the <pb facs="5422062_5_0902.jpg" n="3"/>unfortunate Greek students did not have the right to make the sign of the cross, or the right to pray according to the custom of the church.</p>
   <p>This state of affairs lasted for three years in our very midst; more than three hundred pupils were taught in the Greek school which is built on the property of the Holy Trinity Greek Orthodox community. Was it the desire of the church community to appoint and pay a relative of "Bishop" Papadopoulos to teach the poor pupils not to use the sign of the cross?</p>
   <p>In the meantime, you may ask what our three theologians and priests were doing. This is a condition which we find very hard to explain.</p>
   <p>What have our church boards done to correct this evil? What have the parents, the Greek businessmen, and the members of our Chicago community done about it? This is the important question which we shall attempt to analyze and throw light upon.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0903.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Saloniki proposes to find the truth. Just as it attacked the sham bankers and all the loathsome elements of our community, so today begins our gigantic battle to smash and expose the propagandists by revealing the truth. Many of them have been working silently, profiting from the internal strife and discontent within our community and from the attacks and accusations against our priests. Propagandists had created many scandals in the church governing boards and had succeeded even in penetrating into our schools until the day that this paper fought the destructive influence of Papadopoulos' sermons and forced him to behave and until his sister-in-law was relieved of her duties. In addition, Georgiades was driven out of town. Saloniki will expose all those liars and imposters who are betraying and undermining the Greek Orthodox church.</p>
   <p>The Greek people of Chicago, who are making rapid strides forward in business and industry, need to be informed about conditions in the community, in the schools, in the churches, in every kind of enterprise. They must be told about every dishonest and fraudulent activity.</p>
   <p>Saloniki will enlighten our good people, but it will discover and destroy the <pb facs="5422062_5_0904.jpg" n="5"/>evildoers.</p>
   <p>Let us all lend a helping hand to Saloniki in her gallant and unselfish struggle to save our national Greek consciousness and our church institutions from being undermined.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
