<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1928-03-31">March 31, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Declaration and Friendly Advice.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0512</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0512.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1928-03-31">March 31, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">DECLARATION AND FRIENDLY ADVICE.</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many of the irregular Greek priests in Chicago, I am informed, were disturbed and embarrassed, and made an uproar on account of my article last week, regarding the ecclesiastical question. To those who were dissatisfied with the article, I solemnly declare that no means or power will be able to stop me from publishing the truth, to advocate right and to advise the Greek public not to fall in errors which would have diastrous consequences.</p>
   <p>That is the duty of a publisher, as I understand it. That is exactly what I have done in the past and shall continue to do in the future. I am not frightened or dismayed by any one, and if one can show me wherein I am without right or reason, I will gladly congratulate and compensate him for his services. On the other hand, if the naked truth which I advocate refuses, by common sense reasoning, to be clothed with the bejeweled togas of unrighteousness, then the ax of right and truth will fall where it may.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0513.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Fortunately, I live in a land where freedom of the press and defence of right and truth are the corner stories of this great United States. Hence, for the dignity of the press, and my obligation to the public, it is my imperative duty to exercise such influence. I would remind the irregular priests that there is a civil and penal law here in this country which prosecutes those who appropriate rights not belonging to them, and they have the right to seek the protection of that law if need be.</p>
   <p>Therefore I advise these non-canonicals, for their own interest first, for the sake of harmony, amity and peace, for the spiritual welfare and progress of the Greeks in Chicago and for the dignity and prestige of the Greek church, to cease their non-canonical attitude and actions, and recognize the regular ecclesiastical authority. Their persistence will benefit none; on the contrary it will be detrimental to all.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0514.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is true that in their efforts to recognize the prevailing authority, the irregular priests will meet impediments and obstacles from the irregular parishes, but this can be overcome by organizing a brotherhood among themselves, and with united front, ask the councils of the parishes to accept the Ecumenical mandate.</p>
   <p>For that reason, I undertake to organize that brotherhood and invite the priests, who wish to participate, to send their names and addresses to me. Of course they will remain unknown to the public until the organization of the brotherhood is complete; then their resolution will be published and their names signed.</p>
   <p>This is, I think, a beneficial and dignified way to end the division of our church, which tends to disrupt the edifice of our faith. If we do not do it, and do it quickly, we will all repent when it is too late.</p>
   <p>C. Salopoulos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
