<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1911-11-25">Nov. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Star Stands the Wrong Way in Accusing Free Masons.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0949</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0949.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1911-11-25">Nov. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK STAR STANDS THE WRONG WAY IN ACCUSING FREE MASONS.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Kalliontzis' article, published in the Greek Star, against Free Masonry and Socialism, is wholly disapproved by the Greeks in Chicago. Many fellow-Greeks, by writing and phoning to us registered their utter disapproval of the article in the Greek Star which expressed disrespect to fellow-Americans and fellow-Greeks who are Masons or Socialists.</p>
   <p>In our last edition of Loxias we expressed we forgave our eminent physician Dr. Kalliontzis, the author of the article, taking into consideration Christ's example when he said, "Father forgive them, for they know not what they do."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0950.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But the publisher of the Greek Star, though ignorant and illiterate, cannot be forgiven. Because he, as an editor and publisher, must know the duty and obligation of the press towards people. He should know that such inaccurate and unfounded articles should not be printed for publication. A little knowledge of history, common sense, and respect for justice, right and good, would have been sufficient to guide the publisher of the Greek Star to refuse to publish the article of Dr. K. Kalliontzis, against Free Masons and Socialism.</p>
   <p>My friend Dr. Kalliontzis and the uneducated publisher of the Greek Star should know, if they must, that true Christianity stands upon Socialism and Cosmopolitanism.</p>
   <p>Indeed, from the nationalistic point of view, i. e. from the point of view of Hellenic Nationalism, Socialism, Cosmopolitanism as well as Ecumenical Christianity, are bitter enemies to any nation.</p>
   <p>Below this you find an article written by G. Matalas titled, "The Obstruction of Civilization. It is a very interesting article to read, providing you are far above the line of the average partisan, narrowminded patriot.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
