<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Aster</title>,
<date when="1927-11-11">Nov. 11, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The March of Progress of the Greeks of Chicag</title><title level="a" type="sub">Introduction</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1442</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1442.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Aster</title>,
<date when="1927-11-11">Nov. 11, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE MARCH OF PROGRESS OF THE GREEKS OF CHICAG</title><title level="a" type="sub">Introduction</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although the history of the land known as "the glory that was Greece" dates back three thousand years, the birth of the Greek nation is parallel with the growth of the great city of Chicago. It was but a hundred years ago that Greece was recognized by the world as an independent nation; about the same time, Chicago was placed on the map as a part of the United States.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding the fact that it was Columbus, an Italian, who discovered America, this country is known as the true daughter of ancient Greece, for it has adopted and developed Greek civilization to the point of perfection. The traditional and historical relationship of the two countries was the vital spark that inspired the Greeks to come here and become loyal American citizens. There were half a million Greeks who participated in the great exodus from the motherland.</p>
   <p>I was one of those who came to a strange land. Unable to speak English, <pb facs="5422062_5_1443.jpg" n="2"/>despondent, I caught the "I Will" spirit of Chicago.</p>
   <p>When I came here, I saw the ruins of the Chicago fire, men with long mustaches, women with long, trailing skirts; I saw Chicago in its infancy of progress, when there were no movies or automobiles, and when Greek restaurants and confectioneries were as scarce as were bathtubs in Chicago homes. I remember the masculine hat of the "eighties", which is today worn only by comedians; the "toothpick" shoes; fur caps; coats and pants of men worn ridiculously tight. There were no skyscrapers, but only one-and two-story dwellings; Lake Michigan in the summer was devoid of bathers, and even in the winter people were afraid to come near the lake for fear of catching pneumonia. I remember when a phone was a rare luxury in Chicago, when there were no stoves in any of the horse-drawn cars, but only hay on the floor in severe weather. In those days barbers were dentists as well. There were no first-class hotels; there was no electricity, no telephone communication, no bathing beaches, no elevated lines; there were no fancy shops with show windows, no cement sidewalks, and the quickest means of transportation from North Avenue to 39th Street, or from the Loop to Ashland <pb facs="5422062_5_1444.jpg" n="3"/>Avenue, was by way of the express wagon.</p>
   <p>If Father Dearborn were alive today and could view our beautiful lake front, dotted with magnificent buildings which have emerged from the little dwellings that were once there, he would certainly be a most amazed person. He would see the greatest metropolis of the western states, which sprang from a little village, and the marvelous growth of which was inspired by the "I Will" spirit. Chicago's wondrous development I compare with that of Athens' golden era--the golden age of Pericles, which is so clearly manifested in Chicago today.</p>
   <p>Gazing back over the history of Chicago, and forward to a great future for this metropolis, I realize that the Chicago fire and the World's Fair were the two guiding stars that led Chicago to its present stage of development. The Chicago fire was, at the time, a catastrophe, but it was the milestone that made Chicago what it is today.</p>
   <p>As Kinzie, La Salle, and Marquette dreamed of Chicago as the city of the future, so did the fifty thousand Greeks who placed their confidence and <pb facs="5422062_5_1445.jpg" n="4"/>their affection in Chicago.</p>
   <p>During the thirty-five years of my residence in Chicago, I participated in Americanization work, having felt that Chicago was my home--that Chicago had given me its utmost, and that I would give it mine. As a poet once said, "I slept and dreamed that life was beauty, I woke and found that life was duty".</p>
   <p>Thought a lonely immigrant when I came here, I have had the pleasure of corresponding with presidents of this country--Roosevelt, Harding, Wilson, and Coolidge--and have participated in many civic movements in my desire to help make Chicago greater and better than I found it. I have had to fight the battles of my fellow Greeks, with whom I have grown in hardship as well as in prosperity.</p>
   <p>During the World War, under the auspices of the National Security League, I assisted in organizing the seventy-five different nationalities in Chicago and, at a patriotic dinner, I had the privilege of speaking from the same <pb facs="5422062_5_1446.jpg" n="5"/>platform as Bainbridge Colby, then Secretary of State and President Wilson's spokesman, and Governor F. O. Lowden. I acted as host to Prince George of Greece, when he visited Chicago; to Bishop Lutas of Zanda, and to Meletios, president of the Holy-Synod, who brought greetings to Chicago from the Venizelos government. I likewise had the pleasure of extending greetings to the Greek ambassadors Coromilas, Russos, and Simopoulos. I headed a committee of fifteen Chicagoans who called on Eleutherios Venizelos to extend him greetings on behalf of Chicago; presented him an album bearing the signatures of hundreds of leading officials, and offered him the Key to the city. I was a host to Prince Paul of Greece on his visit here a few years ago; I entertained him at the Hamilton Club, and spoke at a banquet given in his honor.</p>
   <p>I am the author of the article on Pericles and Lincoln, comparing the two great funeral orations; the article was published in a Sunday edition of the Chicago Herald and Examiner a few years ago. I spoke on the subject at the Hamilton Club on the birthday of "The Great Emancipator", and brought out the fact that it took the world two thousand years to produce another man <pb facs="5422062_5_1447.jpg" n="6"/>as great as Pericles, in the person of Lincoln, the martyr, whose name is now immortalized by his efforts to preserve the Union and united the people under one flag.</p>
   <p>Pericles' funeral oration and Lincoln's Gettysburg address, both masterpieces in eloquence, stand today as the most idealistic documents there are on the principles of democracy. It would take the pen of Thucydides, or the poetic talent of Homer, to sing the hymns of the two illustrious champions of the principles of freedom.</p>
   <p>The Achievements of Chicago Greeks</p>
   <p>A new chapter in my career was occasioned by the fact that a Philhellenic newspaper, the Chicago Herald and Examiner, chose me to write a series of articles, which appeared in its columns on November 4, 5, and 6, 1927; these articles dealt with the achievements of the Greeks, and their contribution, from both a patriotic and commercial standpoint, toward a greater Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1448.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>I rejoice over the growth of our city and the progress achieved by our people, with whom I join hearts in saying that we are proud of the fact that we are the descendents of Themistocles and Leonidas. But we are also Americans among Americans and Chicagoans striving toward a greater America, and we are proud to call Washington and Lincoln our own.</p>
   <p>Through the courtesy of the Chicago Herald and Examiner, we are reproducing the aforementioned series of articles; we intend to print them in booklet form, and distribute them free to those interested in the story, "The March of Progress of the Greeks of Chicago."</p>
   <p>P. S. Lambros</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
