<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-09-13">Sept. 13, 1928</date>,
<title level="a">p. 1 the Ecclesiastical Question in America Must Be Solved.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0495</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0495.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-09-13">Sept. 13, 1928</date>,
<title level="a">p. 1 THE ECCLESIASTICAL QUESTION IN AMERICA MUST BE SOLVED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The election in Greece has shown that the Greek people have profited by the misfortunes which have befallen them on account of political passions in the past, and they have risen supreme and united before the threatened danger of political and national annihilation.</p>
   <p>They realized their deplorable failing rather late, but they have put an end, through their vote to the confusion of political decay and race subjugation. They have shown once more that they are free people.</p>
   <p>In America Hellenism are being gnawed by the plague of ecclesiastical division and national decay. Indifference, hatred, abhorence, scorn, ridicule, and sneers are directed towards the Orthodox church and the Greek language towards customs, habits, and traditions towards everything Greek. And all this from Greeks. What has contributed to this state of things? The political division, first, and the ecclesiastical division, secondly.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0496.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It would be to no purpose, and withal injurious, to go back to seek the causes of this sad phenomenon among the Greeks of this country. However, we emphasize this:</p>
   <p>Since we are separated from the beloved, illustrious and glorious Greecian land by great bodies of land and water, let the connecting link of language, the strong bond of traditions, and the spiritual palladium of the Orthodox Faith, bind us together.</p>
   <p>As things are with us today in America, the Greek language is slipping away from the new generation; the church is being deserted; the faith is being undermined; the traditions are being forgotten; and Hellenism is becoming benumbed and lost, from the business point of view. What is the cause? Division, lack of organization and systematic pursuance of our aims.</p>
   <p>The main and mortal obstacle towards unity and universal cooperation is the ecclesiastical division.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0497.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Rodostolian camp maintains that it is the official, legitimate, and recognized ecclesiastical authority in America. Very well, but how can such an organization of clergymen impose itself upon the people and be recognized by all Greek Orthodox Christians in view of the fact that it has not presented so far any program, any constitution any workable system, nothing concrete, sound, or enlightening? Churches are bought, parishes are organized, catechetic schools are launched circulars are sent. Much is murmured and sung to the detriment of Saint Rodostolou, perhaps groundless and false, nevertheless unanswered. A group of clergymen came together and organized themselves to their own satisfaction, drew their constitution, and appeared thus before the Greek people of America, demanding recognition of, and submission to, this organization. Many of our people stand bewildered not knowing what this ecclesiastical organization represents.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0498.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Hellenism of America demands. 1. A direct spiritual dependence on the Mother Church. 2. Establishment of a Greek Orthodox Theological Seminary in America for spititual guidance and for the proper training of our future priests. 3. Priests should come from Greece to guide the Greek populace of America, according to the creeds of Orthodoxy. 4. Preservation of the Greek language, the language of God, in the holy mass. 5. Churches and communities to be administered by a mixed committee of laymen and clergymen, proportionately. Real estate and other property to belong to the communities rather than to Archiepiscopal organizations. 6. Establishment and maintenance of Greek American schools and colleges, where the Greek language, history, and the beautiful traditions of our glorious race are to be tonight. Finally, we desire to have an Orthodox Church, Greek, genuine, pure with all its traditions, and governed according to its holy cannons and dogmas.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0499.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>To this and a congress must be held by all our Greek people to which delegates ought to be elected, who are to meet with the representatives of the clergy and bring about the desired unity. Another aid to unity would be an ecclesiastical Legate sent from Greece to whose authority all communities in America are to be submitted.</p>
   <p>In any case, preparatory work for the attainments of the points cited above should begin without delay so that we can go ahead united in the realization of our race's ideals, determined to preserve our precious treasures. Religion, Language, and Traditions. Let us go forward.</p>
   <p>Dr. Kleomenis</p>
   <p>G. Papatheodorou.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
