<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1917-12-01">Dec. 1, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Soldiers in Army Training Camp</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-12-01">Dec. 1, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK SOLDIERS IN ARMY TRAINING CAMP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The stereotyped question I have been answering upon my return to Chicago was, "What is Chillicothe and what is it like?" I have asked Saloniki to print this article concerning the Camp at Chillicothe, and the Greek soldiers in it.</p>
   <p>Chillicothe is just a little town with a population of fifteen thousand inhabitants. Three months ago, its existence was practically unknown, since it had no distinctive characteristic. Today, it has become one of the best-known towns in America. It is small in size, but has assumed great importance because of the United States Army Camp located on the outskirts of the town. This camp has been named after General Sherman. In Camp Sherman, the men are taught the use of arms and trained in maneuvers and drills, in order that they may defend their country efficiently, against those forces seeking to destroy the democracies of the world and</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1299.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>the rights of a people to rule themselves.</p>
   <p>Chillicothe, with its thousands of defenders of freedom, holds a high place among the sixteen Army training camps in this country. There are many men of Greek descent in this camp who rushed to the aid of their adopted land at the first sign of danger. They are easily recognized, wearing the eternal khaki, and drilling on the field; they seem to walk a little more gracefully than the others, and their heads are held a little higher. The American soldiers stand and secretly admire them as they pass. In a speech, before the 332nd Infantry, a sergeant said, "There's the Greeks for example"; he was trying to imbue his men with a sense of loyalty and patriotism and used the Greek for an example, of what he wanted them to imitate.</p>
   <p>Can we suppress the glow of heartfelt joy at this honor paid our people? Can we be blamed for feeling a thrill upon hearing an American officer praising the Greek race? Of course not! And the Greek soldiers in the various divisions of the Army are striving to live up to the expectations of their</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1300.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>superior officers. They are particularly enjoying the new types of exercises adopted by the Army. The Greek soldier not only uses the training he receives in the American army, but he also practices the training he received under the blue sky of Greece. As I passed among these Greek soldiers I heard snatches of democratic Army songs, sung by homesick men. And so, singing and training, the Greek soldier, at Chillicothe, prepares to defend the honor of his beloved America.</p>
   <p>A. Alexopoulos</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
