<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-10-14">October 14, 1930</date><title level="a">The Question of Unity and Cooperation of the Greek Communities of Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0321</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0321.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGO GREEK DAILY</title>,
<date when="1930-10-14">October 14, 1930</date><title level="a">The Question of Unity and Cooperation of the Greek Communities of Chicago.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The unity of the Greek communities of Chicago is the main subject to hold the attention of the communities and their officials, at present. There are many that confuse the community question with that of the church division in America, as a whole, and imagine that the matter of straightening up our communal difficulties depends on the solution of the church question. Well, the question of limitation of the number of churches in Chicago, is the local question of our community and it will be settled by the needs of our parishes.</p>
   <p>For the settlement of this question the Legate seemed to be willing to serve the parishes, as their arbitrator, and the representatives signed a protocol, wherewith, they accepted the offer. When, in a few days, the Legate returns to Chicago, every parish will submit to him its plan and views regarding the consolidation of the communities.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt that every parish will have a different plan with good reasons. In addition, each one will believe that its plan is the best, but <pb facs="5422062_5_0322.jpg" n="2"/>we, duty bound, have to caution all to put some water in their wine, and that is, that if every parish believes its plan will unite the communities, the members must understand, once for all, that nothing will be done.</p>
   <p>That which Chicago needs if the cooperation of the parishes and that co-operation is possible on matters in which the parishes have common interests, but in points of opposing interests, it is not so easy to have unity. For the present, at least, we urge the parishes not to sacrifice the question of co-operation.</p>
   <p>The question of merging the communities being a local one concerns the ones which are divided, as for example, the Holy Trinity and St. Basil communities. They must find a way of mutual understanding and submit their differences, for arbitration, before Legate. Likewise, on the South Side, the St. Constantine and St. Nickolas communities must do the same. On the North Side, the Annunciation, St. George, St. Andrew and St. James communities must also do the same.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0323.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It must be understood by those directly interested, that the Cooperation of all Parishes is a most important and vital question. The question of union is a specific one and belongs to the parishes directly concerned. It will be accomplished through economic pressure. These parishes have, now, a good chance, in the Legate's being present, to determine the way of their unity and we urge them not to let it slip by.</p>
   <p>The question, however, of common cooperation by all communities, on matters of general interest, by having every community contribute its share, and that all Greeks be obligated to register in their parish, and a central committee be formed in accordance with the federal system, we consider to be a question of great importance, from which we gradually expect many benefits. It is to this, in the main, that we call the attention of the Legate and officials of the communities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
