<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-04-18">April 18, 1931</date><title level="a">Our Communal Matters.</title><title level="a" type="sub">p. 1. Let us Not Expect Everything from the Archbishop.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0262</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0262.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGO GREEK DAILY</title>,
<date when="1931-04-18">April 18, 1931</date><title level="a">Our Communal Matters.</title><title level="a" type="sub">p. 1. Let us Not Expect Everything From the Archbishop.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the solution of our Church communities under one ecclesiastical authority in America, it is about time to take up the job of readjusting our communities. The Ecclesiastical Regime, eliminated, has left behind so much havoc as to require from us much time and labor to straighten out the affairs of the communities.</p>
   <p>We must, in the first place, understand that we should not expect this to be done by the Archbishop, alone. Each community must work separately to straighten out its communal affairs, and must ask the intervention of the church authority only in such a case as that, in which the local paragons would not be able to settle their differences. The Archbishop, in other words, will be the mediator of such matters upon which differences of opinion may arise, and his decision must be respected by all. We know our affairs better than anybody else and it is our duty to acquaint the Archbishop with them.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0263.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What we mean to say is that we must not expect the Archbishop to remove as by a magic touch, the havoc that held sway for a decade, while we take a back seat and cross our hands and maybe our fingers. Let us start setting the example right here in Chicago, where Mr. Athenagoras will come shortly; let us ask the different executive counsels of the communities: What preparatory work they have done, so far, for the solution of our communal problems?</p>
   <p>The Subdivision Into Parishes.</p>
   <p>The idea was brought up of determining the boundaries of every community, and the subdivision of Chicago into parishes. In an off-hand discussion, with the Archbishop, on his arrival, and with the priests of the different communities and their representatives, the idea was accepted in principle. But, has there been any serious study upon this most important matter? Or should we wait for the Archbishop to come and define for us the boundaries of our parishes? We emphasize this matter in particular, because it will be the first matter, perhaps, that would come up for discussion when the Legate arrives ant it is the duty of every community to study it, in advance, and not wait for the last moment to think about it.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0264.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Unification of the Communities.</p>
   <p>In addition, there is one more important question that concerns the community of Chicago, and that is, the unification, or merging of some communities. We do not mean the closing up of churches, as we have dealt with this question, often, and we repeat, today, that for the present, at least, no discussion whatever is necessary on the subject of the closing of the church A or the church B. It is certain that such a matter presents many reefs and, we must, by all means, avoid it for the present in order that we may achieve the solution of more important and urgent matters.</p>
   <p>But, regardless of the question of the closing of any of the churches, the immediate necessity of merging some communities comes up, and specifically,the merging of the Holy Trinity Church with St. Basil Church and that of St. George Church with the Church of the Annunciation.</p>
   <p>We mention the above communities because the question of determining the boundary lines of the parishes, most certainly will present us with many difficulties. On the other hand, economic reasons dictate the unification of the above Communities and especially the churches of the West Side Community, i.e. St. Basil <pb facs="5422062_5_0265.jpg" n="4"/>Church and Holy Trinity Church.</p>
   <p>The Matter of St. Nickolas Church.</p>
   <p>Another matter equally important, which concerns, in the main, the community of the Holy Trinity Church and that of St. Nickolas Church is the separation of the two communities of these churches. This matter was taken up repeatedly in their meetings by the members of Holy Trinity and a final decision was to be taken in their general meeting, May 3rd. This matter must be settled before the arrival of the Archbishop. The idea of separating St. Nickolas from the West section is the only correct and natural one. The community of Holy Trinity Church has no reason, any longer, to maintain a church on the South Side where St. Nickolas Church is located.</p>
   <p>During the time of church dissension a mistake was made as a retaliation for the buying of St. Basil by the former Bishop Philaretos. To buy St. Nickolas today, with church unity achieved, is no good reason for the community Holy Trinity to have one more church out of its boundaries on the South Side of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0266.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This mistake has been of enough expense to Holy Trinity and it is time to have things in their rightful place. Inasmuch as the merged community of St. Nickolas has offered to buy this church, the Holy Trinity community should be obliged to sell it. To this we shall refer later.</p>
   <p>Upon all these matters, the officials of the communities, today, ought to think seriously and form certain definite plans to be submitted to the judgment of the Archbishop. The Communities of Holy Trinity and St. Basil, certainly, must understand, well, that their uniting into a corporation is an imperative act. It is to their interest, on the other hand, and sound judgement demands their good understanding before the Archbishop arrives. They should not leave the settling of the matters to him. Such an understanding for the merging of the two churches was had a month ago. It is good to go over this again, that they may understand that their merging is indispensable and bound to achieve pleasant results.</p>
   <p>These questions, for the present, are what we considered our duty to suggest to the officials of our communities, and we do not doubt they will be taken into consideration.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
