<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1929-11-16">Nov. 16, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Girls in Chicago Their Duties and Obligations to the Greek Race</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. Papatheodorou</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1360</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1360.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1929-11-16">Nov. 16, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK GIRLS IN CHICAGO THEIR DUTIES AND OBLIGATIONS TO THE GREEK RACE</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. Papatheodorou</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.- The Grecian maidens of Chicago are the image upon which every Greek looks with reverence. Upon them the race builds its hopes for the inspiration of Greek idealism. To them the race confides the perpetuation of Greek religion, language and the traditions of Hellenism. To them, as to the holy ark, we deposit and entrust for safety the jewels and heirlooms of our glorious race.</p>
   <p>Our Grecian maidens fully understand their great responsibility, and gracefully respond to their imperative duty. In order to effectively discharge their obligations, the girls have formed societies and clubs among themselves and with body and soul serve the interests of the community. Their work and activities are highly appreciated by all, and this appreciation is manifested by the great success they have, whenever they hold a social affair. The community willingly responds <pb facs="5422062_5_1361.jpg" n="2"/>to their requests. The Greeks of Chicago are very grateful to them and Hellenism in general looks upon them as the guardians of our race.</p>
   <p>Our pride, esteem, and admiration for our beloved maidens would be enhanced if they, in their gatherings and social affairs, used the Greek language, as a means of conversation, and they, in their circulars and invitations, used also the Greek language. English is the language of the land and all of us know it and use it every day as a necessary thing, means of commnication. Using the Greek language is a priviledge and is a sacred service to the race, which cannot exist without the language. Greek language and Greek religion keep the race from extinction.</p>
   <p>Their action in using the Greek tongue will create a deep sympathy and untold reverence for our maidens. Their actions will immediately be followed by others because our girls are the leaders in the life and energy of our community. It would be the most desirable thing and a great service to our community if the Greek maidens took the initiative in employing the Greek language whenever possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
