<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-11-14">Nov. 14, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Reasons for the Dismissal of Paschalakis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-11-14">Nov. 14, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE REASONS FOR THE DISMISSAL OF PASCHALAKIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1. -- We have cited the reasons given by those on the Bishop's side for the dismissal of the Reverend Father Paschalakis as neglect of duty and the necessity of having a married priest. This last reason, the necessity of appointing a married priest in his place, tells us so much that it is of no se to add anything more.</p>
   <p>But for the sake of more elucidation we ask: Why do they want a married priest now? And why did they persist in having an unmarried priest as president of St. Basil's Ladies' Society before?</p>
   <p>The reasonsgiven by those around Paschalakis are different for they say that the motives behind his dismissal were the Bishop's petty egotism and jealousy of the Bishop, who knew that the priest enjoyed the esteem of his flock and as pastor was distinguished for his conscientious performance of his duties, and that as president of the <pb facs="5422062_5_0461.jpg" n="2"/>Ladies' Society he enjoyed the love and respect of its members.</p>
   <p>The dismissed priest and president of the Ladies' Society really was amiable in appearance, handsome in countenance, refined in manner, and a jovial, powerful, and forceful speaker. In other words, he had all the qualifications which a pastor ought to have. The Bishop had assigned to him in addition the duties of president of the Ladies' Society. His reputation was spreading so much that many who did not belong to St. Basil's parish, both men and women, went there to see him.</p>
   <p>All these qualities, then, according to Paschalakis's friends, aroused the Bishop's envy, since the attention and the interest of the parishioners were directed towards Paschalakis.</p>
   <p>Without assuming any responsibility we simply publish the claims of both sides as we have them from official sources, and let the public pass judgment upon this important question, which has divided the congregation of St. Basil's Church into two hostile camps.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
