<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1907-09-27">Sept. 27, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Reverend Leo Pygeas' Error</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1052</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1052.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-09-27">Sept. 27, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">REVEREND LEO PYGEAS' ERROR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, the Reverend Leo Pygeas, of the Saint Trinity Greek Orthodox Church, delivered a violent and vitriolic attack against the Greek press of America and against several political figures in our community. We were greatly shocked to hear of this, for it is well known that the church pulpit was never intended to become a political battleground where bitter and violent differences are fought over and thrashed out.</p>
   <p>By this action of his, the Reverend demonstrated in a disgusting way his ability and intention to introduce modern, strange, and original innovations in our churches. He wants to imitate the people of the New World who have such a flair for novelty and for new-fangled ideas. Is he willfully indifferent to the long-established and revered rules and regulations of our church?</p>
   <p>In passing, let us remind our priests that they do not have the authority to introduce up-to-date methods and ideas into the Greek church. Their sacred <pb facs="5422062_5_1053.jpg" n="2"/>duty compels the Greek clergy to obey and enforce the laws and regulations of the Greek church as established and dictated by tradition and by the supreme ecclesiastical authorities of the Greek church. Our priests have been given authority to provide spiritual and moral leadership and enlightenment for our people; they have been trusted to advance and protect our national Greek interests on every occasion. Therefore, Reverend Pygeas should not have assumed the great responsibility of defying the church, his immediate superiors, his flock,as well as the Greek press and the individuals whom he attacked.</p>
   <p>We ask this bold and impertinent clergyman: Is this the sermon which you were supposed to preach last Sunday? We ask you: What is the connection between the minister of God and the activities and the affairs of the press in the services of the church? Should our clergy sow the poisonous seeds of strife, hatred, and political rancor in the sanctuary of the church--a place where spiritual love must reign, where every sin is destroyed, where perfect harmony, brotherly love, <pb facs="5422062_5_1054.jpg" n="3"/>and mutual co-operation should predominate?</p>
   <p>We hear that the Reverend aimed his hostile arrows at The Star. Even if this is not true, it is our duty to mention, with deep sorrow, that our 'distinguished' clergyman should not transform the sacred pulpit of the church into a fort from where he can hurl his invectives against anyone he pleases. On the contrary, it is the duty of the priest "to love all in Christ" and follow His teachings and commandments, offering to the faithful at all times the blessings of brotherly and spiritual love.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
