<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1924-08-02">Aug. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Orthodox Diocese of Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0659</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0659.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-08-02">Aug. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK ORTHODOX DIOCESE OF CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1-On June 24, 1924, by an impressive ceremony in the Church of St. Constantine, the Right Reverend Bishop Philaretos, D.D., was installed as Bishop of the Diocese of Chicago according to the charter of the Greek Archdiocese of North and South America.</p>
   <p>Bishop Philaretos also has temporary jurisdiction over the Diocese of San Francisco, which he will govern until it installs its own bishop.</p>
   <p>The Greek Archdiocese of New York and the Dioceses of Boston, Chicago, and San Francisco form the Greek Orthodox Church of North and South America under the sovereignty of the Ecumenical Patriarchate of Constantinople.</p>
   <p>This sovereignty was transferred to the Holy Synod of Greece by the decree of 1908. In 1922 the decree was revoked, and it was recognized and officially acknowledged by the Church of Greece that the Greeks in America and elsewhere are again under the jurisdiction of the Ecumenical Patriarchate.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0660.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Under the jurisdiction of Bishop Philaretos are fifty-two priests and fifty-three Greek communities.</p>
   <p>Bishop Philaretos has already shown that he has administrative ability combined with zeal and diligence.</p>
   <p>He visits every week one or two of his communities, and he does everything in his power to inspire interest in religion and to elevate the moral tone of the faithful.</p>
   <p>He is especially interested in the church's music, in the discipline of the clergy, and in the appearance of his churches.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0661.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In order to have closer communication with his Diocese he has established an admirable system of correspondence and regularly sends out encyclical letters and instructions.</p>
   <p>The offices of the Diocese are temporarily in the church of St. Constantine, where he has so organized his office staff that it operates with great efficiency.</p>
   <p>In the same office is the primary spiritual court for the discipline of the clergy and the regulation of marital relations and divorces.</p>
   <p>The secondary court is the Synod, consisting of the Archbishop of New York and the bishops of the archdiocese.</p>
   <p>The highest ecclesiastical tribunal is the Court of Appeals in Constantinople.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0662.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Under the spiritual guidance of Bishop Philaretos is the Union of Greek Clergymen, with over fifty members, which renders valuable service to the Greek laity of this district.</p>
   <p>The financial needs of the Diocese are supplied by the ecclesiastical treasury, which is supported by the fees collected by priests for marriages and baptisms.</p>
   <p>The Diocese of Chicago and the Diocese of Boston have cooperated to support several students of the defunct Theological School of St. Athanasius in the continuation of their studies in the Episcopal Seminary of Nashotah, Wisconsin, of which Bishop Philaretos received his degree of Doctor of Divinity.</p>
   <p>The Bishop also cultivates friendly relations with the clergy of other denominations and does everything possible to elevate the standards of the Greek clergy in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0663.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>One of the Bishop's dreams is to establish a home for the Greek orphans of his Diocese.</p>
   <p>With Bishop Philaretos and his now proved ability to guide them the Greeks of Chicago will undoubtedly endow and support the Diocese in return for the spiritual service which it renders.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
