<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1909-05-05">May 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Pointed Paragraphs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0988</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0988.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1909-05-05">May 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">POINTED PARAGRAPHS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.- Our community problem will either be solved during the coming two weeks or all hope will be abandoned. As we see it, the North and South Side communities are for having a central committee to plan the course of events for both churches.</p>
   <p>If the two or three men who rule the community intend to fulfill their duty for the good of the entire Greek population of Chicago, we welcome them; if not, we ask them to resign before they start anything at all.</p>
   <p>All clubs, organizations and governments have a leader. The Greeks of Chicago have more trouble with their leaders than the Sultan of Turkey has over his entire dominion. We are being made a laughing stock because twenty or thirty Greeks, out of a population of 20,000 cannot agree on any one subject.</p>
   <p>We have written about this plenty of times, but the church question will really never be solved until we conquer our one great weakness - that of being jealous of our fellow countrymen.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0989.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We would have been happily united last year, if Mr. Argyros hadn't shot out his poisonous arrows at the meetings. He is the man who has caused strife and discontent ever since. We are trying again this year. Who knows whether we shall succeed or not?</p>
   <p>Many say it is too late to have a Panhellenic Union, but at least we can have a general meeting, occasionally, of all the communities in our city. We can decide the boundaries of the churches and settle all problems that may arise.</p>
   <p>The situation is in a very critical spot and we doubt if anything will be done about it, especially now that the hot weather has come upon us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
