<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-06-26">June 26, 1926</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">The Eucharistic Congress and the Vatican.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0610</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0610.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-06-26">June 26, 1926</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">THE EUCHARISTIC CONGRESS AND THE VATICAN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In my previous publication I have written the essentials and nonessentials of the Eucharistic Congress. I emphasized, the imperative duty of the Greek Church as well as all the Christian Churches to participate in the Eucharistic celebration as one Christian family.</p>
   <p>But the systematic and scientific propaganda of the Vatican, to dominate Christendom and become St. Paul's successor and Autocrat of all the Christians of the world, must be exposed for the sake of record. Future generation of Christendom will be astounded by the intrigue, and deliberate falsifications and prevarications of the Vatican.</p>
   <p>The prince of the Vatican, Cardinal Bonzano, on the first day of the celebration, read the Papal annuncio, with which the Pontiff of the Vatican asks the unification of all the Christian Churches, and the recognition of the Vatican's head as the only leader of Christendom, and consequently the absolute terrestrial representative of Jesus Christ.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0611.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Things might have been good and successful for the unification of Christendom, if the history of the Vatican was not besmeared with deception hypocricy, intrigue and falsification of the truth. A reporter of The Chicago Daily News under date of June 21st sent the following telegram:</p>
   <p>Pope Pius the XI on the occasion of the day, announces the ratification of the newly elected Greek Patriarch undoubtly, the object of the telegram was to creat an impression that a Greek Patriarch went to Rome to take the oath of allegiance to the Pope, and be blessed by the Pope.</p>
   <p>No Greek Patriarch in the history of Orthodoxy ever went to Rome to take an oath of allegiance to the Vatican. The intelligent, informed and sane mind knows, that the Greek Patriarch does not swear allegiance to the Vatican.</p>
   <p>The truth is, than an Armenian monk named Mogagad of the Armenian Benedicts of Antioch, went to Rome to receive the blessing of the Pope.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0612.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Such falsifications are only small incidents in the past and present history of the Vatican, which is beclouded by untruths, intrigues and non-Christian methods and activities.</p>
   <p>If the Pope in Rome was willing and ready to alter the present system, and stop advocating the perpetuation of monarchies, and retilize the colossal wealth of Catholicism for educational and philanthropic purposes, the unification of the Christian Religion would be realized in a very short time.</p>
   <p>N. Salopoulos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
