<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1926-12-25">Dec. 25, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Birth of Christ.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0584</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0584.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-12-25">Dec. 25, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE BIRTH OF CHRIST.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new born babe in the manger. A star shining in the East. A few shepherd had seen it hover over the stable, were led thither to wonder, then worship.</p>
   <p>Three wise men guided across deserts by another pointing straight to Bethlehem, came and brought gifts of gold. A primitive setting, the step-father, a carpenter; the mother, a woman of the people, the shepherds, simple and unlearned folk; the cradle a manger where the beasts of burden ate: the mother's couch, the straw on which the beasts slept.</p>
   <p>But Kings came also. Robes of royalty mingled with the skins of the herdsmen, men of high degree and those of low, met at the same place in the stable at Bethlehem, and knelt at the same lowly shrine.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0585.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was democratic. It was a leveler of many traditions that had pictured the coming of a conqueror, a man who would lead tens of thousands of charioteers and swordsmen to the subjugation of a world, beneath the feet of those chosen to rule that world. It was a rude awakening from dreams of broadened realms, increased power, a mightier throne, and power in the destiny of the human race at the beck of one.</p>
   <p>The world was weary of the Roman Legions traversing up and down the world, and laying other people under tribute to the Imperator. It had sickened of free men made slaves for the pleasure of their victors. It was nauseated with the sight of roped women and men following the chariots of Caesars, Pompeys and Syllas, of Spartacus fighting to the death the gladiator, his own Kin, for a Nero, or a Domitian, to smile.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0586.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The world felt ashamed, that in the capital of this great empire the gold statue of the horse of Caligula, had incense burned before it. The incense did not typify faith, but a display of religion. The world was satiated with the bestiality of gorged Rome, and the sophistries of the Greek philosophers. No setting for the emergence into a better state could have been more wisely chosen by the Creator. The manger, the stable, the bewilderment of Joseph and the helplessness of Mary, in a trying situation, constituted a negation of all that Rome then stood for. The might of Rome, built upon the purely physical, fell, and an edifice of the spiritual was built that day. The man born in the manger won the kingship over all Kings.</p>
   <p>No wonder that Herod, the then Roman governor, quaked in his sandals and felt the earth tremble. No wonder he sought the death of this infant. Herod saw the coming of the cross as a substition for the Roman standard.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0587.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The might of everything material, fell, in the past and will fall in the future, if it is not upheld by spiritual faith and culture. The Greeks of this country owing to their feverish desire to acquire the almighty dollar, due to keen competition, forget divine duty towards themselves and others so that spiritual development is neglected for the sake of material gain. In Building big and beautiful Churches, and decorating them with golden Irons will not give us spiritual culture, and going to Churches, to be seen by others, will not alter the fact. The giving of money for public charity, for the sake of publicity will not make us Christians. Participating in celebrations of rituals and pompous ceremonies will not give us a particle of spiritual advancement. We attempt to deceive others, and others deceive us. We play a game of hide and seek.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0588.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Let us be true to ourselves. Let us, at least, follow our progenitors in sincerity and integrity. The ancient Greeks although not knowing the real God of the world and being idolaters, as Socrates in his apology to the Judges called them, were nevertheless sincere in the belief of the twelve Olympian Gods.</p>
   <p>The Saviour of the world brought light instead of darkness; He brought truth instead of illusion. Let us follow the star of truth in spite of where it may lead us. The teachings of Christ not only will help us to acquire spiritual wealth but will also help us to acquire material wealth through being sincere with ourselves and others. In our daily struggles, in our business, in our domestic affairs, and in everything, if we are true to ourselves, others will soon know it and esteem us accordingly.</p>
   <p>Christmas stands for Truth, Love, Charity and Joy. Let us follow the Star of Bethlehem.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
