<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-06-01">June 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Ravens' Invasion - B Is the Vatican a Christian Institution?</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0434</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0434.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1929-06-01">June 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">RAVENS' INVASION - B IS THE VATICAN A CHRISTIAN INSTITUTION?</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In our previous publication we have written of the descent of the Vatican birds of prey upon Greece. They came under the instruction of the Pontiff, disguised as Greek priests, and began to spread their heinous propaganda. These Jesuits and Ounites are a real menace to the Greek race. Not only the government of Greece, but Greek people the world over, must take drastic measures to defend themselves from the rapaciousness of these carnivorous birds of the Vatican.</p>
   <p>These articles are written for the Greeks of America, who must stand united and ready to defend the religion of their race. As you are aware, that many efforts of unseen powers to undermine the structure of our religion in America have been made, you are counselled to be on your guard when approached by these so called Greek Catholics. Our Mother church has nothing to do with these pseudo-Greeks, who call themselves Greek Catholics.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0435.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Roman Church as a Christian institution could have been and could be yet a great factor in Christianity, if she were democratic, and worked, in cooperation with the other Christian faiths for the welfare and peace of mankind and upon the principles of Christianity, as taught by Jesus Christ.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately the Vatican inherited all the vices and traditions of the Roman Empire and being unable to utilize the Roman Legions, the Vatican sent out the Jesuits and its clergy, to mentally and physically subjugate the human race. Is the Vatican a Christian institution? Judge for yourself.</p>
   <p>The Pontiff of Rome, who maintains that he is the only representative of Christ upon earth, aspires to Imperial rights, political predominance over all Catholic countries, and wants to impose his will upon non-Catholics with un-christian methods.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0436.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>How can he represent Christ, who was democratic, who walked with the people, and who decried the rogues of religion, the hypocrites and the Pharisees?</p>
   <p>The Pope, after signing a treaty with Mussolini and deciding to visit various Italian cities, made up a private train, worth a million dollars, equipped with up to date luxurious extravagant equipment and bearing the Imperial emblems. What a difference between the modesty and meekness of Christ, riding a donkey, and the arrogance, boastfulness and Mega Lomania of his representative, traveling in a private train with the pomp and display that no world master or emperor had ever dreamed of in past history. Thus the Vatican endeavors to build its power upon the illiteracy and fanaticism of the common people, and gradually has become the most mysterious organization in the world.</p>
   <p>Is the Vatican a Christian institution? Is the Pope the representative of Christ? The answer is for you to find, after you weigh the evidence impartially.</p>
   <p>The time will come when the Catholic people themselves will uproot this mysterious organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
