<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-07-30">July 30, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Criminal Silence of the Greek Ambassador and the Consecration of Bishops at San Francisco.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0552</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0552.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-07-30">July 30, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE CRIMINAL SILENCE OF THE GREEK AMBASSADOR AND THE CONSECRATION OF BISHOPS AT SAN FRANCISCO.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.. In one of our former articles we wrote about the unjustifiable silence maintained by Ambassador Simopoulos with reference to the decision of the Greek Government in regard to our ecclesiastical matters; and we characterized this silence as a gesture of disdain. This characterization of ours was very mild in view of the effect of silence on so important a problem as that of our church disunity. Now, though the rumor of the impending consecration of another bishop at San Francisco has been confirmed - which, of course, will increase the disunity and widen the breach in American Hellenism - the ambassador persists in his silence, a silence which can no longer be called disdainful but is rather to be termed criminal.</p>
   <p>It is an indisputable fact that the Greek Government has revised its decision, which would have revolutionized the present state of affairs, and according to the Greek newspapers and the United Press the Minister of the Church and of <pb facs="5422062_5_0553.jpg" n="2"/>Education at Athens has determined to dispatch a legate from the Holy Synod of Greece to reorganize the paralyzed Greek Church in America under the rule of bishops. Such was the news received by telegram from Athens about a month ago and subsequently confirmed by the Athenian Press. Thus the report is not a rumor but is based on facts of which Mr. Simopoulos has complete knowledge. We have therefore repeatedly invited Mr. Simopoulos to make an announcement by any method which he chooses to employ, orally or through the newspapers, to the Hellenism of America, not to satisfy our curiosity but to enlighten us and most important of all, to anticipate the impending consecration at San Francisco which will increase the dissension in the Church.</p>
   <p>The archbishops themselves fail to perceive how detrimental their mere presence in America is to Church unity, and that the fact that they are here is the cause of all the dissension in the Church, for the "paralysis of the churches in America," to quote the Greek Minister of the Church and Education. And yet in the face of all this the indifferent ambassador maintains his silence, thereby promoting church disunity, and in consequence his silence must be termed criminal silence.</p>
   <p>It should not be difficult for Mr. Simopoulos simply to announce that the Greek <pb facs="5422062_5_0554.jpg" n="3"/>Government has taken our church matters under consideration and will hand its decision to him later. After all, this latest consecration of bishops at San Francisco is going to make the problem more complicated, and his silence will be more difficult to maintain.</p>
   <p>Now it is indisputable that if the consecration of Messrs. Philaretos and Alexopoulos takes place in spite of the protests of the majority of the Greeks in America and even of the National Herald - this will be due principally to the fact that the Government of Greece pays no attention to these protests. And as long as the Greek Government is supposed to be taking our church problems under consideration and is contemplating the dispatch of a Synodical legate to America, we are impelled to ask Mr. Simopoulos whether the impending consecration at San Francisco has the Greek Government's approval. If the Greek Government has given its approval, we should naturally like to know how it was possible to obtain such approval when Mr. Simopoulos well knows that the Government is still studying our church problem and has not made any definite decision.</p>
   <p>In view of all these considerations it certainly is the duty of Mr. Simopoulos to break his criminal silence, which has become an embarrassment to American Hellenism. We are sure that the evil would be averted if the ambassador would <pb facs="5422062_5_0555.jpg" n="4"/>only speak. We assure him that this silence, if he persists in it, will be criminal silence.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
