<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-01-21">Jan. 21, 1932</date>, p. 2
<title level="a">Our Churches</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0158</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0158.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-01-21">Jan. 21, 1932</date>, p. 2
<title level="a">OUR CHURCHES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We journalists are making an appeal to the people of the Greek Community of Chicago, to the committee hands of the various churchs and even to the highest executive Archishop Athengoras, to save the two churches which are in peril of closing. The psychology of our countrymen we know very well once they are aroused they will do all in their power to save these two establishments. After these appeals, we are sure the Greek people will gather together hold an ecclesiastical meeting, and solve the problem. The Greek Press is looking forward to this.</p>
   <p>We are not trying to prove that we are saintly people nor is it in our right to dictate or map out a program for the Hellenism of Chicago concerning this matter. We are also taking into consideration the great economic crisis we are now going through. We wrote what we wrote because what is needed can be clearly seen. We want to make the way easy for the two churches to open the road for them, enlist the help of all Greeks.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0159.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Whatever His Holiness, Archbishop Athenagores does no matter how little, will be a great blessing. We have refrained from mentioning the names of the two churches because it would be adding an insult to injury- so to speak. The only reason we have made this situation public is because the churches are being confronted with a problem too big to cope with alone.</p>
   <p>We don't won't this matter to be taken lightly. If $85,000 are not forthcoming immediately, the two Greek Orthodox Churches will go into the hands of receivers. A meeting was called last week and new officers of the churches were elected. We hope they are capable. They have made a good beginning so our faith is in them to save the buildings.</p>
   <p>You cannot afford to ignore this plan because every one of you will be directly or indirectly affected by what happens. The Greek Orthodox religion is at stake. We must have it at any cost.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
