<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1933-09-30">Sept. 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago's Social Column</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0073</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0073.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos-Progress</title>,
<date when="1933-09-30">Sept. 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO'S SOCIAL COLUMN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The decision of the Diocese or Archdiocese to exclude the magnificent Church of St. Varilios from being the place of the coming convention of clergy and laity very much chagrined the parishioners. The parishioners of this church think, and very rightly too, that the location of the church and the accommodations and the comforts found in it are unequalled by any other Greek church of Chicago, and it is more convenient than any other for the delegates of the convention, on account of its proximity to the Greeks of the West Side.</p>
   <p>But if the Church in general ignored this magnificent edifice for its convention, the Arcadians, as Mr. Kyriakopoulos writes, showed a practical spirit and decided to hold the convention of the Pan-Arcadians there because of the many conveniences which St. Varilios's provides. The Arcadians are to be praised for their choice.</p>
   <p>On another page of this issue we publish a splendid and enlightening article <pb facs="5422062_5_0074.jpg" n="2"/>about the education of the Greeks, not only of the youngsters but also of the adults.</p>
   <p>We believe that the activities of our various organizations could be made more beneficial and enlightening if they tried by lectures and other instruction to continue the education of the grownups, so keeping the fire burning for education and the development of the adult Greek immigrant.</p>
   <p>We intend to write about various foolish and smart exploiters who are intruding in churches and in other organizations to show off, to exploit, or to graft, and we shall be merciless with them.</p>
   <p>You may be sure that in the columns of Proodos you will learn all about the shameful conduct of those who trade in everything held holy and sacred among Greeks--about all who have been involved or are now messing around in the churches and their treasuries.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0075.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The extortioners who plunder the dead, who exact fares for crossing the styx, and the various exploiters of the public, such as buyers of churches at auction after bankruptcy proceedings, and all who, according to our information, participate in any social or community racket will be reported through these columns as news of interest to the public. All these plundering gangs who prey on Greek organizations must be uncovered and exposed so that everybody may know who is who.</p>
   <p>Now, when people are suffering, those lightheaded fools ought to try to take care of the poor and destitute instead of inventing ways to extort money from the public.</p>
   <p>Some time ago Mr. Constantine Paleologos Mamonas tried to organize a committee for the poor in the Logan Square Ahepa chapter, to be incorporated with other similar organizations under the name United Greek Charities of Chicago. When such an organization is an absolute necessity to help poor starving Greeks, these various societies care only for the election of their foolish and grafting officials! What have they to say?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
