<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-10-13">October 13, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Decay of the Religious Sentiment.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-10-13">October 13, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE DECAY OF THE RELIGIOUS SENTIMENT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1.- The impious events that were staged at the former Masonic Temple at which place by an election the church was given the name of St. Andrews, prove that the Rodostolian church not only from the beginning of its career split the Greek people of America in two, and continues to keep them divided, but, also, by its actions has laid low religious sentiment and humiliated the Greek Church.</p>
   <p>It could not have done otherwise since, from the very beginning, it had deceived its followers.</p>
   <p>1) Because Meletios Metaxakis first appeared as a Metropolitan Bishop of Athens and, as such, had the communities and priests follow him. Later on, he detached them from the Patriarchate of Constantinople when he was elected as Patriarch.</p>
   <p>2) The Archbishops and Bishops were declaring that they were dependent on the Patriarchate of Constantinople, in order to draw from it a moral sanction where in reality, they were an independent and self-administered Church, with no relations whatsoever with the Patriarchate.</p>
   <p>3) They are deceiving the Greek government by letting it believe that the Greeks of America are following them as a whole, while they actually are divided.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0476.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>4) They became the cause of severance of bonds between Greece and the Hellenism of America. There thus, became alienated, ecclesiastically, 500,000 Greeks by establishing, without reason, an independent church alien to the Greek Nation and serving, absolutely, no National useful purpose.</p>
   <p>5) They have withdrawn from the traditional ecclesiastical authorities of the Greek-Orthodox Church and endorsed the Catholic system by abolishing communities and absorbing their property which according to their constitution would go into the possession of the Bishop, via the churches of St. Basil and St. Andrew.</p>
   <p>6) They held a liturgy and intercommunication with dignitaries of other religions despite the canons of the Greek Orthodox Church.</p>
   <p>7) They departed systematically from the formality of the church by performing marriages according to the Protestant ritual.</p>
   <p>8) They abolished by systematic activity the Greek language from holy rites, substituting English, performing the sacraments in English, and of late translating the holy Mass into English in order to introduce it in our churches.</p>
   <p>Of all this we have indisputable proof, on the other hand, their course and objectives have begun to be public knowledge.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0477.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And now we ask you:</p>
   <p>- What your ecclesiastical system represents?</p>
   <p>- Is your church Greek?</p>
   <p>- Do you have any relations with the Church of Greece?</p>
   <p>- Are you dependent upon the Patriarchate of Constantinople?</p>
   <p>- To what church are you responsible?</p>
   <p>All these questions you are in duty bound to answer for the Greeks of America and determine where do you stand, because even your followers do not know your actual footing. They believe that you are dependent upon the Ecumenical Patriarchate while, in reality, you have nothing to do with it. The most to be regretted is that you have no relation, whatever, with the Greeks of America because your Church is Alien to them.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
