<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-02-16">Feb. 16, 1933</date><title level="a">Weekly Chats</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Nick John Matsoukas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-02-16">Feb. 16, 1933</date><title level="a">WEEKLY CHATS</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Nick John Matsoukas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4.- On the shadow of the Chicago loop skyscrapers, just a stone's throw from Goddess Demeter's super-imposed throne on La Salle Street, in the heart of Greek town, on the West side, rises a small Church spire, anachronous to the spirit of the Church edifice, but sufficiently Christian to embody all the human qualities of early Christiandom, the days when people actually practiced Christianity and Church leaders were just mere servants for the good of the sheepfold.</p>
   <p>At some time or other you all have visited the Church of the Holy Trinity. Chicago Greeks may come and Chicago Greeks may go. They may rise and they may fall. They may condemn and they may praise; but their debt to that little Church on the near West Side will never be repaid.</p>
   <p>The Church of the Holy Trinity is the mother Church of Chicago Greeks. It is the Church of the early settlers. The first home for Chicago's Greek Orthodoxy.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0098.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Immaterially how high brow our North siders get to be, with the coming of the years, the Church of the West side will still forecast its shadow and read their fingerprints. We all came from there.</p>
   <p>Its school, "Socrates", thought many of us who, today, try to assert ourselves within the paralyzed tissues of the local Greek social structure.</p>
   <p>Last Sunday this Church gave a dance. The purpose was to raise money for payment of debts. Their Church stands today in a better financial position than any other Greek Church in this city. But some debts must be paid. It seems that jealousy of other directors, not all, but primarily those of the North Side Community, made it a point to be absent in a body.</p>
   <p>These gentlemen have, for some reason or other, taken it upon themselves to convince their meagre selves that they are somebodies and they do not have to attend any of the functions of the "low down West Siders."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0099.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Furthermore, they have been flattered by various types of exploiting individuals that they are progressive and so, they attend special functions at the Church of Annunciation with tuxedos.</p>
   <p>Poor Emily Post; and she spent a lifetime writing a book of etiquette. Poor style experts; your dictates do not include these "Giants."</p>
   <p>Gentlemen, you may feel the way you do. You might hope and cherish the notion that someday the Bishop will close the other churches so that you may flourish and pay the debts. Before you will accomplish any of your hopes and aspirations you should prove yourselves worthy Greeks and good Christians. You should attempt to help your brother Greeks. In body you should attend the functions of other Churches. Instead you were absent in body. Do you expect then the younger generation to follow any respectable road? They, too, know the Greek proverb, "To psari apo to kefali vromai". ("The Fish smells from the head.")</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0100.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Furthermore, they have been flattered by various types of exploiting individuals that they are progressive and so, they attend special functions at the Church of Annunciation with tuxedos.</p>
   <p>Poor Emily Post; and she spent a lifetime writing a book of etiquette. Poor style experts; your dictates do not include these "Giants."</p>
   <p>Gentlemen, you may feel the way you do. You might hope and cherish the notion that someday the Bishop will close the other churches so that you may flourish and pay the debts. Before you will accomplish any of your hopes and aspirations you should prove yourselves worthy Greeks and good Christians. You should attempt to help your brother Greeks. In body you should attend the functions of other Churches. Instead you were absent in body. Do you expect then the younger generation to follow any respectable road? They, too, know the Greek proverb, "To psari apo to kefali vromai". ("The Fish smells from the head.")</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
