<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-11-14">Nov. 14, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Plight of the Rodostclian Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0462</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0462.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-11-14">Nov. 14, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE PLIGHT OF THE RODOSTCLIAN CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1 --- We have dealt repeatedly with the case of the pastor of St. Basil's Church and in continuing to do so, we wish to state that we are not preoccupied with the dismissal of the Reverend Paschalakis from his office. This question by itself is the private concern of the Reverend Mr. Paschalakis, his Bishop, and the church committee, and we are not interested in the private affairs of a Philaretos-owned church nor in the committee which Philaretos has appointed.</p>
   <p>Our interest as well as that of the public must be, primarily, for the communal churches which belong to all and are the property of the Greek people of America.</p>
   <p>The churches controlled by the Bishop and the Rodostolian ecclesiastical regime, as must by now be understood, have nothing to do with the Hellenism of America. They are organizations foreign to our Hellenism, having gained entrance among us with one main purpose in view, namely, <pb facs="5422062_5_0463.jpg" n="2"/>to alienate us from our ancestral habits and customs. That is why the priests who adhere to the Rodostolian regime are trying to introduce the English language into their churches and to perform marriages according to the Protestant ritual.</p>
   <p>We have dealt, however, with this case of the pastor's dismissal in order to show how this church is administered, what the relations of priests and bishops are, and how they suspect one another and to show to those who do not know the Rodostolian regime that it was created only for scandals and to keep the Greeks of America divided.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
