<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-12-26">Dec. 26, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Transfer of the Annunciation Church</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. John Volicos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0163</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0163.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-12-26">Dec. 26, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE TRANSFER OF THE ANNUNCIATION CHURCH</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. John Volicos</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.- In my previous article I wrote about the establishment of the first Greek church in Chicago, the Annunciation.</p>
   <p>This church building was used as a temporary meeting place. Neither the building nor its location was suitable for a temple of God. Because of the urgent need the church was established,with the thought in mind, that it should be transfered at the first opportunity to a better building and location.</p>
   <p>The transfer took place at the close of the Century of Progress and during a period of depression which shook the foundation of many a business house in Chicago. All nationalities in Chicago felt the adverse conditions and most of them applied for relief. The Greeks were an exception. I can verify this statement. The American press commented on the fact that not a single Greek or a single Greek family had asked for help.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0164.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In spite of the devastating effects of the depression, they managed, through mutual assistance to weather the storm.</p>
   <p>The prominent Greeks of the Lycurgus Society, after a general consultation of all the Greeks, transfered their church to a beautiful hall of the Masonic Lodge at Kinzie and Clark Streets, paying $50 per month rent.</p>
   <p>A great deal of money was required for the establishment of the new church as well as for a substantial salary for the priest because of his large family. The Lycurgus Society, on my initiative, decided to give the first Greek theatrical performance titled, "Babylonia." When circulars of the forthcoming comedy were distributed, the Greeks flocked to Turner Hall, notwithstanding their financial stress. The proceeds were more than expected. The money having been raised, the decoration of the church was completed, icons, a huge chandelier, seats, linoleum and other necessary ecclesiastical furnishings were bought, and the hall was ready to be consecrated for church services.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0165.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The appointed committee of the Lycurgus Society headed by the Rev. Fiampolis, invited the Russian Archbishop to officiate at the dedication. The Archbishop, accompanied by his archdeacon and the Rev. Vrettas, Pastor of the Slavs, was received by the Greek priest and the committee at the new church, 320 Kinzie Street. The liturgy, conducted jointly by the Russian and the Greek clergy, was deeply affecting. Two Greeks and two Russians sang alternately the holy hymns.</p>
   <p>After the ligurgy, Archbishop Antonius, delivered in Russian, translated by Rev. Vrettas into Greek, a eulogy for the Greeks of Chicago. He said that as true sons of the Mother Greek church they should never fail to perpetuate her traditions. He congratulated the Greeks in general as true Apostles of Christ's church.</p>
   <p>A symposium took place afterwards, in which many participated. The Archbishop with his assistants, discovered before departing that the Greeks harbored no ill will towards the Russian Church because of the attempts of the Russians to proselyte the Greeks while they were attending the Russian Church.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0166.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It would be a great mistake not to mention the good work done by our Greek ladies. Of course there were not many, but nevertheless they were ready and willing to contribute their services to the welfare of the community. Some of the names I recall are: Mrs. A. Manousos, Mrs. John Palamaris, Mrs. Spyros Poulis, Mrs. Kerkiraios, Mrs. N. Kavouras, Mrs. N. Michalopoulos, Mrs. Koumoundouros, Mrs. C. Michalistis, Mrs. Thomas, Mrs. Brown, Mrs. Mitchell, Mrs. James Mazarakos, and Mrs. Poriotis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
