<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1916-05-13">May 13, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">St. Constantine Church</title><title level="a" type="sub">Amazing Progress of This Church's Parish</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0846</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0846.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-05-13">May 13, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">ST. CONSTANTINE CHURCH</title><title level="a" type="sub">Amazing Progress of This Church's Parish</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Conclusive evidence of the patriotism and religious spirit of the Greek people can be found in the many Greek Orthodox Churches in America. This spirit has always been strong in the Greek race, whether it has been free, enslaved, or, as now, as immigrants to this country.</p>
   <p>When the Greek people were free and powerful, they built the famous Saint Sofia and thousands of other Byzantine churches and monasteries.</p>
   <p>The enslaved Greeks "fought ferociously and died gallantly," according to the words of a demotic song--"for the sacred faith of Christ, and the freedom of the fatherland."</p>
   <p>The Greek immigrants built over one hundred churches in a period of fifteen years. One of these churches is the South Side Church of <pb facs="5422062_5_0847.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago, Saint Constantine. In a short time this church will be completely paid for, and will stand as a beautiful tribute to orthodoxy and the patriotism of the Greek immigrants.</p>
   <p>Thousands of dollars are spent, and they all come from the pennies contributed by God-fearing Hellenes. But these pennies are not spent carelessly or thoughtlessly;--and today St. Constantine supports a Greek school accomodating one hundred Greek children.</p>
   <p>We do not intend to give a financial report, because that can always be obtained from the board of trustees. Today we take this opportunity to congratulate the officials of the Church, because we consider it our duty to do so. They repaid $3,325 to various kind persons who had lent money to the Church a few years ago. Besides that they reduced the Church's debt to fifteen thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>The board has justified the faith and trust the people placed in them in regards to the financial matters of the Church. This was shown during <pb facs="5422062_5_0848.jpg" n="3"/>the Easter week services, when the collections amounted to nine hundred dollars more than the sum collected last year. The names of these trustees, which belong on a roll of honor, are: John Papanastasiou, president; Theodore Sperison, vice-president, Athan. Balis, treasurer; Michael Petropoulos, secretary; and S. Rekas, N. Nomicos, N. Karafotias, Peter Ladas, N. Bekinis, P. Vasilopoulos,.....</p>
   <p>We have been informed that the Church is about to purchase a cemetery, to be used exclusively for Greek people. If this is done, the Church will have made an outstanding contribution to the Greek community of Chicago. Not only are the church officers deserving of thanks and plaudits; but the patriotic parishioners are also, as they are the real heroes of the day. They made these achievements possible, by giving their wholehearted support; and what is even more important, they gave their hard-earned nickels and dimes to make this the finest church in Chicago.</p>
   <p>However, it would be a serious mistake if we were to omit the name of the respected priest of the Church--Reverend Theodore Prousianos. Much of <pb facs="5422062_5_0849.jpg" n="4"/>the credit must be given to him, because he worked zealously and earnestly for the progress of his parish.</p>
   <p>The school of the parish is well-conducted and its standards are kept very high. It is under the direction of Mr. P. Demopoulos, who is fully capable of fulfilling such a responsible task.</p>
   <p>This is the condition of St. Constantine Church. We honestly feel that it is the outstanding Greek parish in Chicago. We hope that the good work will continue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
