<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-01-20">Jan. 20, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Official Telegram from the Ecumenical Patriarchate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0734</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0734.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-01-20">Jan. 20, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">OFFICIAL TELEGRAM FROM THE ECUMENICAL PATRIARCHATE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.-2- Protocol number 1356</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois</p>
   <p>Jan. 11, 1923.</p>
   <p>Dear Mr. Editor:</p>
   <p>I have the nonor to request that you will publish in your esteemed newspaper a communication from the Most Reverend Ecumenical Patriarch of Constantinople. With my respects and many thanks,</p>
   <p>The Consul General</p>
   <p>Vasilios Mammonas.</p>
   <p>"To my great sorrow I have been informed that a movement is in progress which aims to establish an independent Church. Our paternal responsibility impels us to transmit the following advice from the council of the Patriarchate, trusting that those of the clergy and of the laity who feel that they are members of the Holy Orthodox Church will comply with our request. An independent Church, according to the holy canons may be established if it is composed of all the Orthodox Christians who live in America regardless of language and nationality. Since we take it for granted that to-day it is impossible to establish an independent Orthodox Church, any movement in this direction is by us prohibited. The offense <pb facs="5422062_5_0735.jpg" n="2"/>of which those persons will be guilty who shall attempt to found an independent Church will be the same which resulted in the condemnation and the excommunication of the Bulgarians from the Orthodox Church. We warn all the children of the Orthodox Church that the condemnation of those of the clergy and the laity who support this movement is inevitable.</p>
   <p>For this reason we admonish all whom it may concern to come to their senses, considering the wrong which they are committing against themselves and against the Church."</p>
   <p>Patriarch Meletios.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
