<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-10-10">Oct. 10, 1928</date><title level="a">You Are the Dividers of Greek Nationalism</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0481</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0481.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-10-10">Oct. 10, 1928</date><title level="a">YOU ARE THE DIVIDERS OF GREEK NATIONALISM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- The Ecclesiastical indecencies that transpired in Lowell, Mass., last Sunday, with Vasilios as the hero, and the ridiculing of the religion by the four hierarchs of the Rodostolian church in Chicago, prove the decay and humiliation of the religion of the Greeks of America. Wholly responsible for this condition are the Bishops, Archbishops and the Metropolitan Bishops, who undertook to tend the flock of Hellenism in America and promote religious sentiment.</p>
   <p>And we consider the Rodostolic came equally as responsible as that of Vasilios, because we have never supported the latter. We have the right however, to ask the Rev. Alexander and his associates what were the causes of Vasilios coming to America and their stay here till now? And if they have not the courage to answer, we reply that the seasons were the same as those of their Bishops, namely, purely partisan in essence.</p>
   <p>The Venizelist camp repudiated the Archbishops of America and the Bishops of Boston, Chicago and San Francisco, and, on the other hand, the Royalist camp declared Vasilios Metropolitan Bishop of America and Canada.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0482.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dividers both! And the division will continue. The animosity between the Greeks will continue and the disgrace of religion will go on so long as the causes remain active.</p>
   <p>What else do they, the Rodostolic came and that of Vasilios, represent in America but division?</p>
   <p>But even if the ones about Rodostolou who bears the title Archbishop of every Greek in America, claim that they are recognized by the Patriarchate and the Holy Synod of Greece, and, therefore, are the legitimate ones, every one has the right to ask the following question: Of what benefit are your recognition and legitimacy, and the support from the Ambassador and the Consuls, insofar as you have failed, for so many years, now to bring about harmony in our Ecclesiastical matters In reality you are making things worse from year to year.</p>
   <p>And just for this reason, supporters of Rodostolou must be considered as bearing greater responsibilities, and therefore being the only persons responsible for the situation of Ecclesiastical division. Because in spite of the recognition and moral support given by the Patriarchate and</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0483.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>the official representatives of the Greek government, to the Rodostolians, not only have they failed to establish harmony in the congregation, and restore order in the church, but, on the contrary, they are becoming the cause of division and decline of religious spirit in the Greeks of America.</p>
   <p>It is high time to realize that you have shown complete incompetency in the authority you have assumed, and that you are not worthy of any further support from those who placed you in charge over the Greek communities of America and that so long as you remain here there is no hope whatever in uniting the Greeks. On the contrary, you are going to keep them divided, because you were the original dividers and you are going to always remain as such.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
