<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-07-24">July 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The New Star of Education</title><title level="a" type="sub">Peter Lambros Speaks in Protestant Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0886</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0886.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-07-24">July 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW STAR OF EDUCATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Peter Lambros Speaks in Protestant Church</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Saloniki was the first Greek newspaper to expose the dirty propaganda being preached and spread by certain moronic individuals led by Mr. Papadopoulos of Chicago. Do not think that the Saloniki is the only paper striving to enlighten the Greek community of Chicago. Oh, no! Aside from Mr. Papadopoulos, who is the editor of the Elpis, we have Mr. Peter S. Lambros, editor of the Star. Mr. Lambros has--by his own confession--spoken on religious subjects in a Protestant church. We know that he is working in harmony with his cothinker, Mr. Papadopoulos, and has become his champion.</p>
   <p>The same Peter Lambros, who preaches religion in Oak Park, was also the organizer and leader of the Hellenic Women's Club which, until it disbanded, held its meetings at Hull House. The ladies came to these meetings, drank tea, and heard Mr. Lambros speak, until they began to understand his intentions.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0887.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then they all resigned from the Club. We wish to congratulate Mr. Lambros, for giving the Greeks of Chicago an opportunity to see him in his true colors, and to understand the reason for his silence concerning all subjects relating to this wave of propaganda. In the editorial columns of his newspaper he has not struck one blow in behalf of his religion, but, more significant than that, he has struck no blow against the cheap propagandists led by Papadopoulos. It is obvious that "Bishop" Papadopoulos is the pal of "orator" Peter Lambros. The Greeks of America have got your number, Mr. Lambros! And the people of Chicago, due to the efforts of the Saloniki, are fully aware of the facts; and are taking steps to drive out the undesirable element that has pushed its way into the Greek community.</p>
   <p>Mr. A. Mouzakeotis and Nicholas Govostis, both respected citizens, took the first drastic steps towards showing these propagandists what the Greek community thinks of them and their beliefs; by publicly burning over five hundred of their leaflets and tracts on the corner of Halsted and Harrison Streets. No decent Greek would <pb facs="5422062_5_0888.jpg" n="3"/>even touch those propagandistic tracts with their hands, especially, now, that they know that the tracts have been condemned by the Greek Church. The burning was witnessed and cheered by over five hundred Greeks, including Mr. Petropoulos, representative of the National Herald. This paper has eagerly taken measures to inform the Greeks of the entire United States that there is a subversive element at large among them. As long as the Greek press keeps the people informed by printing the true facts, let the champions of this propaganda--namely, Lambros and Papadopoulos--make as many speeches as they may desire.</p>
   <p>Forward,Greeks! Rid your ranks of these unpatriotic, irreligious, immoral quacks who seek to turn us from our beautiful, uplifting, and basic religion.</p>
   <p>Forward, Greeks! Prove that our Holy Orthodox religion is above all others since it is the mother religion from which all others sprang. Does any religious school deny the fact that the Bible was originally written in Greek, and then <pb facs="5422062_5_0889.jpg" n="4"/>translated into the other tongues? Does any group of students, or religious scholars and research workers, find any Church, other than the Orthodox, to be the mother of all Christian Churches?</p>
   <p>Therefore the Greeks, who have been baptized in that Church, should be proud of that fact. When a Papadopoulos or a Lambros presents himself and desires, by his eloquent speeches and his subversive methods, to cast aspersions upon the Orthodox religion, the Greeks will know how to handle him in the future.</p>
   <p>The Greeks of Chicago are kept well informed of these activities by the Saloniki, which will always be on the side of decency and honor. The Saloniki is also striving to bring about a unification of the three churches in Chicago, in order that they may present a united front against the gangrenous growth. But this cannot be accomplished as long as the two above mentioned gentlemen are allowed to distribute their so-called newspapers to the Greek public. The curious part of it is that neither paper charges a subscription fee --both are given away on <pb facs="5422062_5_0890.jpg" n="5"/>street corners. Can it be that these editors are journalistic philanthropists, or are they using the papers as organs for their propaganda? "Something is wrong in the State of Denmark." Send back their dirty sheets, and let them know in what estimation the community holds them and their propaganda.</p>
   <p>We give fair warning to all those individuals taking active part in this business, that in the future we shall not be so kind in either our verbal or physical treatment of them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
