<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-08-17">Aug. 17, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A Judgment</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0081</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0081.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-08-17">Aug. 17, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A JUDGMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is obvious that this modern age is a period of disagreement and of petty bickering; in fact, it has all the characteristics of a discontented, fear-ridden society....This modern spirit is well exemplified in the condition of the Greek churches of Chicago: it is doubtful if they have taken one step forward in the forty years that have passed since the opening of the first Greek church in Chicago.</p>
   <p>We have multiplied in numbers and have organized an active social life; but in matters requiring co-operation or unity we have retrogressed rather than progressed. If, in the past, we could not display any such achievements as new, beautiful church buildings, we could at least be proud of our zeal and enthusiasm in coping with all our social problems. Today, it seems that our carefully-built social structure is doomed to destruction. Why? Because no one has injected a creative or progressive element into it. Meaningless structures have been <pb facs="5422062_5_0082.jpg" n="2"/>erected to satisfy our love for glory of form. But where is the spirit of our social structure?</p>
   <p>We still remain little men with a thin veneer of civilization and culture. A characteristic of little men is that they do not see any further than their noses, and so they are incapable of creating things which pulsate with life, or that adequately represent the spirit of their group. In other words, we Greeks of Chicago are not being true to our heritage. We number at least fifty thousand, and yet our potential strength has never been used.</p>
   <p>If we keep on this downward path, it is to be feared that all too soon our inglorious epitaph will be written. The world and our people will not have been benefited by our existence and our accomplishments.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
