<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Year Book of St. Constantine Church and Korais School</title>,
<date when="1936">1936</date>, p. 53.
<title level="a">Historical Pages of the Community of St. Constantine and St. Helen. 1st. the First Greeks in America.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1396</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1396.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>YEAR BOOK OF ST. CONSTANTINE CHURCH AND KORAIS SCHOOL</title>,
<date when="1936">1936</date>, p. 53.
<title level="a">Historical Pages of the Community of St. Constantine and St. Helen. 1st. The First Greeks in America.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The present or future historical writer in his attempt to set the date of the first Greek in to this country, will be compelled to liken him with Columbus. However, the Greek is here and the date of his arrival may remain unknown.</p>
   <p>The Greek is an alien amongst aliens, alone amongst many, without knowledge of the English language, rather uneducated, poor but honest, acquires friends and becomes a paragon of industriousness and honesty amongst the many.</p>
   <p>His inherent desire to progress soon makes him conspicuous. He multiplies more and more by bringing his relatives and friends from the old country, to the new country of hope.</p>
   <p>Whenever you find ten Greeks, you'll find an organized society; a church as their meeting place and adjoining the church a Greek school to perpetuate the Greek Language and Greek Nationalism.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1397.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In a short time the Greek will go into business and prospers. In his prosperity he does not forget his Mother Country, hence, the American Greek becomes the good angel and benefactor of Greece.</p>
   <p>Millions and millions of dollars are sent to Greece yearly to build schools, roads, streets, new villages to eliminate slums and beautify cities. Along with his dollars he sends American ideas and views. His ultimate aim is to get rich and go back to his Mother Country, to his family, wife and children, but the influence of the environment alters his views and instead of going back, he sends and brings his beloved over here.</p>
   <p>That change of his original aim, becomes a great national problem for the nation of Greece and the church. Never before in history was the Greek devoured by the influence of a new environment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
