<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1928-01-06">Jan. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Hellenic Post Elects New Officers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1244</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1244.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1928-01-06">Jan. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">HELLENIC POST ELECTS NEW OFFICERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Hellenic Post Number 343 of the American Legion will install its new officers on January 30, 1928, at the Hotel La Salle.</p>
   <p>The following officers have been elected and will be officially installed on the thirtieth: Commander, Hercules Malapanes; Senior Commander, Demitrios A. Tasiopulos; First Junior Vice Commander, Louis Nigas; Second Junior Vice Commander, Peter Machales; Finance Officer, Demitrios J. Georgetsis; Medical Officer, Dr. Minas Joannides; Publicity Officer, Demitrios N. Delevois; Judge Advocate, George S. Porikos; Service Officer, Demetrios J. Pierce; Athletic Officer, James Pappas; Historian, George Georgandas; Auditor, Demetrios, E. Alex; Chaplain, Alexander P. Castritsis; Sergeant-at-arms, Nicholas Z. Kollias; Executive Committee, Hercules Malapanes, Demetrios A. Tasiopulos, Demetrios J. Georgetsis, George J. Alex, Demetrios N. Delevios, Gust Patsios, Dr. Minas Joannides, Nicholas Z. Kollias, Thomas Leventis.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1245.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The adopted sons of America, of Greek birth, as well as those born here of Greek parentage, can mutually share in the honor of victory in the World War, in which thousands of Greek soldiers participated. All marched shoulder to shoulder with the American boys to dedicate the American flag, victorious on the field of honor in the new Thermopylae of Belgium and France.</p>
   <p>The Hellenic Post, which occupies a prominent position as a group of the American Legion, stands today among Greeks as the divine inspiration of patriotism and Americanism. Our young men have proved by fighting in the World War that they came to this country not only to be benefited by the rich opportunities afforded to them as citizens but also to share in the responsibilities of their adopted country. To those heroes who stood by the principles that are symbolized by the Star-Spangled Banner we owe ever-lasting gratitude for the great service which they rendered to their country and to humanity.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1246.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We are proud that they are scions of the "glory that was Greece," and now belong to the land that stands for the highest and noblest ideals of republican government. More power to the members of the American Legion who strove to conquer the enemy that freedom might triumph!</p>
   <p>As the deeds of the brave men will be forever remembered, so the American Legion and the Hellenic Post will persist as long as one man of them survives. The success of the American organization inspires us with memories of the noble deeds of the martyrs of the great war who made the supreme sacrifice, leaving to their comrades the rich inheritance of all that is highest in America and in her institutions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
