<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1921-09-02">Sept. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A Self-Governing Church in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0744</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0744.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1921-09-02">Sept. 2, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A SELF-GOVERNING CHURCH IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- The articles published by us about the necessity of establishing a self-governing Greek Orthodox Church in America have moved a prominent lawyer in our community, Mr. Andrew Vlachos, to send us the following article, which we publish with pleasure.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vlachos's Article</p>
   <p>Mr. S. Kotakis in four consecutive issues of the Greek Daily has dealt with the question of establishing a self-governing church in America. His fourth article closes with these words:</p>
   <p>"In projecting this idea we have been motivated by the abnormal situation created in our church administration, and we shall be only too glad to hear the opinions of others who are able to discuss this question."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0745.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Although the writer does not claim to be in a position to express an authoritative opinion on a matter of so much importance and significance, he nevertheless records some thoughts upon the question.</p>
   <p>The main point which Mr. Kotakis makes, upon which all others depend, is this: Is there need of establishing a self-governing church in America?</p>
   <p>We, being concerned with the main objective of these articles, abstain from expressing any detailed opinion on the famous ecclesiastical question of who is the legitimate Metropolite of Athens. We confine ourselves to saying that the solution of the ecclesiastical question under dispute as to who is the legitimate Metropolite of Athens depends not on the judgment of the Greek press nor on the opinion of the Greek people nor on legislation by the Greek Parliament nor on governmental decree nor on decisions of one or the other Holy Synod of Greece nor on the attitude of those who vie for the throne of Metropolite of Athens.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0746.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The solution of this question, which is of the utmost religious and ecclesiastical importance, depends on the decision of a Synod called by the Ecumenical Patriarchate according to canons pertaining to the solution of questions of this nature.</p>
   <p>Regarding the question of establishing a self-governing church in America much could be written one way or the other.</p>
   <p>In part, we could say that in America there are as many self-governing churches as there are Greek communities. Every community is a legal entity, recognized by the state in which it is located. All Greek churches in America belong to self-governing Greek communities, and they constitute their first and most important property. The executive councils of the communities appoint and discharge the priests. The latter, being hired by the communities, are in this regard a sort of employee, and as a rule the communities can engage any priests whom they want regardless of whether they belong to the Church of Greece or to the Ecumenical Patriarchate or to the Patriarchate of Jerusalem or to that of Antioch or to that of Alexandria. If there is no rule in the constitution providing <pb facs="5422062_5_0747.jpg" n="4"/>for such a detail, the executive council has the right to engage any priest of either of the Patriarchates or of the Holy Synod of Greece or even a priest who has been ordained by a Russian Orthodox bishop.</p>
   <p>The same applies to the appointments even of the bishops. A Greek bishop of whichever church may come to America and ordain priests. The priests, in turn, are appointed by the communities to serve them. Exceptions to this rule are those communities whose constitutions provide for appointment and discharge of the priests by the Holy Synod of Greece, or by some other church.</p>
   <p>All this concerns the government of ecclesiastical matters in the Greek communities of America and nothing more. For, as Mr. Kotakis indicates in all his four articles, no dogmatic or spiritual questions are touched upon at all, for these must always be settled among the Greek churches of America, isolated or united as the case may be, and the self-governing Church of Greece and all the other Orthodox churches. As things stand, this administrative dependence on the Holy Synod of Greece will continue to exist as long as we expect priests and bishops to be sent from Greece to America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0748.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>If there were a reasonable number of priests in America to draw from,there would be no power able to prevent it if the communities wished to employ them here.</p>
   <p>Inasmuch as we have bishops in America to-day, there is nothing that can prevent our having priests ordained by them so as to enable our communities to secure them much more easily. Priests who know the English language, the habits and customs of the land, and also the characteristics and needs of the Greeks of America are preferable to those who come from abroad and are not acquainted with these things.</p>
   <p>If the writer in the Greek Daily, my friend Mr. S. Kotakis, in talking about the self-governing church in America means the formation of an association of the Greek churches in America, whose constitutional regulations would provide, among other things, the manner of appointment and recalling of bishops and priests in America, then we agree with him on the need of launching such an ecclesiastical association possessing legal entity and functioning according to a constitution recognized by <pb facs="5422062_5_0749.jpg" n="6"/>the American authorities, because many are the advantages that will accrue for Hellenism in America from so serious an effort toward ecclesiastical organization of Greek-Americans.</p>
   <p>Needless to say, this ecclesiastical association of the Greeks of America will bear the title of "The Greek Orthodox Church in America," will be based on the fundamental tenets of Orthodoxy, and will be spiritually united with all Orthodox Churches of the world and consequently with the Church of Greece.</p>
   <p>But here the question springs up: Who is that ecclesiastical giant who will undertake with intelligence and devotion to put this idea into effect? And how can this be realized so as to maintain harmonious relations between the self-governing Church of America and that of Greece so long as the Panhellenic ecclesiastical question of the legality of the Metropolite of Athens, which caused the ecclesiastical split of the Greeks, as my estimable friend Kotakis correctly puts it, remains unsolved?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0750.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>This is the question which I wish to answer in the Greek Daily, and to this public discussion every Greek should give heed, showing his interest in things pertaining to Greek life in America.</p>
   <p>Andrew J. Vlachos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
