<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-06-26">June 26, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">How Long Is Hellenism Going to Remain Divided?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0613</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0613.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-06-26">June 26, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">HOW LONG IS HELLENISM GOING TO REMAIN DIVIDED?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1-Hellenism can benefit from the splendid congress organized by the Catholic Church if it will learn this lesson, - that only by uniting will it be able to command respect in this country.</p>
   <p>The religious sentiment continues to be very lively, and it will continue to be so in the future. For this reason the bonds between Greece and the Greeks in America must be tightened; they must not be allowed to remain lax, thus causing incalculable harm to our national interests which partisan blindness will not let us perceive.</p>
   <p>The establishment of the self-governing American Church, which pretends to be under the jurisdiction of the Patriarch of Constantinople, is the result of party differences; more specifically, the establishment of that independent Church by the ousted Metropolitan Vasilion is due to factional discord, and it gave rise to those partisan speeches which were made by Archbishop Melitiou.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0614.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The existence of both Churches has no other effect than to perpetuate the the division and the dissipation of our national strength.</p>
   <p>It would be hard to express, as the Church of Greece knows, how wholehearted our support of the Archbishop's regime would be if we had the slightest hope that it could unite Hellenism in America. Unfortunately, however, its efforts toward this end have failed, and factional strife continues, continually waxing stronger. Thus the Archbishopric, in spite of its official recognition by the Greek hierarchy and the support granted to it by the Greek Government, has up to this time failed to effect a union of the Greeks in this country.</p>
   <p>Well, as long as a large number of Greek Orthodox churches refuse to recognize the Archbishopric, preferring to follow an ousted Metropolitan instead, and as long as the majority of the priests in those churches and of the communities which support them remain independent, upholding a leader who broke away from the authority of the original ecclesiastical order because he did not wish to comply with its decree and go to Athens, -as long as these conditions prevail, there will always be obstacles to unity.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0615.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That is how things are; and it is time for the Patriarchate and for the Greek nation to examine conditions with more sagacity and to prevent the division of Hellenism by finding a way to facilitate unity and peace in the Greek Church of America.</p>
   <p>We believe that the best solution and the easiest way to effect the establishment of such peace and unity is the way followed by the Church of Greece and the Patriarchate of Constantinople when they came to an agreement on the restoration of the former status quo; only by the dispatch from Greece to America of a legate of the Holy Synod will all the churches and their priests be persuaded to submit to one ecclesiastical order.</p>
   <p>We believe this, that Hellenism, having had enough of these quarrels and dissensions, desires to find a way to adjust its differences, and that the constituents of the Archbishopric and those of Vasilion no longer desire because of petty personal interests to oppose a solution that will make possible the union of Hellenism and the restoration of ecclesiastical prestige.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0616.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We do not believe that either the Patriarchate or the Holy Synod of Greece is enthusiastic over all the dissension which has harassed the Greek churches in America for so many years; neither should the Greek Government be satisfied with such conditions. However, it is time for them to realize that the Patriarchate, the Holy Synod, and the Greek Government are themselves responsible for the perpetuation of this discord, and that only by their cooperation and intervention will union be made possible. They have created the present ecclesiastical situation in America by failing for the last three years to subject the churches of America to their administration; and these independent churches comprise no small number of communicants.</p>
   <p>How much longer shall you delay?</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
