<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-07-19">July 19, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting at New Parish of Koimisis Tis Theotukou</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0768</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0768.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-07-19">July 19, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING AT NEW PARISH OF KOIMISIS TIS THEOTUKOU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Despite the terrible heat last Sunday, a large number of people attended the meeting at the new parish of Koimisis Tis Theotukou, at which they were fully informed of the plans, ambitions, and hopes for this parish. Mr. J. Dimitrakopoulos, former principal of Socrates, gave a beautiful speech. Some of its highlights follow.</p>
   <p>"Each time a group of people wanted to build their own church, others were found who placed every obstacle in their path. This happened when the North and South Side churches were built, and later when this West Side church was built. However, the other two churches were improved, and today they are fine structures, while our church is a hovel, and is in debt.</p>
   <p>"We are here today to see what can be done about lessening these existing evils, for the benefit of ourselves and the entire community. Again, the <pb facs="5422062_5_0769.jpg" n="2"/>forked-tongue enemies of progress and development are haranging and protesting against our actions. But the church has been bought! This church will be rebuilt and will become one of the best in Chicago, and the day will come when this church will not be able to hold all of its parishioners....."</p>
   <p>These were the words of Dimitrakopoulos, and in the midst of the applause he introduced Mr. G. Sellas. In a direct and evidently sincere manner, he gave his knowledge of the affairs of the church. He uncovered the situation, and revealed the gangrenous condition, which caused the church to backslide and to cease its progress. He said that the blame rest not only with this church itself, but with all the churches.</p>
   <p>Later, in detail, he described the purchase of the church.....After he visited the three reverends of the other churches, and having received enthusiastic responses from them, he called in an architect to draw up plans for the church. When the plans were completed, they were presented <pb facs="5422062_5_0770.jpg" n="3"/>to the Board of Trustees.</p>
   <p>Instead of studying the plans, and then presenting them to a general meeting, the Board of Trustees deemed the matter unworthy of any consideration and threw the plans in the...(sic), and no mention of the above was made at any general assembly.</p>
   <p>Sorrowful, at the neglect of the church which he so eagerly desired to progress, Mr. Sellas proceeded to buy the church himself.....Mr. Sellas then left the platform, with applause ringing in his ears. Mr. N. Lambropoulos, a hearty supporter of all that is good and progressive, was the next speaker of the afternoon.</p>
   <p>The Speech of N. Lambropoulos</p>
   <p>"This large assembled audience gives me pleasure as a parishioner and also as a journalist. This group is not one of idle curiosity-seekers, it is <pb facs="5422062_5_0771.jpg" n="4"/>motivated by great interest in the true condition of our church. This group is a deathblow to backwardness, rotteness, and all the other evils that weigh so heavily upon this parish.</p>
   <p>"You assembled here to see the holy place in which you will pray from now on. You assembled here to see with your own eyes the building from which so many sacred and patriotic benefits will be derived. Lastly, you came here to see the new church called "Koimisis Tis Theotukou," which is now yours.</p>
   <p>"The few individuals who purchased this church are from the middle class, such as, ourselves. They are not people who have degrees from universities; they are people who have had experiences and have learned through their experiences. Letters are not the most important thing needed to make a success of your life. Something else must be present such as is possessed by Venizelos.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0772.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"I am not here to give a political speech, because the time for talking has passed, and the time for action is here.....</p>
   <p>"No! ladies and gentleman, the church was not bought for the profit of a few individuals, as some people might cause you to suppose.....</p>
   <p>The Saloniki, is going to run a new column called "Ecclesiastical Matters," in which all news of the progress of the church and its parishioners, will be published.</p>
   <p>This event marks a new era in the progress and development of the Chicago Greeks</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
