<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-01-02">January 2, 1926</date><title level="a">Debasing the Greek Language.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0646</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0646.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1926-01-02">January 2, 1926</date><title level="a">Debasing the Greek Language.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the influence and the financial backing of the Vatican, a degenerate Greek, pseudo professor, came recently to Athens, to pursue the abdominable activity of debasing the Greek language, and the Greek orthodox church and faith.</p>
   <p>The financial means, which, this degenerate possesses is $50,000.00 which he spends right and left. This money emanates from the Vatican City of Rome, which very much resents the Greek language of the Gospel, and longs for its alteration.</p>
   <p>This froglike, Franco-Levantine, Greek, who went to Paris from Constantinople, educated himself in the brothels of Paris, renounced his Greek religion and his country, Greece, and become a Catholic serf of the Vatican. In this City with the inexhaustible supply of money at his command, he endeavored to persuade the Greeks of Paris to change their religion and become puppets and serfs of the Catholic church, leaving nothing undone, that should be done, to Catholicize the Greeks of Paris. As long as the appropriated money lasted, his pupils helped him spend it. Leaving Paris he soon made an appearance in <pb facs="5422062_5_0647.jpg" n="2"/>Athens where, with the help of 50,000 American dollars, he succeeded in forming a clique, to fight against the Greek language and the Greek orthodox religion. His cohorts audaciously yelped, "Vive Jean Psihari Le Sankoule De Paris!" following him everywhere as long as the dollars lasted.</p>
   <p>This dishonorable being published some books under the instruction and guidance of the Catholic church, which books he distributed gratis among his followers. Some of those books made their appearance here in Chicago. Only one glance through this book is sufficient to cause the reader to realize the ugliness and the strangeness of the written language; it is the language of the Vatican, the language that the Vatican wants the Greeks to learn and speak.</p>
   <p>A distinguished Englishman of letters named Joseph McCabe speaking at the auditorium of the Catholic church said, "For twenty years I was a professor at the Vatican, teaching ministers, I, therefore, know what is Catholicism; it is the most mysterious organization in the world. In England Catholicism is advocated and supported by H. G. Wells and Mr. Chesterton, under the auspices and financial assistance of the Vatican. These two men published a newspaper for the Catholics.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0648.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"In France I met, besides others, a Greek named John Psihari, who advocates Catholicism. This Greek makes himself conspicuous, owing to the fact that he is small in height and his frog-like face makes a display of professional education; in reality he is not educated."</p>
   <p>Now, my dear Greeks, if and when you see a book of this degenerate Greek, take a look at it, convince yourself of its ugliness and depravity, and then burn it up. The Greek language and Greek religion will remain unaltered if we really are the sons of Greece. The above mentioned imitation of a human being cannot be a Greek.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
