<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-03-27">Mar. 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">The Grand Vespers in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0134</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0134.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-03-27">Mar. 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">THE GRAND VESPERS IN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.--It is a pleasant surprise for one who has been absent from the large cities of Greece for a long time to attend the impressive ceremony and hear the liturgy of grand vespers in Chicago, celebrated by a bishop assisted by many priests. It brings back pleasant memories of the good old days and of the times when Orthodoxy exerted its influence all over the Christian world with its magnificent ceremonies.</p>
   <p>This was one of the occasions which brings together large crowds of Greeks of Chicago and its vicinity,--the celebration of the Annunciation of the Virgin.</p>
   <p>The early arrival of some of the faithful at Evangelismos Church, mostly women, reminded one of a mass in Passion week, when Greeks usually crowd their churches.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0135.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The magnificence of the Right Reverend Bishop Kallistos, followed by the eight priests of the other eight Greek churches of Chicago, among them the Reverend Fathers Marlou Petrake, Daniel Gamvrile, Const. Papanicolaou, Dion. Sakelariou, Averkios Demakopoulos, and Constas. H. Demetry, added to the effect of the impressive religious ceremony.</p>
   <p>Beautiful sacred music, a mixture of old Byzantine and modernistic European sung by the church choir directed by Mr. J. Papageorge and led by Messrs. John Xeros, Theo. Spyropoulos, and Geo. Demopoulos, experienced singers of Byzantine chants, lent a unique charm to the ceremony for those whose ears were attentive to the canticles.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0136.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The melodious "Isakouson Mou Kyrie," (Lord, hear me!) was splendidly sung by the choir, and the "Chaire Nymphe Anympheute" (Hail, Virgin Bride!) as well as the "Plousioi Eptocheusan Kai Epinasan" (And the Rich Are Turned Empty Away), were perfectly rendered in Byzantine music with variations which gave the impression of an oriental celebration.</p>
   <p>The timely preaching of the Bishop, the impressive and magnificent ceremony, and the large crowd showed the difference in such celebrations between large and small centers of population and the influence of Greek Orthodoxy in comparison with other denominations.</p>
   <p>After the vespers the Bishop, the priests, and all the members of the councils of the other churches were invited to the hall in the basement of the church, where a light supper was served.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
