<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1908-12-25">Dec. 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Our Church</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1027</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1027.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>THE GREEK STAR</title>,
<date when="1908-12-25">Dec. 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">OUR CHURCH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek Orthodox Church of America has occupied the attention of the Greek immigrant from the very beginning. Wherever the Greek immigrant goes, he feels the need of the Greek Church's support and protection. No Greek community worthy of that name is without a church. From time immemorial, the Greek people have lived and prospered under the guidance and with the blessings of the Greek Church. The great spiritual and intellectual forces that constitute the Greek Church have shaped our lives which are inextricably linked with the national Greek state. In days of power and glory as well as in times of disasters, despair, and defeats, faith in God and adherence to the church have kept our people united and conscious of their dependence on higher principles of mind and spirit.</p>
   <p>The Greek War of Independence was won, primarily, with the help of the National Church. She prepared the revolution and gave hope and courage <pb facs="5422062_5_1028.jpg" n="2"/>to its leaders. The Greek nation has grown and developed with the invaluable support of those who minister to our spiritual needs and who first undertook to educate the people.</p>
   <p>The future of our people in America will be conditioned by the influence of the Greek Church of America.</p>
   <p>Our church institutions here in Chicago have been the nucleus around which all our social, economic, educational, and spritual activities tend to express themselves and develop.</p>
   <p>In forthcoming articles, The Greek Star will analyze the Greek Church in America and especially our own Community for the purpose of informing the people of the tremendous contributions which it has rendered and is rendering the Greek people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
