<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-11-15">Nov. 15, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">The Congregation of the Communities a Necessity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-11-15">Nov. 15, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">THE CONGREGATION OF THE COMMUNITIES A NECESSITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- The appointment of the Bishops of America to Metropolitan positions in Greece, officially announced to them by the Legation, amounts to the final solution of our Church question regarding the elimination of the Independent Church in America. Concerning this point, the Greek government, the Greek Church, and the Legate of Patriarchates as well have done all they could to terminate the division and restore the Orthodox churches of America to their regular ecclesiastical authority.</p>
   <p>But to complete the job of restoration and ecclesiastical order, it is necessary that the Old Church regime be replaced by a new one which will comply with the needs of the Greeks of America and originate in their will, for then only will it enjoy the respect of the Greek populace of America, and it will function, in the main, if it fulfills their desires. Nobody else knows what the Greek people of America want but themselves.</p>
   <p>Such being the case, it is necessary to have a convention of all the communities of America called by the Legate to discuss and decide about the rules and regulations of their ecclesiastical government.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0299.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>And we consider the convocation of such a convention as an indispensable necessity, not only because we firmly believe that except the Greek people of America, properly represented, nobody knows their needs, but also because the bitter experience of the past has convinced us that decisions taken in their absence will assuredly cause new troubles and complications, which common sense dictates that we should by all means avoid in the future.</p>
   <p>The most important reason for the failure of the abolished church regime and for all the evils caused by it in America was that the Greek people of America were not called upon to express their will and to ratify it by their vote - because it did not comply with the people's needs and desires.</p>
   <p>The convocation of the convention of communities is a supplement to the Legate's work because after the successful accomplishment of the first part of the mission, that of the abolition of that ecclesiastical regime which caused the division and the union of the Greek communities in America under one authority, the Mother Church, it is now necessary to have the second part of the mission consummated, namely, the organization <pb facs="5422062_5_0300.jpg" n="3"/>of the Church in America according to the canons of our Orthodox Church and in harmony with the needs of Hellenism in America.</p>
   <p>And so far as the question of organization according to the Church canons is concerned, it should be left, surely, to the knowledge and experience of the Legate; but when it comes to applying these canons and to matters concerning the needs of the Greek population in America, they ought to have the first word by their representatives.</p>
   <p>For these reasons, we think it is necessary to have the convention as soon as possible, since it is high time to put an end to the present abnormal conditions.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
