<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1921-09-03">Sep. 3, 1921</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">The Self-Governing Church.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0740</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0740.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1921-09-03">Sep. 3, 1921</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">THE SELF-GOVERNING CHURCH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We published, in yesterday's issue the opinions of our friend, Mr. Andrew Vlachos, lawyer in regard to the question initiated by the Greek Daily of Chicago, that is whether there is need of establishing a self-governing church in America.</p>
   <p>Mr. Vlachos agrees with us in principle recognizing the necessity of a self-governing church in America. However, he propounds the question.</p>
   <p>"Who is the eclesiastical giant who will undertake with intelligence and devotion to put this idea into effect?"</p>
   <p>Necessity Creates</p>
   <p>To this question we answer that, having dealt with the question from a higher standpoint we did not carry out the plan so far as to be able to point out the man who would undertake to put our design into effect.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0741.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If we really need a church of our own here in America, as we believe, the ways and means of acquiring it will undoubtedly be found as well as the man fit for the task.</p>
   <p>In regard to the necessity for recognition of the Church of America by the Holy Synod of Greece, how can that be done as long as the question of the legality of the Metropolite of Athens remains unsolved?</p>
   <p>We answer, unequivocally, that the question of recognition of the self-governing Church of America by the Holy Synod of Greece, or by other Churches, is a question depending on the way of the establishing the church in America. It is necessary, perhaps, to answer this question: Are the Orthodox churches of America controlled by any Church in particular? Or to put it in a better light. Could the Holy Synod of Greece or the different Patriarchates raise claims of jurisdiction over the churches of America?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0742.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Regarding the question of the Metropolite of Athens and its dependence we say without hesitation to Mr. Vlachos that we doubt that there is such a question in Greece.</p>
   <p>This answer of our necessitates some explantion because otherwise we may be understood as contradicting ourselves. Namely how can we be friendly to Metropolite Metaxakis while we doubt that there is a Metropolite question in Greece?</p>
   <p>Our readers will remember, perhaps, that since the arrival of Metaxakis in America we have expressed, the opinion that, in view of all that has occurred in Greece and the overthrow of the King, the Areopagite, the generals the University professors, and other high functionaries,it is not impossible that the bishops and metroplites may be overthrown.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0743.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>One more thing. It is not the Greek people of America that will solve the Metropolite question of Greece. We still stand by that.</p>
   <p>We support Metropolite Metaxakis and recognize that his personality and his ability can render great service in the organization of the Greek people in America, especially in ecclesiastical matters.</p>
   <p>The Greeks of America undoubtedly need to be organized, and when a personality such as that of Metaxakis comes here, those who sincerely desire this organization do not intend to start a war against him even if they disagree with him in part.</p>
   <p>The Metropolite question, if there is one, will be straightened out soon. The organization of the churches in America however, is irrelevant to it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
