<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-08-02">Aug. 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Without a Title</title><title level="a" type="sub">by N. Lambropoulos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0765</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0765.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-08-02">Aug. 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">WITHOUT A TITLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">by N. Lambropoulos</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have been informed that the temporary board of trustees of the Koimisis Tis Theotokou Church has sent a letter to the president of the Holy Synod of Rodostolou, asking for recognition of the church.</p>
   <p>Since His Holiness is known to be a just man with democratic and liberal tendencies, we are sure that he will recognize this church. This church has all the requirements for its sacred purpose: it commands respect and reverence and is an honor to our religion and the Greek name in this strange country. To recognize this church, he must be made familiar with its previous disgraceful plight.</p>
   <p>The Saloniki, which has aligned itself on the side of the rebuilders of this church, will be the first to thank Rodostolou, and will be the first <pb facs="5422062_5_0766.jpg" n="2"/>to bend over the hand the signs the notice of recognition, which will lift the yoke of backwardness from the neck of this West Side Church. This church has all the indications of becoming even greater than the other churches and will stand as an example of democratic organization.</p>
   <p>One reason after another, which can be knocked down as easily as a house made of cards, is presented by the foes of this church. They said that the church was an antique. We answered that Saint Sofia was five hundred years old and was used for a stable by the Turks. Then they said the color was ugly, because it was of red brick. Mr. Fortin, the architect, said that those bricks would last from two to five hundred years. Some said that the building had settled and that it would lean over and collapse. We told them that we had seen many old people whose backs were bent, and yet those people did not fall. They said that the church was near a car line and that people would be killed while crossing. So we told them that as yet not even a fly had been injured by a car, because the church faces a lovely park--flies don't go in the park because they <pb facs="5422062_5_0767.jpg" n="3"/>are assembled in front of the old wooden hovel where it is very clean (?).....</p>
   <p>During the meeting, last Sunday, Mr. Williams played some hymns upon the wonderful pipe organ of the church. One individual, who told me that the church cost $2,000, would probably evaluate this great organ at fifteen cents--cheaper than a wooden tambourine. Perhaps he meant to say two hundred thousand-dollar bills. If so, I must apologize.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
