<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-05-31">May 31, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Our Church Problem</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0562</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0562.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-05-31">May 31, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">OUR CHURCH PROBLEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- Father Averkios Demakopoulos gave us a new surprise on the day before yesterday when he declared his recognition of the religious hegemony of Greece's Holy Synod, thereby renouncing his support of the Archbishopric, the authority of which he had recognized only a month ago.</p>
   <p>When our three newspapers recognized the Bishop, the Reverend Father Philaretos, we wrote that this recognition of him was not of much significance, since it was not the first time that he had been recognized, and it would not be the last. To-day we make the same statement with reference to Father Demakopoulos's change of attitude because such shifts in policy have been observed before, and there is no end to them. Since, however, we censured our newspapers for shifting their support from Greece's Holy Synod to the Archbishopric, we find it expedient, if we mean to follow the same line consistently, to praise Mr. Demakopoulos made a serious error in recognizing the Archbishopric, for by so doing he opened the way to ecclesiastical strife and disunion, which as long as it remains will keep <pb facs="5422062_5_0563.jpg" n="2"/>America's Hellenism divided into factions. Fortunately he saw his mistake early and returned to the establishment. If all the priests who foster the present ecclesiastical disunion by recognizing the Archbishopric would follow in the footsteps of Averkios Demakopoulos, all discord would instantly cease; there would be no ecclesiastical problem, and the Holy Synod of Greece would send a synodical legate as it has done in the past. And if the opposite thing were to happen, that is, if all the priests in America unanimously recognized the Archbishopric in North America, again there would be no ecclesiastical problem to contend with. When, however, the priests array themselves in two opposing camps, of which one recognizes the Archbishopric, and the other repudiates it, they create a state of affairs which detracts from their ecclesiastical dignity and fails to inspire the veneration and the confidence which the laity normally feels for its pious directors. To Father Demakopoulos's perception of this fact we ascribe his sudden conversion to that ecclesiastical authority by which all America's Hellenism should be governed.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0564.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After the return of Father Demakopoulos to the regular establishment it would be extremely beneficial not only for the priests who still dissent but also for the dissenting newspapers to follow in his steps. Indeed, it was these newspapers which brought Vasilios to Chicago and acknowledged him as their ecclesiastical head. Now then, if we term the recognition of the Archbishopric an "error", then we must use the word "crime" to label the recognition of an ousted priest. And if we say that the Archbishopric of North America should not have a place among us because it divides Hellenism in America, we must likewise declare that the existence of Vasilios in America creates a schism and necessitates the correction of those priests who follow him and of the parishes which admit him in their churches.</p>
   <p>As for us, the Archbishopric and Vasilios have become to us symbols of factious discord; they have no place any more among the Greeks of America. All those who desire the unity of Hellenism in America should pray and work for the expulsion of those who create ecclesiastical discord.</p>
   <p>The Contradictor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
