<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1930-08-09">Aug. 9, 1930</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">The Patriarchic Exarch in the Cathedral of St. Basil.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Bishop Philaretos Resigned.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0353</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0353.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1930-08-09">Aug. 9, 1930</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">THE PATRIARCHIC EXARCH IN THE CATHEDRAL OF ST. BASIL.</title><title level="a" type="sub">BISHOP PHILARETOS RESIGNED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The stately liturgy, at the cathedral of St. Basil, in which the Patriarchic Exarch Most Rev. Damaskenos officiated, was magnificent and imposing. Right Rev. Philaretos, bishop in Chicago and all the clergy, assisted in the holy mass.</p>
   <p>This liturgy will remain a historical event in the annals of the Greek Church of America, because the division of the church is ended. Mr. Damaskenos, who, besides his ecclesiastical authority, is also pleni-potentiary of the Greek government, unified the Church. He brought the olive branch of peace and unity. The prevalent ecclesiastical authority resigned and respectfully accepted the wishes of the Mother Church. Bishop Philaretos solemnly relinquished his authority and was appointed as Metropolitan of Syros and Tenos.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0354.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The erudite Greek Hierarch Mr. Damaskenos, pointed out the necessity of harmony and unity, and very solemnly urged the laity and the clergy to abide by the decision of the Ecumenical Patriarch. The mandate of the Mother church prevailed. Division and emnity exist no more.</p>
   <p>The Right Rev. Philaretos, who for eight years in Chicago served the interest of the church and endeavored to pacify and unify the affairs of the various Greek churches sent his resignation to the Exarch, who reluctantly accepted. Bishop Philaretos, whose services to the Greeks in America were and are very valuable is highly esteemed by the Mother church and the state. The Greek government, in appreciating the good work of the Bishop honored him with the award of the Higher Taxiarch.</p>
   <p>Peace, harmony and unity, again reign supreme in the Greek church of America. All brothers in Christ, are reunited again and act at the voice of Mother church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
