<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-04-19">April 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Missions from Greece</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0631</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0631.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-04-19">April 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">MISSIONS FROM GREECE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We continue our discussion of missions from Greece and consider it our duty to describe the situation of Hellenism in America as it actually exists to those in Greece as well as to those who compose the mission here, so that they may not deceive themselves by imagining that the Greeks of America, divided among themselves, can contribute to whatever cause those in Greece desire them to help.</p>
   <p>We consider it necessary, since the Most Reverend Father Gennadios and the gentlemen who, along with him, compose the mission are here, to present the situation to them as it really is, so that when they return to Greece, they will be able to interpret things accurately. For we do not believe that if they had had the slightest idea of the situation, they would have crossed the ocean, headed by a church dignitary who, regardless of right or wrong, had already drawn up a plan to visit the churches of one camp and to refuse his blessing to the other, ignoring its churches.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0632.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is no need of criticism or comment to make people realize the result of such an attitude on the part of the leader of the mission, nor is it necessary to emphasize how injurious it is to the purpose for which the mission came.</p>
   <p>If they had been aware of the existing situation, either they would not have decided to come to America, or they would know how to face it, for those who know the facts always find a way to meet them, and only those who do not know them or do not want to learn them find themselves in predicaments.</p>
   <p>What has taken place in Chicago is a strange phenomenon for the Greeks of America, not seen since pre-war times. To wit, all parishes, together with their executive councils and priests, are to participate in the reception of this mission, to organize a very splendid supper in its honor, and to show a sincere desire to cooperate for the success of the mission.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0633.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>What has broken up our cooperative action over here and again provoked dissension and chaos? The ignorance of persons in Greece and of those who come from Greece about persons and things here.</p>
   <p>Yes, gentlemen, just as yesterday you broke up the concord and cooperation of the Greeks of Chicago and chilled their eagerness to contribute toward your project, even so have those in Greece split the unity of Hellenism in America by dividing it and, worst of all, by keeping it divided.</p>
   <p>..... The wrong conception has prevailed in Greece about the break in church bonds between Greece and the Greeks of America. The recognition of the diocese established here for partisan reasons is equivalent to a national crime, and whoever thoughtlessly and heedlessly in any way promotes the continuance of interrupted relations between the churches in Greece and the churches here is an involuntary contributor to this error.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0634.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>And therefore any Greeks whatsoever, whether on official mission or not, who come here and do not investigate the situation, or who do not want to understand it, are voluntary contributors to this national crime and are wholly responsible for this dissension of the Greeks and the failure therefrom resulting of every national and patriotic purpose toward which they might greatly contribute.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
