<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-10-10">Oct. 10, 1931</date><title level="a">Greek Monastery in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-10-10">Oct. 10, 1931</date><title level="a">GREEK MONASTERY IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4.- The undisputable fact that the Greeks of America will remain citizens of this great democratic country is once more apparent from the following fact: the establishment of a Greek monastery in America.</p>
   <p>The Greek originally did not come here to stay and become a part of this great Republic; he came here to earn dollars and go back to his beloved Greece. However, the American ideals, the nobility of the American spirit; the greatness of the American form of Government; and the liberty and justice which he loves and enjoys under the American flag, enthused the Greek immigrant of the past and made him an integral part of American life. The Greek began to build his beloved Greece here in America, his future home and future country. The idea of going back has been given up. The idea of putting his shoulders to the American wheel of progress and of helping to construct appeared. He built houses, stores, theaters, schools, churches, bought farms, and real estate, and now he has established a Greek monastery, the first of its kind in the Greek life of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0200.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The mixed council of the Greek Archdiocese for a long time contemplated the feasibility of such an institution as a spiritual center for the Greeks of America. Gastonia, North Carolina, has the distinction of having the first Greek monastery in this country. St. Stephen is the name it was given. The estate is composed of 420 acres and known as Crowder's Mountain, where formerly was functioning Linwood College. It includes the famous springs known as All Healing Springs. The many buildings of the former college have been transformed and reconstructed for the monastic life of the new occupants. The mild climate and the salubriousness of the place makes it an ideal spiritual center.</p>
   <p>The estate was bought by the Greek Archdiocese through Greek contributions. New buildings are erected and a new Church is practically completed, as new contributions come in. Bishop Philaretos of San Francisco is in charge of regulating the institution. Thousands of Greeks all over the country who will visit the monastry will have the opportunity to hear the churches' bells chiming Byzantine music.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0201.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Is it possible for the progressive Greek mind to be contented with one monastery for the 500,000 Greek-Americans? No! This is the beginning of a new era. In years to come the Greeks in each State of the Union will meet one another, exchange a few words, and a new religious and educational building will go up, symbolizing their progressiveness and determination to remain Greek-Americans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
