<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1928-11-17">Nov. 17, 1928</date>, p. 8
<title level="a">The Pope Dreams of Dominating the East.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0451</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0451.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1928-11-17">Nov. 17, 1928</date>, p. 8
<title level="a">THE POPE DREAMS OF DOMINATING THE EAST.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greeks of Chicago and the world over are informed of the diabolical schemes of the Vatican to subdue and subjugate the Greek Orthodox Church and extend its dominating powers over Anatolia.</p>
   <p>The infernal religious propaganda which is carried on for centuries in all parts of the world by the Vatican of Rome, was openly and officially acknowledged by the Pope last week.</p>
   <p>The Vatican prodigally spends fabulous sums of money to proselytize, non-christian countries, but christian countries, and especially countries of the Greek Orthodox faith from which christendom was spread Westward.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0452.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Vatican's activities, executed under cover, are known to the vigilant eye of the Greek Orthodox Mother Church, and the Pope's declaration of a systematic propaganda to prosilytize Orthodox people is ill-advised nevertheless it reveals the insatiable appetite of Rome's monster to swallow, not infidel but Christian lands, and especially Greece, which really is the apostle of Christianity.</p>
   <p>It grieves him, says the Pope, to hear of the persecution of the church in Russia, yet due to his intervention with the Bolshiviks, permission was granted him to financially assist persecuted clergymen and freedom to catholic missionaries to propagandize.</p>
   <p>The Pope was extremely chagrined by the Czar's death the head of the Greek Orthodox Church, and for the church's fate, tossed hither and thither by a turbulent sea, due to lack of a master-pilot. And for that reason, says the Pope, he considers himself the proper and logical successor.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0453.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is true that the Vatican appropriates fabulous sums of money to carry out the Pope's corrupt intentions, but he should bear in mind that Greece will not grant him a fertile field to propagate his diabolical schemes. The Popes in the past and now have spent and are spending colossal sums of money in maintaining missionary apostles in many parts of Greece and especially in certain islands. They have erected educational and religious mansions, but these objective after all becomes more remote, ineffective and unproductive.</p>
   <p>It probably is the first time that a Pope has openly and officially declared the activities of the Vatican's propaganda.</p>
   <p>Many, undoubtedly, were astonished, but not the vigilantes of Orthodoxy. The Pope's declaration solves a mystery which long ago, was known to the mother of Christianity.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0454.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Pope wishes, as he says to substitute the vanished head of the Orthodox church whom he considered was the Czar of Russia, but cunningly he refrains from mentioning the full name of the Orthodox church, the Greek Orthodox church, under whose wings are Russia, part of Poland, Jugoslavia, the schismatic Bulgaria, Rumania, Abyssinia, the Armenians, the Syrians, etc., and headed as always is the case, by a Greek Patriarch as Ecumenical Patriarch of all Orthodoxy.</p>
   <p>The Pope now is raising money in America to educate missionaries in a private Vatican college, where the language, habits and customs of various countries in the Near East are taught, thus preparing them to bite off bit by bit the holy Greek church of Christ. Is the money raised for a Christian cause? Are the motives of the Pope christ-like? Can he becloud the truth of Christ always? The answers are No! No! No!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
