<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-05-05">May 5, 1931</date> p. 1.
<title level="a">Cooperation and Understanding Is Necessary</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0255</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0255.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-05-05">May 5, 1931</date> p. 1.
<title level="a">COOPERATION AND UNDERSTANDING IS NECESSARY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are certainly going to insist on the demand that the Archbishop come to Chicago so that he may help us settle our community matters. But what preparations have we towards that objective ourselves? So far, there is no understanding and no program laid out by the Communities to be discussed with Mr. Athenagoras upon his arrival.</p>
   <p>Apparently, everybody is expecting Mr. Athenagoras to settle our pending questions by magic, without knowing anything about the points in question. Many, perhaps, may think that if each community presents him with their problems, he would say "presto" and all their problems would be solved.</p>
   <p>But this is exactly the big mistake they committed when Legate Damaskenos was here and we are afraid that they will repeat. This repetition we shall try to avoid by urging the officials of the communities to come together as soon as possible in order to lay out the program and plans for the organization of our community.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0256.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To believe that the Archbishop will solve our pending community, matters alone is an error that must be overcome before his arrival. If we do not lay out our plans and come to a common understanding as to our communal organization, the Archbishop will find himself confronted with unsurmountable difficulties. It is our dity to help relieve him of such an imposition.</p>
   <p>With the old ecclesiastical regime, which kept us divided, there was no possibility of coming to an understanding, because the non-recognition of the then existing authority by the majority of the Chicago parishes.</p>
   <p>Now, however, when there is no division, the parishes, being under one authority, understanding and cooperation among them is imperative and the various communal paragons ought to come together as soon as possible and propose of effective measures, for the re-organization and progress of this great community of Hellenism in America.</p>
   <p>It must be understood, at last, that only by cooperation can we get anywhere. One-sided activity and narrow mindedness must cease and broad mindedness in thought and conception of things must prevail. It must be understood above <pb facs="5422062_5_0257.jpg" n="3"/>all that only by cooperation and common action can the interests of the individual community be served.</p>
   <p>It is an imperative necessity, therefore, for the officials of the different communities to get together before the arrival of the Archbishop, because it is the only way they will hasten the re-organization of our community and facilitate the work of the Right Rev. Athenagoras.</p>
   <p>Sp. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
