<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1909-05-12">May 12, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Our Communal Affairs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0983</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0983.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1909-05-12">May 12, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">OUR COMMUNAL AFFAIRS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- With joy we hear that the members are beginning to realize their mistakes and are doing what they can to rectify them. We hope this good work keeps up till everything is brought under control. Three officers, one from the West, one from the South and one from the North Side are expected to meet some time this week. These men hope to reach an agreement on the various small problems which are impeding the progress of the Panhellenic Union.</p>
   <p>The central organization is expected to put into effect the following:</p>
   <p>(1) To buy or rent for a long period seven halls where various meetings can be held.</p>
   <p>(2) To divide Chicago into three ecclesiastical communities, the North, South, and West.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0984.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>(3) To see that voters vote in their respective communities instead of trying to vote at all three in one day.</p>
   <p>(4) Each community will elect its own officers, who will be expected to be present at all of the central committee's meetings.</p>
   <p>(5) Three delegates will be elected, one from each community, to represent their respective presidents. They will be elected annually at the same time the presidents are elected.</p>
   <p>(6) The officers will submit monthly reports to their presidents, who will verify them and see that they are printed in the Greek newspapers so all may know what is being done.</p>
   <p>(7) For patriotic or philanthropic benefits, the officers of all communities must be consulted and an agreement reached before anything is done.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0985.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>(8) The property on Loomis street is to be sold. The money gained in this way is to be divided among the three churches and is to be used for ecclesiastical and educational purposes only.</p>
   <p>(9) Instead of spending their time in taverns and coffee-houses the priests are to teach the children of their parishioners on week-days. When the priest has a sufficient number of pupils, he will be paid $30 a month extra for teaching them.</p>
   <p>(10) The church on 19th and State streets is to be the main headquarters.</p>
   <p>(11) All little problems are to be cleared up immediately and -</p>
   <p>(12) All must vow to help all they can instead of starting arguments over petty trivialities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
