<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-05-17">May 17, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Mother's Day Celebration.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1347</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1347.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-05-17">May 17, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">MOTHER'S DAY CELEBRATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.6.- Beautiful indeed was this year's celebration, of Mother's Day, being held by the splendid society of the Greek girls of South Side, the New Generation Society.</p>
   <p>At about 3 p.m. the best element of our community started coming in from all directions. A half an hour later the charming lady, Miss Kary Mitchell, with a wonderful introduction in faultless Greek, explained in brief the meaning of the feast. Then, Mr. G. Kampas and his orchestra, played Greek and American hymns. The witty little Nikolatseas recited two poems, and Miss D. Siepi another, all of which were received with enthusiasm. Then Miss Maria Mitsoula gave a few piano selections.</p>
   <p>Immediately following, the chairman introduced Dr. P.A. Hronopoulos, speaker of the day. Dr. Hronopoulos did not confine himself to the usual customary sentimentalism, and abstained from using any rhetorical stunts, that might provoke momentary emotions. He went far into the subject of Motherly affection. He refreshed our recollection of sorrowful mothers <pb facs="5422062_5_1348.jpg" n="2"/>in Greece, and the meaning of the feast, for those of us who are away from home. He made a comparison between the filial affection towards father, on one hand, and mother, on the other, and said that love for Mother is hearty, is life's poetry, while that for father is acquired rather than instinctive.</p>
   <p>Then Mr. Hronopoulos, in developing his subject, showed how social institutions, as those of the Crusades, can up-root what we call motherly affection, and how, also, a martial and savage environment, as that of the Souliotes, idealizes still more the sentiment of love.</p>
   <p>The speaker expressed his conviction that a healthy civilization by exalting the woman, exalts at the same time the Mother. As an illustration he used the mother of the golden rule of Athens, who was respected as hetaera, and forgotten as Mother, in contrast with the present day woman who is respected as Mother.</p>
   <p>Conservative, however, as Mr. Hronopoulos is, he pointed to the weak spots of civilization, in this hysteric and neurasthenic epoch of ours, when we acquire bigger restaurants and ball rooms, theaters and club <pb facs="5422062_5_1349.jpg" n="3"/>rooms, but smaller apartments, and compared them to the pills of the doctors, few of which restore us to health and when many cause loss of a patient.</p>
   <p>"We can expect, however," he said, "that this hysteria of divorces and jazz will pass over, and civilization will give us the ideal mother, namely the prop of the family, and comfort of the home." The speech of Mr. Hronopoulos, well developed and original as it was, made a vivid impression</p>
   <p>For variety, then, Mr. Tsoumas, accompanied by Miss Olga Massia, rendered first the song, "The old Man Demos", followed by other selections. Father Tsourounakis rendered a beautiful prayer for mothers, and right after refreshments were served, a dance was held till 10 P.M.</p>
   <p>The young ladies of the South Side are to be congratulated for organizing such beautiful feasts, and should be supported whole-heartedly by the whole community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
