<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-03-20">Mar. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Clergy of Chicago in Agreement</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0913</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0913.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-03-20">Mar. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK CLERGY OF CHICAGO IN AGREEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first victory of Saloniki in its struggle for co-operation and harmony has manifested itself in the form of an agreement made by the three priests of Chicago. The Reverends Leon Pygeas, Ambrose Mandilaris, and Constantine Hadzidimitriou have sent a letter to this paper pledging their support. The letter is published below.</p>
   <p>This letter is the first step towards the unification of our Greek parishes. It is a well-known fact that the outcome of any issue, good or bad, is the direct result of the type of leadership involved. As spiritual leaders of the Greek community of Chicago, these three priests have assumed the responsibility of creating harmony and uniting the non disorganized Greeks of Chicago. They will of course be aided by every patriotic and progressive Greek in Chicago. Saloniki is prepared to devote its every column to this <pb facs="5422062_5_0914.jpg" n="2"/>purpose.</p>
   <p>We publish the letter received from our priests with the sincere hope that everyone will read it with great care. It clarifies certain facts and explains others which the community has apparently overlooked. In this letter our clergy make certain complaints which are well justified. We must give heed to their words, for the success of our plan depends upon them.</p>
   <p>The clergymen ask the Greek people to awaken their dormant consciousness and free themselves of their mental shackles. Only by doing so can we achieve our goal. The following is the epistle received.</p>
   <p>"Dear Editor of Saloniki:</p>
   <p>"Among your many editorials--all of which urge the Greek people to better themselves--one far surpasses the others. We refer to the article urging <pb facs="5422062_5_0915.jpg" n="3"/>the unification of the three Greek church parishes into one centrally controlled parish. In this article you ask for the opinion and reaction of the community, particularly the Greek priests. We sincerely appreciate the gallantry of your gesture for we are unaccustomed to being consulted in these matters, although they are very pertinent to us. It seems that no one cares what the priests themselves think. Even the lowliest parishioner has more influence in church affairs than the priest himself. However, since you have asked for it, we present our true opinions on the subject.</p>
   <p>"We are, as you have said, 'leaderless and overwhelmed with individual leadership at the same time'. Such a condition must be rectified. The three churches should be centralized so that all Chicago Greeks may derive the same benefits from the church they attend. If such a thing were done better accounts could be kept of income and expenditure.</p>
   <p>"If this unification is to be realized we must wipe out egoism, individualism, sectionalism, pettiness, jealousy, and all the other faults which seem to be <pb facs="5422062_5_0916.jpg" n="4"/>the common failing of the Greek people. Perhaps the Holy Synod of our native land will send us an ordained leader. If this happens we shall be very fortunate.</p>
   <p>If this leader is accepted and revered the unification of our church will not confine itself to the boundaries of Chicago--then our church will be united throughout America. If this does not happen--if the people do not accept him as a superior--then we shall deserve our fate. And that fate will be a sad one. The world will brand us with its scorn and ridicule. We shall be the only people on earth who neither look out for our own interests nor have sense enough to listen to someone wiser than ourselves.</p>
   <p>"Sincerely yours,</p>
   <p>"Leon Pygeas</p>
   <p>"C. Hadzidimitriou</p>
   <p>"A. Mandilaris."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
