<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-06-19">June 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Agitators</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0906</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0906.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-06-19">June 19, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE AGITATORS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great number of programs and leaflets have been distributed in the Greek quarter lately, which are signed by someone called Papadopoulos, who pretends to be a printer, a doctor, and a teacher. This person has a meeting place at Grant and Monroe Streets (sic) where he preaches against the divinity of the Holy Virgin, the saints, and the holy images of our church.</p>
   <p>It is certainly not our duty to answer the arguments of this versatile printer, doctor, and preacher. Our three learned priests and theologians, however, should curb the nefarious activities of this character immediately, because we have positive information that more than sixty poor Greek families have been listening to Papadopoulos' sermons regularly without being able to learn exactly what the nature and purpose of his teachings are. These people go <pb facs="5422062_5_0907.jpg" n="2"/>to his assembly hall with the promise that suitable employment will be secured for them, though we know that this technique is merely a means to an end.</p>
   <p>So, little by little, Papadopoulos teaches that our Holy Mother is not a divinity, that the saints of our church are not worthy of adoration, and that the sacred images or icons represent and mean nothing because they are just pieces of wood and a combination of a few dull colors.</p>
   <p>No doubt, these blasphemies and heretic utterances are the cause of great injury to the religious convictions of our Greek Orthodox Christians. We know that he is a despicable hireling of some other religious sect whose purpose it is to undermine our faith.</p>
   <p>We all know that the divinity of our Holy Virgin has been accepted by us, <pb facs="5422062_5_0908.jpg" n="3"/>and that she has been worshipped by 130,000,000 Orthodox Christians and 300,000,000 Roman Catholics for many centuries. She has not been imposed on our consciousness and spirit by force or by the sword, but only by her loving-kindness and maternal love as the immaculate Mother of Jesus.</p>
   <p>Even Papadopoulos' Turkish friends, even the Jews, respect our Holy Virgin, whose name they often invoke in moments of anguish and pain with the exclamations: Oh, Holy Virgin, help me! Save me, Holy Virgin!</p>
   <p>Papadopoulos and his followers are fighting divine goodness and grace. We shall mention all of them by name so that they will not be able to parade under false colors and pretend that they are Greek Orthodox, and thus poison the innocent and simple minds of our people.</p>
   <p>This man also owns the Hermes printing shop, with the Kastritsis brothers as <pb facs="5422062_5_0909.jpg" n="4"/>his co-workers, and is now printing and distributing various leaflets and manifestos in order to get more customers.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, the book of the notorious Cyril Georgiadis is being printed in this shop. In the heyday of Georgiadis, the Greek community of Chicago was divided as a result of his efforts. It is this same community that we have been trying to reunite and reconstruct with the co-operation of everyone under the leadership of our three able priests. Only thus will we be able to oppose this new attack against our sacred religious convictions and customs. You may notice that this new imposter does not talk openly to any Greek he meets. He uses a clever technique with which he seeks gradually to divorce our people from their religion.</p>
   <p>It is true that he cannot lead many families astray by false promises to provide employment, but he is surrounded by a group of fanatic followers who <pb facs="5422062_5_0910.jpg" n="5"/>are mostly employees of the Hermes printing shop. We do not care what they believe or think. Everybody is free to believe as he pleases. We are greatly concerned about those poor families, however, who submit to his evil influence in the hope of obtaining charity or some other favor. It is a pity that many of our people accept these teachings and ideas without having the courage or strength to fight these dangerous enemies of our faith. Their hope of obtaining some assistance and a piece of bread, however, prevents them from making any objections.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we should not allow our needy families to suffer. Our consolidated Greek community must exercise its humanitarian duties and minister to the needs of our poor through the church, so that they will not be forced to accept any help or services from the underminers of our race and institutions.</p>
   <p>The Greek Women's Club should find out which families are in need. It is <pb facs="5422062_5_0911.jpg" n="6"/>imperative that our great and prosperous Greek community of Chicago unite and endeavor to relieve poverty and suffering among us. It will thus prove that there is no room for agitators among the Greeks of Chicago.</p>
   <p>May we call the attention of our priests, especially, to the need for correction of the evils that beset us? We will gladly offer the columns of this paper free of charge for the discussion of this serious agitational danger.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
