<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-10-26">Oct. 26, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The Debt of the Cleric Convention to the Greeks in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0052</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0052.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-10-26">Oct. 26, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE DEBT OF THE CLERIC CONVENTION TO THE GREEKS IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The representatives to the convention of clerics and laymen are pouring into the city from every state in the country. The convention will open next Monday morning. His Holiness, Archbishop Athinagoras, will arrive Saturday, and Sunday he will conduct the Liturgy in the Evangelismos Church. No doubt the Church will be packed to overflowing, for the Archbishop is known to have a beautiful voice.</p>
   <p>The Greeks of America are vitally interested in the plans, proposals, and decisions of this gathering of priests and laymen. This can be proved by the tremendous amount of space devoted to the subject by all the Greek papers printed in America. The Greek press seems to be in agreement as to the measures and means that should be examined and discussed by the convention. Of particular interest is the fact that they all want a decentralization of <pb facs="5422062_5_0053.jpg" n="2"/>power in the future system of Church government.</p>
   <p>This idea has been presented through this column many times. It is generally accepted as true that centralization of power in one individual or even in one restricted group cannot serve the needs of and work to the advantage of a large number of governed groups. This is not necessarily due to egoistic or selfish tendencies on the part of the leaders. Natural handicaps which are hard to remove enter into the situation. We are quite sure that the Archbishop will agree on this point. Past events prove it beyond a doubt.</p>
   <p>The foregoing statement does not signify that we believe His Holiness, the Archbishop, has dictatorial intentions as far as the government of the Greek Church in America is concerned. The Archbishop is known to be one of those rare individuals who has an open mind. He is not at all stubborn or prejudiced, and he does not believe that everyone is wrong except himself. He readily accepts any suggestion that may tend to serve the general interests. For these reasons we dare to print our opinion as to the social needs and improvements <pb facs="5422062_5_0054.jpg" n="3"/>of our Church. We feel that they will be given sincere and serious attention by the convention presided over by the Archbishop.</p>
   <p>Matters pertaining to the regulation of government of the churches, rather than religious matters, will receive the most attention. After all, the religious needs are no greater and no different than before, so that they are not of primary importance to this convention. Furthermore, there has been no controversy regarding the religious aspect of the Greek Church; therefore the representatives will be able to devote all their time and energy to settling disputes pertaining to methods of church government.</p>
   <p>As we have repeatedly stated, a division must be made in the duties and obligations of the clerics and the laymen. It must be made in such a way that one cannot become the organ, the vassal, or the dictator of the other. If, up to now, the clerics have been viewed a little doubtfully by the laymen, it is mainly due to the former's lack of tact and understanding at crucial moments. In no way do we wish to seem in agreement with those who brand the clergy as <pb facs="5422062_5_0055.jpg" n="4"/>selfish, mercenary, and unpatriotic. The Greek clerics in America are as patriotic, and as idealistic as other Greeks.</p>
   <p>Forced as he is to have the co-operation of a Board of Directors--which nine-tenths of the time is worse than incompetent--a priest, desiring to protect the parish entrusted to him, very often assumes full responsibility and leadership. This is exactly the "bone of contention" which is causing so much division and hatred in our Greek churches. This condition must be bettered or eliminated if the Church is to survive for long. New systems must be worked out that will not give rise to such situations nor cause friction. The future of the Greek Church in America depends upon the action of the convention--which will be greatly influenced by whatever attitude Archbishop Athinagoras takes. We hope that His Holiness and the entire group of representatives will keep this continuously in mind.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
