<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Evening Post</title>,
<date when="1930-08-02">Aug. 2, 1930</date>,
<title level="a">in the Scrapbook, P. 49, of Mr. P. S. Lambros, 130 N. Wells St. Chicago, Ill.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Noted Emissary Here to Oust Greek Bishop</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0364</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0364.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago, Post</title>,
<date when="1930-08-02">Aug. 2, 1930</date>,
<title level="a">in the Scrapbook, P. 49, of Mr. P. S. Lambros, 130 N. Wells St. Chicago, Ill.</title><title level="a" type="sub">NOTED EMISSARY HERE TO OUST GREEK BISHOP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Hot Row Brews</p>
   <p>The Most Reverend Father Damaskinos, ecumenical emissary of the Metropolitan of Corinth, arrived in Chicago today as the guest of Bishop Johannides Philaretos, head of the Greek Archdiocese of Chicago and the Middle West, and will officiate on Sunday at St. Basil's Church, 733 Ashland Avenue.</p>
   <p>Casual readers of this item will find nothing therein to distrub their equilibrium. If the story went no further,the copy desk would write a line, "Greek Prelate in Chicago," and let it go at that.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0365.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But the emissary's visit may be the culmination of a fifteen year feud which has torn the Greek Church in Chicago.</p>
   <p>In the Greek-American community, as you doubtless know if you read the Greek newspapers, the coming of Damaskinos has had somewhat the effect of stirring up an immense ant-hill. It has caused a wave of excitement which has swept from coast to coast.</p>
   <p>And the Greek Star, today is issuing a special edition, sixteen pages crammed full of protests from all parts of America.</p>
   <p>Incidentally the distinguished emissary's visit places Bishop Philaretos, his host in a rather delicate position. The Bishop must be cordial to his guest, even though the guest has come to depose him.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0366.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At St. Basil's Church on Sunday all will be sweetness and light, but deep under the surface hot emotions will be stirring.</p>
   <p>As Peter S. Lambros, Greek-American leader and editor of the Greek Star puts it.</p>
   <p>Constantinople is trying to Romanize the Greek Church in America, but the Greeks in America will not submit to it.</p>
   <p>"Our Church over here is an autonomous body, and you cannot establish a nation within a nation."</p>
   <p>A dramatic incident occurred in Jackson Heights, New York, recently in connection with the emissary's visit.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0367.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Damaskinos presented his demands to Archbishop Alexandros, head of the Orthodox Greek Church of the United States and Canada. When the latter refused to step out, according to the Greek newspapers, Damaskinos offered him $20,000, decorations galore, and a cathedral in Cyprus.</p>
   <p>Came Two Years Ago</p>
   <p>"Damaskinos first came to America two years ago," said Mr. Lambros."</p>
   <p>"He came to collect funds for the relief of the earthquake sufferers in Corinth. He looked around and was impressed by the size and the resources of this country. He saw that the Greek Church was becoming decentralized. He waved the olive branch; then he returned to Corinth to think the situation over."</p>
   <p>"Now he comes as a dictator. He has appointed himself the Mussolini of the Church, proposing to move bishops about at will as if they were pawns on a chessboard.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0368.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>He would have our communities dominated by the Patriarch of Constantinople.</p>
   <p>"But the Greek Church in America will not accept an autocracy which would make the Patriarch supreme."</p>
   <p>"Conditions here are not like those in the Old World. We can accept neither the Patriarch as pope nor Damaskinos as dictator."</p>
   <p>Others on the List.</p>
   <p>The Most Reverend Father Joachim, Bishop of Boston, and the Most Reverend Father Kallistos, Bishop of San Francisco, are said to be the next on the Damaskinos list.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0369.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Archbishop Alexandros, although he stood up for his rights, was officially deposed by Photios II of Constantinople, it is said, without receiving an opportunity to present his case.</p>
   <p>Bishop Vasilios, head of that branch of the Church which still adheres to the Gregorian calendar, was excommunicated but pardoned.</p>
   <p>Thousands of protests against the attempted dictatorship have been received by Mr. Lambros, not only from the clergy but also from the laity including many prominent business-men, civic clubs, and other organizations.</p>
   <p>The other side however, says that the emissary is entirely within his rights whatever action he takes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
