<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1917-12-19">Dec. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Curious Things. the Ignorant Greeks and Their Wise Priests.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0801</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0801.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1917-12-19">Dec. 19, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CURIOUS THINGS. THE IGNORANT GREEKS AND THEIR WISE PRIESTS.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As we have been informed, last week five marriages and nine christenings were performed by our priests, who collected $800 for seven hours' work (to be exact). The commercialized priesthood gathered by the collectionplate method $800 in other words a little over $114 an hour.</p>
   <p>Very, very well, ignorant Greeks; you have started something here in America, and you will have to suffer for it. It is ridiculous and outrageous for the Greek clergy in America to get so much money above their regular salary. It is neither just nor wise to let the priest gain $1,000 a month and to allow the needy families of brother Greeks to go without proper aid. Greek widows and orphans who are too proud to ask Greek societies for help go to the City Hall and get bread, sugar, and coal to mitigate their suffering.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0802.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Bravo Greeks ! Your habit of loading the priests with dollars will eventually corrupt our clergy, and they will no longer differ from the Vatican's highly commercialized priests of the Vatican.</p>
   <p>Very few Greeks in the city know how philanthropically the City Hall cares for needy orphans of every nationality. The Greek is of course a philanthropist, but not in the strictly Christian sense, for he is still a slave to papadocracy or priestcraft. He is so ignorant as to believe that the marriage ceremony and other things are religious sacraments, sanctioned by our Savior Christ...</p>
   <p>And very few Greeks know that the methods practiced by Greek priests in Chicago and elsewhere are not permitted by the Holy Synod of Greece. We advise the clergy not to abuse the ignorance of the people, for we will expose them to the ecclesiastical authorities.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0803.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At last our suggestions and urgings have begun to bear fruit the minds of both the wise clergy and the ignorant laymen; for we were informed a few days ago that a wedding had taken place in the South Side community at which the sum of $236 was collected, but the priest was allowed only $10 out of that, and the balance was given to the groom to distribute to needy people for Christmas. Bravo!</p>
   <p>Let us establish this as our regular procedure. This is philanthropy. The priests are well paid; a hundred dollars a month in salary and three or four times as much in gratuities is sufficient for a priest. My goodness! A thousand dollars a month is too much. If we cut it down to four or five hundred dollars a month, a equal amount will be saved and made available for Christian charity.</p>
   <p>Brother Greeks, go to the City Hall and seek out the widows and orphans not only of Greeks but of all races and help these. That is philanthropy and true service to the Church.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0804.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Our over-paid priests will verify this fact when you ask them for the information. Christmas-time, which is now approaching, it is the duty of each and every Christian to gladden the hearts of the poor, the needy, and the suffering.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
