<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-04-11">Apr. 11, 1931</date>, p. 5
<title level="a">Greek Archdiocese of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0270</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0270.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-04-11">Apr. 11, 1931</date>, p. 5
<title level="a">GREEK ARCHDIOCESE OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago April 4, 1931.</p>
   <p>To the Reverend Clergy, and pious children of the Archdiouse in Christ.</p>
   <p>This year the church being united, and all being brothers in Christ, we pray that our participation in the divine services of Holy Week and Easter be accompanied by a general collection that should be taken for the Ecumenical Patriarchate of our Mother Church in Christ. The pillar of Arthodoxy, owing to innumerable obligations in its universal activities for the welfare of the millions of Christians who are under the scepter of its auspices, needs financial assistance to perpetuate its work in Christ.</p>
   <p>Beloved children in Christ, we know, and sympathize with, the present financial predicament of the world, and you as a part of the whole undoubtly did not escape that devouring fury of the calamity.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0271.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We know, and pray to our Saviour in His great mercy, to guide us to a better condition and state of life.</p>
   <p>In spite of your financial difficulties, and your every day struggle to keep body and soul together, the opportunity is given to you to renew your devotion to the Ecumonical Patriarchate. Here is the occasion for you to manifest all of your love and reverence for the Mother of Arthodoxy in Christ by giving, according to your power, to her financial restoration and to manifest also that you are standing by her side ready to defend her perpetuation.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Clergy will elucidate the appeal to you, and, with the cooperation of presidents of the communities, the collected sums should be forwarded to me at once.</p>
   <p>Being assured of your devotion and love, I wish you the joy of Easter, and my blessing to you all.</p>
   <p>America's</p>
   <p>Athenagoras.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
