<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-08-09">Aug. 9, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Sending of the Legate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0543</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0543.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-08-09">Aug. 9, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE SENDING OF THE LEGATE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1. The news which the telegraph transmitted to us today, about the appointment of the metropolitan Mr. Trapezountos Hresanthou as legate of Greece's Holy Synod for the Greek churches in America, comes as a supplement to our news of the day before yesterday about the recalling of Alexandrou and Vasiliou; for, since the recall of these two ecclesiastical leaders has been decided upon, Greece should also send a prelate to unite the two positions which will have been vacated.</p>
   <p>In reference to the sending of Mr. Hresanthou here as legate for the American Orthodox Churches no doubt the reader remembers that we wrote about such a step long ago. We are sure this demonstrates how truthful the information in the Greek Daily is concerning ecclesiastical matters. It also proves that we have finally succeeded after a great struggle to bring the attention of the Greek government and the patriarchate to our church problems.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0544.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This news of today is of superlative importance for the Hellenism of America because even if it doesn't entirely solve our church problems it is, at any rate, a step in the right direction, and, without a doubt, it - this news - will be received by everybody with delight.</p>
   <p>We are limiting ourselves today to the few comments which we have just made. At a later date we will write again on this important theme.</p>
   <p>The Contradictor</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
