<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-10-31">Oct. 31, 1931</date><title level="a">Church Rules Drawn Up by the Committee of the Archdiocese to Be Submitted for Approval by the Congress of Greek Communities to Be Held in New York on Nov. 16, 1931.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0187</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0187.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-10-31">Oct. 31, 1931</date><title level="a">CHURCH RULES DRAWN UP BY THE COMMITTEE OF THE ARCHDIOCESE TO BE SUBMITTED FOR APPROVAL BY THE CONGRESS OF GREEK COMMUNITIES TO BE HELD IN NEW YORK ON NOV. 16, 1931.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1-Article 1.- By the word "Ecclesia" the "aggregate of the faithful" is meant, and by the word "church" the "Temple of God" is understood. Accordingly, to the Temple of God due reverance is rendered. Every regulation and humble observance is followed with the church. The Priest of the church and the committee--are held responsible for their occurence.</p>
   <p>Article 2.- From now on, only communal churches are to be considered as legitimately established. Private churches are absolutely excluded as per article number three. Exceptions to this rule are the chapels in orphanages, hospitals and old people's homes.</p>
   <p>Article 3.- No church is to be erected, or bought, before the formation of a community and before it has been proven to the Ecclesiastical authority that the community has the funds needed for the erection and maintenance of it.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0188.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Article 4.- There can be more than one church in one city, if the requirements of the community call for it, and if such will not be injurious to the economic interests of others.</p>
   <p>Article 5.- As per suggestion of the Archdiocese all Orthodox Greek Christians must become members of the parishes to which they belong.</p>
   <p>Article 6.- The churches are serving, not only the requirements of religion, but also the educational and philanthropic needs of their members exactly as is provided in the special rules.</p>
   <p>Article 7.- It is the spirit and the letter of this article, that a church can be established only after a petition by Orthodox Greeks, in sufficient numbers is made to the Archdiocese. The new church may then be built only after a specific permit is granted by the Archbishop.</p>
   <p>Article 8.- The supreme leader of the churches is the Archbishop. To him are submitted, unreservedly, all financial and other reports, annually, in regard to philanthropic educational, and social, activities with all details and signed in duplicate.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0189.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If incomes show a decrease, or expenditures are aimless and unjustifiable it is left to the discretion of the Archbishop to actively intervene according to the rights bestowed on him by the Sacred Canons.</p>
   <p>Article 9.- The plans and specifications for every church to be erected are to be, without fail, submitted to the Archbishop by the Committee, the Priest, and, if possible, by the architect, with an itemized estimate of the cost. The Archbishop may point out any change in regard to the plan, location, and cost. Too large an expenditure, one exceeding ability, is not to be encouraged. It is urged that every community for future expediency, when possible, endow its church with an income.</p>
   <p>The same reason is equally applied to the purchase of a lot for the erection of a church, school, or philanthropic institution. The Archdiocese has the right to be consulted as to the purchase of lots, or houses of prayer that can be leased for church services.</p>
   <p>Article 10.- The church of every community once consecrated is considered the church, of that community always, except when the Archbishop thinks otherwise, following a petition submitted by the members in general congregation.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0190.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Article 11.- In case of dissolution of a community, its property in the form of money or real estate, goes to the Archdiocese which, after the lapse of three years, may dispose of the same to the benefit of economic interests of the closest regularly organized Greek Orthodox Church Orthodox Greeks of the same community.</p>
   <p>Article 12.- Every increase of the mortgage of a church must be made known to the Archdiocese before the signing of the contracts.</p>
   <p>Article 13.- If resources permit, and the committee submits the particular petition, there may be employed two or three Priests in the same church. The first one will have the rights of a presiding clerical, as provided for in an act passed in Greece and elsewhere, and the second and third are considered as assistants.</p>
   <p>Article 14.- The pastoral circulars of the Archbishop are always read in the church by the parish Priest according to instructions from the former.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0191.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Article 15.- The church is open every day for Christians, and the Priest is there during assigned hours except for valid reasons. He resides, as close as possible to the church, inasmuch as no residential quarters have been provided for him within the communal building.</p>
   <p>Article 16.- A Singer, or singers, posted in Byzantine music, will be appointed in sufficient numbers recommended by the priest, assigned by the Ecclesiastical committee, and approved by the Archbishop. Singers must be pious and prudent and wear the usual long black clock while in the church.</p>
   <p>Article 17.- The Ikon painting of the church must be entrusted to Ikon artists, graduates of a polytechnic school, posted in Byzantine art and recognized, in writing, by the Archdiocese.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
