<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-02-28">Feb. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The White Flag with Red Stars to the Greek Churches</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1288</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1288.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-02-28">Feb. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE WHITE FLAG WITH RED STARS TO THE GREEK CHURCHES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- Our churches in Chicago are not following the example of other churches in displaying the white flag with red stars. This is perhaps attributable either to humility or to negligence. In either case the Greek churches are not to be excused.</p>
   <p>Churches of all creeds in Chicago are displaying huge white flags with red stars denoting the number of their parishioners who have enlisted in the United States Army. These flags are flying high on the churches and proclaim the glory and honor of those members of the church who have responded to their country's call. And those churches which have the largest number of red stars on their white flags are most remarked and most esteemed by the masses.</p>
   <p>It is an incontrovertible fact that the Greeks, in proportion to their total population, are far ahead of other nationalities in number of <pb facs="5422062_5_1289.jpg" n="2"/>enlistments in the United States Army and Navy, Where are our churches' flags with red stars? Why not render to Caesar that which is Caesar's? The country is at war; why this humility or negligence in displaying the red stars? All elements of the country, from devil to saint, must cooperate for its welfare and its victory. When the country is at war, all its people must become one indivisible body to fight for it, and those who fail to cooperate, on one excuse or another, are enemies of the country. And he who is an enemy should be shot before sunrise.</p>
   <p>To my own knowledge there are Greek churches here which have the right to display more than four hundred red stars, according to the statistics of the community's council. What glory for the church showing four hundred parishioners enlisted in the army of the country!</p>
   <p>It is urgently recommended to the councils of the churches that steps be taken as quickly as possible to raise their red-starred banners.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
