<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1914-01-31">Jan. 31, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">One Hundred and Ninety-Three Patients</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0941</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0941.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-01-31">Jan. 31, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">ONE HUNDRED AND NINETY-THREE PATIENTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to the statistics of the Alexian Brothers Hospital, one hundred and ninety-four Greeks were hospitalized in that institution last year. The thing that is worthy of note is the shocking fact that all the patients registered as Catholics.</p>
   <p>This must be attributed to the fact that very seldom or never has a Greek Orthodox priest visited our sick fellow countrymen in the various hospitals of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The parable of the second coming of Christ says among other things, "I was ill and you visited me; I was in jail and you came to comfort me; I was hungry and you gave me to eat, etc." This same gospel is often read in the Greek churches, but evidently its teachings are not put into practice.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0942.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In our estimation, the failure of our clergy and church leaders to minister to the sick in our community has made a very painful impression on everyone. Much of the propaganda of other religious faiths and much of their proselytizing among us must be attributed to the failure of our clergy to visit the sick, to relieve suffering and poverty, to dispel ignorance, and to destroy sin by active work.</p>
   <p>Many priests and church workers of other religious faiths have taken the opportunity to visit, comfort, and encourage our sick Greek brethren in the hospitals. Why, then, should not they become Catholics or Protestants, when in their most critical hour some Catholic or Protestant has comforted them?</p>
   <p>Many Greeks who have been treated in the Alexian Brothers hospital now feel that it is their duty to attend the Catholic church which is located on the hospital grounds. It is natural that they should do this, since they are only showing their gratitude and thankfulness to those kind Catholics who visited them when they were lying in agony and pain on the hospital bed.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0943.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Many Greeks are deserting the ranks of our Orthodox church. We can only save them by active faith.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
