<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-04-14">Apr. 14, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Orthodox Diocese of North and South America.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0725</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0725.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-04-14">Apr. 14, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK ORTHODOX DIOCESE OF NORTH AND SOUTH AMERICA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To our Clergy and to the Boards of Trustees of the Churches of the Diocese of Chicago:</p>
   <p>In a previous circular letter we made it known that the Ecumenical Patrioarchate has consented to ratify without change, the new constitution of the Greek Orthodox Diocese of North and South America which was drawn up last August by the second general assembly of the Diocese.</p>
   <p>According to article A 1 of this constitution besides the Diocese of New York three more dioceses shall be founded, the Diocese of Boston, the Diocese of Chicago, and the Diocese of San Francisco. According to article B 1 the canon law of the Holy Synod is introduced with the Archbishop as president, and the other three bishops as members.</p>
   <p>According to article 16 of this constitution the Greek Orthodox Diocese of Chicago shall first elect its Bishop in a special ecclesiastical assembly, which shall convene by invitation of the Archbishop and nominate three candidates, choosing them among those clergymen of the Archdiocese who have graduated from <pb facs="5422062_5_0726.jpg" n="2"/>theological seminaries recognized by the Ecumenical Patriarchate and its Holy Synod.</p>
   <p>According to article 12 of this constitution the special ecclesiastical assembly in each of the above mentioned dioceses shall include all the clergymen of the diocese and of one lay representative from each church thereof. These lay delegates shall be organized as an association and shall be elected by the boards of trustees of their several churches.</p>
   <p>Likewise according to the wish and commandment of the Ecumenical Patriarchate, the office of bishop at least in the two Dioceses of Chicago and Boston must be filled without delay. The Diocese of Chicago comes first according to article 16. The election of these bishops and the prompt organization of the Holy Synod of the Archdiocese are imperative for many reasons of an ecclesiastical and nationalistic nature. We must comply with the Patriarchate's wishes and complete the regulation of our activities by forming an ecclesiastical association.</p>
   <p>For this reason we have appointed as the time for the meeting of the ecclesiastical assembly of the Greek Orthodox Diocese of Chicago for 6 P. M. of this <pb facs="5422062_5_0727.jpg" n="3"/>coming Wednesday, Apr. 18, 1923, and the place shall be the Church of St. Constantine, 6105 South Michigan Avenue. We invite thither the clergy of diocese and also all the lay representatives elected by the board of trustees of the churches of the diocese.</p>
   <p>The meeting there assembled shall show by secret ballot a majority vote for one of the three candidates who shall be nominated according to the specifications of the Ecumenical Patriarchate and the Holy Synod, and so shall the Bishop of Chicago be regularly elected.</p>
   <p>Among our clergymen the following persons are qualified to be nominated as candidates: Alexopoulos Ioakim, Argirides Christophoros, Ioannides Philaretos, Mitatakis Simeon, Papaioannes Germanos, Papageorgopoulos Kallistos, Saltas Arsenios, Statheros Constantinos, Smyrnopoulos Damaskinos, Fousianis Methodios.</p>
   <p>Because of the importance of this meeting we are notifying all our clergymen of the Greek Orthodox Diocese of North and South America who belong to the Diocese of Chicago, and we also advise the boards of trustees of the churches that each one of them is expected to send its lay representative.</p>
   <p>We have faith that our invitation and advice will be obediently received for the <pb facs="5422062_5_0728.jpg" n="4"/>benefit of the church, the nation and the godly Hellenism of America . We invoke for you the grace and the peace of God.</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Apr. 9, 1923.</p>
   <p>Your Servant in Christ,</p>
   <p>Alexandros.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
