<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1905-02-17">Feb. 17, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The Affairs of the Greek Community-Topsy-Turvy.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1168</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1168.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1905-02-17">Feb. 17, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">THE AFFAIRS OF THE GREEK COMMUNITY-TOPSY-TURVY.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is two months now since the court ruled that the former by-laws of the community's constitution are null and void, and the new constitution, which was accepted by the court as the right one, should be adopted. But while the community's treasury is in good condition, Dr. G. Papaeliou, president of the community, does not intend to give up without a further fight. So one appeal after the other is made in order to prolong the topsy-turvy condition of the Greek community in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Does that bring you credit and respect, doctor? I should say not! It is not progress, doctor, to prolong the illness of the patient, and you know it. The community needs a Greek school, a gymnasium, a hospital, and many other social and philanthropic institutions, which everywhere in the world are founded in communities much smaller than the Greek community of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1169.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Your appeals to defeat justice and retard the growth and progress of the community are about to be exhausted, and the court will soon order new elections, which should have taken place on December 12, 1906.</p>
   <p>Your presidency of the community, doctor, proved to be incompetent, inefficient, unconscientious, and very disastrous to the treasury. Your refusal to have the books of the community audited reveals either a despotic disposition or a deficit. Doctor, your days in office as president are now numbered, and you shudder at the new constitution, which hangs over you like the sword of Damocles. The new document, doctor, abolishes the office of president and authorizes the appointment, by the court, of an ecclesiastical committee of twelve, under the aegis of the Chicago Greek Consul General, to conduct the affairs of the community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
