<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1928-08-28">Aug. 28, 1928</date><title level="a">Moonlight Dance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0500</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0500.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1928-08-28">Aug. 28, 1928</date><title level="a">MOONLIGHT DANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night the young ladies of the Nea Genea gave us a wonderful dance. The unusualness of the dance made us all glad.</p>
   <p>The beautiful park, the decorated hall, the warm evening, the moon, the stars, the beauty, the joy and happiness surrounding everyone,--all these made it an evening that will not be forgotten for a long time.</p>
   <p>The young ladies of the Nea Genea have a right to be proud of their affair because of its enormous success.</p>
   <p>It is only a few minutes before the Greek Press is to go to the printers, yet we cannot refrain from adding the names of these young ladies who deserve so much praise. The officers are: Stauroula Flouda, president; Basiliki Batsaki, vice-president; Angeline Markoutsa, secretary; Helen Kardara, treasurer. The members are: Konsantina Soulantzis, Bas. and Sophia Stamos, Tasia Tsamou, Mary Hoida, D. Chronis, Mary Psihalinos, K. Mitsoula, P. Manios, S. Mouzakiotis, M. Collins, B. Spirrison, Georgia Chronis, D. Kefaliotis, D. Chronis, G. Barrela, Amalia and Catherine Bossina, Christina Georgakopoulos, Froso Georgakapoulos, <pb facs="5422062_5_0501.jpg" n="2"/>Georgia Giannopoulos, Theodora Doukas, Catherine Thaniotis, E. Kardara, Helen Lampros, Venette and Joanna Lempesi, A. Markoutsa, E. Mitos, B. and T. Petrakis, P. and A. Petropoulos, and Helen Passialis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
