<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-04-13">Apr. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Celebration of the Ninety-Seventh Anniversary of Greek Independence Mr. Constantine Mammonas Appeals for the Third Liberty Loan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0789</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0789.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-04-13">Apr. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CELEBRATION OF THE NINETY-SEVENTH ANNIVERSARY OF GREEK INDEPENDENCE Mr. Constantine Mammonas Appeals for the Third Liberty Loan</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday the ninety-seventh anniversary of Greek Independence was solemnly commemorated and celebrated in all the Greek Orthodox Churches of Chicago.</p>
   <p>It happened that on the same day the Greek Orthodox Churches honored the Annunciation of Blessed Mary and the Adoration of the Cross. At all church services of the three Greek churches of Chicago there were huge crowds of people. Flowers were distributed by the priests.</p>
   <p>In all churches, which had been beautifully decorated with Greek and American flags, appropriate speeches were delivered. The celebrations were especially magnificent in the Metropolitan Church of Holy Trinity, the pastor of which is one of the most distinguished clergymen of Chicago, the Right <pb facs="5422062_5_0790.jpg" n="2"/>Reverend Leon Pygeas.</p>
   <p>In this church two speeches were made. One speech, concerning the Liberty Loan campaign was made at the beginning of the service by our distinguished citizen, scholar, and orator, Mr. Constantine Palaeologos Mammonas, director of the Greek-Italian division of the great Chicago Central Trust Company of Illinois, 125 West Monroe Street. Another panegyric was delivered after the doxology by the brilliant teacher [name not given] of our greatest Greek educational institution on the West Side. Speeches for the Liberty Loan campaign were delivered in the other churches also.</p>
   <p>Below we are publishing the speech delivered by Mr. Constantine Palaeologos Mammonas for the Liberty Loan. This speech was, as usual, given extemporaneously.</p>
   <p>"Right Reverend Father, Brethren in Christ: Today we are participating in <pb facs="5422062_5_0791.jpg" n="3"/>two national and two religious celebrations. The two ecclesiastical ceremonies are the Annunciation of the Blessed Mary, and the Adoration of the Cross. The two national celebrations are the commemoration of our Greek National Independence, and the beginning of the great Liberty Loan drive for the preservation of American freedom.</p>
   <p>"The object and purpose of these four occasions which have so happily coincided are sacred and blessed, for they aim to ensure the blessings of liberty and humanity.</p>
   <p>"The celebration of the Annunciation of the Blessed Mary is a sacred occasion, for it reminds us of the Lord's Angel, who descended from Heaven and appeared before Virgin Mary saying: 'Rejoice, thou hast been favored, the Lord is with you!' On this occasion it was announced to the Virgin Mary that, through the grace of the Holy Ghost, she shall conceive the Savior and Redeemer of Humanity, the destroyer of idolatry.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0792.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"The celebration of the Adoration of the Cross is a sacred event, for by the Holy Cross and crucifixion we are reminded of the sufferings that Jesus Christ underwent and the patience that He demonstrated in His struggle for the sake of His divine principles. The Cross reminds us of the sacrifice He made for the prevalence and freedom of Christianity.</p>
   <p>"The celebration of our National Independence is also a sacred occasion because, on the twenty-fifth of March 1821, the flag of our independence was raised in Agia Laura by Bishop Germanos, and the church bells together with the echoes of the guns announced to the tyrants the resurrection of the Greek people, and that they had decided to win their freedom.</p>
   <p>"The celebration of the beginning of the Third Liberty Loan drive is also a sacred undertaking, because we are called upon to give our material and moral support for the construction and use of the means by which freedom will be returned to those Christian peoples that have been enslaved by the conqueror.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0793.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We are asked to frustrate the barbarous and anti-Christian aims of blood thirsty subjugators of nations who are seeking by iron and fire to deprive humanity of its freedom. We are seeking to re-establish and fortify the ideas of Christianity in a struggle against infidel barbarians and followers of Satan.</p>
   <p>"Another gentleman will speak to you about the importance of the first three religious and national anniversaries. I have been asked by the Federal Liberty Loan Committee, through its Greek division, to speak to you about the object and significance of the Third Liberty Loan. I deem it an honor and an imposed duty to do so.</p>
   <p>"Again, gentlemen, the bell of liberty calls the loyal and devoted sons to their duty. The performance of this duty is demanded by our benefactor, our beloved adopted country, in which we are living and enjoying all the blessing's of liberty, and in which we are reaping all those fruits which are being justly distributed under the same laws to all the people of this great <pb facs="5422062_5_0794.jpg" n="6"/>and glorious country. With respect and in agony do all our brothers in our homeland, the struggling peoples on the European and Asiatic continents, who are fighting desperately, look to this country, expecting it to offer support in men and instruments of war. Support from this country will decide the disastrous war which is ravaging the entire world, and which bloodthirsty and tyrannical peoples have caused in order to subjugate and enslave us and the peoples of the earth.</p>
   <p>"Loyal and faithful men, aroused by this bell's call to duty, are enlisting in the army and navy, ready to sacrifice themselves on the altar of freedom. Those who are not favored by being called to active service by the draft ballot, are asked to give their material support. Thus, we will equip, supply, and strengthen the soldiers who are fighting for our freedom. In this way, we will obtain the means by which our cherished hope, the victory of our army and the defeat of the enemy, will be realized. This is the only way we can secure our freedom.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0795.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"The bell is rung, warning us of the danger, by those of us who have been authorized to guard and provide for the three most precious possessions of our personal and national existence: that is, our life, our property, and our freedom, without which human existence is not possible or tolerable.</p>
   <p>"Who are they? Our government. And what does it say to us? Exactly what our ancient Greek ancestors used to say: 'There is need of money without which,nothing can be done.'</p>
   <p>"To whom will this money be given? To the government. And who is it [the government]? We, ourselves, who are being represented by it in national and administrative affairs. Why are they asking for this money? In order to protect and defend our national freedom and independence and, there-fore, for the serving of our own interests.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0796.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>"And what is freedom? The absolute right to think and act according to the laws. What is the advantage derived from justice? It is the most absolute and greatest of all good, representing the happiness and welfare of the individual.</p>
   <p>"Can there exist any moral, material, or national good without freedom? No, gentlemen, because freedom is the master of all these things. Is there anyone who will hesitate to offer a small part of his material wealth, which is inconsequential, and tolerate even the thought of losing his personal and moral freedom?</p>
   <p>"Who is so foolish and ignorant that he will not dare to spend a part to save the whole? Permit me to say, no one.</p>
   <p>"But what does our government ask? The part or the whole? How is it [the money] asked? To be donated or lent? By whom is this asked, and for what <pb facs="5422062_5_0797.jpg" n="9"/>purpose? These are the questions that I repeat to you.</p>
   <p>"We are asked to give that part of our money which we are able to lend for the protection of our freedom, happiness, and wealth. Are we under obligation to do this? Most certainly, and under a most sacred one at that, for we have gained our material prosperity in this land, we live in this land, and with the help of this land, we will secure our freedom and prosperity.</p>
   <p>"But, there may be some who will say to themselves: 'We are Greeks and want to keep our money in our pockets or in our strong boxes to enjoy it when we return to Greece.'</p>
   <p>"I will answer these gentlemen. It is true that we are Greeks by birth and descent and we should be proud of it, because Greece was the cradle of civilization and the sacred temple of freedom. We must never forget, however, <pb facs="5422062_5_0798.jpg" n="10"/>that we are also American citizens; that we live and work in America. So we have two glorious fatherlands, the one is our natural and the other our adopted country, both of which we are proud of. Besides, both countries are struggling together with the same common purpose, the freedom and safety of their people, who are threatened by the great barbarous and Teutonic cataclysm. By the money which is being given, even our fatherland will be benefited and relieved, for our adopted country will offer much-needed help to it.</p>
   <p>"Under these circumstances, beginning tomorrow, all must hasten to buy Liberty bonds, which are sacred papers. The purchaser of a fifty-dollar bond must pay two and one-half dollars down and two dollars weekly for twenty-two weeks. On the last week, which begins on October 14, 1918, $3.25 will be paid.</p>
   <p>"I am willing to answer any question in regard to the procedure of purchasing Liberty Loan bonds, for I am connected with the Central Trust Company of Illinois and have experience in such matters. So, I advise you to purchase <pb facs="5422062_5_0799.jpg" n="11"/>these bonds because you are both helping your country and making a good safe investment.</p>
   <p>"I announce to you with pleasure that His Excellency the Ambassador of Greece to the United States, Mr. George Rousos, is coming here to emphasize the importance of the Third Liberty Loan campaign. He will speak in Orchestra Hall, 216 South Michigan Avenue, so all must receive him with great pleasure, and respect. Paul Shorey, the distinguished Professor of Classics at the University of Chicago, will also speak at this meeting. His Excellency the Governor of Illinois may also be present. Jacque's famous band of three hundred pieces will play. On the same evening, a dinner will be given in honor of Ambassador Rousos by the National Security League in the magnificent La Salle Hotel.</p>
   <p>"Assured that you will all do your duty, as good patriots and true Americans, I urge you to buy the sacred Liberty bonds and I now ask you to shout with me:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0800.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>Hurrah for Greece! Hurrah for our glorious and great adopted country, America! Hurrah for Liberty!"</p>
   <p>The great crowd started shouting joyfully and enthusiastically, while the Reverend Leon Pygeas and the excellent Church choir continued with the Church service with elaborate and most imposing ceremonies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
