<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1914-03-07">Mar. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Go to Church on Sunday!</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Paul Demos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0917</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0917.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-03-07">Mar. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">GO TO CHURCH ON SUNDAY!</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Paul Demos</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What an excellent piece of advice! All have raised their voices with this precious admonition on their lips. Everyone has understood that the church is the only road to salvation for all peoples. We have become accustomed to church habits and practices. Small and large newspapers, periodicals, all sorts of literature; teachers, priests, preachers, and wise men, are urging the people to adhere to the unshakeable institution of the church.</p>
   <p>We now pose the question: Do we attend church regularly? And if not, why not? Do we profit any by going to church?</p>
   <p>Let us stop and think what benefits we derive from the church. Regardless of whether we differ in regard to the interpretation and the way of expressing our religious conceptions and beliefs, there is a common <pb facs="5422062_5_0918.jpg" n="2"/>spiritual bond which unites us all in worshiping a common Father and a common beneficent and almighty heavenly deity. This common feeling finds perfect expression in the work and symbolic ceremonies of the church.</p>
   <p>Nowhere else can we hope to receive the grace of God and learn how to practice the Christian ideals of love, hope, and faith. It is with the help and inspiration of God that we make the relationships among our fellow human beings more perfect. It is in the church that we have the best opportunity to communicate directly with God.</p>
   <p>No one can object to these thoughts. Our present civilization has been fashioned and created by religion. Did not the ancient Greek civilization begin with religion? Did not the ancient Greeks revere and sacrifice everything, if need be, to their gods? Did not Abraham offer his beloved son as a sacrifice to God? To whom do we Greeks owe our freedom and our present happy state of prosperity and national greatness: Who is responsible for the preservation and salvation of our sacred national ideals, <pb facs="5422062_5_0919.jpg" n="3"/>traditions, and culture? The church and our clergy have given us our freedom; they have preserved and protected our national heritage; they have defended us from all enemies; they have fought undaunted for our rights as Orthodox Christians, as Greeks, as civilized human beings.</p>
   <p>Our priests must be highly respected, for they are as the Apostles of Jesus Christ: they have been divinely delegated to disseminate and spread the word of God among all peoples and all nations. The forerunners of our priests of today, the monks of the monasteries, taught and preserved our language. Many a time they ran to the mountains with valuable books and manuscripts where they lived and taught for years, thus avoiding capture and saving priceless volumes and manuscripts. Through the church, these men kept the spiritual and intellectual lights burning and prevented them from being irretrievably extinguished. It was the silent, patient, and pious priest who gave the enslaved Greeks hope and courage, by keeping alive their faith in a just God, during four long and indescribably dark centuries of slavery and tyranny. It was a priest who first gave the <pb facs="5422062_5_0920.jpg" n="4"/>long-awaited signal for our people to rise and fight for their freedom in 1821.</p>
   <p>It was a priest (Patriarch Gregory of Constantinople) who suffered himself to be hanged and desecrated by the barbarous Turk horde while defending the sacred rights and ideals of the Greek subjects.</p>
   <p>So, we have cause to be grateful to our church, to its servants, to its glorious past and revered history. We should all attend church, for it is within her bosom that we shall find strength and comfort in our efforts to serve our people and humanity.</p>
   <p>It is not too late to acquire the habit of going to church. God will forgive those who remember Him and return to Him.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
