<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-07-05">July 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Degradation of Archbishop Vasilios by Order of the Holy Synod</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0667</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0667.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-07-05">July 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">DEGRADATION OF ARCHBISHOP VASILIOS BY ORDER OF THE HOLY SYNOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.-1-....Order of the Holy Synod of the Ecumenical Patriarchate for the degradation of Vasilios Komyopoulos, Archbishop of Methymnes and Metropolitan of Haldea.</p>
   <p>To wit: They Holy Synod, judging the accused in absentia finds him guilty as charged and announces: That by unanimous vote the Holy Synod finds that he is guilty of act against the cannons as charged and must therefore be punished of these violations; That the Synod by a majority vote imposes the penalty of degradation from the office of archbishop and from the rank of clergyman and restores him to the class of the laity; That the Synod orders the service of this decree on the degraded clergyman by the Greek Archdiocese of North and South America and through publication of the decree in one Greek newspaper and one American newspaper in America; and That the Synod gives him the privilege to use legal means to defend himself before its tribunal.</p>
   <p>Indited, announced, and done on the same day, whereto witness: The Patriarch of Constantinople, Kyzikou Kallinikos, Nikaeas Vasilios, Halkidonos Ioakim, Derkon Constantionos, Pringeponeson Agathagelos, Neokaesaraeas Hambrosios, Philippoupoleos Veniamim, Philadelphias Fotios, Varnes Nikodemos, Selyvarias Eugenios, Phodopoleos Kyrillos, and Aneon Thomas.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0668.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Patriarchate, May 17, 1924.</p>
   <p>The First Secretary of the Holy Synod,</p>
   <p>Diaconos Dorotheos Georgiades.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
