<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-04-12">April 12, 1924</date>, p. 2
<title level="a">Regretable Incident in St. Constantine Church Provoked by Publisher of Greek Daily.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Our Dutiful Answer.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0674</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0674.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-04-12">April 12, 1924</date>, p. 2
<title level="a">REGRETABLE INCIDENT IN ST. CONSTANTINE CHURCH PROVOKED BY PUBLISHER OF GREEK DAILY.</title><title level="a" type="sub">OUR DUTIFUL ANSWER.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the Daily's issues of March 26, 27, 28 and 29, the publisher, Mr. Sp. Kotakis, published a lot of myths and vagaries regarding the unpleasant incident in the church of St. Constantine where our National Holiday was celebrated. Undoubtedly Mr. Kotakis does not as yet realize that he was the cause and perpetrator of the unpleasant occurrence.</p>
   <p>The official program, of the celebration of the Anniversary of Greek Independence, was published and of which the Consul General was informed to attend.</p>
   <p>In the program it was fixed that the religious speech would be delivered by the Right Rev. Philaretos, and the panegyric speech by Mr. Michael Galanos.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0675.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As usually is the case, the Consul General is supposed to deliver a speech, which he did. Also in the program was announced that the pupils of Koraes school will participate and sing in the doxology and national hymn.</p>
   <p>The program was approved and confirmed by the executive council of the church. It was formulated, with the consent of the Bishop, by Dr. K. Theodorou, chairman of the council, who suggested that Mr. Galanos, while in Chicago, be invited to deliver the panegyric speech. The Bishop agreed to the suggestion.</p>
   <p>On such important holidays it is a known and accepted fact, that the program of the celebration must function precisely as it is fixed. But Mr. Kotakis, who appeared at the church during the last moment, declared that he wanted to speak.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0676.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The president of the church informed Mr. Kotakis that it would be impossible, owing to the fact that he was not on the program, and that he (the president) did not wish to abuse the patience of the people by adding one more orator on the already crowded list of three. Mr. Kotakis insisted that he wanted to deliver a speech announcing the declaration of Democracy in Greece. The president endeavored to avoid a commotion advising Mr. Kotakis that such an action would indicate that he Mr. Kotakis, is very much enthused and interested in the event in Greece, and that the Consul General was not. He further advised the militant Mr. Kotakis, that the people already heard the news of the event, through newspapers and other public announcements, and that the Consul General would announce the event when he would be officially notified.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0677.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Unfortunately, Mr. Kotakis, the veteran of many speeches who knows all the rules and regulations governing such events, became boisterous and when the audience began to murmur its disapproval, the Bishop, for the sake of peace discipline and dignity of the church, beseeched Mr. Kotakis to change his mind.</p>
   <p>The publisher categorically refused to retreat from his purpose, and then the president of the church informed him, in stern Greek, that under no consideration he would permit Mr. Kotakis to speak, because the order and discipline of the church was in the hands of the executive council who would not tolerate any disturbance.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kotakis remained unmoved in his determination to create a scandal, and when Mr. Galanos was taking his place to deliver the panegyric Mr. Kotakis, disregarding order and decency, jumped upon a pew and began to speak.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0678.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>To the dismay of the audience, the president and the council, their faces red from indignation, again implored him to stop, but Mr. Kotakis ignored them and continued to speak, until some people in the audience near him lost their patience and compelled him to cease talking.</p>
   <p>This is the naked truth and all the audience witnessed it. In regards to Bishop Philaretos, who endeavored to frustrate disorder, no one present will say otherwise save Mr. Kotakis. The stories published in the Daily against the Right Rev. Philaretos, holding him responsible for the incident, are not true but are purely vagaries.</p>
   <p>The rest of the stories of the incident are not worthy of an answer.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0679.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Mr. Kotakis for some reason does not consult his reason when he publishes accusations, and it appears that he does not read his newspaper either. A few months ago, not only did he publish many articles praising the character and the hierarchical guidance of the bishop, but he also delivered a surprisingly fiery speech at the La Salle Hotel, in behalf of the newly created bishop.</p>
   <p>We wish to believe that Mr. Kotakis was in a state of psychical turmoil when he dictated those articles of vituperation which some opportunity-seeking sharks of scandal, utilized for their own interest and gain.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0680.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>We wish further to believe that in the immediate future Mr. Kotakis will recognize his error and wish then that he had not published those myths and vagaries.</p>
   <p>The Executive Council</p>
   <p>K. Theodorou, President</p>
   <p>E. Kotsonis, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
