<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-05-31">May 31, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Meeting of the Greek Community</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1086</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1086.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-05-31">May 31, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE MEETING OF THE GREEK COMMUNITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With forty charter members and as many more non-registered members, the much heralded meeting of the Chicago Greek Community took place last Thursday, at the Masonic Temple.</p>
   <p>Reports were made and accounts were given by the officers of the community. Those who were present approved and commended the activities and doings of the administration.</p>
   <p>Among the many things discussed, the establishment of a fourth church took most of the time. The discussion of the establishment of a Greek school was so brief and so quickly shelved, our reporter did not have time to turn a sheet in his notebook.</p>
   <p>What an irony! Our eloquent speakers of the Greek community, who are known to be chips of old Demosthenes when debates in the abstract take place, <pb facs="5422062_5_1087.jpg" n="2"/>could not find words to praise the establishment of the Greek school, which our community needs. Indeed not. Their talent of rhetoric is only for abstract things, and not for mere material things. Indeed, great minds who explore the universe with their rhetorical prowess, will not stoop so low as to permit themselves to discuss a mere and insignificant thing like the establishment of a Greek school in Chicago.</p>
   <p>What a shame! Is not this a paradox?</p>
   <p>The immortal Greek language, the instrument of expression for ancient and modern gods, for expounders of divinity, for rhetoricians, and for great thinkers, and which, paradoxically is taught in the very institution the Greek meeting failed to discuss; the Greek school.</p>
   <p>Educators, lawyers, doctors, and theologians were present at the meeting of last Thursday. Not one of them dared to touch upon this important subject.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1088.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But for the establishment of a fourth church, plenty was said.</p>
   <p>Our youngsters, who through our negligence are deprived of the opportunity to learn the language of the gospel, will think unfavorably of the present fathers of the community when they attend Greek churches not knowing what it is all about.</p>
   <p>As generally is the case, important things are always overlooked and neglected by us humans, so in the present case the importance of the establishment of a Greek school is set aside and things of secondary importance and value are discussed first.</p>
   <p>The Star will continue to bring before our eyes the necessity of the Greek school, hoping that the time will not be far away when the fathers of the <pb facs="5422062_5_1089.jpg" n="4"/>community will see as well as we do the absolute need of establishing the Greek school for our present and coming generations.</p>
   <p>Now, Greeks the world over who want to uplift their intellectual faculties study the Greek tongue, while the Greeks of Chicago until now have deprived their future intellectuals of the opportunity to study the immortal and divine language. What a paradox?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
