<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-10-04">Oct. 4, 1930</date><title level="a">To Reunite Chicago Communities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0326</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0326.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGO GREEK DAILY</title>,
<date when="1930-10-04">Oct. 4, 1930</date><title level="a">TO REUNITE CHICAGO COMMUNITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The president of the West Side Association called a membership meeting to pass on and grant authorization to the Most Rev. Legate for a regulation limiting the number of churches in Chicago, as per the resolution adopted by all the presidents of Chicago communities, when called upon by the Most Rev. Legate to confer on the question of limiting churches that have been established due to the ecclesiastical division and which have, no longer, any reason for existence.</p>
   <p>We urge all the other sections to follow the example of the West Section, as per their promise to the Legate, and the protocol that their representatives signed, so that they may be ready on the return of the Legate, who will be here the middle of October to discuss the most important matter of saving our churches and schools from financial disaster.</p>
   <p>Certainly, the question of limiting the number of churches is not so easy, no matter how urgent the need is considered by all, but the difficulties, and the different conceptions, about the manner in which the limitation will be</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0327.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>effected, must give way before the precipice of economic disaster, towards which we are heading. Rather general thoughts must prevail and community spirit with personal ambitions must be set aside, for, what is dictated by necessity must be done. It is fortunate that the Legate undertook the burdensome task of arbitration in differences that would come up, and made his final decision on them so easy, when we, ourselves, would never have reached a decision on how to straighten them out.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, there are many things which dissension among the churches did not let us, up to now, enforce. However, now, that all of us have one ecclesiastical authority, the forming of a Central Committee in which all communities are to be represented, should be in order. This Central Committee would then discuss and vote on and clean up general matters.</p>
   <p>All this certainly could be easily attained even if we do not resolve to form one Community.</p>
   <p>In any case we believe that it is possible to come to an understanding</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0328.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>and we urge the presidents of the Communities to call their individual members to a meeting so as to be authorized to start the transactions.</p>
   <p>(Literal)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
