<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-05-09">May 9, 1931</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Courage.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1736</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1736.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-05-09">May 9, 1931</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">COURAGE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek race besides its other characteristics is distinguished for its courage. Men and women alike are found to be very courageous. They have not only the physical courage, which distinguished Greeks on the battle front, but spiritual courage.</p>
   <p>Courage is a divinegift. It takes courage to be just and give justice, it takes courage to fight temptations, to tell the truth, to do right, to govern and to believe in the true God. It takes courage of body and soul to do anything worthwhile.</p>
   <p>Bravery and courage are not synonymous. On the impulse of the moment one may show bravery, but it does not establish the fact that the person is courageous.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1737.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Every progress, in the annals of history, is based upon courage, courage which includes patience, deliberation stability and right thinking.</p>
   <p>It was courage in the case of the greatest philosopher, Socrates who defied the Judges and told them they were foolish to condemn him to die. It was courage that fortified him to resist the pressure of the Judges, and that of the people who could not understand him. He refused to be smuggled away, when one of his pupils bribed the Jail guard and he died with the immortal words "The time is at hand to be separated; I to die, and you to live. Which of the two is better God, only, knows."</p>
   <p>Many philosophers, scientist, and God advocating people, were persecuted in the name of religion, bias and superstition all over the world. Those persecuted martyrs of all the nations are exemplified by their courage, and stand today as pillars of the human edifice.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1738.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It was courage that made the two Spartans refuse to kneel before the great King of the Persians; "The Great King," as he was called, not knowing the courage of the Greeks, sent two messengers to demand from them a surrender of land and sea. The Greeks, contrary to prevailing rules angered by the humiliating demand to surrender did away with the two messengers.</p>
   <p>The infuriated King sent other messengers to remind the Greeks of prevailing rules concerning the immunity of messengers demanded an apology and above all a surrender of arms. The Greeks acknowledging their error in slaying the messengers agreed to send two Spartans to be killed by the Persian King in retaliation.</p>
   <p>The two Spartans were brought before the King and ordered to kneel before him in salutation.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1739.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>They refused to kneel or to bow their heads saying, "We came to be killed and not to bow. Greeks bow only before God, not before a human." This episode distinguish these two youths of Sparta, whose men and women are known the world over for the courage they possess.</p>
   <p>In ordinary life it is courage, and not bravery, that makes a man say "No" when the odds are against him. Unfortunately, few of us possess courage. We are afraid of this and of that and we become nothing but parrots. We have not the courage to tell the truth, lest we hurt the feelings of somebody. We dress act and live according to established rules of society. We flatter and want to be flattered. Due to lack of courage we are not ourselves but strange creatures. We become serfs and "yes men" owing to lack of courage. We prefer to become unjust rather than lose our popularity. Why? Because it is easier to bow and flatter, than to be high-minded, noble-hearted and determined. It requires power courage and determination to swim up stream, whereas, even an inanimate object can navigate down-stream.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1740.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The desire for popularity has reached its zenith. This tendency has become so great that the morals of political men are absent. Consciences have become more elastic.</p>
   <p>The same moral cowardice is prevalent amongst high and low levels of society. The hypocricy and debasement of the high levels are followed by the hypocricy and debasement of the low levels. If the so called moguls of society have not the courage to openly express their opinions what can be expected of the low elements?</p>
   <p>Mental courage is an indispensible factor in maintaining independence of character. Coinciding, with the sayings of A-or B-, in order to be in harmony and accord is mental cowardice, not politeness. Courageous men rule and govern the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1741.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The courageous man is noblehearted and minded chivalrous to his enemies. History gives many examples of chivalry among generals, in the midst of furious battles.</p>
   <p>From what we have already said, it becomes very clear that courage is the corner stone of character. Intellectual giants, or ordinary people, are one and the same if they have no character.</p>
   <p>The Spartan mother sending her son to war on handing him his shield said "Come back with it or upon it." You see determined courage, not bravery, in the words of the Spartan woman.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
