<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-09-04">Sept. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Needs of Our Community</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0598</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0598.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-09-04">Sept. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEEDS OF OUR COMMUNITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- The Greek community in Chicago, largest of the Greek communities in America and distinguished for its patriotic sentiment, is not in a very pleasant condition from the communal aspect. The North Side, embroiled in court with its former rector, has expended more than a few thousand dollars, and still the litigation is not ended. The West Side has been in need of a new church for a long time and realizing it has labored toward that end, but so far it has not succeeded in accomplishing its object. The South Side has been literally without church or school since the burning of its church.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately it will cost many hundreds of thousands of dollars to build these churches; and the economic situation is not very encouraging to the attainment of this end. However, neither the West Side nor the South Side can remain without a church because the West Side's existing church is not only insufficient for its future needs but in the condition in which it stands is no honor to the Greek community; and as for the South Side the <pb facs="5422062_5_0599.jpg" n="2"/>erection of a church is a matter of absolute necessity.</p>
   <p>Because of our great concern for Hellenism in Chicago we have not undertaken to deal with this subject heretofore; on the West Side the erection of a church was so sure that it seemed an accomplished fact, and we therefore did not think that it would be to the interest of the community to deal with this matter, for we feared that a public examination might place obstacles in the way of its achievement. We took the same attitude with reference to the South Side district. But this condition of churchless districts cannot continue, and since so much time has passed without accomplishment, we have decided that it is our duty to abandon our reserve and to proceed with a thorough investigation of the matter. We propose to arouse the interest of the members of the community so that the object in view may be achieved; that is, the erection of churches on the South Side and on the West Side.</p>
   <p>Now we wish to have it understood that we have stirred up this subject so important to our interests for only one purpose, - to lighten the work of the committees which undertook this very strenuous and difficult task.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0600.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On this matter we will first try to get the opinions of those members of our community who have taken part in communal work before; they are in a position to give opinions and to drive at the mark.</p>
   <p>We shall begin this thorough investigation within a few weeks, and we are confident that we shall help to hasten the church-building. It is something which has been considered absolutely necessary for a long time. The reason why it has not been accomplished is that interest has been lacking. People do not show the interest which is necessary for the execution of large community projects. In fact, though one observes much progress in the private enterprises of Chicago Greeks, one does not see such progress reflected in their communal undertakings. Now it must be understood that it is not permissible for so prosperous, flourishing, and successful a community to lag behind in its communal problems, and it is no credit to the enterprising and businesslike Chicago Greeks to consider churches, schools, hospitals, and clubs - institutions which always advertise the race before foreign people's eyes - as unworthy enterprises.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0601.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We believe that it is about time for us to rouse ourselves from the stupor which has overwhelmed us and to begin to take an interest in community projects. Without these projects it is impossible for us to appear as a large, flourishing, and prosperous community, - a community which claims to be first among Greek communities in America.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
