<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-07-27">July 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">The Constitution of the Church Brings Peace</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0127</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0127.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-07-27">July 27, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">THE CONSTITUTION OF THE CHURCH BRINGS PEACE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 1.--It is about a year since the new constitution of the Greek Orthodox Church in America was drawn up and ratified by the Ecumenical Patriarchate. This constitution has now been printed and sent back to the Greek communities to be put in effect.</p>
   <p>By applying this new constitution we shall end the chaotic condition of the Greek Orthodox Church in America, which was created by the dissension of political factions in the churches.</p>
   <p>These factions turned religious organizations into battlefields of political antagonism.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0128.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The new constitution has been made as nearly perfect as possible in its details and in its regulation of the various activities of the Church. It provides the first sound and stable basis for this venerable institution and guarantees a united, well-governed, and well-disciplined Greek Orthodox Church. It is hoped that the constitution will be the shining lighthouse of which the beam will save us from religious shipwreck.</p>
   <p>The adoption of this new constitution by every Greek community and by the Greek Orthodox Church will terminate that anarchy which has now prevailed for years, and which has been expleited by every profit-seeker.</p>
   <p>The Right Reverend Archbishop Athenagoras the task has been assigned of applying this new constitution. Archbishop Athenagoras, in the short time of his administration here, has shown ability, tolerance, and charity worthy of the confidence and trust which the Hellenism of America has placed in him.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0129.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The communities one after another are meeting and adopting this new fundamental law which was worked out almost to perfection by the Church's representatives in the assembly of the clergy and the laity to fit the unique conditions of the Orthodox Church in America. All that the communities have to do is to ratify formally the constitution drawn up by their own representatives.</p>
   <p>It is about time to end partisanship and discord in Greech churches and to surrender the government of the Church to those who are entitled to govern it--the clergy. Too much meddling of the laity in church affairs is what caused the recent disorders in the Church. Now let us allow the clergy to govern the Church and see whether they will measure up to their task and take good care of their flocks!</p>
   <p>The adoption of this new constitution, besides curbing the interference of the laity in church affairs, will concentrate the government of the Church in one leader who will be responsible for his acts to the Nation, the Church, and to history, and we are sure that no one will dare to put any obstacles in the way <pb facs="5422062_5_0130.jpg" n="4"/>of such a leader.</p>
   <p>The time has come for the Greeks and the Orthodoxy of America to take thought of what impression they make on their environment and to prove that the race and the language which received Christianity and spread it all over the former world of barbarians are still the salt of the earth, and that they can again make practical application of the ideals, and the high teachings of Christianity of its virtues and its principles, in this country at the present time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
