<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-06-13">June 13, 1931</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Monstrous Historical Inaccuracies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1732</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1732.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-06-13">June 13, 1931</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">MONSTROUS HISTORICAL INACCURACIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In justice to Greek history, in justice to the masterpieces of the creative Greek mind, and for the enlightenment of those pseudo-authorities in historical lore, we write this article, hoping that the monstrous inaccuracies blazoned in the New York Newspaper, will be corrected.</p>
   <p>The great publication, The New York Times, last Monday, published a telegram sent by its correspondent of Athens. It said:</p>
   <p>"The merchanical genius of the ancient Romans and that of the modern Americans, in unison, made its manifestation at the official inauguration of the new hydraulic works of Marathon, which, with the Andrian acqueduct, that was built 1800 years ago, will, in the future supply Athens, Peraeus and the suburbs, with the necessary quantity of water.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1733.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Venizelus, Prime Minister, opened the fountain, which was specifically made for the ceremony, at the remains of the great Temple of Zeus, underneath the portal of Adrian.</p>
   <p>Athens, Peraeus and the suburbs, with their present population of over one million, had obtained, for the last 1,800 years, their water supply from the aqueduct which was built by Emperor Adrian, 115 A.D. when Greece was under Roman sovereignty. In spite of the great admiration to ancient Greece, by America and the whole world, for her architectural masterpieces, America, knew more in regard to water works and hydraulics, than the Greeks. The aqueduct was sufficient to supply water for a population of 200,000, and it is so well built that it is as useful, today as it was in ancient times. Noteworthy of the hydraulic works is the dam of Marathon, which, it is said, is the only dam in the world made entirely of marble.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1734.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The different kinds of marble came from the famous marble mines of "Penteli" the dam is one thousand feet long."</p>
   <p>The Athens correspondent of the New York Times, were he not entirely non-historical, would have been able to know, that the Adrian aqueduct, built 1800 years ago is purely, from top to bottom, a product of Greek craft. The architect, engineer and workers were Greeks, according to the very explicit language of historical data. The only thing connected with the Roman name, is the money. Emperor Adrian appropriated the money for the construction of the dam. If we take into consideration the history of dams, in Europe and America, we find it is shorter than one century, the 1800 year life of the Adrian aqueduct therefore is a miracle of the Greek mechanical mind.</p>
   <p>The Times correspondent also tells us that the Adrian dam is the only marble-made aqueduct in the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1735.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This second inaccuracy is just as huge as the first one, the fact is that this eminent correspondent is lacking historical knowledge. The marble-made aqueduct at the shores of Bosporus, built, over 1000 years ago, which is a masterpiece of mechanical ingenuity and art, is not known to the correspondent of the "Times."</p>
   <p>This Byzantine artifical lake for over ten centuries supplied the inhabitants of Constantinople with water. This is for the enlightenment of the Times correspondent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
