<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1907-03-08">Mar. 8, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Society of Family Men of Chicago and Their Priest Cyril Georgeadis, Archimandrite</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1107</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1107.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-03-08">Mar. 8, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE SOCIETY OF FAMILY MEN OF CHICAGO AND THEIR PRIEST CYRIL GEORGEADIS, ARCHIMANDRITE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In order not to be caught in the ecclesiastical imbroglio of the Greek community in Chicago, which is demoralizing the community in both a political and a religious sense, the Society of Family Men has deemed it advisable to establish its own church, and has thus avoided any of those entanglements which arise from the caprices and the irresponsibility of certain eminent persons, from their lack of respect for ecclesiastical law and order, and from their willingness to drag reputations in the mire in order to gain power.</p>
   <p>And as the minister of our church we have appointed the Reverend Cyril Georgeadis, recently condemned without trial, whose good standing as a priest, established for years, the Holy Synod of Greece cannot and will not deny when that august body has recovered its self-respect.</p>
   <p>For this reason we have been classed by the administration of the Chicago <pb facs="5422062_5_1108.jpg" n="2"/>community and by the governing body of the mother church, the Holy Synod of Greece, as rebels and dividers of the Chicago community. As for our priest, whom the community's bosses have failed to subjugate to their purposes, the Holy Synod of Greece, influenced by these bosses, has issued a decree depriving him of his ecclesiastical rights, nullifying as uncanonical all religious rites by him performed, and commanding him to report for trial, thus leaving the Chicago Greek community without a priest.</p>
   <p>After hearing of the unprecedented action of the Holy Synod of Greece, or at least of persons who designate themselves the Holy Synod of Greece, we, the Society of Family Men, have requested the Reverend Father Georgeadis to remain here and to minister to our religious needs until the misconduct of the bosses has been demonstrated, and the mother church has had an opportunity to reconsider its hasty decision. Father Georgeadis has committed no crime, there is no reason why he should be deprived of his right to administer sacraments or to exercise other religious functions, and the hasty decision of the Synod has no justification.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1109.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For the information of the general public, which heretofore has not known the inside story of the whole affair, it is the duty of this Society to publish an account of what has occurred in this controversy, and to reveal how the innocent victim has become involved with his superiors, who in turn have got themselves into hot water as a consequence of the proper and lawful intervention of the Greek consul general in Chicago, the Honorable Dr. N. Salopoulos. We exhibit below certain official documents of the Greek consulate in Chicago:</p>
   <p>"To the Most Reverend Cyril A. Georgeadis, Archimandrite, Chicago:</p>
   <p>"I, the representative of His Majesty the King of Greece, command you to perform funeral rites for the deceased Konstantine Koutsoumbis, and I will be responsible therefor to all whom it may concern.</p>
   <p>"His Majesty's Consul,</p>
   <p>"N. Salopoulos"</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1110.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Another command to perform the same religious rites is dated September 7, 1904: "To the Most Reverend Archimandrite Cyril Georgeadis, Chicago:</p>
   <p>"I hereby direct you to perform ecclesiastical rites at the funeral of Demetrius Bouzos,and I will be responsible therefor, since the community has no other priest besides you."</p>
   <p>Another order from the consul general putting father Georgeadis in further disagreement with the Synod of Greece:</p>
   <p>"I, His Majesty's Consul General, hereby command you to administer the sacrament of baptism to the ailing infant of John Tzebolis, since there is no other priest here.</p>
   <p>"The Consul General of Greece,</p>
   <p>"N. Salopoulos"</p>
   <p>And another dated September 11, 1904:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1111.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"To the most Reverend Cyril Georgeadis, Archimandrite of the Greek Orthodox Church, Chicago:</p>
   <p>"His Majesty's Consul General instructs you to officiate at the christening of the ailing infant of Dem. Lambrakis, having no other priest to perform the sacrament.</p>
   <p>"The Consul of Greece,</p>
   <p>"N. Salopoulos"</p>
   <p>What an anomalous situation! The Holy Synod of the Church of Greece, as sovereign ecclesiastical authority, has enjoined the so-called apostate priest to cease to perform his ecclesiastical duties, decreeing that, if he does not cease as commanded, all his religious acts will be null and void because uncanonical. On the other hand the consul general of Greece in Chicago, who in the territory under his jurisdiction is the sovereign authority <pb facs="5422062_5_1112.jpg" n="6"/>of the Greek state, and whose duty it is to protect and defend the subjects of Greece whether they are canonical or uncanonical, has commanded him to perform the ecclesiastical duties which the hasty decision of the Synod forbade him to perform.</p>
   <p>The representative of Greece, under whose jurisdiction the church functions, and who has precedence over the church and the power to command the ministers of the church to serve the needs of His Majesty's subjects, has lawfully commanded the so-called rebel priest to disregard the mandate of the Synod on the consul's own responsibility.</p>
   <p>Is not this a delicate situation? The Chicago Greek priest, whom the Holy Synod chose as the clergyman best qualified to serve the needs of the Chicago Greek community, and who has proved by many years of faithful and devoted service that he is a pillar of the mother church, is now between two fires. Obedience to the mandate of the mother church is disobedience to the sovereign authority of Greece, and vice versa. Naturally, not being able to blow hot and cold at the same time, he has obeyed the command of Greece and has consequently incurred the disapproval of the Synod, which has declared <pb facs="5422062_5_1113.jpg" n="7"/>him a rebel and an apostate.</p>
   <p>Now let us examine how the Holy Synod has erred, consciously or unconsciously, and how it has permitted itself to be caught in a political entanglement which will undoubtedly diminish the laity's respect for that august body.</p>
   <p>The Greek community in general, and many eminent Americans who are friendly to the community and very much interested in its welfare, not knowing the real facts of this complicated situation, have permitted themselves to become the victims of a misconception and have accepted as authoritative and regular the Synod's mandate recalling Father Georgeadis and forbidding him after receipt of the protocol to perform any ecclesiastical function.</p>
   <p>In this connection we hasten to inform the public and our esteemed philhellenes that civil and religious laws are superior to individuals. Every citizen, from the humblest to the highest, and every man of the cloth, including His Holiness the Ecumenical Patriarch, is under the sovereignty of the law. When the Synod of Greece or any part of the Synod violates the constitution of the church, the action of that august body is null and void <pb facs="5422062_5_1114.jpg" n="8"/>and has no weight or significance.</p>
   <p>That is precisely the situation in the case of the Synod's decree regarding Father Georgeadis's recall and punishment. According to the church's constitution the Holy Synod, or at least those members of it who signed this document, deliberately erred in causing the decree of recall to be unofficially delivered. And the object of so delivering it was to avoid responsibility under the law for such violation of it. Shrewd action by the head of the Synod, who happens to be the godfather of Gregory Papaeliou, the president of the Chicago Greek community! Political strategy! But is it consistent with the integrity and the dignity of that ecclesiastical body?</p>
   <p>The agreement of the Church of Greece with the sovereign state of Greece is as follows:</p>
   <p>The Holy Church of Greece may correspond with cities, nations, and individuals abroad only through the official channels of the sovereign state of Greece; that is, all documents, protocols, petitions, appeals, and other communications emanating from the Holy Synod of Greece for delivery abroad must go to <pb facs="5422062_5_1115.jpg" n="9"/>the Ecclesiastical Ministry, which in turn submits the correspondence to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Secretary of State in the United States). The Ministry of Foreign Affairs, following the prescribed method of communicating with the outside world, dispatches this correspondence to the representatives of His Majesty, that is, to his consuls, his ministers of legations, and his ambasadors, for delivery.</p>
   <p>The general public of the Chicago Greek community and the community's American friends and sympathizers, who are inclined to look upon us as dividers of the community, have not realized the seriousness of the perplexing and unprecedented situation created by the illegal action of the Synod, which has rocked that body to its foundation.</p>
   <p>Neither the representatives of His Majesty nor the clergy of the church are at liberty to inform the public of the transactions which take place in their respective offices; and in this case neither the Greek consul general in Chicago nor the accused minister of the church, because of this restriction, could let the public know of the irregularity of the Synod's decree of recall.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1116.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Naturally, under such circumstances, since the truth was not known, public opinion, Greek and American alike, was against us and the pious Father Georgeadis. But truth, which is no respecter of political or religious personages, will eventually shine through darkness; its powerful rays will dissolve the clouds of unrighteousness, falsehood, and misconduct. The truth even now shines as a bright star to guide the ignorant and the credulous away from the darkness of illusion and scepticism.</p>
   <p>This revelation of the truth is not made for any purpose except to disabuse the minds of thousands of our Greek and American friends who have been dubious about the correctness of our procedure.</p>
   <p>To err is human, to forgive, divine. But a deliberate and premeditated error in conduct, especially when committed by men in high ecclesiastical office, must not be allowed to go unrebuked, lest it be repeated and thus further diminish the reverence of the laity for the clergy as a whole because of the misconduct of a few clergymen.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1117.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>That the president of the Synod and the four members who signed the punitive document were conscious of the error of their procedure is demonstrated by the very fact that the said document was surreptitiously delivered. Every Synodical document, in order to be official, effective, and valid, must go through the procedure specified by the law of the land; and the outline of the law's requirements is as follows: The document must bear the number of its issue and the number of its execution and registration in the official registry of the Synod, and it must be transmitted to the Ecclesiastical Ministry to be disposed of as we have stated above.</p>
   <p>In the specific instance of the Reverend Father Georgeadis the Synod's decree of recall, which was signed by the president and by four members of the Synod, bore the number of its issue but not the number of its execution, and none of the other requirements of the law were complied with. Two days before it reached its destination, it was published in Chicago in the Greek newspaper Hellas.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1118.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>Irregularity, illegality, and connivance par excellence! Gross disrespect for the dignity and the integrity of the mother church! The mortification of pious and devout Christians, the schism in the Chicago Greek community, the humiliation of the church in the eyes of the American people, as well as many other evils, emanate from the folly of those five members of the Synod who lowered themselves to intervene in a political affair.</p>
   <p>Undoubtedly their skill in evasion will pull them through if and when an ecclesiastical tribunal is set up to examine the surreptitious handling of the document. It will be a clear victory for them, for they will say,</p>
   <p>"Indeed, the document of recall bears our signatures, but it was not executed, for the registry shows no record of its execution. Consequently no responsibility attaches to us. How the document flew out of the Synod's office and reached Chicago we do not know, for if it had been intended to be dispatched it would have been numbered, executed, and delivered through the proper channels; therefore, the burden of responsibility lies somewhere else and not with us."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1119.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>Is not this a wonderfully clever defense?</p>
   <p>An impartial observer might say that we are going too far when we assume that the signers of the documents deliberately permitted it to proceed from the Synod's office and reach Chicago, and that our assertions to that effect may be the result of illusion or malice on our part. Such questions are pertinent and just and for the benefit of all concerned must be thoroughly examined, lest we stray from the truth and defeat our own purpose.</p>
   <p>That our assertions are not presumptuous nor the effect of illusion, and that they are free from bias, malice, or vindictiveness, the events which succeeded the publication of the decree of recall will demonstrate.</p>
   <p>A thunderbolt struck the Greek community of Chicago when the Greek newspaper Hellas, the mouthpiece of the president of the community, Dr. Gregory Papaeliou, published the Synod's ultimatum. Thoughts of bitterness and resentment, expressed and unexpressed, were directed against the Synod and Dr. G. Papaeliou for this unjustifiable action. The blow was so unexpected that it took people's breath away.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1120.jpg" n="14"/>
   <p>We shall now convince the public and our American friends that our action in establishing a new church was justified, and that our charges have been substantiated by our account of the events which ensued.</p>
   <p>The entire council of the Greek community, headed by the vice-president of that body, sent out through the secretary hasty invitations to the members of the community to attend a general meeting and there discuss the action of the Synod. The meeting took place at Hull House and was attended by five hundred bona fide members of the community. Hundreds of telegrams from other members who were not able to attend were read at the meeting; all expressed their disapproval of the Synod's action.</p>
   <p>The general assembly unanimously passed a resolution, and an executive committee was appointed to convey the resolution to the Greek consul general and inform him in person of the choas and disintegration which would befall the community if the Synod's order was not rescinded.</p>
   <p>We print below the consul general's cablegram to Greece:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1121.jpg" n="15"/>
   <p>"August 18, 1904.</p>
   <p>"To the Ministry of Foreign Affairs,</p>
   <p>"Athens, Greece.</p>
   <p>"Church council and community vehemently protest against the recall of priest Georgeadis. I transmit prayer exhorting Synod to rescind order.</p>
   <p>"Chicago Greek Consul General,</p>
   <p>"N. Salopoulos"</p>
   <p>Here is the telegram sent by the church council to the Holy Synod: "Holy Synod,</p>
   <p>"Athens, Greece.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1122.jpg" n="16"/>
   <p>"Georgeadis' recall impossible. Community in turmoil. Restore his rights. Appointment of a new priest not accepted.</p>
   <p>"Church Council: St. Spyrakis, vice-president; Basil Petropoulos, Dem. Tsimbas, D. Karambelas, B. Georgakopoulos, N. Kokinis, K. Demas, and K. Stavrakos, by Phil. Kekos, secretary"</p>
   <p>Another telegram:</p>
   <p>"To the Ecclesiastical Ministry,</p>
   <p>"Athens, Greece.</p>
   <p>"Synod has recalled our priest Cyril. We beg you to intervene. Disorder will follow if our request is not heeded.</p>
   <p>"Church Council: St. Spyrakis, vice-president; B. Petropoulos, D. Tsimbas, <pb facs="5422062_5_1123.jpg" n="17"/>D. Karambelas, B. Georgakopoulos, N. Kokinis, K. Demas, and K. Stavrakos, by Phil. Kekos, secretary"</p>
   <p>Many other telegrams were sent by bona fide members of the Greek community to the Holy Synod, requesting it to reconsider its illegal order. The general public anxiously awaited the outcome of all these urgent petitions and requests addressed to the Holy Synod of Greece.</p>
   <p>Absolute silence was the answer of the Synod. The high ecclesiastical authority of liberated Greece did not deem it advisable to answer the deluge of appeals. Not one word did it utter to justify its hasty decree of recall--not a word to set at rest the disturbed minds of its sheep. The Synod, by its silence, preferred to shake the implicit faith of the people in their mother church rather than to correct the error of its first hasty action and its subsequent error of endeavoring to silence the opposition by accusing the innocent priest of continuing to function as a priest after he had received the Synod's document of recall.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1124.jpg" n="18"/>
   <p>We have stated above that the Chicago Greek priest Georgeadis, upon receipt of notice of his recall, ceased to officiate in religious ceremonies except as directed, ordered, instructed, and commanded by the sovereign power of His Majesty to do so, thus disobeying the orders of the Synod; hence the new accusation of disobedience.</p>
   <p>That our assertions have documentary substantiation, and that we are not going too far in assuming that the original charge and the subsequent charges against the Reverend Father Georgeadis were made by the Synod contrary to ecclesiastical law and order, are facts clearly proved by those by-laws of the church's constitution which relate it to the constitution of the state of Greece. We present below the article pertinent to our case:</p>
   <p>"Article 14.</p>
   <p>"Canonical punitive measures after Trial:</p>
   <p>"(a) Debarment of a priest from exercising any religious function and loss <pb facs="5422062_5_1125.jpg" n="19"/>of his claims upon the parish:</p>
   <p>"These decisions, whether of bishops or of the Synod, must be accounted for and supported by quotations from the holy canons upon which they are based, and which have the approval of the Ecclesiastical Ministry, and in order to be valid the decisions must bear the signatures of all the members of the Holy Synod and must be approved by a majority of the members thereof; otherwise they are null and void."</p>
   <p>On the basis of this article of the ecclesiastical law, what authority have five members of the Synod to order the Chicago Greek priest to cease to function? That is the reason why the members of the Society of Family Men have taken the action for which they are classed as rebels and dividers of the Chicago Greek community.</p>
   <p>Article 20 of the ecclesiastical law clearly and emphatically says:</p>
   <p>"Under no consideration may the Synod correspond with political or ecclesiastical <pb facs="5422062_5_1126.jpg" n="20"/>offices abroad independently of the Ecclesiastical Ministry, which shall submit the Synod's correspondence to the Ministry of Foreign Affairsfor delivery through the representatives of the nation."</p>
   <p>What document of the Synod bearing on this case has been sent to Chicago through the regular channels prescribed by this law? None whatsoever! The Synod's first error was the surreptitious dispatch of the recall document. It anticipated no resistance, taking the Chicago Greeks for ignorant fools, and it has deliberately continued to err in order to cover up its first violation of the law.</p>
   <p>We further submit to the public what the Metropolitan of Athens, as president of the Synod, said to our appointed representatives in Greece who appealed to His Holiness in person:</p>
   <p>"Gentlemen, in order not to waste your time, I tell you that the Chicago case is closed. We had the right to recall Georgeadis, and we did so."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1127.jpg" n="21"/>
   <p>The public and our American friends have hitherto been under the impression that our action in establishing a new church was motivated by something other than our desire to protest against the acts enumerated above, that is to say, against the injustice which the Holy Synod has seen fit to inflict upon us in order to gratify its desire to maintain the power of Dr. Gregory Papaeliou, the favored godchild of His Holiness, the president of the Synod.</p>
   <p>In the next issue of this paper, in order to eliminate the slightest doubt in the mind of the general public as to the Synod's deliberate violation of the ecclesiastical law, we shall publish for purposes of comparison all documents which have been sent by the Synod to Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Executive Committee of the Society of Family Men,</p>
   <p>Chicago</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
