<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-05-24">May, 24, 1907</date>.
<title level="a"/><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1575</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1575.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-05-24">May, 24, 1907</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Greenhorn fellow Greeks arriving in Chicago, or other parts of the United States, from Greece are complaining against the exploitation practiced upon them by steamship agents in Greece.</p>
   <p>The Star, as <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>of the Greek <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in Chicago and elsewhere, cannot overlook the injustice just because it is committed on the other side of the ocean, but will take up the battle and <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>future citizens of Uncle Sam. The greenhorn immigrant of today is a prospective member of our community and a future citizen of the United States, and any injustice done to him reflects upon our future relations and friendship with Mother Greece.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1576.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That is their reason The Star wants to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>not only the exploitation will cease to exist, but also the actual friendship and sentiment of the Greeks and both sides of the ocean will be of the best.</p>
   <p>It is common knowledge to all of us that the fish begins to smell from the head, so in this case the unscrupulous agents are only the tail of the smelling fish, the head is the Greek government.</p>
   <p>The responsibility of the fraud, graft and thievery rests squarely with the Greek government which abandons its protection to the departing immigrant, who through <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> becomes a prey of the highway agent.</p>
   <p>Greeks of America are always responsive to Mother-Greece's voice, and always ready to assist, and assist generously, when need be. Is the Greek immigrant protected from the sharks when he buys a ticket for his journey of adventure, prosperity and colonization? No! He is left to his fate, to be robbed, and to carry with him the unpleasant and unhealthy memory <pb facs="5422062_5_1577.jpg" n="3"/>of his treatment at the hands of blood-sucking leeches. His government, apparently, has no use for him. But as soon as he is established in the new world and by the sweat of his brow accumulates a few dollars, sweet songs solicit his generous contributions.</p>
   <p>Who, if not the government, could be responsible for this thievery? Who is the one to prosecute dishonesty, if not the government?</p>
   <p>Our appeal is directed to the Greek government, the immediately responsible party to push the prosecution of the guilty and if this fails The Star, unwillingly, will appeal to the good name of the Steamship companies in Greece, to take measures and clean the rank and file of dishonest and unscrupulous agents, a disgrace to the companies.</p>
   <p>Undoubtedly the Steamship companies will be more interested than the Greek government in stopping this unhealthy practice, because it not only reflects <pb facs="5422062_5_1578.jpg" n="4"/>upon the integrity and good name of the companies, but also is injurious from a commercial point of view.</p>
   <p>Let us hope that the situation will be remedied either one way or the other.</p>
   <p>But the real object of this article is to interest the Greek government in taking a hand against the abuse of the greenhorn and prove to all of us that Mother-Greece is interested in her sons, whether living in Greece or going abroad.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
