<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1928-09-29">Sept. 29, 1928</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Chicago Greek Episcopate and Greek Culture for the New Generation.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0492</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0492.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1928-09-29">Sept. 29, 1928</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">CHICAGO GREEK EPISCOPATE AND GREEK CULTURE FOR THE NEW GENERATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question of Greek culture for the new Greek-American generation, which for a long time hovered in the atmosphere of the Chicago Greek Community, is at last crystalized. It became a material entity with bone and flesh through the energetic and progressive activities of the Right Rev. Philaretos, Bishop of the Chicago Greek Episcopate, who today met with members of the Board of Education of the diocese, at the La Salle Hotel, and laid before them his profound thoughts urging them to cooperate and assist in the proposed program of Hellenizing our youth.</p>
   <p>The Board of Education of the Diocese which consists of the Very Rev. E. Tsourounakis, the Rev. K. Hatzidemetriou, Dr. N. Salopoulos, Dr. K. Theodorou and G. Alexander, after listening with relief and joy to the proposed program of Mr. Philaretos, accepted it unanimously and promised their cooperation and assistance.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0493.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Besides the profound words of Bishop Philaretos, the introduction of Dr. N. Salopoulos, former Greek Consul in Chicago, who is distinguished in the Greek philological world for his undying love for mother Greece and our immortal language, made a deep impression upon the assembly.</p>
   <p>Dr. K. Theodorou, who also spoke with enthusiasm and love for Greek culture, and who is known in the city for his devotion to the Greek-American school Koraes, asked the assembly to elect new officers. The elected officers are: The Right Rev. Philaretos, President; Dr. N. Salopoulos, Vice-President; G. Alexander, Secretary (general); Dr. Theodorou, Treasurer, and apostle of the idea. Council: The Very Rev. E. Tsourounakis and the Rev. D. Hatzidemetriou.</p>
   <p>With his proposed program of solid foundation the problem of educating our youth is already solved and shortly will be in operation.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0494.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The work of Bishop Philaretos, who has on his side all the healthy element of his Bishopric will become an historical event in the annals of the Chicago Greek community, and his example will be followed by other national and Ecclesiastical Hierarchies of Hellenism the world over.</p>
   <p>Owing to the profundity of Bishop Philaretos' educational program and for the benefit of other Greek communities in America, on another page we print the entire program.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
