<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-06-23">June 23, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Why Keep Silent about the Protestant Wedding?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-06-23">June 23, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">WHY KEEP SILENT ABOUT THE PROTESTANT WEDDING?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1-We have repeatedly challenged both Father H. Demetri and the archbishopric to explain an occurrence which is unprecedented in the history of the Orthodox Church, that is, the performance of the marriage ceremony by Orthodox priests according to the Protestant ritual in one of our churches because the bridegroom was a Protestant.</p>
   <p>In our columns, however, we have generally limited ourselves to narrating the facts in the case (for instance, we have printed the names of the priests who officiated) and to echoing public opinion, but the Bishop has kept silent, showing that the clergy are guilty of all of which people accuse them.</p>
   <p>That which we should like to tell them today is that this affair is not going to comply with their wishes and retire to oblivion; before long they will have to render an account of their actions even though at the present moment they appear to be both defendants and judges empowered to pass sentence on their own actions.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0561.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Fortunately a telegraphic communication from Greece announces that the Synod intends to dispatch a legate to America, and the cablegram adds among other things the Synod's opinion that the Greek Church in America has been afflicted with paralysis, but the Synod likewise assures us that it will very soon make an end of all these disorders, and that those who derive profit of our religion will be put in their proper places. For we have been informed that Father Demetri was very generously rewarded for conducting this Protestant wedding.</p>
   <p>We challenge Father Demetri to disprove what we have said, especially our statement that he received a liberal fee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
