<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-04-28">Apr. 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Nomination of Candidates for the Office of Bishop of the Greek Orthodox Diocese of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0716</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0716.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-04-28">Apr. 28, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">NOMINATION OF CANDIDATES FOR THE OFFICE OF BISHOP OF THE GREEK ORTHODOX DIOCESE OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>By order of the Partiarchate of Constantinople the Archbishop of North and South America as representative and head of the independently governed Orthodox Church of North and South America fixed a date for the nomination of candidates for the office of Bishop of the newly established Diocese of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The nomination of candidates for office took place in the imposing South Side Church, St. Constantine's.</p>
   <p>The progressive and gracious committee had not only decorated the church beaurifully but had also prepared a supper which was served in the basement rooms in honor of the Archbishop, the clergy and the lay delegates. The meeting began at 6 p. m. under the presidency of Archibishop Alexander, with the Archdeacon as secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0717.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At this meeting the following clergymen attended as nominators:</p>
   <p>The Reverend Fathers, C. Hadzidemetriou, Chicago; D. Vainikos, Chicago; Germanos Papaioannes, Dayton; Markos Petrakis and Chrysosotomos Trahadias, Rockford; D. A. Ermogenes, Chelsea; Ferontis Paesios, New Orleans; Par. Papotheophrastis, Youngstown; Simeon Mitatakis, Indianapolis; V. Pantazopoulos, Mason City; Meletios Kronides, Warren; Ioannes Zographos, Cleveland; George Doyekos, Lorain; Ars. Saltas, Minneapolis; Emmanuel Papastefanos, Toledo; Kyrillos Papagregorios, Fort Worth; Parthenios Kolones, Martin's Ferry; Emmanuel Kafkakes, Detroit; Th. Lekkas, Dallas; G. Petrides, Detroit; Iacovos Kaloudes, Canton; A. Papademetrios, Memphis; Arsenios Prakas, Racine; Fr. Panatzines, Akron; Al. Papastefanos, Fond du Lac; Kyrillos Georgiades, Columbus; Methodios Fousianes, Gary; Veniamin Kollias, Milwaukee; Constantine Harvales, Sioux City; Ioannes Panos, Moline; and Merkoures Papamerkoures, Oklahoma.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0718.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The lay delegates were: Messrs. Constantine Paleologos, Cleveland; Paul Demos, Rockford; C. Theodoros, Chicago; I. Goulakos, Detroit; C. Petros, Toledo; Emmanuel G. Soterakis, Fond du Lac; P. Kaparliotes, Mason; George Halepas, Warren; Alexander Eliopoulos, Gary; Vasilios P. Zampides, Racine; C. Stefanopoulos, Milwaukee; Stavros Stefanides, New Orleans; D. Loues, Akron; D. Stamos, Dallas; C. Tselemengos, Youngstown; D. Zacharias, Indianapolis; E. D. Frimas, Columbus, A. K. Yakalos, Dayton; A. Kallopoulos, Minneapolis; K. Koures, Sioux City; and G. Bouras, Moline.</p>
   <p>The meeting began with a brief devotional service, which was followed by the election of a secretary, the reading of the telegraphic order of the Patriarchate and of the archiepiscopal circular, the roll-call of the nominators, the announcement of the qualifications of the candidates and the election of an advisory committee consisting of two clergymen and two laymen to supervise the election.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0719.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>After a brief discussion, the voting took place under the direction of Mr. Paleologos and Mr. Freeman, after which the votes were counted. Mr. Paleologos announced the results. The secretary and the advisory committee then checked the count and marked it down carefully so that no mistake would be made. The result was that the largest votes were cast for Archimandrites Alexopoulos, 31 votes, Ioannides, 31 votes and Mitatakis 25 votes. The proper documents were drawn up and signed by the president, the secretary, and all his nominators, and the meeting was dismissed with the blessings of the Church as befitted so sacred and imposing an assembly.</p>
   <p>Later all the delegates and the others in attendance descended to the large room in the basement of the church to partake of the supper. After dinner speeches were made by Messrs. Paleologos, Theodoros, Trinketas and Kotakis and by the Archbishop.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0720.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This is the first time in the history of American Hellenism that so important a meeting has taken place. This is proof that the Greeks living in America consider their Church and their religion the highest of all duties and those who are in charge of our communities should undertake a constructive religious movement. Archbishop Alexander is to be congratulated on his modest, progressive and careful ecclesiastical policy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
