<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-08-03">Aug. 3, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Request for News-Items in Greek</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1209</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1209.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-08-03">Aug. 3, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">REQUEST FOR NEWS-ITEMS IN GREEK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1--To our request published in Proodos last week for news from our readers we have not had enough replies with items of interest to the general public.</p>
   <p>We do not believe that our readers thought that they were expected to pay for the publication of their news. Of course they are not. The only expense is three cents for postage. (You know that last July the letter-postage was increased from two cents to three cents.)</p>
   <p>The receipt of social news through the mail to be published free of charge saves our going after the news or maintaining a staff of reporters and also benefits the children and the adults who report the news to us, and we are grateful to them besides. So we beg once more that you will let us hear from you with your news.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1210.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Election of Hellenic Post 343 of the American Legion.</p>
   <p>At the election recently held by Hellenic Post 343 of the American Legion the following officers were elected: John M. Dayannes, commander, George S. Poricos, vice-commander, Photis Petniezas, second vice-commander, Theo, Anastos, third vice-commander, Dem. Tassiopoulos, financial officer, Minas Joannides, health officer, Alex. Kastritses, publicity officer, A. A. Panteles, legal adviser, Dem. Pappas, drill officer, P. Kastanes, auditor, the Reverend John Giannakakis, chaplain, and Photis N. Tselekas, sergeantat-arms.</p>
   <p>John Payannes, George Poricos, D. A. Tassiopoulos, Elias Verdos, Arist. Kollias, P. I. Georgitses, Nick Z. Kollias, Theo. Anastos, and George Kopitas were elected members of the board of directors. Dem. A. Tassiopoulos was elected to represent the Post at the Illinois convention.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1211.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A Happy Marriage.</p>
   <p>p. 1.--On last Sunday Mr. John A. Dravilas and the charming Miss Maria D. Economopoulos were joined in holy matrimony. The ceremony was performed in St. Andrew's Church by the Reverend E. Tsurunake.</p>
   <p>John Bussales was best man. After the ceremony the newly-weds received the congratulations of the crowd, and a magnificent banquet was served in the spacious hall of the church followed by a dance which lasted into the late hours.</p>
   <p>The happy couple left on their honeymoon trip accompanied by the best wishes and the blessings of their friends and their relatives.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1212.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Picnic of Thermopylae and Gorgo Gapa Lodges</p>
   <p>p. 1. The third annual picnic of Thermopylae and Gorgo Gapa Lodges in Paul's Grove was a great success and left indelible memories in the hearts of all who attended.</p>
   <p>The fine weather and the painstaking preparations of the indefatigable committee on arrangements, George Delahanes, Anast. Markakes, and Vasilike Bonsiou, combined with the fraternity's genuine spirit of brotherhood, were the reasons for this success.</p>
   <p>The attendance was increased by the presence of the members of Aeschylus Lodge of Gary, Indiana, who came over in a body a hundred and fifty strong. Their band composed of youthful members of the Lodge, was the life of the picnic.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1213.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The guests listened to addresses made by various brothers, and it was announced that the Gary lodge's picnic will take place on August 21, and that of Navarinon and Hestia Lodges on August 28.</p>
   <p>Summer in the Country.</p>
   <p>Since last week the family of Mr. P. Tsiovane has been living in a delightful country cottage at Longbeach, Indiana, where they intend to spend this summer.</p>
   <p>In this first week of their residence in By-the-Way Cottage they have entertained as guests Mrs. Drew and her children, Mr. Athena Tsiovane, and Miss Stamatina Karamina.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
