<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-10-16">October 16, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">We Challenge You.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0473</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0473.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-10-16">October 16, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">WE CHALLENGE YOU.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.3.- The Rt. Reverend Bishop Ioakim of Boston has expressed, by telephone, his dissatisfaction on our public statements, characterizing them as untrue and accuses us of having the division of the Greek populace of America as our objective.</p>
   <p>We do not hesitate to make public these characterizations of the Rt. Reverend, because we do not consider the ecclesiastical question to be personal but one rather, concerning the Greeks of America as a wholenor do we wish to conceal our opposition. On the contrary, we state that if the Rt. Reverend wishes to refute our public pronouncements we shall be perfectly willing to open our columns to him.</p>
   <p>Therefore, as his Reverence believes that what we wrote was untrue and that the purpose was to divide Hellenism in America for sake of the truth and for the sake of more effective enlightment of our nationals, we Challenge him to a public debate in one of the largest halls, that our people may hear and be convinced one way or the other.</p>
   <p>We challenge the Rt. Reverend to contradict us, not by telephone, but <pb facs="5422062_5_0474.jpg" n="2"/>publicly because the ecclesiastical question is a vital one and people want to hear the diverse opinions regarding it. We, as a matter of principle, believe that the truth comes out by having opinions on both sides confront one another.</p>
   <p>We furthermore state, that if in a public debate we are contradicted, we shall acknowledge our error publicly and shall become ardent supporters of the Rt. Reverend Ioakim's opinions.</p>
   <p>And so, to be in order, we again submit to the public the questions which he is duty bound to refute publicly as he has characterized them as false over the telephone.</p>
   <p>Inasmuch as you, the Rt. Reverend, have the truth, step forth, to enlighten the public and do not hide from your public.</p>
   <p>(The eight points may be found translated by referring to my note of October 13, 1928,- Translator)</p>
   <p>Upon all these we have indisputable proofs and we challenge you to refute them in public debate, if you have courage and truth in your favor.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis, Manager, Chicago</p>
   <p>Greek Daily.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
