<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-21">Dec. 21, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">A Pitiful Failure</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0101</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0101.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos</title>,
<date when="1932-12-21">Dec. 21, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">A PITIFUL FAILURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We deeply regret that we are compelled to criticize the policies of our archbishop; we regret it still more deeply because it is not in harmony with the spirit of the holidays which we are about to celebrate. Nevertheless we shall not hesitate to voice our opinion of the work and the mission of Archbishop Athenagoras in America.</p>
   <p>From our observations, the policies and the tactics of the archbishop since his arrival, and their effects upon our ecclesiastical institutions, clearly justify all the fears and the prophecies of those who, from the beginning, have criticized the methods and the policies of this high official of orthodoxy, whom we all were to accept as a messiah.</p>
   <p>What do we see now after three years of Archbishop Athenagoras' operations here? If we are to judge him by the incident which we describe in another column, <pb facs="5422062_5_0102.jpg" n="2"/>that is, by his conduct in the meeting at St. Demetry's Church, and by the general conditions of our ecclesiastical affairs, this prelate, who has been so much advertised as the only one able to reorganize and direct our church affairs in America, is far from fulfilling the hopes and the expectations of his flock. Instead of correcting things he has made the confusion worse.</p>
   <p>Our new director of religion, who was thrust upon us with so many promises when he was sent over to reorganize and renovate orthodoxy in America, has shown himself not only incompetent to perform this heavy task but actually dangerous and harmful, because his attitude withers the religious sentiment of his followers, if they have any religious sentiment left, and causes Orthodox Greeks to lose hope that anybody will ever be found capable of saving our national and religious institutions. This man on whom all Hellenism based its hopes, and whom it received with so many honors, has proven after three years' trial that he does not at all measure up to our expectations, and that he does not justify the expense which Greeks have incurred on his account. In other words the Right Reverend Archbishop Athenagoras does not rise to the height of his mission, <pb facs="5422062_5_0103.jpg" n="3"/>the purpose of which is to reorganize and govern the Greek Orthodox church in America.</p>
   <p>In order that we may not be vague and indefinite in our criticisms as to the incapability of our new eccelesiastical chief, we will publish some well-known facts relative to his activities during the time he has been among us.</p>
   <p>It is well known that the much-advertised assembly of clergymen and lay representatives, under the influence of this leader, adopted the new church constitution in the last minutes of its session. What is the result of this assembly's work? The total paralysis of our church organization is the result, a condition worse than its former state of discord and dissension. Why? Mainly, in our opinion, on account of the inability of the chief to decide impartially and definitely the various problems presented to him. This same assembly created a mixed council of clergy and laity, to which was entrusted the management of the property of the archdiocese. What happened to this mixed council?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0104.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A letter, published in these columns some time ago, from Mr. Canoutas to the board of trustees of the church, threw light on the policies and the tactics of the new leader of the Greek Orthodox Church in America. The lack of real administrative ability, the application of dictatorial methods, the reaching of decisions in secret, many of them so ridiculous that they have had to be reversed in a short time--these things have resulted in loss of confidence in the Archbishop's judgments. Nobody knows what may be done in important matters, and nobody has any more confidence in him. Appointments and transfers of priests, in spite of threats and fines, have been disregarded because of the unstable character of the archbishop. Lack of confidence in him and lack of respect for him have resulted in acts of disobedience.</p>
   <p>Another sad result of the inherent incapability of our new administrator is that in New York and elsewhere many churches, like the priests, do not pay any attention to this chief of ours. They have lost faith in him and are so badly disappointed in his policies and his tactics that they prefer to be apostates rather than to submit to him.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0105.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We do not know what is going on in the lobbies and in different departments of the church because of the despotic attitude of our archbishop. The only thing which can be observed is that a clique of flatterers is directing the performance from the wings, and that the government of the church suffers greatly through the influence of these courtesans.</p>
   <p>For all these reasons the administration of our new chief is a pitiful failure. In our opinion further direction of affairs by Archbishop Athenagoras, and his continued residence here, will be disastrous for Hellenism and orthodoxy; there-fore, we humbly suggest that this learned, versatile, affable, and impressive chief of ours take the road back to his native land, retiring as an incompetent leader from activities which have been detrimental to the progress of Hellenism in America.</p>
   <p>Proodos, as we said in the beginning, regrets that it has been obliged to change its policy in religious matters, but in the face of facts and information received concerning the policies of our leader Archbishop Athenagoras and the clique <pb facs="5422062_5_0106.jpg" n="6"/>around him we find ourselves in the difficult position of having to change our vows and our attitude. But we are convinced that the longer our Archbishop remains the worse the results will be for Hellenism, orthodoxy, and the Christian faith of the Greeks in America.</p>
   <p>On this subject the columns of Proodos are open for free discussion, and we will publish opinions and information in a sincere endeavor to help in the reorganization of our church. We wish to publish a true account of things, as well as sincere opinions expressed in dignified style on this, the most vital problem of Hellenism in America, the matter of the government and the reorganization of the Greek Orthodox church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
