<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-10-12">October 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Saints' Election in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0479</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0479.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-10-12">October 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE SAINTS' ELECTION IN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1.- In yesterday's issue we described now the Saints, were put up as candidates at the former Masonic Temple on Winthrop avenue.</p>
   <p>Now the parishioners and all nationals of our community understand why this church remained nameless for two years while holy rites were continually being observed. Apparently, the Rector of the church, Hadji Dimitri, was waiting for a suitable time to complete and present his schemes to his parishioners. He had summoned the thierarchs from far distant parts of America to aid in the execution of his plans.</p>
   <p>Having carried the primary election at the Morrison Hotel on the night of October 6th, the doors of the church were opened the following morning by Archbishops and all, in order to carry the election, and to determine the god of glory, namely, he who was to offer the most money.</p>
   <p>The crowds packed the church to capacity, and a bargaining by the voters began. The leading candidates were our Savior, Jesus Christ, supported by the Priest and Rector of the church, Hadji Dimitri, and the thierarchs; the Apostles were supported by the lawyer, Paul Demos, and others.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0480.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Incredible as these may seem to you they are facts verified by a thousand persons, who were present. We are just giving you the faintest idea of what transpired. The struggle finally boiled down to one between Christ and his Apostles. A strange election battle!</p>
   <p>The more the Rector, Hadji Dimitri was shouting for his candidate, our Savior, Jesus Christ, the more anti-Christ voters were becoming. This vote hunting on the part of the pious Priest created a very bad impression among the congregation. If such a comedy was necessary to give a name to this renowned church there was no reason whatever to bring in the name of Christ.</p>
   <p>So horrifying and nauseating was the spectacle that many started to express their dissatisfaction. That the name of Christ had no place whatever in such irreverent comedies played to the detriment of religion and the prestige, the Greek church.</p>
   <p>In spite of all appeals made by Priest and thierarchs, Christ lost, taking second place in the vote. St. Andrews won the election.</p>
   <p>(Summary).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
