<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-28">Sept. 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Twenty-Five Thousand Greeks That Have Accomplished Practically Nothing</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0076</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0076.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-28">Sept. 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">TWENTY-FIVE THOUSAND GREEKS THAT HAVE ACCOMPLISHED PRACTICALLY NOTHING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The general condition of the Greek churches and parishes in America is deplorable. Nothing but complaints and fears are heard from their leaders, who seem to think that our people will soon be assimilated to the point of obliteration in this country. Naturally the financial situation in the entire country had to be felt by the churches as well as by other institutions. Many towns were almost depopulated, due to the lack of industry, and the Greek churches there were also forced to close their doors because of lack of funds and parishioners. Churches in small towns also suffered, because their parishioners moved away to more active centers to seek a livelihood. The few families which usually remained were unable to support a church and a priest.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0077.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The natural result will be the same as it has been in Europe: the only communities which will survive--or, at least, postpone assimilation and obliteration--will be the ones located in the large cities of the nation. Therefore, all our efforts should be directed toward making our parishes strong and powerful, in order that they may hold us together. The existence and maintenance of schools, churches, and other national organizations in the large cities will be possible as long as we unite ourselves and hang together.</p>
   <p>The main problem confronting us is how to put into practice a system of cooperative and unified effort among our various parishes. At present, they are individually governed, and at times they seek to destroy each other because of jealousy or selfishness. This fact is admitted by a majority of our clerics and our leading laymen. The problem which baffles us is how to organize our beliefs and forces so that the danger which threatens the future of our people will not be allowed to persist.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0078.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The condition of the Chicago Greek community is in especial need of immediate attention. Our editorials have always been written in a rather conservative vein, and never have been given to enthusiasms, or false and impossible aims. We merely have contended repeatedly that there is no justification for the lack of social unity which prevails in our community. Accepting the fact that there are over twenty-five thousand Greeks in Chicago, we have examined our record of achievement to note the accomplishments of so many thousands of people. We see that we have nine churches that are still open, due to the generosity of certain well-to-do individuals.</p>
   <p>Not one step forward! A school worthy of the name has never been established Our churches are mortgaged or rented buildings. Many congregations struggle along in constant fear of foreclosure. Of hospitals, orphanages, or old people's homes there has never been a thought. Therefore all we can look at are our churches and schools--such as they are. And we are forced to <pb facs="5422062_5_0079.jpg" n="4"/>ask: Is it impossible for twenty-five thousand people, who pride themselves upon being Greeks, to be in a position to have one well-organized parish? Are we to believe that the spirit of indifference prevails to the extent that we are helpless in the face of the danger of losing our "national ego"? Such a conclusion is not only impossible to accept; it is also disgraceful to consider.</p>
   <p>We, too, can achieve, if we cast aside our outmoded beliefs and methods and acquire the modern progressive system of planned action. Let us limit the number of our church parishes, and then work to better the ones we have left, so that we can be proud of them. Let us establish at least three Greek day schools, and insure them fine leadership and sufficient funds for the school year. This is the only road to racial permanency.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
