<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-08-28">Aug. 28, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Hellenism in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0347</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0347.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-08-28">Aug. 28, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">HELLENISM IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.- For ten years we have found ourselves waiting for a mechanical God to correct our problems. In moments of deep despair we have considered calling our mother country to the rescue. The spirit with which P. Meletiou, Patriarch of Alexandria, tried to help us was greatly criticized by many of our countrymen here. Hellenism in America was not satisfied with his attempt to settle Ecclesiastical problem. It did its best to ruin Greek religion in America and now is angry because one man does not patch it up immediately.</p>
   <p>Because the Greeks were dissatisfied, they sent to Greece for a liturgant to tell them what to do. The Great Metropolitan Corinthian, P. Meletiou, was sent immediately upon request. He came to our rescue, so to speak, without a program or an idea as to how he was going to perform this miracle.</p>
   <p>The solution is easily found. As soon as all the Ecclesiastical bodies stop thinking of themselves and try to cooperate a little, or reunion of <pb facs="5422062_5_0348.jpg" n="2"/>the church will be effected. The only trouble is that each group considers itself in the right and wants His Holiness from Greece to correct the faults of the other groups.</p>
   <p>This is the condition of the Greeks in America and it is high time for them to realize that they should fight together instead of one another, if they want Hellenism preserved.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
