<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1909-03-05">Mar. 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">The First Official Session of the Greek Community</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1005</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1005.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1909-03-05">Mar. 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIRST OFFICIAL SESSION OF THE GREEK COMMUNITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, the members of the Greek Community of Chicago convened in the Germania Hall at the request of the newly elected community and church administration. More than one hundred and eighty active and influential members of the Greek settlement were present during this first highly important session of the Community.</p>
   <p>Indeed, the meeting of the Greek Community last Sunday was an historic one, because, on that occasion, important decisions were made concerning the unification and consolidation of our community into one body, which, in the future, will work in concord and harmony. In that case the many needs of the Greek settlement will be taken care of. The supplying of <pb facs="5422062_5_1006.jpg" n="2"/>these needs will most certainly raise our community to a high social, economic, and cultural level; in this way, we can all work for the common good.</p>
   <p>The present new executive council of the Greek Community of Chicago has assumed authority with a complete program of work for the improvement and the continued advancement of our public affairs. Judging by the work which has been accomplished by the council to date, we can see that it is indeed inspired with excellent ideas and purposes. It did not start making arbitrary decisions, though, according to the community's constitution, it is given that power. It enforces no official decree or law without the consent of the majority of the Community, which entrusted the administration with the guidance of the destinies of the Greek people of Chicago. This means that the executive officers are not doing whatever they please, without the advice and consent of the people.</p>
   <p>This was proved during last Sunday's meeting when an attempt was made to <pb facs="5422062_5_1007.jpg" n="3"/>settle the case of the Reverend Archimandrite Cyril A. Georgiades. The important case of this member of the higher Greek clergy occupied the attention of the council from the very beginning, and, rightly so, because it is directly connected with the problem of unifying our Community forces. This vital problem was neglected for some reason in the past; that is why little progress has been made.</p>
   <p>As Mr. Spiro Kotakis very aptly expressed it--much ink and paper have been used in connection with the aforesaid problem. Unspeakable insults and accusations have been hurled at the venerable Father Cyril Georgiades. To these insults, the Reverend Father submitted with the patience of Job and a spirit of true Christian brotherhood in the hope that some day justice would pervail.</p>
   <p>The case of Father Cyril was finally disposed of at last Sunday's meeting <pb facs="5422062_5_1008.jpg" n="4"/>when, by request of the executive council of the Greek Community of Chicago, the Reverend Archimandrite Cyril Georgiades agreed to deed the Saint Nicholas Greek Orthodox church at 1927 South State Street, as well as the recently purchased cemetery lots near Elmwood, to the official Greek Community of Chicago for the sum of $1,800. The Community also takes possession of the furniture and all the equipment of the purchased church.</p>
   <p>One of our priests will take charge of the Saint Nicholas Church until the new church building on the South Side is put up. At the same time, Reverend Cyril will direct and supervise our Community school as he has long experience and the necessary qualifications for this most important position. Very soon, he will be asked to organize a new school for the needs of the Greek families on the South Side.</p>
   <p>Because of the existence of another Greek church, though a small one, a <pb facs="5422062_5_1009.jpg" n="5"/>great amount of friction developed, which divided our community into two warring and competing factions. Father Cyril, who was pastor of the Saint Nicholas Church; the executive council of the Greek Community of Chicago; those who participated in the meeting, that is, both the majority and minority parties, must be congratulated for restoring order and peace to our formerly divided community.</p>
   <p>The new administration of our community has demonstrated that it is able to promote the common interests of the Greek people. Meetings such as last Sunday's which give the people the opportunity to discuss and debate questions of general policy are what we need. The opinion of the majority group prevailed last Sunday. That is why we tackled successfully the problem of party and church unity in Chicago; that is why our school has been put on a sound basis; and that is why the members of the Greek Community carry on courageously in their daily lives with full confidence and high hopes for the future welfare of our people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
