<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-12-12">Dec. 12, 1931</date><title level="a">The First Greek Church in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0174.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III C (Russian)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-12-12">Dec. 12, 1931</date><title level="a">THE FIRST GREEK CHURCH IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.- In my previous article, I wrote of the Greek pioneers of Chicago and the establishment of the first Greek community.</p>
   <p>Greeks, the world over, live with Greek traditions. A Greek community without a Greek Church and a Greek school, cannot fulfill the traditions of the Hellenic race. At first, the Greeks in Chicago were attending holy services in the Russian Church. This branch, of the Mother Greek Church, through a systematic propaganda, attempted to Slavicize the worshipping Greeks.</p>
   <p>The worshippers attending the Russian church were Polish, Russian, Roumanian, Serbian, Bulgarian, and then the Greeks of Chicago. The priest of the church was a Serbian. The Russian Archbishop of San Francisco, <pb facs="5422062_5_0175.jpg" n="2"/>wishing, (for Slavic reasons) to do honor to the Greeks of Chicago, transferred the Serbian priest, and in his stead sent the Rev. Procopios Vrettas, a Greek from Macedonia. This new Greek priest of the Russian Church, although highly educated, failed to Slavicize the Greek worshippers. When he was convinced of the utter impossibility of fulfilling the dictates of the Archbishop of San Francisco, he refrained from further attempts, lest the Greek community ostracize the Russian Church.</p>
   <p>This was the situation in the Greek community in 1890. The news of the World's Columbian Exposition spread far and wide and more Greeks came to Chicago anticipating great gains from the Exposition. In 1892, the first Greek society was founded and named Lycurgus. The President of Lycurgus Society was Uncle Constantine, and Mr. P. Lambros, the present editor of the Greek Star, was its secretary. The meetings of Lycurgus Society were many and were composed of prominent members, who had nothing else in mind but how to draw the Greeks away from the Russian plot. Some, I remember, were Papageorge, John Rifakis, Karelas, Vlachandreas, N. <pb facs="5422062_5_0176.jpg" n="3"/>Mazarakos, I. Prokos, N. Koumountzis, I. Palamaris, A. Manousos, L. Gianacopoulos, Capt. Kolas, Metaxas, Brown from Samos, the Vournazos brothers, Antzaklis brothers, Sarantos Loumos, N. Kavouras, and others whose name I cannot recollect.</p>
   <p>The result of those meetings was a Greek Church and a Greek priest. So an appeal was sent to the Mother Church. The Metropolitan of Athens, taking into earnest consideration the appeal of the Chicago Greeks, at once dispatched the Rev. Fiampolis, accompanied by his large family, who for many years served the Greek community of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Preparations were made to shelter the priest and his family, and the expenses were borne by the Lycurgus Society. Plans were made to fix up the fifth floor of a warehouse at 130 Union Ave. This place was chosen as a temporary church. Of course, it was not the proper place or the proper neighborhood for a church, but due to the fact that most of the <pb facs="5422062_5_0177.jpg" n="4"/>Greeks were in the fruit business in that neighborhood, they decided to have the church in a centralized location, at least for a while.</p>
   <p>When Father Fiampolis and his family arrived, the temporary church was ready. The place was sanctified by the Greek priest and named Annunciation. This, then, was the foundation of the future Greek Orthodox Church of Chicago. The first mass, by a Greek priest in a Greek Church was performed here in this humble place. In this place also officiated the Most Rev. Dionysios Lattas, Archbishio of Zante, who came here as plenipotentiary of Greece to the Universal Religious Convention, at the World's Columbian Exposition.</p>
   <p>The prelate of the Mother Church, after the holy liturgy, delivered his memorable address in the crowded church, and, as I remember, there was not a single person persent who did not shed tears of joy. Briefly, I will try to give exerpts from his address.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0178.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"This commercial edifice, sanctified, serves the Holy Greek Orthodox Church, the Mother of Christendom. The divine spirit of Orthodoxy is here, in spite of the humble edifice and its surroundings. This is the cardinal stone of the future Orthodox Church in your community. The Savior of the world war born in a stable. Magnificence is pleasing to the eye and mind. Spiritual faith is above all. You are to be congratulated on perpetuating Greek traditions, emanating from God, and in God you rejoice. Greeks, the world over, have begun with Alpha and reached Omega; the time is not far distant when your community will have its own church. In the name of our Holy Mother Church, I bless you all."</p>
   <p>So in 1892 began the functioning of the first Greek Orthodox Church in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
