<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1933-09-30">Sept. 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Has the Salt Lost its Savor?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0060</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0060.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1933-09-30">Sept. 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">HAS THE SALT LOST ITS SAVOR?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2.--Somewhere in the Holy Scriptures is written,</p>
   <p>"If the salt has lost its savor, wherewithal shall it be salted?"</p>
   <p>And this salt was and is the officials of the Church who represent it.</p>
   <p>And now let us examine what is going on among the clergy, in particular among the clergy of our great city of Chicago, where Greeks abound.</p>
   <p>Let us begin with the head of our Church, the Right Reverend Bishop Kallistos of San Francisco, who ought by this time to have been named Bishop of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0061.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In these times of dreadful depression all that he does is to take care of himself and his subordinates, the priests. Now when all are afflicted with financial difficulties and terrible sufferings, he is interested in his own comfort and in that of his priests and tries cruelly and inhumanly to tax his pious and faithful flock under the pretext of saving the churches and the schools and to promote the infamous Union of Priests with all the ruthlessness that people will endure.</p>
   <p>We wonder why the mystery of the priesthood and the discipline of the ecclesiastical hierarchy are not ties sufficiently strong to maintain the unity of the clergy.</p>
   <p>Has not the Church sufficient authority to impose discipline on its priests in their relations with their flocks? Must they form a distinct Union, an authority within authority?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0062.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Is not the result of a similar union among Boston policemen still fresh in our memory, that is to say, their strike?</p>
   <p>Has Bishop Kallistos tried to care for the numerous victims of this depression among his pious flock? Has he organized any agency to relieve these persons who are now the pariahs of his society?</p>
   <p>In the Greek center on the West Side where two of his churches are located are two apostates, Greeks, who are scorned for their apostasy, and who daily vociferate there. But these heretics distribute food to the destitute Greeks of that neighborhood, and the Greeks go to listen to them and get a few bits of food donated by other Greeks from whom the apostates collect it in their rounds.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0063.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>All other Churches and various social organizations have established centers for the care and relief of the poor; only our glorious Orthodoxy sleeps under the mandrake and satisfies itself with a few appeals and pompous pretensions.</p>
   <p>And what shall we say when, as we are told, clergymen are engaging in profitable enterprises, neglecting their high calling to become real-estate dealers and stock-market manipulators, frankly admitting that they care only for the few who can pay regularly (so we are informed), and that they are indifferent to all others? That shows their mentality and their sense of duty.</p>
   <p>But the matter which is most talked about, most scandalous, and the greatest source of temptation among Orthodox Christians is the fact that the Diocese here has for years kept as its secretary a former apostate, Mr. Alexander, who may be a man of ability, a man in every way qualified for this position, but who nevertheless repudiated his faith some years ago and now has returned and receives a salary!</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0064.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We do not know how to define or to characterize this, but if it is not commercializing our holy faith, we cannot distinguish light from darkness.</p>
   <p>And this is not all. This gentleman some time ago undertook to organize catechetical Sunday schools for children; he is considered a specialist in this field because the sect to which he adhered before his reconversion to Orthodoxy, or rather the sect to which he probably still adheres, has an excellent system of proselyting, and so he was the one to whom this task was entrusted.</p>
   <p>But to accomplish this, he appointed young ladies to teach the children of Greek Orthodox parents the system of the sect with which he had been affiliated, and to teach them in English from the books printed for that sect! He himself devoted only five or ten minutes of the time to teaching them in Greek, and all the remaining time was applied by his instructors to teaching in English!</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0065.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>This secretary has become so powerful that he directs the office-work of the Diocese here as he pleases, and he wields an intolerable influence over the Bishop, who is probably unconscious of what is really going on.</p>
   <p>Besides these and other minor indications that the proselytizing influence of this propaganda has been steadily crawling to the very doorstep of the head of our Church, we have lately been informed that the club of girls and boys which he organized some time ago in St. Demetry's Church was disbanded because this gentleman began to preach to the youth things which he wanted to be kept secret from their parents, a rumor which our judgment of the man and of his ability leads us to discredit.</p>
   <p>Not wishing to continue at length on this subject nor to add more details, we cannot avoid expressing our astonishment that no able Orthodox Greek among the clergy or the laity could be found to fill the office of secretary of the Diocese except this reconverted apostate!</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0066.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Why cannot people realize the injurious effect upon this flock and upon Greek Orthodoxy in general of this gentleman's scandalous propaganda?</p>
   <p>Are there not Orthodox Greeks to transact the business of that office? And will not the impression prevail that in order to be promoted, one must first be an apostate to the Greek Orthodox Church?</p>
   <p>And in conclusion, observing the various strange and paradoxical actions of the present organization of the Greek Orthodox Church here, we cannot help expressing our astonishment and asking whether the salt has not lost its savor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
