<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-11-14">Nov. 14, 1931</date><title level="a">The Greeks in America, Then and Now</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. Volicos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1421</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1421.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-11-14">Nov. 14, 1931</date><title level="a">THE GREEKS IN AMERICA, THEN AND NOW</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. Volicos</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.- The influx of Greek immigration to America began fifty years ago. Thousands of young Greeks came to the land of hope. Tens of thousands followed them. And a little over 500,000 Greeks are now living all over the country, and are not lost souls, as the leaders of Greece inferred, when thousands upon thousands were departing for America, the far away country, the country of the Indians, etc. Greece was sad at loosing so much young blood, and very skeptical concerning the welfare of those departing souls.</p>
   <p>Indeed it was difficult for those political leaders of Greece to picture in their mind any favorable outcome for those departing emigrants. Why? Because they felt that these people, most of which were uneducated, with no vocation, with no knowledge of the country to which they were going, with very little experience even in the life of their own country, would not be able to adjust themselves to the new environment of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1422.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The great majority of Greek immigrants came from farms and small villages. Not speaking the language of the land to which they were going, the unfriendly attitude of the natives, and many other things were considered by the administration of Greece, to be of disadvantage to the departing young Greeks.</p>
   <p>It is true the Greeks were surrounded by all these disadvantages, with the exception of the unfriendly attitude of the Americans. The American people not only were friendly to those Greeks and all immigrants in general, but gave them any and every possible assistance for their welfare. The wise and well-goverened American with a far-reaching vision in his mind, received and treated those Greeks as well as all the coming foreigners, with the same care and tenderness as the natives received. There was no discrimination made in favor of any one. Freedom, justice, and protection to all. There was education by day or night to suit the wishes of the immigrants and great tolerance towards the ignorance of this new element.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1423.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The writer of this article, living in Chicago for the last forty years, owing to his medical profession, has visited many centers inhabited by Greeks, and has obtained a true picture of the struggling Greek element in this country. Dr. Volicos tells of a distinguished American delivering an address, who said, "In this world of today, anyone wishing to live, must take into consideration three things, that he either works, steals, or bags." The wise and learned American, Laconically, spoke a profound truth.</p>
   <p>The Greek immigrant, who brought with him his religious devotion to the laws of the country and Greek progressiveness, could not do otherwise but choose work for his career. The vicissitudes were great. The Greek immigrant, encouraged by the covenants of this country, engraved in his mind work and progress. He soon learned enough English to transact business, adopted the American standard of living, accumulated a little money and soon had his own business. But the responsibilities and the obligations of the Greek towards his beloved ones and his mother country were not neglected or forgotten.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1424.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Millions and millions of dollars were sent to relatives and the mother country. Thousands of Greek girls were brought here to perpetuate the Greek race in America. Churches and schools sprang up every where to keep up the Greek traditions. Americanization in big strides began to flourish. Colleges and Universities enrolled tens of thousands of Greek-Americans. Social and political life began to take notice of the product of the poor immigrant Greek. And so the political leaders of Greece (if they are alive) began to reckon that the Greek emigrants departing from Greece, fifty years ago, are not lost souls. The present leaders of Greece, look upon the Greek polity of America, as the future hope and strength of that country that once was great. The Greece of America today is looked upon by all the Greeks of the world as the best promising foundation for the race. Educated in American institutions, in every branch, these young and vigorous Greek-Americans are setting out to bind the world into a new civilization.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1425.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The wise and just American fathers of this great Republic, whose minds could see the future, made no mistake in receiving the Greek and the rest of the immigrants with friendliness, tolerance non-descrimination, justice, and will not regret the great expenditures made for the education and welfare of these Greek immigrants. With pride, I say that the Greek-American element, which is an integral part of the American Republic, if it is not the best, is one of the best. The Greek of America, today, is educated, devout in his religion and faithful and obedient to the laws of this country, and a philanthropist to the extreme point. Work and progress are his Greek traditions. What else makes a good citizen?</p>
   <p>But Greece, his original mother country and the mother country of all the civilized world, is always remembered and honored. The Greeks of America pay homage to Greece by excursions, in order to spread good-will bringing America and Greece closer together in their relationships.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1426.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The Greeks of America have contributed greatly to the erection of American colleges, Y.M.C.A's, hospitals, orphanages, and many other institutions. So, in closing my article, I'm proud to say that the Greeks of America, in such a short period of time and with all the handicaps mentioned, has evolved great progress. I also wish to say with certainty that the new Greek-American, in generations to come, will unfold the Stars and Stripes in every part of the world, as Alexander the Great spread the Greek civilization of the past.</p>
   <p>(Summary)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
