<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1917-08-08">August 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Greeks for America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1310</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1310.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1917-08-08">August 8, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">GREEKS FOR AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>History tells us, and every child knows, that the United States, many times has been the benefactor of Greece. To us Greeks, America, is so dear and beloved that Greece and America are inseparable countries. A Greek who does not love America does not love Greece. And he who does not love his benefactor is an ungrateful being.</p>
   <p>The Greeks are not ungrateful beings, because they love America. Right now, according to statistics there are 10,000 Greek volunteers in the army, and 5,000 in the navy. The volunteer service of the Greek in the United States navy in big numbers is not a new thing. When Mixoulis, a Greek Man-of-War, arrived in New York, two of the biggest cruisers of the United States, New York and Kentucky, came the next day for salutation. On these two boats alone there were 500 Greek sailors in the service of the United States navy.</p>
   <p>At the naval battle of Manila, Greeks played a brilliant role as gunners. Greeks were the first to die for their country, and the first to storm the forts.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1311.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Greeks all over the country head the volunteers' list. They excel any other nationality per capita. That is a record, and an honor for the Greek name. But we could never do too much for America. The American Army is composed of many nationalities. Let us play our role in this composite army, that the Greek race will be distinguished. Let us play our part with such enthusiasm and self-denial that the rest of our brother-soldiers will take notice.</p>
   <p>Whatever part we play now, America, likewise will play in the interest of mother Greece when hostilities are terminated. When the congress of peace takes place, the American Greeks must have valid ground to request America to speak in behalf of Greece. And that valid ground will be our response to the needs of America. Therefore, every Greek community in the United States must do more than its share in order to maintain our past distinction. Respond to the call of our country and respond first. America is at war. Clothe yourself with the grandest emblem in the world, the United States flag. Fight under it and you will be honored.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
