<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-10-26">Oct. 26, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Our Church</title><title level="a" type="sub">What Is Wrong with the Archdiocese and the Mixed Board of Trustees?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0107</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0107.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1932-10-26">Oct. 26, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">OUR CHURCH</title><title level="a" type="sub">What Is Wrong With The Archdiocese And The Mixed Board of Trustees?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Revealing Letter by Mr. S. Kanoutas</p>
   <p>New York, Oct. 7, 1932.</p>
   <p>To The Honorable Boards of Trustees of the Greek Communities of America.</p>
   <p>Gentlemen:</p>
   <p>I, the undersigned, having been elected by the Fourth General Assembly as a member of the Mixed Board of Trustees of the Greek Archdiocese of North and South America, and having accepted this elected trust with the sincere desire and intention of performing my duties conscientiously and faithfully, consider it my duty and obligation to report to you, with regret and bitter disappointment, the following:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0108.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>First, that although it is almost a year now since the election of the Mixed Board of Trustees took place, this body has not as yet been installed officially in its duties, nor has the property of the organization been delivered over to it, except for a small amount of cash delivered by the former treasurer to the new one.</p>
   <p>Second, that in compliance with my duties, I repeatedly pointed out to the Archbishop as president, both verbally and in writing, that it was the obligation of the new Mixed Board of Trustees to take over the property of the organization, including receipts and minutes of the meetings of previous boards, titles, contracts, money, and all documents of the organization, so that they might get acquainted with the condition of the organization, its property rights and social obligations and be able to apply a proper economic system suited to present conditions and the critical circumstances we are going through, but he paid no attention to my suggestions.</p>
   <p>Third, that to my conception although the Board of Trustees, according <pb facs="5422062_5_0109.jpg" n="3"/>to law, is responsible for handling the affairs of the Archdiocese, it is ignored almost entirely by the Archbishop in all important problems of the organization, and it is only a formality, not the governing body the community think it is. For these reasons Mr. Eliaskos, a member, has resigned and I myself am thinking of resigning so that I will not have such responsibilities any longer.</p>
   <p>Fourth, that, and this is more specific: (a) The Board of Trustees does not receive any monthly report, nor has it any knowledge of the condition or the expenses of the organization, as Article 18 of its rules specifies, and it has not received any such report in at least two or three months; (b) The bills to be paid are not submitted to the Board for examination and approval, as Articles 6 and 19 specify; (c) The Board of Trustees does not handle 'the whole property, real and personal,' of the Archdiocese, nor 'inspects and examines the government and administration of the estates of the monasteries, philanthropic institutions, etc.,' as <pb facs="5422062_5_0110.jpg" n="4"/>paragraphs a, b, e, and f of Article 10 of the rules specify, nor was it ever given the opportunity to ascertain with exactness the condition or financial status of the organization, so that it could put them in order on decrease expenses, as paragraphs g, h, j, f, and k, of Article 10 specify, and also the latter part of Article 15; (d) The minutes of the formal meetings of the Board for unimportant matters are kept by the accountant, read by the Archbishop, and later copied in a book kept by the Archbishop, which book has never been touched by the secretary or any of the other members of the Board; up to this day they have not even been signed, as Articles 4 and 6 specify, so there are no valid minutes, and the decisions of the Board, if any, usually are not executed.</p>
   <p>Fifth, that the Mixed Council, or Board of Trustees, was never notified about the hiring and firing of the personnel of the Archdiocese, as Article 10 specifies; in consequence, the Board does not know any more than you do of what is going on there in the Archdiocese. There was never any discussion about or serious consideration of the orphans and the poor, <pb facs="5422062_5_0111.jpg" n="5"/>although it is written down on the rules concerning the rules of the Board (Article 10, Par. e) that 'it is the duty of the Board to supervise the philanthropic societies, etc.'</p>
   <p>Sixth, that various encyclical letters of the Archdiocese to the communities and the priests, or published in the press, never were submitted to the Board, and they unfortunately contain inaccuracies and contradictions on matters never decided or approved by the Board, as well as unprepared and exaggerated statements impossible of performance, as for example, the subject of contributions, or the statement of getting together all the Greek orphans three years old or over and sending them to an orphanage which does not exist; also about a committee of Lawyers; about a decision to buy a new building; about cutting down the salaries of the personnel, etc.</p>
   <p>Seventh, that in general, this organization (a corporation) is governed in a peculiar and singular way, not in conformity with either the <pb facs="5422062_5_0112.jpg" n="6"/>laws of the State of its own constitution, but by one individual, the Archbishop, who in spite of his good intentions is not well familiarized with everything that goes on, on account of his many trips and his insufficient knowledge of the laws, customs and conditions. Consequently, he makes mistakes and contradictory statements that reflect upon the whole Board, which as I said before, has no knowledge of his actions, his promises, or expenses.</p>
   <p>Eighth, that because of this lack of system, order and sincere cooperation, the whole service is crippled, and financial conditions of the organization is in a state of chaos, no matter how much money be collected. The building of the Archdiocese is mortgaged for double its value. Various suits against the organization, the largest of which is that of former Bishop Philaretos of Chicago, for $19,000, never were discussed or examined. No thought was given or suggestion made for their payment or to cut them down. This terrible financial condition of the organization, as I learned unofficially, is admitted by the Archbishop <pb facs="5422062_5_0113.jpg" n="7"/>himself in a letter sent to the communities three or four months ago, undersigned by him, the secretary, and the treasurer.</p>
   <p>Ninth, that from the above and other indications, which I cannot report in this open letter, I am convinced that the Archbishop does not want to cooperate with advisers who have an independent opinion. Not withstanding his official and open declaration at the General Assembly last year that he would not accept to rule as a dictator even if it were offered to him, the fact is that he now is ruling as one with private counsels who are ignorant or seek personal profits. As a result if he ever pays attention to the rules it is to interpret them as he likes.</p>
   <p>I thought, Honorable Presidents and members of the Board, that I would fail in my duty and obligation if I did not report to you the above mentioned facts. I know that in reporting these facts I am probably displeasing many, even my own friends, but I thought of my responsibilities before you and before the law, if I were to keep silent forever.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0114.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Finally, I wish to declare that I am not in favor or against the dictatorial system, as it is the right and privilege of the Greek community to decide on the system they prefer.</p>
   <p>If it is good, beneficial and not in violation of the laws of the country to adopt a dictatorial system, if the various communities want it, if the Archbishop desires to accept all alone such responsibility, I think that must be declared openly and sincerely. In that case then the organization now in existence since 1921 must be disolved. The religious corporation now under the name Greek Archdiocese of North and South America, incorporated, which according to the law must be governed by a responsible Board of Trustees, must cease to exist officially and the Board also, instead of being in existence only as a formality, but bearing full responsibility for whatever its president does.</p>
   <p>I remain</p>
   <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>S. A. Kanoutas</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
