<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-02-18">Feb. 18, 1932</date><title level="a">Our Churches</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0145</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0145.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-02-18">Feb. 18, 1932</date><title level="a">OUR CHURCHES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.- Well aware of our journalistic duties, and our great respect and love for our countrymen, we are once again prompted to bring up this church matter. For thirty-two months the Greek Press has been trying to make a better future for the Greek people of America and for their children. Raising a scandal or indignant response by this article we are now writing is the farthest thing from our minds.</p>
   <p>From much study and observation we feel that we know quite a bit about this church matter and are in a position to speak our minds. We are not speaking against any individual or any group of individuals. We are thinking of Hellenism in Chicago as a whole. We want to add our advice and suggestions, because we feel that the problem has gotten beyond the few who have tried to solve it.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0146.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Greeks in Chicago are free to go their own way, doing as they please, under obligation to no one; but there comes a crisis when they must "stick" together. Such a crisis is before us now. Nothing can be done without the wholehearted support of every Greek in the city. The church plays an important part in everyone's life and must not be taken lightly.</p>
   <p>It is known to all, that for the last three years some of our churches have been on the brink of closing, and we have done nothing about it. What can we do? They say it is a great crime and a great shame if we are forced to close our churches. But how can we prevent this? The Bishop's plans have not worked. They have helped, but we still have a debt of $475,000. The presidents of the churches are on the verge of despair; the priests are afraid to lose their jobs; the people, their religion. All is chaos! And the solution is so simple. Why not close two or three of the churches and concentrate on saving the others? It can easily be done. It is better to have a few strong churches than none at all. We can afford to keep all our priests, but not all our churches. Think over this suggestion and act upon it soon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
