<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-07-18">July 18, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Papanastasiou Visits America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1641</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1641.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-07-18">July 18, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">PAPANASTASIOU VISITS AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the exception of but one other time, the Hellenism of America has never expressed more strickingly the love which still binds it to Greece than it did yesterday when Alexander Papanastasiou was met at his train. Great and glorious Greece, whose ancient citizens are still considered the finest exponents of thought and science, cannot claim many great men during the past hundred years. She cannot point out strong and dynamic leaders who will leave evidence of their existence in the history of the world; she has few international figures. Four hundred years of slavery destroyed every idealistic and creative urge in the people. The productive capacity of the land itself was lessened rather than increased. Cicero once said, "Wisdom was enthroned in the very hovels of the Greek people." All that was destroyed by the Turks during their tyrannical reign.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1642.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The lamp of knowledge, which had belonged to the Greeks for thousands of years, was dimmed when Constantinople was made an eastern city. While Greece was intellectually deteriorating, the Western Hemisphere was rapidly learning, socially and ideologically. Following the liberation of the Greek nation, the Greek intellectuals turned to the western world for illumination. At first, only the children of wealthy parents could go to Europe for study. Before long, however, the middle classes began to realize the importance of intellectual training and made every effort to study abroad. By the beginning of the twentieth century the majority of Greek intellectuals had been educated in Europe, Up till then, most of these students had had very practical reasons for going to Paris or Berlin. They merely wanted to get better positions in their fields of activity. From 1905 to 1910 we see a noteworthy number of Greeks going to Europe on government scholarships for the express purpose of studying the various governments and the political policies of that turbulent continent. All who lived in Greece during that period probably recall the plethora of intelligentsia who having studied in Europe, returned armed with the knowledge of the new social cosmogony which was then spreading over Europe. A spirit of <pb facs="5422062_5_1643.jpg" n="3"/>liberty was growing and horizons were widening, preparatory to a new, synchronized social rebirth.</p>
   <p>These men were the brightest Greek minds of their time, and for that reason won the support and admiration of the people who, due to the foolish governing policies to which they had been subjected, were seeking new men to lead them. One of those men who saw the rapid widening of the new horizon and who sensed its tremendous possibilities was Alexander Papanastasiou. He was one of that group of sociologists....The map of Europe and the rest of the world underwent many changes during these times. Governments and political organizations were basically changed, and some were completely uprooted. Kings and tyrannical dictators made their appearance upon the scene. Apostles and heralds of the social change went over to the side of the enemy and "blackjacked" the freedom of their countries.</p>
   <p>Alexander Papanastasiou was the only man in Greece to remain true to his political and moral beliefs.....Active in the political life of his country, he reached <pb facs="5422062_5_1644.jpg" n="4"/>high peaks of renown; for, despite the many upheavals and radical changes he maintained his spiritual and moral precepts, and remained true to his political faith. He knew his beliefs were founded on truth and justice. This is the brief outline of the life of Mr. A. Papanastasiou, who is internationally acknowledged as a great leader; and who is now the defender of democracy in Greece. Educated as are few other Greeks, a modern patriot, calm in spirit, and above petty political jealousies--he has earned the respect and love of every Greek in the world. To an even greater extent has he earned the love of the Greeks in America who have acquired a social consciousness about liberty and equality because they live under a government run according to the rules of the Constitution as outlined by Jefferson. Jefferson has always been the idol and inspiration of our celebrated visitor and, therefore, has indirectly helped to write the Constitution of our own Greek democracy--fought for and won by Alexander Papanastasiou.</p>
   <p>The Greeks of Chicago are proud to welcome a great democrat.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
