<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-06-06">June 6, 1918</date>, p. 2
<title level="a">Curious Things the Greek Bazaar</title><title level="a" type="sub">Consul's Picture Bought for $5.25</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0787</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0787.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1918-06-06">June 6, 1918</date>, p. 2
<title level="a">CURIOUS THINGS THE GREEK BAZAAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">CONSUL'S PICTURE BOUGHT FOR $5.25</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek Bazaar, which ended last week with great success, brought to light many curious things.</p>
   <p>Merchants of all descriptions sent in many and various articles to be sold for the benefit of the Bazaar. Housewives and young women sent in a great variety of handiwork laces, embroideries, woven blankets, rare fine Cretan work, and what not. But the most curious and the strangest article for sale was the picture of the Greek Consul-General of Chicago. The Greek diplomat as a contributor to the success of the Bazaar deemed it advisable to send in his picture, set in an artistic five dollar frame, to be sold for the benefit of the Bazaar.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0788.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The picture was not easily disposed of; indeed, there was no buyer for such a article of houseware or hardware. And the barker's hammer brought the price of the picture, with frame and screws included, to $5.25; that is, five dollars for frame and screws, as the barker advertised their cost, and twenty five cents for the picture of the diplomat.</p>
   <p>Well, of course it is not the fault of the Greek Consul that his picture was so cheaply disposed of. The fault lies with the auctioneer, who should have known better and have said that the frame alone had cost $50 or $100 and not five dollars as was actually the case. Anyway, barkers must set a limit to their cries, and when they see that an article is useless, they generally let it go for practically nothing in order to get rid of it. Well, the Bazaar must be satisfied, for the Consul's picture brought in twenty five cents. Better luck next time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
