<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-04-04">April 4, 1931</date><title level="a">Hellenic Archdiocese of North and South America</title><title level="a" type="sub">To the Most Pious Hectors, Honorable Communal Councils and the Pious Flock of our Holy Archdiocese.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0276</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0276.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-04-04">April 4, 1931</date><title level="a">HELLENIC ARCHDIOCESE OF NORTH AND SOUTH AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">To the Most Pious Hectors, Honorable Communal Councils and the Pious Flock of our Holy Archdiocese.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear and loveliest children of God:</p>
   <p>It is a consolation to notice among the tradition prevailing here taking up a collection in our churches, on Easter Sunday, for the needs of the Great Mother of the Church of Christ, the Ecumenical Patriarchate.</p>
   <p>Se know well, our dear children, the economic crisis that you are going through at present. We watch your obligations; we sympathize with you from the bottom of our heart and pray that the Almighty fortify you in your noble struggle for life.</p>
   <p>But we are certain, that you are aware of the conditions of your religious center also, and you realize its economic difficulties and its many obligations and, assuredly, you have compassion like grateful and affectionate children.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0277.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Here is, then, the opportunity to show up all your devotion towards the Ecumenical Patriarchate, here is the opportunity to express, this year also, all your love and reverance to this Great Holy Mother, by contributing according to your ability for her economic support so that she may exist to perpetuate your religious ideals.</p>
   <p>The rectors of the holy Churches shall read and explain this circular to you and with the various honorable presidents of the communities collect what funds you offer which funds shall be forwarded to us immediately.</p>
   <p>Remaining confident that your piousness will not fail us this year, but that it will better your contributions of past years, we wish you the joy of Christ Resurrection, whose great mercy, and with our blessings, be with you all.</p>
   <p>New York, March 26, 1931</p>
   <p>Athenagoras of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
