<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>
      <date when="1928-10-25">Oct. 25, 1928</date>
      <title level="a">Peace</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0466</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0466.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>
     <date when="1928-10-25">Oct. 25, 1928</date>
     <title level="a">PEACE</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- We have been unceasingly expressing our opinions through these colums, regarding our Ecclesiastic division having one aim, that is, how to bridge the chasm that divides the Greeks of America into two hostile Ecclesiastic camps and how to accomplish the unity of our churches under one Ecclesiastic authority.</p>
   <p>We shall continue to call the attention of Greeks to this most important Ecclesiastical question, which has paralyzed the cooperation, unity, and strength of our communities. It will completely destroy and ruin them before long---churches, schools and all.</p>
   <p>We were often severe in our attacks, but at the same time we never ceased urging calm discussion and understanding of those who hold prominent positions in our society, because we believed that such an approach between members of both sides could not but lead to satissfactory results, and contribute greatly towards finding ways and means for unity and peace.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0467.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After divulging the facts in these columns, in order to show what deplorable condition our church affairs are in, we appeal again to those who hold high positions in our community and are involved in this question to contribute towards the restoration of Ecclesiastic peace and to devote all their efforts towards revising their thoughts for the sole purpose of bridging the chasm so that clamness may be restored amongst our communities again.</p>
   <p>We know that many who have the best and noblest patriotic sentiments have a false impression about the matter. Most people see only the surface and are in the dark altogether in regards to the reality of this sad and deplorable question, ignorance and fanaticism being the guiding lights for their actions</p>
   <p>It is for this reason exactly, that we challenged those whose duties were to take up our questions, answer them publicly, disclose their views, and submit back to us any questions. If they had answered us openly there would not be any feeling among us that they are dealing in subterfuges and distortions.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0468.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They evaded our challenge to have a public discussion, and sidde stepped the opportunity to enlighten the public on the subject. Why? We have the right to say that it was because it was against their interest that people learn the truth, their interest being to keep people divided so tha they may rule.</p>
   <p>Is it not lso the desire of Vasilios to perpetuate division and dissention? How otherwise could Vasilios remain in America if it was not for division? But if the Ecclesiastical interests are to have as their principle the maxim "Divide and Rule", must we tolerate two hostile camps for the interests of some gentlemen of the cloak?</p>
   <p>It is not time that we, as men bearing all the responsibilities of our communal conditions, come together and stop this serving of the intersts of these gentlemen? How can our communities be maintained? How can our schools be operated? How can the big debts of our communities be paid? How can education and preservation of our nationalism be upheld so long as we are divided into two opposite camps?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0469.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>For this reason we appeal again to the members of our community to come together, and as good patriots, pleace above everything else the communal and national interests, and let the clergy go to one side.</p>
   <p>Set this exampple and unity of our communities will certainly be accomplished. In this way Chicago would have the honor and distinction of leading the way towards unity of the Greek communities of the America.</p>
   <p>All good patriots from both sides coming together will accomplish peace, and to their patriotic sentiments we appeal.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
   <p>Summary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
