<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-07-12">July 12, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Who Is to Blame?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1061</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1061.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-07-12">July 12, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">WHO IS TO BLAME?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An official statement of the church committee appeared in Hellas which embodied the decisions reached in conference by our clergymen and church leaders. In a sense, this statement is a protest against our fair criticism of the way the affairs of our church community are conducted. We felt that we should undertake this criticism since we consider ourselves the vigilant guardians of the interests of the community.</p>
   <p>By this statement, the heads of our parish purport to prove that our community or parish is far from divided or disorganized, that it is making rapid progress in a spirit of complete harmony. They have taken this stand because, come what may, they do not wish the Greek communities in other states to know that we are divided.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1062.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Even though they are illusory, the statements made by the members of our church governing board are really comforting. But let us say that the progressive spirit of the twentieth century does not tolerate wishful thinking; it demands facts and achievements.</p>
   <p>Although the Greeks are a progressive group, we have noticed that, as a whole, the Greek Community of Chicago has made no progress despite the great efforts and contributions which all of us have made. It is impossible to have peace and harmony in a community which is divided into contentious groups, which is torn apart and plundered because of suits and court actions involving our clergymen.</p>
   <p>A community with three wrangling factions, each supporting a different priest, with the Holy Synod and the Greek people of Chicago as silent onlookers, and with so much bitter personal hatred among the warring supporters of the priests, cannot be a peaceful and harmoneously functioning organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1063.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In vain have the members of the church board attempted to dispel the prevalent idea that there is civil war among the priests and their followers. That civil strife does exist is a widely known and self-evident fact, not in the least doubted by those who can judge. To be convinced of this, one has only to remember that throughout the last five years, right up to this very day, violent controversy and continuous strife have been going on because of this same problem of our priests. Even the casual student of our community will notice that our wrangling is the order of the day in the city's courts.</p>
   <p>Though we have high respect for the sacred calling of the ministry, may we be permitted to observe that the entire attention and all the energies of our priests have been diverted to this strife among themselves? They are doing their very best to discredit and ostracize one another; each is trying to get the largest number of followers. This is the reason why they participated secretly in the last community elections, in spite of the unconstitutionality of these election activities of theirs. They even succeeded in forming parties <pb facs="5422062_5_1064.jpg" n="4"/>of their own, so that who can deny that today we have one party headed by the Reverend Cyril, one headed by Reverend Mandilaris, and one controlled by Reverend Pygeas?</p>
   <p>Is this state of affairs going to be perpetuated? Who will disagree with The Star's suggestion that only the recall of all these priests to Greece by the Holy Synod of Athens and by the responsible bishop will restore peace and harmony among the members of our community?</p>
   <p>Now, leaving the matter of our priests, let us consider the question of Mr. Geocaris' gift of one hundred dollars to the church. The members of the church board have declared that the secretary's work would be endless if letters were to be sent to each and every benefactor or to everyone that contributes to the church. By Jove, we never expected such an excuse, for there were very few who donated more than one hundred dollars. But, in the final analysis, will you please tell us why we pay the secretary? The church never even mentioned the <pb facs="5422062_5_1065.jpg" n="5"/>name of Mr. Geocaris, as it did in the case of other contributors, nor was his name mentioned in the minutes of the various meetings, as required by article forty-three of the bylaws.</p>
   <p>The church leaders are now making noisy statements expressing their attitude toward the incident of Reverend Cyril and their desire to establish a new church and Greek school. Much has been written on these subjects. There is no need to waste time in the discussion of a subject which has assumed so many different aspects in the political confusion of our community. Besides, we are tired of hearing about the erection of new churches and new schools. Such projects exist only in the imagination of our "ambitious" leaders, and who knows when the day for their realization will come?</p>
   <p>In publishing the above-mentioned statement of protest, our good church board members have shown that they did not have the courage and the strength to accept our criticisms. On the contrary, they attacked us for meddling unnecessarily in the affairs of the church. We consider it the duty of this newspaper to <pb facs="5422062_5_1066.jpg" n="6"/>stand fearlessly and calmly, despite the violent attacks directed against it. We shall continue to call a spade a spade, oblivious to our friendship with some of the wrongdoers and unaffected by the abusive language which is directed against us by an old and decrepit newspaper which is being edited in a "stable".</p>
   <p>Independent, as always, and belonging to the people, we will never cease condemning every evil influence, and we shall continue to denounce all those whose activities are detrimental to the best interests of the people. We shall do so for the sake of the community and the truth.</p>
   <p>Quite a few individuals were annoyed because we took the initiative in attacking th extravagant and costly administration of our community. We have done so only after long study and careful investigation have provided proof of who is responsible for this extravagance and waste.</p>
   <p>We are submitting a detailed list of the extravagant and unnecessary expenditures which were made by our church administrators as actual evidence of the <pb facs="5422062_5_1067.jpg" n="7"/>incompetence of our church leaders and the injustice which is being done to our community. [Translator's note: This detailed list has been ommitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>So we see that in a period of four months, $1,203.70 was spent unnecessarily and with no profit or appreciable return to the church community. Of course, this money was spent honestly and in accordance with the provisions of the bylaws, so we cannot accuse Mr. Rifakis and his associates of dishonesty. But we must admit--and we should be ashamed of the fact--that this amount has been spent for no worthy purpose. For example, last March we gave a big dance which cost us $590. This was the sacrifice which we offered to our fatherland on the anniversary of our national independence. Another luxury was the expenditure of ninety dollars for golden church lamps. Does the difficult lot of our fatherland warrant such huge expenditures for the church? Is this the way to show our patriotism and wisdom?</p>
   <p>There are many other articles which were not needed. As truthful and fair men,</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
