<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-03-19">March 19, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Movement Toward Separation Continues the Simultaneous Purchase of Three Churches in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0577</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0577.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-03-19">March 19, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE MOVEMENT TOWARD SEPARATION CONTINUES THE SIMULTANEOUS PURCHASE OF THREE CHURCHES IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- Undoubtedly Orthodox Christian people will leap for joy today, both the influential Patriarchate of Constantinople and the Holy Synod of Greece - the Most Holy Patriarch of which, Alexander Kos Meletios, will especially rejoice - when they hear the great message which in these columns of the Greek Daily will be promulgated throughout the Orthodox world. The Greek community of Chicago has acquired three new churches within the space of one week!</p>
   <p>This is no trivial matter; it merits the attention of all those who follow the development and the progress of Orthodox Christianity, and who from such observation derive conclusions and form opinions. These conclusions and opinions, interpreting the significance of what has been achieved, will naturally be very favorable; leaders of the Orthodox faith will heap <pb facs="5422062_5_0578.jpg" n="2"/>blessings and eulogies on the founders of these three new churches, institutions of which the purpose is to glorify and bless the name of our Lord and to teach devotion, harmony, and love for our fellow-men.</p>
   <p>This really cannot be considered a small or insignificant event. Here we have the actual conversion of three churches of other denominations into Orthodox churches. Thus on the South Side we see a Swedish Protestant church transformed to a Greek Orthodox church; on the North Side a Masonic Temple now houses an Orthodox congregation; and a Hebrew synagogue on the West Side turns to Orthodox Christianity.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, however, this achievement, this news which serves as the basis for many consoling and cheering conclusions, is not so great as it appears. A study of the causes for the acquisition of these three church buildings will result in anything but joy and satisfaction.</p>
   <p>First of all, this fact is apparent to every one, that because of the limitations imposed by the immigration laws, we do not now have many immigrants from Greece, and consequently there is no justification for <pb facs="5422062_5_0579.jpg" n="3"/>the simultaneous foundation of three Greek Orthodox churches. However, that which really alters the significance of this news is that neither Christian zeal nor the urgings of faith caused the purchase of these three new churches but the hatred, the passion, and the spirit of revenge which serve petty interests and cultivate the seeds of separation. Aye, it is the vicious demon of separation rearing his head again, that demon who has plagued America's Hellenism for so many years. With his experience he is certainly in a position to guide and encourage his devotees, the separatists.</p>
   <p>More specifically, these churches were not purchased in order to fulfill the community's requirements, for there are two churches on the North Side and two on the West Side, and as for the South Side, though its church has burned down, church services continue, since another place has been rented. No, the community required no new churches, but the archbishopric, having no parishes of its own in Chicago, decided to form some out of the existing parishes, and with this intention Archbishop Alexander came to Chicago and formulated a plan for founding new parishes and purchasing churches in order to break the agreement reached in the ecclesiastical settlement of Chicago's Greek community whereby all the <pb facs="5422062_5_0580.jpg" n="4"/>churches except that one which was burned, St. Constantine's, acknowledged the religious hegemony of the Holy Synod of Greece. This, and this only, is the reason for the archbishopric's founding these churches. In other words, separation and discord are being fostered in Chicago's Greek community in order to fulfill the saying, "Those who come without peace leave discord behind."</p>
   <p>And now, O purchasers and proprietors of your new churches, open their doors and come out in all your glory that the world may pay homage to you, but remember one thing, one fact which remains indisputable: you have no places except those which you have purchased, for the parishes of Chicago's Greek community have closed the doors of their churches to you.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
