<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-03-15">Mar. 15, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Products for America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1676</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1676.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-03-15">Mar. 15, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK PRODUCTS FOR AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An examination of the condition of the present-day Greeks and that of those who first came to America thirty years ago will reveal the great economic and social progress of the Greeks in this country. Of course, some of this progress must be credited to the natural growth of America and the opportunities the country afforded; but the greater part of it is directly due to the Greeks own hard and untiring labor and struggles. The Greek, even when enslaved in body, never loses his individualism, and never ceases to think as a free man. These characteristics, which have always distinguished him, provided him with the weapons necessary to fight for existence in a foreign country. They provided him with the spiritual strength which is so necessary for success. And it was these very same qualities that gave him the courage to enter into business in this country to such a great extent that now he practically <pb facs="5422062_5_1677.jpg" n="2"/>monopolizes certain branches of it......</p>
   <p>Greeks succeeded in weathering the worst of the depression a great deal better than most other groups . Today the number of Greek stores is as great, if not greater than the number in 1929, when America reached the zenith of its prosperity. During this entire period the Greek entrepreneur did not lose any of his courage, and today he can be justly proud that he is still running a successful business. In addition, the Greeks have not as yet begun to lose their hold upon their national ideologies; they continue--despite the ever-increasing pressure of their environment--to remain ideologically the same Greeks they have been throughout the ages. And this is not all. The benefits Greece has derived from her emigrated sons proved to be her savior at various times. The hundreds of thousands of dollars the Greeks in America sent home proved to be the greatest cure for the many ills of the country.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1678.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Now that the Greeks in America have settled, made homes, and are rearing families, the number of letters from Greece asking for money will naturally be decreased. However, there are other ways in which we can still help our patriots back home. If the power of all the Greeks in America is properly organized it can be a most influential factor in benefiting Greek commerce. For many years, all the imported Greek products were destined for the ultimate consumption of Greeks. Many other products which were bought primarily by our race, are being imported from Spain or Italy. This is due in part to the small amount of products exported by Greece. However, the main reason is the fact that Greek exports do not have the quality, dependability, and attractive packaging that the products from other nations have. An example of this is the superiority of the Spanish olive oil over the Greek oil which is sent to America.</p>
   <p>Today, a new opportunity has opened the doors to success for both Greeks and American-Greeks. Now, Greek businessmen will be able to purchase and sell <pb facs="5422062_5_1679.jpg" n="4"/>imported Greek liquors, especially the famous Greek cognac. If the thousands of Greeks who sell liquors will "push" the Greek brandies, wines, and whiskies, they will succeed in making them well known to the American people; and thus a demand for these Greek liquors will be created. Such a demand would greatly benefit Greek industry; and to be instrumental in bringing about such a demand would be a highly patriotic deed. The Greeks have a chance of a lifetime to help their fatherland and make money themselves. Of course, the quality of the Greek exports will have to be improved if they are to compete successfully with other exported commodities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
