<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-10-11">Oct. 11, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">We Have Two Countries</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-10-11">Oct. 11, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">WE HAVE TWO COUNTRIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We, Greeks of America, must finally realize that we are bound not to one, but to two countries. Most of us came here for the purpose of acquiring a large fortune with which to return to our beloved Greece. As a result of this, America has become the object of a secret grudge or resentment on our part. Some of us who came here intending to stay but a short while, have a feeling of antipathy toward the nation which gave us our opportunity and material wealth. We believe that if America did give us many luxuries and material possessions that she simultaneously robbed us of the joy of living. Some of us can hardly believe that we have ever lived any other way than we do in America. Childhood in Greece seems to be only a beautiful phantasmagoric creation. No, we have not lived our lives; we have only labored through life. And now, after many years of ceaseless labor, we ask that America give back to us our stolen years.</p>
   <p>This great land is unmoved by the fate of her victims, and allows them to <pb facs="5422062_5_1418.jpg" n="2"/>do whatever they please. The complainants finally decide to cast from their feet the dust of America, and to return to their sacred fatherland. They do not desire to live in a land where people do not know the art of living. They desire to enjoy the natural beauty and Attic skies of Greece. And, above all, they do not want their children to be reared in America where they will be assimilated in the great "melting pot" of Americanism--a pot which will destroy every trace of Greek ideology, religion, language, and respect for Greece in their children. The family tree must not be so wrecked with storm that any wind can break and scatter in all directions its branches. Therefore, such people, sooner or later, if their finances permit, return for permanent residence in Greece.</p>
   <p>One would then expect these persons to be extremely happy and contented. The opposite is true. It seems that many months do not elapse before their hearts are filled with nostalgic thoughts of America, which was more hated than loved, and which, they believed, they would never care to see again. America then becomes a second fatherland for them. She is sought, <pb facs="5422062_5_1419.jpg" n="3"/>missed and prayed for by people who blessed the day they left her shores. Many are heard to say they would give a fortune to see America once again. "Now that we have returned to Greece, we realize how well off we were in America," said a sad-faced man.</p>
   <p>Anyone who leaves, even for a short time, discovers that America is like a mother who, though left behind, is never forgotten. She is remembered, not only for her bounty and opportunity, but because in her, the immigrant has a chance to find himself; in her every individual has freedom of thought and action; in her whose bounty transforms people into ladies and gentlemen, and gives education and careers to all who eagerly seek them.</p>
   <p>To us, the Greek people, she has been especially kind, because we are a peaceful and hard-working people. In her live our dreams of a happy world; and on her soil is freedom for our ideas and writings. We should love all these things more than the nearly forgotten relationships we still have with Greece. We are free to retain our customs and language, so we cannot <pb facs="5422062_5_1420.jpg" n="4"/>blame this nation if they do not survive. It is up to us, to maintain them in our homes and in our children. Our children would not have one tenth of the opportunities they have if we were in Greece.</p>
   <p>America may, at times, break our hearts and our bodies; but she repays us for our sorrow many times over by giving our children the chance to earn fame and fortune. Love Greece as a beautiful memory giving a cultural background to our lives; but adore America, for she lets us live in freedom and peace. She is active in her welfare and serves us continually. If anyone doubts, let him take a trip.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
