<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1929-01-04">Jan. 4, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Regulation of the New Calendar</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1929-01-04">Jan. 4, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE REGULATION OF THE NEW CALENDAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question that has arisen with the adoption of the New Calendar and the division of Orthodox Christians into New Calendar and Old Calendar camps is to be regulated definitely and once for all in a manner satisfactory to the Old Calendarites.</p>
   <p>The Old Calendar followers, we mean those who are acting in good faith, have presented as their sole objection the point that a question of such importance ought to have been regulated by a common decision of all Orthodox churches and not by that of the Patriarchate of Constantinople only, which has been endorsed by the majority of the churches but not by all.</p>
   <p>The contention of the Old Calendar followers has been proved to be justified, and therefore it has been considered necessary to call a Pan-Orthodox Convention which is to decide by a common resolution the matter of calendar regulation because with the decision of the Ecumenical <pb facs="5422062_5_0444.jpg" n="2"/>Patriarchate there are some matters in connection that have not been regulated, among which is the Easter Sunday celebration date. That, with the adoption of the New Calendar, continues to be celebrated in accordance with the Old Calendar.</p>
   <p>...... This contention of the Old Calendarites has been proved to be true in part because time has shown that Easter Sunday ought to be celebrated according to the New Calendar, and to accomplish this a Synod will be necessary, since the celebration was established by a Synodic resolution, and by another such it must be regulated now.</p>
   <p>In any case this specific decision is to be taken by the Pan-Orthodox Convention to be convoked, in which all Orthodox churches will participate, and it will thus partake of the nature of a Synod. It is not easy to have an Ecumenical Synod with the situation in which the Ecumenical Patriarchate at present finds itself, and it is not to the interest of the Greek Church either.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
