<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1927-08-27">August 27, 1927</date><title level="a">The Power of the Tongue, by the Most Rev. Gregory Mylonsdaki</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0537</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0537.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1927-08-27">August 27, 1927</date><title level="a">The Power of the Tongue, By the Most Rev. Gregory Mylonsdaki</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The tongue is the organ of the "Logos" (the word). The divine John tells us, "In the beginning was the word, etc." The power of the tongue is a divine gift to the human race. Apostle Jacob says, "The tongue is the bridle, the rein, through which we tame everything, the fire which is able to start a conflegration. The living word is spoken only through the mouth of the Prophets and Apostles. The power of the tongue does not depend entirely upon eloquence which eloquence is a gift of God to few of us, but upon the power of the speaker to express his thoughts, emotions, etc., a single word of sympathy and love will suffice to stem the approach of a cataclysm. It is not necessary for us to use high and scientific words in order to effect our purpose. One word followed with tears and revealing the emotions of the speaker, will be more beneficial than a whole book written by an author."</p>
   <p>When the husband comes home fatigued from his daily labors, where he might have had jeers and humiliation, a single tender word from the mouth of his wife will suffice to make him cheerful, happy, etc. The same is true with the husband towards his wife.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0538.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A great writer once said, a well chosen word has often sufficed to check a running army, change defeat to victory, and save an Empire. Therefore, my dear children, the power of the tongue plays a great role in our lives, not only in great and specific occasions, but also in every day life, private or public. A tender and sympathetic word towards everyone, will help to change the whole structure of our present civilization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
