<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1916-01-22">Jan. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A Discovery</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Reader Solves a Puzzle</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1514</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1514.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-01-22">Jan. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">A DISCOVERY</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Reader Solves a Puzzle</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today, by chance, I discovered the solution to a question that has puzzled many people for a long time. The alarming influx of Greek immigrants has stumped journalists, sociologists, and statisticians. And I, a simple individual, came upon the answer--quite accidentally, I must confess.</p>
   <p>Yesterday I was making out bills, to be sent to my subscribers. While I was dating them, I had a hard time remembering that I should write January 13, 1916; I kept writing January, 1915. This in itself is not unusual, because it has happened to many of us at one time or another.</p>
   <p>I went out for a walk meditating on the fact that thirteen days of the New Year had already gone.</p>
   <p>The next morning I received a letter from Greece, and it was dated December 14, 1915. Immediately, I understood the reason for the heavy immigration.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1515.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The letter I received, dated December 14[Greek calendar], took seventeen days to reach Chicago, and reached me on January 13[American calendar or on December 31, Greek calendar]; or thirteen days earlier according to the Greek calendar, the difference between the two calendars being thirteen days.</p>
   <p>I realized that if I sent a letter to Greece, dated January 13[American calendar], it would reach Greece 17 days later, but due to the 13 days difference in our calendars it would arrive in Greece on January 17[according to the Greek calendar].</p>
   <p>The person receiving the letter would see the dates and would think that it took only four days for the letter to come from America. Therefore, many Greek people think that America is very close to Greece and they set out in boat loads for a jaunt to America. When they get here they realize how far they have traveled from their homeland.</p>
   <p>And all of this miscalculation is caused by a slight difference in the calendars.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1516.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Here is the simple explanation for a question that has long bothered all of us.</p>
   <p>If you believe my discovery to be a significant one, I gladly present it to you for a New Years's gift.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
