<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-10-17">Oct. 17, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Political Struggle in Greece</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1620</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1620.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-10-17">Oct. 17, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL STRUGGLE IN GREECE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Now, more than ever before, the Hellenism of America steadfastly maintains a lively interest in the affairs and events of the motherland, when matters are going from bad to worse. The sudden upheaval in Greece very justifiably disturbs every Greek in America because the change does not better the situation in Greece, but points to events of catastrophic nature. Anxiety is increased by new reports received from Greece, reports which military censorships have allowed to go through. Indications are that the concept of the "state" as the world conceived it during the last century has acquired a new interpretation during the last ten years.</p>
   <p>In our own analysis of the Greek situation, we have not overlooked, certain significant facts which have led to the present critical period. In practically <pb facs="5422062_5_1621.jpg" n="2"/>every nation of the world, a death struggle is taking place between two opposing trends of social and political thought. One of these trends is based upon the subservience of the individual to the state.....The other allows the individual to live in freedom, in harmony with his fellow men, and to be served by the State.</p>
   <p>The aspects of this continuous struggle change according to the type of arena in which it is fought. In Europe the struggle assumes the characteristics of the foremost leaders of each faction. Many European nations are trying to keep in the middle of the road. In others it has assumed extremes in the form of dictatorships or semidictatorships--forms of government very popular since the war.</p>
   <p>In our own country such a struggle has been going on during the last twenty-five years. All through this time the two opposing policies have assumed many guises. Always the struggle has been based upon the relationship between the <pb facs="5422062_5_1622.jpg" n="3"/>state and the individual.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
