<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1916-07-15">July 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Parishes of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0841</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0841.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-07-15">July 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK PARISHES OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the past year the Saloniki has printed article after article urging the Greek church parishes of Chicago to unite. The benefits of such a procedure have been pointed out to the priests and boards of trustees, time after time. We have placed great emphasis upon this unification because it will be easier for the united parishes to combat the evils that now, so boldly, threaten our religion.</p>
   <p>One of the greatest threats to our Orthodox religion is the spread of evangelistic propaganda, that is turning some of our people from their Greek religion. These evangelists are found in all kinds of public centers; in coffee shops, restaurants, cafes, and even in our churches themselves. They sneer at our icons and insult our Madonna. If we want to eliminate these would-be converters from our midst, we must present a united front.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0842.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is true that we have been aided by certain progressive and responsible members of the clergy. Reverend C. Hadzidimitriou wrote many articles denouncing the traitors and advising the Greek people to ignore them and their subversive propaganda.</p>
   <p>Recently we have not published any denunciatory articles; so our friends, the propagandists, have come out from hiding, and are beginning their activities again. Like all deadly microbes, they are hard to kill because they are so good at hiding in dark corners. Curiously enough, they are indirectly aided by the priests and trustees themselves. These officials quarrel among them-selves and go so far as to make insinuating remarks about [each other's] character and morals. Naturally, the evangelists, who seek ammunition to use against the Greek church and its officials, avail themselves of such a fine opportunity to create dissension.</p>
   <p>If these evangelists are to be conquered, the three churches and their respective trustees must unite harmoniously and with dignity, to overcome this evil <pb facs="5422062_5_0843.jpg" n="3"/>influence. No one man or church can do it alone. We must build an impenetrable fortress, composed of the whole Greek population of Chicago.</p>
   <p>As a result of a long series of articles, the churches finally started a fund for the benefit of needy families. During the year, many poor people have been aided by this fund. However, a strange system has been seen to prevail. Certain poor families have received none of the aid they applied for, while other families have made it a habit to ask for help, and have received it, not only from one, but from all three churches.....</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, this is not our only criticism of the manner in which this fund is handled. As yet there has been no rendering of keeping of accounts. No one knows how much money has been collected for this charity fund, and no one has kept an account of who received the money. It is impossible for such a fund to continue to exist if this condition is not remedied immediately.</p>
   <p>We accomplished another good thing by our series of articles. The various <pb facs="5422062_5_0844.jpg" n="4"/>Greek church affairs are no longer held on the same nights. Thank goodness, that awful situation has been eliminated. Imagine three churches giving a dance or a picnic on the same day--not accidentally, but purposely--in order that the affairs of the other churches should fail. The fact that each church was cutting off its nose to spite its face did not stop them. Now the churches co-operate and do not allow their social affairs to conflict. As a result, the affairs have been much more successful and profitable than they were in the past.</p>
   <p>Problems that demand immediate solution still face our Chicago churches. All of them can be solved if the three parishes work as a unit. Scandals and arguments must be eliminated, so that our enemies will not be given ammunition with which to fight us.....</p>
   <p>The Evangelismos Church should found a Greek school, as the other two churches have done. The Greek doctors should start planning a Greek hospital. These things are not hard to accomplish. Leadership and initiative are the most important requirements. We have enough money in the community to accomplish these things.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
