<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-12-11">Dec. 11, 1930</date><title level="a">Aliki Diplarakou</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0289</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0289.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-12-11">Dec. 11, 1930</date><title level="a">ALIKI DIPLARAKOU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- All last week finishing details were attended to for the affair the St. Andrew Women gave on Dec. 8 at the Aragon.</p>
   <p>The greatest sensation was caused when Miss Diplarakou arrived at the La Salle Street Station on Sunday morning. The Ellinopoula (Greek Woman), whose name was known to every person in America, was accompanied by her mother and an American friend. She was greeted by every member of St. Andrews church and by thousands upon thousands of Chicagoans who wanted to get a glimpse of her. She was escorted by automobile to the Stevens Hotel. Her suite was filled to overflowing with bouquet after bouquet of flowers which friends and admirers had sent. After a brief chat with those present she was left alone to rest a little.</p>
   <p>All day Monday telephones were ringing back and forth. Everybody was discussing Miss Diplarakou and the coming dance. Although she was scheduled to appear at 10 P.M. at the Aragon, the ballroom was jammed by 8 P.M.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0290.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It seemed as if every single person in Chicago was present. Everybody had an air of eager expectation on their faces.</p>
   <p>At exactly ten P.M. the Greek and American flags were put on the stage. Everybody tried to get as close as possible to the stage. As Miss Diplarakou walked across the stage, a hush came over the crowd. Then a bombardment of applause and cheers greeted her for three full minutes. The ladies of St. Andrews filed in after her and the Greek and American anthems were played. President P. Rifakis was the first speaker. Mrs. P. Lambros presented her with a huge bouquet. Various other speeches followed while the audience patiently waited to hear "Miss Europe" speak.</p>
   <p>Her words to the 6,000 assembled there were brief but unforgettable. Her voice, her gestures, her words, all portrayed graciousness and breeding. She remained on the stage while the dancing was resumed and chatted with prominent persons who came up to speak to her. In the wee hours of the morning the audience consented to let her go, and everybody went home still talking about the beauty from Greece, Aliki Diplarakou.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
