<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-08-01">Aug. 1, 1931</date>, p. 4
<title level="a">The Creation of Woman.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1687</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1687.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-08-01">Aug. 1, 1931</date>, p. 4
<title level="a">THE CREATION OF WOMAN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As generally is the case, "The Greeks have a word for it" and we find a Greek story of how God created woman as his last creation.</p>
   <p>I can not vouch for the authenticity of the story's origin nevertheless, as the custom is, when you are in doubt, or in ignorance of anything, we paraphrase it as, "It is Greek to me." I will attribute the origin of the story to Greek Mythology.</p>
   <p>God (of course God was Greek) after creating all of the things of the universe, the law of necessity appeared before him and suggested that he should give form to that which we now call woman.</p>
   <p>As all of the elements of creation were exhausted and as all characteristics were bestowed upon the things already created after careful thought God decided to take parts here and characteristics there, from the already created things, to form a woman.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1688.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The story goes that he took the roundness of the moon, the winding of the snake, the tears of the crocodile; the instability and changeability of the wind, the timidity of the hare, the self-conceit of the peacock, the lightness of the wing, the hardness of the diamond, the sweetness of honey, the ferociousness of the tiger, the burning flame of fire, the coldness of the snow, the prating of the magpie, the cooing of the dove, and the cunningness of the fox. He put everything in a trough, mixed them thoroughly and out of this mass he molded the masterpiece of nature; blew life in to the nostrils, named it woman, and gave her to the male, to illumine his mind and soul.</p>
   <p>It is said that the creator made an error in blending all the above characteristics in one creature, and that the world pays very dearly for that error. Of course, as Flamarion says, "Woman is a necessary evil," the creator therefore made no error.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
