<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1908-12-09">Dec. 9, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">[Misuse of Community Funds]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1038</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1038.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1908-12-09">Dec. 9, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">[MISUSE OF COMMUNITY FUNDS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Everywhere one hears of nothing but the organization of the Greek Community of Chicago. We are presenting here the whole problem in a nutshell.</p>
   <p>The constitution of the organization of the Greek Community of Chicago says that at the end of every year reports of the various committeemen are due and elections of new officers for the coming year will be held.</p>
   <p>This law was not carried out at the end of the first year. Nor was it carried out at the end of the second year. Members were silently dropping out without anyone's knowledge.</p>
   <p>Not only that, new members were continually joining, but they were not residents of Chicago. They were continually having dances and benefits to raise more money which went straight to their own pockets.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1039.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A drive was inaugurated and 750 new members joined the organization yielding a total of $1,500. But the officers forgot that the people were getting "fed up" with giving and not receiving. These people found that $129 was listed as the price for coal for 8 weeks, while only $7.30 was paid out. $600 were listed as expenses for a dance while only $300 was paid out.</p>
   <p>The members became suspicious. "How could there be a $129 coal bill for two months for a church? This isn't Marshall Fields."</p>
   <p>The officers' answer to this was, "Sit down, you are out of order." Thus they calmly take care of troublesome members and just as calmly they feathered their own nests.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1040.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They thought that the Chicago population was sound asleep and only they knew what was going on. They should be ashamed of themselves. But are they capable of shame? We doubt it.</p>
   <p>This year, though, they aren't going to have their cake and eat it, too. For years they have been asking for money and people have been giving more than they could afford--"for the church". A stop has been put to this.</p>
   <p>Thirteen honest members of the organization are sending a letter to the Governor of Illinois, making known to him the facts in the case. In this way they won't need the unnecessary expense of a lawyer, trial, etc. With only six dollars these 13 patriotic men will see that certain undesirables be excluded from our Greek Community and put where they belong--behind bars. Thus we will be able to progress rapidly and efficiently.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
