<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-11-03">Nov. 3, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Community of Chicago against the Oligarchy of New York</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0181</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0181.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-11-03">Nov. 3, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK COMMUNITY OF CHICAGO AGAINST THE OLIGARCHY OF NEW YORK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are only two weeks away from the opening of the congress of the communities, and the daily press (Greek) of New York keeps silent upon the subjects that are to be discussed in it, as if they were questions of no interest at all to the Greek population of America.</p>
   <p>Only the day before yesterday Atlantis touched upon the question, confessing that it was a matter of significance and emphasizing the necessity of representation for the communities, in order to terminate its article with a recommendation to the communities to appoint their representatives among residents of New York.</p>
   <p>In other words, the congress is to consist of Greeks of New York. The famous plans laid down by the wise New Yorkers will be voted upon by them and accordingly those in New York will direct the Hellenism of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0182.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Chicago Greek Daily has revealed these intentions of the New Yorkers and has characterized the newspapers' silence as the silence of guilt. Now, from what Atlantis publishes in its issue of Nov. 1st, our forebodings are completely realized, and we have the revelation of how the gentleman of New York have staged the congress, and how by their method of representation through residents of New York they have planned essentially to exclude other communities.</p>
   <p>And there is no doubt that the communities swallowed the bait. Chicago would have been caught in the net if it had not been for the Greek Daily, which hastened to reveal their wily schemes and to emphasize the necessity of each community's sending its own representative so as to have all represented and to present a united front against the meditated attempts of the New York combination, which thought to dominate the whole Greek population of America by such means.</p>
   <p>We wish to assure the New Yorkers that in times like these, in which the spirit of democracy prevails from one end of the world to the other, not only Chicago but the whole Greek population of America is against the <pb facs="5422062_5_0183.jpg" n="3"/>adoption of the oligarchic system which the New Yorkers thought of establishing with the famous "Mixed Council," and it is high time for them to realize that the Archdiocese of North and South America belongs to all Hellenism and not only to the oligarchy of New York.</p>
   <p>Fortunately the Greek community of Chicago perceived the snare in time and unanimously condemned the method of forming the "Mixed Council". Those in New York took care to have it elected only by residents of New York; Greeks of other communities would have had no right to office. We have not the slightest doubt that the opinion of Chicago will prevail in the congress, no matter how much the New Yorkers, by their method of representation, have tried to pilfer the votes of the communities which they supposedly would represent.</p>
   <p>We are pleased to say that we have been informed that all our communities have decided to send representatives to the congress, and that even those which had previously decided to authorize representatives in New York have revoked the authorization, and thus all Chicago communities will be represented.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0184.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Thus far representatives have been elected by the communities of St. Andrew, St. Nicholas, Holy Trinity, St. George, Assumption, and St. Constantine. Next Sunday the communities of Annunciation of the Virgin Mary and St. James will follow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
