<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-10-06">Oct. 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Taking Advantage of the Patriarchate</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0532</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0532.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-10-06">Oct. 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">TAKING ADVANTAGE OF THE PATRIARCHATE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1.--Moved by the arrival in our community of a representative of the Ecumenical Patriarch, namely Archimandrite Thadamou Lekkas, who has been sent by the Patriarch to request financial assistance of the Greeks of America for the manifold needs of the Mother Church, we should like to ask a reasonable question of the Reverend Father Philaretos: How is it that the Patriarch, instead of asking him to secure this financial aid through the medium of the American Archdiocese, which is supposed to represent the Patriarchate, assigned this task to Archimandrite Lekkas?</p>
   <p>For us, assuredly, the answer to this question is clear beyond the shadow of a doubt. We know well enough that the Archdiocese of North America and its bishops have no connection whatever with the Patriarchate and constitute an independent organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0533.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This question, however, is always present in the minds of those who believe their bishops' assertions that they are an extension of the Patriarchate, and to these believers it is Bishop Philaretos's duty to give an answer.</p>
   <p>We are well aware that the founders of this independent ecclesiastical organization are in the most unscrupulous manner making use of the name of the Patriarchate in order to avail themselves of its authority and prestige. However, as soon as the Patriarchate finds itself forced to request aid from the Hellenism of America, the leaders of this independent church organization turn deaf ears to its entreaties.</p>
   <p>Again we have the right to ask these holy fathers: What attitude are you going to take toward the Patriarch's representative? For the legate received his appointment nearly six months ago and is thus coming to America after the lapse of more than adequate time for them to have learned of his impending arrival.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0534.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Yet the Archdiocese of North America, though it maintains that it is an extension of the Patriarchate, has not said a word to the Greeks of America about his coming. This, of course, gives rise to doubts. Perhaps the Patriarch failed to inform the Archdiocese that he had appointed a representative, or perhaps the Patriarchate is not aware that it has an Archdiocese in America. However, if the Archdiocese has been informed, then it apparently has turned a deaf ear to the prayer of the Patriarchate and has kept its action secret, thus interposing obstacles to the dispute of the representative and obstructing the execution of the commission intrusted to him by the Patriarch.</p>
   <p>To-day the representative of the Patriarchate is present in Chicago, and according to what we have learned he is busily securing contributions for the Patriarchate. That is to say, the legate is in the territory governed by Bishop Philaretos, who maintains that he is a bishop under the jurisdiction of the Patriarch of Constantinople.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0535.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Accordingly, if Bishop Philaretos is really a bishop connected with the Patriarchate, it would be profitable for him to clarify his position with reference to the Patriarchate's representative and to inform Orthodox Christians whether Archimandrite Lekkas is really the Patriarch's representative. Does the legate have authority to collect funds for the Patriarchate?</p>
   <p>The Patriarchate informed the Archdiocese of the appointment of Father Lekkas as its representative. Perhaps Father Lekkas is taking advantage of the name of the Patriarchate and is acting without its consent. Bishop Philaretos must understand that it is his duty to inform the Hellenism of America what his position is with reference to the Patriarch's representative, for Archimandrite Lekkas might be profiteering in the name of the Patriarchate, and Bishop Philaretos by remaining silent would connive at this profiteering.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0536.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Hellenism of America is justified in its desire to know who the people are who are taking advantage of the Patriarchate.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
