<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1909-08-07">Aug. 7, 1909</date><title level="a">Greek Community</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0972</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0972.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1909-08-07">Aug. 7, 1909</date><title level="a">GREEK COMMUNITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new angle has recently been introduced into our community problem. We are referring, of course, to the changing of our constitution. Last year a meeting of 250 members was called to discuss this question. Nothing came of it. The 40th article of our constitution, which is a law of Chicago and a law of Illinois says the following:</p>
   <p>Article 40 - This constitution cannot be changed or altered for a period of ten years, after which, it may be changed, if 250 members of the community are present and are willing to have it changed. Chicago, Illinois, December 14, 1902.</p>
   <p>According to this article, it is unconstitutional for us to try to change the constitution. If we try now, to revise this constitution or form a <pb facs="5422062_5_0973.jpg" n="2"/>new one, we will find ourselves once more in heated quarrels, endless arguments, etc., just as we have succeeded in finding peace.</p>
   <p>Until December 14, 1912, we will not be able to change one word of the constitution. We suspect that certain members of our community are not satisfied with their positions and want to take more power into their hands. If this is true, we must forestall them.</p>
   <p>We are having enough trouble with our churches right now. Why must new problems be invited?</p>
   <p>Why is there such animosity between the North and the South Side Churches? Recently the South Side gave a picnic and invited all Chicagoans to attend. The North Siders held a secret meeting and resolved that not one of them should go to the South Side picnic. But the South Side was undaunted. The success was so great that the officers decided to give $1,000 of the profits to the North Side Church. This should make all North Siders ashamed to raise their heads in public.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
