<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-11-08">Nov. 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A General Assembly of the West Side</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Parish Members]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0760</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0760.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-11-08">Nov. 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A GENERAL ASSEMBLY OF THE WEST SIDE</title><title level="a" type="sub">[PARISH MEMBERS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At last, the parish members of the West Side church have awakened from their lethargy of indifference, and have started to contemplate buying the new church. Praise God!</p>
   <p>Last Sunday was the day of this general assembly which was called not to discuss the purchase of the new church, as was stated upon the notices, but to talk about the purchase of a Jewish church building, which was discovered by the Psaltist [Chanter], Mr. N. Dokos.</p>
   <p>The president of the board of trustees, Mr. Tsambas, called the meeting to order, and in dictatorial tones requested all the speakers to confine them-selves to the subject. He entirely forgot to acquaint the audience with the decisions that were reached by the board of trustees at their meetings of the last three months.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0761.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Demopoulos was given the floor and he said that a Jewish church, situated on Ashland Boulevard, had been found. After praising the structure very highly, he said that its price was only $70,000, of which $30,000 would have to be paid in cash immediately. The rest of the sum would be paid in yearly installments.</p>
   <p>Mr. K. Yriakopoulos then spoke and asked that a committee be appointed to examine the proposed church and present its findings to a future general meeting. Mr. [George] Sellas arose and expressed his regrets that the president had not seen fit to tell about the church on Ogden Avenue that has been purchased and nearly paid for. He did not see why the parish should be burdened with a $50,000 debt, when the Ogden church was just as good as the Ashland Boulevard church. He continued and said, "We owe $25,000 on the old church and $40,000 for enlarging the school. If we add $70,000, we will have the impressive debt of $150,000, which will cost us $10,000 a year for interest and taxes. Who, gentlemen, can guarantee the payment of this money, especially under the jurisdiction of the present board of trustees? We have no <pb facs="5422062_5_0762.jpg" n="3"/>intention of dividing the parish--as has been said by some; to prove this, I say, change the governing system and you will have our full co-operation."</p>
   <p>Mr. Sellas was enthusiastically applauded, and he introduced Mr. Nick Lambropoulos. Mr. Lambropoulos asked the president to have the serious matters which the board had voted upon opened for discussion. These matters concern the Reverend L. Pygeas, the cemetery, and the schoolrooms of the Greek school. The president asked that Mr. Lambropoulos' words should be stricken from the records. Mr. Lambropoulos insisted upon knowing whether or not the vote of the board means anything, because if it does not mean anything, what would be the use of its voting upon any other subject, since the voting results are entirely ignored? These words resulted in great disturbance among the audience. He sat down, but arose again and said in nervous haste, "Mr. President, the individuals who purchased the church on Ogden Avenue, are neither Hindus nor barbarians; they are the select members of this parish. They are members who have always worked for the betterment of this church; and who, perhaps, helped you to win the president's chair, which you now occupy. You <pb facs="5422062_5_0763.jpg" n="4"/>should have brought the matter of the church on Ogden Avenue to the attention of this general assembly, which by right is the only body having the right to settle such an important question.</p>
   <p>"But you did not do so, because your actions are motivated by selfishness and stubbornness, and not by a desire for the general welfare and benefit.</p>
   <p>"I wish to state that no matter which church is finally purchased, the twelve men who have bought the church on Ogden Avenue will have the everlasting gratitude of the community, because they have forced you to at least talk of buying a new church--a matter which would have never occurred to you."</p>
   <p>Mr. Psimoulis arose and said that it is impossible to buy the church because funds are necessary, and so far no one had shown a disposition to provide them. "Clapping," said he, "is very nice, but is does not buy churches." Mr. [P.D.] Agriostathis recommended that a committee examine both churches and then <pb facs="5422062_5_0764.jpg" n="5"/>select the better of the two.</p>
   <p>Seeing the lack of appreciation shown toward the efforts to do something for the community, Mr. Sellas arose and left the assembly. Those who remained did not recognize the church owned by Mr. Sellas on Ogden Avenue, and voted for the purchase of the Ashland Avenue church. After a committee was selected, the meeting was adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
