<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-08-09">Aug. 9, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1667</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1667.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-08-09">Aug. 9, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The two opposing political parties in Greece seem to be trying to reach some sort of agreement so that the threatening evils of dictatorship and tyranny may not win as a result of national unrest. The contentions which divide the two parties are purely of a parliamentary nature. There is no dispute over major national issues. Beside this, both of these groups are officially opposed to Socialism and Fascism. This should be enough to prevent any movement toward dictatorship from developing in Greece, as it has done in other European countries.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, however, Greece has a certain percentage of leaders who dream of a day when Greece shall have a totalitarian form of government. Pangalos formed a dictatorship that lasted fourteen months; and the Minister of War, Kondilis, publicly expresses his desire for a dictatorship. The only difference is that he, himself, wants to be the dictator. The threats of Kondilis are, perhaps, the greatest cause of the decrease of hostilities <pb facs="5422062_5_1668.jpg" n="2"/>between the two major political parties of Greece.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Kondilis must, of course, have some friends and supporters; but they are not many, and there is little hope that their number will greatly increase in the future. His influence lies with the army, which respects him for the courage he has demonstrated. Greece, however, is one nation which has never been in the power of the army, except during one or two brief periods. Anyone who believes he can dictatorially rule Greece through the support of the army is displaying great ignorance of Greek psychology, which is opposed to an army-supported government.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
