<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-11-08">November 8, 1930</date><title level="a">The Suspense of the Church Question is Ended.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGO GREEK DAILY</title>,
<date when="1930-11-08">November 8, 1930</date><title level="a">The Suspense of the Church Question is Ended.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1. The news that reached us today about the selection and appointment of the hierarchs departing from America for Greece, puts an end to the suspense of our church question that had kept us from the work of our Church's restoration and the settlement of our various communal differences.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Greek Daily was the only paper that always expressed itself positively about the appointment of the bishops who resigned and took positions in Greece, and never for a moment had a doubt that it was possible for complications to arise in the slowly but normally effected solution of the ecclesiastical question.</p>
   <p>Just because we were absolutely sure that the hierarchs here were to be placed in positions, that the Legate here and the Government of Greece had promised them, we reproached them, because by their refusal to depart from here, they were showing bad faith in the promises of the Legate and the government of Greece. By their stay here they caused the suspense to be prolonged and hindered the Legate's work.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0305.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Happily, however, the latest wire from Greece has verified our predictions, and the bishops are leaving at last fully satisfied that their positions are assigned in Greece. Let us hope that they will bless those that contributed to their leaving America instead of cursing them. And let us hope that they will be placed in positions in the best Metropolises of Greece, and permit us to say that the major part of these blessings we are justified in claiming for ourselves.</p>
   <p>For, if up to this time we kept silent about our activities that were known officially in both Greece and Constantinople, we did so because we thought that the occasion was not opportune, and because we did not desire to create incidents which would place the least obstacle in the work of restoring order in our church affairs in America.</p>
   <p>In due time we shall publish in these columns, extensively, how the pleasant solution of the Church question was brought about, both as a matter of journalistic duty, and because we know that many want to know the details of a job accomplished, and many know and confess the fact as to who was the leading figure that brought to a solution the church problem that for such a long time had been confronting the Greeks of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
