<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1907-03-01">Mar. 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Installation of the Community's Newly Elected Officers - Brilliant Ceremony - the Question of the So-Called Rebel Priest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1907-03-01">Mar. 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">INSTALLATION OF THE COMMUNITY'S NEWLY ELECTED OFFICERS - BRILLIANT CEREMONY - THE QUESTION OF THE SO-CALLED REBEL PRIEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 4 -- In a brilliant ceremony the newly-elected officials of the Chicago Greek community were installed last Sunday. The installation,which was witnessed by 3,500 people, took place in the Masonic Temple. A group of bands, headed by the Chicago Greek Philharmonic Society, made the building and the circumambient air vibrate with the tones of Greek melodies. Black-eyed, raventressed Grecian maidens attired in colorful national costumes scattered to the curious crowds car-loads of flowers and threw tantalizing kisses right and left. The demigods of the Greek community, attired in their snow-white kilts and immaculate woolen stockings with knee-garters, formed a protective phalanx around the Greek nymphs.</p>
   <p>A magnificent celebration by magnificent people in the most magnificent country in the world. Well done!</p>
   <p>After the formalities of the installation and the departure of the two hundred eminent guests who came to admire this Greek ceremony the president of the community, the Honorable Dem. Manousopoulos, mounted the tribunal and <pb facs="5422062_5_1131.jpg" n="2"/>delivered his inaugural speech.</p>
   <p>The newly-ordained president repeated his promise to have nothing undone to restore the community to its former status of unity, peace, and progressiveness.</p>
   <p>For the sake of harmony and to promote unity,Mr. Manousopoulos made no mention of the shortcomings and errors of the last administration but cleverly insinuated that if we are wise, we shall profit by the errors of others and avoid repeating them.</p>
   <p>He also directed some of his remarks to the case of the Reverend C. Georgeadis, the so-called rebel priest who performs his ecclesiastical functions in spite of his rupture with the Holy Synod of Greece.</p>
   <p>Mr. Manousopoulos in his speech urged the good father to comply with the <pb facs="5422062_5_1132.jpg" n="3"/>established rules of the Mother Church and to cease to administer sacraments which are nullified by the Synod as uncanonical. Innocence of any charges preferred against him by a previous administration of the community does not justify his action in dividing the community, said the president. The Society of Chicago Greek Family Men, which was incensed at the recall of Father Georgeadis and established a church of its own on the South Side, where Father Georgeadis officiates uncanonically, would never have offered such an affront to Mother Church if he had refused to act as pastor of that congregation.</p>
   <p>Here again the president of the community cleverly avoided castigating the hot-headed members of the Society, who knew as well as the priest that their action was open rebellion against the Mother Church, and Mr. Manousopoulos has thus opened the way for the departure of the good father, who has been requested to report to the Holy Synod within forty days.</p>
   <p>Editor's note: Undoubtedly the Greek priest is absolutely innocent of all charges preferred against him, but that will not justify him before that <pb facs="5422062_5_1133.jpg" n="4"/>august body, the Holy Synod, until he appears in person, defends himself, and accords due respect to his superiors.</p>
   <p>The ceremony of the installation was something extraordinary, and the desire of the people to terminate all antagonism in the affairs of the community was plainly revealed by the participation in the ceremony of all factions. The newly-installed administration has promised to do wonders for the welfare of the community if and when all factions co-operate. It now has four fifths of the community behind it; let us hope that the promised improvements will materialize.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
