<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>St. Paul's Bote</title> (English-German Monthly Magazine) Vol. 44,
<date when="1938-12">Sept. Dec. 1938</date>.
<title level="a">History of St. Paul's Church 1872-1890.</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0331</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0331.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>St. Paul's Bote</title> (English-German Monthly Magazine) Vol. 44,
<date when="1938-12">Sept. Dec. 1938</date>.
<title level="a">HISTORY OF ST. PAUL'S CHURCH 1872-1890.</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During Easter 1872, the congregation in an extraordinary meeting concluded to rebuild the new church on the old foundation. In January 1886, Pastor Rudolph A. John succeeded Pastor Hartmann.....The new pastor continued his principal preaching services in the language of the fathers and only from time to time arranged for services in the American tongue, which everybody gradually began to understand. Mr. C. A. Weiss, a young talented organist, who resided in Kansas City, Mo., was called to assume charge of the church music.</p>
   <p>From the early beginnings, old St. Paul's laid stress upon associating with forceful preaching an artistically communsurate character of ecclesiastical music......Through the influence of Pastor Hartmann, Professor H. Rahn was called to assume the duties of choir direction and the playing of the organ. He proved to be the right man in the right place, and for many years the people of St. Paul's delighted in the spirit of an ideal companionship, as exemplified by the great spiritual leader and his intelligent and intensely loyal organist....</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0332.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The newly formed combination of Pastor John, the author, and C. A. Weiss, the composer, was productive of a class of church music for thousands of our congregations in this country that could in no other way be termed but by the word "ideal." The choir selections, written by them, first sung in the church in Chicago, were quickly secured through their ready help and sung with enthusiasm in the churches of the farmlands and in those of many of our principal cities. These choir anthems surely filled a long-experienced want.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
