<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-06-08">June 8, 1930</date>, p. 6
<title level="a">Photios, by the Grace of God,Archbishop of Constantinople, New Rome and Ecumenical Patriarch.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0377</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0377.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-06-08">June 8, 1930</date>, p. 6
<title level="a">PHOTIOS, BY THE GRACE OF GOD,ARCHBISHOP OF CONSTANTINOPLE, NEW ROME AND ECUMENICAL PATRIARCH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the respected fellow nationalistic press in America, charity and the peace of God our Lord.</p>
   <p>While stressing the importance of the firmness of our fellow Greeks in America, as a select part of the Patriarchal throne and as a great contributing factor in the affairs of the Church and of the nation, we regret the deplorable division prevailing among them. It has caused much harm to the Church and to the nation for many years.</p>
   <p>We are confident that the disastrous effect of this division and strife has been realized by all. Once more there is now awakened in the hearts of all, great expectations of the revival of the piety and steadfastness that has always distinguished our nationality.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0378.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are encouraged to believe that these changes are now taking place because of your love and devotion to the Mother Church. Because of these hopes we send as our special Patriarchal Legate and Representative the eminent and very beloved Archbishop, the Most Reverend Damaskinos of Corinth. Under his guidance we believe the past conditions will be buried in oblivion, and the former bonds, cementing us together and to the Mother Church, will be restored.</p>
   <p>We ask our press to strengthen this work of reconciliation and unity. In keeping the idea of harmony paramount, the press is performing a great work to the church and to the nation, and will receive the benediction of the church for its great service.</p>
   <p>May the Lord inspire and strengthen all in this work of reconciliation and peace.</p>
   <p>May the grace of God and everlasting mercy be with your Honor in your labors.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0379.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>April 9th 1930</p>
   <p>Photios, of Constaninople, ordained prayer to God for all.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
