<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-07-06">July 6, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Committee Appointed to Examine Records of Papaeliou's Administration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-07-06">July 6, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">COMMITTEE APPOINTED TO EXAMINE RECORDS OF PAPAELIOU'S ADMINISTRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4- At the last meeting of the Chicago Greek community held at Hull House, at which the consul general of Greece presided, a committee of three was appointed and authorized to examine the books of Dr. Papaeliou's late administration.</p>
   <p>The Star, as vigilant guardian of the Greek community, advises the committee to take time to unearth all the ins and outs, the good and the evil of the administration of the retiring president, who for the last three years has involved the community in unnecessary litigation. The people want to know the facts as they are, not as they seem to be.</p>
   <p>Our suggestion is by no means a direct or an indirect attempt to influence the minds of the committee, but it is a direct appeal to those in charge to perform their duty and to meet their obligations to the community fearlessly and impartially. They must render to Caesar that which is Caesar's.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1141.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If the Star's allegations concerning Dr. Papaeliou's conduct are not true, and the honorable doctor has been maliciously dragged in the mire, the public has a right to be so informed by the examining committee, and due credit and honor must be given to him. If on the other hand the allegations are true, it is the imperative duty of the committee not to whitewash the administration in its report, for the Star has authentic documents to prove its charges, and the sword of Damocles will fall upon the committee itself. The report must be full, accurate, and complete. An impartial report is what the public requires. The people in order to support the community must know where its thousands of dollars went and why. The present administration of the community should not cover up any misconduct of its predecessors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
