<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-03-14">Mar. 14, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">[Greek Uprising Short-Lived]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1656</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1656.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-03-14">Mar. 14, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">[GREEK UPRISING SHORT-LIVED]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Short-lived, and if we are to believe the final announcement of the Greek Government in regard to the casualties with insignificant losses in men, the revolt against the Greek government has been suppressed, terminating in a complete surrender of the mutineers. To most people--even to those with a modest knowledge of Greek affairs--this late political upheaval in Greece came as a complete surprise. There were many reasons and a multitude of grievances to justify a mutiny of small proportions. Few, however, could concede that there were causes great enough to warrant a revolt of major proportions.</p>
   <p>Greece was saved from an actual civil war by this victory of the government forces; for had the rebels displayed sterner tenacity, the result would <pb facs="5422062_5_1657.jpg" n="2"/>have been disastrous. A country as poor as Greece could not have stood the strain of prolonged internal strife. Without making any hasty decisions, there is no doubt in our minds that, as the days roll by, a new concept as to the real causes which brought about this ill-fated revolt will be formed. We are happy that it ended as it did, thus averting a great and irreparable catastrophe.</p>
   <p>What the future holds in store cannot be predicted. The immediate result of the victory of the government, although not a blessing in itself, is much more salutary than had the outcome been otherwise. For, after all, we, the Greeks of America, ask nothing more for the country which gave us birth than that peace and good will may reign in the hearts and minds of our brothers in Greece.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
