<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<title level="a">Nea Gemea Tea-Dance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0383</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0383.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<title level="a">NEA GEMEA TEA-DANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>pan.5 Last Sunday the young Ladies of the South Side gave us a very enjoyable day to remember. We think even they did not expect such a crowd at their Mother's Day tea-dance.</p>
   <p>The program was long and varied. It started when G.Kambas' orchestra played the Greek and American Anthems. Miss Mitchell, president of the club gave a brief address in Greek explaining Mothers Day. She then presented little M.Nikoletsea, seven years old, who recited a long poem. The audience demanded two encores before they would let him go. As he took his place at his parents' table, the clapping of the audience was deafening. He was followed by Dr. P. Chronopoulos who is president of the Greek Professional Men's club. Miss Sieppis recited. Young A.Tsoumas song "Gero Dimus" accompanied by Olga Massias on the piano. He encored two American songs and "Xenichtioes". Archrev Tsourounakis said a prayer for "Mother" Mr. Kambas closed the program by again playing a few selections. After tea was served, everybody danced. The young <pb facs="5422062_5_0384.jpg" n="2"/>ladies are to be congratulated on their success. They are Miss Mitchell, president; Miss Petropucus, vice-president; Miss Markoutsas, secretary; Miss Bossinas, treasurer; and Misses Mouzakiotis, Spirrison, Darrellas, Batsakis, Kournetas and Dilmberakis, trustees. Ex-presidents Mitos and Floudas should be included.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
