<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-02-23">Feb. 23, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">We Fight for Parish Unification</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_0094</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0094.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-02-23">Feb. 23, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">WE FIGHT FOR PARISH UNIFICATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ever since the first issue of the Greek Press, its editors have written articles and editorials urging the unification of the Greek churches of Chicago. We have pointed out the many advantages of a central governing body. Such a board would eliminate all the evils that are now undermining our strength.</p>
   <p>This belief of ours is based upon the success of the Greek churches in Egypt and Turkey. We know that with the passing years the need for unity will make itself apparent. Therefore, we again seek for action in this direction on the part of the church governors so that it will become a fact now--when our race is at its zenith.</p>
   <p>The Greek community of Chicago is heartily in agreement with our suggestion.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_0095.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The only exceptions are the priests and the ecclesiastical leaders. This division of opinion is rapidly causing trouble and antagonism in the community. However, our Bishop seems to have suddenly become aware of the dangers confronting us; and some steps have been taken toward our goal.</p>
   <p>We have been informed that the five-member committee has had two conferences with the Bishop; but, as yet, no information has been given to the public concerning the discussions. Resentment is felt because of this unnecessary silence. The public has the right to know exactly what has been said and done at these meetings. It also has a right to know the names of the individuals composing the committee. We know that Mr. Emmanuel Chirigos, who was one of the five originally chosen, did not accept, and that someone else was put in his place. This was done without the consent of any of the churches. We are aware that persons pass on, but situations and problems persist for a long time. It is also known to all that persons influence situations. For this reason, also, it is necessary that we know the persons who are involved in this union of the church and the <pb facs="5422062_5_0096.jpg" n="3"/>community.</p>
   <p>Public opinion clamors for knowledge concerning the plans for centralization. The public knows that such an action is of lasting importance and should be consummated by capable, educated, experienced individuals. Only such a group can form a union which will safequard the interests of both the church and the community. The problem is purely a local one, and can be settled by ourselves without assistance from the church heads. We say this because the problem does not concern the spiritual and religious aspects of our churches; it deals merely with their financial and material problems. Therefore, laymen are more capable of dealing with the situation than are the clergy.</p>
   <p>Regardless of who is at the head of this movement, the cause must be furthered. The public is convinced that such a move is imperative; it demands that its voice be heard in this matter. The community also demands that it be kept informed on any action that is taken, so that it may form an opinion and pass judgment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
