<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-04-27">Apr. 27, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek Community of Chicago Released from its Predicament - New Life and Hope on the Horizon - a Coalition Council under the Greek Consul to Rule the Affairs of the Colony.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_5_1142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-22">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-04-27">Apr. 27, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK COMMUNITY OF CHICAGO RELEASED FROM ITS PREDICAMENT - NEW LIFE AND HOPE ON THE HORIZON - A COALITION COUNCIL UNDER THE GREEK CONSUL TO RULE THE AFFAIRS OF THE COLONY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1 - Better late than never. The dissension, litigation, and back-biting which prevailed in the Greek community of Chicago about the administration of its affairs are things of the past. The Star's clamor for the unification of the colony into one body under proper leadership has at last borne fruit, and with joy and delight we announce the resignation of Dr. Papaeliou as president of the community. At last he has heeded our exhortations to relinquish his judicially-sponsored presidency, thus relieving a difficult situation and promoting the progress of the community.</p>
   <p>The Honorable N. Salopoulos, the Chicago Greek consul general, has undertaken, as we suggested, to govern the turbulent affairs of the community, supported <pb facs="5422062_5_1143.jpg" n="2"/>by a numerous committee representing all factions. This is the first coalition government of the Greek community in Chicago. The members of the council who will be under the scepter of the impartial and very much esteemed Greek consul are:- Messrs. J. Prokos, E. Karavelis, D. Tseronis, D. Giannakopoulos, J. Chamales, H. Vretos, J. Refakis, N. Protopapas, J. Mangas, Gr. Karkazes, Tryphon, Argyropoulos, D. Tsambas, S. Lambardakis, P. Koutsouris, A. Yokaris, John Orphanopoulos, K. Boozos, and K. Stavropoulos.</p>
   <p>The general assembly of the Greek community which was called together for the specific purpose of accepting Dr. Papaeliou's resignation, did not trouble itself with the usual parliamentary procedure of requesting the retiring president to give an account of his administration but simply and quietly accepted his resignation and approved of it, leaving the door open for him to follow his own desires and inclinations. It was wisely done.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_5_1144.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>To give an account of the depleted financial resources of the community could not and would not help matters.</p>
   <p>It is the duty of every member of the community to stand solidly behind the Greek consul and his coalition council in administering the affairs of the community and so to help to build up its strength, prestige, confidence, and financial resources.</p>
   <p>The work ahead of the new leaders is a tremendous undertaking, but it will be done.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
