<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-03-16">Mar. 16, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">To the Friends of the Liberal-Minded Sunday School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0811</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0811.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-03-16">Mar. 16, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE FRIENDS OF THE LIBERAL-MINDED SUNDAY SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A liberal-minded Sunday School was founded for the North side a short time ago at 58 Clybourn Avenue.</p>
   <p>The meeting, which was held last Sunday afternoon, has shown, however, that the parents of the children attending the Sunday school have very little interest in promoting the purposes and aims of the school. What other explanation could be given for the fact that out of about one hundred and fifty parents and twenty members only three attended the meeting.</p>
   <p>It is clear that under such conditions the Sunday school of the North side cannot prosper.</p>
   <p>The main purpose of the Sunday school is to give the children a liberal-minded education.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0812.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All those interested in the progress of such a school should help.</p>
   <p>For this reason, another meeting will be held in the near future, the exact date of which will be made public in due time by the Arbeiter Zeitung.</p>
   <p>A large attendance is absolutely necessary, otherwise the Sunday school will have to be dissolved for lack of interest.</p>
   <p>We hope that this reminder will be sufficient for we think that the value of free-thinking schools is fully realized by the parents and that it is only sheer laziness which prevents them from taking an active part in the meetings. We urge you, therefore, wake up!</p>
   <p>The Editor</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
