<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-04-22">Apr. 22, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">The Staats-Zeitung</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0535</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0535.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1898-04-22">Apr. 22, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">THE STAATS-ZEITUNG</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday the Illinois Staats-Zeitung celebrated its fiftieth birthday with a magnificent edition worthy of the memorable occasion. The Staats-Zeitung has seen Chicago grow from a village of twenty-thousand inhabitants to a metropolis of two million people, and it has been one of the controlling factors in the promotion and direction of this prodigious and unparalleled growth.</p>
   <p>At an early stage in her eventful history, Chicago became the mecca of Germans who flocked here in increasing numbers and who today constitute the largest group of our cosmopolitan population. It was a foregone conclusion that an element so strong in numbers, and possessing all of the essential qualities of good, progressive citizenship, would exercise a decisive influence upon the development of the community at large, provided their efforts were united and well directed. The Staats-Zeitung stood ready to lead, and its leadership was accepted--to the mutual benefit of the Germans, the newspaper itself and, last but not least, to Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0536.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Staats-Zeitung has been most fortunate in its owners and editors, who have all been strong, broad-minded, patriotic and progressive men, ready to further meritorious undertakings and able to assert influence in the politics of the city, the state and the nation.</p>
   <p>Chicago owes much to its German citizens and their great paper; in education and art, no less than in business, finance and politics, their conservative and yet progressive spirit has been a potent force. We may all unite in extending our heartfelt congratulations to this sturdy representative of journalism in Chicago on the occasion of its semi-centennial. The Skandinaven adds its best wishes for the continued success and prosperity of its contemporary, and it also hopes and expects to be among the guests who will celebrate its centennial jubilee. May the Staats-Zeitung live to see this, our city with five million inhabitants!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
