<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-04-18">April 18, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">German in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0714</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0714.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-04-18">April 18, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Germania Men's Choir of Chicago has presented to the Germans in the United States and to the German people in general a brilliant Easter present, namely the first volume of a German literary work, containing epical and lyrical poetry and bears the title: German in America - Contributions to the History of German-American Literature, made its appearance yesterday. The Germania Men's Choir of Chicago is sponsoring this work.</p>
   <p>This volume is printed upon a fine paper in clear, easily readable type, has 264 pages, containing numerous portraits, biographical sketches, and specimen copies from the works of 165 German-American poets. This splendid volume is the result of Dr. A. Zimmerman's efforts. Some years ago he published a similar collection. Now he has enlarged it in cooperation with the committee appointed by the Germania Men's Choir.</p>
   <p>The book also contains a preface by Dr. Zimmerman which presents a summary of German-American literature and is divided into the following periods of time:</p>
   <p>I Religious Period 1673-1825</p>
   <p>II Political Period 1825-1850</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0715.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following is the preface of this work which contains informations not only about the complete set of which this book is the first volume, but also about the magnificent plans which the Germania Men's Choir is striving to carry out:</p>
   <p>Preface</p>
   <p>About a year ago we planned to establish a German-American library which was to include everything written in this country. This idea aroused an immediate and hearty response wherever German-Americans were intellectually wide awake. We went to work and our collection of books contains several hundred volumes already, among them works of rare art from the first edition of the Bible printed by Chr. Saur, until the present time. We have laid the foundation for a comprehensive work, which will not only include everything which has been published until now, but which can be supplemented with new books appearing from time to time in German-American Circles.</p>
   <p>To let the German-Americans share in the treasure which has come to us from German-Americanism, we have obtained from one of our members, Dr. G. A. Zimmerman, the material collected by him over a period of years, and have undertaken the publication of the history of German-American literature. The first two volumes <pb facs="5418474_8_0716.jpg" n="3"/>of the comprehensive work to be published under the title, Germans in America will contain the history of literature. If the first two volumes are readily accepted by the public, than a third volume will be published, illustrative of the achievements of German-Americans in the realm of music and composition; likewise a fourth volume about German arts such as painting, sculpture, and architecture.</p>
   <p>The publication of this volume is not only a German achievement, but it designates also the beginning of a new period in the history of culture. It is the first time that a German-American association, felt the urge to call attention to German-Americanism so emphatically, and to point out so definitely the achievements of Germans in all phases of human endeavor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
