<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-12-07">Dec. 7, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">The Fair at the Vorwaerts Turner Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0870</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0870.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-12-07">Dec. 7, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">THE FAIR AT THE VORWAERTS TURNER HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A bazaar was given yesterday at the Vorwaerts Turner Hall for the benefit of the Sunday school. As may be noted from former reports, the Vorwaerts Turnverein has always--and especially since its "rejuvenation"--shown that it not only desired to improve the physique--by exercises which develop the muscles and make them supple--but also to improve the mind--hence the new Sunday school. The latter is well attended, definite proof of its excellence.</p>
   <p>The school was reopened after the summer months but the Verein soon came to the conclusion that it could not maintain the school unless it resorted to extraordinary measures.</p>
   <p>Thus the wives, daughters, and friends of the members resolved to open a bazaar--a stupendous affair--to further the cause. If the fact that the <pb facs="5418474_8_0871.jpg" n="2"/>weather was unfavorable is taken into consideration, the affair had an exceedingly auspicious beginning.</p>
   <p>While the Turners [the male members] saw to it that the hall was suitably decorated and that other necessary preparations were made, stands erected, etc., the women members made it their business to gather objects of all descriptions to provide for the material aspect of the festival. How well they succeeded became apparent yesterday.</p>
   <p>Rows upon rows of stands showed a wide assortment of articles. Toys, household items, clothing, and what not, were available in abundance and little coaxing was needed by the salesladies to induce liberal buying.</p>
   <p>To give a more detailed account of the hall and its interior arrangement--which was very artistic, by the way--we shall insert, at this point, a description of the stands and the names of the ladies in charge: Finery and dolls, Mrs. Belohradsky; dry goods, Mrs. Brauer and Mrs. Pooth; music and books, Miss L. Schuettler; sweets and bakery goods, Miss M. Fricke and <pb facs="5418474_8_0872.jpg" n="3"/>Miss L. Knuehl; cigar stand....; wines.....; toy stand....; flowers....; church articles....; game [i. e., wild fowl, etc.]....; drugstore items....; post office....; ladies' police....; songbirds....; fishpond....[Translator's note: The dots indicate the omission of names of persons.]</p>
   <p>The following ladies constituted the hall committee: Mrs. B. Kretlow....[Altogether twenty-four names].</p>
   <p>After the school children had sung....under the leadership of Mr. Schoessling, Mr. H. Stahl introduced Mr. Lackner, president of the North American Turnerbund, who gave the opening address. He said:</p>
   <p>"My Friends! Undoubtedly the most important and most worthy task of mankind is the development of the children who are entrusted to our care, that they may become accomplished members of society. This object is realized by the inculcation of strict morality and the instilling of culture. Anyone who has performed that task deserves greater gratitude from the state than the greatest diplomat, although the teacher may not be remembered with monuments, and his name may not <pb facs="5418474_8_0873.jpg" n="4"/>be reverenced by future generations. The future of a state depends upon the proper education of its youth. If the ground is not adequately prepared to receive the seed and develop the fruit, neither culture nor progress is possible.</p>
   <p>"If it is necessary that certain subjects be taught, it is, on the other hand, equally essential that certain things remain untaught.</p>
   <p>"A person, for instance, who has been brought up to show deference to a hereditary king, or who has absorbed the spirit of submission from his mother's breast, will have more difficulty in comprehending the principles of equality and independence than a person who has been nurtured in mental as well as physical liberty. After all, it is not important how much the child learns, but it is imperative that he become conversant with the right subjects.</p>
   <p>"If a child's education is given a good foundation, if the beautiful, the <pb facs="5418474_8_0874.jpg" n="5"/>precious, and the useful are made available, then, as the child develops, it will have a different outlook than a person who has been stuffed with learning, prejudice, and false ideas.</p>
   <p>"For the furtherance and realization of these ideals the Turnverein Vorwaerts founded the Sunday school, and now seeks the support of the residents of the Southwest Side; in fact, it appeals to the inhabitants of the entire city.</p>
   <p>"Women have worked hard to decorate the hall, and are now beckoning visitors to buy. The fair sex has always beautified the world and lent enchantment to fleeting time.</p>
   <p>"Therefore, in this instance we might ignore our praiseworthy habit of frugality and spend wholeheartedly, since a beneficial purpose is involved!"</p>
   <p>After Mr. Lockner concluded his speech, gymnastic exercise were performed in a very capable manner under the leadership of Mr. Gloy.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0875.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The pupils of the Sunday school gave an astounding demonstration of their command of arithmetic, and their instructor deserves full recognition for this great feat.</p>
   <p>The Fair surely had a good beginning and undoubtedly will be even more successful as the week progresses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
