<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-11">Dec. 11, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the First German Sport Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1169</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1169.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-11">Dec. 11, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING OF THE FIRST GERMAN SPORT CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Friday, at the Logan Garden clubhouse, the general assembly of the first German Sport Club of Chicago was held. The interest of the members in the proceedings was quite keen. The administration was in the hands of the first chairman Richard Jaitner, who gave a resume of the year that has just passed. He gave special thanks to the members for their co-operation, and for the trust put in him.</p>
   <p>The annual reports of the individual men in charge of various groups were not favorable. The man in charge of football, Leo Eignen, gave a detailed report of the activities of his men. It was received with applause. Foreman Mueller reported the activities of the heavyweights who, from lack of sports tournaments, had not won the expected number of prizes. The lightweights, according to the report of Foreman Richard Teutsch, acquitted themselves quite bravely. The junior department managed to get a few first, second, and third prizes at the <pb facs="5418474_8_1170.jpg" n="2"/>sport fest of the Schutzbund. Rudolph Schaper, leader of the handball department, reported that, owing to a slackening of interest in handball his branch had resorted to fistball games, in which it managed to get good results. The ladies's department, under the leadership of Frau Sophie Eisenberg, made splendid progress, and was able to render valuable service to the club, not only in the realm of sports, but socially and financially as well.</p>
   <p>Great interest was given to the annual report of the treasurer, Ernst Mueller. His report showed financial improvement over last year. The chairman thanked Ernst Mueller, in behalf of the members, for his activities and sacrifices. After such a successful year, it seemed natural that no changes would be proposed concerning officers for the coming year. All qualified officers, with some few exceptions, were re-elected. Under the leadership of the chairman of the election committee, Herman Eisenberg, with Joe Haas and Hans Mundt acting as co-chairman, the following officers were elected:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1171.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>First chairman, Richard Jaitner, 2904 North Damon Avenue, Telephone Wellington 9450; second chairman, Heinz Irge; secretary and keeper of records, Franz Lotz, 2433 Crawford Avenue; treasurer, Ernst Mueller; heavyweight foreman, Georg Mueller; football foreman, Henry Joswig, 1905 Wolfram. Street; manager of second team, Gustav Bonk; handball and fistball, foreman, Rudolph Schaper; lightweight foreman, Richard Teutsch; in charge of publicity, Herman Eisenberg; leader of the ladies' department, Mrs. Sophie Eisenberg; delegates to the Schutzbund: Richard Teutsch, George Pfister; delegate to German Day, Richard Jaitner.</p>
   <p>The meeting which was quite harmonious, agreed unanimously that, by continued cooperation of the members, the first German Sport Club may be justified in its aspirations for a fruitful development.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
