<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-07-22">July 22, 1878</date><title level="a">The First Day of the Seventh District Turn Festival.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1516</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1516.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-07-22">July 22, 1878</date><title level="a">THE FIRST DAY OF THE SEVENTH DISTRICT TURN FESTIVAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday morning the Turners assembled at the North Side Turn Hall, to march together to the festival grounds at Ogden's Grove.</p>
   <p>About 500 Turners participated in the procession, marching with flying banners following the rythm of the Chicago Orchestra which formed the head. It was a splendid sight, these Herculean, fine looking men, marching along orderly and erect.</p>
   <p>About 5 o'clock the first speaker of the Turn community, Mr. Emil Hochster, pointed to the obstacles which the German festivals generally find in deeprooted American prejudice. He told how the Germans took up the fight against this resistance and victoriously carried it through. Yes, the German festivals have come into their own, of which the active participation of Americans is the <pb facs="5418474_8_1517.jpg" n="2"/>best proof. And the Turn festival is a German, - yes a specifically German feast.</p>
   <p>Recounting the history of gymnastics (Turnerei) the speaker explained that already in gray antiquity the classic Greeks maintained and cultivated the noble art of gymnastics. Our local Turnerei is however, a daughter of Germanic culture, and in German history the merits of Turners are engraved with golden letters. Old father Jahn wrote with a brazen pencil in the book of Clio, about the gymnastic deeds during the wars for German liberty. But also the bloody battlefields which laid waste America's plains in the years of 1861-65 are saturated with the blood of German Turners! They were surely not the last ones to sacrifice their blood for the American eagle, or to carry the Star Spangled Banner, under the shadow of which they had been so hospitably received, from victory to victory. And as the Turner helped to break the chains of the slaves so he breaks all chains, especially those which are trying to shackle the spirit. Superstition and ignorance are two enemies, which <pb facs="5418474_8_1518.jpg" n="3"/>the Turnerei will continually combat, as it has done in the past. The Turner desires the consistent and fearless execution of the principles of self-government. The government should not be misused by a handful of politicans to enrich themselves in a despicable way.</p>
   <p>A people's state, a free republic, is the goal of the real Turner, and this goal he will and must reach....The speaker was frequently interrupted by applause, which redoubled at the end.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
