<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-09-06">Sept. 6, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">The Schuetzenfest</title><title level="a" type="sub">First Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0204</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-07">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0204.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-09-06">Sept. 6, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCHUETZENFEST</title><title level="a" type="sub">First Day</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's great Schuetzenfest (Marksmen's Festival) had an auspicious beginning.....The weather was delightful....contrary to....the predictions of....pessimists....The first train brought the riflemen and visitors....Participants numbered many thousands....The riflemen formed a parade in the morning and....welcomed the out-of-town guests.</p>
   <p>As far as we could ascertain, the following gentlemen attended: [A list follows, of visitors from Bloomington, Illinois; Monroe, Illinois; Bellevue, Iowa; Joliet, Illinois; Milwaukee, Wisconsin; Highland, Illinois; and St. Louis, Missouri.]</p>
   <p>Most of the guests arrived at the Milwaukee and Northwestern depot.....About fifty visitors came by train....and were conducted to the hall.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0205.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The parade started on Illinois Street at 9:30 A. M. and marched in the following order: The fifteen target pointers led, followed by six bowling pin boys, all with the insignia of their rank; then the Grand Exposition Band with its leader, Mr. Nitschke; next the cadet corps under Captain Bauhn; then the marksmen from out-of-town and, finally, the Chicago marksmen. The parade consisted of about two hundred men. The route: On Illinois Street to Wells Street, thence on Erie Street to Clark Street; then on Randolph Street to the depot on Clinton and Canal Streets.</p>
   <p>The festival train reached the Park at about 11 A. M., and those who arrived later formed in ranks conforming to the previous order and marched through the Park to the Reception Hall.</p>
   <p>The Schuetzenpark (Marksmen's Park) has been considerably improved. The Park has an area of eighty acres. Of these eighty acres, forty are used as a park, ten form the rifle range, and the remainder is cultivated by Hermann <pb facs="5418474_8_0206.jpg" n="3"/>Fink, the caretaker.....[Translator's note: Here follows a description of scenery, paths, flowers, fountains, pumping outfit, well, and building.] Further improvements are contemplated.</p>
   <p>....The parade, marching to the music of the Grand Exposition Band, reached the Park building where A. Boese, the president of the Club greeted them in approximately these words:...."Friends!....A year has passed since we last met....Let us celebrate the festival and remember the proverb of the aged Swiss gentleman:</p>
   <p>'No apprehension, youngsters!</p>
   <p>But shoot while you may</p>
   <p>Our fathers also wasted</p>
   <p>Powder in their day.'"</p>
   <p>The banquet started at noon. It differed from banquets held at similar festivals in that there were no toasts....Mr. Fink, or rather, his culinary staff, <pb facs="5418474_8_0207.jpg" n="4"/>deserve the greatest praise.</p>
   <p>After the banquet, shooting and bowling were in order, and about 150 marksmen participated in the shooting competition. In general not much can be said, as the results will not be made known until the end of the festival.</p>
   <p>We shall therefore speak....about the prizes.</p>
   <p>The Honor target: 47 prizes; the first, $50 in cash; second, $40, etc.</p>
   <p>The next target: Highest prize, $35.</p>
   <p>The King's target: Only the king's marksman can win the first prize; he must have the highest score for a hundred shots. The prize is $40 in cash and a gold token of honor, worth $20. (The cost of the latter has been defrayed by Bartholomae and Leicht, brewers.) Other prizes:...</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0208.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The prizes for bowling amount in all to $250. The first prize is $75 in cash....</p>
   <p>The cadet marksmen had a special tournament. Adolph Guntrum received the first prize and became cadet king.</p>
   <p>A bugle call at 3:30 P. M. brought the assembly to the speakers' platform,....in front of the Park building, where Mr. Busse....introduced A. C. Hesing.</p>
   <p>Speech by A. C. Hesing</p>
   <p>"Marksmen and friends! Permit me to express my hearty thanks to the Schuetzenverein (Marksmen's Club). I appreciate my having been selected as today's speaker. You may rest assured that I am grateful for your confidence in me....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0209.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"I welcome the members of other clubs in the name of the Chicago Schuetzenverein. The festival celebrating the foundation of a Schuetzenverein should....always draw attention to its lofty purpose and its beneficial, far-reaching effect. Particularly the large English-speaking contingent should be familiarized with the festival--in view of the importance of marksmanship and its influence on the American nation in its period of development.</p>
   <p>"The objects of marksmanship are manifold, and only we Germans and the Swiss can fully understand the wide-spread effects which the great....Swiss and German....tournaments have produced.</p>
   <p>"While marksmanship is regarded as a sport and has difficulty in developing in monarchies, it is practiced to the fullest extent here in this free land, where it becomes a civic duty. Marksmanship in America should be recommended, practiced, and encouraged in every conceivable manner.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0210.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"In considering the serious side of the question--the civic duty, whereby every citizen becomes the defender of his home--let us remember that this is not the sole object; our constant chasing after the dollar will become less intense as we find time for recreation. Our American national character--still in the formative stage--would also absorb a liking for popular festivals. The virtue of comradeship, which is almost entirely absent from our indigenous population, would be developed. This pastime would provide an opportunity for that exchange of opinions among citizens which is so essential to a free state. Former differences would be ironed out.</p>
   <p>"As the main attributes of a good marksman are clear sight and strength, the body is developed by this sport.</p>
   <p>"One may say that the Schuetzenverein bears the same relation to the older men that the Turnverein (Turner Society) does to the younger generation. In other words: Whereas the latter is concerned in developing the body <pb facs="5418474_8_0211.jpg" n="8"/>and furthering liberal, progressive attitudes, the former creates a brotherly alliance of free citizens and patriots; we may regard it as the citizen soldiery of the republic.</p>
   <p>"The wonderful influence which the Swiss Schuetzenvereine have exercised in creating concord and good fellowship among the various Swiss communities is too well known to require repetition here.</p>
   <p>"You all know that in the small, exemplary republic of Switzerland, the people regard marksmanship as one of the main pillars assuring unity, freedom, and independence.</p>
   <p>"In as far as these marksmen's tournaments affect the various provinces of Germany, one might mention the recent meeting at Stuttgart, where mutual encouragement and brotherly comradeship....strengthened the bond of friend-ship, and where friendly understanding with our racially related neighbors, the Swiss people, was renewed. That incident may well serve as an example.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0212.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>"The Germans in America succeeded in introducing gymnastics, which proved a great blessing to our youth. The movement[gymnastics]has been started here and has taken root. Eventually it will be a permanent feature.</p>
   <p>"Our German song clubs awakened a feeling for music among our American-born citizens and helped immeasurably in making the people conscious of the proverbial German sociability.</p>
   <p>"But none of these associations are as suitable as marksmanship for introducing German ideas and the German spirit in this our adopted land. The American plays with guns while still in the cradle. In later years it becomes second nature. The average American has the proper qualifications: good sight, sturdy arm, and the necessary iron nerve or quiet cold-blooded-ness--characteristics now considered synonymous with Americanism.</p>
   <p>"What the American can do as a mere sharpshooter was proved in a splendid <pb facs="5418474_8_0213.jpg" n="10"/>manner during last month's tournament in England. But the only object the American has in mind is to hit the bull's-eye, and here the civilizing influence of the German ideals of marksmanship will be needed, so that the American can understand the true significance, the deeper motives, involved.</p>
   <p>"I have no doubt that we are on the threshold of an American joint festival, similar to the German and Swiss affair, which is celebrated to promote good fellowship. This American festival should be a gathering of the Northerners, the Southerners, people born on foreign soil and, in fact, all who call themselves citizens of this republic. At the large tent with the American flag, representing unity,....the people will meet to resume old friendships,....thereby strengthening again the eternal alliance of the separate states.</p>
   <p>"An American Joint Marksmen's Festival according to the German-Swiss pattern! What a sublime thought!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0214.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>"When shall we practice a custom like that of the Swiss, and send one or more delegates from each county of each one of the thirty-eight states of the Union, to appear at such a festival? Can there be any doubt that such a tremendous gathering of the best elements from all parts of the nation would do more for the unification of the North and South than all reconstruction and Ku Klux laws?</p>
   <p>"Such a meeting would form the germ of an adequate defense system for our republic, and even though all of us hope that the necessity will never arise to call such a system into action, nonetheless proper provisions should be made to protect us from possible contingencies.</p>
   <p>"By organizing a cadet corps composed of German-American children, the Chicago Schuetzenverein has shown that it takes full cognizance of this important question. The great strides which this young contingent has made in its marching and in the handling of its toy guns prove that a fertile field has been found, and only little effort will be needed to make our <pb facs="5418474_8_0215.jpg" n="12"/>youth amenable to manly efforts later. Upon youth, according to the ideas implanted in it, depends the future greatness or decadance of the Republic.</p>
   <p>"Impress youth with a taste for beneficial exercises, as the turners do, and you will avoid the problem of finding the youngsters on street corners after working hours, insulting women and old men.</p>
   <p>"And we can truthfully say that, if the youth of all the larger cities throughout the country were enrolled in turner societies or Schuetzenvereine, the rowdy and loafer element--the canker of our American social structure--would be instantly abolished. Affiliating the youths with your Schuetzenvereine is also the surest and quickest method to implant marksmanship and make it acceptable to the people as a national institution. Permit me, before closing, to call attention to one important factor.</p>
   <p>"To realize such lofty goals the German Schuetzenvereine should encourage <pb facs="5418474_8_0216.jpg" n="13"/>native-born Americans to participate in target practice and at the festivals[of the Schuetzenvereine]. In this manner the Americans will become familiarized with the club's activities--both useful and diverting. The clubs should induce the native element to emulate our Chicago Germans.</p>
   <p>"Perhaps I have considered this question too seriously, but it seems very important to me--in so far as our adopted country is concerned. Therefore I could not refrain from giving a brief explanation of the benefits accruing to the republic from a proper development of marksmanship.</p>
   <p>"In closing I wish to be forgiven for not having mentioned the fair sex in connection with today's festival. Who, after all, could think of such a festival without considering the lovely representatives of the species? Women are the main attraction of any German gymnastic, song, or marksmanship festival and like Martin Luther, I must exclaim:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0217.jpg" n="14"/>
   <p>"'Whoever does not love wine, women, and song Will never be a good marksman!'"</p>
   <p>When Mr. Hesing concluded his speech, the president of the festival called for a triple hoch for the speaker.</p>
   <p>Target shooting was continued after this interlude and the first day showed the following results:</p>
   <p>J. B. Hefner of Chicago shot the first twelve flags. Mr. Vickart of Highland Park shot the next twelve flags....</p>
   <p>The Committee on Arrangements....deserves full credit....The festival provided excellent entertainment; music, a good concert, a wheel of chance, etc.</p>
   <p>Marksmen from St. Paul, Minnesota; Dubuque, and other localities are expected....also the members of the local English-American Rifle Club, since the <pb facs="5418474_8_0218.jpg" n="15"/>latter were....invited.</p>
   <p>The second and third days....promise to be a social occasion, since the marksmen generally bring their families then....No one should fail to be present when the prizes are distributed....</p>
   <p>Illinois Staats-Zeitung, Sept. 7, 1875.</p>
   <p>Second Day</p>
   <p>The Schuetzenfest had its second inning yesterday. Although the crowd was smaller than that of the first day, there was nevertheless a large throng at the Schuetzenpark. As previously mentioned, the second day was dedicated to serious work. At eight o'clock in the morning a cannon was fired, indicating commencement of activities. A large number of the marksmen remained at the Schuetzenhalle (Marksmen's Hall) at the Park in order not to be tardy. Real liveliness began to be manifested, however, with the arrival of marksmen on the eleven o'clock train.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0219.jpg" n="16"/>
   <p>Target shooting continued from morning until six o'clock in the evening with the exception of one hour for lunch. The beginning and end of that period were announced by the firing of a mortar.</p>
   <p>Silver medals were awarded to twenty-three marksmen. The silver medals were given to all who could score one dozen hits in the center of the target. J. W. Codon of Bellevue,....and N. M. Plottke, of Chicago, were thus honored. [Translator's note: Here twenty-three names appear. A large Chicago German group won in this division.]</p>
   <p>The medals were not given at the end of the various competitions, but immediately upon being earned. The recipient was led in a triumphal tour, headed by the master marksmen, and amid music was brought before the great marksman and punster, "Natz'1" (Mr. J. B. Hefner) who bestowed the prize while giving a suitable speech.</p>
   <p>The largest number of bull's-eyes were made by the following: D. Wiget of <pb facs="5418474_8_0220.jpg" n="17"/>Highland, 85; M. Grau of Chicago, 69....</p>
   <p>On this target 7800 shots were recorded....Other results: Union target:....George Beuttenmueller of Chicago, 67 ringers....Man's target: Highest numbers: John Pfefer, 78 ringers....all of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Otto Mutschlechner, known as one of the oldest and most ardent members of the Schuetzenverein, said, as the silver medal was given to him amid great acclaim, that he does not consider himself one of the best marksmen any more, but that, nevertheless, he will always work....for the furtherance of marksmanship and the abolition of anything which proves injurious to the sport. In conformance with the aforesaid, as well as at the request of the Schuetzenverein, he [Mr. Otto Mutschlechner] and Messrs. Starke and Hartmann advocated and succeeded in bringing about an alliance of the marksmen of the East and the West.</p>
   <p>After calling attention to the great benefits gained from such a union, <pb facs="5418474_8_0221.jpg" n="18"/>Mr. Mutschlechner expressed the hope that the West will be well represented at the next marksmen's festival at Philadelphia; and asked the assembly to hail the new alliance, whereupon all concurred vociferously.</p>
   <p>The president of the Schuetzenverein, A. Boese, agreed with the proposal and showed why the Schuetzenverein desired to be affiliated with the Eastern alliance. He, too, gave three cheers for the Schuetzenbund der Vereinigten Staaten von Nordamerika (Riflemen's Alliance of the United States). [Translator's note: The original does not explain whether this is the regular name of the Chicago Schuetzenverein, the Eastern alliance previously mentioned, or the proposed name for the Chicago and Eastern alliance.] Later....additional cheers were given by....various members, including the co-founder of the club, Abraham Stuedle.</p>
   <p>There was also considerable activity at the bowling alley. Last evening 1,070 rolls were recorded. Up to the present, John Bortenschlager has succeeded in dislodging the nine pins forty-two times, and William Starke <pb facs="5418474_8_0222.jpg" n="19"/>and Jacob Schmidt are tied--each has scored forty.</p>
   <p>Today marks the end of the festival. Shooting will continue during the morning. Most of the more ambitious riflemen remained at the Park[overnight at the clubhouse]to gain the desired points.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hefner will distribute the prizes after proper calipering of the various shots and computing the ratings.</p>
   <p>Good music, dancing, and concert selections are announced again for today, and in every way ample provisions have been made for good entertainment.</p>
   <p>Illinois Staats-Zeitung, Sept. 8, 1875.</p>
   <p>The End. The Winners</p>
   <p>The Schuetzenfest of 1875 came to an end yesterday. A large crowd came <pb facs="5418474_8_0223.jpg" n="20"/>from Chicago and vicinity, anxious to observe the final results....Trains, buggies, wagons, and other conveyances were....needed to accommodate the throng. Attendance....during the afternoon probably exceeded ...expectations....The festival was successful in every respect, and the weather was favorable throughout the duration of the riflemen's tournament. Interruptions which are usually associated with such affairs were no noticed.....</p>
   <p>Target shooting and bowling started at an early hour with a few intermissions for refreshments. A mortar shot at three o'clock proclaimed the end of the festival. The rifles were laid aside and everyone awaited the announcements....An hour later a bugle sounded, whereupon the assembly gathered before the clubhouse, where the master marksmen, the president, and J. B. Hefner, who attained the title "King of the marksmen," were stationed to distribute the prizes.</p>
   <p>Mr. Boese, the president of the club, stepped forward and spoke approximately <pb facs="5418474_8_0224.jpg" n="21"/>as follows: "My Friends! During these days we have had ample opportunity to talk about marksmanship, and voice our diverse opinions.... and it is hardly possible to make additional comments.</p>
   <p>"The casual observer may think it a simple matter to distribute prizes during such an event. It is not. Every rifleman knows what it means to compete for three days with an able adversary.....and Mr. Hefner did just that. It was not easy for him to win. Mr. Wiget of Highland is an expert marksman. But and unflinching eye, a sturdy arm, and some luck made Mr. Hefner a master marksman. He is the 'King of the Riflemen' and it is my pleasant duty to award him the diploma and the gold medal!"</p>
   <p>The new king was given three resounding cheers, and he expressed his thanks in a few words. He said that he was elated over the victory and that he felt that the entire club shared his sentiments. "Let me say of Mr. Wiget that he is the best marksman in the United States, and in comparison to his I am a mere bungler. It was luck rather than superiority which gave me success."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0225.jpg" n="22"/>
   <p>In closing he again expressed his hearty thanks for the good will shown by his friends and by the fraternity of marksmen in general.</p>
   <p>Then Mr. Hefner awarded the various prizes to his fellow marksmen and added a few words of praise in every instance.</p>
   <p>The results: Union target, first prize: Wiget of Highland and Beuttenmueller of Chicago, fifty dollars in gold and forty dollars paper money; second prize: M. Grau, Chicago, thirty dollars:</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Forty names appear, and three targets are listed.]</p>
   <p>Mr. Plotke obtained three prizes, and when Mr. Hefner awarded them he observed that Mr. Plotke had been a member for only two weeks and that such a victory had not been recorded since the time when the club was founded.</p>
   <p>Other prizes:....[Translator's note: The prizes are not listed in their <pb facs="5418474_8_0226.jpg" n="23"/>entirety and my computation shows that $671 was paid out; adding the amounts which were not published and the $229 paid for bowling prizes and the medals, I find that about one thousand dollars in prizes were distributed.]</p>
   <p>....Altogether, 17,236 shots were fired.</p>
   <p>In the bowling alley 3,705 rolls were recorded. As first prize, W. Starke, who was pronounced king, received a gold medal and seventy-five dollars in cash.....</p>
   <p>At the completion of the distribution of the prizes music emanated from the dance hall. Many found this an added attraction.</p>
   <p>At nine o'clock in the evening it was announced that the train was about to leave.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0227.jpg" n="24"/>
   <p>This was a delightful festival which will linger in the memory of all.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
