<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-01-21">Jan. 21, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Steuben Park.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1586</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1586.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-01-21">Jan. 21, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">STEUBEN PARK.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago citizens of German descent have introduced a motion, the purpose of which is, to honor a man of their race, whose name will always be connected with the history of America. They intend to erect a monument in honor of Baron Friederich von Steuben, the organizer of the revolutionary army of the United States, and valued co-worker of George Washington. A petition, signed by more than 200,000 representatives of the German element of Chicago, was presented to the governor, yesterday. The committee was composed of several hundred persons having at its head Dr. John Dill Robertson. In the petition the governor is requested to give his support to a bill which will be submitted to the state legislature in regard to the creation of a Steuben Park on the Northwest Side of the city boundary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1587.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is the desire of the Chicagoans of German descent to obtain the grounds in Dunning upon which the state institution for the insane is now located. After the removal of the institution, the grounds would be transformed into a park, which would be named Steuben Park.</p>
   <p>Judging from comments, which Governor Small expressed, the prospects are good. It is a wise policy to name parks, streets and places after those men, who distinguished themselves by their services for this country. But only a small number of such heroes of American history have found recognition in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The citizens of German descent, who have contributed to the development of the United States, have been treated unkindly, as a rule. It is natural, then that the German-Americans of Chicago should be anxious to have those unsatisfactory conditions changed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
