<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-03-17">March 17, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Germanistic Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0384</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0384.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-03-17">March 17, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANISTIC SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the place of Dr. Hans Heinz Ewers, Prof. Paul Goode of the University of Illinois, gave a very interesting lecture. Even if the members and friends of the Germanistic Society, assembled in Fullerton Hall, regretted that Dr. Hans Heinz Ewers, who was expected to speak had been prevented from appearing, they enjoyed a lecture which was very instructive, and expressed their thanks to the president. Prof. Paul Goode explained, with the help of lime-light pictures, the development of Europe, up until today's crisis, and the excellent logic which he drew from his development theory did not fail to win the assent of his listeners. The speaker went back to the time of the emigration of nations, and showed, that the geological condition of Europe, favored the foundation of individual states. On one side, the advantageous position of England, protected from the danger of invasion; the colossal circumference of Russia; the confining position of Germany; the different developments of each country were illustrated by lime-light and Prof., Goode's explanatory words gave the listeners a clear picture of conditions, which, naturally, had to lead to the result we are seeing today. Referring to the unity of Germany, under the leadership of Prussia which after 1870 developed in a surpassing manner, into an <pb facs="5418474_8_0385.jpg" n="2"/>industrial state, the lecturer showed in his lime-light pictures, the progress of commerce and export, against imports, not only of Germany but of England, France and Russia, in comparison to the United States. He particularly laid stress upon the way the German government, supported in every conceivable manner the country's commerce; how it represented the interests of all everywhere as a mercantile trust. In conclusion, he mentioned the basis of national wealth and said that coal and iron are the most valuable objects, to promote, in the first place, the industrial and financial progress of a country. Starting with this assertion, he declared that coal and iron were the original causes of the World War.</p>
   <p>In his last lime-light pictures, he named those countries which were richest in both minerals, successively: America, England, Germany, Spain, Belgium, Sweden, and so forth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
