<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1897-11-08">November 8, 1897</date><title level="a">Turnbezirk, Chicago (Turn District) the Discussions at the First Semi-Annual District Mesting.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1318</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1318.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III B I</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1897-11-08">November 8, 1897</date><title level="a">Turnbezirk, Chicago (Turn District) The Discussions at the First Semi-Annual District Mesting.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About one hundred delegates, representing twenty-three clubs of the district, came together, yesterday, in the Hall of the Columbia Turner Club, 62nd and Halsted Sts. Turner August Kiesling welcomed the delegates. Secretary Ahrens of the District, opened the session. As temporary officials there were elected: Turner Greubel (Vorherts) President; Turner L. Folz (Voran), Secretary. From the reports of officials we take the following items:</p>
   <p>The excursion to the League Turner Festival gave the district a profit of $443.72. At the request of districts New York and Pittsburgh, plans of the Natatorium and Athletic Field in Douglas Park, were put at their disposal. The suburb has taken a position against the oppression of the striking miners in Pennsylvania, also is in favor of the introduction of the "Referendum" and the "Initiative" - Turner Otto Koenig of LaSalle has been sent to the Gymnastic Teacher's College in Milwaukee. The Club, Northwest, dissolved during the summer, its fifty-one members of good standing having joined other Clubs. The suburb was in the position, to pay the League Tax of $700. in <pb facs="5418474_8_1319.jpg" n="2"/>in advance. The income of the district was $1,545.00, expresses were $1,091.45 and balance on hand is $523.57. The suburb submits to the section the following recommendation:</p>
   <p>"To order the suburb, once every year, to rent a large theatre and use it for a good program by a selected troupe, and arrange to use it annually for a grand district exhibit with exercises for Decoration Day (Memorial Day). The Committee for examination of delegates reported that twenty-three clubs with one hundred and two delegates are represented. The temporary organization was made a regular one, and completed by the election of Turner Landau (Aurora) as Second Speaker, and Turner Rautenberg (Garfield) as Assistant Secretary. Four Committees were nominated: a Committee for League and District Affairs; a Technical Committee; a Committee for Spiritual Efforts, and a Finance Committee."</p>
   <p>The dispatch of business went on smoothly, and the most important resolutions have, briefly, the following contents:</p>
   <p>"The Mayor shall be made to understand at the next election that the Turners take amiss his disregard of their wishes in his nominations for School Board positions. The suburb shall take active measures for keeping the library open on Sunday. The movement for the installation of "Referendum and Initiative"</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1320.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>shall be supported. The next district festival shall be held in Grand Rapids, and Philadelphia shall be proposed for the League festival in 1000. Congress shall be appealed to for the passing of on injunction against the misuse of Injunction Writs exercised by Federal Courts. The next district session shall be held in the new hall of the West Side Turner Club.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
