<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-06-29">June 29, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Marksmen's Festival</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-07">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-06-29">June 29, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE MARKSMEN'S FESTIVAL</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday marked the end of the Northwestern [Marksmen's] Alliance's prize shooting event; it was one of the most interesting affairs ever given in Chicago, and today the festival comes to a close.</p>
   <p>For today, a special program has been arranged: Crossbow shooting, bird and star targets, sack and foot races, Bengal lights for night illumination, the crowning of the "Rifle King," general distribution of prizes; all of which will undoubtedly draw thousands of people to the park.</p>
   <p>Today two trains will be available, one at ten o'clock in the morning, the other at one o'clock in the afternoon; return trips will be at 6:30 P. M. and 10 P. M.</p>
   <p>The delegate meeting is also scheduled for today--the first thing in the <pb facs="5418474_8_0143.jpg" n="2"/>morning.</p>
   <p>The Scores</p>
   <p>The total scores cannot be published at this time, because the tabulation had not been completed when the evening train left for Chicago.</p>
   <p>We append some data which we obtained from some riflemen who came to Chicago yesterday: The highest score on the King's target was made by William Hayes of the Manhattan Rifle Club, New York. His score was 210, and he will be proclaimed "King of the Riflemen" today. Hermann Blick, of St. Louis, scored 91 on the Man's target, and he will receive the first prize. First prize on the Union target was won by John B. Hefner of this city; he will be given one hundred dollars, donated by the Chicago Schuetzenverein. Second prize (same target) goes to John Fresler, of St. Louis; his score was 64 bull's-eyes. The prize money, $72, was donated by the Missouri Scharfschuetzenverein, of St. Louis.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0144.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Scores on the small target were: W. Hayes, Newark, 182,.....[highest]. D. Wirth, Highland, 40; [lowest]. [Altogether, 14 names].</p>
   <p>The total scores will be posted today.</p>
   <p>Bowling</p>
   <p>Bowling has been popular, and very good scores have been recorded. Today the championship will be decided. We again publish the rules:</p>
   <p>Any player may win two prizes, but not a third one.</p>
   <p>Whoever strikes the most "nines" will be "Bowling King," and will receive a nice gold medal worth $50.</p>
   <p>Whoever hits the most rings (eight pins around the King, without striking the King) will receive a gold medal valued at $25.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0145.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Whoever succeeds in striking the King without toppling any pins, will be given $100 cash.</p>
   <p>The other prizes are:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1st</cell>
     <cell>prize:</cell>
     <cell>$75.</cell>
     <cell>2nd</cell>
     <cell>prize:</cell>
     <cell>$40.</cell>
     <cell>3rd</cell>
     <cell>prize:</cell>
     <cell>$25.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>4th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>15.</cell>
     <cell>5th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>10.</cell>
     <cell>6th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>8.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>7th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>6.</cell>
     <cell>8th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>4.</cell>
     <cell>9th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>3.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>10th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>2.</cell>
     <cell>11th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>2.</cell>
     <cell>12th</cell>
     <cell>"</cell>
     <cell>1.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>13th, 14th, 15th, 16th prizes, one dollar each.</p>
   <p>Registration fee for five throws is fifty cents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
