<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-10-04">October 4th, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The German Section.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I V</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGOER ARBEITER ZEITUNG</title>,
<date when="1881-10-04">October 4th, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The German Section.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The monthly business meeting of the German Section was held last night at 54 West Lake Street at which Herman Ullrich acted as German, Messfs. Fabe, Niemann, Schoening and Sewer were proposed for members, but the definite acceptance of their membership, has been postponed until the next meeting. The report on finances has been read, and submitted to the auditing committee, for an examination. Messrs. August Spies, Oscar Neebe and Henry Bonnefoi, were appointed delegates to the Central Committee.</p>
   <p>The Congress question was the next subject to confer upon, and with a certain purpose in mind, it has been decided, to hold the congress in Chicago, instead as it has been first planned in Cincinnati, for which October 21st, has been chosen,.. As delegates of the Chicago Section to the Congress, Messrs. Jacob Winnen, August Spies, Jim O'Meara and A. R. Parsons were appointed. The out of town Sections, which wont be able to send their own delegates to the Congress, can appoint any of the following named members of the Chicago Section, and who have been approved to act as proxies: August Winiger, H. Dusey, F. A. Stauber, Wm. Jeffers, Osear <pb facs="5418474_8_1137.jpg" n="2"/>Neebe, Wm. Blum, R. Lorenz, H. Stein, P. Peterson and E. Johnson. The sections or groups, which wish to be represented by Proxies, are requested to send their instructions at the earliest possible noment, to the secretary of the Central Committee, August Spies, 87 Fifth Avenue.</p>
   <p>It has been also decided to arrange a festivity or a banquet, for which a committee has been appointed, consisting of Paul Grottkau, Oscar Neebe, and H. Ulrich, who have also been entrusted with the arrangements for the meeting of Congress here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
