<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-12-08">December 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Germany's Colonies Lecture of Professor Ernest Daenells before the Germanistic Society. Germany's Colonial Policies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1042</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1042.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-12-08">December 8, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANY'S COLONIES LECTURE OF PROFESSOR ERNEST DAENELLS BEFORE THE GERMANISTIC SOCIETY. GERMANY'S COLONIAL POLICIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Caprivis' mistakes cost Germany its best colonies. The balance is not fit for colonization and as a market of products.</p>
   <p>The question, whether Germany would be able to settle its surplus population and find a market for its industrial products, was discussed by Professor Ernest Daenell, of the University of Kiel, in a lecture on the German colonial policy, yesterday evening, in Fullerton Hall, Art Institute, upon request of the Germanistic Society. The answer which Professor Daenell gives to this question, is not very encouraging. Except for comparatively small sections in Africa, Germany's colonies are not fit for settlers, on account of climatic conditions. As markets they are useless, at present. Germany therefore, has to strive to find territories to which can be sent to and to dispense of its industrial products, without taking possession of these territories. Germany has to be satisfied with economic expansion.</p>
   <p>For this purpose South America and China lead and in certain respects Turkey <pb facs="5418474_8_1043.jpg" n="2"/>also could receive attention. In South America, Brazil, which in its three Southern provinces contains a population of 400,000 Germans, might be considered. The German Emigration might be directed towards these provinces, which kept in touch with their mother country, would create an excellent market. Of course, politically the Germans in these provinces, are lost to the Fatherland. Therefore the maintaining of economic and moral relations only would receive consideration. China, where in Kiautschan, a foothold has been established, can not be considered at all for German emigration. Only economic conquests may be expected. The import trade is in spite of largely populated adjoining provinces, insignificant. On the other hand, the export trade is capable of development, because the country is very rich in products of the earth- coal and iron-ore.</p>
   <p>Also, in Turkey economic conquests could be considered but not the settlement of German emigrants in large numbers. The construction of the Bagdad Railroad to the Gulf of Persia promises, in the near future a settling and economic promoting of districts, which formerly were the most productive of the earth, AsiaMinor and Mesopotamia.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1044.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In them, with progress through development, markets for German products could be established.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
