<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-09-18">Sept. 18, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Eleventh Anniversary</title><title level="a" type="sub">Friends and Sympathizers of the Organization Paper Eintracht Hold Gay Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0436</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0436.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-09-18">Sept. 18, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">ELEVENTH ANNIVERSARY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Friends and Sympathizers of the Organization Paper Eintracht Hold Gay Celebration</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The friends and sympathizers of the German weekly organization paper Eintracht yesterday celebrated the eleventh anniversary of the publication of the periodical. The celebration took place at the Lincoln Turner Hall, 1005 Diversey Parkway, and consisted of a concert, followed by a dance.</p>
   <p>The concert was opened with a few numbers by the orchestra of E. Dorazil's.</p>
   <p>Following a melophone solo by Josef Kunst, there were songs by the Styrian yodlers, with zither accompaniment. Josef Lenz and Carl Wieser won much applause. Then the Burgenlaender Maennerchor, under the direction of Franz Beidel, entertained with Zank's pleasing composition, "Schatzerl Klein," which was enthusiastically received.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0437.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Other choral numbers which contributed to the enjoyment of the concert, and which were received with great applause, were given by the Alpenlaender Maennerchor, under the direction of Woldemar Christoph; by the South Side Saengerbund, directed by Ewald Barginde; as a brilliant climax, there was singing by a mass chorus, made up of the Styrian Saenger-Bund, the Burgen-laender Ledertafel, and the singing section of the "Hungarians," all under the tested leadership of Director Beidel. In a most accomplished manner they rendered the famous "Blue Danube" waltz, by Strauss.</p>
   <p>The soprano singer, Miss Anne Marie Gerts, sang "Unter dem Lindenbaum" by H. Felix, and "O, habet acht," from Strauss' operetta, "The Gipsy Baron," accompanied on the piano by Hildegard Gotthold. Another soloist was Irma Ferenezy-Komarik, who gave a few Hungarian folk songs. She was accompanied on the piano by Director W. Christoph, and won great applause. Other singers were Mr. W. Blailock, who commands a sonorous baritone, and Mr. Curt Schlegel, who sang a few humorous songs.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0438.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The most important speeches were given by the president of the county council, Emmett Whealan, who spoke in English, and Mr. Peter Schock, president of the United Singers of Detroit, who spoke in German. Both were presented to the guests by the manager of the festival, Mr. Josef Maschek, and each gave a short but fitting account of the significance of the celebration. Michael Schaut, editor of the Heimatbote, and Jury Commissioner Charles Newmann, made short congratulatory speeches. The editor in chief of the Eintracht, Mr. Gabriel Jung, responded with heartfelt words, and gave his sincere thanks to all for the support of the festival.</p>
   <p>The committee, which deserves much credit for the success of the festival (and especially for the fact that no one was allowed to go hungry or thirsty, and that everyone found enjoyment in a jolly dance) was composed of: Joseph Maschek, president of the festival; Fred Augustin, treasurer; Michael Holz, in charge of ticket sales; Henry Meisl, Martin Krispin, Joseph Lorenz, Joseph Aver, John Wrska, Thomas Riedl, Frank B. Bieschke, Anton Langhammer, <pb facs="5418474_8_0439.jpg" n="4"/>Josef Herzog, August Kerschner, Mary Bengesky, Marie Lang, and Minnie Strobl.</p>
   <p>Ludwig Gebert announced the individual numbers of the program.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
