<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-03">Apr. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Name "Goethe Street" to Remain City</title><title level="a" type="sub">Council Refuses to Make a Change</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1591</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1591.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-03">Apr. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE NAME "GOETHE STREET" TO REMAIN City</title><title level="a" type="sub">Council Refuses to Make a Change</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The name of Goethe Street will not be altered. The attempt of some people who live near the street to have it changed to Boxwood Place was frustrated yesterday by the City Council. Alderman John Haderlein of the Twenty-fourth Ward led the fight against the change. He was supported by Alderman B. S. Schwartz. Both members of the Council severely criticized the attempt to change the name. Alderman Haderlein said: "Goethe Street was laid out in 1843 when that part of the city was parcelled. Nobody made any objection to the name at that time. Everybody could pronounce it. Suddenly some persons who live near the street approached the City Council demanding that the name be altered because it is very difficult to pronounce. We know what is in back of the request. The proposal has been before the Committee on Streets and Alleys for weeks. It was not reported for action because and election was imminent. The people who insist on the change should not call it 'Boxwood Place,' but 'Nutwood Place'. That would be a more appropriate designation for them."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1592.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Alderman Haderlein moved that the proposal be shelved. His motion was supported by Alderman Schwartz, who declared: "Any American city can be proud to have one of its streets named after the great German poet. Goethe has nothing to do with the War. The objection that it is difficult to pronounce the name is untenable. It would do some people good if they learned how to pronounce it. The same objection could be raised to the name 'Kosciusko Street,' and also to others. No intelligent person can possibly be offended by the name 'Goethe Street'."</p>
   <p>The motion to table the proposal was unanimously adopted. Aldermen O. L. Watson, Twenty-seventh Ward, and C. J. Walker, Twenty-first Ward, left the session before the vote was taken, but returned afterward.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Subsequent paragraphs are irrelevant.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
