<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-11-01">Nov. 1, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">In Regard to the Goethe Monument, Which Was Been Proposed for Lincoln Park.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1671</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1671.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-11-01">Nov. 1, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">IN REGARD TO THE GOETHE MONUMENT, WHICH WAS BEEN PROPOSED FOR LINCOLN PARK.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It will be remembered that the "Schwaben-Verein intends to dedicate a statue to Goethe, the old master of German literature. It is to be erected in Lincoln Park, opposite his friend and famous compatriot, Schiller. The necessary funds are to be obtained, by appealing to all the Germans of our city and thus far, the Schwaben-Verein has succeeded in raising $1,000.00, from its own resources. Carl Haerting, who is a member of the Schwaben-Verein traveled to his old fatherland last summer. Partially at the instigation of the association members and because of his own initiative he viewed the most known and valuable monuments of the heroic poet, in order to find a suitable model for the Chicago locality. Mr. Haerting came to the definite conclusion, that the statue at the Thiergarten, (Zoological Garden), Berlin, is most preferable. It has always been conceded, that it is the most beautiful and ideal, since it represents the great man in the prime of his life and in a most serene manner. The originator is the famous sculptor Schaper. The result of Mr. Haerting's inquiries, in regard to a reproduction of the magnificent masterpiece for our Chicago district, brought the <pb facs="5418474_8_1672.jpg" n="2"/>following response from the artist. "Berlin, Oct. 14, 1890. Estimates for a reproduction of the Goethe monument which I orizinally made for Berlin. In regard to the above monument, which I executed in marble; the necessary models thereto were made at the time. They are one half as large the finished product. I customarily work in this manner, as it gives me grater latitude when proceeding with the marble cutting. There are, therefore, no full sized models available, only those of one half the dimensions and a copy of the monument could therefore be made. If the statue is to be reproduced in bronze, them full sized model, patterned after the smaller ones will have to be made, so that a form for the cast can be obtained. In this case, however, a few minor changes will be essential because of the inherent peculiarities of the different material. For my part, I would prefer to make the reproduction in marble, as the entire appearance will be more sympathetic, artistic and effective. It is true though, that the durability of marble, when compared with bronze, is rather short, but a work art made of marble makes an animated intimate impression, direct from the artist to the beholder, whilst in bronze it is cool and abstract.</p>
   <p>If, in the course of time, the marble should show signs of deterioration, then a form made of it and a subsequent cast in bronze, will assure its continued existence.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1673.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This method has been used repeatedly here, whereby monuments from the last century have been preserved, (Ziethen, the old Dessauer, etc. Field Marshal Ziethen from Dessau, army of Fredric the Great.) "However, by exercizing due care in the cutting of the marble cautious selection of material and in a fair climate, marble of second quality will last longer then the one century, but during that period one bus the unristricted effect of the artist's true conception.</p>
   <p>In regard to the size of the monument, the surroundings must be taken in to consideration. Here, in Berlin, the monument is almost entirely surrounded by dense shrubs, so that it appears to standing a closed room. In a more open space, the proportions should be larger. The total height of the Berlin creation is 6.00 meters; that of Goethe, 2.70 meters. In free surroundings, the figure should reach 3.00 meters, and the entire monument 7. meters. I have been informed, that the work should be in readiness for the Chicago World's Columbian Exposition in 1893. This entails considerable difficulty but is not impossible, provided that the labors are promptly started, at the beginning of 1891.</p>
   <p>In regard to the price of the monument, according to my present estimate it would require 130,000 to 150,000 marks: somewhat higher for bronze.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1674.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If it is preferred, however, to produce a suitable companion piece to the Chicago Schiller monument, then the Goethe statue, alone would suffice: cast in bronze, mounted on a simple granite pedestal, similar to the Schiller monument. This would naturally diminish the price to almost one third of the above sum, and the completion of the monument by 1893 would be assured.</p>
   <p>The enclosed photographs give a view of the monument in its entirety, and then separate portrayals of each pedestal groups. Pictures showing the Goethe statue, only, have not been made, but it would be a simple matter to obtain a good, small but accurate copy which could be mailed.</p>
   <p>In the belief, that I have answered all the desired phases of this proposition, I remain Very respectfully, F. Schaper, F. Schaper, Berlin , W. Buchen Strasse 4."</p>
   <p>The photographs which professor Schaper forward, will be placed on exposition at some suitable place to enable those who are interested in the proposition, to obtain a comprehensive idea. The artist has also offered to mail a small picture of his Goethe figure, in which the ornamental and magnificent pedestal groups are excluded. But, since the original object was to obtain in a counterpart for <pb facs="5418474_8_1675.jpg" n="5"/>our Schiller monument, it is obvious that a bronze reproduction mounted on a simple granite foundation, as described by the artist, will be mostly favored by the committee. This accomplishment gives the Germans an opportunity to display their noble ambitions and deeds before the enlightened Americans. There should be no procrastination so that the "World's Fair" visitors from the fatherland will find the two figures of these foremost aristocratic poets here.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
