<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-05-15">May 15, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Unveiling of Fritz Reuter's Statue Amidst Huge Crowds</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1639</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1639.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-05-15">May 15, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">UNVEILING OF FRITZ REUTER'S STATUE AMIDST HUGE CROWDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The marvelous statue of the immortal Low-German, poet, Fritz Reuter, was unveiled yesterday in a truly glorious manner.....</p>
   <p>People flocked to the beautiful spot in Humboldt Park, from all directions gathering around the still unveiled statue. The sound of trumpets in the distance announced the approaching parade which would add thousands more to the already huge crowds. The sonorous voices of the united men's choirs, the eloquent and deeply touching words of the speakers, the glorious spring sun focussing its rays upon the bronze statue, all uplifted and filled every heart with stirring emotions. This solemn and almost religious mood of the people truly represented the immortal spirit of Fritz Reuter.</p>
   <p>The parade was brilliant and impressive.....In the first division the guests of honor rode in richly decorated carriages. They were: Privy Councilor Wermuth, Germany's Commissary to the World's Fair, his aides and other representatives from the Reich....the German Consul, Dr. Buenz, the commissaries of the German women's department, Mrs. E. Kaselowsky, and Miss Hoffman; and the West Park Commissioners with the Central Committee of the Fritz Reuter Club. The participating clubs and organizations of the first division <pb facs="5418474_8_1640.jpg" n="2"/>were led by Marshal H. Pieper, and made a splendid impression with their uniforms and decorations. This division contained the Knights of America, the Teutonia Men's Choir, the Orpheus Men's Choir, the Schiller Singing Club, the Humboldt Choral Society, the Almira Glee Club, the Plattdeutsche (Low-German) Society of Chicago and the Citizen's Club of Avondale.</p>
   <p>The whole second division consisted of the Plattdeutsche (Low-German) Guilds of Chicago. They marched rather briskly under the command of Marshal H. Wulff, and his assistants, V. v.d. Lankern, and F. W. Huxmann.</p>
   <p>The third division, led by H. Gruenebaum, who was assisted by Heinzmann and J. Baus, was composed of the following organizations: the Mutual Benefit Association of Chicago, the Schleswig-Holstein Benefit Association, the Avon-dale Lodge D. O. H., the Garden City Grove V. A. O. D. No. 13, the Hamburger Club, the Schleswig-Holstein Society of Music, the Schleswig-Holstein Men's Choir, and North-German Mutual Benefit Association.</p>
   <p>The fourth division included the German War Veterans and the Military Associations, as well as the many German Athletic Clubs. This division was led by E. S. Dreier, M. Hecht, W. Niehorster, and their assistants.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1641.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A row of carriages with members of the Chicago Turn Gemeinde, and members of the German Press brought up the rear. The abundance of beautiful flags and banners made a grand and imposing impression.....</p>
   <p>A large orchestra then played a beautiful overture and Mr. Hesing addressed the audience. The statue was unveiled, and presented to Park commissioner C. Moll, who replied with a brief speech. Then the United Men's Chorus, under the direction of Ehrhorn, sang a song of dedication.</p>
   <p>The principal speaker was the president of the Plattdeutche (Low-German) Societies, Mr. E. F. L. Gauss, who was followed by W. Vocke who spoke in English. Mr. W. Meyer's speech in low-German concluded the celebration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
