<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-01-02">January 2, 1878</date><title level="a">The National German-American Seminary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0862</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0862.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-01-02">January 2, 1878</date><title level="a">THE NATIONAL GERMAN-AMERICAN SEMINARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Editor!</p>
   <p>If Mr. Bernays would not be known as a truth-loving, honest-thinking man, his article published in this newspaper last Saturday could make us believe, that he wants to be highly intelligent at any price. Seemingly, following this urge, he does not show any respect for any ideal agitations and human achievements.</p>
   <p>As a fact, Mr. Bernays is known to us as a sober thinking, righteous and sensible head, and just for this reason we deem it necessary to bring all facts, as cited and doubtless unintentionally distorted by Mr. Bernays, in the right light of logical discussion.</p>
   <p>Apparently Mr. Bernays did not know that the Seminary Society has already funds of $20,000. Otherwise he certainly would not write that there is not more than $10,000 on paper.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0863.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Also Mr. Bernays could not have known, that the Seminary project took shape and form only three years ago. Otherwise he would have hesitated to call this fine project an affair of graft dragging along during the last five years.</p>
   <p>There is now already a sufficient number of Seminary foundation societies in existence, which guarantee every year an income of about $4,000 for the Seminary.</p>
   <p>Also Mr. Bernays obviously was unaware of the fact that an institution which owns a stock of apparatus, books and financial assets of altogether $80,000 has offered its building, material and money for immediate use to the new Seminary. And still, Mr. Bernays dared to write that the Seminary plan is still on the same spot on which it was in the beginning.</p>
   <p>We are convinced that Mr. Bernays did not take his time to be informed <pb facs="5418474_8_0864.jpg" n="3"/>sufficiently on this subject, before he wrote down his opinion.</p>
   <p>As is the situation today, the German-Americans of this country will strain every nerve to make the National German-American Seminary a success. The same will be opened on September 1st, 1878.</p>
   <p>Signed:</p>
   <p>W. N. Hailmann</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
