<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-10-09">Oct. 9, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">After Eight Years</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1478</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1478.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-10-09">Oct. 9, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">AFTER EIGHT YEARS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Flames devastated Chicago eight years ago. The ominous day is again recorded on our calendar, but we are not beset with terror as in the days of the past. The devastation is not apparent any more--only a few still vacant lots give mute evidence of the Great Fire's course. The hard times, when business and trade were at a standstill--a loss which for years proved greater even than that caused by the fire--that dismal period has now passed.</p>
   <p>We seem to have greater confidence, and a brighter future beckons to us. Today we may look with satisfaction at what we salvaged, even though many lost everything and never regained their former status. Our possessions--what we have now--were not given by a whim of fickle fortune; the wealth we acquired was based on hard work, perseverence, and honest effort.</p>
   <p>The Germans of Chicago have special reasons to be grateful today. They lost <pb facs="5418474_8_1479.jpg" n="2"/>more than any other contingent in the city, since so many of them were tradesmen, merchants, and manufacturers; today their factories and stores have been rebuilt, wages are increasing, and the small shopkeeper notices a perceptible boost in sales. Everywhere there has been a change for the better--not merely in financial matters. For years, our Germans were divided. What one wanted was opposed by the other; if one acquired anything, he aroused the envy of his neighbor. Today we perceive more unity. We have a different attitude. The Germans seem to understand that they have a common goal, that they must be united if they wish to maintain the standing they acquired by helping suppress the Rebellion, that there must be no dissension in the German ranks if they wish to benefit by the numerical quantity they represent in the nation.</p>
   <p>As to the aforesaid, we now have an opportunity to prove our loyalty to a common cause by helping the Chicago Turngemeinde (Turner Association). The financial aspect of the organization is anything but pleasant. The beautiful hall, on which the Germans spent many a dollar, is threatened with foreclosure <pb facs="5418474_8_1480.jpg" n="3"/>unless the Germans as a whole arise and declare, "This building shall remain among us, since it is dedicated to the interests of our people!"</p>
   <p>If all make a common cause of it, there will be no difficulty whatsoever in averting the impending loss.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
