<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-05-28">May 28, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Gymnastic Exhibition.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1302</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1302.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-05-28">May 28, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">GYMNASTIC EXHIBITION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5 - Every Turner society, connected with the Chicago Turner District, was represented yesterday at the gymnastic exhibitions of the Turners held at Sunnyside Park. The net proceeds will be used to cover the transportation expenses of the active members who wish to participate at the association's Turner festivities in Philadelphia.</p>
   <p>Regardless of the unfavorable weather, several thousand people witnessed the exhibition.... An overture, played by Forest's band, opened the festivities. The first of the gymnastic exercises was performed by a group of young girls who wore very becoming uniforms. The exactness of their performance was rewarded with loud applause....Members of the Social Turner Society gave an excellent exhibition in bar exercises. The practice with dumb-bells and the building of the pyramid, by the active team of the Almira Turner Society was so perfect that, according to the oldest members of the Turner association, they surpassed all the performances of that kind ever given before.</p>
   <p>The woman's section of the La Salle Turner Society showed its fine ability as Turners, in the way of general exercises. The general bar exercises <pb facs="5418474_8_1303.jpg" n="2"/>performed by the active members of the Chicago Turner District, were under the leadership of Turner Cobelli. And finally, we can not omit to mention the fine performance by the active members of the Vorwaerts, La Salle, Lincoln and Einigkeit Turner Societies. It brought to light the great progress which has been made in Turner art. (Explanation: Vorwaerts: Forward. Einigkeit: Concordance, solidarity.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
