<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-10-01">Oct. 1, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">[To the Members of the German Section]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-10-01">Oct. 1, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">[TO THE MEMBERS OF THE GERMAN SECTION]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On request of Mr. Stauber, Altpeter, Lorentz, Ch. Meyer and George Meilbeck, a meeting of all members of good standing of the Socialistic Workman's Party will be held in Chicago next Saturday night, at 54 W. Lake Street. The object of this meeting will be a collective action of all party comrades with references to the coming elections. After the excitement of the discussions for and against cooperation with the Greenbackers had cooled down, since the Greenbackers themselves have refused at their last convention in Chicago to make concessions to Socialism, and since the majority of the Socialist Party in Chicago has decided to depend entirely on its own strength and to introduce their own program; the time has come, when a cool discussion should a gain unite the temporarily estranged party members to common action and cooperation. The Chicago Central Committee of the Socialistic Workman's Party officially has no concern with this meeting, but the individual members of same are also of the opinion, that all endeavors, to restore harmony amongst <pb facs="5418474_8_1141.jpg" n="2"/>various members of the party should have their full support. The same tendency is prevalent with the "Socialistic Publishing Society" and with the management of this paper. The crisis, which had existed with us, has been completely overcome. Experiences of the facts and a constantly increasing number of supporters of our paper has taught us, that the confidence of the people to the sacred cause of Socialism and its publications cannot be subdued by agitation of the opposition, hostile to our cause. The zeal of the German, Scandinavian and Bohemian comrades of the party in hours of danger and difficulties and their loyalty to our cause has given us the above gratifying results. We herewith openly express our recognition and gratification for their service. Also the last shadow of discontent and estrangement amongst all honest thinking comrades should be removed as much as possible. Therefore the endeavors of the above mentioned gentlemen, of the members of the Central Committee and the management of this paper should be supported by all true Socialists. We ask all members of the German section to attend the meeting on Saturday in large numbers and cooperate that way towards a restoration of the harmony of the party in the cause of the Socialist program. <pb facs="5418474_8_1142.jpg" n="3"/>We hope that all those, who did not object weeks ago to take part in those animated discussions will not stay away, and thereby prove, that they do not wish to make a personal question of a tactical question of dispute, which had since been overcome, or that they would quit the cause on account of not having been able to carry through their opinions. The Socialists point of view has been maintained and brotherhood can now take its place.</p>
   <p>To support this ideal view will bring pleasure to every Socialist.</p>
   <p>Forward! members of the German section, come Saturday, man for man to the a-foresaid meeting for the above mentioned object.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
