<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-30">Sept. 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of German Temple of Art.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1653</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1653.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-30">Sept. 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF GERMAN TEMPLE OF ART.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The alter of art, which the spirit of Germanity in one city has created after long continued, prodigious attempts, has been dedicated and a home for the Muse is now established in our new Fatherland. It was a long, stubborn fight, continued through years of doubt, failure and homelessness for the German Muse. But philanthropic men were exhilarated by the thought of making a financial sacrifice, since they felt, that the innate spark of enthusiasm for art is still dormant in the German heart. It was their purpose to rekindle this faint glow into a glorious flame and that was <pb facs="5418474_8_1654.jpg" n="2"/>achieved. From the masses came support for the great work and it was indeed just that the name of that heroic figure "Schiller" should grace the new temple, since his immortal creations endeared him to the hearts of the people..............For the present generation of Germans....we should consider and follow the proverb: "Support it, if you wish to own it."</p>
   <p>THE THEATER.</p>
   <p>The large main entrance, ornamented with the finest grade of marble, connects with a spacious aisle at right angles to it which branches off to the stairways, right and left of the auditorium. This space is brilliantly illuminated by powerful electric lights, which, with the dazzling reflections from the scintillating marble gives the whole a most <pb facs="5418474_8_1655.jpg" n="3"/>elegant appearance. By lengthening the main entrance hall......draft has been entirely eliminated......The seats on the ground floor are in terrace formation while the balcony and gallery are devoid of supports and pillars, providing an unobstructed view. A master work indeed has been created in this particular instance by the builders, Adler and Sullivan, who conceived this ingenious plan by anchoring the "I" beams on the walls. With all its gilding and color splender, a harmonious unit has been obtained, which is very satisfying to the beholder. The abolishment of the many galleries, angles and odd corners marks a great progress in theater building; it creates larger seating capacity since the gallery extends far outward towards the stage. Simplification has made far greater safety for the public...................The architects have created something unique in the wall decorations. Allegorical sculptured groups in high relief, depicting Greek mythological and historical scenes, form an <pb facs="5418474_8_1656.jpg" n="4"/>elaborate network of ornamentation, along the upper wall surfaces and in turn are surmounted by colossal arches of a pale green, restful hue which augments the apparent height of the theater.........Two masterworks, a pair of immense oil paintings, nearly cover the entire background of the balcony.. To the right, as seen from our vantage point at the bottom, we note the famous scene of Mary Stuart and Queen Elizabeth, as Schiller depicted it. The artist, Arthur Feudel, selected the moment, just after Mary, Queen of Scot, arose after kneeling before her captress and exclaimed: "I have endured as much as man may.</p>
   <p>Go hence now, docile indifference,</p>
   <p>Implore heaven, oh suffering patience!</p>
   <p>Long nursed hatred -</p>
   <p>Burst thy restraining shackles at last,</p>
   <p>Come forth from thy cavernous depths!"</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1657.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In the other picture the artist depicts the scene from Goethe's play, where Marguerita repulses Faust, on the way to church with the terse exclamation: "I'm not a Miss, nor am I beautiful. I am able to go home, unescorted!"</p>
   <p>The painter has shown the entire market place with the multitude and, in one of the groups, the conspicuous physiognomy of Mephisto predominates. He does not appear overly elated about his protege's discouraging experience, and the sinister force contemplates other hellish plans.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1658.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Mr. Feudel is a German with an international reputation. He also painted the frieze in the Metropolitan Hotel in Chicago. The auditorium is 90 ft. long, the plot of ground, 80 ft. wide. There are 1,300 seats, wide and comfortable. Exceptional liberality was shown in the dimensions and it enables egress without inconvenience.</p>
   <p>The stage covers the entire width of the lot, 80 ft....The opening which faces the public is 30 ft. (This appears to be an error, when considering the other proportions, it is probably larger). Thirty-eight feet deep. Top of scenery equal loft 75 ft. Cost of the Theater $250,000 of which $50,000 is listed for the stage and its equipment. Total cost including office building, about $800,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1659.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Speech By Hesing:</p>
   <p>"The proverb proclaims: 'Nothing succeeds like success!' We have gathered here to celebrate this realization!"</p>
   <p>Speech By E. G. Hirsch.</p>
   <p>"It was a most fortunate choice that the builders used Schiller's name in this instance. We have obtained as much inspiration from the World's great theaters, as from churches: let the scoffers therefore consider their opinions. Here we have a new realm, where bigotry and low, religious intolerance have no place."</p>
   <p>Music By Hand's Band.</p>
   <p>Location: Main entrance on Randolph Street., between La Salle, Clark Streets.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
