<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-12-03">December 3, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">German Sport Societies Act as Germans.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1233</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1233.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-12-03">December 3, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN SPORT SOCIETIES ACT AS GERMANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The official founding of a Protective Association of German sporting societies is a successful achievement. Chicago's German sports societies have made a great decision. Forgotten were all rivalries, Germans were sitting among Germans in a peaceful conference for the best of the sport, for the best of the German sporting ideals. The forming of a workers' union of German sports societies which repeatedly has been proposed by the Abendpost was successfully put into effect. How simple this sounds, and still what significance lies in these words. It is, as if the hour of redemption had struck for German sport in foreign countries, the hour of redemption from small subterfuges. It is possible that through this union of German sports societies, the aim will be reached of creating for German athletics in America, or better still in all countries to which we have access, a lasting and worthy home.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1234.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The intention is clear to work harmoniously together. The protection of interests, shall be adjusted to remove difficulties. If the inner front is established, suspicious removed, then action can be taken. Led by these considerations, establishment of a workers' union was started last Tuesday. The societies represented accepted the proposition made for the founding of a society for protection of German sports interests. In the lodge room of the Lincoln Turnverein, thirty persons were present, mostly representatives of societies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
