<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-26">Nov. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Germania Broadcast Celebrated its Eighth Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0728</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0728.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-26">Nov. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANIA BROADCAST CELEBRATED ITS EIGHTH ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The eighth anniversary of the Germania Broadcast, celebrated yesterday afternoon with a concert and followed by a ball at the Marigold Garden, was an event of musical and social significance. Noted men and women artists who have been heard on the program since the Germania radio concerts were begun, participated in the anniversary program. Three conductors took turns at directing, which showed the adaptability of the audience and the capability of the maestros, for the value of the orchestral renditions were unimpaired. The performance of the finale from the second act of the operetta, "Die Fledermaus," was a mass performance by soloists and other participants and a musical treat that held the attention of the audience until the end. The length of the program bears witness to the skill with which the program was arranged. This was the work of the manager of the Germania Broadcast, William L. Klein.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0729.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The concert proved extremely enjoyable for lovers of good musical recitals. Among the conductors of the concert first rank was taken by Concert Master Otto Vandsburger who was made to repeat his success with the Fledermaus performance. He also gave his conception of the melodies in the Fledermaus operetta which he interpreted as coming within the scope of the concert. It was given as a lecture with much ardor and enthusiasm. Beside him Siegfried Volstedt earned musical laurels with the recital of a number of Wagner compositions. Georg Hessberger, as conductor, likewise contributed to the program during the concert; and, especially when, during the later part of the program, he succeeded in introducing merriment and a spirit of good humor among the dancing guests.</p>
   <p>Under Reinhold Walter, the Schiller Liedertafel achieved a performance of Mohr's composition, "Am Altar der Wahrheit," which, considering the technical difficulties, was worthy of recognition. In addition there were presented the lady soloists, Florence Kaiser, Lucie Westen, Miga March-Fiechtl, and Irma Fereney, and the gentlemen soloists, Georg Trabert, Willard Andelin, and <pb facs="5418474_8_0730.jpg" n="3"/>Angelo Lippich. Then came the ladies, Ilka Diehl and Anna Fransch, who staged a sketch "Frau Suess" and "Frau Sauer". Their art is well known and appreciated.</p>
   <p>Curt Benisch, the stage manager of the successful Fledermaus performance, delivered and interesting prologue, and Kurt Kupfer came upon the stage in the role of the prison warden, Frosch, and contributed to the good humor of the audience.</p>
   <p>The radio revue at 11 P.M. and the raffle that followed did not allow the time to drag for the audience, so that the circle of guests who came to the festival were able to prolong their entertainment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
