<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-06-13">June 13, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Long Ago and Now</title><title level="a" type="sub">Illustrated Lecture about German Family and Child Life the Swiss Home at Neutal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0955</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0955.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-06-13">June 13, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">LONG AGO AND NOW</title><title level="a" type="sub">Illustrated Lecture about German Family and Child Life The Swiss Home at Neutal</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the Evangelical Church of the Reverend Alfred Meyer, Hoyne and Pensacola Avenues, there is going to be on Monday, June 16, at 8 P.M., an illustrated lecture under the title: "German Family and Child Life, Then and Now." The pictures show views of the German family and child life drawn by well-known artists such as Uhde, Thoma, Richter, etc. These sympathetic, gay pictures of the "Once" constitute the bright background for the discussion of the family and child life of the "Now", with all its shadows dark as the night and hopeless. These bleak scenes are relieved by pictures of the charitable acts of a blessed man, Julius Kuder, who in his beautifully situated Swiss home, Neutal, has for years been gathering the most miserable children from all parts of the unfortunate German homeland, and restoring them to mental and bodily health. This institution of Christian love is, for its continuance, <pb facs="5418474_8_0956.jpg" n="2"/>entirely dependent upon American aid. It has, in Chicago, a number of friends, especially among those who personally got acquainted with the noble work of love done by the director of the institution and by his self-sacrificing collaborators.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
