<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-11-02">Nov. 2, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">In Union There Is Strength</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1296</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1296.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-11-02">Nov. 2, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">IN UNION THERE IS STRENGTH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a fitting climax to the completion of the athletic grounds, the Chicago Turn Community gave a dedication banquet last night. All the Turner societies were well represented. In spite of the unfavorable weather, a host of friends of the Chicago Turn Community attended the celebration. The newly renovated hall was crowded with guests. Mr. Heinrich Suder, superintendent of gymnastics in the public schools, acted as chairman and formally welcomed the assembled guests. A mass chorus then sang "The Hermit" and "The March of the Singers," by Kern. Mr. G. A. Schmidt was the first speaker of the evening. He compared the community to a sick man who could only be saved by a surgical operation. The Administrative Council of the Turn Community has most successfully performed such an operation.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1297.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now, that the patient is convalescing, it is up to the Germans of our city to give him the necessary care in the future. There is no nobler aspiration than to cooperate in the education of body and soul....."In Unity There is Strength." Therefore, the Chicago Turn Community hopes to meet the representatives of other Turn societies more often in the future.....The next speaker was Mr. Louis O. Kohtz, a former member of the school board. He said:</p>
   <p>"We have met many times in this hall on previous occasions. This hall has witnessed many successess and brilliant accomplishments of the Turn Community. It has always been the place where Jahn's spirit dominated. Here youth and adult mingled freely; here is where real Turners were trained. Each new success strengtened our courage and spurred us on to greater things.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1298.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The realization of our high ideals was made impossible because of the disasters suffered by our country. But we, and our courage were saved, which enabled us to make a triumphant entry into this new home of athletic art. We are eager to show our friends that the Turn Community does not give up, although it had to sustain a continuous struggle with adversities"..... Mr. Kohtz was loudly applauded at the end of his speech.</p>
   <p>Turner George L. Pfeiffer, of the Turn Society Vorwaerts, indicated that the Chicago Turn Community is the pioneer Community of athletic art in the West. He also expressed the hope that in the near future all the Chicago Turn societies would be united under one head.....A lovely musical program concluded the affair.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
