<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-10-04">Oct. 4, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Swiss Turners</title><title level="a" type="sub">Yearly Fair a Marked Success.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1241</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1241.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-10-04">Oct. 4, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">SWISS TURNERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Yearly Fair a Marked Success.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swiss colony met yesterday for the yearly fair of the Swiss Turn Verein; the fair is to last for two days. The hall, festively decorated, was filled quite early, and the most pleasing atmosphere prevailed. Upon entering, one was greeted by the bazaar arranged by the women, and the women's "turn class." It did not take long for one to be taken into the right mood by the melodious Swiss songs and refreshing musical pieces. The entertainment had all the easygoing characteristics of the Swiss. Of course, the Swiss dialect reigned supreme.</p>
   <p>The Schweizer Liederkranz (Swiss Singing Circle) and the Schweizer Damenchor (Swiss Ladies' Chorus) sang a few songs. These were followed by performances of the fighting class of the turn society Vorwaerts (Forward) and by other gymnastic exercises.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1242.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The committee, under the leadership of Mr. Walter Gesle, deserves full praise. The committee comprised, among others, the following ladies and gentlemen: Ernst Senn, Karl Mueller, George Spaet, Robert Burger, Eugen Tricker, Mrs. Robert Burger, Adolph Schachermann, Marie Hammer, Ernst Wirth, and Albert Langhorst.</p>
   <p>The festival, which as already mentioned, was well attended, will continue this afternoon.</p>
   <p>No less successful was the arrangement of the twentieth anniversary by the singing section of the German Krieger Verein (Warrior Association). Their efforts were rewarded by a large crowd. The festival committee stood under the leadership of Mr. Henry Bartsch and, with song and dance, the crowd was entertained until late at night. Excellent ball music brought the mood of those present to a high pitch and, every time there was a lull the talented singers of the Krieger Verein were on the spot to a man. From among their performances <pb facs="5418474_8_1243.jpg" n="3"/>may especially be mentioned "In Leiterer Gesellschaft" (In gay company), a song suitable to the panel of the entertainment. Further songs were a soldier's march, "Tag des Herrn" (Day of the Lord), and "Harmonie".</p>
   <p>The following gentlemen, among others, were members of the festival committee: Dietrich Paulson, Adolph Kopp, August Wolf, John Steven, Arthur Oeschler, Otto Kern, and Philipp Wagner.......</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
