<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-03-22">Mar. 22, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">German Assistance Union.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1734</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1734.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-03-22">Mar. 22, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN ASSISTANCE UNION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The section convention of the German Assistance Union of Chicago was held Thursday evening in the Lincoln Turner Hall. The temporary president, Joseph M. Schon, gave a short retrospect of its activity during the last four years and substantiated with satisfaction that the membership has more than doubled during this time, Jas. J. Heidy was elected temporary secretary.</p>
   <p>After the examination committee reported that 12 sections with 61 delegates were represented, the following officers were elected: Joseph M. Schon, president; Henry Schlosser, Vice-president; Jas. J. Heidy, secretary; Joe Schabhuettl, treasurer; Valentine Dietz, guide and Albert Eggers, supervisor.</p>
   <p>Among the approved recommendations to be submitted in May to the supreme convention in Pittsburgh are the following: That the per capita tax be abolished; that an insurance up to $2,000 be allowed; and that the old age treasury pay double the amount of the paid-in assessment to the heirs of deceased members. Of the class "B" recommendations, which were approved, the most important is that a member after 20 years, should, upon request receive a certificate in which the heirs are assured, that they will receive the paid-in assessment, together with 6% interest.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1735.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The supreme representatives, Joseph M. Schon, Henry Schlosser and Paul Pappendorf, were re-elected by acclamation in appreciation of their meritorious services during the past four years.</p>
   <p>The German Assistance Union with its 65,000 members and a reserve capital of over four million dollars, is the largest German-American organization for mutual insurance and is equal to any of the English-speaking associations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
