<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-14">June 14, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Honoring General Steuben</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1559</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1559.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-14">June 14, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">HONORING GENERAL STEUBEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the rotunda of the old post-office building are three plaques representing three heroes of the Revolutionary War. The three heroes came from distant lands to aid the colonies in their struggle for freedom. The plaques are of Pulaski, Kosciuszko and Lafayette, two Poles and one Frenchman. They contributed their part to the victorious struggle, and the honors bestowed upon them by the American people are well merited. But still it is regrettable that the German general, Von Steuben, has been overlooked until now.</p>
   <p>It has ever been a weakness of the German-Americans to keep their own light dimmed. They have not forgotten their old fatherland, but they have been too quickly absorbed in the American national life. They have not shown sufficient pride in their German ancestry, and perhaps have been too modest to demand the <pb facs="5418474_8_1560.jpg" n="2"/>deserved recognition for themselves and their fellow nationals. Now, the incentive to make good the omission has been given, and a plaque of General von Steuben should be placed on a pillar of the rotunda of the post-office building.</p>
   <p>The idea has fallen upon fertile ground. Postmaster Ernest J. Kruetgen has promised to give it his support, and a committee has been formed to execute the plan. The next step is to procure the necessary money. By this Steuben plaque, the whole German population of Chicago can honor itself, and therefore a call is issued to them to participate fully in the collection.</p>
   <p>One should not understimate the importance of this plan. Here is the rotunda of a public building, in the second largest city of the country, in which Polish and French heroes of the wars of independence have received honorable memorials. The German hero's plaque is missing. This German is no less a person than General Frederic William von Steuben, creator of the American army, the man who, out of a badly armed, badly equipped and trained mob, created a well-disciplined armed <pb facs="5418474_8_1561.jpg" n="3"/>force which was ever ready to attack. Without his active co-operation, the struggle would perhaps never have had its victorious end.</p>
   <p>The fact that his plaque is missing is a silent reproach to Chicago's Germans, and it is high time to make good what has been omitted. Therefore, all German-Americans should make it a point of honor to contribute their share to this fund.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
