<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-04-04">Apr. 4, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The German Cycle Club</title><title level="a" type="sub">Founding of the Club yesterday witnessed by Many</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1220</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1220.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-04-04">Apr. 4, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN CYCLE CLUB</title><title level="a" type="sub">Founding of the Club yesterday witnessed by Many</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the first German-American Cycle Club of Chicago was founded yesterday, the dream of bicycle sport fans was at last realized. Germans will now have the opportunity of sending their representatives to cycling contests, thus achieving what is customarily required of every sport organization. These Germans will, not doubt, defend the German colors with the same interest and zeal manifested in the past by members of other sport clubs, and thus will contribute to the eminence of the German people.</p>
   <p>Great joy was manifested by all present over the message received from those well-known leaders in the field of bicycle sport, Otto Petri, Franz Duelberg, and Chicago's "Hy" Kockler, who offered the new club their assistance at all times. Nick Kockler's offer to enlist as co-worker for the Club, was cordially accepted. (Nick is the brother of one of the foremost cyclists of the day.)</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1221.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When the National Bicycle League meets tomorrow, the affiliation of the new club and its members will be requested. Thus ample time will be provided for members to participate in the contests which are scheduled to take place in the near future. The members of the new organization also decided to take active part in the German Day Celebration and, moreover, to appear as a unit in the parade.</p>
   <p>Temporary officers were then elected, with the following results: H. Nordegg, president; Nick Kockler, vice-president; Joseph Koch, secretary; Gerhard Stielau, treasurer; Hellmut Stolle, correspondent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
