<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-03-04">March 4th, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Carl Schurz Memorial Society.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1627</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1627.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-03-04">March 4th, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">CARL SCHURZ MEMORIAL SOCIETY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The National Carl Schurz Memorial Society, which was formed soon after the death of the famed German-American, and which has its main office in New York with branches in Chicago, St. Louis, Milwankee, Washington, Baltimore, Philadelphia, and Boston has just given details of their plans.</p>
   <p>The first is the erection of a memorial to the value of $250,000 of which $40,000 have been signed for by some friends of the deceased. The society however will not stop with the erection of the dead statue of stone, but will act in the spirit of the dead by effective agitation of the civil service system, a movement of Which the dead was the chief for many years, the development of the German movement in the United States of America of which Mr. Schurz was a busy agitator as President of the German Museums Society, the Harvard University and Vice President of the German Society of New York.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1628.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The permanent retention of his name in Hampton, which is dedicated to the volution of two races, for which he has worked officially and privately during his lifetime, was especially sponsored by the executive committee. In Hampton, Carl Schurz, as Secretary of the Interior made his first successful experiments with the education of the Indians, which led to the present system of government schools with their civilized influence. It was his wish in the last years of his life to contribute to a proper installment of such institution and it is the plan of this society to accomplish these wishes. The former American ambassador at the English Court, Joseph H. Choate is the Chairman and the Banker, Isaac N. Seligman, is the Secretary of the National Society. Mr. Wilhelm Bocke is Chairman and Mr Otto E. Schneider, Secretary of the Chicago branch. The Milwaukee branch will erect a memorial themselves and after completion they will participare on the National movement in honor of Carl Schurz. The Society will also honor Schurz's activity for the development of the Negro and Indian races by the erection of a suitable building or in other suitable manner in the institution of Hampton, Va.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
