<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-09-13">Sep. 13, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">[Freedom of the Press]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0571</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0571.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-09-13">Sep. 13, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">[FREEDOM OF THE PRESS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among many liberties enjoyed by the sovereign American citizen, the unlimited freedom of the press ranks foremost.</p>
   <p>An attempt from any quarter to curb this liberty would draw a tempest of indignation which might prove dangerous to that political party which sponsored such a move.</p>
   <p>The American glorifies especially this alleged symbol of a free nation, Surely freedom of the press and speech are prime and main necessities of a social structure where culture and liberty can develop.</p>
   <p>But when, as is the case in this country, dust is being thrown in the eyes of the people with big words about press freedom, while on the other hand the population becomes more and more enslaved, we arrive inevitable at the conclusion that this liberty not only is of no use at all but might prove under circumstances ruinous for the development of a nation.</p>
   <p>Under the present depressing conditions of today there are only a very few in a position to actually realize the advantages deriving from unlimited <pb facs="5418474_8_0572.jpg" n="2"/>press freedom. The working class man of today does not read the papers for education or enlightenment but to kill what little spare time he has, and he does not question the value of what he reads.</p>
   <p>How can there be any talk about freedom the the press in a system of society where everything is written only for money?</p>
   <p>If one newspaper or magazine actually writes the truth there are ten others who come out with lies, errors and corruptions.</p>
   <p>Above all things required for a journalist, unscrupulousness is essential, as there cannot be any sentimental regard when it comes to destroying the moral reputation of persons not in favor. Whoever is able to fill these requirements can be a big success in the newspaper world, even though he or she be otherwise a rogue.</p>
   <p>No other place can there be found so many misunderstood geniuses as in the German-American press of this country. It is therefore pure hypocritical <pb facs="5418474_8_0573.jpg" n="3"/>demagogy to inject into our people the idea of what a big advantage we have with our free press in comparison to other nations.</p>
   <p>Whoever is not able to see through American conditions should glance at England where although unlimited freedom of the press has been in existence for 150 years, the population is less enlightened than the poorest classes in Germany and people actually starve for lack of food in spite of that free press.</p>
   <p>The workers' press shows the same demoralizing influence of today's system; here too you can notice that it is partially the fight for existence which makes workers' papers fight against each other and dirty themselves under cover of the principle.</p>
   <p>Such attitudes do more damage to the labor movement than an outspoken capitalistic paper ever would be able to do.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
