<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-12-02">Dec. 2, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Goethe the Human Being.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Professor Scherger Speaks of the Greatest German Since Luther.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0942</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0942.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-12-02">Dec. 2, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">GOETHE THE HUMAN BEING.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Professor Scherger Speaks of the Greatest German Since Luther.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The subject of his yesterday's lecture was "Goethe the artist of living" and in a captivating manner he described the genial manner, the never ending desire for learning, and the inexhaustible power to create, or the man whom he calls the greatest German since Luther. All who came in touch with Goethe, he says, felt drawn to and inspired by the imposing personality of the great poet, whose fame and esteem have only increased, with every new decade.</p>
   <p>What Goethe created, he drew from occurrences in his own life, which once made his heart glad or mournful, or diverted his spirit from the daily path. In contrast to the pure idealist, Schiller, Goethe was a realist, who saw things as they were, a characteristic which even found expression in his big, lucid and speaking eyes. Goethe possessed a deep religious belief, even if he opposed the orthodox confession of both Christian denominations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0943.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He was a pantheist and in connection with those views he carried on his brisk activity in natural science, his striving to grasp the secrets of the heavenly works and to disclose them. In a similar way, his ethical convistions were expressed and his poetic creations too. The last mentioned the speaker only touched on briefly, referring to one of Goethe's beautiful sentimental poems: "Above all the tree tops is repose."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
