<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-22">Feb. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">German-American Historical Society's Membership Not as Large as Desirable</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0377</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0377.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-22">Feb. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN-AMERICAN HISTORICAL SOCIETY'S MEMBERSHIP NOT AS LARGE AS DESIRABLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The secretary of the German-American Historical Society reports that the year-book of the association, published in 1914, has been received with the same enthusiasm as former editions, and that indications are that the demand for it is constantly increasing, especially among scholars and in university circles. The University of Chicago Press distributes the yearbook now, a task which formerly was done by the Society itself. A small surplus of former publications is similarly taken care of. Older editions, particularly the first year's issue, are practically exhausted.</p>
   <p>Although its cultural work progresses constantly and rapidly, the Society's membership list does not show auspicious indications. The secretary's list contains 190 paying members. The German-American Historical Society is today the only association of its kind in the United States, and its findings, edited by Prof. Julius Goebel, of the Illinois State University, have <pb facs="5418474_8_0378.jpg" n="2"/>never been excelled by any other institution of this kind. Its thoroughly original historical articles are a fund of information for future historians. A movement is now being contemplated to publish general articles of German-American historical value, articles which will reveal the deeds of our German pioneers in America and other incidents only known to the historically initiated but which will tend to inspire self-confidence among our German immigrants and their descendants, thereby fortifying them against any eventual falsifications and fabrications about the past.</p>
   <p>But regardless of this project, we may look forward to considerable activity along other roads of endeavor. To begin with, several public lectures are now in the offing.</p>
   <p>Of five directors whose terms have just expired, four were reelected for two years, with Mr. G. E. Uihlein [probably Uhlein] elected for the vacancy of the fifth.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0379.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>All the regular officials were re-elected. The 1915 Year-book is now in print, and will be issued earlier than usual.</p>
   <p>Every German society or group should be a member of the German-American Historical Society of Illinois. The dues are only $3 a year both for associations, and individual members. Applications may be made to the secretary, Max Baum, Room 1608, 5 S. Wabash Avenue. Life membership may be had for a single cash payment of $25.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
