<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-05-13">May 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">District 381 of Deutsche Unterstuetzungsbund Celebrates its Silver Jubilee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1694</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1694.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-05-13">May 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">DISTRICT 381 OF DEUTSCHE UNTERSTUETZUNGSBUND CELEBRATES ITS SILVER JUBILEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>District 381 of the Deutsche Unterstuetzungsbund (German Benevolent Alliance) celebrated its silver jubilee yesterday. Many members and friends were present at the festival, which was very enjoyable and well arranged. The guests of honor were Ernst Herklotz, president of the Alliance and Organizer Theodor Huettner, of Pittsburgh.</p>
   <p>Each performance on the program was announced by the master of ceremonies, John Hermann, who also introduced the speakers and prominent officials who were present as guests. All the Chicago districts were represented, as well as the Central Committee and Districts 632 and 728 of Milwaukee. There was also a large delegation from the Vereinigten Deutsch-Oesterreichisch-Ungarischen Vereine (United German-Austrian-Hungarian Societies).</p>
   <p>Krachtus' well-known orchestra was entrusted with a large part of the <pb facs="5418474_8_1695.jpg" n="2"/>program and acquitted itself of its task in a way that met with general approval. The women's chorus of the Deutsche Unterstuetzungsbund, under its new director, Wilhelm Taegtmeyer, as well as the women's chorus Lorelei and the Westseite-Saengerkranz (West Side Singing Circle) under the directorship of Ludwig Lohmiller, received well-deserved applause for their singing and contributed much to the success of the festival. The Glueckswalzer (Happiness Waltz), arranged and conducted by Mr. Lohmiller, was so successful that it had to be repeated. Most delightful of all was the clog dance of little Margareth Gregory and Martin Heim. Henry Hermann Brandau, Adam Mueller, and M. Kessler, a mandolin-zither trio, won enthusiastic but well deserved applause.</p>
   <p>The first of the inevitable speeches on such occasions was given by the chairman of the festival, Alois Botthoff, who welcomed those present, especially the two guests of honor from Pittsburgh.....In the principal speech of the occasion Adam Gabriel set forth the history of the society and praised its past and present officers. At the close of his speech he presented Emil Kazar, the only living charter member, who had been <pb facs="5418474_8_1696.jpg" n="3"/>secretary for many years, with a gold medal in the name of the district. Mr. Mathias Taugner, another member of long standing, who had formerly been very active, he presented with a gold ring, a gift from the national office.....</p>
   <p>President Herklotz, after he had transmitted to District 381 the hearty good wishes of the national officers, in a rather long address discussed the excellent condition of the Alliance, financial and otherwise, and expressed the hope that the Chicago region, and not least this district which was holding the festival, would co-operate in the future as in the past in building up the Alliance.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
