<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-03-23">Mar. 23, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Fritz Glogauer, Founder of Abendpost, Dies in Cincinnati.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0471</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0471.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-03-23">Mar. 23, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">FRITZ GLOGAUER, FOUNDER OF ABENDPOST, DIES IN CINCINNATI.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From Cincinnati comes news of the death of Fritz Glogauer, founder and for many years manager of the Abendpost, The announcement of his death does not come as a surprise.</p>
   <p>In a few months Mr. Glogauer would have reached the Biblical age, the age at which the human being has to prepare itself for the departure to the beyond. In addition, Mr. Glogauer was a sick man for years. He suffered from hardening of the arteries. At times this malady appeared in a mild form, but sometimes it became so bad, that the patient suffered terribly. Now death has relieved him. Therewith a career has been brought to a close, which was rich in interesting and inspiring moments.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0472.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Fritz Glogauer led the life of a restless and indefatigable fighter. The fight was his life element. His inclinations and talents referred him to the terrain of journalism and politics, and he cheerfully followed the hint of nature and of fate, with his whole soul. He was born June 15, 1857, in Falkenberg, in the province of Gilesia, son of a Jewish rabbi. He received an excellent education, as is traditional and usual in these families. The political field allured him at an early age. At that time the waves of social movements were high and it was only natural, that the young academician from Breslau, should join in the fight on the extreme left. He was already active as a journalist, when a young man, and preached in stirring words, the gospel of social revolution. When 20 years old, he came to the much praised country of the free. Here also a strong radical movement among the German working classes was noticeable, which found its center in radical German newspapers. One of these papers was the Volksstimme, (the Voice of the People) in Cincinnati, where Fritz Glogauer <pb facs="5418474_8_0473.jpg" n="3"/>found employment. But journalistic occupation during the day, left young Glogauer ample time to turn his attention to American life, in all its manifold and interesting forms. And Cincinnati offered him a lucrative and grateful field. The old "Queen of the West " was in those days an extremely pleasure loving city. Here was the great amusement center of the whole American west, which was actually quite wild at that time. But Cincinnati was also a prominent center of culture. It was at that time the leading musical city of the country. Here lived a number of distinguished German-Americans, men who gained undying honor for the spiritual development and history of the German-Americans.</p>
   <p>Here Fritz Glogauer learned for the first time the powerful spiritual forces which stirred in the Germans of this country. Here he got acquainted <pb facs="5418474_8_0474.jpg" n="4"/>with the appearances of German-American life, here he laid the foundation for his later activities as leader of a great German-American daily newspaper. And Cincinnati must have had a drawing power, which it exercised upon the young German newspaper writer, because in this city did he spend the years of his old age and leisure, and here did he end his active life.</p>
   <p>When the workers' movement began to lag, the Cincinnati Volksstimme died a natural death, Glogauer felt disappointed and sobered, and decided to recuperate from the distortedness of humanity, in nature. The magic of distance was calling, and like so many young German writers and bookworms, Fritz Glogauer also decided to rest in the virgin forests from the disquietude and confusion of the large city and the political struggles.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0475.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>He went in the company of a few friends to the northern part of Michigan. Here the young men led a very primitive life in the bosom of mother nature. But to the restlessly active young journalist this life, which was devoted to fishing, hunting, and meditative idling, became soon too monotonous. He returned to civilization.</p>
   <p>In the winter of 1879 he joined the editorial staff of the Cleveland Awzeiger, which was published by Wilhelm Kaufmann. At the same time he married a young lady, with whom he lived very happily.</p>
   <p>From a reporter, Glogauer soon worked himself up to the position of chief-editor of the paper, and when Mr. Kaufmann in 1881, with several Germans of St. Louis, founded the evening paper, the Tribune, in that city, he transferred its management to Mr. Glogauer. But his activity in St. Louis was spoiled by a tragic event. In quick succession death snatched away his wife and the child she bore him.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0476.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>A broken-hearted man, Glogauer returned to Cleveland. He joined again the Awzeiger, and in the course of years, the wounds healed. In the year 1883, he contracted a second marriage. The bride was Miss Caroline Siebel from Rochester, New York. This union proved to be a source of great blessing. His wife presented him with four beautiful daughters. And amidst his family, Fritz Glogauer found animation and enthusiasm for his restless journalistic and political activities. Here he found recreation from his grinding and fatiguing activity of newspaper work.</p>
   <p>At that time, the fight against nativism and prohibition, belonged to the life work of the German-speaking press. In this fight Fritz Glogauer stood in the front ranks. He called an organization into life that included most of the associations that carried the fight against puritanism upon their banners. This alliance for local self-government developed into a strong and spirited weapon against prohibition.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0477.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>That it was later exploited for political purposes, was not the fault of its founder. For years Glogauer played a leading role in German circles of Chicago, and the leadership was relinquished to him gladly by his countrymen. They knew that he could judge a situation properly, that he fully understood the methods and aims of practical polities, and that he fought disinterestedly and unselfishly for the German element. In a word, they knew that their case was in good hands and for that reason they gladly entrusted to him the leadership.</p>
   <p>In public life Glogauer was regarded as a man who divided his existence between professional duty and his family, for whom sociability among like-minded friends did not exist.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0478.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Fritz Glogauer possessed a pronounced sense of humor. It is true, that his humor often had a slight coloring of irony, that he sometimes changed to satire. But Glogauer understood the art of laughter. And he could laugh just as heartily when his friends poked a fun at him at his expense, as if he had played them a successful trick.</p>
   <p>It is therefore obvious, that such a man found himself at home in the Schlaraffia. He also visited their meetings in Chicago, Munich and Cincinnati, and he never appeared with empty hands. He always could offer a lecture, which according to the occasion was either serious, or saturated with humor.</p>
   <p>In all endeavors and events pertaining to the German element, he took a lively and active part, and to all charitable endeavors, he contributed <pb facs="5418474_8_0479.jpg" n="9"/>checks, which sometimes represented large amounts.</p>
   <p>In latter years Mr. Glogauer undertook several trips, partly to find relief from his old malady, partly to see his old home again. - And now death has taken from the hands of this tireless man book and pen, and carried him to that country from where there is no return. He finished his life's work and his deeds and accomplishments will outlast his death.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
