<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-01-08">Jan. 8, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">German Lecture at the Planetarium</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0913</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0913.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-01-08">Jan. 8, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN LECTURE AT THE PLANETARIUM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Planetarium is one of Chicago's objects of interest. Almost every stranger visiting this city goes to the Planetarium to look at the wonders of the firmament. The Planetarium, as is well known, is a product of German genius; it was built by the firm of Carl Zeiss in Jena, Germany.</p>
   <p>Mr. Franz Fieseler, who is the representative of this firm, is at present staying in the United States. He will lecture in the German language at the Planetarium January 14th.</p>
   <p>Mr. Fieseler occupies a leading position at this world-famous business house of Carl Zeiss. He traveled all over the world and became acquainted with numerous members of European nobility, ministers and other prominent and distinguished personalities. He has also made many friends here, in Chicago, where he stayed for some time on the occasion of supervising the installation of instruments at the Planetarium. The entire German population of Chicago will have the opportunity to make his acquaintance next week; also to learn something about the Zeiss- <pb facs="5418474_8_0914.jpg" n="2"/>works in Jena, which is the greatest optical institution of the world; therefore, in a large circle of the German-American population the interest is great and they anxiously look forward to the lecture.</p>
   <p>A committee was formed which takes care of the necessary preparatory work of the lecture. The committee consists of the German Consul-General, Dr. Hugo F. Simon, Professor Philip Fox, Karl Eitel, Daniel Goldberg, Richard Grieper, Heinrich Heine, Heinrich Haff, Ludwig W. Kauffl, Henry Kober, Ernest J. Kruetgen, Paul H. Mueller, Paul H. Ortman, Richard Pick, C. F. Pegenan, Ludwig Plate, Authur Pransnitz, A.C.E. Schmidt, Dr. Otto L. Schmidt, Alfred B. Steffens and Bernard De Vry.</p>
   <p>The lecture as mentioned before, will be held in the German language. Prof. Philip Fox, who is the director of the Planetarium, has personally endeavored to secure Mr.Fieseler for this lecture, because it is his wish to interest also the German speaking population in the Planetarium, which undoubtedly is the greatest attraction of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0915.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Therefore it is not surprising that in German-American circles the greatest interest prevails for this occasion, owing to the fact that the Planetarium is the work of German genius and German ability.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
