<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-04-02">Apr. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">As Things Used to Be</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. H. H. Maurer Speaks on German-American History</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0957</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0957.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-04-02">Apr. 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">AS THINGS USED TO BE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. H. H. Maurer Speaks on German-American History</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The lecture which was delivered last night by Dr. H. H. Maurer before a large and eager audience in the main hall of the Lincoln Club, and which lasted for nearly two hours, could be appropriately entitled: "The Eventful and The Uneventful in German American History." Doctor Maurer restricted the immigration of the "forty-eighters" [immigrants who fled from Germany in 1848]. He will deal with later events in a second lecture scheduled for April 15, when he will bring his account up to date.</p>
   <p>German immigration to America, stated the lecturer, was never continuous or uniform: rather it occurred in waves of varying intensity, which arose as a result of the particularily drastic manifestations of imperialism on the other side of the ocean. The first such wave, resulting from Louis the Fourteenth's invasion of the Palatinate, precipitated nearly 250,000 German immigrants on the shores of North America. Further mass migrations from <pb facs="5418474_8_0958.jpg" n="2"/>German areas were occasioned by the Napoleonic wars by Metternich's spy system, and the events of the year '48.</p>
   <p>The German immigrants brought with them the traditional virtues of industry, honesty, and cleanliness, which they applied in their subsequent activities and dealings in a manner which brought credit to themselves and their new homeland. With these virtues, they combined a love of gaiety, and sociability, and physical exercise. Their outlook on life was in sharp contrast to many of the views held by their new neighbors from puritanic England. This contrast had been previously noted by an early German immigrant: it led him to remark:</p>
   <p>"The Americans do not know how to enjoy themselves. What do they do they get together? They sit around a fire and --spit!"</p>
   <p>Many names famous in German-American history were mentioned by Doctor Maurer in the course of his lecture. Some of these men were mentioned only incidentally, but the careers of others --including Muehlenberg, <pb facs="5418474_8_0959.jpg" n="3"/>Pastorius, Steuben, Konard Weisser, Schlatter, Beissel, Herkheimer, Stiegel, and Christoph Saur--were briefly outlined in a short but comprehensive sketch. The speaker dwelt for some time on Christoph Saur, since his achievements and influence had been so intimately related to the daily life of the German-American of his time. The lecturer said:</p>
   <p>"If in the year 1754 you had entered a German home located anywhere between New York and Georgia and asked who was Christoph Saur, you would have learned that the Bible which was used in the house had been printed by Christoph Saur; that the book of Sunday hymns, taken from the psalms of David, had likewise been printed by Christoph Saur; that the family almanac, filled with medical and historical lore and containing, in addition, a day-by day weather forecast, had come from the printing shop of Christoph Saur; that the newspaper which kept the German living on his farm informed about the events in this country and other lands had been printed by Christoph Saur; that the ink and paper used by the immigrant to write to his dear ones overseas had come from Christoph Saur's store and had been manufactured in his workshop; that the six-panelled oven which during the long winter days emitted such comfortable <pb facs="5418474_8_0960.jpg" n="4"/>warmth had been invented by Christoph Saur and could be ordered from his place of business; that the medicine which stood in the corner cupboard ready for all occasions had been compounded and prepared by Dr. Christoph Saur; that the horrible privations and humiliations to which immigrants were exposed during the ocean-crossing had been mitigated by the energetic protests of a man and that this man had been Christoph Saur; that the immigrants who were ill when they landed in philadelphia had been welcomed by a friend, had been taken into his own home where they were well cared for until they could continue their journey into the wilderness and that the unselfish friend who had done all this had been Christoph Saur that; in a word, Christoph Saur had been the noblest German of them all, and had been most justly named 'the good Samaritan of Germantown.'"</p>
   <p>Doctor Maurer preceded his lecture by a briefly paying his respects to the memory of Bismarck. Yesterday was the anniversary of the great Chancellor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
