<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-12-02">Dec. 2, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">German Language Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0972</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0972.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-12-02">Dec. 2, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN LANGUAGE SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Prof. D. Martin Schuetze makes a fiery speech. The branch, Chicago of the General "German Language Society", held yesterday evening, in the Hotel Kaiserhaf, its second recital. The principal speaker of the evening was Prof. D. Martin Schuetze, of the University of Chicago. As a subject he choose, "Language and Race." He said among other things: "The modern consciousness of language originated only of late. It joins two powerful personalities of the second half of the 18th century. One is literary (Frederic the Great), the other political, (Herder), and in peculiar contrast. Frederic the Great, the despiser of the language for which he first had to lay the foundation of its rebirth. Herder, the father of Historical comprehensiveness, excelled in the clear, naive conception of the language. He perceived that a race does not mean the accidental grouping of people, on the basis of a voluntary treaty, or any external aims and labor, but that a race is founded by historical living conditions. A race, to him was the total personality, that possesses all the physical and mental characteristics which have developed under the influence of historical events and destiny, having an insoluble unity.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0973.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The language and poesy of the race won their modern rich value only through Herder. Since Herder, we have much deeper insight in the truth, that who ever attacks the language transgresses on the inner life of a race, that who ever wants to kill a race must first kill its language. The language is the clear stream, which like the blood in our body nourishes the spiritual existence. The language and with its language it decays, with it, it disappears from the circle of races.</p>
   <p>It is not a striking occurrence that Frederic the Great and Herder lived in the same age. They were the two greatest workers in the preparation of the modern history of the German race and language. Frederic the Great, on his part, did not fall like a shooting star from heaven. It was the pinnacle of a development which began imperceptibly at the time of Germany's greatest decay during the thirty years war, the development of the Brandenburg-Russian Idea.</p>
   <p>This idea started only with Frederic the Great's entrance into the history of large nations. The idea was further developed in the wars of liberty, the war of 1870-71, and now in the largest and most just, and so God will, the <pb facs="5418474_8_0974.jpg" n="3"/>most decisive of all wars, (The World War). The Russian political and Herder's literary ideas are now, through generations of the greatest cultural and indefatigable work done in sweat and faith, in blood an iron welded into German ideas. Germany is here, as everywhere else, the first race educator. The history of all European races in the last hundred years is the history of the reawakening of the race states, the unity of race language and of the state. Germany is fighting now for this idea against seemingly crushing superior forces of human beings and money, and above everything else against the offspring of meanness, which puts all the fiends of history deeply in the shadow, the organized lies. But Germany possess the courage, strength, ethical force. The whole of Germany is one soul. But how does it stand with us millions of German blood, German language and German mind, as in America? We are citizens of another country. We accepted political ideals, we gave ourselves to duties, which we must and will observe loyally. Our children are born here. We are grown together with a hundred deeds of work, friendship, love and duty, and the honest conviction in the present and don't let us forget, in the future of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
