<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-11-10">November 10, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Praise of the German Press.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0514</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0514.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-11-10">November 10, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">PRAISE OF THE GERMAN PRESS.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We received a telegram from Philadelphia that the Evangelical-Lutheran pastor, George von Bosse, a famous explorer, took the opportunity to make a remarkable speech about the German press in America. The worthy divine illustrated the work done in these hard times by the German-American press and closes with the words: "And our thanks must consist that everybody who is able to read German should take a German paper. Excuses and grumbling should cease. It does not matter that the German paper once in a report omitted a name, or in this or another article expressed a view which did not please the reader, but it must be conceded that the German paper intercedes for the German people of which we are a part and therefore it is our duty to support her. This can best be done if we take the paper, not borrow it from our neighbor but subscribe to it. In this manner we assist her to soar and gain power with which the English press has to reckon. The German-American press is worthy of our support and we certainly owe her our support."</p>
   <p>As grateful as we are to Pastor Bosse for his acknowledgment, we cannot endorse the concluding sentence of his speech. It is impossible to think of <pb facs="5418474_8_0515.jpg" n="2"/>supporting the German press in order to pay a debt for past and future services. Such a "support" would not help the German press nor the German nationality to obtain the necessary powers. The Germans in America should be awakened not to the support of the German press but to the recognition of the necessity of a German press. The German newspaper must become a necessity of the Germans in America, an item of the household, like the bed on which he accumulates the strength for next day's work, or the bath in which he cleans himself of the accumulated dirt. And not only in times of need when he must have a friend but also in times of peace when he desires the German newspaper as a friend.</p>
   <p>The German newspapers in this country have, with but few exceptions, done superhuman work since the beginning of the war. We may point with proud satisfaction to the fact that this paper in the fight for truth always stood in the front ranks, and intends to hold this place also in the future. We forego all rewards, but we wish that every German in Chicago in his own as well as the interests of all Germans, acknowledge that this paper is a necessity. In this alone lies the recognition of this paper and its right to exist.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
