<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-05-24">May 24, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Meeting of the German-American Historical Society.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0414</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0414.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-05-24">May 24, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE MEETING OF THE GERMAN-AMERICAN HISTORICAL SOCIETY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5.. The newly founded German-American Historical Society of Illinois met for the first time last night. Responding to invitations, many guests were present. The success with which the evening was crowned, inspired Mr. William Vocke, the president of the association to announce that social evenings which will combine humor and instruction are planned by the society. The meeting was exceptienally well attended, with due appreciation to the ladies.</p>
   <p>In his speech, Mr. Vocke pointed out that the association not only welcomes the help it receives from the ladies but it depends upon it to a large extent. According to the secretary's report, the membership of this new society, founded only two months ago, is already 154. Many more persons, a large number of ladies included, joined the society after the close of the meeting.</p>
   <p>The speakers of the evening were Messrs. William Vocke, E. Mannhardt and E. F. L. Gauss. Mr. Vocke explained the aim of the society, of which the most essential points were the following:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0415.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"When the large area of the of the Northwest Territory was given its constitution in the year 1787, the pioneers of the West settled in those as yet inaccessible states. A strong contingent of Germans joined those pioneers, and every German should be proud of their participation in spreading culture, as well as their work in colonizing and their influence upon the character of a nation in the making. Only one hundred years ago, these pioneers lived in deadly fear of the blood-thirsty Indians, being forced to live close to the military posts for the sake of protection.</p>
   <p>"At the present time, the state of Illinois has 4,000,000 inhabitants, 50 percent of them living in Chicago. Educational and art institutions have been erected throughout the state. In view of the fact that the population of Illinois is 30 percent German, the question arises; Did the German element contribute toward the development of the state in the same proportion, as did the elements of various other nationalities? Did German immigration raise or lower the stamina of the American nation? And finally, have these Germans stood faithfully by when their adopted country was most in need of them?</p>
   <p>"To investigate these, and to search for true facts, is the sole aim of this <pb facs="5418474_8_0416.jpg" n="3"/>organization. But it may safely be stated, that German culture, although not always readily accepted, is pushing its way through. German prominence in the field of science, trade and industry in this country, and especially in Illinois, is not to be denied.</p>
   <p>"The German farmer is undeniably a great blessing to his adopted country. He brought about the transformation of the barren western states, now rich in agricultural beauty. But the greatest service which German immigration has rendered to this country is the German spirit and sentiment which have planted itself deeply in the national character of America.</p>
   <p>"And what influence did German music have upon the soul of the American nation! All of these spur us on, toward a thorough investigation of the history of the German Americans of Illinois. The records of this investigation will be preserved in the archives for lasting remembrance of German contribution in the development of Illinois."</p>
   <p>Mr. E. Mannhardt, the secretary of the society, then explained that the society will issue a monthly magazine for the benefit of the members.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0417.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Highly interesting was the sketch of the 19th century immigrant. To give it more color, the lecturer used material, which was loaned him by the descendants of those pioneers. He pictured the dreadful hardships those people suffered and said that the soil of this state was enriched not only by the sweat of their brow but also by the heart's blood of the German immigrant. It is the duty of the present German-American generation, to erect a monument to those martyrs.</p>
   <p>Mr. E. F. L. Gauss pointed out that as long as a country is in a stats of development, no society is more important than the historical society. It is the duty of every self-respecting German-American of Illinois to keep alive the memory of the part taken by their fathers in the development of this country. This is an urgent plea, because the attempt has already been made, to deprive our pioneers of the honors due them for their accomplishments.</p>
   <p>It is the duty of every German-American to interest himself in the German-American society of Illinois. The speaker appealed to the women, the mothers of the world, to lend their assistance and thus promote the work undertaken.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
