<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1924-08-03">Aug. 3, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">American Welfare Association for German Children</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1752</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1752.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1924-08-03">Aug. 3, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN WELFARE ASSOCIATION FOR GERMAN CHILDREN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have received the following communication from the Institution for the Feeble-minded and Epileptics in Alsterdorf, Germany: "The Red Cross sent us a donation, an original contribution by Mrs. B. Kment, and one from Mrs. Kempf of Chicago, for which we are very grateful. Our institutions in Alsterdorf were established sixty years ago. They have been dedicated to the care of the feeble-minded, epileptics and cripples, stressing education, and creating interest in an occupation in as far as individual cases permit. In promoting this work, we always had to depend upon donations. The War, and the following years played havoc with our financial condition, and, although, one notes a general monetary improvement, we are still very much dependent, upon the help of true philantropists.....</p>
   <p>Originating in a private home, where four idiotic children were cared for, the institution expanded until there are nearly one thousand inmates....We hope that the humanitarian work can continue.... May God give His blessings."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1753.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>C. Krisser, director.</p>
   <p>Sister Anne Marie Wenzel investigated the following cases and evokes the aid of benevolently inclined people .....</p>
   <p>Wilhelm Winkler, Berlin,.... formerly a rich manufacturer in Petersburg, (Petrograd, Russia,) where his family lived as foreigners - Germans, lost everything. Was held as a prisoner. Parents in delicate health; children suffering.</p>
   <p>A professor of an academy, wife and two children, on the verge of starvation .... Mac Lean, architect in the Government's employ, and eleven children of school age in distress. Has no income, because building operations are practically at a standstill.</p>
   <p>The wife of the Councillor of the Board of Health .... eight persons destitute.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1754.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A divorced young mother, and four dependent children; Doctor Manitius, theologian, and wife .... are also listed.</p>
   <p>The latter was given help recently, as I had been notified of his plight. His profound gratitude was heart-rending.</p>
   <p>The American Welfare Association accepts donations for all these unfortunates who must suffer through no fault of their own. 128 North La Salle Street, Room 47, Phone: Franklin 0339.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
