<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-07-03">July 3, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Marksmen's (Sharpshooter's) Festival.</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Chicago Marksmen's Club Meets the New Yorkers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1344</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1344.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-07-03">July 3, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE MARKSMEN'S (SHARPSHOOTER'S) FESTIVAL.</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Chicago Marksmen's Club Meets The New Yorkers.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the Schuetzen Park of the Chicago Schuetzenverein, could be heard the detonations of rifles - and of champagne bottles. The International Columbian Prize-Shooting and Bowling tournament, which the Chicago Club arranged in honor of the World's Fair, induced the internationally known Independent New York Marksmen's Association to make a trip to Chicago, for the dual purpose of seeing the exposition and acquiring a few additional medals.... From the moment that the cannon-shot signaled the commencement of the contest, until the tolling of the bell at six, every target was in use, and whoever was not at the range found company at the tables among the brother and sister marksmen where toasts were drunk to the guests.</p>
   <p>New York was not the only contributor. Milwaukee sent representatives, Toledo (Ohio) had two; the president of the Joliet Marksmen's Club, Mr. Sehring, also participated in the prize shooting yesterday, and during the afternoon, Mr. William Ehrenpfost of San Francisco arrived. He is an honorary member of the New York Association.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1345.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At 10 o'clock yesterday the merry crowd had gathered at the Pan-Handle Station, Canal and Madison Streets. The members of the local club and the out of town guests turned out in unexpected numbers, so that the regular train had to add two extra coaches.</p>
   <p>The contest began at eleven o'clock. Before the cannon summoned the riflemen to their posts, however, they were greeted with a song by the Kreutzer quartette. After several hours of ardent, if not arduous work, the men congregated at the horseshoe shaped tables and proved that they also could excel in eloquence when the occasion required it.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ambrose Andree, well known president of the Chicago Schuetzen-Verein, greeted the New York guests, during the repast, in the name of our local association. Mr. W. V. Weber, captain of the New York Independents, replied in behalf of his own club. He congratulated his Chicago comrades upon their genial idea in giving them this opportunity to see the "Fair" and also combine with it this contest in honor of Columbus and he closed his speech with the trite, yet always most welcome reminder: "Boys, let us have a drink!"....</p>
   <p>Capt. Weber who has done much in behalf of the cause was given a surprise. <pb facs="5418474_8_1346.jpg" n="3"/>He suffers from eye strain and therefore was not a participant; nevertheless he deserves the Columbia medal, and so it was pinned to his lapel by Mr. Albert Boese, acting secretary of the festival, amid the jubilant acclaim of the multitude.... Mr. Carl Graeff, president of the Bingen Marksmen's Club, who also is an honorary member of the New York Association, came from Germany to be present at this convivial convocation, where he has become conversant with German-American accomplishments.</p>
   <p>After the final dinner course the proud, confirmed bachelor made an eloquent address in which he gave due praise to the ladies. At 6 o'clock shooting was discontinued; it will be resumed today.... Secretary Boese has not as yet computed all the scores, but we can confidently assert that nearly every one of the New York marksmen earned the golden medal.</p>
   <p>It was surprising not to find Gustav Zimmermann, the "Champion of the World," at yesterday's meeting. He admits confidently, that he will remain for another week and take in the sights of the Midway at the "Fair" and he will not compete, until he has seen the exposition. By that time his eagerness will have subsided and his hands will not be so restive....</p>
   <p>New York sent from 40 to 50 participants, many of whom were accompanied by <pb facs="5418474_8_1347.jpg" n="4"/>their wives. Mr. Diettrich, editor of the Marksmen's Journal (Schuetzen-zeitung), was one of the guests. For this evening a social meeting has been arranged.</p>
   <p>The Chicago and New York clubs will be entertained at the Columbia, 130 S. Clark Street, President Andree's place. The "Independents" leave on Tuesday and intend to celebrate the fourth of July in Milwaukee, Wisconsin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
