<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-08-01">Aug. 1, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">One Hundred Years of German Gymnastics in America.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1222</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1222.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-08-01">Aug. 1, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF GERMAN GYMNASTICS IN AMERICA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In these days when thousands of American gymnasts are sojourning in Germany, while in Cologne-on-the-Rhine, where a large gymnastic festival has just ended, it will be of interest to review the development of German gymnastics in the United States.</p>
   <p>One hundred years ago, Karl Beck, with his translation of Jahn's "German Gymnastic Skill," inculcated the idea of gymnastics into the American people. His work served as guide in private schools. As the founders of German gymnastics in America, besides Karl Beck, Karl Follen and Franz Lieber must also be mentioned. They were young German scholars, who were driven to America by the political storms in their homeland. All three of them were political friends of Jahn and ardent gymnasts. They were also highly educated, enthusiastic men, and capable of realizing their aim in this country.</p>
   <p>Jahn's ideas meant a great deal to America. Just as without Jahn's gymnastic ideals the German war of liberation could not have been fought, so the Civil War could not have been won without the German gymnasts, the pupils of Jahn.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1223.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Gymnastics were taught for the first time in the year 1825 by Karl Beck the neighborhood of the Round Hill School in Northampton, Mass. This therefore can be considered as the first gymnastic school in America. example of Round Hill was followed by Yale and Amherst in the following year.</p>
   <p>Little was heard for a long time of German gymnastics; the three brave pioneers had to restrict their activities. Then help arrived! Every new year brought more and more fugitives to America. Young patriots and famous scholars set foot on the shores of the Republic. They all wanted to promote the German gymnastic system.</p>
   <p>In 1848 the first German Turnverein was founded by the famous fighter for independence, Frederic Hecker. Foundations in New York, St. Louis and Chicago followed, and two years later, the organization of individual societies was so far advanced, that they were able to form the North American Turnerbund. This mighty organization still existing today, is composed of 195 societies with 35,000 members.</p>
   <p>The German Turners in America remained true to their principles. From the very beginning they advocated individual liberty, physical training, and <pb facs="5418474_8_1224.jpg" n="3"/>political and social progress. Their Turner societies were, at the same time, educational institutions. Inestimable is the influence which the German Turner exercised upon the Americans.</p>
   <p>The magnificent gymnasia and playgrounds, in almost every large city of America, are the results of propaganda by the German gymnasts. But not only physical and moral development of its youth does this country owe to the Turners. The German regiments which fought for the Union during the Civil War were mostly composed of Turners.</p>
   <p>After the war, the development of the German gymnastic system received a fresh impetus. In the year 1869, a German gymnastic teachers' seminary was founded. Until 1907 it was connected with a similar institution in Milwaukee, but it was afterwards transferred to Indianapolis.</p>
   <p>Although the admission of young Americans gradually led to the disappearance of the typical German Turnverein, the ideals of Jahn will forever remain impressed on the minds of thousands of Americans. Of all the German establishments in America, the American Turner federation will endure the longest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
