<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-04-20">April 20, 1878</date><title level="a">The Business Situation of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0598</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0598.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1878-04-20">April 20, 1878</date><title level="a">THE BUSINESS SITUATION OF THE ILLINOIS STAATS-ZEITUNG.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Editor of the Freie Presse (Free Press) has been brought to court by one attorney for spreading the rumor that one newspaper is nearing a state of bankruptcy.</p>
   <p>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung was forced after the great Chicago Fire to build its own establishment and therewith, like so many concerns, had to borrow money at 10% interest from a Chicago Bank.</p>
   <p>The excellent business standing of our newspaper has been used by our lawyer as a sound and fundamental argument, to obtain for us a lower interest for our debt through some acceptable transaction.</p>
   <p>One lawyer's various negotiations with banks doubtless leaked out and tempted the Freie Presse to suspect a weak standing of our financial capability. As a fact our business affairs never have been more prosperous thanright now, and we are expecting a steady expansion of our circulation. Based on this <pb facs="5418474_8_0599.jpg" n="2"/>favorable state of affairs, we have finally succeeded in stablizing our debt on sound bonds at 8% interest. This favorable transaction in conjunction with our bank has naturally increased and solidified our credit and expansion capacity.</p>
   <p>The payment of our bills, salaries and running expenses has not stopped a minute during the described transaction. This fact has been completely ignored in these mentioned rumors, which we are clearing now in court.</p>
   <p>In the meantime we call our readers' attention to the fact that the Illinois Staats-Zeitung has the largest circulation of all German newspapers west of the Allegheny Mountains.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
