<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-05-09">May 9, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The German Demonstration Was a Great Success.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1728</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1728.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-05-09">May 9, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN DEMONSTRATION WAS A GREAT SUCCESS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The great charity concert for the benefit of the destitute and sick German immigrants which was held yesterday at the De Paul auditorium, turned into a great German demonstration. A fine concert started the well attended celebration. The artists were greatly applauded.</p>
   <p>Especially interesting were the performance of the charming dancer Helen Junteg of the Uptown theater, who exhibited several solo dances. She was accompanied on the piano by the well known pianist Mrs. Engle-Lidge, who also played the 14th Rhapsody by Lizt. Many other excellent performances were offered, A procession took place after the conclusion of the concert.</p>
   <p>Counsel Michael F. Girten, president of the German Club, made a speech in which he mentioned the charitable enterprises of the German-Americans, and presented to Dr. Jack W. Kobalter, president of the United Austro-Hungarian Societies of North America the honorary degree of the Union of Expatriated Germans.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1729.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Pastor Alfred Mayer held the festival speech. He pointed to "Mother's Day" and reminded the assembly of mother Germania. Anyone who reveres his mother should remember her especially in time of need. The speaker urged loyalty to the German language and described the duties of the Germans living abroad. Especially did he emphasize the refutation of lies concerning the origins of the World War.</p>
   <p>Dr. Kobalter then thanked the audience for its attendance. He mentioned his activities in behalf of the Germans living abroad and regretted not to be able to reward everyone who had given his support. The official part of the evening closed with the singing of the American and the German National hymns.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
