<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1899-08-18">Aug. 18, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">The German Press Club of Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0530</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0530.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1899-08-18">Aug. 18, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN PRESS CLUB OF CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At last a German Press Club has also been founded in this city. Chicago is second only to New York in the number of its German inhabitants; its German newspapers, although so highly developed, as in no other western city, have found attempts to form a Press Club among the German-American newspaper writers, futile. The necessity for a well organized alliance of all German-American journalists, may be summarized as follows:</p>
   <p>The German-American Press is still in an early stage of development, regardless of the various individual achievements; consequently, the class consciousness, which animates the purpose and is at the foundation of the National Alliance, has not manifested itself sufficiently among the German groups. It is the aim of the new organization to arouse and develop this comradeship. The more numerous the colleagues, who see in the practice of journalism, only an auxiliary means of support, who follow the vocation because of necessity and, therefore, are hardly able to renounce their own conceptions, the more is required in the <pb facs="5418474_8_0531.jpg" n="2"/>interests of the professional journalists, that we recognize the lofty calling and the identical ideals which confront all of us, who dedicate our mental and physical powers to the service of the German press. We must concentrate our efforts in one direction, that of having practically all German journalists affiliated with the National Alliance, either directly or by becoming members of future local clubs, and, if necessary, to support this work by supplying the needed time and money. We must not Stint. The exclamation of the poet is especially applicable among the German-American newspaper writers: "Let your ambitions be directed towards a complete work and if you are not able to succeed in your goal, then attach yourself as an assisting member to a finished product!"</p>
   <p>If the National Alliance will include the German-American journalists within the near future, then it will be possible to properly promote the interests of the profession in an adequate manner, and it will preclude the possibility that our standard of mental work will be degraded to the level of the day laborer or tradesman. We do not have the slightest feeling of animosity towards the publishers, or wish to antagonize them, we intend, however, to prove to the publishers, that it is to their interests, since their intellectual co-workers are excluded from proletarianism to aid them to reach that respected social position which best enables them to fulfill their difficult and responsible duties. In no other <pb facs="5418474_8_0532.jpg" n="3"/>branch is such complete harmony among capital and labor so easily obtained as in the newspaper business if only a mutual will and correct understanding are aroused.</p>
   <p>The meager, material reimbursement, which the German-American writer obtains, as a rule, practically precludes the possibility, that he can save sufficiently for an adverse period. One of the noblest duties of these associations consists in he helping the individual when the occasion makes it imperative. The second stipulation of our National Alliance intends to provide for a large found from which disbursements may be drawn for impecunious members, such as widows and orphans of German-American journalists. What has been realized in Germany and Austria by several large clubs, the Concordia, for instance, also the Berlin Press Club, Schiller Association, etc., only two years ago, should not be so difficult of attainment in this wealthy nation. America.</p>
   <p>In retrospection: the success of the New York German Press Club may be duplicated by following its general principles. When the by-laws were drafted, particular stress was laid on the fact, that they should coincide with the rules of the National Alliance, since the German Press Club is to be affiliated with it. In the main the provisions are: To further the interests and elevate the status of <pb facs="5418474_8_0533.jpg" n="4"/>its members by co-operation; To support destitute members, likewise their widows and orphans, in accordance with available funds.</p>
   <p>The club consists of ordinary, estra-ordinary and honorary members. Voting privileges, and requests for support apply only to the ordinary members.</p>
   <p>Extra-ordinary members belong to the following classes: Newspaper publishers, provided that they are not writers in which event they would be eligible as ordinary members; book-publishers, and such persons, whose vocations are definitely linked with the progress of the press and literature.</p>
   <p>Eminent exponents in literature, art and science, may be accepted as honorary members. Voting and requests for assistance are permissable only to the ordinary members.</p>
   <p>Fees for ordinary members are $4.00. for initiation and $.50 monthly. This includes the contribution to the National Alliance. Besides the regular dues, each newly accepted member shall pay $1.00 for the death fund of the National <pb facs="5418474_8_0534.jpg" n="5"/>Alliance. Extra-ordinary members pay $10.00 upon initiation and $3.00 quarterly.</p>
   <p>Honorary Members pay no fees of any kind. If an unemployed member refuses to accept a position which the employment bureau of the Alliance has obtained, then the Alliance's support may be withdrawn by a majority resolution.</p>
   <p>Assistance shall be given only for a quarter ear, except in special cases. . Resignations and customary business procedures do not differ very much from those of other clubs and therefore are not of general interest; they are therefore omitted here. Representatives of all local German publications were present.</p>
   <p>The election results were as follows: Theo. Janssen, President; Dr. Max Henius, Vice-President, F. Glogauer, Treasurer, and four others Permanent headquarters will be considered at the next meeting. It will be the pride of the members to promote true concordance in their future home, that the German Press Club may grow and thrive!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
