<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-09-05">September 5th, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Altgeld Memorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1617</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1617.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I V</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-09-05">September 5th, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Altgeld Memorial.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The "John P. Altgeld Memorial Association" is going to have several brass plates put on the tombstone of the former Governor. On these brass-plates will be citations from his speeches and writings. These plates were unveiled yesterday at the Garrick Theater, where a large crowd of Altgeld's friends were assembled. The Chairman of this meeting was D. L. Cruice.</p>
   <p>The address for the occasion was given by G. F. Williams, Other speeches were held by Rev. T. E. Cox, W. E. Clark, and L. Merriweather of St. Louis. Appropriate songs by the Men's Choir of the Sinai Gongregation added to the diginity of the occasion. After this followed the unveiling of brass-tablets by Miss Oris Gottlieb.</p>
   <p>The inscriptions upon the tablets are characteristic of Mr. Altgeld's attitude and standpoint in public life. One of the inscriptions is taken from a writing of his, in which he explained the reasons for setting free the anarchists, Schwab, Fielden and Neebe. Another inscription is taken from the letter addressed to Grover <pb facs="5418474_8_1618.jpg" n="2"/>Cleveland, in which he protested against the use of national guards during the Pullman strikes. It reads: "The teaching that might is right has caused only misery upon earth. In crushing the weak, it also ruins the strong. Sooner or later every cruelty, every injustice, every deceit reacts destructively upon the one committing them. Justice is moral health and produces happiness. Injustice is a moral disease and causes moral death."</p>
   <p>The following notation is pointed against those who are afraid to take a definite st nd: "People who keep neutral, who are willing to compromise and those who can be swayed in matters of justice and right, have never changed social evils and bad conditions. They have never maintained or introduced liberal institutions; not have they ever fought for human rights."</p>
   <p>Reconciliatory and full of hope sounds the last of these citations;"I am not discouraged. Things will adjust themselves. The pendulum swings first to one and then to the other extreme, but the force of gravity always pulls it back to the center. Every building must be erected in straight lines, in order to stand. The <pb facs="5418474_8_1619.jpg" n="3"/>same is true of nations. Sometimes it may appear, that unrighteousness is triumphant and justice suffers defeat, but the force of gravity governing true justice is anchored to the throne of God. Political and social institutions must be in line with eternal justice in order to endure."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
