<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-09-11">Sept. 11, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Turner Society Celebrates its 75th Anniversary.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1228</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1228.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-09-11">Sept. 11, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO TURNER SOCIETY CELEBRATES ITS 75TH ANNIVERSARY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Turner Society, the oldest Turner society of Chicago and one of the oldest organization of the city, is preparing the celebration of its 75th diamond jubilee festival on Oct. 2nd. The celebration will last four days, namely from Oct 2nd to October 5th.</p>
   <p>In a historical festival play episodes of the history of the Turner society will be reproduced....The first part of the four main scenes of the festival play will represent the founding of the Turner society of Chicago, the inaugural ceremony of the first Turner hall on Griswold Street (now La Salle Street,) the brilliant festival ball with ladies wearing the styles of those times.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1229.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Well known characters such as Garl Stone, Emil Dietsch, Dr. Ernst Schmid, Casper Butz, Lorenz Brentano, Casper Hesing, will be called back to life in this performance.</p>
   <p>The second scene will represent the Civil War. Lincoln's "Call to Arms," the enlistment of the Turners, Mayor Wentworth's speech, and the presentation of his pistol to the captain because he himself could not go.</p>
   <p>The third scene will stage the great Chicago Fire of 1871; Turner Hall in flames; the dance of the "Flame-Ghosts," with music; Chicago Singverein singing the great "Fire Song" by Max Bruch from Schillers "Bell." Turners forming a safety council, - the Illinois Staats-Zeitung building burning down....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1230.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the fourth scene the rebuilding of Chicago closes the play. It represents the rebuilding of the Turner Hall.</p>
   <p>The future appears in a rosy light. Youth looks on in confidence, and promises to keep up the good cause. Turners compete in graceful exercises. A poetically beautiful epilogue with music, brings this wonderful "Pageant" to a splendid conclusion...</p>
   <p>The musical part of this program has been entrusted to Mr. William Boeppler. The costumes will be furnished by Minna Schmidt.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
