<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-19">Mar. 19, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">(An Evening Edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung).</title><title level="a" type="sub">To the Germans of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0541</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0541.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-03-19">Mar. 19, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">(AN EVENING EDITION OF THE ILLINOIS STAATS-ZEITUNG).</title><title level="a" type="sub">TO THE GERMANS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Germans in Chicago have a right to demand accurate and complete information regarding current events. From the beginning of Chicago's existence they have contributed a large share to the growth of the city. German labor and capital have been steadily increasing, and all ranks of the German population have taken an active part in public affairs. It is, therefore, easy to understand that they wish to be informed about news as soon as possible....</p>
   <p>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung is, therefore, of the opinion that its plans to publish an evening edition beginning March 27, in addition to their regular publications, will meet with the approval of the whole German population of Chicago and vicinity.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0542.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The evening edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung will be available for one cent per copy. This edition will be equal to the morning edition, the most widely circulated German newspaper of the West. It will contain a complete news service, covering the United States and foreign countries. It will also carefully publish local events. Thus it will offer a very desirable supplement. The evening paper will be a real newspaper - which in a very short time will be admitted into every German family.</p>
   <p>We trust we can depend upon all the German clubs and societies to support us in this undertaking. We have made arrangements so that the paper can be purchased at all the news-stores of Chicago, or orders can be placed with all the delivery boys of the Staats-Zeitung.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
