<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-05-30">May 30, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">The 29Th Day of May</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-07">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-05-30">May 30, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">THE 29TH DAY OF MAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Never has it been more evident than yesterday that the German population is an inseparable part of the American nation. Because the celebration that was dedicated to the German victory, the German unification and the European peace safeguarded by them, was not only a German, but a general celebration....Here it was not a question of scanty concessions of individual city offices as public institutions...All banks were closed, the stock market celebrated, the Federal offices, the courts, the post, the municipal authorities had announced that they would regard the German peace celebration as a national holiday. The City Hall was adorned from the dome downward with German and American flags. In short it was a holiday not for the Germans only, but for the whole population.</p>
   <p>All fears that the parade (like former ones) would make a poor, pathetic <pb facs="5418474_8_0250.jpg" n="2"/>and meaningless impression, or would be abused for shoddy advertising, were happily confounded. The parade of the 29th surpassed the highest expectations and Chicago in future need not be afraid in regard to German demonstrations of any comparison with New York.</p>
   <p>....The American politician may only have been impressed by the numerical size of Chicago German-don, and may have told himself how stupid it would be to overlook the unified German vote. But the American thinker will have seen more than that. He will have told himself that a people of so striking an individuality and so conscious of it, cannot dissolve in the English and Celtic mixed race but sooner or later will conquer recognition.</p>
   <p>Because the world believed that the German wanted peace only, not also his rights and his honor, therefore it has mocked him as the "German Michel". But this German Michel has exercised the superhuman strength of an archangel Michael and with quick, tremendous blows has shattered the empire of lies, of deception, of hypocrisy, of flossed-over barbarism, and painted prostitution. Very well the German in America, too, may have been a sleeping Michel;- <pb facs="5418474_8_0251.jpg" n="3"/>but he may and shall wake up as a Saint Michael and shall crush with a strong arm the powers of darkness, that is the Welsh-dom ("Walscht-hum" might be translated as Welsh race or nation, but "Walsch" means also a moral quality; the latter meaning is influenced and characterized by the phonetic resemblance of "walsch" and "falsch" - falsch meaning false) of American that here, too, tries to enthrone scarcely veiled barbarism in the place of civilization, showy ostentation in that of right, and shameless glittering dishonesty in that of moral decency.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
