<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-10-21">Oct. 21, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">German Press Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0453</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0453.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-10-21">Oct. 21, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN PRESS SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After the monthly business meeting, which the German Press Society held yesterday evening at the Bismarck Hotel, the yearly meeting followed. Then, as always on this occasion, a large number of members were present, who were ready to discuss several important questions. The German Press Club, as it is commonly called, exists since 1908, but as should be expected, under present conditions, it has not a large active membership. The Abendpost, Eintracht, and the Heimatbote are represented.</p>
   <p>So far as total membership is concerned, this society, naturally, also had to suffer from the disfavor of the times, which can be noticed from the number of members. Close connections it was proposed, should be entered in with the technical and commercial societies, and stress should be laid upon the necessity <pb facs="5418474_8_0454.jpg" n="2"/>of friendly relations between these three societies. President Karl R. Freitag could only report, that the society had a quiet year behind it. The business meetings were regularly held, but there were no special events, which had to be debated.</p>
   <p>The yearly report of the treasurer, A. Danneberg, showed that the amount of the cash on hand at the close of the year remained the same as before. It was pointed out, that the usual festival, which the society arranges every year, closed for the first time with a surplus. As there was no unexpected larger expenditures to meet, such as were caused last year by several deaths, it was not difficult for the society to meet its obligations.</p>
   <p>In the yearly report of the financial secretary, H. A. Gammert, details were given about the number of members. The society lost, through death, an active member, its president and later honorary president for many years, Mr. Paul F. Mueller; it also lost another of its most active members, <pb facs="5418474_8_0455.jpg" n="3"/>Mr. Martin Ballmann, who as second vice president and as president of the amusement committee prominently worked in the interest of the society. These two deaths and the resignation of a number of other members, reduced the membership to sixty-five; twenty-two active and forty-two passive members, and one honorary member, one of the founders of the society, who for a number of years has now been living in Germany.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
