<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-08-21">Aug. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The German Press in the United States</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0482</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0482.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-08-21">Aug. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN PRESS IN THE UNITED STATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Four hundred and ninety-nine German language newspapers and periodicals of various kinds were published in the United States in 1918, according to Ayer's Directory of Newspapers and Periodicals. During the War the German language press had to cope with many difficulties. At that time newspapers suspended publication, and at present only three hundred and forty-four newspapers and periodicals are being published. In some cases German papers ceased publication temporarily, for the duration of the War, with the intention of resuming operations at a more favorable time. Ten papers which formerly were issued in German now appear in English, and some papers which formerly were "all German," are now part English and part German. Twenty-nine of the three hundred and forty-four German papers are dailies; the others are weeklies, monthlies, bi-weeklies or bi-monthlies. Included in this number of newspapers and periodicals are also scientific papers and publications which circulate only among certain religious, professional, or fraternal organizations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0483.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The disappearance of so many German language newspapers does not mean that the number of readers has been correspondingly reduced. It is a well-known fact that the agents of the surviving publications solicit subscribers among the readers of the publications which have suspended circulation. Since the Armistice was signed, reports that German newspapers are being established or resuming operations have come from various parts of our country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
