<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-10-24">October 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Year Book of the Germans in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0690</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0690.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-10-24">October 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">YEAR BOOK OF THE GERMANS IN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As a beginning and promise, the first Year Book of the Germans in Chicago appeared a year ago. As an accomplishment and a comprehensive work, the second attractively bound volume presents itself to its readers.</p>
   <p>Even before the war, the thought had been formulated to retain all the most important occurrences of a strong population complex such as the Germans here in Chicago. That the plan was not carried out, is a new proof of German self-sufficiency, which does not set itself aims, and therefore, does not have to fight. But since the beginning of the war, a vital necessity has arisen which has forced us to collect our own experiences and activities for these big events.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0691.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The war became a purgatory for German-Americans, in which they were stripped of all weakness and so could fight against insinuations and baseless in-citations.</p>
   <p>In regard to the actions of the Germans of Chicago, as members of the German race and as citizens of the United States, the interest for a summary of their actions, which offered a yearly survey, arose.</p>
   <p>If Dr. Singer deserves to be honored, to have filled with his Year Book a tender space in the intellectual life of the Germans, therefore, nobody but him is more justified and eligible to finish the chronology of the war year.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0692.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That the majority of the German people discovered themselves again, goes to the credit of Dr. Singer, his incessant warning to unite, to shake off indifference, cowardice and weakness, and wage an energetic battle for the ideals of their race, as well as against the feigned and perfidious actions of the government on the question of neutrality.</p>
   <p>From mere spectators to direct participants in the gigantic struggle of Germany against hostile superior forces, nothing could have been more welcome, than a revival of almost forgotten words and deeds sacred to the memories of Chicago Germans.</p>
   <p>Therefore,for the sake of memories of great hours of trials and tribulations and sufferings of the Chicago Germans, the Year Book of 1916 should be owned by every German.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0693.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is but natural that this year the Year Book is greatly influenced with events in connection with the war but, nevertheless, it contains an abundance of the life and endeavors of the Germans of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The excellent article of Prof. Goebel about the revival of "Knownothingism" showing a parallel between the narrow minded senselessness of 1850, and the present "Anti-Hyphen-Fever," will find sympathy; also the well thought out, careful opinions of Horace L. Brand's "The Future of German-Americanism in Chicago."</p>
   <p>Dr. Otto Gunether's charming memories of the visit of Mirza Schaffz's in America, which belongs to the past, also the reminiscences "Of Olden Times" by Francis J. Dewes, which are both very interesting.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0694.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Then back again to the present times, of Dr. Singer's contributions of "German Stage Life and the German Theater in Chicago", which apart from their cultural historical value, arose the pleasant understanding of the local reaction of German muses in Chicago, are extraordinarily interesting reading.</p>
   <p>We became acquainted with the struggle and creative achievements of the Germans in Chicago, about their activities in political, religious, spiritual and economical spheres.</p>
   <p>The exceedingly clear and instructing details about the Germans in economic life of Chicago, about the Lutheran and Evangelical church synods, the German-American national federation, the German representatives of the Democratic and Republican parties, the Columbia Ladies Society, the German Historical Society, and the Germanistic Society of Chicago, are <pb facs="5418474_8_0695.jpg" n="6"/>proofs of the many-sidedness of this excellent volume, which represents a proud German-American cultural document.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
