<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-03-10">March 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Professor Henderson.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1052</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1052.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-03-10">March 10, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Professor Henderson.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Professor Charles Raymond Henderson gave last night at the Fullerton Hall of the Art Institute a lecture on German Socialism. The lecture was sponsored by the Germanistic Society and was supposed to be spoken in German. At the last minute, Prof. Henderson was advised to lecture in English, which he did.</p>
   <p>The World has been inclined to believe, Professor Henderson said, that German Socialism, as practiced by the German government, has been merely an experimental political campaign, to forestall a German revolution. This foreign standpoint is absolutely wrong.</p>
   <p>While German industry and commerce was growing into gigantic proportions, the German government, with a broadminded understanding for the working classes, has not been idle and continuously studied the relations of Capital and Labor.</p>
   <p>Business and Industry in Germany, like anywhere else, had the right and <pb facs="5418474_8_1053.jpg" n="2"/>financial means, to organize and herewith dictate the prices for any kind of products and merchandise. The outcome of this organizing process were Chambers of Commerce, Trusts, Monopoly, Chainstore Systems, etc.</p>
   <p>To counteract the organized power of money, the German workers solidified their already existing Union system (Gewerkschafts-Verbande) State-Employee Societies (Beamten-Vereine( and Commercial Employee Societies (Kaufmanns-Angestellten-Vereine). Furthermore, in order to bring the prices of merchandise in easier reach of the poorer public, Comsumers' Associations (Consum Vereine) sprang up all over the, Reich.</p>
   <p>And still, the German workers, organized or not organized, were helpless in many directions to meet all situations in their growing struggle for existence. The German government felt its responsibility and duty, to step in and create the Government Invalid and Sick Benefit Institution Laws, which proved to be a blessing for the German people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
