<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-11">Dec. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Schuetzenverein</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annual Banquet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1269</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1269.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-11">Dec. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO SCHUETZENVEREIN</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annual Banquet</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anyone who has ever participated in the festivities of the Chicago Schuetzen-verein (Chicago Rifle Club) knows in advance that he is going to have the sort of good time which true huntsmen and marksmen enjoy. The untiring president of the Club, Judge George Kersten, who has been in the center of activities for years, always tries to show his club members a good time. This was also anticipated for the great ceremony of distributing prizes for accomplishments during the closing year, which was to take place yesterday in the Atlantic Hotel, but at the last moment word was received that Judge Kersten was confined in bed with a fever. This, naturally, put a damper on the festive spirit.</p>
   <p>A real riflemen's dinner was held, after which Dr. E. C. Sayre, master marksman, delivered an address to those present, encouraging them to take active <pb facs="5418474_8_1270.jpg" n="2"/>part in the shooting exercises in Palos Park. Dr. Sayre had contributed a splendid silver cup, which was won by Mr. Andreas Kolar. Secretary J. W. Weccard then gave a detailed report of the activities of the club during the past year, which was received with great applause. From his comments it could be learned that 130 members of the club had joined the colors, a fact which, naturally, was reflected at the shooting exercises. As the prizes were distributed, the following marksmen came out victorious:</p>
   <p>Charles Urban: First prize, military shooting in standing position, gold medal; second prize, military shooting in sitting position; second prize, military shooting in prone position; second prize, pistol shooting. The three last-mentioned prizes are silver medals.</p>
   <p>Andreas Kolar: First prize, target-rifle shooting, world record, gold medal; first prize, hunting rifle, gold medal; first prize, shooting in prone position, gold medal; second prize, military shooting in standing position, silver medal; <pb facs="5418474_8_1271.jpg" n="3"/>third prize, military shooting in sitting position, bronze medal; third prize, competitive shooting of novices, bronze medal.</p>
   <p>Walter Wolf: First prize, dummy target, 58 points; second prize, sporting match, 264 points.</p>
   <p>A. B. Snyder: First prize, ten-shot reentry, 228 points; first prize, king target, 330 points; first prize, military shooting in prone position, 265 points.</p>
   <p>Geo. W. Stockwell: First prize, prone position, military shooting, grade 3, 241 points.</p>
   <p>A. J. Huebner: First prize, union target, 71 points; second prize, competitive shooting with revolver, Class B, 101 points.</p>
   <p>Gustav Schweitzer: First prize, "Stichscheibe," 36 points; first prize, revolver shooting, 893 points. [Translator's note: I cannot find out what kind <pb facs="5418474_8_1272.jpg" n="4"/>of special target a "Stichscheibe" is.]</p>
   <p>Mrs. Walter Wolf, ladies' competitive shooting: First prize, hunting rifle, 47 points; first prize, novices' competitive shooting, 240 points.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
