<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-05-21">May 21, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">The Schuetzenfest.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1689</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1689.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1877-05-21">May 21, 1877</date>.
<title level="a">THE SCHUETZENFEST.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual opening of the Schuetzen Park, on the Pittsburgh, Cincinnati and St. Louis Railway, about a mile south of Washington Heights, took place yesterday, and was participated in by about 800 of Chicago's German citizens. The day was set apart for the purpose because it is that upon which Whit (Pfingst) Sunday fell. The weather was anything but propitious, but notwithstanding, the opening day was a success and passed off pleasantly to all who took part in the exercise.</p>
   <p>About 10 o'clock yesterday morning a procession composed as follows left Schuetzen Halle, on North Clark Street: Platoon of police, North Side TurnGemeinde, etc. etc.... The procession marched north on Clark Street to Chicago Avenue, west on Chicago Avenue to Wells Street, south on Wells Street to Ohio Street, east on Ohio to Clark Street, south on Clark to Randolph Street, west on Randolph to Clinton Street, and north to the Kinzie Street Depot, whence the excursionists embarked.</p>
   <p>Just after the procession started the rain poured down in torrents, and when the procession arrived at the depot the Turners and the Marshal and his aids <pb facs="5418474_8_1690.jpg" n="2"/>looked not unlike half-drowned rats. But this little inconvenience was quite forgotten in the foaming mug of lager and the hilarity which it occasioned. In good time the party arrived at the Park, where Schnitzel, Schinken, and other light edibles and much lager were done away with as repasts. The excursionists scattered about as they saw fit, but, as the grass was wet, the great hall formed the main attraction, and soon, amidst the strains of Strauss, merry dancers were whirling in the merry waltz.</p>
   <p>At 4 o'clock President John B. Gartenman introduced Mr. William Rapp, of the Staats-Zeitung, who made a happy speech, appropriate to the day and occasion. Prof. Honne showed how he could walk the tight rope. Shooting was indulged in by the Schuetzen Corps. The best shots at the union target were Schotter, etc. etc.... Taken as a whole, the opening was a success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
