<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-06-26">June 26, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Monument of the Anarchists a Solemn Unveiling in Waldheim Cemetery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1637</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1637.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-06-26">June 26, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE MONUMENT OF THE ANARCHISTS A SOLEMN UNVEILING IN WALDHEIM CEMETERY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Waldheim Cemetery, where the four executed anarchists August Spies, Adolph Fischer, George Engel, Albert Parsens and Louis Lingg, who committed suicide-are buried, the solemn unveiling of the Anarchists monument took place yesterday afternoon. A large crowd mostly working men of German, Polish and Bohemian nationality-was present. Many societies, clubs and unions appeared. The celebrations was preceded by a procession in the city, which ended without any disturbance. The "Pioneer aid and Support Association," whose President is Matthias Schmiedinger, had charge of the preparations. The march moved from Market Street Square on Madison Street to 5th Avenue and from there to the Northern Pacific R. R. Station on Harrison Street, from where the crowd was transported by trains to Weldheim. There in the vicinity of the monument a speakers' stand was erected. Mr. Schmiedinger opened the unveiling celebration with a short speech, after which the Sculptor, Weinert handed over the monument he created, to the President of the "P. A. &amp; S. "Association.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1638.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The cover was removed by the 12 year old Albert Parsons. After the singers performed the Masschorus "Wake Up," Mr. William Holmes held a speech in English, and the chief festival speaker Dr. Ernest Schmidt occupied the platform.</p>
   <p>His long speech was received with great applause.</p>
   <p>In closing also spoke Mr. Bernhard Herz, editor of a Bohemian newspaper, and Mr. Joseph Rybakowski in the Polish language. The statue was as previously mentioned designed by the sculptor Adolph Weinert, and cast by the "American Bronze Works" in Grand Crossing, on a granite pedestal, two female figures rise, which symbolize the "Revolution" and "Liberty."</p>
   <p>The pedestal bears the inscription of August Spies last words before his execution: "The day will come, when our silence will prove mightier, than the voices, which you throttle today."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
