<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1901-04-26">April 26, 1901</date><title level="a">German in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0667</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0667.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1901-04-26">April 26, 1901</date><title level="a">GERMAN IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German-American finds a certain satisfaction in the fact that educated Americans begin to recognize not only the commercial importance, but also the intellectual and ethical significance of the influence of the German population and their descendants upon the development and culture of the American nation. For decades the Germans met with stupid prejudice lack of understanding and arrogant self-conceit.</p>
   <p>The study of the German language in the institutions of higher learning is evidence of the changing attitude. Originally, perhaps, it served a practical purpose only, but is now leading to a critical analysis of the Germanic influences and, consequently, to a deeper understanding of the same. As gratifying evidences of this tendency can be shown the establishment of German museums, to the organizing of German societies, and German libraries at outstanding Universities of our country.</p>
   <p>The German Publication Fund of America, a recently organized association has undertaken a very maritorious work. It expects to publish a series of treatises, which will explain and emphasise the influence of the German- <pb facs="5418474_8_0668.jpg" n="2"/>American population upon our national developments in all phases. The program of the association is very comprehensive and adequate, and the essential matters for discussion will be the following:</p>
   <p>First, the literary relationship between American and Germany--German literature, originating in the United States, German literature, reprinted here, American translations from German literature and the influence of American literature in Germany.</p>
   <p>The second part has to do with the lighting relations between these two countries, with special consideration of the German dialects in American, and the influence of the German Language.</p>
   <p>The third part will contain treatises about the German drama and stage in the United States----The German drama on the German stage, the same on the English stage, the literary value of the German drama in America, and German stage plays written in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0669.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The fourth part is dedicated to music. Then follow the influence of club activities, athletics and other societies, German culture, science, philosophy, theology, pedagogy in the United States. There will also be discussed the German industrial activities, professional and technical sciences, the German, press, the relationship between the German and the American press, diplomatic relations between the two countries, the participation of Germans in American wars and finally biographies of German-Americans.</p>
   <p>It can be readily seen that the program will demonstrate in a very comprehensive and understandable way the influences and activities of the German-American element of the population and bring it to the attention of the American public. The association appeals for support to the public. They expect to raise funds to the amount of $100,000, and the interest from this capital to pay for the expenses of publishing the pamphlets.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
