<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-05-02">May 2, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Art and Nervous Afflictions</title><title level="a" type="sub">Professor Weygandt of the Hamburg University Held an Interesting Lecture</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0919</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0919.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-05-02">May 2, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">ART AND NERVOUS AFFLICTIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Professor Weygandt of the Hamburg University Held an Interesting Lecture</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the great ballroom of the Knickerbocker Hotel, a selected group gathered to listen to a lecture, "Art and Nervous Afflictions," by Professor Weygandt.</p>
   <p>Professor Weygandt was introduced by his fellow-countryman Mr. Alfred B. Steffans as co-founder and pride of the young University of Hamburg. The professor belongs among those scholars who do not limit themselves to one professional field, but who connect their special spheres with practical life and never lose contact with reality.</p>
   <p>That a man of such spiritual rank is specially capable to hold popular scientific lectures, is clear. Professor Weygandt at once took his audience firmly in hand. He spoke in a plain. sensible way and his power for description was such that not for a single moment did the lecture become monotonous.The audience followed his words with the greatest interest from start to finish.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0920.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>With the aid of pictures, Professor Weygandt showed the works of artists and dilettantes, works which were created under the influence of nervous and mental disorders. It was noticeable that the lecturer had a deep knowledge of the matter and was limiting the subject to its most outstanding aspects. What he said was selected with such care, that the whole field seemed exhausted to a certain degree when he finished. Occasionally the professor became sarcastic. For instance, when comparing the paintings made by mentally afflicted dilettantes with the masterpieces of the modern cubists or other ultra radicals, he stated that there were no definite distinctions between them, a fact which was pleasantly acknowledged by the audience every time a comparison was made.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
