<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-24">Apr. 24, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Superstition</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Lecture by Doctor Emil G. Hirsch</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1072</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1072.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I C (Jewish)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-24">Apr. 24, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">SUPERSTITION</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Lecture by Doctor Emil G. Hirsch</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A small, but select audience gathered at the Central Music Hall last night to hear Doctor Hirsch lecture on the highly interesting subject, "Superstition." The speaker was introduced by Doctor Frank Gunsaulus.</p>
   <p>Doctor Hirsch's lecture follows. "It is an indisputable fact that superstition existed since time immemorial, and will continue to exist as long as life is perpetuated. No argument founded on reason, nor religion itself, could prove sufficiently powerful to eradicate the deeply rooted superstition.</p>
   <p>"Much takes place in the ether, in the distance between Heaven and earth, of which pedagogues have not the slightest conception." This led the lecturer to the justified remark that to a certain degree every member of the human family is inclined to lean toward superstition. Continuing, Doctor Hirsch said, "It is also an established fact that religious persons are far more susceptible to superstition than moderate believers."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1073.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was a most cleverly prepared lecture. At the conclusion, Doctor Hirsch wisely omitted the advice to throw off the yoke of superstition. How well he knows that superstition cannot be laid aside at will. To relinquish one's religion is far less difficult than to throw off superstition.</p>
   <p>As regrettable as the fact is, it would be quite impossible, due to lack of the necessary space to print the complete lecture of that learned Rabbi. Thus, we must confine ourselves to the most important excerpts of his speech. The lecturer spoke about the origin of superstition, rather than about superstition itself. He gave his theory of its influence and transmission, also the relationship between religion and superstition.....An unsuccessful war was waged by science, and by the church, against superstition, which also shows itself early in the life of every child....</p>
   <p>"The poet also gives rise to superstition," said Doctor Hirsch, "since he <pb facs="5418474_8_1074.jpg" n="3"/>lets the flower whisper, brooks prattle, and speaks of the language of stars...."</p>
   <p>The speaker then defined at length the superstition of an "evil eye", still dreaded by mothers of small children, to an extent as if Satan, himself, were at work.</p>
   <p>Many phases on the subject of superstition were included in this learned man's lecture. Doctor Hirsch also gave a splendid analysis of superstition among seamen, and in conclusion gave a humoristic oral sketch of the custom of showering newlyweds with rice, and finally, when leaving home, throwing old shoes for good luck after them.</p>
   <p>It was indeed a highly interesting evening, the last one in the Central Music Hall. The building which can be regarded as a part of Chicago's history, will soon become only a memory. Doctor Hirsch was loudly acclaimed at the close of the lecture.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
