<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1878-08-26">August 26, 1878</date>.
<title level="a">The Swabians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0183</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-07">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0183.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1878-08-26">August 26, 1878</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWABIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The festival of the Swabians or Wurttembergers (Cannstadter Volksfest), which was spoiled by rain a week ago, came off with great eclat yesterday. It rained hard again Saturday night, and it was feared that Jupiter Pluvius would play another Swabian trick (Schwona Streich) upon the good natured Swabians in this city. But no such ill luck was in store for them. During the night it cleared up, and the sun arose yesterday morning as bright and beautiful as at any time this summer.</p>
   <p>A strong north wind dried the wet ground very rapidly, and made the picnic-grounds at Ogden's Grove fit for use. Not the least interesting part of the festival was the grand procession which marched to Ogden's Grove. The procession moved from the corner of Halsted and Randolph streets at about 10 o'clock. It marched east on Randolph street to Clark, north on Clark to Chicago avenue, west on Chicago Avenue to Larrabee, north on Larrabee to Clybourn, etc. etc., to Ogden's Grove. It was a very imposing pageant, and <pb facs="5418474_8_0184.jpg" n="2"/>took about half an hour to pass a given point. In the van of the procession was a platoon of police, under command of Lieut. Baus. Then came the Chief Marshal, Mr. Joseph Schoenninger, and staff on horseback.</p>
   <p>A band of music in an elaborate wagon followed. A carriage came next, containing a gentleman with spectacles and a goldembroidered black-velvet suit. He represented Judge Kegele, who for many years opened the Cannstadter festival in the Old Country. The rest of the procession consisted of five divisions, etc, etc....</p>
   <p>The streets through which the procession passed were through with people, and many of the houses were nicely decorated with evergreens and mottoes. Arrived at the Grove, the President, Mr. Ernst Hummel, made a short speech of welcome, after which a beautiful column ornamented with all sorts of fruits was unveiled.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0185.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After everybody had refreshed hinself a grand concert was given. At 3 o'clock Mr. William Rapp, of the Staats Zeitung, delivered a fine oration, and Mr. Emil Dietzsch, the genial Coroner, read an original poem. Besides this there were given during the afternoon and evening numberless tableaux and dramatic and musical entertainments and such other amusement as prevail in "Wurtemberg" on occasions of the kind. The attendance was immense, it being estimated that no less than 10,000 persons were present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
