<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-14">Nov. 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Birthday Celebration of the Ladies' Circle of the United German Press</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-14">Nov. 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">BIRTHDAY CELEBRATION OF THE LADIES' CIRCLE OF THE UNITED GERMAN PRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Eight years have gone by since the ladies' circle of the German Press Organization was organized; this was the occasion for a birthday celebration held yesterday afternoon at the Bismarck Hotel with a good attendance on the part of the members and numerous guests. A luncheon was followed by entertainment. The president of the German Press Organization, Herr Karl Freitag, was present as a guest of honor, and with him were three more members of the organization--vice-president Paul H. Ortmann, treasurer Adolf Danneberg, and Leopold Saltiel.</p>
   <p>Frau Anna Ballmann, president of the circle since its foundation, opened the program with a speech of welcome in which she made brief mention of the history of the organization. Then she thanked the founder and guest of honor, Herr Freitag, who only the day before had celebrated his own birthday, <pb facs="5418474_8_0425.jpg" n="2"/>for his exceedingly industrious activity, and rewarded him by tendering him a wreath of flowers. In his rejoinder, Herr Freitag emphasized that it was the industry of the ladies' circle which contributed so much to the success of the German Press Organization. Mr. Dannenberg then, in the name of the organization, presented the ladies with a beautiful bouquet of autumn flowers. Mr. Saltiel and Mr. Ortmann made short addresses.</p>
   <p>Miss Frieda Stoll, accompanied at the piano by Frau Florence Ferraro, sang three songs, of which the first--"Waldandacht", by Abt--was especially dedicated to Mr. Freitag. Her further presentations were Mozart's "Halleluja" and "Elsa's Traum", from "Lohengrin". She has a clear, well-modulated voice, and gained well-deserved applause.</p>
   <p>Humor came into its own with the staging of the operetta "Am Hochzeitstage", for which Rosa Norman Kloepfel, who was at the same time the play manager, Marie Lange Zeder, and Lola Stephenson again displayed their histrionic <pb facs="5418474_8_0426.jpg" n="3"/>talents, for which they have been known for some time. Frau Elsa Kuntzen, at the piano, contributed much to the success of the piece by her accompaniment.</p>
   <p>The artists, as well as the guests and members who came, were cordially thanked by Frau Ballmann, and thus this nice birthday celebration was brought to a close. The other ladies of the management, no less than the chairman, are all active in their respective offices since the foundation of the circle; the first vice-president, Frau Charlotte Freitag; second vice-president, Frau Julia Gertz; secretary, Frau Marie Saltiel, and treasurer, Frau Tillie Danneberg, Frau Anna Denner is chairman of the entertainment committee, and Frau Elizabeth Weir is part-time treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
