<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-07">Apr. 7, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The German-American Historical Magazine</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0404</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0404.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-07">Apr. 7, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN-AMERICAN HISTORICAL MAGAZINE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The second edition of The German-American Historical Magazine, which is published quarterly by the German-American Historical Society of Illinois, has just appeared. This issue contains elaborate articles and illustrations that may well compare with those published in the first issue. The "older" generation has already proven the intense demand for this excellent magazine, the reading of which is strongly advised for the younger generation in particular. The second publication of this magazine is a striking success--and why not--since the composing room staff has been greatly increased. Space has also been reserved for the "questionnaire", in view of the fact that so many of our readers are dubious whether or not they are entitled to answer the "questionnaire", not being members of the association. Our answer to this group is that the German-American Historical Society of Illinois was not established for business purposes; on the contrary, it is an educational institution intended to collect historical material dealing with Germans of Illinois and of the Northwest in <pb facs="5418474_8_0405.jpg" n="2"/>general. Publishing merely the history of those whose financial status would permit them to secure space in our magazine is not the policy of this association. Moreover, the German-American Historical Society of Illinois was founded for all German people alike, whose private lives or associations are irrelevant to this organization. Furthermore, the society encourages the return of the questionnaire and would appreciate any information in which the chief feature, namely, the subject proper is not disregarded. With this in mind, the organization would consider it indeed a service of extraordinary value regardless of its source.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, the research conducted by this association is of course of great importance to the German people, which as may easily be conceived requires great financial sacrifices. Therefore, it is quite natural that this organization is very eager for contributions from those who do appreciate the greatness and the importance of this undertaking and urges such persons to join the association by paying a "nominal membership fee." The foregoing explanation inspires our confidence that an abundance of interesting material will <pb facs="5418474_8_0406.jpg" n="3"/>reach the offices of the publisher of the Historical Magazine, a quarterly which should be the pride of every family. The issue that has just appeared contains the following interesting items:</p>
   <p>"'The First Annual Meeting of the German-American Historical Society of Illinois.'</p>
   <p>"'The History of German People of Quincy,' by Heinrich Bornmann. "'The Pioneers of McHenry County,' by Mrs. Lena B. Seiler. "'The Commencement of German Religious Life in Illinois,' by The Secretary. "'Historical Research Sketches,' a lecture delivered by Professor Louis Schutt. "'Primitive Administration of Justice in the west,' by Dr. August Richter. "'The Development of Marksmanship in Illinois,' by Albert Boese. "'Recollections of Heinrich Raad,' by C. E. Knorr. [Introduction by the Secretary.]</p>
   <p>"'Lincoln and Linkhorn,' a lecture by E. P. Hennighausen."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0407.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>General remarks. Donations--Assisting Committees--Membership list--Miscellany writings.</p>
   <p>The subscription cost for the annual publication of the Historical Magazine is $3.00.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
