<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-05-21">May 21, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Leaders in German Athletics Warmly Greeted at Banquet</title><title level="a" type="sub">Chicago's German-Americans Welcome Doctor Lewald and Doctor Diem at Hotel Atlantic</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-05-21">May 21, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">LEADERS IN GERMAN ATHLETICS WARMLY GREETED AT BANQUET</title><title level="a" type="sub">Chicago's German-Americans Welcome Doctor Lewald and Doctor Diem at Hotel Atlantic</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"German athletics has made such rapid progress during the last ten or fifteen years that America would have every reason to send a commission to Germany to learn about athletics from the Germans." This was the opinion expressed by Avery Brundage, president of the A. A. U. [Amateur Athletic Union] , at the banquet held yesterday at the Atlantic Hotel in honor of Theodor Lewald, former under-secretary of the interior [of the German Reich] and Doctor (honoris causa) Carl Diem, both of whom are leaders in German athletics. The two German guests are at present on a tour of this country for the purpose of studying American athletics.</p>
   <p>In words which obviously came from the bottom of his heart, Doctor Lewald thanked the A. A. U. (whose guests he and Doctor Diem are) for its kind hospitality.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1213.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He recalled the fact that he had visited Chicago, for the first time, some thirty-six years ago, and expressed the opinion that no other city in the entire world had experienced such a phenomenal growth in such a relatively short time as had Chicago. He had nothing but the highest praise for every phase of American athletics, in particular for the incomparable athletic facilities in this country, in respect of which [facilities] Germany could not even begin to compare with America. To be sure [he said] a great deal of hard work is being done in Germany, and it was his ardent wish that American athletes would visit Germany for purposes of study. It was his hope that the German team which will attend the Olympics in Los Angeles in 1932 would meet with success.</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of his speech, delivered in fluent English, Doctor Lewald awarded the medal of the Deutscher Reichsausschuss fuer Leibesuebungen (The German Reich's Committee on Calisthenics) to the following, in recognition of their splendid services in behalf of American athletics: Avery Brundage, president of the A. A. U.; Reinhold Oeschler, president of the Schutzbund Deutscher Sportvereine Chicago (Alliance of German Athletic Societies of <pb facs="5418474_8_1214.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago); and Fred Klotz, of the Illinois Soccer Football Association. These three men accepted the honor with felicitous expressions of gratitude.</p>
   <p>Doctor Diem, also, expressed his heartfelt thanks to his hospitable host, the A. A. U.; nor did he forget to mention the many German-Americans in Chicago who had prepared such a hearty reception for him and for Doctor Lewald. He, too, had visited Chicago some sixteen years ago, while engaged in a study of the American physical culture movement. America and Germany [he said] have much in common as far as athletics is concerned; and if an American commission were to visit Germany in the near future for purposes of study, its members would undoubtedly be surprised to find athletic fields and recreation parks in almost all the large German cities, which, in respect of their facilities, are quite similar to their American prototypes. This proves [he said] that Americans and Germans are alike in their love of nature. He, too, had been impressed by the phenomenal growth of Chicago during the last few years. Expressing his desire for useful co-operation in the development of athletics, and for friendship between the two countries, Doctor Diem concluded his heartily applauded remarks.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1215.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In addition to the two German guests and Avery Brundage, there were speeches by Ernest J. Kreutgen, representing the German delegation associated with the World's Fair; Doctor Schueller, vice-consul, appearing for Doctor Hugo F. Simon, the indisposed general consul; and Doctor Peter Peel, President of the U. S. Soccer Football Association and the Illinois Soccer Football Association.</p>
   <p>Reinhold Oeschler served as chairman, and Attorney Leopold Saltiel was the toast-master. The latter, an old turner [member of a Turnverein, a turner (gymnastic) society] and, for many years, first speaker of the Illinois Turnbezirk [Illinois Turner District], expressed, in his customary humorous manner, his great pleasure in being able to welcome, in the person of Doctor Diem, not only a worthy leader in athletics but also an old turner comrade.</p>
   <p>The banquet was attended by: [the names of about sixteen German-Americans are listed]. Miss Gertrude Clauss sang a number of German and English songs. . . . .</p>
   <p>After the banquet, the men proceeded to the Broadway Armory to attend the carnival of sports arranged by the Schutzbund Deutscher Sportvereine Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1216.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The sports carnival at the Broadway Armory, held in honor of the German leaders in athletics, unfolded itself in splendid fashion. The athletes and turner members turned in impressive performances, which were warmly applauded by the numerous people that attended.</p>
   <p>The parade of all the participants in the carnival presented a colorful picture. The procession was headed by the cyclists of the Deutscher Radsport Klub (The German Cycle Club); then came the feminine members of the Illinois Turnbezirk; and then--in double file--the athletes of the Schutzbund Deutscher Sportvereine and the masculine members of the Illinois Turnbezirk. As the parade came to an end, R. Oeschler, president of the Schutzbund Deutscher Sportvereine, welcomed Doctors Lewald and Diem, in the name of all the turner members and athletes. He expressed the hope that athletes and turner members would continue to enjoy friendly relations, of the kind manifested at this carnival.</p>
   <p>Doctor Lewald, who was warmly greeted, addressed a few words of thanks to the German athletes and turner members, who had prepared such a hearty reception <pb facs="5418474_8_1217.jpg" n="6"/>for both him and Doctor Diem. He was especially grateful to the A. A. U., in particular, to its president, Avery Brundage. From the day of the arrival of the German leaders in athletics, the A. A. U. had--in exemplary fashion--done everything to make their visit to America as pleasant as possible. They were everywhere afforded the opportunity to inspect athletic facilities and to make studies. In concluding, he expressed the wish that German-American athletes would continue to cultivate German customs and the German way of life, and would maintain friendly relations with their old homeland.</p>
   <p>Doctor Diem . . . invited all athletes, who planned a trip to the homeland, to visit the Reichsausschuss, where they would be most heartily welcomed. Avery Brundage, president of the A. A. U., voiced the hope that, at the Olympic games to be held in 1932 in Los Angeles, he would be able to welcome a really strong German team, which would certainly prove America's most formidable rival.</p>
   <p>The program [at the Broadway Armory] was opened by a gymnastic exhibition given by the feminine turner members, who were briskly applauded. The old men's class of the Illinois Turnbezirk performed splendidly, and received well-earned applause.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1218.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The athletes then competed in the forty-meter dash, the 400-meter run, and the 1500-meter run. The winners of these events and the victors in the wrestling and weight-lifting contests were wildly applauded by the spectators. Indeed, all the events were enthusiastically received by the attending public.</p>
   <p>Today, the German leaders in athletics will inspect the West Park System and the athletic facilities of the Western Electric Company. The Hawthorne Club has invited the two men to lunch. In the afternoon, Doctors Lewald and Diem will be the guests of Wm. J. Wrigley, and will witness the baseball game between the Chicago Cubs and the Pittsburgh Pirates.</p>
   <p>Yesterday, Doctors Lewald and Diem visited the Chicago A. A. [Athletic Association] and, later, the University of Chicago. With [A. A.] Stagg, the well-known veteran in the world of sports, acting as guide, they inspected all the athletic facilities, and then lunched at the South Shore Country Club. In the afternoon, they inspected the South Park System, under the guidance of Park Commissioners Donahue and Brown. Doctor Diem was particularly interested in the splendid equipment of Gage Park, which even serves as a model for Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
