<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-05-25">May 25, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[Resolution of the Chicago Gruetlti Society]</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Participation in the Peace Festival]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0252</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-07">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0252.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-05-25">May 25, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[RESOLUTION OF THE CHICAGO GRUETLTI SOCIETY]</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Participation in the Peace Festival]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In pleasant contrast with the aggressive stand taken by some Swiss in St. Louis against the Westliche Post comes the resolution adopted by the Chicago Grutli Society to participate in the Peace Festival. This resolution shows that there are after all a good number of Swiss who neither have forgotten nor want to forget that German blood pulses in their veins....Earlier than in Germany itself here in America Low Germans, (Plattdeutsche) and High Germans, Prussians and Swabians, Bavarians and Mecklenburgers have recognized that they are before anything else Germans, and among the many factors that developed in Germany during the past twenty-five years the national feeling of such emigrants, who only in America came to national consciousness, is surely not to be forgotten......Till the War of 1870 brought French sympathies of a part of the German speaking population of America to the surface, hardly anyone had made a difference between those born in Germany itself and the German natives of other European countries. The German speaking Alsations, just as much as those from Lorraine, or those from Switzerland or the Russian Baltic provinces were simply counted among the German speaking community, and if they ever protested against it that must have been a rare occasion. We never heard of it. On the other hand, not a few cases could be enumerated where natives of <pb facs="5418474_8_0253.jpg" n="2"/>Alsace Lorraine and Switzerland got into public office on the strength of their German-Americanism. The German Mayor of Milwaukee, the former German chief of police in Chicago, were Alsatians. A prominent German member of our city council is Swiss etc. etc. Even the Hollanders being thrown into the same pot with the Germans as "Dutchmen" make the best of it and polish up, here in America, on their somewhat rusty German.</p>
   <p>.....Just as Herr von Holst born as a subject of the Tzar is by everybody regarded as a German-American and not as a co-national of our Russian fellow citizens in Alaska, so it is right that the Swiss and Alsatians of German extraction remember the good German saying: "Kind does not let from kind" - or, as the English language has it; "blood is thicker than water".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
