<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-29">Apr. 29, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">Gymnastics in Public Schools</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1401</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1401.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-29">Apr. 29, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">GYMNASTICS IN PUBLIC SCHOOLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following circular was issued and sent to all societies of the Chicago Turner District on April 11:</p>
   <p>"The Turnverein Vorwaerts to all societies of the Chicago Turner District:</p>
   <p>"The Bible says: 'Don't put your light under a bushel.' It is the opinion of the Vorwaerts Turnverein and doubtlessly yours also that the Turner societies of Chicago are making a mistake, to their own disadvantage as well as to that of all Turner societies of the whole country, by not endorsing a matter which is not only worth while but also deserves to be considered under the circumstances as really admirable.</p>
   <p>"We mean the introduction of gymnastics in public schools, and more than that, the ways and means by which it is cultivated.</p>
   <p>"The Turner societies of the city of Chicago have a perfect right to be proud <pb facs="5418474_8_1402.jpg" n="2"/>of the fact that no other city of this large country promotes gymnastics in the public schools to such a degree as does Chicago. Indeed, we have a double right, for this result was achieved through our propaganda and by the technical ability of men who were trained in our circles.</p>
   <p>"It is to the interest of the North American Turner Bund as well as to our own to honor those persons by public appreciation of their merits, since we must attribute these excellent results to their admirable achievements. It is furthermore our duty to let these facts be known to our brother societies.</p>
   <p>"The Vorwaerts Turnverein therefore requests the societies to instruct their respective representatives in the District executive board to support the following motion, explained by what we have said above:</p>
   <p>"'The executive board of the Chicago Turner District shall be ordered to compose a memorial concerning the introduction and the development of gymnastics in the public schools of Chicago and shall have printed the aforesaid memorial <pb facs="5418474_8_1403.jpg" n="3"/>a sufficient number of copies and send it for instructive purposes to all the Turner societies of the Bund.'</p>
   <p>"Turnverein Vorwaerts"</p>
   <p>This motion, not to be underestimated in its effect on the further development of gymnastics in the public schools, was approved of and accepted. The following persons were elected to prepare the memorial: Suder, Nettelhorst Hibbeler, Zipp, Weidemann, and Wenter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
