<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-09-26">Sept. 26, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">German Carnival</title><title level="a" type="sub">Chicago Turngemeinde Intends to Hold a Carnival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0057</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-07">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0057.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-09-26">Sept. 26, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN CARNIVAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Chicago Turngemeinde Intends to Hold a Carnival</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Turngemeinde needs money! After the Chicago Fire the association erected a large building for German activities, but despite all efforts to meet expenses interest on the mortgage is now $2,000 in arrears. Because of the depression the accumulating deficit was simply unavoidable. The Executive Board therefore decided to hold a rather unique festival to raise the money; a carnival featuring scenes from the works of famous German authors is to be given.</p>
   <p>An arrangements committee was nominated some time ago; the members are Julius Cohen, Carl Meier, Max Stern, Louis Kohtz, John C. Miller, Julius Zimmermann, Leo Ernst, C. F. Hunke, Fritz Goetz, and Hettich. Since most of the work will involve the ladies, the committee invited the women's division, and a meeting was held yesterday to consider ways and means.</p>
   <p>About fifty ladies were present, and after Mrs. Jacob Enders, president of <pb facs="5418474_8_0058.jpg" n="2"/>the women's division, had opened the meeting, Julius Cohen explained the details in general. He said that the Turngemeinde wishes to arrange a carnival which shall excel all former festivals held at Turner Hall. Scenes from the works of German authors will be presented, and a bazaar is also to be held. Turner Hall will be festively decorated for the occasion. The last Thursday in October, the 30th, has been tentatively selected for the opening day, and the festival will continue to Monday, November 3. Scenes in pantomime from classical German works will be given in the evenings; on Sunday Wallenstein's Lager will be on the program, and on Monday prizes will be offered to those who wear the best German provincial costumes. A dance will be given at the close of the carnival. Admission 25 cents per evening, $1 for the series.</p>
   <p>The speaker then gave the reasons for organizing the festival--which we mentioned at the beginning of the column--and asked the ladies for their co-operation; he also requested that ticket-sellers who call at the homes of Germans shall emphasize the point that it would be deplorable if Turner Hall, which was built especially for German activities, should be lost through foreclosure.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0059.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Carl Meyer then addressed the assembly. In his opinion it was important that young and pretty girls predominate at the carnival. His appeal for two hundred charming ladies to participate in the festival found concurrence, and he was assured that such a number could be found.</p>
   <p>Max Stern then expressed his appreciation of the ladies' unanimous consent, and he then advised those who are going to solicit purchases of tickets to be prepared for sales resistance; if any one says that the Turngemeinde is always begging, the answer should be:</p>
   <p>"The Turngemeinde does not want the money. We are interested only in maintaining Turner Hall, which provides a meeting-place for Chicago's Germans whenever our interests are at stake. The two hundred members of the Turngemeinde not only have always donated money but have paid regular admission to the festivals and devoted time and effort besides. The Germans are not asked to help the Turngemeinde. We appeal to Chicago's Germans to think of their own interests."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0060.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The date of the next meeting was then considered, and since the festival is to be given soon, it was decided that the names of the participants should be listed promptly. On the motion of Miss Greifenhagen the next meeting will be held on Tuesday.</p>
   <p>Julius Cohen jokingly remarked that the participants may expect a twofold reward: first the fun provided by the festival itself and second the great prospects in store for the young ladies. As a result of the last fair given by the association, twelve girls are now married.</p>
   <p>Of course all our German girls will co-operate in making the festival a success! American girls are also welcome.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
