<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-03-13">March 13, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Professor Oncken Honored. Receives a Diploma as Honorary Member of the German-American Historical Society.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0395</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0395.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-03-13">March 13, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">PROFESSOR ONCKEN HONORED. RECEIVES A DIPLOMA AS HONORARY MEMBER OF THE GERMAN-AMERICAN HISTORICAL SOCIETY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As is well known the German-American Historical Society elected at its general meeting the prominent German professor, Dr. Oncken, at present in Chicago as an honorary member of their institution. The artistic diploma has been handed to him in the presence of the German and Swiss Consuls at a dinner by Judge Eberhardt, the president of the society. The dinner had been given by Mr. Otto C. Schneider, second vice-president of the Historic Society, at his home, in honor of Prof. Oncken. Also the directors of the board had been invited.</p>
   <p>A number of toasts were given and Prof. Oncken in his acceptance speech demonstrated that the German-Americans who fought for the interests of the North in our Civil War had a very great influence on the unification of Germany. He accepted the membership offered not as a reward for his services already done but the ones he intends to do in the future. It will be his goal to open the eyes of the German university students about the great mission of <pb facs="5418474_8_0396.jpg" n="2"/>of the Germans in this country and to promote the study of American and German-American history.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
