<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-02-28">February 28, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Examination of Midwives.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0771</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0771.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-02-28">February 28, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">Examination of Midwives.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The end of the 25th semester of the German Midwife school of Dr.Scheuermann 191 North Avenue, combined with finishing examination was celebrated last night in the institution. Besides the pupils from the last course, a great number of previous years were present to indicate their appreciation and esteem for the director of the institution and its other teachers, Dr.Nitz, Voller and Wolpers. The ever well-attended courses of the school are held for six months and start February and September of each year. How seriously the director takes his duties is shown by the fact that none of the pupils get their diploma if they are not found to be really capable midwives, to execute their responsible profession. At the close of the present semester, Dr.Schenermann, to his great regret, after a thorough conference with the other teachers of the institution, had to refuse two of the pupils their diploma. Dr.Schenermann with moving words handed diplomas to the following pupils: "Baners, Gerlach, Holdersbaih, Kryaski, Markgraf, Penartz, Scharf, Schroeder, Stovm and Waltennvitz". Dr.Nitz spoke hearty words of farewell, and cautioned the leaving pupils to persevere truly in their difficult profession. A very friendly gathering took place in the home of Dr.Schenermann, where the graduating pupils had arranged a lively affair.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
