<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1874-07-09">July 9, 1874</date>.
<title level="a">The Great Music Festival</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Good Beginning</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0228</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-07">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0228.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1874-07-09">July 9, 1874</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREAT MUSIC FESTIVAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Good Beginning</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last evening, at eight o'clock, a meeting was held in the club room of the Sherman House for the purpose of discussing preliminary arrangements for the great music festival which is planned for the spring of the coming year, and which has been the principal subject of conversation during the past few weeks.</p>
   <p>Mr. Louis Sievers opened the meeting and briefly explained its purpose.</p>
   <p>Alderman White was elected to act as chairman, and Robert Thiem as secretary.</p>
   <p>The following organizations were represented: Liederkranz, represented by Hans Balatka, and Robert Thiem; Germania Maennerchor, Dr. Bluthardt (sic), F.W. Dietzsch; Orpheus, John C. Meyers, Louis Sievers; Apollo Club, E.C. Curtis; Beethoven Society, Hubbard (sic), Lewis (sic); Turngemeinde (Mixed Chorus), Arthur Erbe, Lorenz Mattern, J. Zernitz; Schweizer Maennerchor; Scandinavian Society, "Freja".</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0229.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>By general request Mr. Balatka presented the following plan:</p>
   <p>"A music festival such as is contemplated must be presented on a grand scale or not at all. Chicago must not go at the matter halfheartedly. It has been a long time since Chicago has sponsored a worthwhile enterprise of this kind, for Gilmore's project was a complete failure. More than a year ago I spoke about the matter to several music lovers, among them Mr. Fred Upton. All of them expressed a desire to hold a great music festival in Chicago, and this desire would have been realized if the financial crisis had not interfered. If the proposed festival is a success, it will convince able musicians that there is a real future for them right here in Chicago; and it will induce them to come to this city and stay here, instead of remaining aloof, as many of them do now.</p>
   <p>As far as the necessary material for this kind of festival is concerned, it can easily be found here. After the elimination of undesirable voices it would not be difficult to obtain six hundred trained singers here; and <pb facs="5418474_8_0230.jpg" n="3"/>by calling in reserves from Fort Wayne and Milwaukee, the number could be increased to eight hundred. A chorus of this size is sufficiently large to render any desirable composition. A larger choir would be unsuitable for the purpose, for it would be difficult to direct. If such a choir manages to present a number well, this success is attributable to good fortune and not to the ability of the choir or its conductor. Also, at a festival such as is proposed, male choruses could be permitted to do more work than is usually accorded them, for instance at Cincinnati.</p>
   <p>By the use of instruments available in other cities we could also organize an orchestra composed of home talent. And as far as obtaining the necessary prominent soloists is concerned, we could, perhaps, secure the services of Signor Costa, of London, who could direct one of his own oratorios. For music of a lighter vein we might secure the services of Strauss of Vienna; and as prima donna, perhaps Mrs. Mallinger, of Berlin, or Mrs. Peschka-Leutner, of Leipzig. But no matter what we decide or whom we choose, there must be no deception in connection with this festival; there must not <pb facs="5418474_8_0231.jpg" n="4"/>be even the slightest indication of anything but honesty and diligent work. The duration of the festival could be about two weeks. The expenses could best be defrayed through the establishment of a guaranty fund through donations from prominent citizens of Illinois and all other states of the Northwest."</p>
   <p>Mr. Florenz Ziegfeld was asked to give his opinion. He declared that Mr. Balatka had just about exhausted the subject, that the enterprise could be carried out if there was a will to do so; that Chicago had an advantage in that it had access to the necessary hall, whereas the building in which the music festival in Boston was held had to be erected at a cost of twenty-five thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>Mr. Otto Lob agreed with the preceding speakers. Mr. Pratt (sic), Mr. F. Roesch, Mr. H. Claussenius, Mr. Lewis (sic), Mr. Molter (sic), Mr. Ziehn (sic), and other prominent men were also present in this meeting, and they all declared that they were in favor of giving the festival. Thereupon a <pb facs="5418474_8_0232.jpg" n="5"/>committee was appointed to make arrangements for a permanent organization. The following men composed this committee: Florenz Ziegfeld, Hans Balatka, C. C. Curtis, John Lewis, Alexander White, H. Claussenius, Otto Lob, F. C. Dohn, C. Wolffsohn, Dr. Bluthardt.</p>
   <p>The committee was also instructed to mail invitiations to the directors of the Exhibition Building.</p>
   <p>Adjournment followed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
