<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-12-03">Dec. 3, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">The Correct Answer!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0815</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0815.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-12-03">Dec. 3, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">THE CORRECT ANSWER!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last fortnight the proletarian movement in Chicago has once again given the English papers an opportunity for complaints and lies. The reason for it is the liberal Sunday schools, which are represented as being obscurantist centers where the manufacturing of bombs is taught. Some of the papers demand their suppression from Bonfield or request Roche to prohibit them entirely.</p>
   <p>This vulgar agitation against the progressive Sunday schools is plausible. It must indeed be a disappointment for the reigning clique to witness the rapid growth of these institutions and the increasing desertion of neighborly religious Sunday schools.</p>
   <p>For the exploiters want obscurantist institutions for the children of the proletarians so that they may raise them to become good natured, patient imbeciles, with only one task in their life: to labor, and only one hope and one wish: to get recompensed in heaven.</p>
   <p>It is revolting to expect the worker to accept a promissory note for "heavenly <pb facs="5418474_8_0816.jpg" n="2"/>joys" in lieu of profits stolen from him by greedy sharks. That the children of the proletariat shall not how to such an economic system is the aim of the liberal Sunday schools. Such a system should be attacked regardless of what type of weapons are used.</p>
   <p>The only correct answer to the attacks of the papers has been given yesterday at a gathering in the Aurora Turn Hall. After having explained the importance of the progressive Sunday schools and after having refuted the attacks against them, the speaker receive the support of the assembly for the foundation of a progressive Schul-Verein (School Society) on the Northwest Side.</p>
   <p>This was the only good answer which could be given by progressively minded men and women of this city to Bonfield's boasting an to the capitalistic agitation. That this answer has hit the nail on the head is proven by the howls of rage of the capitalistic press regarding this meeting.</p>
   <p>But these exploiters and their henchmen should not only get a slap in the face on the Northwest Side. Similar meetings should also be held in other districts of the city. If such Schul-Vereine (school societies) could be formed everywhere, it would decrease the number of Sunday schools conducted <pb facs="5418474_8_0817.jpg" n="3"/>by priests and their helpers.</p>
   <p>Therefore, on with the work, comrades!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
