<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-16">Dec. 16, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Premiere of the Treut Film</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0734</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0734.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-16">Dec. 16, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">PREMIERE OF THE TREUT FILM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The homeland films of the Society for Germans in Foreign Lands seem to have hit a warm spot in the hearts of Chicago's German-Americans. The films enjoy such great popularity that even yesterday, though the weather was unusually cold, their loyal supporters came in creditable numbers to see Dr. Treut's latest homeland film. Although the audience was, of course, not very large, it nevertheless included more people than could have been expected during such inclement weather.</p>
   <p>In his introductory speech Dr. Robert Treut faced the situation with good humor. He said that he realized that his Chicago shows are handicapped both by the depression and the artic temperature, and that it is all the more remarkable that the loyal supporters came to the show. Dr. Treut then spoke of the old fatherland and the work of the Society for Germans in Foreign Lands. Among other things, he mentioned that the children in Berlin's public schools <pb facs="5418474_8_0735.jpg" n="2"/>collected twenty thousand marks in the last few weeks for the Society.</p>
   <p>The Saengerbund (Singing Society) Freiheit, led by its director, Karl Rekzeh, was present in full force. The singers presented the song of the "Lorelei" and "In Einem Kuehlen Grunde," and by dint of their true mastery, created the right mood for the moving picture.</p>
   <p>The film, "Von Watercant bis Alpenrand" (From the Waterfront to the Border of the Alps), is truly a film from the homeland. Each visitor was shown a part of his homeland, a region of German soil of which he has grown fond. It shows the general public a cross section of German scenes and German life.</p>
   <p>As indicated by the title, the film conducts the onlooker through the whole of Germany from north to south. With a skillful hand and subtle insight, the pictures and scenes were selected, and every device of modern technique was resorted to in the making of the photographs. In many cities the contrast is shown between today and yesterday--between the old town and the new--and so <pb facs="5418474_8_0736.jpg" n="3"/>the public is taken for a visit through Bremen and Hamburg, through Hannover, Berlin, Frankfurt, Stuttgart, and Munich. These scenes are interpersed with landscapes and pictures showing the lives of the people.</p>
   <p>Humor does, of course, come into its own. But especially charming is the observation that our nationals abroad are turning to the past in their search for consolation and strength in the dire misery of our time. Pictures from the Bavarian Alps deserve special mention, for they are magnificent examples of landscape photography. Dr. Truet provided a running comment for the show.</p>
   <p>During the intermission, the singers sang two songs, "Spinn, Spinn, Toechterlein" and the "Jaeger aus Kurfalz," which gained them thunderous applause. The organ accompaniment was taken over by Mr. Hermann F. Mayer, who discharged his duties in his usual, skillful manner.</p>
   <p>The show is going to be repeated today and Sunday night. Sunday afternoon at 3 P. M. there will be one performance at moderate prices. Monday, December 26, <pb facs="5418474_8_0737.jpg" n="4"/>the German population of the South Side will be given an opportunity to see the film. The show will take place at Pastor Schick's Immanuel Church, 7008 South Michigan Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
