<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-01-25">January 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Orden Der Hermann Schwestern</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Order of the Sisters of Herman)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1781</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1781.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-01-25">January 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">ORDEN DER HERMANN SCHWESTERN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Order of the Sisters of Herman)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Order of the Sisters of Herman, State of Illinois, held its 12th annual Grand Lodge meeting at the Wicker Park Hall last Wednesday night. There were 76 representatives of 18 lodges present, who listened to the very favorable report of the first Grand Lodge officer.</p>
   <p>The cash amount of money on hand is $19,529.00 of which $10,114.00 belong to the Life Insurance Department. The total expenses have been $4552.00 of which $3450.00 has been paid to the families of deceased members. The Illinois Order had 2135 members on the 1st of January, 1908, showing an increase of 149 members during last year.</p>
   <p>Several rules of the Order's constitution were changed after a short debate. Then the following new lodge-deputies were elected: Barbara Windbiel, Alvina Spalding, Augusta Rutzen, Minna Lehmann, Wilhelmina Dorn, Christina Conroy, Elsbeth Kern, Barbera Stump, Minna Meffert, Emilie Saxler, Anna Merten, Maria <pb facs="5418474_8_1782.jpg" n="2"/>Hamel, Paulina Maesse, Margaretha Drinhaus, Maria Butenhen, Friedericke Roebke, Elise Krick and Lena Faber.</p>
   <p>After the election came a delightful banquet, given in honor of the present Grand Lodge officers. All participants enjoyed the wonderfully served meal, while the toastmaster Mrs. Franziska Marzolf entertained with several short speeches.</p>
   <p>The Order is owing its growing membership to its usefulness as a sick benefit and life insurance lodge. Besides this, the Order is cultivating zealously the preservation of German arts, literature and German language.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
