<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-11-04">Nov. 4, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[Our Newspaper Amd the Great Fire]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0639</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0639.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-11-04">Nov. 4, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[OUR NEWSPAPER AMD THE GREAT FIRE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At last we are able to present the Illinois Staats Zeitung again in decent shape. That it could not be done earlier, was not our fault. Our orders for type, papers, and presses, went out inside twice twenty-four hours after half of Chicago had been laid into ashes, but unfortunately, they were based on the unscrupulous trickery of agents who assured us that the goods were lying ready to be sent at a minute's notice. Had we not been deceived in this way, or had we been given help from the German press outside Chicago, such as the American press of Chicago received, the Illinois Staats Zeitung might have appeared, at the latest, then days after the conflagration, in the size in which it now goes into the hands of our readers.</p>
   <p>However, we have received in the last few weeks proofs so conclusive of the faithfulness of our readers, that we feel sure of their forgiveness of imperfections, the abolition of which was not earlier in our power. We all had to get along in Chicago with various makeshifts. Our big business men who transacted, until a few weeks ago, their business in marble palaces, do it now in huts made of boards. But the interim is now passed. The two copies of the Illinois Staats Zeitung which have appeared since the fire, will form in the future only an episode in the history of the paper. What has been written in these copies will sometimes testify to the feverish excitement in <pb facs="5418474_8_0640.jpg" n="2"/>in which the employes of the paper found themselves, just as much as tens of thousands of others, who lost through the fire the labor of many years.</p>
   <p>To collaborate in the giant task of reconstruction with such energy that Chicago will more than ever become a bulwark of Germandom in the Northwest, that will be the joy and pride of the Germans; to keep step with the new growth of Germandom; to represent it according to the most honest insight and with all our strength, and to look to it that it shall not occupy in the new Chicago a less influential position than it has in the one that burnt down; that will be the contribution of the Illinois Staats Zeitung to the reconstruction. Whatever existed before the ninth of October in the way of small frictions, cavils, and animosities among the Germans should be buried with so many other things under the giant heap of debris. Whoever wants to, may dig it out from under there - we wont.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
