<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-12">Nov. 12, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Fifteenth Anniversary Concert a Huge Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1697</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1697.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-12">Nov. 12, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">FIFTEENTH ANNIVERSARY CONCERT A HUGE SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German-American Musicians' Sick Aid Organization yesterday celebrated its fifteenth anniversary with a concert in the Mozart Hall, 1536 Clybourn Avenue. Nothing was left to be desired, neither in the program nor its rendition. There was a large attendance. There was scarcely standing room available when the first notes of Offenbach's overture to "Orpheus in the Underworld" sounded. The orchestra of about fifty men, under the direction of Geo. Lowitz won hearty applause. They gave several encores.</p>
   <p>A no less flattering success was had by the post office orchestra, under the direction of their conductor, Karl Meder, many of whom are members of the D.A.K.U.V. They played three numbers.</p>
   <p>The vocal part of the concert was handled by the German-Hungarian Ladies' choir under the direction of conductor L. Zohmiller, and by the Alpenlaender Maennerchor, directed by H. Steinmetz. Both organizations accomplished <pb facs="5418474_8_1698.jpg" n="2"/>their task excellently, and deserved their applause.</p>
   <p>Two soloists followed: Miss Helen Stumpfel, and outstanding violin player, and Miss Barbara Schmidt, an excellent piano player.</p>
   <p>A sextet consisting ofJulius Krupp, Philipp Moore, Julius Krupp, Paul Hargel, Adoph Krupp, and John Wershing played Bolzonis Minuet, and gave a good performance. Mary Wish, Rose M. Broska, and E. Nesalik performed a "tambourindance" that was quite beautiful. A duet was offered by Anton Holstern and Josef Stein, and finally a potpouri "A Hot Time in the Old Town", by a village orchestra.</p>
   <p>A surprise that was received with particular enthusiasm was accorded Director Lowitz when, in the name of the organization, President Frank Philips handed him a beautiful gold watch in recognition of his efforts in behalf of the organization. A short while previously, President Philips had addressed the <pb facs="5418474_8_1699.jpg" n="3"/>assembly with a brief speech extending a cordial welcome and pointing to the progress made by the D.A.M.K.U.V. This part of his address was made especially effective because suddenly a trumpet was blowing "reveille" from behind the stage and then the orchestra played"The Star Spangled Banner" and the whole assembly rose to their feet.</p>
   <p>Dancing followed. The entertainment committee consisted of Geo. Miller, fest president; Frank Philips, president of the organization; J. Netzer, fest secretary; Stephan Gross, treasurer; G. Lowitz, conductor; J. Sassarath, vice-conductor; M. Schmidt, ticket treasurer; J. Amberg, P. Amberg, W. Hollmann, P. Pill, J. Werth, J. Cultner, J. Konrath, N. Willer, C. Neumann, C. Steiner, M. Probst, E. Schoepke, S. Ramholz, Lorenz Amberg, J. Schwarzer, and S. Marksteiner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
