<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-04-17">Apr. 17, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Ridder's Second Lecture</title><title level="a" type="sub">Orchestra Hall Again Filled to Capacity Impressive Warning</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0980</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0980.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-04-17">Apr. 17, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">RIDDER'S SECOND LECTURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Orchestra Hall Again Filled to Capacity Impressive Warning</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some day, when history will judge the attitude of the nations which remained "neutral" during the present war, the chapter "America's attitude toward Germany during the Great War" will occupy a large space. Much will be said that won't sound exactly flattering to the North American republic, but then again men will be gratefully mentioned who, putting aside all personal considerations, stood up for right and justice. One of these will be Bernhard Hermann Ridder, who delivered his second lecture in Orchestra Hall last night. The moral influence which Mr. Ridder exerted by his winning personality, his great knowledge, and splendid oratory, even on his Anglophile listeners, was clearly evidenced by the remarks which could be overheard in all sections of the large auditorium. His speech last <pb facs="5418474_8_0981.jpg" n="2"/>night has won quite a number of intelligent friends for the German cause. By and large, Mr. Ridder spoke as follows:</p>
   <p>"No matter how many generations there are between the American of German descent and his German ancestor--and I confess to be a member of the third generation of a German family--a warm sympathy for the fate of our old country is firmly rooted in our hearts. In the veins of us [German] descendants there flows the same warm German blood as in the veins of those who have just recently emigrated from Germany to become Americans. The English, in contradistinction to the Germans, are always trying to convince the world that they are the protectors of the oppressed and of the weak, and seek the world's sympathy by distorting facts. For this purpose, they do not shun any kind of unfair competition, or any shady business deal. For instance, while China tried so hard to protect her hapless people from the devastations of opium, by instituting stringent legislation, England, in 1908 brought all her pressure to bear that this <pb facs="5418474_8_0982.jpg" n="3"/>insidious poison might continue to be imported, because it proved such a wonderful source of revenue to that English shopkeeper nation. This killed two flies at a time; the Chinese people are weakened and the British money bags swelled.</p>
   <p>Poor Memory</p>
   <p>"The present relationship between England and the United States in general, and our Federal Government in particular, is the result of England's cunning and conniving, through distortion of facts, bribing of the press, and other manipulations, to mislead and confuse the American people. The men at the helm of the American Government seem to have forgotten completely that England has tried, for 140 years, to do every conceivable damage to America, while Germany,during this long period, has always proved herself to be America's friend. Secretary of State Bryan recently made another one of those alibi speeches, in which he attempted to explain the attitude of <pb facs="5418474_8_0983.jpg" n="4"/>the Administration during the present war. In it, he said that no president of the United States has had so many opportunities to make mistakes as President Wilson has right now. He should have added that no president has ever welcomed the chance to commit so many blunders as has President Wilson.</p>
   <p>"The German ambassador Count Bernstorff, was probably the most popular member of the diplomatic corps in Washington before the war. But under the present circumstances he cannot convey any [German] note to the Washington government, or make any utterance without being thoroughly misunderstood and criticized. If war should break out today between the United States and Germany, all that would be left to do would be to mobilize the army against her; everything else has already been done. Trade between the two nations has already been interrupted and, to our export of arms to the Allies, we would Just have to add export of troops.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0984.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>With England's Gracious Permission</p>
   <p>"In the concert of nations, we have long ceased to play a part. And now we act amazed that Germany's attitude towards the United States has become bitter, after all that our Government has done to that country. A Chicago morning paper published an article today in which it says that England was going to give us "permission" to export certain kinds of goods to Germany. Who has given England the right to exercise guardianship over our Government? What has happened to American prestige in the world when even Mexico and Japan treat us en bagatelle [trifle with us]?</p>
   <p>"But in spite of all this, the American people seem to come out of their trance, because voices are increasing in Washington which demand emphatically that our arms traffic to Europe be stopped. My utterances regarding the peace terms to be formulated by Germany have been misunderstood by numerous people. When I said that I believed Germany would be satisfied with the status quo ante bellum, I started from the premise that the Allies would have initiated <pb facs="5418474_8_0985.jpg" n="6"/>negotiations by now. But the longer they keep this war going, the more sacrifices Germany will have to make, the harsher will be the peace terms Germany will impose upon the Allies."</p>
   <p>The Discussion</p>
   <p>After his speech, Mr. Ridder encouraged his listeners to ask him questions. The first question was, "Who started the war?"</p>
   <p>"A comprehensive reply to this question would take more time than my lecture," Mr. Ridder responded. "Anyway, Russia sent a note to Serbia, directing her not to accept, under any circumstances, the Austrian demands after the assassination of Archduke Francis Ferdinand. The assassination of this prince was the signal for the mobilization of the Russian army."</p>
   <p>"What are we to think of the Belgian Neutrality Act?" was another question.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0986.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>"When, in 1838, the act was signed, guaranteeing Belgium's neutrality, France and England demanded that the then little Prussia become a co-signatory. But, in 1871, Thiers [French statesman] declared: "The next world war will be between France and Germany, and French troops will march thru Belgium into Germany". During the Morocco crisis, the French government sent experts to Belgium to find out whether an expeditionary force of 160,000 English troops could be landed in Belgium. The world was ignorant about all this, but after the occupation of Brussels by German troops, irrefutable evidence was discovered in the Belgium state archives documenting the intentions of the French and English to violate Belgium neutrality in case of a war with Germany."</p>
   <p>Italy's conduct during the present war was also the object of discussion. Mr. Ridder called Italy the barometer of the war situation. It always pointed to the side where the greatest advantage for herself seemed to lie.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0987.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>There was only one difference between Italy and America, namely, that the Italian press did not fall for the same "phony boloney" stories as the American press.</p>
   <p>The war movies exhibited after the lecture, seven reels in all, fascinated the audience to a high degree, and contributed a lot to the German cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
