<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-04-06">Apr. 6, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's Festivals</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1760</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1760.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-04-06">Apr. 6, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">YESTERDAY'S FESTIVALS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The double flag dedication, arranged by District 379 of the Deutsche Unterstuetzungsbund (German Benefit Society), and held at Social Turnhalle, corner of Belmont Avenue and Lincoln Street, last evening, turned out to be an impressive ceremony.</p>
   <p>Members and their friends and acquaintances appeared very early, and soon the Hall was the scene of merry activity. The committee had arranged a diversified program which provided amusement for young and old.</p>
   <p>An excellent orchestra played popular selections, and vocal and instrumental music was rendered alternately according to a well-ordered plan. A cornet solo by Mr. K. Tuma and several numbers by the Deutsche Militaer-Gesangverein (German Military Chorus) received well-merited applause.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1761.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Of course, the high light of the celebration consisted in the presentation of the two flags--one being the American flag and the other the flag of the Association--to District 379 by the president of the Unterstuetzungsbund, Mr. Louis Volz, of Pittsburgh, who had come here especially to make the presentation.</p>
   <p>In his address he called attention to the faithful services which District 379 had rendered, and congratulated the members upon their performance. After Mr. Karl Barack had accepted the flags in the name of District 379, several more vocal and instrumental pieces were given, and then a ball offered opportunity to the young people to get their money's worth.</p>
   <p>The success of the festival was due in great part to the committee which made the arrangements. It consisted of the following persons: Karl Barack, Viktor Pollak, Erich Klein, [Translator's note: The names of fifteen more persons are given.]</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1762.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Deutsche Unterstuetzungsbund was organized twenty-six years ago, has a membership of 32,000 and a capital of $1,637,356. More than a million dollars has been paid in sick and death benefits, and $1,225,000 has been returned to members of more than ten years' standing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
