<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-01-31">January 31, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">German-English Kindergartens.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0835</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0835.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-01-31">January 31, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN-ENGLISH KINDERGARTENS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The plan of the local district of the National German-American School Association to open, if possible, with the start of the new year (Sept. 1), Free German-English Kindergartens on the North, South, Northwest and Southwest sides of the city, has met with general approval amongst the Germans of Chicago. Now it is necessary to start with the realization of the beautiful thought. The furnishing of the four kindergartens, furniture and teaching material, will require about $2,000.</p>
   <p>The school association expects to obtain localities free of charge from local school, and church parishes, or clubs. The salaries of four teachers and assistants are estimated to amount to $3,000. The entire expense for the first year will amount to about $5,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0836.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The expenses for buying and upkeep of furniture and teaching materials will, of course, decrease in future years, so that the average expense will be around $4,000 a year, or $1,000 per Kindergarten. Inorder to obtain the means to execute the plans, the local school association should grow to a membership of 5,000 individuals, who would pay an annual contribution of at least $1 each. Should not there be found such a member of public spirited men and women among the 230,000 Germans of Chicago? We do not doubt it!</p>
   <p>But still more is necessary than what we already mentioned. The project must not remain dependent on a casual offering. Furthermore, the number of German-English kindergartens should be increased in future years. They shall become lasting and useful places for cultivation of the German language. Therefore it is necessary to create, little by little, funds the interest on which will take care of the upkeep of the kindergartens.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0837.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For the realization of these plans a Ladies Club already has been founded within the National German-American School Association. Also German lodges and clubs were requested by the administration to grant yearly contributions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
