<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-08-16">Aug. 16, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The North Chicago Marksmen's Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1506</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1506.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-08-16">Aug. 16, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORTH CHICAGO MARKSMEN'S ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The North Chicago Marksmen's Association held its regular session at Conrad Folz's hall yesterday. Otto Zetz, president, opened the meeting. About sixty members were present.</p>
   <p>After the reading and acceptance of the minutes of the last meeting, the committee gave its report about the property located at Clybourn, Western and Belmont Avenues, which the Association considered buying for a shooting range. The committee learned that the land in question is encumbered by a mortgage, and that the Association should procure a charter before buying the place.</p>
   <p>It was decided to attend to incorporation procedures immediately, and to send the papers to Springfield as soon as possible, so that the Association can buy the property.</p>
   <p>The organization committee made a provisional draft of the Association's <pb facs="5418474_8_1507.jpg" n="2"/>constitution, which was read by the secretary. The plan provided for the usual bylaws and that the officials of the club shall be a president, a vice-president, a financial secretary, a recording secretary, a treasurer, an executive board of five members, and two master marksmen. The duties of the officials, were explained.</p>
   <p>The treasurer shall relinquish all sums in excess of three hundred dollars (sic), and bills not exceeding twenty-five dollars shall be paid with the concurrence of the president and secretary. All larger bills can be paid only if the membership agrees.</p>
   <p>A majority opinion of the executive board shall suffice to pass a measure. Each member of the board shall give a five-thousand-dollar bond. The treasurer and financial secretary each shall give a one-thousand-dollar bond.</p>
   <p>The constitution was accepted by a large majority. The bylaws will be considered next Friday.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1508.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Since the last meeting, bonds sold and dues received amounted to $1,550. The club, according to yesterday's compilation, has at present 167 members. Altogether $2,240 has been collected, and there are prospects that the organization will be one of the most thriving associations in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
