<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Fackel</title>, (Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung)
<date when="1880-09-05">September 5, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Festival-Excursion of the " Lehr and Wehr Verein" Prize-Target Shooting</title><title level="a" type="sub">At Colchour's Farm in South Chicago, selected as Festival Place.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0035</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-07">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0035.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Fackel</title>, (Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung)
<date when="1880-09-05">September 5, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">FESTIVAL-EXCURSION OF THE " LEHR AND WEHR VEREIN" PRIZE-TARGET SHOOTING</title><title level="a" type="sub">At Colchour's Farm in South Chicago, selected as Festival Place.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Arranged by the Socialist Workers Party, there will be held with the participation of the Armed Organizations, on September 12th, a large excursion to Colchour's Farm in South Chicago. This place was selected, mainly because in spite of its being located outside of the city, it can be easily reached by two railroad lines, which go there directly.</p>
   <p>For this excursion a prize target shooting has been arranged for the purpose of offering an opportunity to the members of the Armed Organizations to show how much they have perfected themselves in the art of shooting. For this purpose two targets will be erected, one for muzzle-loading, one for repeating rifles. At every one of these targets, the shooting will be done for four prizes. The first prize is a beautiful Springfield rifle, the second prize is a Remington Revolver, the third prize 100 cartridges and the fourth prize 50 cartridges.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0036.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Festival promises to be very successful on account of participation of all the "Lehr and Wehrvereine."</p>
   <p>The Committee of Arrangements will take care of a plentiful supply of food and drink and offers to the public all the comforts possible. Families can visit the Festival even with a number of children, because in contrast with other excursions where they were compelled to walk several miles, while here, the railroad stations are practically on the grounds. There will be no dearth of music and dance and the excellent band of the "Lehr and Wehrverein" is going to perform some beautiful pieces. Further details, as previously stated, will appear in the daily newspapers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
