<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-02-20">Feb. 20, 1891, P. 7</date>.
<title level="a">Big Split Among the Turners</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1376</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1376.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-02-20">Feb. 20, 1891, P. 7</date>.
<title level="a">BIG SPLIT AMONG THE TURNERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The split in the ranks of the Turners has come. The strongest society in the National Turnerbund, in fact the society that organized the national body, has practically withdrawn from the big organization. Its eight hundred members will be undoubtedly followed by Turners all over the United States, and it is predicted that in a short time the famous and powerful Turnerbund will be a reminiscence. The trouble originated several years ago on account of the influence Socialists and Anarchists began to exert through the national order. Three blows were struck against this radical rule in Chicago, the last by the North Chicago Turngemeinde. This last is expected to be the final blow which shall divide honest Turners from designing Anarchists and Socialists.</p>
   <p>A few years ago, the better class of Turners allege, socialistic and anarchistic organizations secured membership in the Turnerbund by misrepresentation. It was not long before they began to show their hand. Johann Most and his disciples outnumbered the more conservative members, and the Turnerbund became a machine in their hands. They wielded it for their own purposes. They passed their own laws, one of which was that no member of an individual society could <pb facs="5418474_8_1377.jpg" n="2"/>be expelled except by the Turnerbund, which meets tri-yearly, and that pending the decision of the national body, the accused member was qualified for election to office.</p>
   <p>Some of the Turners talked of repellion. Dissatisfaction grew. And then began the war. Chicago is the stronghold of the Turners. It contains thirty-four societies with a membership of about five thousand. Here it was that the first blow was struck against the radical Turners. The West Side society withdrew from the Turnerbund and formed what is called the National Turnverein. But the blow did not cripple the Turnerbund. It proceeded on the plans laid out by Most and his satellites. About two weeks ago came the second shock. The South Side Turners withdrew and formed an independent organization. Things began to look ominous for the Turnerbund.</p>
   <p>But the withdrawal of the North Side Turners is looked upon as the knock-out blow. The indirect causes of the latest split is Julius Vahlteich, a photographer, who is said to have fled from Germany after having been condemned for his connection with anarchistic societies. He joined the North Chicago Turnergemeinde. Not long ago, he was tried for disclosing secrets of his society and defaming the officers of the organization, and found guilty. The society wished to expell <pb facs="5418474_8_1378.jpg" n="3"/>him, but some of the members said this would be unconstitutional. Attention was then called to the arbitrary law of the national body, and the majority of the North Siders favored ignoring the constitional provision.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, the district board, a body that is supordinate to the national organization, and has control over the societies in the Chicago district, stepped in and notified the North Siders to defer action, until a decision could be rendered in the Vahlteich case. The North Chicago Turngemeinde ignored the district board, and also determined to ignore the national body, the Turnerbund.</p>
   <p>Wednesday night the Turngemeinde met at the North Side Turner Hall. The gathering was the largest in the history of the society, and the session lasted until after midnight. President Blum of the district board was present and asked that Vahlteich be permitted to remain in the society until a decision could be received from the highest authority. A warm discussion arose about the anarchistic and socialistic leaders taken in by the Turnerbund. It was shown that since the national body took on its more radical complexion, quarrels between it and the North Chicago Turngemeinde had been frequent, and the best way to avoid repitition of these quarrels would be to withdraw from the Turnerbund. The question of Vahlteich's expulsion came up and he was custed by a vote of 132 to 37.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1379.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This is in effect the Turngemeinde's resignation. It refuses to obey the laws of the national body, and will therefore have to be suspended. This is what the local body desires. The North Chicago Turngemeinde organized the national body; it was the leading power in the Turnerbund until the radicals secured sway, it contains about eight hundred members, and its standing and strength secure it a large following.</p>
   <p>It is now expected that the split will extend throughout the United States and that all conservatives will leave the Turnerbund and form independent societies, as has been done here. The chances are that a new national body will be formed by the conservative element, after which the division between radicals and conservatives will be complete. The withdrawal of the patriotic element will sap the strength of the Turnerbund, removing from it tone and standing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
