<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-02-04">February 4, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">A Lecture of Professor Francke</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1056</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1056.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-02-04">February 4, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">A LECTURE OF PROFESSOR FRANCKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Professor Kuno Francke, German professor of Harvard University, gave last night at the Fullerton Hall of the Art Institute a very interesting lecture in German cities and their origin.</p>
   <p>Aided by lantern slide-pictures, Professor Francke showed and explained, how small settlements about some German town or castle slowly grew up to become towns and later large cities.</p>
   <p>The period from the 10th to the 14th century is representing a steadily progressing development of the townfolks, of whom some families became extremely wealthy. The cities soon took over the whole administration and tore loose from the domination of nobility. Also gradually the free cities were fighting off the domineering interference by the then mighty Catholic Church.</p>
   <p>While the Trades organized their various powerful Guilds, the wealthy Patricians consolidated their influence and privileges as prosperous <pb facs="5418474_8_1057.jpg" n="2"/>merchants and bankers. With the final exclusion of noblemen, the city-councils then consisted of about 2/3 guildsmen and 1/3 patricians. During this period up to the beginning of the 16th century, Germany controlled the commerce of the whole Europe and was predominant in trades, arts and science.</p>
   <p>The Reformation by Martin Luther gave German intelligence a powerful impetus towards world dominion, if it would not have been for the 30 years's war, which set Germany back for 100 years in its future development, until the rise of the Kingdom of Prussia and German Empire.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
