<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-10-03">Oct. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">New Yearbook Almost Completed</title><title level="a" type="sub">German-American Historical Society of Illinois Active Again</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0371</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0371.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-10-03">Oct. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">NEW YEARBOOK ALMOST COMPLETED</title><title level="a" type="sub">German-American Historical Society of Illinois Active Again</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Now that the World War has practically ended, we can confidently express the hope that reason and clear thinking will return to our country. We hope that the artificially created sentiment against anything German will soon disappear and with it the persecution mania which has been directed toward so many of our fellow-citizens. The work of German-American culture has had to wait long and patiently for the moment when it can again step before the public and unfold its sublime and idealistic contents without interference.</p>
   <p>During this interval, since the entry of the United States into the war, the German-American Historical Society of Illinois had had to keep out of the public eye. They did not hibernate however; they have been continuously collecting material which can and will be used to create a great work-not only for the German element in America, but for all Americans regardless of racial origin. This work will serve the whole world as an inspiring example for the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0372.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since its inception it has been the earnest endeavor of the German-American Historical Society of Illinois to uncover the truth from the shadows of the past. Inspired by the same principle, the long anticipated annual chronicle of 1917, Historical Leaflets, Volume XVII, is to be placed before the public within the next few days.</p>
   <p>The feature of the yearbook is the "Diary of the Anspach-Bayreuthian Soldier, Conrad Doehla, during the American Campaign, 1777-1783." This account tells of his experiences from the time of his departure from Bayreuth until his return to his native land. Doehla fought on the English side and his diary is a very interesting work, doubly so now, because in the last war American soldiers fought together with the British and French against Germany. A comparison of this diary with the many war diaries which have been published in recent years is extremely interesting and educational.</p>
   <p>A second article, by Oscar F. Fernsemer, relates to "Daniel Defoe and the Palatine Emigratior of 1710: A New View of the Origin of Robinson Crusoe".</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0373.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Then there is an article by Max J. Kohler on "An Important European Commission to Investigate American Emigration Conditions, 1817-1818". There follows an extract from the work, "The German in North America," which was published by Moritz von Fuerstenwarther in 1818.</p>
   <p>There is also an extremely interesting article, "Julius Minding, a Forgotten German-American Dramatist," by Paul Eimmormann.</p>
   <p>This short outline indicates the abundant contents of the yearbook which, like its predecessors, will show the cultural influence of the German spirit on the American scene.</p>
   <p>The preparations for the yearbook of 1918-1919 are in progress now, and a large number of important articles are ready for the printer.</p>
   <p>The headquarters of the Society are still on the sixteenth floor of the Mallers Building and its secretary, Mr. Max Baum, will gladly give any information desired.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0374.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The yearly dues of the Society are still three dollars, and this fee entitles each member to a free copy of the book.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
