<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-06-01">June 1, 1871</date><title level="a">Addenda Ad: Peace Celebration.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0246</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-07">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0246.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-06-01">June 1, 1871</date><title level="a">ADDENDA AD: PEACE CELEBRATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The quiet which prevailed yesterday in the city was to be admired, and the Germans deserve credit for it, because there certainly was no lack of provocations. Already early in the morning a proclamation in English was found distributed in a hundred thousand copies all over the city in which the citizens of Chicago were asked to remain inside their houses and not even to look at this parade of despotism, and of the murderers of liberty. All the Germans did was to tear down these posters and destroy them. At north Clark, close to the bridge hung a big inscription: "Denmark mourns with France". In Clinton Street lives a fanatical Irishman who did not permit anybody to stand before his house. In order to drive away the unwelcome spectators he poured water from time to time on their heads. All along the route of the parade there were Irishmen and Irishwomen who uttered abuse and argued and frequently became so absolutely insulting that it needed indeed, German patience to avoid brawls. Only in one case a somewhat too obstreperous fellow got one over his back with the blunt side of a sabre that he had to be led away by his friends. A <pb facs="5418474_8_0247.jpg" n="2"/>Frenchman, M. George Duponte, in South Clark Street, had fixed a rope across the street just in front of the triumphal arch, and suspended on it a picture, showing Napoleon III hanging on the gallows, with the caption: "Vile assassin" and "Homme du 2 decembre".</p>
   <p>For the first time the German fashion of erecting tribunes was adopted in Chicago. In all parts of the city stood tribunes for 50 - 500 persons, and one had to pay 50 cents to $1.00 for a seat. For some windows $5.00 had been paid, while in some parts of the city even seats on the roofs were offered for 25 cents.</p>
   <p>The English press gave the celebration not a little attention. The Times had a very long report, that, however, was full of the most grotesque mistakes, due to total ignorance of German history. The Tribune likewise reported at length, but has the most annoying habit of interspersing articles about things German with the four words that from the whole German vocabulary of the editors: namely, "Gemuthlichkeit", "ein Lager", "noch Zwei" and now and then name "Gretchen". There lies a goodly portion of impudence in this.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0248.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The editor of the Republican issued a short, carping, malevolent article. He believes in carrying favor with his special class of readers by maligning the Germans. The Evening Post expresses unconditional recognition and the Journal is outrightly enthusiastic. It says: "Chicago has been taken by storm by the Germans...The big procession was the longest and most impressive Chicago has ever seen.."</p>
   <p>On the whole the English press is delighted and gives unstinted praise to the magnificent event....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
