<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-02-21">February 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">German Circles Beginning of the Golden Jubilee Celebration of the Aurora Turner Club.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1276</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1276.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-02-21">February 21, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN CIRCLES BEGINNING OF THE GOLDEN JUBILEE CELEBRATION OF THE AURORA TURNER CLUB.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The history of this Club, is, in short, as follows: The Aurora Turner Club was founded on February 22nd, 1864 and consisted at that time of 28 members. The Club treasury contained $42.00 and the meetings were held at the old Aurora Turner Hall, Milwaukee Avenue and Ohio Street.</p>
   <p>In June 1865, the Club joined the North American Turner League. In 1867, the Aurora Turner Hall at Milwaukee and Huron Street was built and the Club increased its membership during the following 10 years.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately the income of the organization did not keep in line with its expenses and in 1877 the Club was compelled to sell the hall. Although the membership went back again from 250 to 28 members, the Club remained active. The conditions of the rapidly growing City forced it again and again to move its home, first from Milwaukee and Huron to Ashland and Division, then to Milwaukee and California, and at present its home is the former Gut Heil <pb facs="5418474_8_1277.jpg" n="2"/>Turner Hall, at Belmont and Albany Avenues. Within the last decade, the Turner Clubs Westside, Voran, Fortschritt, Gut Heil and Almira merged with the Aurora Club and the pioneers of all these societies are today assembled to celebrate the Golden Jubilee of the Aurora Turner Club. They will recall the time when the "Knownothings" tried to disturb their meetings, when the fights between "Reds" and "Blues" were common. More than that, they will think of the periods when they returned from festivals decorated with laurel wreaths and medals. They also will remember those, who with never-tiring interest, published the Club magazine "Die Waage" (The Scale).</p>
   <p>The festivities began yesterday evening at the Wicker Park Halls and will last for two days. All Chicago Turner Clubs, the Ladies Turner Club Aurora, and several singing societies will participate in the program...</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
