<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-11-28">Nov. 28, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Turngemeinde and General Grant</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1452</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1452.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-11-28">Nov. 28, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE TURNGEMEINDE AND GENERAL GRANT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Public: In response to criticism involving the Chicago Turngemeinde (Turner Association) because of Messrs. Max Stern's and Peter Hand's unfortunate solicitation of funds from General Grant, the Turngemeinde desires to submit the following facts to the people of Chicago, who so generously are trying to raise money to pay the second mortgage on the Turnhalle (Turner Hall):</p>
   <p>1) The Chicago Turngemeinde did not send a committee to see General Grant.</p>
   <p>2) The committee, consisting of Messrs. Stern and Hand, was nominated by the citizens' committee which was in charge of the drive. But even the citizens' committee gave no hint whatsoever that General Grant should be approached in the matter.</p>
   <p>3) The collections committee did not receive any compensation for its activities, and none were promised, neither by the citizen's committee nor by the Turngemeinde. If any reimbursement should be called for, the money would have to be provided by the members of the Turngemeinde, <pb facs="5418474_8_1453.jpg" n="2"/>since the collected moneys were earmarked for one purpose only--the payment of the Turnhalle's second mortgage.</p>
   <p>4) The second mortgage, held by Mr. Freygang of New York, was secured by personal guarantee of thirty-five members of the Turngemeinde so as not to jeopardize the $40,000 given by Chicagoans when the Turnhalle was built.</p>
   <p>5) The Turngemeinde does not care to take part in a newspaper controversy, but is willing to give any bona fide committee all possible information on the subject in question. The conduct of our Association during the last quarter-century, and our reputation in general, we believe, give sufficient guarantee for the truth of our statements.</p>
   <p>In behalf of the Chicago Turngemeinde:</p>
   <p>Joseph Kaufmann,</p>
   <p>Philipp Stein,</p>
   <p>Carl Meyer,</p>
   <p>Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
