<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-02-13">Feb. 13, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[Lecture before the German-American Historical Society]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-02-13">Feb. 13, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">[LECTURE BEFORE THE GERMAN-AMERICAN HISTORICAL SOCIETY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German-American Historical Society held last night their annual general meeting in the "Chicago Historical Society". Judge Eberhardt the President, opened the meeting at half past eight and introduced Dr. Evarts E. B. Greene, of the University at Champaign. He spoke about Gustav Koerner, the typical German-American diplomat. The speaker mentioned first the bad political condition of Germany after the wars of independence. He pointed out the activities of the League of Virtue and the secret societies of students and gave a short description of the Frankfort attentat. By his participation in this unsuccessful riot Gustav Koerner was obliged to flee from Germany. He came to Belleville and established hinself as a lawyer. He became one of the most important members of the legislature and was chosen by the governor as a member of the State's Supreme Court. At the following election the nomination for this office was offered to him, but he had to refuse as the salary of $1200 was insufficent for the maintenance of his family. Soon afterwards as a Democrat he was elected as Vice-Governor, but before the expiration <pb facs="5418474_8_1063.jpg" n="2"/>of his office he turned Republican, which was considered much in his favor because of his personal relations with Senator Douglas. He attended the Republican National Convention at Chicago in 1860. He was the first of the delegates to visit Lincoln at his modest residence at Springfield after the convention. As an an anecdote it is said, that Koerner advised Mrs. Lincoln, when she prepared a reception lunch for the delegation, which had come to inform Lincoln about his nomination, not to put any whisky and champagne on the table as among the members of the delegation there might be some prohibitionists. Koerner had been chosen by Lincoln as a successor to Schurz, who retired as ambassador to Spain to join the army, but he was not much taken with this office, as he expected a higher position in the diplomatic service of the Republic such as an ambassadorship to Berlin or Vienna. After the end of the war Koerner did not take much part in the political field, but till his death a few years ago he was a good example of true citizenship and had the esteem of his follow citizens in large circles.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1064.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Lincoln and the Germans</p>
   <p>The second speaker of the evening was Mr. Otto C. Schneider who gave a description of the relationship of Abraham Lincoln and the German-Americans. He started with the political change caused by the acceptance of the Kansas-Nebraska Bill, especially the influence of same with the German-American element of the citizens in the North; how the greater part, which formerly had been Democratic now went Republican, and how he helped to organize them. In the year 1858, when Lincoln, who 2 years previously nearly became Vice-President to Fremont, opposed Douglas in the Senate, the cream of the Germans in Chicago under guidance of George Schneider, Kaspar Batz, Henry Greenebaum etc., sided with the Republican candidate. Karl Schurz, who for this election had been lent from Wisconsin, did much in the campaign on the side of the Republican Party. Lincoln's nomination in the year 1860 was the result of an arrangement between the Radicals voting for Seward and the Conservatives. The election of Lincoln according to the election reports was the result of the voting of 500,000 German-Americans for the Republican candidate. If only half of them had voted for Douglas it would have turned the scale in his favor. Lincoln often expressed himself favorably about <pb facs="5418474_8_1065.jpg" n="4"/>the loyalty of the German-Americans. The well-known modesty of the German citizens in not pushing themselves to the front in the job hunting, is the reason, that the German element was not considered to a great extent in the administration. The speaker than pointed out the dissatisfaction in German circles at the beginning of the administration caused by the long period of waiting and delay about the repeal of slavery. There was a movement to nominate in 1864, an independent Republican opposing candidate. Fremont who had already accepted the nomination however refused later. Especially two newspapers the Milwaukee Herald and the Cleveland Guardian were for a long time opposed to Lincoln; as he would not put their demands in his programme, that after the subduing of the rebellious Southern States, the slave holders should have to give up their lands and properties as a punishment for their misdeeds.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
