<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-08-23">August 23, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">German - English School of Fick and Schutt.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0822</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0822.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-08-23">August 23, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN - ENGLISH SCHOOL OF FICK AND SCHUTT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German-English school, managed by Fick and Schutt and located at 621-623 N. Wells Street, is starting its third term on Monday, the 3rd of September.</p>
   <p>This school was established to meet the need of locally ambitious Germans, who desire that their children should learn the German as well as the English language, and that they should be trained to think independently, instead of merely exercising the faculty of memory thoughtlessly. The rapid growth of the school under the able and sympathetic leadership of its directors and teachers is sufficient evidence of the widespread and urgent demand for it.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0823.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The progress that has been achieved so far must be recognized as very satisfactory, generally speaking. A considerably higher degree of knowledge and skill was obtained, on the average, than with children in public schools of the same age and in the same grades. This fact has been proved by the results of examinations. In view of the many difficulties experienced in forming a new school where children come together with various degrees of preparatory instruction, the above is a very outstanding result.</p>
   <p>The Fick and Schutt school hopes to equip its scholars for the practical and realistic phases of living, by giving them the following fundamental training: Complete mastery of the English as well as the German language, thorough and lasting training in all important branches of knowledge and skill, as, for instance, arithmetic, theoretic and applied, geology, physiology, chemistry, anatomy, hygiene, natural history, drawing, singing, <pb facs="5418474_8_0824.jpg" n="3"/>needle-work, and, besides this, as far as possible, a comprehensive understanding of world-history, and an extensive acquaintance with the treasures of literature, particularly in the German and English languages. To state briefly: It is the aim of this school to give to its scholars the best training possible during the periods provided, to educate not only their heads but also their hearts, and develop their eyes, their hands, and their whole bodies by gymnastics.</p>
   <p>A number of magnanimous German-American citizens planned the construction of a larger building. It was erected during last winter and, according to the unanimous opinions of experts, it is the best arranged school of its kind in the whole United States. It has been built with particular regard toward guarding and maintaining the health of the children. All classrooms are large and provided with abundance of daylight; the heating <pb facs="5418474_8_0825.jpg" n="4"/>and ventilation is well taken care of, and there are also large play grounds equipped with gymnastic apparatuses, separate for boys and girls. The school moved into this new building at the beginning of May. Its favorable location, where it can be easily reached by street cars, is also recommended. This all has been done to make the benefits of this school available to a larger number of children of German-American parents and other nationalities, who can appreciate the advantages of such a school.</p>
   <p>In the name of those who have donated of their means to this institution not from selfish motives, but to establish a good foundation and a permanent location for a German-English school - the undersigned appeal to all German fellow-citizens to send their children to this German-English school, provided, of course, they have the necessary means, and desire to give their children a true education for mind and heart, and to retain for them the treasure of their mother-tongue.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0826.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The school can reach the degree of perfection desired by its founders only if the German-Americans send their children in greater numbers to this school, thereby making it possible for the officials to obtain more efficient teachers.</p>
   <p>Hermann Raster,</p>
   <p>Carl Beer,</p>
   <p>Ph. Henne,</p>
   <p>Ed. Koch,</p>
   <p>Th. Karls,</p>
   <p>E. Mannhardt.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
