<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-06-28">June 28, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Victorious Turners Return.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1299</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1299.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-06-28">June 28, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE VICTORIOUS TURNERS RETURN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5 - A reception befitting our victorious turners was arranged for them, by their fellow turners. The turner halls were beautifully decorated, for the welcome home, of the proud prize winners from Chicago, who have added another glorious victory, to the annals of the turners.</p>
   <p>On their arrival, they were officially greeted by Turner Berkes. Soon, the procession headed by a band, and by bearers of flags, was on the way to the North Side Turner Hall. There, they were welcomed with a thunderous "Gut Heil!" by the passive members of the Turner Society, and by almost all the members of the woman's association, who formed a lane on the staircase. After the enthusiasm died down, Comrade Emil Hoechster thanked the returning turners, in the name of the turner community, for the glory <pb facs="5418474_8_1300.jpg" n="2"/>added to the society at the recent festival, held by the United Turner Societies, in Philadelphia.</p>
   <p>The singing section of the turners, is giving an entertainment at the North Side Turner Hall this evening, in honor of its conductor, Mr. F. A. Kern. It was under his leadership that the singers were awarded the first prize for class two - and this in spite of the fact, that all the other competing singing societies, were represented by at least 12 more men each. The Chicago Turner Association won, through their representatives at the last festival, the following prizes: The Turner's Male Chorus, first prize of class 2; Alfred Arens, first prize for the one-mile cycling-race, and also for the five-mile race; C. Waldbott, first prize for rapier fencing, and second prize for saber fencing; L. O. Greiner, first prize for saber fencing and second prize for rapier fencing; Georg Freibert, fifth prize for rapier fencing.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1301.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>An almost royal reception was given the victorious Turners of the Lincoln Turner Society. After an enthusiastic welcome home, Comrade Chris. Meier addressed the prize winners, but was stopped frequently by the wildest applause. The leading gymnast, Aug. Hoffmann, then delivered to Chris. Meier, the first speaker, the wreath of laurels with a diploma, which he won as the 7th prize of grade 3 for gymnastic exhibitions. Turner teacher, Mr. Meier, presented then to the assembled guests, the 12 prize winners, who composed the champion team. He presented also Messrs. Aug. Hoffmann, Fritz Zeller, Richard Wagner and Fred Zansius, the winners of prizes for individual gymnastic exhibitions. The audience honored them by a long continued ovation.</p>
   <p>The Central Turner Society, the "Fortschritt" and the Aurora Turner societies also paid due tribute to their returning prize winners.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
