<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-25">Nov. 25, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Professor Schuetze Lecture before Deutsche Literarische Gesellschaft</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0899</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0899.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-25">Nov. 25, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">PROFESSOR SCHUETZE LECTURE BEFORE DEUTSCHE LITERARISCHE GESELLSCHAFT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Deutsche Literarische Gesellschaft (German Literary Society), which held its regular meeting at the Bismarck Hotel yesterday evening, secured the services of Professor Martin Schuetze as speaker. Professor Schuetze, who has been at the head of the German Department of the University of Chicago for many years, is an enthusiastic champion of the German language and German literature. His many years' experience with men and women students has taught him how the teaching of German in this country can be maintained and made fruitful.</p>
   <p>In his many appeals to Chicago Germans, Professor Schuetze has always emphasized the fact that language is not only a practical means of expression, but that it expresses in a living way, the spirit, mood, and nature of a people. Professor Schuetze began his lecture yesterday by stating this view; and he again emphasized the fact that this theory of the nature of language, which was originated by Herder and developed by Goethe, must be considered an extremely important factor <pb facs="5418474_8_0900.jpg" n="2"/>in the teaching of German in this country.</p>
   <p>For this reason Professor Schuetze wishes to start a periodical which would give students of the German language an opportunity of write in German of their observations, impressions, and views, and to convey these thoughts and feelings to their fellow devotees. He not only desires to give the youth in the schools, and all those who cherish the German language, access to German culture, but he also wishes to give them an opportunity to express American life and its reactions in the German language.</p>
   <p>Professor Schetze was able to give his remarks a personal touch. He illustrated his lecture with many allusions to history, and also drew material from his own rich horde of observations and experiences.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
