<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-05">Oct. 5, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Football Reports</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1204</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1204.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-05">Oct. 5, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">FOOTBALL REPORTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Schwaben Athletic Club vs. Chicago Sport Club.-- The matches of these teams have always been interesting, and for the last few years they have also been the most decent one could see. It was not always like that, but fortunately both camps arrived at the conviction that more can be attained by comradeship and friendly spirit than by club fanaticism. And so this time a match was played in which every player displayed great zeal to gain victory for his own flag, remaining fair and decent withal. Neither team had enough players to put on a spectacular battle. The Sport Club was compelled to play without Tan-nert, Kroll, Boyens, and Frey. Mueller was playing with an injured hand. The Swabians had to replace such players as Jordan, Breithaupt, Teschner, Absiel, and Trimmel. The substitute men of the Swabians were superior to those of the Chicago Sport Club, and thus the Blue-and-White victory.</p>
   <p>The eleven victors deserve the praise of all. For the Chicago Sport Club, Rudel, Daiber, Mueller, Weiss, and Schmuck were the stars.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1205.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Last Sunday the first team of the first German Sport Club had their third match against the Football Club Wanderers. Although the men, because of the incapacity of some of the players, could not step out in the manner they intended, they did their best to chalk up points.</p>
   <p>Vienna Football Club vs. Norwegians</p>
   <p>The Norwegians turned out a strong and quick team last Sunday. With a little more luck they might have succeeded in winning all the points from the Viennese.</p>
   <p>Wanderers vs. Danes</p>
   <p>The second Wanderer team seems to have recovered its composure since last year. Being sure of themselves, they could beat the second team of the Danish eleven. Good offensive and defensive work left no doubt about their superiority.</p>
   <p>Wanderers Freedom Football Club</p>
   <p>The third team of the Wanderers is now going from one victory to another. The <pb facs="5418474_8_1206.jpg" n="3"/>team is possessed of an excellent sporting spirit. Considerably strengthened by two new players, they decisively beat the strongest opponent in their division. The whole team took part in the victory and every individual player deserves praise.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
