<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-12-29">December 29, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Jahn Statue</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1284</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1284.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-12-29">December 29, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE JAHN STATUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Turner Club of Chicago had for some time the intention of making a present to the new Fredrich Ludwig Jahn School at their opening celebration in honor of the name of the great Turner master, adopted by them. A committee of five had been selected to study the situation. They came to the conclusion of having a bust made of bronze and an original drawing of the Master. None of the busts however correspond with their expectation to serve as a model and the committee instructed the well-known sculptor Hermann Gensch with the production of an original bust. This great master has produced a wonderful worl according to the opinions of experts one of the best Jahn busts in existence. The picture, an original sketch made by Turner Hermann Rascher will be suitably framed and will be hung up in the new school. The Friedrich Ludwig Jahn School is located at the corner of Lincoln and Belmont and is built according to the newest and most modern plans.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1285.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Turner of Chicago can be proud of the worthy memorial, that the school board of Chicago has created by giving the school the name of their father Jahn and they therefore appreciate the work of the Committee in presenting to the school the best they could find regardless of expense.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
