<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-01-20">Jan. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Germany at War</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Greatest Moral Spectacle the World Has Ever Seen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1015</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1015.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-01-20">Jan. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANY AT WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Greatest Moral Spectacle the World Has Ever Seen</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A realistic picture of the spirit which moves the German people in their hour of trial was given yesterday by Dr. Eugene Kuehnemann in his lecture entitled "Das Deutschtum in Seiner Entscheidungsstunde" [The Critical Hour of Germany] before the members of the Germanistic Society of Chicago [Translator's note: not to be confused with the German Society, a charitable organization] in Fullerton Hall of the Art Institute. The large attendance proved that the German element of Chicago takes the most vital interest in the struggle of the German brothers overseas. The Hall was filled to overflowing. Even the stage had to be used to accomodate the crowd. The stormy applause which frequently interrupted the speaker showed that his listeners were in accord with his views. That the speaker had stirred his audience to enthusiasm could be seen from the fact that at the conclusion they all rose from their seats and sang "Deutschland, Deutschland ueber Alles" [German National anthem].</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1016.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Using Goethe's "Faust" as an example, the speaker showed that the ultimate aim of all human endeavor is working for the common good of the people. Goethe's "Faust" clearly had the Deutschtum of today in mind. He [Faust] was the promulgator of German thought, the same that is inspiring the German people in their present struggle.</p>
   <p>"Now," the speaker continued, "one has discovered here in America that German Kultur means something other than the English culture. German Kultur is something special, according to that American professor whose work should find a place in the books on logic as an example of irrational reasoning. The German word in particular, means the individual development of the soul, which has found its relation to the eternal spirit and lives in harmony with it. The German people have acquired this harmonious relationship.</p>
   <p>"Frederich the Great planted into the German soul the longing for a greater Germany, unified and free. But the German spirit [soul] and the German state [form of government] were still at odds with each other. The tribulations <pb facs="5418474_8_1017.jpg" n="3"/>of the Napoleonic wars changed that. Only in 1813 did German idealism find an expression in the national idea of government, with which it became identical. This national idea was based on the conception that it was a man's supreme duty and honor to bear the responsibility for his country's greatness and existence as a nation, and it is still the basic reason for Prussian militarism and for compulsory military service, which is not so much a duty as it is a privilege. In 1848 the German [liberal] thought and the German state almost came to terms, but it remained for Bismarck to complete the merger and make it official. Bismarck instilled into the German soul the longing for power and participation in the affairs of the world. An agricultural Germany became industrialized, a feudal Germany became democratic. The first decade of the new Reich saw the old men in power, but with the youthful emperor William II a new era was ushered in.</p>
   <p>"A young monarch and a young people did not see eye to eye. The Kaiser wanted to be a second Charlemagne. He wanted to supervise any and all activities in the Reich. The Germans are not the most docile people in the <pb facs="5418474_8_1018.jpg" n="4"/>world (I know another people who think they have a monopoly on freedom, but are much more docile); but they are the proudest and most independent. They want to shape their own lives, develop their own art and literature, and direct their own politics. When the Kaiser attempted to meddle in foreign affairs, the entire nation, including the Reichs-Chancellor, rose in protest. It was then that the German people asserted their democratic spirit. Name me another ruler who was ever told by his people not to interfere in foreign politics.</p>
   <p>"The greatest ambition of William II was to be recorded in history as the 'Prince of Peace'. But things turned out differently. Just as Prussia during the Seven Years' War was forced to establish her right to an existence the new German Reich has now to defend her right to exist as a nation. This struggle, which was forced upon us, will reveal the German spirit. We Germans are individualists. Our political life proves it. There has never been a case in our history in which the entire people have unanimously accepted a certain idea. But now this has happened. From the first day [of the war] <pb facs="5418474_8_1019.jpg" n="5"/>the nation was solidly united. In a single day the German soul [spirit] revealed itself in all its glory. There was only one desire: to give--to sacrifice everything for the national idea."</p>
   <p>Dr. Kuehnemann related several instances to show the unanimity of the German people when making sacrifices in this war. France wanted this war. Her own reckless policy and the conniving of her allies had unloosed the catastrophe. Russia had wanted war in order to satisfy her ambitions for a great Russian continental empire, comprising Asia and Europe with Constantinople. England wanted war. But Germany did not need it to fulfill her mission. That is why the German people went to war gladly and with a clean conscience, knowing that it was divine providence that decreed it. Pre-war Europe had found it impossible to grant the Germans the right to live. The result had been this war, which the German people had gladly and unanimously accepted. They fought for truth and liberty. That alone should have been reason enough for America to understand the German people, but England's shameless lies prevented this understanding.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1020.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"Anyone who has seen these people in their unity and sacred determination to win knows that they cannot be defeated, that victory will be theirs," the speaker continued. "Russia and France know that they cannot win. Once England has realized that her plan to starve out Germany, which is so characteristic of British civilization and humanitarianism, must fail--and any economist can tell you that it will not work--she too will awaken to the fact that Germany is invincible. The war has already disclosed one fact: The invincible British fleet has failed in its mission. There never was such heroism as that of Germany and Austria-Hungary, standing alone against a world; and this world will not get the better of them. This Germany of the first five war months presents the greatest moral spectacle the world has seen for centuries. The war has proved Germany to be a storehouse of inexhaustible moral resources. The spirit of Frederick the Great has become the spirit of the German people. The spirit of his tenacious perseverance has been revived again in Germany."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
