<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1870-08-30">Aug. 30, 1870</date>.
<title level="a">The Fair Opens</title><title level="a" type="sub">Farwell Mall Beautifully Decorated</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0263</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-07">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0263.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1870-08-30">Aug. 30, 1870</date>.
<title level="a">THE FAIR OPENS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Farwell Mall Beautifully Decorated</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note: The first seven paragraphs of this article are an appeal to the public to co-operate with the German Patriotic Aid Society by attending and purchasing articles at a fair, held for the benefit of wounded German soldiers of their widows and orphans. This part of the article is irrelevant.]</p>
   <p>The following committees and salesladies have been appointed by the central committee:</p>
   <p>First table</p>
   <p>Finance committee: Miss M. Hinrichs, Mrs. G. Pruessing, Mrs. G. Lippmann.</p>
   <p>Salesladies: Miss. Emeline Kurth, Mrs. B. Leon, Mrs. O. Horwitz, Miss I. Lackner, Miss Clara Hinrichs.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0264.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Second table</p>
   <p>Finance committee: Mrs. E. Juessen, Mrs. P. Campbell, Mrs. C. Mueller.</p>
   <p>Salesladies: Miss B. Florsheim, Miss E. Juessen, Mrs. B. Mueller, Mrs. N. Greenbaum.</p>
   <p>Third table</p>
   <p>Finance committee: Mrs. J. Polatscheck, Mrs. C. Jordan, Mrs. D. Anderson.</p>
   <p>Salesladies: Miss M. Polatscheck, Miss A. Richberg, Miss. P. Staab, Mrs. O. Clare, Mrs. C. Reed.</p>
   <p>Fourth table</p>
   <p>Finance committee: Miss F. Somme, Miss P. Hepp, Mrs. D. Engel.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0265.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Salesladies: Miss H. Assendorf, Mrs. W. Molter, Mrs. O. Stolz, Miss M. Oertel.</p>
   <p>Fifth table</p>
   <p>Finance committee: Mrs. C. Goodkind, Mrs. P. Reinhold, Mrs. D. Schmidt, Mrs. E. Wothenow.</p>
   <p>Salesladies: Mrs. G. Hevermann, Miss R. Mertle, Miss F. Melms, Miss C. Hochbaum, Miss A. Mannheimer, Miss H. Shaberg, Mrs. A. Kirchhoff.</p>
   <p>Sixth table</p>
   <p>Finance committee: Miss M. Heinrichs, Mrs. D. Bluthardt, Mrs. A. Magnus.</p>
   <p>Salesladies: Mrs. P. Knadler, Miss H. Meyer, Miss D. Friedberg, Miss M. Telschow.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0266.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Seventh table</p>
   <p>Finance committee: Mrs. F. Hoffmann, Mrs. O. Goldschmidt, Miss C. Kurz.</p>
   <p>Salesladies: Miss L. Hartmann, Miss H. Kahl, Mrs. P. Baum, Mrs. A. Loeb, Mrs. M. Meyer.</p>
   <p>Eight table</p>
   <p>Finance committee: Miss D. Kirchner, Mrs. J. Bertrand, Miss L. Mehrle.</p>
   <p>Salesladies: Miss G. Oppenheimer, Miss F. Huschle, Miss M. Hevermann, Miss K. Saum</p>
   <p>Ninth table</p>
   <p>Finance committee: Mrs. C. Vocke, Mrs. O. Thiele, Mrs. F. Frese.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0267.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Salesladies: Mrs. M. Lichtenhein, Miss A. Unna, Miss L. Manigold, Miss P. Cassel.</p>
   <p>Tenth table</p>
   <p>Finance committee: Mrs. E. Knipke, Miss E. Metzke, Miss L, Juessen.</p>
   <p>Salesladies: Mrs. A. Steiger, Miss E. Suss, Miss C. Hahler, Miss B. Mannheimer, Miss M. Reitler.</p>
   <p>The parade in which the local Italian societies will participate promises to be very impressive.</p>
   <p>Order of the parade</p>
   <p>First division</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0268.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Meeting place: Randolph Street and Michigan Avenue.</p>
   <p>Order</p>
   <p>Police</p>
   <p>National Guard</p>
   <p>Company B. National Guard</p>
   <p>Great Western Light Guard Band</p>
   <p>Marshals and Adjutants</p>
   <p>Chicago Turngemeinde</p>
   <p>Union Turnverein</p>
   <p>Aurora Turnverein</p>
   <p>Vorwaerts Turnverein</p>
   <p>Germaina Turnverein</p>
   <p>Chicago Schuetzenverein</p>
   <p>West Side Schuetzenverein</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0269.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Second division</p>
   <p>Meeting place: Michigan Avenue and Washington Street.</p>
   <p>Order</p>
   <p>Freier Saengerbund</p>
   <p>Germania Maennerchor</p>
   <p>Concordia Maennerchor</p>
   <p>Arion Gesangverein</p>
   <p>Orpheus Gesangverein</p>
   <p>Frohsinn Gesangverein</p>
   <p>Teutonia Gesangverein</p>
   <p>Schleswig-Holstein Verein</p>
   <p>Hamburger Club</p>
   <p>Frohsinn Geselliger Verein</p>
   <p>Berliner Humoristischer Club</p>
   <p>Union Veteranen Unterstuetzungs Verein</p>
   <p>Arbeiter Verein</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0270.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>Third division</p>
   <p>Meeting place: Wabash Avenue and Washington Street.</p>
   <p>Order</p>
   <p>Order of Hermannssoehnf</p>
   <p>All Orders of Chaldaeer</p>
   <p>Teutonia Lodge, #96, Harugari</p>
   <p>Harmonia Lodge, #130, Harugari</p>
   <p>Concordia Lodge, #15</p>
   <p>Independent Order of Red Men</p>
   <p>Robert Blum Lodge, #6</p>
   <p>Goethe Lodge, Independent Order of Odd Fellows</p>
   <p>Northwestern Lodge, Independent Order of Odd Fellows</p>
   <p>Knights of Pythias, Humboldt Lodge, #2</p>
   <p>Arbeiter Unterstuetzungs Orden</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0271.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Chicago Arbeiterverein</p>
   <p>German Employees of Union Hide and Leather Company</p>
   <p>German Workmen's Union</p>
   <p>Route</p>
   <p>South on Wabash Avenue to Van Buren Street, west to Desplaines Street, north to Lake Street, east to Wells Street, north to Ohio Street, east to Clark Street, south to Lake Street, east to Wabash Avenue, south to Madison Street, west to Farwell Hall.</p>
   <p>Any other lodges or societies desiring to join in the parade are requested to apply to Mr. Peter Hand, 130 North Clark Street.</p>
   <p>All the societies of the North Side will meet at the North Side Turnhalle on North Clark Street, at 8:15 A. M; the Societies of the Northwest Side will meet At Aurora Turnhalle, on Milwaukee Avenue, and the Societies of the South Side <pb facs="5418474_8_0272.jpg" n="10"/>at the Vorwaerts Turnhalle, on West Twelfth Street; a band will be ready to lead the societies to their respective meeting places.</p>
   <p>The following men will act as assistant marshals: Alderman Buehler, Gustav Neuhaus, H. Schmehl, F. Schweinfurth, Ernst Sonntag, and M. Gottfried.</p>
   <p>Peter Hand, Marshal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
