<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-12">June 12, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Collection for the Steuben Memorial Has Started</title><title level="a" type="sub">Even the Smallest Contribution Accepted with Thanks</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1562</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1562.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-12">June 12, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">COLLECTION FOR THE STEUBEN MEMORIAL HAS STARTED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Even the Smallest Contribution Accepted with Thanks</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The business office of the Abendpost, 225 West Washington Street, is already accepting donations for a plaque which, as reported before, will be placed in the rotunda of the old federal building, Clark and Adams Streets, as a lasting tribute to the famous German-American, Friedrich Wilhelm von Steuben, the creator of the American Army. Our fellow citizens of Polish descent will put up a plaque in the same place in honor of General Kosciuszko, and those of French descent will put one up in honor of General Lafayette.</p>
   <p>More collection depots will shortly be opened, and will be announced in the Abendpost and Sonntagpost, as will the names of donors.</p>
   <p>The underlying idea that has guided the committee is to make this plaque a gift of all German-Americans of Chicago, and so to make no minimum limit. This will permit everyone to participate in accordance with his financial ability. Every <pb facs="5418474_8_1563.jpg" n="2"/>donation, even the smallest, is accepted with thanks. Children, too, should take part in the collection, because no enormous sum is solicited, but rather a fund which comes from a true cross-section of the German population of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The plaque is to be of truly artistic design, so that the German-Americans may be proud of it. The noted Chicago sculptor, Professor Emil Zettler, is at present occupied with the creation of a fitting design, which will be submitted to a subcommittee for approval.</p>
   <p>Another committee has been named to publicize the cause in wider circles, especially among German-American organizations. Similar work in churches and parochial schools is in the capable hands of Reverend [George L.] Scherger.</p>
   <p>At the head of the committee of outstanding German-Americans who have made it their special task to execute this enterprise, so long planned, are: William P. Doerr, chairman; Albert Weinberger, treasurer; and Paul H. Mueller, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
