<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-09-08">Sep. 8, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Gymnasiums.</title><title level="a" type="sub">The German Athletic Clubs have started the Winter Semester in Gymnastics.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1365</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1365.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-09-08">Sep. 8, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">GYMNASIUMS.</title><title level="a" type="sub">The German Athletic Clubs have started the Winter Semester in Gymnastics.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday most of the Athletic Clubs started to give instructions in gymnastics in their gymnasiums. It appears unnecessary to point out the importance of such training by these clubs. They consider it as one of their chief tasks to instruct children in physical culture; and it is, indeed, exceedingly beneficial for a child to be taught by a capable teacher to steel its body and refreshen its mind by proper physical exercise.</p>
   <p>Nearly all of the local Athletic Clubs have attractive, large, and well ventilated gymnasiums, where gymnastics is a twofold enjoyment. Regular instructions will begin immediately, and the fees are so low that even the poorer classes can afford it. Nobody should deny their children the privilege of taking part.</p>
   <p>The National Athletic Club started its winter term last night with appropriate and well prepared festivity for the children. During the previous term the teacher instructed 216 pupils; but it is expected that this number will be <pb facs="5418474_8_1366.jpg" n="2"/>exceeded during this semester.....</p>
   <p>The Athletic Club Forward, likewise, reopened its gymnasium. This school has greatly advanced under the able instructors, Messrs, Kindervater and Eggert. It is leading in the number of pupils, and its achievements are equal to the best.</p>
   <p>Another Athletic Club which started yesterday is the Southside Turngemeinde. J. Grundhoefer is the instructor. This club enjoys an excellent reputation, and its gymnasium is impressive and fully equipped. Everything warrants a first class training for the children. The fee is $2.00 for the whole course.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Turngemeinde (Athletic Club) possesses not only the most beautiful hall, but also a staff of teachers, headed by H. Suder, who are equal to the best in the country. They are opening today their gymnasium to their pupils. Arrangements have been made for young people, who are not members of the club to take part in athletics and fencing by charging them $2.25 for three months.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
