<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-04">Feb. 4, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A Mistake of the Press</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0427</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0427.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-04">Feb. 4, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A MISTAKE OF THE PRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The shorter work our courts make of gangsters and leaders of criminals, such as Dillinger and Touhy, the sooner our country and city will have rest. The more strictly fellows of this kind are dealt with, the better it will be for the welfare of the people. And the less newspapers say about them, the fewer followers these undesirable men will gain. If newspapers would report their activities as briefly as possible, instead of weaving sensational stories about them, many adventurous persons who are persuaded by stories about criminals to embark upon a career of crime, would be saved from this fate. Once they have entered upon the wrong path, only a very few of them can be persuaded to return to the straight and narrow path. They sink lower and lower until they have become regular desperadoes, devoid of any human feelings, and finally they become Dillingers and Touhys.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0428.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It would be enough if newspapers reported the bare facts, which, of course the public has a right to know. In the case of Dillinger, nothing need have been reported, save that he broke jail and was recaptured and returned to Indiana, where he will be tried for the murder of a policeman. And later these facts could be published: The case against Dillinger has been started; Dillinger has been found guilty and sentenced to death. And finally, Dillinger dies in the electric chair. And the more swiftly these short reports followed upon one another, the more respect the friends, as well as the enemies, of society would have for the law. Why must these scoundrels receive so much publicity? What purpose have the lengthy reports about what a criminal has said, what he has eaten, how he was captured and taken to prison, and how he likes prison life? These matters are certainly irrelevant and merely serve to satisfy the curiosity of morbid minds, and the press should not stoop to anything like that. Or is it absolutely necessary that the States Attorney let himself be photographed walking arm in arm with a murderous bandit? That picture is a public disgrace.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0429.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Of course, since competition must be reckoned with, one newspaper alone cannot bring about a change in policy. It may avoid the worst abuses of sensational reporting, but it cannot desist from giving detailed accounts, even though the editor is aware that they will have a very bad effect upon moral weaklings. The press should agree upon a uniform policy; but as long as a large number of publishers follows the line of least resistance and prints what subscribers like to read, instead of trying to educate them, the other publishers must howl with the wolves and publish longer reports about the lords of the underworld than ever were written about kings or truly great and useful men.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
