<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-12-03">December 3, 1907</date><title level="a">Goebel Lecture</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-07">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-12-03">December 3, 1907</date><title level="a">GOEBEL LECTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Professor Jul. Goebel of Harvard University opened last night in the Recital Hall of the Auditorium, the series of lectures of the Germanistic Society for the propaganda of International culture and German science to a public of 125 visitors.</p>
   <p>Mr. Henry Pratt Judson, Rector of the Chicago University, opened the programme of the evening with a short speech saying that America appreciates the works of the German authors and thinkers and the activity of the Germanistic Societies to make them acquainted with same. He then introduced the speaker of the evening, Professor Goebel. The theme of the speech was:</p>
   <p>"Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, an interpreter of German ways of thinking." The speaker in an introductory way mentioned that American literature, according to the conditions which surrounded same, could not claim an exclusive national character like the Greek or German one. Roman literature descended from the Greek American literature must be regarded as of foreign origin. It had been quite naturally anticipated that it would develop as a branch of the English literature. In the beginning of the 19th century the French influence has <pb facs="5418474_8_0298.jpg" n="2"/>been predominant. This, however, changed in the year 1912 and the chief cause was the book of Mrs. Von Stael, about the glorification of Germany and its science and culture, whereby the foreign countries' attention was called to German literature.</p>
   <p>Like other American authors, Bancroft, Tichnor, Taylor etc. Henry Wadsworth Longfellow has deeply drawn from the fountains of German literature. On his first trip to Europe Longfellow only stayed a short time in Germany, and it can be taken from his works at that time that he was not quite familiar with the German language. A few years later the poet still the mourning the death of the wife, for the second time went to Germany literary influence not only shows itself in his translations the wonks of some German poets, but also to a great degree in his own original works. In his romance. "Hyperion", it can be followed chapter by chapter, how this influence gradually gets stronger.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0299.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A poem like "Voices of the Night" the New Englander Longfellow could not have written without having studied the nature and the world of his German colleagues as for instance Van Eichendorff. Uhland also had a great influence during Longfellow's period of development. Schiller's individuality was never quite understood by Longfellow. The supreme importance of Goethe, he failed to appreciate. The speaker was of the opinion that Longfellow found the material for his creation of the Indian Epics from the book written by the German Indian missionary Heckenfelder referring to the Indians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
