<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-04-27">Apr. 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Yesterday's Social Activity</title><title level="a" type="sub">Splendid Spring Exhibition of Gymnastics by Chicago Turngemeinde</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1259</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1259.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-04-27">Apr. 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">YESTERDAY'S SOCIAL ACTIVITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Splendid Spring Exhibition of Gymnastics by Chicago Turngemeinde</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The great annual Spring exhibition of gymnastics by the Chicago Turngemeinde has always proved to be a popular attraction, not only for the members but also for the general public. Last year's attendance was not quite as large as that of previous years; but last evening the large hall of Lincoln Turnhalle, including the gallery, was filled to capacity by guests, many of whom failed to obtain seats. However, the impressive exercises of the various classes which performed under the able leadership of their teacher, Albert C. Teuscher, made standing not intolerable. It would have been very difficult for a judge to decide which of the classes excelled....The apparatus exercises are always the same, of course, but since Mr. Teuscher has taken charge of instruction, he has always offered something new in exercises for beginners and for female classes. Therefore the marching and maneuvers <pb facs="5418474_8_1260.jpg" n="2"/>of Ladies' Class A, as well as the spirited dances of the beginners, could be called the highlights of the program. The performances on the bars by the First Division of Actives, and those on the horse by the Senior Division, were excellent, as were also the exhibitions of the Second Division of Girls. The program closed with a well-executed pyramid formation by the Actives....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
