<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-17">Jan. 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Illinois Turnbezirk</title><title level="a" type="sub">Intellectual Treat Enjoyed at Meeting in Lincoln Turnhalle</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0964</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0964.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-17">Jan. 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ILLINOIS TURNBEZIRK</title><title level="a" type="sub">Intellectual Treat Enjoyed at Meeting in Lincoln Turnhalle</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Quite a number of turners and their lady companions assembled in the spacious Lincoln Turnhalle on Diversey Parkway at the invitation of the Committee on Intellectual Advancement of the Illinois Turnbezirk (Illinois Turner District), which makes arrangements for similar meetings at one of the turner halls of the city once a month.</p>
   <p>A very interesting program was held under the chairmanship of President George A. Schmidt. The two speakers of the evening, Dr. Michael Singer and The Reverend Alfred Meyer, selected topics which are of current interest. Dr. Singer spoke on "Democracy as a World Principle," and the theme of The Reverend Mr. Meyer's address was: "The Future of Germans In This Country".</p>
   <p>Dr. Singer said in substance: "Genuine democracy can exist only where every <pb facs="5418474_8_0965.jpg" n="2"/>citizen takes a personal interest in the affairs of the community. The citizens themselves are to blame if they thoughtlessly submit to the leadership of a few politicians; sham democracy then supplants true democracy, as has happened in America. The less a democracy is a democracy in fact, the more anxiously will its constituents be concerned about its external form. Boerne once said: 'We do not wish to change the German people; we merely wish to arouse it, for it is asleep.'</p>
   <p>"Even revolutions do not always serve to awaken a nation to true democracy. Thus Napoleon followed Louis XVI in France. Materialism and sensuality threatened to overwhelm Germany because she lacked the leadership of an able statesman and diplomat who could continue not only the militaristic policies of Bismarck, but also his wise diplomacy. Instead of seeking the friendship of all her neighbors she continually increased her armaments, and thus she created the impression that she was bent on world domination.</p>
   <p>"The statements of President Wilson, that he was not warring on the German <pb facs="5418474_8_0966.jpg" n="3"/>people and that he would prefer friendly relations with Germany, are just as true now as they were at the beginning of the war. This attitude of the President was evident during his visit to Europe where he advocated the ideal aims of America in opposition to the selfish designs of the other Allies, who want to crush the German people. Only an alliance of nations patterned according to President Wilson's ideas will avoid the danger of complete nationalization and lead to a true world democracy. Sham democracy is the most dangerous form of autocracy, as is exemplified in England. Americans of German descent must suppress their petty squabbles and take a united stand against every form of sham democracy, so that genuine democracy may be preserved in the United States of America."</p>
   <p>The Reverend Mr. Meyer spoke most eloquently and was rewarded with repeated bursts of loud applause. He said that only a strong will and vigorous action can gain for the German element in the United States of America the place which it deserves. He remarked that he himself is an old turner, and is happy because <pb facs="5418474_8_0967.jpg" n="4"/>the barrier between church and turner has been removed. He advocates the cultivation of the ideal German qualities, but not a state within the state. The latter situation would be so ridiculous that nobody would consider it, and it would certainly find no advocates among the second generation. Germany, more than any other country, was a second parent to America. Even people who are not at all suspected of harboring a friendly attitude toward Germans have readily acknowledged the contributions which German men and women have made to the development of America. The German element, which was often too modest during the war, must realize its true value and regain its rightful place through active participation in public affairs. Despite their unqualified allegiance to America, Americans of German descent must foster the German language; otherwise, the appreciation of the value of German culture will vanish. German culture cannot afford to be a spineless Apollo.</p>
   <p>If we have learned nothing from the sufferings of recent years we are more ignorant than our enemies think we are. Moreover, if we have no liking for <pb facs="5418474_8_0968.jpg" n="5"/>politics, we must not forget that he who would clean an Augean stable cannot avoid contact with filth.</p>
   <p>The Gesangverein Harmonie and the Saengerbund Fidelia sang under the leadership of Mr. von Oppen. Miss Jacobsen and Mr. Alfred Goetze also rendered vocal selections, and Mr. Heinrich Loewenfeldt gave a humorous reading. The ladies' class of Lincoln Turnverein performed a round dance under the leadership of Kruepner, a teacher of gymnastics. A well-trained division of the Lincoln Turnverein gave an exhibition of gymnastics on the parallel bars.</p>
   <p>After the meeting adjourned many remained for a social gathering.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
