<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-11-03">Nov. 3, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of Lessing Momument</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1564</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1564.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-11-03">Nov. 3, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF LESSING MOMUMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dedication of the Lessing Monument was held Sunday afternoon in the Rose-Garden, at Washington Park. The monument was a bequest of Mr. Henry Frank, who died in 1926, and left the sum of $25,000 for that purpose. The monument, which was created by the well known sculptor, Alvin Polasek, consists of a life-size bronze statue of Lessing, the German poet and writer, which stands on a granite pedestal.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ernest J. Kruetgen was among the 300 persons who participated at the celebration.</p>
   <p>The dedication ceremony began with an address by Judge Henry Horner, who in a few words, described the life of Henry Frank. Then the Arion-Mens Chorus under the direction of its conductor, Mr. Franz Biedel, offered two songs, whereupon Vice-Consul Dr. Werner Schueller, unveiled the statue, and Mr. Carl Meyer, executor of the Frank will, officially presented it to the <pb facs="5418474_8_1565.jpg" n="2"/>South Park administration. Mr. Edward Kelly, as president of the South Park administration, accepted it, in a short address. The dedicatory speech was given by Dr. Otto Schmidt, in which he mentioned the importance of Gotthold Ephraim Lessing, to German literature.</p>
   <p>Under the direction of the Arion-Mens Chorus, the National hymn "The Star Spangled Banner" was sung by all those present.</p>
   <p>A wreath, from the Lessing Lodge A. F. A. M., was placed on the monument.</p>
   <p>The donor of the monument, Mr. Henry Frank, came to Chicago with his parents in 1852. He had in the course of years, brought his business to great prominence and financial success. He distinguished himself in the field of social welfare and was one of the founders of the Michael Reese Hospital. He showed great interest for Archaeology and provided for the <pb facs="5418474_8_1566.jpg" n="3"/>establishment of the "American Institute of Archaeology."</p>
   <p>He died in 1926 at the age of 84 years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
