<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-29">Jan. 29, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Poetry</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dorothea Boettcher and Her Newest Creations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-29">Jan. 29, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">POETRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dorothea Boettcher and Her Newest Creations</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is highly gratifying that we still have people who enjoy poetry either as creators or listeners, finding pleasure in the higher realm where the prosaic, mundane environment of our daily life is obliterated for a few hours. Mental stagnation has not yet become universal. For every hundred beer philistines or Skat-players (a German card game), we find one human being emerging from the dismal swamp of intellectual decadence like a lone flower in a murky sphere. This was proved again yesterday by Miss Dorothea Boettcher's recitation at the Germania Club. The small hall boasted of a large audience in which women predominated tremendously. In this flowery assembly one espied occasionally a man or diminutive <pb facs="5418474_8_0318.jpg" n="2"/>gentleman among the listeners just like raisins in a cake, as the poetess so aptly declared in her short prologue. Yes, women represent the bulk on such evenings. As this is nothing new, let us confine ourselves to the story.</p>
   <p>The little rostrum looked like a bouquet, roses everywhere, with Miss Boettcher in the center.</p>
   <p>Theodore Brentano introduced the authoress in a few, well-chosen simple words, whereupon Miss Boettcher spoke to express her gratification at seeing so large an attendance.</p>
   <p>Our prima donna Mrs. Theodore Brentano, who was scheduled to take part in the program, was absent on account of a serious indisposition. At the last minute, Miss Mathilde Rapp obligingly filled the gap, singing the appealing air "Next year, next year, my sweetheart," thus casting <pb facs="5418474_8_0319.jpg" n="3"/>the first spell of magic over the audience. Miss Rapp sang three other selections during the course of the evening....</p>
   <p>Miss Rapp will go far. She has the qualifications of a singer and her instructor, whoever he may be, has done a good job. The immense applause given her should be an inspiration for further effort. The words for her songs were written by Miss Boettcher.</p>
   <p>The poetess recited a number of her creations, which are a treasure of dramatic and humorous poems. Indeed, her labors deserve homage.</p>
   <p>As the newest productions of Miss Boettcher will be probably published in the near future, we shall restrict ourselves to the titles only, which are as follows: "Idealism, and Realism," "Admonition," "The Approach of Fall," "Eyes," "Modern," "Hyper-Modern," "To Youth," "Fantanides," "Sprouting Life," "Macrocosm," "More Light," "Poor <pb facs="5418474_8_0320.jpg" n="4"/>Children," "The Fourth Commandment," "The Miser," "Magdalene," and "The Tempter."</p>
   <p>Miss Boettcher is blessed with exceptional talent; she is a profound thinker devoid of bias, a woman of perspicacity, and follows (although she denies it in one of her poems) the trend of the modern writers.</p>
   <p>That does not signify going astray, Miss Boettcher, to the contrary.</p>
   <p>In the unfortunately short-lived Ludwig Jakobowsky one perceived fractions of a Goethe, Schiller, and Heine; yet he was one of the most modern.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
