<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1891-09-23">September 23, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">[The German Press Club]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0555</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0555.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1891-09-23">September 23, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">[THE GERMAN PRESS CLUB]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The "German Press Club" celebrated last night in their assembly-hall the one hundreth birthday of the "German" poet Theodor Koerner. The program was ingenious and suitable for the importance and dignity of the occasion and it was carried out excellently.</p>
   <p>The President of the Club welcomed the assembly very heartily and in his speech he explained briefly the purpose of the feast and expressed the hope, that the "German Press Club" may become one of the most important factors in the intellectual development of the "German-Americans."</p>
   <p>Then the speaker introduced Mr. E. Schaweaka, the had so graciously dedicated to the club one of his compositions in honor of a poem by Koerner. The dramatic performance of the artist was indeed excellent and made a deep impression.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0556.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Following him the pianist M. Rosenfeld played a Rhapsody and greatly fascinated the audience.</p>
   <p>After a short recess the Vice-President of the club, the editor Albrecht, began his speech for the occasion. The speaker did not picture Koerner as the singer, the player or as the hero, but as a political post, whose patriotic songs aroused the "German" people, who had fallen into slavery. It was Koerner who stimulated their national pride, pressed the sword into their hands and inspired them to heroic actions.</p>
   <p>Concerning depth of thought, beauty and richness of expression, his speech was a pearl of "German" oratory.---Of course, many of Koerper's poems and works were read and declaimed. A young man's choir pealed forth the warcry; "Lutzow's Wild Hunt." They received almost unending applause. A deep impression was made by Koerner's : "Prayer Before The Battle," which was sung with great emotion.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0557.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Special merit was displayed by the well-known elocutionist of Reuter, A. Kobner, who knew very well how to entertain the guests after the official meeting had ended. His marvelous and spontaneous humor nearly caused hysterics.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
