<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-08-22">Aug. 22, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">German Club Soccer Football Teams Now Affiliated with Major League</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1246</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1246.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-08-22">Aug. 22, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN CLUB SOCCER FOOTBALL TEAMS NOW AFFILIATED WITH MAJOR LEAGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After considerable effort, manager Reinhold Oeschler succeeded in having the travelling division of his football players accepted by the Major League. This represents definite progress for the Club and German sports.</p>
   <p>That the Club was able to attain the respect of its adversaries during its speedy rise can readily be shown by the delegate session of the Major League. Altogether, five teams applied for affiliation with the League; three finding acceptance. The German club obtained six votes, North Shore, four; and Harvey, two.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1247.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Now it behooves the German Club to do its best always so that the German colors will be well represented in future games. Simultaneously, the clarion call admonishes all German sportsmen and compatriots to visit the contests, and thereby support the Club in its endeavors. Interested parties can obtain further information at the Club's headquarters, 201 West North Avenue.</p>
   <p>The German Club will leave for Milwaukee tomorrow with its first two teams, to compete with the German club, Wacker. The players will leave at 8:30 P.M. on the steamship "Illinois," Michigan bridge. Return journey: Saturday evening, 11 P.M. arrival in Chicago: Monday, 7 A.M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
