<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-11-05">Nov. 5, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Illinois German-American Historical Society Resumes its Activities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0368</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0368.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-11-05">Nov. 5, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ILLINOIS GERMAN-AMERICAN HISTORICAL SOCIETY RESUMES ITS ACTIVITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After a lapse of more than two and one-half years, the German-American Historical Society of Illinois has resumed its activities which were suspended when the United States entered the World War.</p>
   <p>Dr. Otto L. Schmidt, president of the Society, opened the first meeting. From the report of the clerk it was learned that the Society had lost eight lifetime members and eighteen annual members through death, and that other members had dropped out for different reasons. As a result, the financial status of the Society was rather insecure, but a number of voluntary contributions proved that the spirit of the old guard was not broken, and that the faithful were hard at work to continue and expand the struggle for the noble cause.</p>
   <p>Mr. Francis J. Dewes advocated the publication in English of a history of <pb facs="5418474_8_0369.jpg" n="2"/>the German people, to make Americans familiar with the nature and intelligence of the German character.</p>
   <p>Professor Goebel pointed out that before the outbreak of the World War it had been planned to write a history of the American people, giving special attention to the various nationalities, their character traits, proclivities, and their influence on the development of America. In this way, justice would have been done to the typically German character, but these plans, as far as the German element was concerned, were completely suppressed, while other nationalities were allowed to promote and work for their national interests. He said that, as a matter of fact, many real Americans had vigorously opposed certain foreign propaganda, which had tried to influence the recording of history and the trend of our social and political institutions, and that they had blamed the German-American element for not standing their ground on their own behalf.</p>
   <p>It was resolved, to continue energetically the activities of the Society, <pb facs="5418474_8_0370.jpg" n="3"/>to continue publishing historical notes in the form of a yearbook, and to bend all efforts to win new members for the Society.</p>
   <p>Directors for the next two years were elected: Messrs. Heinrich Bormann, Edward G. Uihlein, H. V. Wackerbarth, Phil. H. Dilg, and Wilhelm Mannhardt. To replace the deceased Mr. Halb, Mr. [Michael] Girten was elected director for one year.</p>
   <p>All the officers were re-elected unanimously.</p>
   <p>The membership dues are only three dollars a year, and the yearbook is sent free to the members....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
