<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-15">Apr. 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">German Odd Fellows Protest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_1758</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-12">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_1758.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-15">Apr. 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN ODD FELLOWS PROTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Representatives of eighteen German lodges affiliated with the Independent Order of Odd Fellows met in the hall at 2517 Fullerton Avenue, and protested strongly against prohibiting the use of the German language in their meetings.</p>
   <p>Both men and women said that the forcible introduction of the English language would cause the ruin of most German lodges. Some of the speakers even went so far as to declare that their lodges would continue to use the German language in their meetings in the future, despite any rule to the contrary, and that they would let nothing deter them.</p>
   <p>Much enthusiasm was displayed at this meeting, which was ably presided over by the co-chairmen, Messrs. H. Baum and H. Hollmann. The following items of business were advanced and agreed to: (1) those Ledges, Camps, and Rebeccas, conducting their ceremonies in the German language have built great lodges and have done splendid work; (3) in most of these Lodges there are members hose knowledge of <pb facs="5418474_8_1759.jpg" n="2"/>the English language is limited, and who, though they can carry on conversation in English, are not sufficiently versed in that tongue to conduct their business and rituals in a manner which would do justice to the high ideals of the order; (3) attention was called to the fact that most of the Lodges concerned would be unable to further the interests of the Order, if the rule made by the Sovereign Grand Lodge were enforced; and, (4) a request was directed to the Grand Sire asking that he exert his influence in behalf of the Lodges, Camps, and Rebeccas, so that they might retain the privilege of doing their work in that language in which they could best pursue and foster the hid ideals of Old Fellowship.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
