<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-02-06">Feb. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">We Can Paddle Our Own Canoe</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_8_0508</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-15">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-08">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0508.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-02-06">Feb. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">WE CAN PADDLE OUR OWN CANOE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Anglo-American press once again is giving a lecture on morals to American citizens of German descent.</p>
   <p>These hyphenated Americans have taken the liberty to survey the political situation of this country, foreign politics in particular, with their own unbiased minds, and refused to look through British-colored spectacles, as the "native sons of America" expected them to. These "Hyphen-Americans" have a wider mental horizon than the dear native cousins, because the former had the advantage, in school and later on in life, to learn more about other governments and countries. They do not criticize the native Americans who, in self-complacent contentment, feel satisfied to know a little about the county they happened to be born in or, at the most, about their native State and the "United States language". By "language" we don't mean <pb facs="5418474_8_0509.jpg" n="2"/>literature. And to "know" a State is not tantamount with knowledge of American history. These fields are reserved for study by a few select scholars, among them a high percentage of "foreigners".</p>
   <p>The newly founded League for Independence is a priori accused of un-American activities by a press which undoubtedly gets its inspiration from England. The New York World, the Evening Post, and probably some other great dailies in the East assume the peculiar standpoint that anybody who has acquired American citizenship by his own volition has to keep his mouth shut after-wards. This absurd opinion is shared by some local English [language] newspapers, which docilely reprint what the "voices from the East" have to say. The Germans--and they are meant by it--are told in an arrogant manner that they are not supposed to have any political opinions, especially now; from which we conclude that only native Americans are allowed to have any. We beg to protest vehemently against any such political arrogance. The hyphenated Americans are democrats in a broad political sense--not from a standpoint of party politics--and are perfectly well aware that they, as <pb facs="5418474_8_0510.jpg" n="3"/>citizens of this Republic, have the inalienable right to speak, think, and act freely. By their education and moral character (culture) they are extremely competent to do their own thinking and control their own actions without any advice (from people who have not the ability to give any) and without any kind of threat. This last measure would be about the least suitable means to make German-Americans "see reason". They are, and have been, accused of fostering sectionalism. And unjustly so. They are organizing their strength in order to fight a sectionalism which has become so increasingly evident since the beginning of the war. Yes, they are fighting it! Let those Eastern and Middlewestern newspapers take note of that! And the Germans are not going to back down or bat an eye, and just as Germans have fought in the War for Independence and later on for the preservation of the Union of this Republic, they are now ready to fight that "sectionalism" which threatens to subordinate the national honor and the independence of the Union to the dictates of the Foreign Office and the Bank of England. This "sectionalism", which has been flourishing so abundantly for half a year, which has applauded gleefully all the calumnies and lies <pb facs="5418474_8_0511.jpg" n="4"/>and the rankest injustices to Germany, a sectionalism which, being utterly ignorant of international law and European history, condemned and scorned Germany immediately upon the out break of the war. This sectionalism alone, and nothing else, was responsible for the birth of the new League for Independence! To preserve the honor of this Republic, which we have grown to love (in spite of all), and in order not to incur the contempt of all South American republics, which are not so quick with their judgment, [on foreign affairs] something had to be done. If the frank intentions of the League are once known, its endeavors will find the most active support by all genuine and truly national-minded Americans.</p>
   <p>We don't have to play hide and seek. We are sure that the people who established the League did so only on account of the shameful fact that Germany was being treated with malice aforethought.</p>
   <p>It was intentional malice and has remained so ever since. The reason for this hostile attitude is the fact that the Anglo-American press received <pb facs="5418474_8_0512.jpg" n="5"/>news reports from London exclusively. But we [German-Americans] do not accept that as an alibi, and refuse to do so in the future. The [American] press had ample opportunity to avail itself of information which thousands of German-born citizens would have supplied gladly. This information was offered, but was scornfully rejected.</p>
   <p>There is an ethical principle, which calls for a mass protest against the malicious treatment that is being meted out to a nation to which America owes so much. The insinuation that "the German-Americans want to dictate to the country" is preposterous, and is probably nothing but a camouflage of "our" policy of appeasing the Anglo-Americans. That stunt has been pulled in every election campaign, we want to state here expressly that we are not going to be fooled or intimidated by worn-out tricks of this kind. The new League will not find it hard to refute this latest calumny. The League does not expect any favors from the "native sons", neither for itself nor for the German-Americans nor for Germany!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_8_0513.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>All it asks is impartial justice. The League also demands that America defend its national honor against any foreign government. Unfortunately, for selfish reasons and with the aid of influential Americans, this honor is about to be thrown on the scrap heap. The League will not be intimidated either by the threat of possible alien legislation against the foreign-born, which was so tactfully suggested by the New York World. It was a "foreigner" who founded the World, and he had brought his brain and business acumen along with him, and did not receive it as a gift from the New England Puritans. The above-mentioned World does not have to bother invoking the spirit of the late Carl Schurz. They have the least right to speak for him, because they never understood him--and never cared too!--as they very well know themselves. The League for Independence will paddle its own canoe. The Declaration of Independence will determine the course; not its traitors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
