<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-07-06">July 6, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Mayor and the Drys</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0670</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0670.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-07-06">July 6, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE MAYOR AND THE DRYS</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A committee of the "drys," led by old man Elmendorff and his chum, Paxton, the snooper, visited the mayor, late yesterday afternoon, presenting a petition with many signatures, asking for the appointment of three special policemen, to be paid by the Reform Alliance, for the purpose of preventing sales of intoxicants to minors. The committee also asked that the licenses of the following three saloonkeepers be revoked: Fitzsimmons, Clark Street; Gemmell, Twelfth Street; and Essex, South Halsted Street.</p>
   <p>The committee thanked the mayor for closing the worst dives on the South Side. The mayor then spoke at length about various social evils, such as intemperance, immorality, and gambling. He said that gambling places and houses of prostitution should be licensed, so that the police can watch them and exercise better <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0671.jpg" n="2"/>control. He stated that he is definitely opposed to the practice of selling alcoholic beverages to minors, except when they are sent by their parents. In the matter of the appointment of three special officers, as outlined, no serious objection would arise; however, at present the mayor did not care to make a decision, but he said that he intends to make personal investigations from time to time, to see how taverns are conducted.</p>
   <p>Mr. Paxton offered to drive about town every evening with the mayor, and added that the Alliance would pay the rental of the coach. But the mayor undoubtedly considered the reputation of Mr. Paxton, and declined.</p>
   <p>The mayor was not willing to revoke the licenses of the three saloonkeepers until he obtains more definite facts.</p>
   <p>All in all, the Elmendorff-Paxton partnership (and their followers) did not achieve much.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
