<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-03-09">Mar. 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal to the Liberal Citizens of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0332</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0332.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-03-09">Mar. 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL TO THE LIBERAL CITIZENS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Register on Tuesday, March 11, and on April 1 vote against prohibition in Chicago.</p>
   <p>On April 1, 1919, Chicago will decide by ballot whether, or not, prohibition is to be instituted here.</p>
   <p>If the majority of the voters--men and women--vote in favor of prohibition, Chicago will be "dry" after April 30.</p>
   <p>That must not happen. Therefore we appeal not only to our members, but also to all liberal-minded men and women who are eligible to vote, to cast their ballots against prohibition.</p>
   <p>The leaders of the "wet" movement are carrying on a quiet campaign, but a very vigorous one, and hope to deceive the liberal voters. For this reason we ask that you give the matter your undivided attention and thus lend your aid not only to the effort to keep prohibition out of Chicago, but also by a large <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0333.jpg" n="2"/>majority vote, to the prevention of prohibition throughout the country.</p>
   <p>National prohibition of alcoholic drinks would be followed by the curtailment of other liberties, thousands of business enterprises would be ruined, millions of people would lose their employment, and, finally, personal freedom would vanish completely.</p>
   <p>Therefore, it is necessary that the liberal element present a united front. The only registration day before the April election is March 11. Every person who has moved from his precinct since the general registration of last fall, or since the registration which preceded the last primary, or has not registered at all heretofore, must register on March 11, or he cannot vote on April 1. Places of registration will be open from 8. A. M. until 9 P. M. Liberal voters,men and women, do your duty!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0334.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Executive Committee of the Allied Societies for Local Self-Government.</p>
   <p>John Koelling, President</p>
   <p>Anton J. Cermak, Secretary</p>
   <p>Adolph D. Weiner, Chairman of the Committee on Political Activity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
