<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-06-09">June 9, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[The Temperance Problem]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0050</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0050.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-06-09">June 9, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[THE TEMPERANCE PROBLEM]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday evening a mass meeting against the temperance fanatics took place in the Northside Turn Hall.</p>
   <p>Herr Michaelis opened the meeting and proposed Mr. Max Eberhardt as chairman. Dr. Lebell was nominated as secretary. On a motion of Mr. Michelson the chairman nominated a resolutions' committee consisting of Messrs. Edmund Jussen. Julius Rutisheuser, Albert Michelson and Cherles Haussner.</p>
   <p>Mr. Emil Dietzsch said the time had come when the Germans at last could energetically demand to be left alone and in peace in regard to the temperance issue.</p>
   <p>Mr. Schlager gave a historical survey of the events since the election of the so-called Peoples Ticket in 1869. The majority has not only challenged the Germans by reinstituting an old ordinance, but had added insult by decreeing the total closing of the inns from midnight to midnight.</p>
   <p>Fortunately, the November elections are not far off. We will have to elect twenty aldermen, and if the Germans use their influence wisely we should be able to elect aldermen who will have promised before the election to insist <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0051.jpg" n="2"/>Whereas the City Council of Chicago has enacted an ordinance on June 5th, prohibiting the sale of alcoholic beverages on Sundays - be it therefore resolved by the German-American citizens of Chicago -</p>
   <p>1. That the German-American element of Chicago declares all encroachment by the Temperance and Prudery Movements on its social and civic rights as unconstitutional......</p>
   <p>6. That we are firmly resolved not to sacrifice our rights for all the demonstrations of professional politicians who tell us that we might endanger the Republican Party. As long as one party represents genuinely republican principles we fight in its ranks, but when it deteriorates into a tool of the Prudery Movement and prestly power (Muckerthum and Pfaffengewalt) then we regard it as our duty to start the organization of a more liberal party......</p>
   <p>9. That we regard it as the duty of all German-American papers fearlessly and energetically to support the German-American interest against the intolerant Prudery Movement, without regard for the possible consequences for any extant party organization......</p>
   <p>11. That a committee shall be nominated to hand copies of this resolution to</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
