<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-08-06">Aug. 6, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Take Note of Them, Germans!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0640</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0640.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-08-06">Aug. 6, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">TAKE NOTE OF THEM, GERMANS!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The agitation of the Puritan-American, against the pleasures and festivals of the Germans, and who display openly their hate of the stranger and his religion, is a well known fact and will not evoke any surprise. It will however, create some astonishment if German-born subjects participate in such detrimental agitations. Several ill-disposed neighbors especially from La Salle Street, and of the well known and attractive pleasure place "Lincoln Pavillion of Mme. Schovengel on Clark Street, near North Avenue, have signed a petition, asking the Mayor not to permit the well appreciated evening concerts, which are visited every night by a well behaved public and which are enjoyed up to a late hour, to be extended until after 10:33 P.M.</p>
   <p>The principal howler against these concerts is Mr. Charles Waller, the Municipal Building Commissioner, who more from mental narrowness than from malice, has put Mayor Harrison, in the disagreeable situation of seeing one of the chief members of his so-called liberal administration in the ranks of the enemies against Germans.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0641.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The effect must be extremely startling, seeing German names amongst the signatures on the petition such as Bomerman, Stretz, John W. Vogt, E. Schaefer, Louis Schaffner, etc.</p>
   <p>We do not know the worthy individuals of the three first named and are not curious to make their acquaintance. E. Schaefer is the well known Coffee House proprietor and a relative of the owner of the real estate where the Lincoln Pavillion is situated. Whilst the latter receives from Mr. Schovengel a good rental, his dapper relative tries to do him harm. For Schafer's excuse, we anticipate that he also belongs to the same category as Waller. Nobody will ask who is Louis Schaffner. He is the same well known arrogant and ignorant braggart who had been elected by the Republican politicians of the 16th ward as their chief. For years, there can be seen hand in hand brotherly united, the Democratic Yankee, Waller and the Republican German-American, Schaffner, men who understand good music quite as much as the elephant does of tight-rope dancing, as they unite to damage one ofthe best and most decent summer gardens. Every sensible open-minded American citizen of the neighborhood and of the whole city, expects, from Mayor Harrison that, he will discourage this group joined together by stupidity and conceit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
