<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-13">Feb. 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Public Utilities</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1313</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1313.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-13">Feb. 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLIC UTILITIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The State Public Utilities Commission has given the local gas company a severe rap on the nose. The Commission has established that all the complaints which the public made regarding the business methods of the company were well founded, and that customers were entitled to a refund of overcharges. Though the reprimand itself was very severe, it will still appear to be very lenient to those of our citizens who were forced to submit to the arrogance of the gas company and its employees. In their opinion the Commission should have made a much more comprehensive and more rigid investigation, and should have dealt more severely with the gas company. However, for the time being these critics should be satisfied with the Commission's decision, since it restores their rights and censures the business conduct of the gas company in most severe terms. If the officials of the corporation have the slightest sense of shame, they certainly must have blushed deeply when they read the verbal lashing of our public servants.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1314.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But it is just in these circles that the pachyderms are to be found who can sense a good business deal a mile away, but are deaf and unapproachable to the complaints of the common people who make the large incomes of corporations possible. These thick-skinned officials pretend to be ignorant of any offense when they are called to account, and entrench themselves behind all manner of legal terminology as soon as the arm of law and justice attempts to force them to make amends for wrongs which they have committed. And these "shrewd" businessmen who take their living from the pockets of the people and give them a kick in return, are very influential, not only in so-called "society" but also in local and national politics, and are past masters at getting around the indolent public and fleecing it. Our citizens should shun these "successful businessmen" as they shun Beelzebub. It is certainly high time thoroughly and impartially to investigate all persons who have derived or are deriving undue profits from public utilities, and to limit their incomes. Most of these gentlemen still operate according to the principle, "The public be dammed," although they are too smart to say so publicly. They make use of any and every opportunity to cheat the public. It is not their nature to do their cheating openly. Their weapons are craft and deceit. In most instances their victims do not <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1315.jpg" n="3"/>notice the fraud until it has been committed--when it is too late. But the methods which were used by the gas company were too crude. The consumers got a whiff of the rot beforehand, made a howl about it, and succeeded at least in establishing their rights and revealing the maladministration of the company. That, indeed, required much effort. For it was not until the cat was out of the bag that tactics of intimidation were dropped and an attempt was made to hush the entire matter. These attempts did not succeed in this instance, because cases of a similar nature were still vivid in the public's memory. Some other time an attempt may be successful. For instance, when the city transportation ordinace which proposed the consolidation of the surface lines and elevated railroads, and the prevention of the acquisition of these transportation systems by the city, was voted on last year, the grab of the millions of dollars which were to be used for purchasing the streetcar lines was frustrated by the small majority of only 30,000 votes. The public promoters of the plan and their hidden wirepullers have noted the small number of their opponents, and are already making propaganda for their schemes, even though they were defeated but a short time ago. Sooner or later, the transportation problem will again be put before the electorate of our city and every conceivable means will be used <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1316.jpg" n="4"/>to persuade the majority to vote for the schemes. The promoters of the schemes are not wrong in thinking, "The dear public will finally tire of voting against us, if we but employ sufficient chicanery, for constant dripping wears away the stone". And so the same old thing happens again and again. Today it may be the gas company, tomorrow it will be the Surface Lines or the elevated railroads, or some other public utility company. Municipal ownership of all public utilities, though there may be a number of valid objections to it, appears to be the only effective way of putting an end to this persistent struggle.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
