<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-08-13">Aug. 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">German-Speaking Element of Chicago Requested to Join Crusaders</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0188</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0188.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-08-13">Aug. 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN-SPEAKING ELEMENT OF CHICAGO REQUESTED TO JOIN CRUSADERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Upon an invitation extended by Mr. J. Russell Forgan, a number of gentlemen assembled at the Bismarck Hotel yesterday afternoon for a debate. Present were the Messrs. Karl Eitel, Ernest Kruetgen, Bernard DeVry, Reinhold Oeschler, Ernest Roepler, Hermann Wollenberger, Dr. Kobalter, Consul General Michael Girten, Dr. Otto L. Schmidt, August J. Fertig, D. D. Fertig, Seymour Wheeler, Col, Reeves, Dr. Carl Beck, Paul H. Mueller, and Paul H. Ortman. The aim of the debate was to interest Americans of German descent in a systematic fight against prohibition.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. R. Forgan opened the discussion with a short explanation of the purposes and methods of the Crusaders. He pointed to the fact that the organization was founded in Cleveland, Ohio, in January of this year. It spread to New York and already has a large membership in cities on the Atlantic coast.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0189.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This organization intends to set up branch organizations in all cities which have populations of 25,000 or more. The Crusaders seek especially to interest the younger element in the battle against prohibition.</p>
   <p>Their organizational methods consist in soliciting memberships in factories, business places, banks, societies, and clubs.</p>
   <p>The Crusaders hope to attain a membership of ten million by the year 1932. Mr. Forgan emphasized, in particular, that the Crusaders have no intention of having their organization compete with other groups which are fighting against the Eighteenth Amendment. These other organizations number many highly respected citizens among their members in a number of cities. They, however, never had any intention of seizing the great mass of voters and uniting them in a strong, fighting wet army. The Crusaders want to bridge this gap in the army fighting prohibition.</p>
   <p>Such an organization is therefore absolutely necessary, because the fight <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0190.jpg" n="3"/>against Prohibition already has created numerous so-called rackets. It is therefore necessary that all those who are determined to participate actively and energetically in this fight be given an opportunity to join an organization whose leaders are widely known as prominent and honorable citizens. Mr. Forgan emphasizes, in particular, that the Crusaders are a nonpolitical organization.</p>
   <p>His effective words were received with great interest. The gentlemen declared that they were entirely satisfied with the aims and endeavors of the Crusaders, and promised to give their full support to the drive for new members among the German-speaking elements of Chicago. There is no intention of forming a separate German group. However, it was emphasized from all sides that the Americans of German descent can consider themselves highly honored that they are the first foreign-language group to be asked to participate in this great work. At the same time different speakers expressed the hope that all voting Americans of German descent would join the Crusaders in order to work energetically for the realization of their aim.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0191.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Finally Messrs. Ernest Kruetgen, Hermann Wolleberger and Bernard DeVry were elected members of the executive committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
