<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-10-14">Oct. 14, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Another Disgrace</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0237</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0237.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-10-14">Oct. 14, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">ANOTHER DISGRACE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Bribery scandals of the most evil variety reek toward heaven in Chicago. To the right and to the left harmless citizens "bite the dust," prostrated by the bullets of ambitious gangsters. Wave after wave of execrations are heaped upon the honest heads of those who stay in Chicago, either because of some unaccountable optimism of theirs or because of some other compelling reason, although Podunk Center would offer them much greater security of life and property. In other words, it is a dismal picture which is daily unrolled in Chicago.</p>
   <p>It must, therefore, be an elevating and enthusing feeling to know that the censoring authorities are watchful over the morals of the citizens, striving to avert dissembling machinations no matter what influential faction they may come from.</p>
   <p>Even though the eye of the law is closed at times, the eyes of the censor are <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0238.jpg" n="2"/>never closed. And it so happened that the police censorship, under the expert administration of a certain Mrs. Mabel Rockwell who, by dint of her avocation as police matron, was qualified to pass on theatre and art products of every description, once again did its best. This time it is a Constance Talmadge film, produced by a Chicago firm, which provoked the weighty scruples of the afore-mentioned lady. It is said that a most terrifying thing happened in the film. A somewhat inconsistent Vienna composer does not devote himself to his legally betrothed wife as much as she deserved. The wife now resolves to "cure" him. This is easy, for she has a twin sister who looks deceivingly like her, and who is a dancer in Paris. Now, the wife in the dancer's dresses, "hooks" the composer and makes life hot for him. It ends with the usual reconciliation.</p>
   <p>The censorship found that such a sister-in-law cure (which is at the same time a wifely cure) is perilous to morals. An appeal was made, but the film is shown all the same. And this is right. Aside from the fact that there is nothing in the story that could not be shown in any school for girls, it is in <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0239.jpg" n="3"/>itself absurd that a police matron with an array of bespectacled "buttermilk mugs" who have reformed should dictate to the Chicago public what kind of films they may enjoy. That is decidedly going too far. And what is more, the administration of the film producers in question is known to be exceedingly strict. Film filth is never shown in their theaters. One is quite free to have any personal opinion about the artistic performances of the Talmadge sisters, but it will have to be admitted that they have never yet condescended to participating in films which are filthy or of ill repute. Being very popular, they do not have to do that; doing so might even do them harm. Accordingly, the question would be justified why the censor acted, bringing obloquy upon himself. The answer to this question was given in this paper before; it is based upon the knowledge established throughout many centuries that every censorship, with no exception, is stupid and must remain stupid. It remains to consider whether it is really necessary to be bothered with long-winded conferences between the theater representatives, the chief of police, the censors, corporation lawyers, and even the appellate court, solely because a small acrobatic performance is shown in a quite harmless film which is not in accord with the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0240.jpg" n="4"/>ideas of morality held by certain uncles and aunts among the censors.</p>
   <p>Does, perchance, the city administration want to introduce something like a Volstead law for films? After the experiences we have had until now, it is quite well capable of this feat. Has it not become an established policy in Chicago to catch the flies and to leave the elephants unmolested?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
