<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1904-08-03">August 3, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">The Immune Meat Trust.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial.)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1904-08-03">August 3, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">THE IMMUNE MEAT TRUST.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(EDITORIAL.)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Attorney General, Mr. Moody, will tell the esteemed voters just why our trust-killing administration will not prosecute the Meat Trust. The president, himself, requested him to do so, as a result of yesterday's Cabinet session, where the question of "apprehending or desisting" was thoroughly thrashed out.</p>
   <p>With drums and trumpets it was proclaimed some months ago, how we'll catch and hang that meat combine ! The Department of Commerce and Labor took charge of it. An army of investigators, snoopers and stool pigeons spied on the Trust, and the information they obtained is simply confounding. A report, containing the results of their endeavors, was submitted at yesterday's meeting of the Cabinet and there our Attorney General added the right dose of legal mustard.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1350.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He said, "Evidently we have indications here, which justify our assumption that the court order has been circumvented by various trust members, but the proofs required to obtain legal action are missing. What has been procured by arduous labor and energy is not sufficient to bring suit for contempt of court, let alone the institution of regular court proceedings and a conviction." The other Cabinet members concurred, whereupon, according to information received, our President acquiesced "with regrets" in the decision to leave the Trust alone. In order to explain the exculpation to the people, Mr. Moody will make a speech towards the end of this month, or in the early part of September.</p>
   <p>The State of Vermont has been selected for the occasion, some distance from the seat of war. What the explanation will be is still in the obscure future. If it gives any elucidation at all, then it will be based on the boastful Republican platform, and a personal exaltation of Theodore Roosevelts' acceptance speech.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1351.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>What did it contain? "Laws, which the Republican party promulgated to protect the public against the unjust discriminations and unlawful transgressions of the great capitalist combines, have been fearlessly upheld by a Republican President." And what does Roosevelt say: "In its attitude towards large organizations, which are known as Trusts, it is not necessary for us to explain why such laws have not been passed, but to show that they have been actually brought into existence, and that laws have been created to make their application more effective."</p>
   <p>The statutes have been produced and are available, that is the proclamation in the plank and presidential address. If anyone asks, "Against whom?" The customary answer is: "We have obtained a writ of mandamus against the Meat Trust!"</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1352.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Of all the hundreds of industrial trusts throughout America, the meat organization is the only one, during the Roosevelt administration, where an attempt has been made to obtain a conviction. Neither the steel-monopoly, sugar, Standard Oil, nor any of the other corporate bodies which increase the cost of life's necessities, have been apprehended, and now it must be admitted before the entire assembly of warriors, that this solitary shot hit only water. On July 27, our President gave us the proud assurance: "We need not explain why such laws were not passed." He finds it necessary on August 2 only one week later, to deputize one of his Cabinet members to give such an accounting. But that happens, when one bites off more than one can chew. To whatever zeal and technical rhetoric the Attorney General may resort, in order to succeed in his task of making that indubitable explanation, in its final analysis it will be the confession: "We were fearful braggarts."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1353.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>And in so far as the final expurgation is concerned, there will appear inevitable phases which will not be condusive towards promotion of the glory of the "Grand Old Party".</p>
   <p>Judge Grossoup, in issuing his warrant, spun a net of the finest texture, as perfect a product as ever was made. If, regardless of such assistance, the Republican law enforcers are not capable of catching anything what must we think of their ambition and abilities? Or their honesty ? The Republican campaign managers always were excellent gatherers, when Trust-fat was to be rendered, i.e. where money was needed for the election warchest, the consolidated corporations gave tribute, because they found the Republican party and its politics were its greatest assets. Is it any wonder, when we remember the precedents, that the entire Republican Trust-killing expedition appears to many to be a farcical performance? And, if it's not that, but, that the rope for the Trusts cannot be located because no one wishes to find it, what then?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1354.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We have the only alternative, which is that the entire Trust-chase lacks essential skill and ambition; that the Republican party suffers in this particular instance from the same malady, (the incapacity with which it accuses its competitor), or else the entire famous Trust legislation is not worth the paper on which it has been written or printed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
