<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-05-12">May 12, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">President of World's Congress Slights the German Language</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1018</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1018.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-05-12">May 12, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">PRESIDENT OF WORLD'S CONGRESS SLIGHTS THE GERMAN LANGUAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German visitors of the World's Fair are rightly dissatisfied with Mr. Bonney, President of the World's Congress. He decided that the English, Spanish and French languages shall serve as the official medium of communication, and that the German language should be prohibited as such. One exception was made, namely, that the German authors will be permitted to read their manuscripts in their language. Is this not a direct and deliberate slight of the German language in favor of the Spanish and French languages? Had the decision been that only the English language should be recognized, then we could complain only about absurdity, but not about injustice, as is now the case. The suppression of the German language - the language of the most highly cultured people in Europe constitutes a brutal disregard, about which the German-American press cannot keep silent. And who is the originator of this infamous decision which betrays such narrow-mindedness, arrogance, prejudice, and stupidity? This man has often been denounced in the columns of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung, and he is none other than Charles C. Bonney:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1019.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He is the man known as a prohibitionist and as a bigot. He is the man under whose leadership the German Press was ignored in regard to transmitting official reports, until a personal protest reminded him of his duties.</p>
   <p>He is the man who gives preference on his program at the World's Congress to Sabbath-Keepers and other reactionaries. He appointed as speakers and honorable members, German professors, who have been dead a long time, and whose life-story he could have found in any ordinary encyclopedia. . . .</p>
   <p>The Germans are not inclined to take quietly a moral stab from the President of the World's Congress.</p>
   <p>They demand the consideration and the respect they deserve! They demand equality for all the great nations! They criticize Bonney's action as unfair, and under no conditions will they tolerate it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
