<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1876-04-25">Apr. 25, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">The Toledo</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1091</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1091.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1876-04-25">Apr. 25, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">THE TOLEDO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is no credit to the Chicago Tribune to print such an untrue account (which can only have been inspired by malice) as "A Riot in the Toledo".</p>
   <p>"On Madison Street near Clark Street is a restaurant, known by the name of Toledo, where beer is served and free music provided besides by two or three women. In one part of the restaurant is a gallery, where irresponsible young men and girls gather. Sunday evenings the restaurant is always overcrowded. Last evening a young man, about 20 years of age was conversing with a girl whom he had escorted down there. Someone offended him and a brief argument ensued, when an uncouth two-hundred pound Teuton took hold of him and threw him down the stairway. The Teuton is a special policeman hired by the restaurant. The young man was not strong and when both came down the stairway in such a rapid tempo, it caused quite a deal of excitement.</p>
   <p>"The crowd hurried to the outer door, where another special policeman pulled his gun and threatened to shoot anyone attempting to leave. Although the uproar lasted several minutes no policeman appeared on the scene.</p>
   <p>Now as a matter of fact, the young man was already partially under the influence of <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1092.jpg" n="2"/>liquor when he arrived and at first the entrance to the place was barred to him. Finally admitted, he misbehaved very soon, overthrew glasses bombarded other guests with paper and used vile and profane language. After Mr. Kaltenbach had remonstrated in vain with him on his conduct, he took him by the arm and led him outside. No riot took place, no gun was pulled, no violence done to the young man.</p>
   <p>We mention the report of the Tribune, not on account of its lack of veracity but on account of the spirit it betrays. When an American is put outside of a restaurant for misconduct by the German owner, this according to the Tribune is a crime. How does a German dare to throw out an American? Where was the police, asks the Tribune, to protect this young American against German brutality? This account reveals the spirit of the know-nothings and we fear that similar accounts will be frequent in the near future. The wish to push the Germans back into unimportant positions becomes daily more prominent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
