<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-07">Jan. 7, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">News from the Tavern Keepers Annual Report of the President of the "Old Tavern Club"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1471</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1471.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-07">Jan. 7, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM THE TAVERN KEEPERS Annual Report of the President of the "Old Tavern Club"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John Prosser, the re-elected president of the Old Tavern Club, made the following announcement to the members of the club when the new officers were inducted.</p>
   <p>"To the Officials and Members of the Old Tavern Club of Chicago: Esteemed Friends: If you expect an exceedingly wordy and elaborate annual report at this time, you will be disappointed. During my last presidential term nothing transpired which may be considered important. The only exception was the election campaign, with its inseparable claptrap and, therefore, an extra report is unwarranted. The conventions, district as well as State, proceeded harmoniously, and our club, with due respect to its standing, was given proper recognition.</p>
   <p>"In our ranks everything stands as of old: the same membership, in spite <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1472.jpg" n="2"/>of the founding of a new association (the Royal Arch), and the same amount of money in the treasury. Attendance, unfortunately, has not improved over former periods. Thanks to the practical methods of our Association's attorney, P. Koehler, our "war expense" was cut down to $65 for the year in spite of the intense agitation of the "dry" element.</p>
   <p>"The great reaper has called two of our venerable members, Herman Kaiser and D. Arenson. Peace be with them!"</p>
   <p>"Although I had not the least inclination to become a candidate again, I have been nominated just the same, and so it behooves me to do my duty. I am especially gratified that my former co-workers remain.</p>
   <p>"The rancorous clamor which heralded the present anti-vice and immorality drive, will soon die out. It is only regrettable that some respectable members of our calling suffered occasionally thereby. We hope that the new year will be auspicious, the most successful we ever had, both from a social and business <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1473.jpg" n="3"/>aspect, and that we may be spared the repetition of former disappointments. Forward! should be our slogan."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
