<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-06-03">June 3, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">License Permits</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0509</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0509.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-06-03">June 3, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">LICENSE PERMITS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only five members of the Committee for License Permits were present at the meeting of the Executive Committee of the United Associations for Local Self Government at the Sherman House.</p>
   <p>The acting Chairman, former Congressmember Koonan, produced a new ordinance plan,stating that it contained the wishes of about four hundred associations and clubs. Most of them were incorporated and all of them were in good standing. They also desired the suppression of indecent dance halls which were spoiling the morals of the younger generation and to give the mayor a free hand in the allowance or refusal of permits. The new ordinance reads as follows:</p>
   <p>1. The mayor of the City of Chicago has the power, if requested in writing, accompanied by a surety and a fee, to issue a license for the retail sale of beer, wine or liquor to an association or club, which has been <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0510.jpg" n="2"/>established in good faith for support, educational, or benevolent purposes.</p>
   <p>2. The applicant shall prove to the satisfaction of the mayor the good faith and reputation of the association and the respectability of the meeting or entertainment, for which the license has been asked. Nothing in this ordinance should be understood for the asking of a license for sale of liquors for indecent localities and dance halls for the purpose of vice and crime.</p>
   <p>3. The duration of the license should be for not longer than 24 hours at a fee of $6.00, payable in advance. The surety shall be for the amount of $500.00(the surety for the saloon license is $3,500.00, but lasts for one year). A discussion took place about the ways and means to submit this proposal to the License Committee and Mr. Cullerton said that the Ordinance should be brought as a special measure to the order of the day. He recommended giving special hours for the duration of the license.</p>
   <p>The Committee of Five was given a free hand and full power and they were thanked by the meeting for their interest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
