<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-15">June 15, 1935</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0076</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0076.jpg" n="2"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-15">June 15, 1935</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This part of the debate was a show of unpleasant hypocrisy. The opponents of the bill maintained that they would vote against it on Moral grounds, inasmuch as it furthers betting on horses and would cause other dangerous consequences.</p>
   <p>There is not one member of the legislature of Illinois who does not know that betting on race horses goes on in Chicago, as well as in other towns and town-ships throughout the state. Anyone who does not realize that must be blind and deaf. The prohibition of these bets cates from a time when the reformers had a majority in the legislature. Similar prohibitions exist in almost all states, but one has never heard that they have been enforced. These measures for the protection of citizens have a quite peculiar significance.</p>
   <p>It cannot escape the careful observer that conceptions of virtue and vice change rather quickly. A few decades ago, for instance, prize fighting was looked upon as the height of wickecness. At that time, the man who happened to be the champion of the world traveled with his promotor and challenger across the whole country, from New York to Texas, from the Atlantic to the Pacific, to find some <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0077.jpg" n="3"/>little spot where the fight could take place. In many cases, the fights had to be held abroad. Since that time, this sport has become highly respectable and completely harmless. There was a time when horse races were regarded as wicked in most states. Then the moral outlook changed, and the races themselves became virtuous. In the course of time, betting at the track came under the heading of harmless popular amusements, but betting with the bookmaker remained vicious, as heretofore.</p>
   <p>Why betting on the totalizator is permitted, while betting with the bookmaker is prohibited, is not quite clear to sane human reasoning. The normal man lacks understanding of the moral difference between the two activities. For this, one must be either a professional reformer or a Republican member of the Illinois state legislature. Above all, however, the gentlemen who indulged in smooth speeches for the salvation of public morals know full well that everyone who wants to place a bet with a bookmaker gets an opportunity to do so. Hundreds of thousands avail themselves of that opportunity. But the acceptance of those bets is illegal, as heretofore, and constitutes an inexhaustible source of corruption.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0078.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This strange condition of affairs will come to an end through Mayor Kelly's bill. With the licensing of his business, the bookmaker will no longer have to pay graft at back doors to politicians and to policemen. He can conduct his business like any other legitimate undertaking, and the authorities will have, besides, a chance to exercise a certain control over the bookmakers' offices. Above all, the bill will presumably bring in a sizable sum which will flow equally into the school fund and into Chicago's general fund. Chicago can make good use of the money. This is why Mayor Kelly deserves full recognition for having sponsored the bill. The public will not be deceived by the unctuous speeches of the opposition. They know that bookmakers are licensed in England, Germany, and many other countries, where they conduct their business openly, and that the youth of these countries have not become demoralized by it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
