<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-05-10">May 10, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Hateful Intolerance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0551</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0551.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-05-10">May 10, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">HATEFUL INTOLERANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The most abominable [act of] intolerance of recent times in the United States is the temporary closing of the World's Fair on Sundays. A comparatively small minority group, in most cases members of wealthy families, had the audacity to demand that the Fair be closed on Sunday, which is the only day when the working people can visit the World's Fair. Despicable hypocrisy, fear of the large moneybags, and of English-American clericalism, compelled Congress to grant these abominable demands, which are against the clear precepts of the Constitution. The same reasons moved the directors of the World's Fair to close the Fair on Sunday, at least temporarily.</p>
   <p>Another horrifying example of intolerance is the movement of reactionary Americans to outlaw, or deprive of their rights, the immigrants and the naturalized citizens, and first of all, the Catholics.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0552.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Honor and self-preservation demand that all immigrants, as well as all friends of liberty and equality unite to combat this sinister element. The history of the old Know-Nothing party is evidence that such movements do not restrict themselves to attacks on one church only; on the contrary, such a movement begins with an attack against one group, and soon all the immigrants will be under attack.</p>
   <p>At a recent conference of German Methodists, two German Methodist preachers, one of whom is a professor at a Methodist seminary, demanded in all seriousness that Catholics should be outlawed, as well as Jews and nonbelievers. Some German Catholic periodicals are also inciting against the Jews.....</p>
   <p>Many German Methodists condemn the disgraceful conduct of the above-mentioned Methodist preachers. Many German Catholics and others also severely criticize the brutal intolerance of some of the Catholic periodicals.</p>
   <p>However, all these incitements to brutal racial and religious hatred work hand in hand with the persecution mania of reactionary Americans. How can anyone <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0553.jpg" n="3"/>who viciously denies equality and liberty to others, expect those rights for himself and his own?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
