<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-04-13">Apr. 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Ban on Tobacco to Follow Prohibition</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0291</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0291.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-04-13">Apr. 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">BAN ON TOBACCO TO FOLLOW PROHIBITION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The prohibition issue in the United States is not dead by any means. It is true that the Constitution states that intoxicating liquor may not be manufactured, sold, or imported, beginning January 1, 1920. However, defenders of personal liberty intend to attack in court the validity of the Amendment to the Constitution, not only because many citizens think that it is contrary to the spirit of the Constitution, but also because it was adopted in Congress and in various state legislatures, not by a three fourth's majority of all representatives, but merely by three fourths of the representatives present at the time the bill was voted on. Accordingly, the issue will probably be taken before the Supreme Court where it will be determined whether or not this new Amendment is constitutional. And they who relish a "good glass" pin their hopes on the belief that the finding of the Court will allow them to enjoy it next year and every year <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0292.jpg" n="2"/>thereafter. That their hope is built upon a shaky foundation is readily conceded. But man has a tendency to hope as long as he lives; for what would life be without hope? Others are inclined to believe that the Eighteenth Amendment, like many other laws, will remain a dead issue because Congress failed to provide ways and means to enforce it, and because the Amendment did not include beer and light wines in its definition of "intoxicating liquors". Whether or not there is basis for this hope depends upon public opinion, which will have ample time and opportunity to express itself by January 1, 1920. When Congress sees that the majority of citizens do not favor Prohibition, it will act accordingly.</p>
   <p>Of course the prohibitionists are rejoicing, for they believe that they have gained the victory. Therefore they are preparing to attack the next object of their reformative endeavors, the use of tobacco, a habit which a good Puritan abhors, or pretends to abhor, just as much as he does alcohol. Since there is no prospect of preventing the use of tobacco in the United States by an amendment to the Constitution, they are resorting to the tactics which proved so effective in the campaign against alcohol. <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0293.jpg" n="3"/>They say that, although it is not nice to smoke a cigar, or a pipe, or to use snuff, one might put up with tobacco in these forms, but that the cigarette is the root of all evil. It must be eradicated! Away then with the cigarette! Now, it is true that an immoderate use of cigarettes, like that of alcohol, has a harmful effect on the human nervous system and other organs of the human body. But if we should count all victims of the immoderate use of cigarettes, we would probably find it to be a very small number. We would find it to be far below the number of those who have contracted diseases because of unsanitary home conditions, or working conditions, or from inferior food, or lack of nourishment. Why do not these gentlemen, who have made it their business to guard their fellow men against sickness, start reforms in places where their efforts promise to be beneficial? Why do they not try to have an amendment passed which would make it illegal to house the families of workers in overcrowded, dirty tenements, or to force laborers to work in, barn-like, ill-smelling, dark, dirty factories. A reform along these lines is certainly more important than a cigarette ban, for the latter would provide neither better food nor cleaner homes.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0294.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>And when cigarettes have been prohibited, a general ban on tobacco will follow, just as surely as the ban on whiskey was followed by general Prohibition. Prohibition fooled the people. Will they learn from this fact, or will they again do nothing but jeer at the enemies of tobacco until it is too late? No doubt, the excessive use of tobacco harms the nervous system, just as alcohol does. Why, then, is the use of tea, coffee, or candy prohibited? These too, when consumed in great quantities, have a deleterious effect on the human organism. Why do they not prescribe to the free American citizen, what he may eat and drink, and how much; and why should these offenders not be jailed? Any fortunate holder of tobacco stock should dispose of it before it is too late.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
