<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-06-17">June 17, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Germans Demand Open Sunday at the World's Fair.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0563</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0563.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-06-17">June 17, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMANS DEMAND OPEN SUNDAY AT THE WORLD'S FAIR.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Germans have a habit of "looking before leaping". If they enter a battle to protect their highest interests, they are well equipped and equal to the occasion. Their plans of battle are the result of thoughtful preparation; consequently, their victory is certain, and the defeat of their enemy more complete. They have not deviated from these tactics in matters pertaining to the "Open Sunday" at the World's Fair. The Prohibitionists as well as Sunday bigots have attempted to sell their ideas to the Board of Directors of the World's Fair. They have not succeeded so far; but the hour of decision is close at hand. Something has to be done by the Liberals, by the German pioneers of personal freedom, to erect a solid bulwark against the attacks of the fanatics to damage the World's Fair, and cover it with shame and contempt.</p>
   <p>The first to raise the battle cry were the "Rhinelander Union". And how they came - the champions of the German clubs and societies - to fight for the good cause! Indeed it was an enthusiastic crowd, which assembled last night, following the invitation of the Rhinelander Union. H. Schurz officiated as chairman, and J. W. Hermann as secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0564.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Besides, the following organizations were represented by delegates: (Twenty six organizations are listed, including singing societies, athletic clubs, benevolent groups, trade unions, veterans' associations, etc.)</p>
   <p>Individually invited guests, A. C. Hesing, Emil Hoechster, and C. Harter of the Catholic Weekly, were also present.....</p>
   <p>After the purpose of the meeting was explained, one of the delegates, Mr. Amberg, announced that the Central Union M. Ch. two months ago circulated petitions among 15 song clubs in favor of the "Open Sunday"... He proposed to circulate petitions for signatures among all German organizations and others which are, likewise, for the "Open Sunday".</p>
   <p>A. C. Hesing then declared: "As always, so today, I an among the champions of personal liberty. It is well and good to circulate petitions, but these petitions have no effect unless power is back of them. Whenever the Anglo-Americans granted us something, they were not prompted by love, but by fear. We must <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0565.jpg" n="3"/>demonstrate to our opponents, that they will feel our strength at the ballot box, if they deny us our rights. A general demonstration is, therefore, more effective, a mass-meeting in a large hall, and afterward a torch-light procession with music to make our demands known. Especially workers, who have no opportunity to visit the Fair during the week days, ought to be protected in this matter.</p>
   <p>"After the Big Fire, when the Germans were not permitted to build their frame houses again, we marched to the City Hall, 20,000 strong, and demanded our rights, which were, of course, granted to us. If we do nothing, the World's Fair is in danger. What would Europe say if the Chicago Fair were to be closed Sundays? We will unite with the Bohemians and Poles to enlarge our forces, we cannot expect much from the Scandianvians. People appreciate liberty; therefore, let them demand their rights, and fight for the same!"</p>
   <p>....Harter, of the Catholic Weekly, stated that the majority of the clergy and the Catholic editors were in favor of the "Open Sunday".....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0566.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Hesing pointed out that this World's Fair is a national affair, and the masses should be kept in mind. The laborers, the farmers, the small business men, the middle classes have no time except on Sunday to visit the exposition. For these something must be done to rescue the "Open Sunday" for them.</p>
   <p>Amberg's as well as Hesing's proposals, were accepted by the assembly...</p>
   <p>A committee was appointed by the chairman to have petitions printed and circulated, etc....</p>
   <p>Another committee, to carry out Hesings proposal, is to be organized later.....</p>
   <p>Thus the ball has started rolling. The German citizens, who took the first step yesterday to arouse the German and the liberal elements of Chicago for the "Open Sunday", expect a most liberal response. Every German is welcome to this great army of Liberals. He honors himself by joining this movement. Victory can not fail us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
