<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-05-21">May 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Serious or Humorous?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0275</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0275.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-05-21">May 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">SERIOUS OR HUMOROUS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After the President's latest address, according to which the period of war prohibition will probably end July 1 and the palaces of Bacchus will be open to the thirsty until the middle of next January, the New York Academy of Medicine issued an especially interesting warning against the consequences of impending national prohibition. The organization declares that a complete ban on all intoxicants will inevitably be followed by an increase in the insanity rate and in the numbers of those who suffer from nervous disorders. It also said that everyone, except the members of the Anti-Saloon League, is able to recognize the humane, social, and sympathetic side of the moderate use of alcoholic beverages. In a report, Dr. A. B. Brill states that people who drink immoderately are either abnormal or defective, that their mental condition would lead them astray in any event, and that if they could no longer <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0276.jpg" n="2"/>obtain alcohol they would devote themselves to activity which would prove to be far more harmful to them than liquor, as well as detrimental to the peace and order of the community in which they live.</p>
   <p>However, the greatest harm will not emanate from these devotees of Bacchus, according to Dr. Brill. He predicts that during the dry era the cost of living will increase above present levels. He tells of people who renounced drinking intoxicating liquor, only to give themselves to the vice of immoderate eating. He relates a story of a man who had escaped from the shackles of the "demon rum" and soon after began indulging in so-called "roast beef jags"; that is, he suffered from eating five to six pounds of roast beef at a meal. And the doctor has worse things to reveal to the people. He knows of several delicate, ethereal-looking women who were delighted, despite--or perhaps just because of--the fact that they weighed only ninety pounds. They abstained from the use of alcohol. He saw one of these "celestial creatures" eat three large slices of toast spread with strawberry jam, one egg, half a pound of ham, six pieces of cake, crab salad, veal cutlets with tomato sauce, and various <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0277.jpg" n="3"/>entrees, all within one half hour. The inferences which he made from these observations are obvious. We may feel that alcohol is intolerable, but we have greater difficulty in tolerating a fragile member of the weaker sex who consumes nearly all the food on earth in a single meal and thus causes the rest of us humans to pay increased prices on the few victuals which she cannot swallow. No matter from what angle one considers these comments of the Academy of Medicine, one can only conclude that every virtuous person who is concerned with his health should henceforth comply with the admonition, "Stop drinking and renounce eating! Prospects are good, indeed!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
