<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-21">Dec. 21, 1934</date>.
<title level="a"/><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1207</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1207.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-21">Dec. 21, 1934</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On January 3 the new Congress will convene. The prospects are that it will enact a series of laws by which the New Deal will be extended or modified. It was generally supposed that the people had taken a definite attitude toward the New Deal in the last Congressional elections, for this election gave the Democrats so great a majority that it left no room for doubt about the attitude of the electorate. Industrial leaders have obviously taken a different view of the matter, however. They assembled in White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia and, after a very lively meeting which lasted three days, adopted a number of proposals and demands which they have submitted to the Administration.</p>
   <p>Naturally, the great industrialists of this country have a right to take this <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1208.jpg" n="2"/>action, and the administration is duty-bound carefully to consider the proposals and demands. The industrialists declare themselves for a retention of the N. R. A. for one year more. They attempt to solve the laber problem by demanding that workers have the right to treat with the employers either individually or collectively, and either directly or through representatives. The memorandum which was submitted also includes demands that the budget be balanced by a limitation of revenues. [Translator's note: "Revenues" (Einnahmen) is probably a slip of the pen for "expenditures".] and that the currency be stabilized. Both demands are modified, however, by the addition of the words, "as soon as possible".</p>
   <p>In this matter the spokesmen of industry are in complete accord with the President, for he has never permitted the slightest doubt that he considered the current deficit and the flexibility of the dollar merely emergency measures. The memorandum sharply inveighs against the Administration's policy of reviving heavy industry and decreasing the number of unemployed by engaging <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1209.jpg" n="3"/>in public works. The attempts to establish a minimum wage and a maximum work week were also roundly condemned.</p>
   <p>The next demands in the memorandum had to do with finances and forms of credit. The Government is to refrain from attempting to influence these in any way. It is also demanded, explicitly, that the law dealing with the sale of securities be modified. And, finally, the memorandum attacks the artificial curtailment of agricultural production. Doubtless the Administration will reject most of these demands. They represent the economic philosophy of the Old Deal. This philosophy and its practical application were chiefly responsible for the collapse of the American economy five years ago.</p>
   <p>It is difficult to believe that the American people are willing to return to that state of affairs. The New Deal certainly has its faults and weaknesses, and it will be the duty of the next Congress to weed these out as thoroughly as possible on the basis of the evidence at hand. But it will not return to <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1210.jpg" n="4"/>the Old Deal. Concerning this it has received a mandate from the American people which cannot be misunderstood.. For it must not be forgetten that not only all the Democrats but also many Republicans in Congress were elected on a platforms the chief plank of which was an unconditional endorsement of the New Deal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
