<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-22"> Mar. 22, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Beer Situation Here and Abroad</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0313</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0313.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-22"> Mar. 22, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE BEER SITUATION HERE AND ABROAD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our brewmasters who are to cease manufacturing that foaming beer on April 30 can console themselves. They are not the only people whose profession has suffered because of the War. The brewing industry of Germany also has cause for just complaint. Of course there is a great difference between the situation here and abroad. Here in the United States the dark cloud of prohibition is spreading its menacing shadow over our land and its people. If those fanatics who want to save not only themselves, but also all other people, according to the principles which they have hatched, should have their way, this country of liberty would soon be like a hunting ground which is overrun with snoopers. Woe to the unfortunate housewife whose fruit juices, preserved in carefully closed and sealed containers, change into wine by fermentation, which has set in according to the inexorable laws of nature! One must shudder at the thought of such an outrage. For it is self-evident that the lady who <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0314.jpg" n="2"/>does the preserving is responsible for the products of her culinary art. But what would happen to the archrogue who knowingly and intentionally makes his own beer at home is known only to the demigods and angels in Congress and the various state legislatures, who in their infallible wisdom have given us this Greek gift, without as much as asking whether we want it or not.</p>
   <p>Germany has not been touched by this prohibition terror which apparently is settling upon our people and country like a nightmare. In Germany not even the Kaiser, or Chancellor, or any other autocrat would have dared to deprive the people of wholesome beer or wine. Any attempt to do so would immediately be followed by a revolution. It is true, the consumption of all kinds of spirituous liquors was restricted during the War. That was necessary. The raw materials used in making beer--barley and hops--were needed for other purposes. In consequence the German brewing industry was forced to operate on a very limited scale. Commissioner of Commerce Anderson stated in Stockholm that, according to the commercial releases of the U. S. Department of Commerce, of 12,000 breweries which were in operation before the war only 5,000 are doing business now. while the brewers of Northern Germany used <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0315.jpg" n="3"/>1,200,000 tons of barley every year in manufacturing their products, they used but 65,000 tons last year. Many small breweries were forced to close. Others tried to save their business by merging with other breweries, or by making substitutes for beer, such as lemonade and all kinds of fruit drinks. The difficulties of the industry were greatly increased by rising prices for materials, poor transportation, wage increases, and the impossibility of making barrels. No wonder that the price for beer rose rapidly and the German had to pay more for his heavily watered "war beer" than he did for the better, stronger, and more palatable brew of prewar days. Naturally conditions in the brewing industry will gradually improve after the conclusion of peace, and after several years Germany will produce a beer which is just as good as that which was manufactured before the War. But how will things look in America then?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
