<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1892-09-26">September 26, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Politics.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1892-09-26">September 26, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Politics.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a bad sign, when notwithstanding all endeavors on the side of the Republicans in Chicago, no large German Republican meeting can be brought together so, that even the Republican Governor had to speak before empty seats. The truth is that the Germans of Chicago like those all over the country in increasing numbers, are deserting the Republican cause. The eyes of the Protestants have been opened by the school question and the German electors are convinced that the party of Benjamin Harrison is very different from the party of Abraham Lincoln. They found it advantageous to stick to the Democratic party. Though the Democrats have their faults and are not all angels, they at least are no fanatics, hating foreigners and are no Monopolists. Their teachings come nearer to the thinking of Germans about the affairs and objects of State. A country that is ruled by parties, can not possibly find the ideal party, as the majority of electors are people who only understand what they can see.</p>
   <p>The opposition of the Democrats to prohibition is very contrary to its cowardly acceptance by the Republicans, and that has won many Germans for democracy. Clevelands tariff message also was a courageous deed, and it does credit to his party, that they have nominated him again. The democrats also supported the freedom <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0561.jpg" n="2"/>of conscience and teaching. Generally speaking the democratic principles are preferred by most of the Germans to those of the Republicans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
