<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1934-08-26">Aug. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Conference of the "Drys"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0087</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0087.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-08-26">Aug. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">CONFERENCE OF THE "DRYS"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>History repeats itself in this case, the history of Prohibition. Anyone who supposed that the noble experiment would be buried for good when the "dry" amendment to the Federal Constitution was repealed, will soon be disabused. The leaders of the "drys" are evidently not of this opinion. In Winona Lake, Indiana, a three-day conference begins tomorrow, at which the "drys" will work out a new campaign. The conference was called by F. Scott Mc Bride, General Superintendent of the Anti-Saloon League. The "dry" leaders of six states, Indiana, Illinois, Michigan, Wisconsin, Kentucky, and Ohio, have promised to attend.</p>
   <p>The meeting in Winona Lake is the first of a series of conferences which will <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0088.jpg" n="2"/>be hold in various cities during the next few months. The "dry" campaign is to be carried on throughout the country. As far in the plans of the leaders are known, they intend to use the strategy which proved so successful formerly; that is, they want to be systematic and to proceed step by step. The individual stems in bringing about Prohibition--local option, county option, state prohibition and National Prohibition--should form the basis of the new campaign, also.</p>
   <p>Large sections of the public may believe that this undertaking or the "dry" organization is useless and ridiculous. They are very much mistaken, however, for ever, for over the most bitter opponent of prohibition cannot deny that the repeal of the "dry" nuisance had by no means the beneficial effect which was expected. The income taxes collected by the Federal Government are far behind the estimate, and moonshine stills and bootlogging flourish as before.</p>
   <p>It is asserted that these unpleasant development can be traced to the fact <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0089.jpg" n="3"/>that alcoholic beverages are too highly taxed. This assertion is, no doubt, correct, but that does not alter the fact that, in both these respects the repeal of Prohibition as at least partially a failure. In the last years before the repeal of the "dry" amendment, it was repeatedly asserted--even by the most severe opponents of Prohibition--that the saloons must not return under any circumstances. This declaration in itself was silly, because there is nothing wrong with the saloon as such.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, it cannot be denied that any saloons, in a number of cities, are run in a way that shocks even those people who do not want Prohibition. An improvement of this situation is scarcely to be expected, for the issuance of licenses rests with the local authorities, and in our political system the local politicians have to take into consideration even the undesirable elements of the population. The resulting conditions which are gladly published and exaggerated by the sensational press, furnish the "drys" with a continual supply of material for new propaganda; and there can be no doubt <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0090.jpg" n="4"/>that this propaganda will be effective, and in this connection there is another Matter which should be Mentioned: Many people are complaining that politicians who, in their private business, are wholesale beverage dealers, misuse their political influence by compelling to buy from them.</p>
   <p>It was to be expected that the lawmaking bodies of cities and states--having had years to consider the matter would devise measures for the adequate regulation of the liquor trade, but they have not done it. Mere, too, politics play a very harmful role. In general, the regulations now in force are exactly the same as before Prohibition. The captain of the police district is still the highest court for carrying out, or the disregarding, of the liquor regulations, and whether he wishes to or not, no must be veryliquor regulations, and, whether he wishes to or not, he must be very careful to consider the wishes of the ward committeeman.</p>
   <p>It is clear that under these circumstances there can be no satisfactory and <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0091.jpg" n="5"/>effective regulation of the lisuor trade. The situation today is the same, as it was before the beginning of the Volstead Era. The most effective way to combat Prohibition is to do away with the abuses of the licensing system. As long as the liquor interests and the authoritios fail to recognize this, the "dry" agitation will persist.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
