<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-19">June 19, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Incessant Patchwork</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-19">June 19, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">INCESSANT PATCHWORK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Rapid Transit Company is strongly advocating the proposed feeder lines and the planned transfer system with motor coaches at the terminals of its lines. The public must help induce the state commerce commission to approve these plans.</p>
   <p>There is hardly any doubt that there is room for improvement in our miserable transportation system. Many would unquestionably be pleased if they could transfer (for one fare) from the elevated to a bus, and so continue their journey. There is no question but that every enlargement of the transportation network, every service improvement, is to be welcomed. But this is not the ultimate solution.</p>
   <p>The management of the elevated is trying to overcome the impression made when <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1186.jpg" n="2"/>the question of a general transfer system between elevated and street carlines was discussed. Only such an innovation would constitute a partially satisfactory improvement of transportation. A transportation system such as Chicago needs (and really should have, as a metropolitan city of almost gigantic proportions) will probably remain nothing but a dream for decades to come. There is no subway. The elevated suddenly terminates, on the northwest and west sides, at picnic spots, and on the south, it ends at the very edge of a business district. At the terminal, one has to resort to other means of transportation. Street cars still form the most complete transportation network. The streetcar system includes many main lines, and many feeder lines. Its rolling stock is quite antiquated, very noisy, and shaky.</p>
   <p>It would certainly be much better if the management of the elevated would do everything in its power to come to an understanding with the street car company in the matter of general transfer system.</p>
   <p>To be sure, there are obstacles to overcome. The law stands in the way, for <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1187.jpg" n="3"/>one thing. But where there is a will there is a way. The public is certainly ready to co-operate whenever they have a chance to do so, but patchwork must be eliminated. The public is tired of the eternal bickerings over questions of transportation, and for many years has paid a high price for a rather mediocre service. Much has been promised, but little delivered. Much is said of the spirit of Chicago, of its progressive nature, of the "I Will": Much has been done in the last hundred years, but the too dense settlements of some wards and the forlorn and blighted areas in other wards will not become balanced until better transportation facilities are created. Today it does not matter so much that the zoo in Brookfield can be reached by the elevated; the important thing is to build an ample system within the limits of Chicago, and to give the people the kind of service they have a right to expect. The demand that the city should take over the transportation companies will no longer be heard if the private companies can show that they are equal to the problem, and are really willing to solve it--not each one for itself, but all of them together.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
