<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-02-21">February 21st, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The First Shot.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0470</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0470.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I B 2 (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>DIE ABENDPOST</title>,
<date when="1910-02-21">February 21st, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The First Shot.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United Associations fired the first shot in the battle against prohibition. It fell on the Southside. The mass-meeting of the German Clubs of the South and Southwest side at the Teutonia Turnhall, Ashland Avenue and 53rd Street, is to be regarded as the opening barrage. The extraordinary response, which was not restricted to the German Clubs gives ample evidence, that enthusiasm for the cause of personal liberty has mounted considerably, since the memorable massmeeting at the Armory of the 1st Regiment, where the "United Association for Self Government" was founded. It was very surprising to find so many clubs of non-German character there, as the meeting was held principally for German participation. The cosmopolitan division, near the stock yards, sent representative of all nations and hundreds could not gain admission as the hall was as too small to accommodate the masses who came voice their protest against the corruption of the Anti-Saloon League. The speakers who illuminated the question from various angles were greeted with great applause, which was also a bestowed to the singers and Turners (gymnasts).</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0471.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Extraordinary recognition was given to A. J. Cermak, Secretary of the United Organization, who showed that Hyde Park, Austin etc., who have no saloons and therefore collect, no liquor tax, are kept clean at the saloon-keeper's expense. This is one of the most important questions we must solve, explained the City father.</p>
   <p>We came from foreign countries to enjoy liberty and now, laws are proposed to dictate food and drink for us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
