<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-04-01">Apr. 1, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Wright, Harrison by B. Baum</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0679</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0679.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-04-01">Apr. 1, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">WRIGHT, HARRISON by B. Baum</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The exact answers of the mayoral candidates, Wright and Harrison, were not given to the Wirthsverein (Tavernkeepers' Association) because of an oversight by the committee--of which I happened to be a member--and, as an impartial citizen, I consider it a duty to submit these replies so that voters may form their own opinions. (We did not interview Dr. Ernst Schmidt [Socialist candidate for mayor], because there is no doubt that he subscribes to the most sensible views on the temperance question).</p>
   <p>We saw Mr. Wright first. In regard to the law pertaining to minors he said, "I hope to see my children grow to maturity, and don't intend to raise them as drunkards, but I would never give my assent to a law which prescribes that a saloonkeeper should be a sort of guardian to my offspring and be held responsible <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0680.jpg" n="2"/>for their conduct because that would be unjust. I would not revoke a saloonkeeper's license if he transgressed in this manner unless it is proved that he knowingly and deliberately had flaunted the law.</p>
   <p>In regard to the closing of saloons on Sundays, he said, "I would not seek a change in the present Chicago Sunday statute; the question was settled in 1873." Concerning the midnight closing hour, he expressed himself as follows: "I would not draw a distinction between a respectably managed tavern and a hotel; both have equal rights." As to whether he was the president of the Citizens League, he said no; his and some fifty or sixty other names were placed on the list without his consent or knowledge; he has never been a member of a Red Ribbon Club.</p>
   <p>So much for Mr. Wright.</p>
   <p>We then submitted the same questions to Mr. Harrison. He said, "Mr. Feldkamp, you know me well enough to know that I am not a prohibitionist." Thereupon, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0681.jpg" n="3"/>Mr. Feldkamp replied, "Of course, I know you, but this does not answer the question about minors." To this Harrison's retort was, "Look at this young man, he is my son. How can you tell his age? He looks as if he were twenty-two years old, yet he is not even nineteen."</p>
   <p>About the Sunday and twelve o'clock closing ordinances, he referred us to his seven-year record as a public official. He said, furthermore, "I've had headaches from drinking too much wine, but also I've had bellyache and cholera morbus from excessive eating, and from drinking ice water."</p>
   <p>That ended the conversation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
