<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-08">Nov. 8, 1934</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1450.jpg" n="2"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-08">Nov. 8, 1934</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>by the ABA., have been confirmed and thus made enforceable by the N R A. It will be possible, from now on, to supervise the whole field of investments by the committee of the IAB in collaboration with the Security and Exchange Commission. The higher court is the National Code Committee, which will also have jurisdiction over all appeals.</p>
   <p>The new regulations are, by their nature, quite complicated, and the chairman of the National Code Committee admitted that it would be possible even for an honest businessman to go afoul of one or the other of the regulations. Only where the defects are intended and serious will the case have to be brought before the control office of the National Code Committee, which has the right to fine the guilty $500 on each count. Should the party fined refuse to pay, then the case will be referred to the N R A, which can change the fine into a prison term.</p>
   <p>Even if the execution of the new regulations and the procedure they involve are sufficiently complicated and, especially in the beginning, be less smooth, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1451.jpg" n="3"/>one must, nonetheless, agree with the purpose of the movement. One must not expect too much, at least in the beginning, and believe that everything from now on that is offered as an investment must be absolutely secure. First of all, it will take time to eradicate dishonest businesses, for they will, with the aid of unscrupulous attorneys, attempt to continue their practices by finding all sorts of loopholes. On the other hand, one must not forget that certain monetary investments are more or less of a speculative nature, although they are offered by honest firms. One must always bear in mind that low interest rates go hand in hand, as a rule, with greater security of the capital invested. Who is out for a greater and quicker gain should keep in mind that not all dreams come true, and that the thing may have an undesired end.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
