<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-24">Sep. 24, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Coopers Speak.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1600</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1600.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-24">Sep. 24, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE COOPERS SPEAK.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The master-coopers of Chicago have spoken and endorsed Altgeld's stand on the prison-labor question in a most forceful manner. Through their president, Daniel W. Ryan, a Republican, who, incidentally is also president of the International Master-Coopers Commercial Bank, and Secretary H. L. Schmidt, they repudiated the Fifer prison commissioners' excuses, in yesterday's session; a lecture which is destined to unbalance Fifer's mental equilibrium.</p>
   <p>When Altgeld started the fight, Fifer's prison commissioners gave an instantaneous reply. Fifer was jubilant, their answer appeared as the salvation which would pull him out of the mire, and on the came evening Altgeld fired his second shot. Since than it is clear to all who followed the controversial issue, that Fifer is actually responsible for the continuance of the horrible prison-labor system, and that it is maintained in defiance of constitutional law.</p>
   <p>Fifer turned and twisted himself like the proverbial worm, but Altgeld quoted official reports, all certified facts, as proof for his arguments, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1601.jpg" n="2"/>and the best part of it, what really counts was, that the manufacturers and laborers whose destiny is jeopardized by this damnable system, now stand united to a man behind Altgeld. The answer from the Master-Coopers Commercial Bank gives us the best assurance, that Fifer's prison commissioners are the representatives of the monopolistic contractors,i. e., the political favorites, while Altgeld upholds the cause of the injured business men and their employees.</p>
   <p>The denunciation which President Ryan and Secretary Schmidt of the Commercial Bank signed, speaks for itself.</p>
   <p>"To the Commissioners of the Joliet penitentiary.</p>
   <p>"You have recently tried to justify your actions, after Judge Altgeld, in his Joliet speech, accused you of ignoring the prison labor law, instead of obeying its dictates. You admit that you transgressed but you blame the legislature. You endeavor to shift the responsibility upon the representatives, when you know that the law of November, 1888, which was adopted at the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1602.jpg" n="3"/>behest of a 20,000 majority, prohibits the leasing of prison labor. Regardless of the existence of a law which was passed with such tremendous efforts, you have deliberately misrepresented the facts to the people of this state, when you claim that the commissioners and the governor are only too anxious to uphold this law.</p>
   <p>"This amendment was adopted on November 2nd, 1836. On the 22nd day of Nov. 1886, the Governor (Oglesby) issued a proclamation, what the law had become a part of our constitution.</p>
   <p>"But shortly before the passage of the constitutional amendment, the commissioners clandestinely signed contracts with the favorites of the state administration, in order to provide an outlet for prison products, evidently fearing that the law would be adopted. This proves clearly and plainly how 'anxiously and eagerly' the commissioners advocated the abolition of prison-labor!"</p>
   <p>The statement of the Coopers Commercial Bank continues with a detailed list, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1603.jpg" n="4"/>giving specific incidents about the separate members of Fifer's prison commission, and the method used to circumvent the law.</p>
   <p>"The commissioners seem to labor under the belief that a prison is a private enterprise and their sole duty is to put it on a profitable basis. That is not the purpose of a penitentiary and the object of the constitutional amendment was to relieve free labor which was entirely displaced by convict workers, From a humane point one can only say, that the great profit upon which the commissioners harp, was extracted from the blood of the inmates.</p>
   <p>"The production of 80 barrels per day has taken the life of many a poor devil who had to work for the contractors. The official list of the prison administration proves only too well that the whisperings of the prisoners are truths. If it is desired to dispatch a convict into the hereafter in the shortest possible time, then he is given employment in the cooperage division.</p>
   <p>"When our committee had an interview with Governor Fifer and the commissioners, we succeeded in convincing him about the odiousness of this system. He, himself and in our presence, admonished the commissioners to abolish it.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1604.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Commissioner Jones, however, objected and because angry, leaving the conference in a bad humor. Fifer has done nothing to redeem his pledge. The prison ring, whose pliable creature he is, won't tolerate it."</p>
   <p>Year Naturalization.</p>
   <p>The Republican campaign managers have now come to the conclusion, that this year's naturalization crop, won't produce which for the Fifer party, while the Democrats will obtain more than the lion's share of the new citizens, which means the Germans, Irish, Bohemians and Poles. They gave up even their apparent efforts to inculcate the new arrivals into the citizenry flock; however, all their work is how concentrated on one point, namely, to halt the progress of the Democrats and their allies by checkmating the naturalization proceedings as much as possible.</p>
   <p>Finally it occurred to them that it would be a good idea to enshroud the naturalization technicalities with such abstruse difficulties, that the dumb "Dutchman" won't dare face a judge and ask for his papers. In all <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1605.jpg" n="6"/>seriousness the Republican committee rulers proposed that the Republican judges should induce their Democratic colleagues, to agree on a co-operative modus operandi. This method was to be a long-winded, most exhaustive questionnaire, calculated to confuse and terrify the applicants until they desist.</p>
   <p>A Republican judge, who happens to be a better politician than jurist, consented to take the preliminary steps and tried dickering with the Democratic bench. They saw the trap, however, and declined, since, so they announced, the law is plain and they see no reason why they should resort to chicanery and ask unnecessary questions of a prospective citizen. The connivance, whereby the Republicans intend to keep immigrants from acquiring citizenship rights will not secure German friendship for them.</p>
   <p>German Bureau.</p>
   <p>At the German Democratic Headquarters, 125 citizens from the northwest and south sides were naturalized. A judge will now preside during the day time; he takes care of naturalization proceedings exclusively so that <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1606.jpg" n="7"/>applicants will be accomodated promptly.... during the day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
