<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1918-08-25">Aug. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Don't Let 'Em Bluff You</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0928</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0928.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1918-08-25">Aug. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">DON'T LET 'EM BLUFF YOU</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With regret we observe the withering of the German press in the medium- and small-sized cities of our country. The only reason why a German [newspaper], or any newspaper for that matter, should forfeit its right of existence is the adoption of an unpatriotic attitude. But this reason does not apply here [i. e. as an explanation of the decline of the German-American press], since all newspapers that have been recently closed down were published by special permission of the government, which fact in itself constitutes an unfailing guarantee of loyalty. The main reason can be found in the intimidation of the readers and advertisers, and that such can be brought about is amazing, since those who conduct the war in this country against the German press have neither the law nor the government on their side. The law does not prohibit the publication and, least of all, the reading of German newspapers. <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0929.jpg" n="2"/>The government itself has publicly declared, through its officials, that it considers the German newspapers a valuable aid, because they disseminate information about the war and its causes throughout those circles which cannot be reached by publications in the English language. It is especially pointed out, with praise, that the German press has been of excellent service in promoting the sale of Liberty Bonds and savings stamps. Therefore, whoever subscribes to or reads a German newspaper does not act against the government, but gives his support to its [the government's] great task in spreading the ideals of liberty and justice all over the world. Thus, there is not the slightest reason to do without German newspapers, and it shows a lack of courage [when one permits himself] to be intimidated by irresponsible people. It will not be long before Germans will be really sorry that they have forsaken their press.</p>
   <p>The unscrupulous individuals who are raving against the German press are old enemies, known in American history under the name of Know-Nothings. Their <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0930.jpg" n="3"/>hatred is directed against anything that does not agree with their limited scope of thought, and even assumes a religious character, as is proven by the history of the Know-Nothing movement. These enemies have known all along that the German press was their strongest adversary, and since it always stood for reason, justice, and a civilized attitude, they could not do it any harm. The present war offers them a welcome means to realize their intentions, which call especially for the destruction of the German press. If they succeed, the defenders will be gone, and we will face conditions similar to those prevailing during that sad period of our history when the Know-Nothings were a political power.</p>
   <p>It therefore becomes an urgent duty to support the German press, which has fought the Know-Nothing movement with such success and there isn't the slightest reason why it [this urgent duty] cannot be performed. The government of the United States will have nothing to do with the kind of people we are speaking of. It respects everyone, regardless of origin or religion, as <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0931.jpg" n="4"/>long as he is loyal. Neither does it evince any enmity against the German press, of which it expects nothing else than loyalty, just as it does of all newspapers. If this duty is fulfilled, there is no reason why readers should feel apprehensive because of irresponsible and lawless individuals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
