<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-28">Apr. 28, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">Washington Centennial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1035</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1035.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-28">Apr. 28, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">WASHINGTON CENTENNIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a few days it will be one hundred years since the "grand" conduct of the American people furnished suitable material for the author of "A Fool's Paradise."</p>
   <p>This event will therefore be crowned with a grand spectacle, excelling all silly tricks up to the present time, and it is baptized "Washington Centennial" because a hundred years ago Tuesday Washington assumed the office of President of the United States, an institution which has in the meantime developed into a kingdom in a full-dress suit.</p>
   <p>After a hundred years of development America has actually succeeded in growing from a people's state, the republic, into a plutocratic state with a citizen-king at the head as executive officer.</p>
   <p>As loyal subjects we have the excuse to get as drunk as lords in pure joy and <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1036.jpg" n="2"/>gladness, to get tipsy not only from brandy, but also from bombast, fireworks, and parades.</p>
   <p>One may cry himself hoarse and show his reverence to god Mammon with a fool's cap on his head. Submissively, yes, the Americans have grown to be good and loyal subjects, although they call themselves the freest people in the world!</p>
   <p>The Americans like to drink a flowery toast just as much as Paddy likes one of straight rye whiskey.</p>
   <p>The plans for this great masquerade which will be carried out in a few days in all the major cities throughout the country are really jolly. The head night watchman in Washington, the night watchmen of the states, and the vice-night watchmen of the different cities have given orders to their loyal subjects to assemble at their places of worship on April 30 and thank God, the Lord, for all the kindness He has showered upon this preferred country during the past one hundred years.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1037.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Yes, this country, which extolls its freedom, is a real paradise for church humbug, an achievement which deserves to be celebrated just as well as the dispossession of the people from their land, money, and government. It is quite a natural consequence that this race of serfs which throws itself in the dust before the money-bagged citizen-throne also remains on bended knees before the third in that union, the "God" who determines the fate of all peoples.</p>
   <p>When the sacrificial services for God, the protector of the United States, are performed, there will be games and shows for old and young, big and little in a general rendezvous on the streets and roads and in the halls.</p>
   <p>The earth will tremble at the manifold public joy and festivity, until the noise will find a dignified and in mad orgies late in the night.</p>
   <p>The next morning the whole population will awake with a tremendous Katzen jammer. But they will again go along patiently on their accustomed <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1038.jpg" n="4"/>ways to the bone mill. We have only one consolation in this tragic comedy: no second Centennial of this kind is going to be celebrated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
