<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-03">Jan. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Matrimony--A Fifty-Fifty Proposition!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0817</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0817.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-03">Jan. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">MATRIMONY--A FIFTY-FIFTY PROPOSITION!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The old story that, when trains arrived in Chicago, the conductors used to shout "Five-minute stop for marriages and divorces!" has a much more serious foundation than many people would believe. The carelessness with which a man and a girl contract a "union for life" and the thoughtless haste with which they shake off the fetters of matrimony whenever it seems convenient to do so, seriously endangers the institution of the family, which is the ethical foundation of all nations, including our own. The disastrous consequences of a couple's separation will only in rare cases be limited to themselves. Judge Hoffmann, presiding in the Cincinnati Court of Domestic Relations, declared recently that, according to a careful estimate, a full third of the children in our country have divorced parents; and that it was also <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0818.jpg" n="2"/>a fact that from the ranks of these children more juvenile delinquents were recruited than from the ranks of those whose father and mother had died. It is not difficult to see the cause for this peculiar fact, typical of the great cities.</p>
   <p>To combat the evil of juvenile delinquency effectively, one has to strike at the root, which lies, undoubtedly, in a family life degenerated more and more by the divorce evil. Where parental care and domestic discipline are lacking, children certainly will grow up without any moral backbone and the way to a life of crime is paved in one's youth. The public school, with a staff composed almost entirely of female teachers, cannot replace the good influence of a home where love and order reign, especially when it is a question of curbing the adventurous spirit or bad tendencies of older boys. The legislature in Springfield will have to occupy itself during the coming session with changes in the state divorce law, which, by the way, are also <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0819.jpg" n="3"/>recommended by several women's organizations. Strange as it seems, the intention is to make divorces easier to obtain, not harder. The proposed measures, for instance, would make neglect of one's home grounds for divorce, and would reduce the time of desertion necessary for divorce from two years to one year, and the time of habitual drunkenness, also, from two years to one year. A local judge warns against the adoption of these measures, pointing out that experience has shown that every relaxation of the divorce laws, or increase in grounds for divorce, serves as an encouragement for divorce. Unless a federal law removes all existing differences between the forty-six separate state divorce laws, any statute in Illinois which makes divorces harder to obtain should be retained.</p>
   <p>The judge could have added that the enactment of a law which put an end to the reckless frivolity with which marriages are contracted in this country would be no less desirable. The existence of Gretna Greens to which couples <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0820.jpg" n="4"/>can go to avoid the marriage laws of their home state, wedding ceremonies performed by ministers without repeated announcements from the pulpit, the issuance of licenses to minors, and many other evils in this connection, should be stamped out.</p>
   <p>If further proof is needed to show that American family life must be protected and encouraged, the fact may be cited that only 2,300,000 children were born in the United States last year. This figure may look large but it is hardly adequate. It means that one child was born to every ninth family. That is not a thing to be proud of. Taking the figures of previous years as a basis, we have to suppose that during the last year at least 2,300,000 persons died, which means that we did not make any gain in population by way of a natural increase. The increasing dislike of American women for bearing children and the decrease of immigration are also unfavorable factors which cannot be overlooked.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0821.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In the local Women's Forum magazine of last week, women discussed the topic: "Is marriage a failure?" without arriving at any final conclusion. To these ladies who thirst for knowledge we take the liberty of suggesting the following topic for their next debate: "Matrimonial union is a fifty-fifty partnership with duties and privileges, in happiness and sorrow, in work and recreation, which only death can render asunder;" providing, of course, that such a definition of married life does not seem too old-fashioned to ladies seized with the spirit of modernism!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
