<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1891-10-31">Oct. 31, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Politic Upon the Englsih - American Pulpit.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0876</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0876.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1891-10-31">Oct. 31, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">POLITIC UPON THE ENGLSIH - AMERICAN PULPIT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last few days a report came that a number of clergymen of the English-American protestant Churches have resolved to Participate directly in the election battle by agitating from the pulpit for their candidates.</p>
   <p>The attempt of religious fire-brands to make the church the arena for politics can not be condemned to severely. No reasonable and logically thinking man will deny the right to any parson, who is a citizen of this country, to take part in politics outside the pulpit. There is no justice in merely permitting him to vote and then to deny him all other political activity. If he has the stuff and the call within him he may declare his political convictions and fight for the principles of his party upon any secular platform. If only a few clergymen, relatively speaking, have made use of their privilege, it is due to the prevailing sentiment against their participation in politics. But other difficulties do exist which confront clergymen, namely that then congregations usually consist of members affiliates with different parties. Political activity of the pastor, therefore, undoubtedly would interfere with the peace and harmony of the congregation. There are few congregations which would not take offence, if the pastor were politically active.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0877.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The attitude of the previously mentioned English-American clergymen appears to be a inconsistent, much more so since they not only agitate politically outside the church, but also use the pulpit for this purpose. Such action can in no wise be justified.</p>
   <p>To use the pulpit for political propaganda is a desecration of the place of worship. People who attend church desire to be edified and to worship. They do not want politics there; nor do they care for discussions about the qualifications of a respective candidate for a political position. Clergymen who use the pulpit for political purposes render their respective religion a very poor service.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
