<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-10-22">Oct. 22, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">Opium Eaters</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0055</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0055.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-10-22">Oct. 22, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">Opium Eaters</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Brother" Peterson, of the "temperance platform," issues a detailed report of the proceedings of the Grand Lodge of Good Templars. In this report some questions pertaining to conscience are asked and answered in a very interesting manner. We quote one:</p>
   <p>Question: "Is the habitual use of opium as a stimulant considered wrong if it causes intoxication or violation of our obligations?"</p>
   <p>Answer: "No. However, great care must be exercised in such cases."</p>
   <p>Here we have the gist of the whole tendency and objective of temperance advocates. Even the most moderate consumption of pure, harmless, and wholesome beverages--beer, wine, and cider--is a great crime in the eyes of <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0056.jpg" n="2"/>these arrogant hypocrites; but the use of opium, the most devitalizing and enervating of all known vices, is not considered to be a violation of their temperance vow.</p>
   <p>By their own admission it is clear why the use of opium in the United States has increased three or four times during the past ten years. The advocates of temperance are using it!! And this association, which admittedly is addicted to this vice which enslaves those who practice it more than any other bad habit can, wants to prescribe for, and force moral laws upon their fellowmen! Was there ever a more infamous or despicable humbug?</p>
   <p>We have seen Chinese in their secret haunts where they indulge in the forbidden use of opium; we have observed them in all stages of the effect of this poison, from the stimulation of the first few drafts to the climax of intoxication and thence to the misery of the inevitable headache and nausea, and thus we have a good idea of what takes place in a private session <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0057.jpg" n="3"/>of the temperance advocates. And now we ask in all fairness: Shall the majority of the people of the United States be governed and bamboozled by these men who are weak slaves to their secret vices?</p>
   <p>Never!!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
