<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1873-02-28">February 28, 1873</date>.
<title level="a">The Celebration of October 9th</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1873-02-28">February 28, 1873</date>.
<title level="a">THE CELEBRATION OF OCTOBER 9TH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Thanks to the initiative of the Illinois Staats Zeitung, the project has arisen of celebrating the second anniversary of the destruction,- or should we say the reconstruction of Chicago, since it was started on the very same day as the Fire,- progressing in a most satisfactory manner. Mayor Medill made his intentions known last Wednesday at a meeting. of industrialists. It is surprising that no Germans were at this meeting. But the Germans are not responsible for that, because the Americans failed to invite them. With an insolent forgetfulness, that characterizes them and which makes them forget at masquerades what they owe to decency, the Americans have once more overlooked publishing the invitation for the Wednesday meeting in the German newspapers. Do Americans believe perhaps that they alone can organize celebrations? If the committee appointed last Wednesday understands its duty, it will make good its neglect and increase its number through representatives of other nationalities. The committee, which is charge of all the arrangements, must be elected by a general meeting, not by a meeting representing only part of the population. It is time that our American fellow citizens begin to realize, that the Germans are tired of being merely endured, that they are not <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1114.jpg" n="2"/>satisfied with a delayed invitation and with the permission to say"yes" and "amen" to every thing, Almost one third of Chicago population is German. In the factories money is earned to a great extent by Germans, and the reconstruction of the German section of Chicago has kept pace with the more proud section of the South Side.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
