<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-04-01">Apr. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The German Way and the American Way</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0950</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0950.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-04-01">Apr. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN WAY AND THE AMERICAN WAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Native German newspapers seldom report correctly about American conditions. They are not always to blame themselves; they are ill-informed. We have before us an article from the Frankfurter Zeitung published in February, 1915, dealing with "our" position as Germans in this country and showing "the Americans in their true colors." We can say right here that the picture is distorted. The author claims to have lived in this country for a generation, and that he is a German teacher. This makes it all the more regrettable that he did not learn any better how to evaluate the attitude of the American towards the German and things Germanic [Deutschtum]. Some people take pains to speak truthfully. Truth itself is never and can never be offensive. It is the way and manner, or the implied intention with which a truth is announced that makes it objectionable. And the truth which our correspondent promulgates <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0951.jpg" n="2"/>in the Frankfurter Zeitung is not only a slight to the Americans, but makes us Germans in this country look like pure simpletons who haven't the courage of their convictions.</p>
   <p>In order to understand, why so many of "our" dear compatriots often are deceived by appearances, we must try to look at things from their mental angle. All the news which they see printed in the English [language] press they read with the same eyes as they would a German newspaper. Since the German is used to depend on the relative exactness of a German news report, he puts equal credence in the reports of the English [language] press. This is the great error which our countrymen over here commit, and which is also frequently made by the German native press. It is not so easy to comprehend the secret mechanism which makes a great English daily paper tick. Only very few English [language] papers derive any profit from the enterprise itself. Every newspaper serves some person or agency, whose particular interest it must, under all circumstances, promote. This <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0952.jpg" n="3"/>necessarily lowers the press from the level of a medium of culture to that of a mere tool, which serves the promotion of personal, corporate or political party interests exclusively. He who knows why the German is so unpopular in the world, will also know that it cannot be the job of the English press to pay honors to German science but that, on the contrary, they feel obligated to fight Germany's economic progress. Anything that is likely to be detrimental to Germany's economic power, is joyfully discussed in the English [language] press.</p>
   <p>All this is easier to understand if one is aware of the intimate relationship between the American and the English press. Spiritually, our press is fed by England and, for the larger part, with [English] money too. Several months before the outbreak of the war, the publisher of the London Times has made a personal check on things here in America. When war came, the Americans cried in unison, pointing at Kaiser Wilhelm, "He did it!" He started the war, and to this day they still stick to it, proofs of the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0953.jpg" n="4"/>contrary notwithstanding. They could and must not tell the truth, even if their editors were threatened with a penitentiary sentence. This shows how loyally they serve the interests of those who own the press, and these interests are English.</p>
   <p>England holds more stock in our great enterprises than is owned in the United States. England could not keep her American colonies under the rule of King George, but she is keeping the United States under the thumb of the Bank of England. Who would assume, therefore, that the Anglo-American press was representative of American public opinion, and would judge the American people accordingly, would do too much honor to that press and would do the people a grave injustice.</p>
   <p>We could write volumes to prove it. If the American would be like the German in this respect, justified and willing to accept the veracity of newspaper reports as does the latter, then we would be correct in holding <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0954.jpg" n="5"/>the people responsible for their attitude. But the American looks upon a newspaper from a business point of view: "I can manufacture whatever I please and I can sell to whomever I care."</p>
   <p>The German cannot easily comprehend this kind of mentality and because he cannot or perhaps does not want to, he is accused over here as being un-American. And the German, vice versa, reproaches the American for lacking in culture. But he who has the capacity to analyze German culture as well as the development of the American people, will find that both do another an injustice. To aggravate matters there is now this war, which tends to bring out the less pleasant aspects of American political and business ethics, in bold relief. The "idea", that it was not unethical to sell war materials to England and company, while Germans did not even get breadstuffs, is of course fallacious, but the American, being a businessman, argues that the business is legal. He would feel grievously wronged, if government would deny him the right to go after this business.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0955.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Otherwise he may feel quite sorry for the poor Germans who are not in the position to buy but, after all, that is not his (the American's) fault. The German, on the other hand, feels that this attitude is unworthy of a man of culture, and forgets that Kultur, the way we conceive it, is wholly alien to the American. The latter may have "culture", may be well behaved in dealings with his fellow man, but Kultur is something totally different.</p>
   <p>The American people are only beginning to become a national entity. We must keep this in mind above all things. The correspondent of the Frank furter Zeitung, asserting that "the designation 'people' is a misnomer for that amorphous mass of humanity that lives over here" is altogether mistaken. A people they are, but they have no uniform and common culture [Kultur]. In future days, when immigration will have come to a standstill, we shall see whether the Germanic, the Romanic, or the Slavic races will have put their indelible mark on the American national character. The <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0956.jpg" n="7"/>East today bears mainly Anglo-Saxon characteristics; English ideologies prevail there, which was the reason for the totally faulty opinion gained by that German teacher from the State of New York.</p>
   <p>But he is hardly an authority, and will become less so in the future. The large Mississippi valley, the vast expanse between the Alleghanies and the Rocky Mountains make up the bulk of this country, and it is here that the future character of the American people will come into being. There we shall see whether the Deutschtum [Germanic element] can develop enough strength to be the decisive factor in shaping this character. In the East it has not been able to. Here, in the Middle West, the Deutschtum has made fairly good progress in this direction. Even though German ideas and suggestions are accepted with obvious reluctance, they are nevertheless heeded every day. And let us be fair; in no country in the world would the foreign-born and those of foreign descent, while adhering to their "alien" customs and ideas, he able to exert a similar degree of <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0957.jpg" n="8"/>influence on public opinion as the German element actually does today in Chicago. There cannot be any talk about subservience in this case. And neither the English [language] press nor the population would ever take it into their head to stop the Germans from following their own customs or displaying their German sentiments and feelings. The totality that is American must be surveyed from a national point of view, not from a local one. The correspondent of the Frankfurter Zeitung has missed his mark by a wide margin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
