<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-14">Dec. 14, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Mental Bankruptcy</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0171</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0171.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-14">Dec. 14, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">MENTAL BANKRUPTCY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before the House Committee of Ways and Means recently there appeared the leaders for prohibition, men and women, to express their opinions about the planned change in the Volstead amendment. What these ladies and gentlemen had to say in this case is, in many ways, remarkable. Their contentions betray stupidity, fanaticism and an amazing inability to think logically. These people experienced the mastery (sic) of prohibition. They saw how an amendment was inserted into the Constitution making compulsory dryness a part of our country's fundamental law. They lived to see that the executive ordinances to this constitutional amendment, the Volstead Law, was written by one of their ablest and cleverest leaders, the late Wayne B. Wheeler, and accepted by a submissive Congress.</p>
   <p>Then they had to make the observation that prohibition did not prohibit, that, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0172.jpg" n="2"/>despite the Eighteenth Amendment and the Volstead law, drinking kept on apace. This made them conclude that the Volstead law was not drastic enough. Accordingly, the dry laws had to be given a keener edge, and the dry fleet was built up to impede the smuggling of whiskey on both seashores and on the Great Lakes. This dry fleet kept being enlarged until it took fifth place among the fleets of the world. At the same time other pithy laws for the suppression of the liquor traffic were passed which in the so-called five and-ten law reached the height of brutality.</p>
   <p>But all to no avail. Illegal traffic in liquors assumed gigantic dimensions; crime was increased, and this resulted in unheard-of orgies of corruption. The turning point came at last. The 1928 elections showed an enormous increase of wet ballots. In the 1930 Congressional elections numerous congressmen and senators were defeated and the latest election brought to the opponents of prohibition a shining triumph.</p>
   <p>All these events passed over the heads of the dry movement without leaving a <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0173.jpg" n="3"/>trace. They know as little about it as though they had been living on another planet all that time. In a dull, reiterating monotony they continue re-echoing the same old worn-out phrases about the blessings of prohibition with which for the last twenty or thirty years they went canvassing the country. They have not noticed that, during the whole dry period, the land had prohibition only in theory, and that in reality the consumption of alcohol was far greater than it had been under the permit system. Their arguments are wholly attuned to the appeal to the emotions. Facts, irrefutable and generally accepted, are shunted by them in a grandiose manner, receiving no attention. These utterances are riotous imbecilities and so stubborn as only blind fanaticism can be.</p>
   <p>A comparison is rather amusing between these goings on and the resolutions of church heads. Recently the department for social reform and education of the committee of Christian churches held a meeting. At this meeting, the following remarkable observation was made: "The endeavors to bring social evils under control, or to do away with them by political action have, in this <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0174.jpg" n="4"/>country, gone far ahead of the process of individual education and enlightenment". If this has any sense at all, it could mean only that that prohibition is a failure, that the enlightenment and education of the individual concerning social evils, of which alcoholic abuse is one, should come first, that it is more important and more promising of results than political action.</p>
   <p>One might exult in knowing that these circles have at last gained insight, but our exultation is premature. Because soon afterward the organization made the following resolution: "We pledge ourselves to support the Eighteenth Amendment and the promulgated laws for its execution. We protest against another referendum as regards the Eighteenth Amendment and its recall". On reading this, one is astounded at the lack of reasoning among these people. They clearly realize that compulsory measures for the combating of social evils are false on principle. But if it comes to deal with an implicit case they want to be identified with those who bravely stick to these futile compulsory measures. It is unnecessary to mention that the circles which the leaders and followers of the Anti-Saloon League, the so-called Christian <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0175.jpg" n="5"/>Temperance Women and other dry organizations come from are the same as in that church committee.</p>
   <p>In the last elections, prohibition was objected to by a preponderant majority of the American people. This cannot be shaken or explained away. We live in a country governed democratically, a country in which the will of the majority has the final decision. This is completely ignored by the mouthpieces of the dry factions. They are in favor of democratic institutions if the majority votes dry; they promptly throw their democratic opinions overboard if the majority differs with them. Taking all this into consideration it appears inconceivable that people who are on such low level mentally, whose ability to think is outdone by a well-trained circus horse, have succeeded to lead millions of people by the nose for many long years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
