<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-27">Nov. 27, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Insull Trial</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1219</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1219.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-27">Nov. 27, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE INSULL TRIAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Samuel Insull and his sixteen co-defendents, who were accused of using the mails for fraudulent purposes, were declared not guilty by the jury, and so were acquitted by Federal Judge Wilkerson. The verdict has raised a great deal of untoward comment on the part of many readers of this paper, making it very distinct that these people have lost confidence in the institutions of justice. It is, perhaps, also to be accepted that the public has absolutely no understanding of the outcome of the trial, and that its comments may illustrate the old German adage "Little thieves they hang, big ones they let go".</p>
   <p>To criticise the procedure of the court, or to suspect the jury, is by no means fair. The trial was excellently prepared by the office of the district attorney, and especially did the assistant district attorney, Leslie E. Salter, who was <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1220.jpg" n="2"/>sent to Chicago by Attorney General Cummings to prosecute the case, prove himself a very able lawyer. He studied and worked on the case quite thoroughly, and submitted it to the jurors in a clear way, easy to understand. It was, however, unavoidable that, in submitting proof of guilt, complicated financial problems had to be discussed, and it is quite possible that not all of the jurors understood them.</p>
   <p>Added to that was the fact that the trial was drawn out too long. For eight weeks the deliberations continued, and the defense attorneys used this circumstance quite skillfully to bring the accused closer to the jury's emotions. Psychological moments of this nature are of great importance, and it is quite understandable that the jury gradually began to feel a certain sympathy for those fallen potentates of the financial world, with whom they actually spent many hours every day. And another thing, the accused derived no profit from the financial transactions for which they were blamed. The public lost, but the accused have lost also. Undoubtedly, this consideration was taken into <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1221.jpg" n="3"/>account by the jurors, and, when the trial came to a close, they must have completely forgotten, thanks to the skillful maneuvering of the facts by the defense, that the defendents were not tried because their undertakings broke down, but because they misused the mails.</p>
   <p>There is, finally, a practical consideration to be made which may have been of importance. To arrive at a verdict, unanimity is essential, according to the law. If the jurors cannot agree, the trial ends The district attorney may then bring up a new indictment; but, as a rule, this does not happen, because experience teaches us that such cases seldom result in convictions. It would have been extremely difficult, in this case, to find a jury which had not formed an opinion of the case. It is possible that the jurors who were originally in favor of conviction took this into consideration, and resigned themselves to joining the majority. It would serve no practical purpose to insist upon conviction.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1222.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>These, however, are only suppositions, but suppositions that crop up when we try to analyze the jury's verdict. What considerations there were which actually led to the acquittal will never be known. Insull, and his friends and advisers, may now be tried on a number of charges in the federal, as well as in the state courts, but whether the necessary indictments will ever be made is rather doubtful. In the face of the failure of the first Insull trial, it seems quite useless to press other indictments.</p>
   <p>The impression the public had from the outcome of the trial must needs be an unfavorable one. Until recently, the inspector of mails was considered a person of dignity. People who received circulars by mail describing certain securities could not, of course, know whether the information given was true. What they knew, however, was that the senders of these circulars would relentlessly be sent to the penitentiary if it came out that they had used the mail to broadcast false information about their business. The stamp on the envelope was a symbol and a token that their undertaking was reliable.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1223.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It is not going to be like that in the future. The Insull trial has shown that anyone may send circular matter by mail, containing false information, without being sentenced for using the mails for purposes of fraud. It is thus inevitable that public confidence in justice is going to be shaken by the outcome of this trial.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
