<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-09-18">September 18, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">Anti-Temperance.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0617</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0617.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1882-09-18">September 18, 1882</date>.
<title level="a">ANTI-TEMPERANCE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night's mass-meeting called by the Turn-Societies, in order to discuss the best ways of blocking the Temperance fanatics, was more or less a disappointment as far as attendance was concerned. Owing to this fact the Democrats had an easy opportunity in trying to win over the new movement for themselves. It is our opinion that the Democrats without in the least intending to have dealt a death blow to the incipient movement.</p>
   <p>Mr. August Spies opened the meeting at 3 P.M. proposing in the name of the Committee to elect Mr. Hochster, chairman. Mr. Frawz Demmler was elected secretary. Mr. Hochster called on Dr. Ernst Schmidt as first speaker of the meeting. Dr. Schmidt who, as a determined fighter for freedom is respected even by his enemies was greeted by thunderous applause; He then said: "I appreciate the welcome you have given me, but I must say, I feel a bit like a horse on parade, brought forward every time during the last 30 years when liberty is threatened. (Applause). The younger generation knows very little of our battles, the shadow of which has drawn us together once again. This is the first time in their lives, that they experience an attack on their liberty and rights. It is the fanaticism of the narrow-minded Puritan, which has spread throughout the country, and is threatening our liberty. In a country like ours, the question of personal liberty should never arise, if the Constitution of our Republic <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0618.jpg" n="2"/>would be lived up to. One such attack on our freedom, if successful, would be followed by a number of others; the fanatics will not be satisfied with one success. No one can love our country more than I do: For its freedom I would do anything. It saddens me to think that those fanatics are trying to trample on our sacred principles, the highest and dearest of human rights. Such a thing must not be suffered!</p>
   <p>Moderation is taught to us Germans: Americans have to learn it yet. If the American mothers would spend more time on educating their children, it would be far better for the young Americans: they would be more able to govern themselves and the temperance question would not be an important issue.</p>
   <p>It is our duty to call into existence an agitation which will prevent a group of irresponsible people from dragging into dust our most sacred human rights. (Thunderous applause). Mr. Francis A. Hoffmann, ex-Socialist and professional politician, was the next speaker. He painted a glowing picture of the glorious past of the Democracy, and called on all, mainly on Socialists, to vote for the Democratic ticket. We don't want to point the dirt and nonsense of his speech, but will confine ourselves to a few short abstracts: "I am surprised that such a seasoned politician as Dr. Ernst Schmidt forgot to tell you to join a political party,- that of the Democrats. For years I have admired the stability of the Socialists, but now I call on them in the name of freedom, to join the Democratic Party. The Democratic platform cannot <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0619.jpg" n="3"/>fail to find the approval of every Socialist. ("Oho, Oho"). It always was the Democratic Party which has stood for human rights". (Loud Laughter).</p>
   <p>The Democrats could not have made a bigger mistake; for their own cause than to have Hoffmann to deliver a speech.</p>
   <p>The chairman then appointed a committee of nine men for the drawing up of resolutions. The members of this committee were: Max Stern, J. Goldzier, F. Kanneberg, Dr. Geiger, Josef Schoninger, H. Lich, J. Sebastian and Josef Kaufmann. Mr. Dietzel, the poet, was the third speaker. He praised the land in which we live and gave a sketch of the battles fought to make it what it is today. He said, a great deal of credit is due the Germans who have taken great interest in the cultural development of this country, and who had a right to resent the ingratitude of the Americans. The temperance question is just one exhibition, of their hatred of foreigners. Concluding his speech he said: My advice to Americans is:- "Learn how to drink, for moderation is a greater virtue than complete abstinence".</p>
   <p>Harry Rubens followed as speaker:- "We are threatened by an enemy whom to defy calls for solidarity. I hope that today's meeting is neither Democratic nor Socialistic, but least of all Republican. To fight the temperance movement, practical measures <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0620.jpg" n="4"/>are necessary. What course do we Germans have to take? The political! What party is most dangerous to us? The Republican Party. He cleverly avoided asking directly for support for the Democratic ticket but he was less than ambiguous indirectly.</p>
   <p>Mr. August Spies the next speaker said: This mass-meeting had not been called by the Turn-Societies with the intention of holding a Democratic rally but, was intended to be a meeting of liberal-minded citizens to confer upon ways and means most instrumental to defy the temperance fanatics. It is unbecoming to use this occasion to spread untrue assertions in order to win votes for one of the corrupt political parties. One of the speakers just has said: "The Democratic party is the only one which stands for freedom and human rights". The truth is that it committed an outrageous crime by upholding slavery. There have been as many other shameful acts committed by the Democrats as those which have been or still are being committed by the Republican Party.</p>
   <p>He urged again to protest against voting on this question and advocated, if necessary, to resort to such means as were employed in the combat for freedom.</p>
   <p>Mr. Stimming, a Republican, defended his Party saying that the Democratic Party is <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0621.jpg" n="5"/>accused of no less faults than the Republican Party is accused of. He said: Notwithstanding the fact, that Kansas was a Democratic state, it was the first state in which Prohibition became a law.</p>
   <p>Mr. Max Stern reported for the resolutions committee. The following resolutions were accepted with a very light vote: Considering that a small but confident Party has the audacity to impose onto the citizens of this country laws, which would destroy one of the important branches of industry and imperil trade in general, etc.etc.</p>
   <p>We, as free citizens and voters of this State pledge our support to those candidates at the coming election, who have preserved an active faith in our Constitution.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
