<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-07">Mar. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0335</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0335.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-07">Mar. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Apparently nothing will come of prohibition, which was to be effective from July 1 of this year.</p>
   <p>The bill which contained proposals for the enforcement of the corresponding Congressional act was among those which, thanks to the Republican filibuster, were cast into the wastepaper basket, and even if the Sixty-Sixth Congress should meet in a special session during May or June, it seems very unlikely that a law implementing the Eighteenth Amendment will be passed, for by that time peace will have been concluded, and then there will be neither excuse nor cause for war measures.</p>
   <p>Wartime prohibition is dead. National prohibition, which is obligatory by reason of an amendment to the Federal Constitution, cannot become effective <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0336.jpg" n="2"/>until next year, if at all. Chicago may have prohibition from May 1 on, for the Illinois Supreme Court has ruled that the prohibition question must be submitted to the citizens for decision in the election on April 1, and if a majority of the voters cast their ballots in favor of prohibition, then Chicago will be "dry" from May 1 on, "bone-dry".</p>
   <p>No doubt there are people who consider that to be impossible; who are inclined to laugh at the thought that it may be possible. But they are mistaken. Today everybody should know that anything is possible; and this (a majority vote in favor of prohibition in Chicago) is very possible. It is possible because there are many among the liberals who think as we have indicated above; because very many permit their wish to become absolute confidence, and their confidence to mislead them into the ever-dangerous underrating of their opponents.</p>
   <p>The stronger the belief of our liberal citizens that there is no danger, and the stronger their conviction that a great majority will vote against prohibition, that a few votes more or less will make no difference, and that they need not <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0337.jpg" n="3"/>go to the polls and vote, the greater the possibility and the probability that the prohibitionists will win. Every vote counts. Every vote is important in this election. For every vote will influence public opinion for or against prohibition.</p>
   <p>The leaders and schemers in the prohibition movement stated that they would not carry on a very vigorous campaign, and that they would make no special efforts to obtain many votes. Let no one be misled. Do not trust them. The prohibitionists are well organized and well schooled. The liberals are not. The prohibitionists can make a strong campaign--in secret, so that the public does not notice it. A quiet campaign is their campaign. The less said and done about the prohibition election, the better for them and for their cause, and the worse for the liberals. The prohibitionists are aware of this. They know that they can get their votes out without loud talking or admonishing; and they know also that the masses of citizens--and these are liberal--are much inclined to put faith in their good cause and in their great numbers, and to let others do the voting, while they stay at home, thinking, "Let George do it".</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0338.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The schemers and leaders among the prohibitionists declared that they would not carry on a vigorous campaign but would ask their followers to cast their vote on the liquor question merely as a matter of form, not because, as they say, prohibition will become effective next January at all events, since it is so decreed by an act of Congress, but because they desire a quiet campaign, and would be well satisfied if most citizens would forget all about the prohibition question on April 1. These leaders announced that they would not concern themselves about prohibition, "since it will be enforced after this year anyway". In this way these schemers hope to keep the vote of the liberal "wets" down to a small minimum, so that the "drys" will have a majority when the votes are counted; and then these "drys" will point to the result of the election in Chicago, which is the stronghold of the "wets," and will make national prohibition certain.</p>
   <p>If liberal citizens do not vote on April 1, national prohibition, which is still doubtful despite all statements to the contrary, will surely become a certainty next January. That ought to rouse even the laziest and most indifferent. But there is more at stake.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0339.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>If national prohibition of alcoholic liquors becomes a fact, then prohibition of other things will ensue. Then, eventually, anything and everything that pleases the ruling element will be demanded of the liberals, and, again, anything and everything that displeases the creators of prohibition will be denied the liberals. For then it will be established by principle that liberty and the right of the individual to determine the course of his life himself no longer exists in America.</p>
   <p>Every citizen of Chicago, without exception, has the duty, owes it to himself, to the city and to the nation, to vote on the "wet-dry" issue on April 1. All citizens whose names do not appear on the polling list, or who have moved since the last election and have not yet registered from their new address, should attend to the duty which they have neglected, and register on March 11; and all voters should ascertain that their names are correctly entered on the registry and polling list.</p>
   <p>Do not forget Tuesday, March 11, the last day of registration!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
