<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-25">Apr. 25, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">They Preach Us a Sermon in Morals</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-25">Apr. 25, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THEY PREACH US A SERMON IN MORALS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We Chicagoans are not particularly well thought of up there in the national capital. In the last few months things have been said about us that are not particularly flattering. Only a few weeks ago she spokesmen of a Chicago reform organization declared that the whole city is wading in a sewer of iniquity and corruption. And now District Attorney Olson has really preached us a sermon. It happened at a hearing on prohibition, before a subcommittee of the Senate.</p>
   <p>Mr. Olson was quite forthright in his statements. He declared that Chicago's criminals had, in previous years, rushed into the beer and liquor trade. But he went after then so vigorously, and cut into their business so much, that they promptly and ruefully returned to their previous occupation, namely, stealing, burglary, and highway robbery.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0213.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The growth of crime here kept pace with the growth of the city, which is quite natural and as it should be. When prohibition was introduced, however, the number of grave crimes was quickly augmented. That came about simply because the bootleggers and liquor dealers made short shrift of the competition and at times also of the police. The number of their murdered victims rose to eighty-seven in the last two years and a half. When one deducts this number from the total of murders committed in the city, its rate will be considerably reduced.</p>
   <p>If District Attorney Olson now contends that he has suppressed the traffic in alcoholic beverages and thus has promoted prohibition in Chicago, he is mistaken. For in this business large organizations are active, well provided with money; they simply could not go on if the illegal liquor traffic were not sizable and lucrative enough. This cannot be denied, although Mayor Dever told the Senate Committee that the contrary was true. It is, however, true that the consumption of beer has been considerably diminished in Chicago. The credit for that is taken by Mayor Dever. He might well have given it all to the district attorney, for as a result (of the suppression of beer) the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0214.jpg" n="3"/>consumption of moonshine whiskey has risen correspondingly, and thinking people are not likely to appreciate the exploit so highly.</p>
   <p>The reproach that local politicians do not greatly exert themselves to enforce the dry laws is certainly justified to the full. These politicians and officials are constantly in close touch with the citizens and they know well enough that prohibition is deeply and cordially hated by them. Being dependent upon the favor and votes of these citizens, why should they act against them and irritate them? Why should they make enemies of their constituents? Methods like these are incompatible with practical politics.</p>
   <p>To be sure, Mayor Dever contends that the city is bone dry and that he and Chief of Police Collins have enforced prohibition. But everyone knows that Chicago is just as wet as any other large city in America, perhaps even a little wetter. In various quarters it is claimed that the district attorney, for purposes of political publicity, is boasting of his achievements in making the city dry. He is said to have the intention of running for mayor as Dever's successor. But what he should really know is that no candidate for mayor can ride into the city hall on the water wagon.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0215.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If President Coolidge comes to Chicago he will be wise not to speak on prohibition. He never yet protested at the votes which the wet Republicans of Chicago have given him and his partisans. If he should do so it would be nothing but a tactless insisting on principles. The statements of the district attorney are based upon an essentially incorrect interpretation of the law and its enforcement. He seems to think that the people exist for the sake of the authorities and that obedience to the laws must be compelled because they are laws.</p>
   <p>But this conception is absolutely untenable and even District Attorney Olson is not consistent in maintaining it. He has no objection to accepting his office from a party which permits the outlawing of colored people in the southern states without a word of disapproval, although two amendments to the Constitution are thereby being violated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
