<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1914-06-17">June 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Nations in Council.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Working to Make a Greater Chicago.</title> By Henry Blackman Sell.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0969</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0969.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1914-06-17">June 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">NATIONS IN COUNCIL.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Working To Make A Greater Chicago.</title> By Henry Blackman Sell.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago's German Citizens: "Chicago's 800,000 Germans are famous for their solid and successful citizenship. The remarkable things about the German in Chicago is that here all the political lines are down in a pan-Teutonic feeling," recently said Harry Rubens, president of the German Mannerchor. "Germans from Austria, Prussia, Switzerland or Germans from Germany, we all stand for better citizenship, as Germans for Chicago."</p>
   <p>Carl B. Roden, whose German birth and early training combined with his splendid work in the Chicago Public Library, has given him a keen insight into the German at work as a Chicagoan, carried this thought further in a conversation with the writer.</p>
   <p>"Your true Chicago German," said Mr. Roden, "is first of all a good citizen of the republic, loyal, intelligent, law abiding, not usually a meddler, an</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0970.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>agitator or a critic of American institutions. He is here not so much a seeker of fortune as of these liberties which our institutions offer and which he found too much hedged about in his former home. He accepts and enjoys these liberties gratefully and with that inborn respect for constituted authority which is one of his strongest traits.</p>
   <p>"If he does not feel inclined to rattle the eagle's feathers neither does he feel called upon to let morality, love of order, and joy of life. His loves and penates are 'sittlichkeit and 'gemutlichkeit', and these may, perhaps, be set down as his chief contribution to American civilization. There is scarcely a department of human activity in America to which Germans have not added their share with honor to themselves and profit to the nation. Chicago would not be the great musical center that it is today without its German citizens. It can barely have retained the right to its name of 'Garden City' were it not for the Germans' love of a garden. But chiefly he has helped us to find ourselves by pouring upon the seething waters of our American life the oil of his stability, his reverence for things as they are and the powers that be, his respect for amenities, moral and political as well as social, his 'sittlichkeit' <gap unit="word" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> so comprehensive that the lord chancellor of England has used it untranslated to connote the whole subject of national and international comity.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0971.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Along with his 'sittlichkeit,'" continued Mr. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, "the German has brought us his 'gemuthlichkeit,' his love of comfort <gap unit="words" extent="3" reason="illegible"/>, his passion for festivals <gap unit="words" extent="3" reason="illegible"/>, his determination to extract whatever of joy <gap unit="words" extent="2" reason="illegible"/> every occasion. His reverence for this <gap unit="words" extent="2" reason="illegible"/> are embraced <gap unit="words" extent="8" reason="illegible"/> without excpeiton or qualification.</p>
   <p>He never wavers in the <gap unit="words" extent="5" reason="illegible"/> things better in the fatherland and especially that they <gap unit="words" extent="4" reason="illegible"/> better. He loves stateliness and ceremonial as much as he loves <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> color and music, and he combines all those in his relaxation whenever he can. No German picnic in a leafy grove is complete without its festival ode composed for the occasion, its chorus singing, its resounding oratory. <gap unit="words" extent="5" reason="illegible"/>. </p>
   <p>"When the German is moved to a protest it is most likely to be when an attempt is made to regulate or <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> his methods of taking his pleasure. Then <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> citizen and respecter of authority that he is, he becomes for the moment a fierce individualist, and is <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> to wield his great political power in defense of his own. But meanwhile much of the color, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, the song, the orderliness and sobriety which prevail in German family lilfe and German festivities have taken root in our own soil to <gap unit="words" extent="2" reason="illegible"/> our life is 
<pb facs="5418474_2_1_0972.jpg" n="4"/>
enriched, our point of view <gap unit="word" extent="8" reason="illegible"/> behavior are clarified and mellowed.</p>
   <p>"Romantic but practical, tolerant but jealous of our privileges, earnest and gay, dignified and happy, and perhaps a little self conscious, the German knows that the German way of doing things is the good way and in that opinion he brooks no contradiction.</p>
   <p>"But always," concluded Mr. Roden emphatically, "and in every relation and capacity, he is a good citizen."</p>
   <p>"The Germans who have been coming to Chicago in large numbers ever since 184<gap unit="chars" extent="1"/> and who have been identified with practically every movement toward a better and a more significant Chicago, are among Chicago's most substantial assets in its development. An inestimable service has been rendered by their "more than 700 organizations" for mutual benefit and the advancement of citizenship.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
