<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-05-21">May 21, 1877</date><title level="a">The Speech by Mr. Rapp ( at the Opening of the Sharpshootes Park)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0882</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0882.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-05-21">May 21, 1877</date><title level="a">THE SPEECH BY MR. RAPP ( AT THE OPENING OF THE SHARPSHOOTES PARK)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is hardly any German whose heart action would not speed up somewhat by the mere mention of the word - Pentecost! Out there in the old fatherland this time of the spring gladdens the hearts of old and young. For upholding this lovely custom of Pentecostal festivities even in America, is largely due to our brave Sharpshooters, Turners, Singers, the Platt-Germans and Warriors of Chicago, who have to be praised for their efforts to keep up this custom. Indeed we are close to the time when the German Pentecostal celebration will be just as such established in Americans is the German Christmas Tree. The Germans delight to go into open sources, especially at this time of the spring, and they do gratify their desire to do so, but with one possible exception, the Sunday forenoon religious services. To make speeches on such occasions as this is an unknown thing to the Germans. This is a bad habit of the Americans.</p>
   <p>...Today's celebration of Pentecost in the old fatherland is saddened by war clouds......</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0883.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We, in this country are so much better off. True, the political and business conditions are by far not what they ought to be, but a change for the better is seen, and what is more important, this country is assured peace and unity for a long time. This prairie to which we came today to celebrate the lovely Feast of Pentecost is not that Picturesque, paradise-like valley of the beautiful Rhein, or that of the Neckars; but this prairie is beautified by the sunshine of peace and freedom....</p>
   <p>This friendly park, its trees and flowers, seen to have heightened their beauty for today, because alongside of their beds are walking German men and women inspired by that innermost feeling: We are Americans, as proud as anybody of the greatness and freedom of our adopted fatherland, but we are Germans also and will never depart from our German customs. we don't given up the serious and conscientious German habits, nothing of the cordiality and genuine feelings nothing of the German untiring willingness for work and nothing of the happy German spirit prevalent on work days as well as on Sundays, and certainly nothing of the German Pentecost....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
