<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>.
<date when="1906-05-24">May 24, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Organized</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0511</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0511.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Bohemian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>.
<date when="1906-05-24">May 24, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">ORGANIZED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The steady pressure exercised by a minority of the population of Chicago by utilizing obsolete laws to curb the innocent pleasures and entertainments of the masses has produced a counter pressure to end it.</p>
   <p>Following the imposing protest meeting held at the Armory Hall, March the 25th, the formation of a Union of all German associations, clubs, lodges etc. has now been established, which systematically will work for the repeal of such obsolete laws.</p>
   <p>More than 350 organizations counting over 60,000 members have become parties to this Union. The objects and purpose of the Union have been explained in previous meetings and Mr. Gloganer indicated, that in a Democratic republic it should be the goal of the majority, to rule for law and public order, and not for the minority to dictate the use of obsolete laws. Mr. Hoechster, the gray-haired speaker of the Chicago Turner Club said, that he has been in the United States 52 years and was just as good an American as any other <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0512.jpg" n="2"/>subject born in this country. This conviction he also has of the great masses of immigrants, whose liberties and rights are now endangered. The German-Americans have proved in the Civil War their faithfulness to their new country. In the Spring of 1861 he was in St. Louis and one of those to go to Camp Jackson, to arrest the rebellious troops and secure the State of Missouri for the Union. Millions of German-Americans are prepared to stand up and defend their new country; but where there are duties, there should be rights. The former Congress-man Nooman as third speaker criticized the faults of the present administration and that only by general cooperation the masses could conserve their rights. Much organized work will have to be done to protect the masses from slavery and suppression.</p>
   <p>The following officers were elected for the organization, John Kolling, President; John H. Cervenka, Frank T. Karch, Stephan Popovich, Vincent Lavieri, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0513.jpg" n="3"/>A. P. Olson, Wm. Haremski and Leop. Neumann, Asst. Chairmen; and George A. V. Massow, Secretary. Mr. Gloganer proposed a Committee of seven to choose a name for the new Union and the working out of a program. Mr. John H. Cervenka read the organization plan worked out by his Committee which was voted on in sections and accepted with some changes. It determines, that the Central management of the Union will be directed by an executive Committee. At the annual convention the 200 associations will be presented each with one vote for each 200 members or a fraction thereof; and to an additional vote for each further 200 members. The executive Committee shall meet at least once a month. The Chairman can all special meetings also at the request of nine members within 4 days on demand. Seventeen members form a quorum. Mr. Gloganer stated, that the name adopted by the Committee for the Union should be: "United Societies for Local Self-Government." The name and the following program have been adopted: "The Chicago United Societies for Local Self-Government" at their convention meeting on May 27, 1906 submit to the public the following declaration of principles: "In a Democratic Republic the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0514.jpg" n="4"/>laws should correspond with the views and the wishes of the people and with the actual social conditions."</p>
   <p>Obsolete laws, not observed by peace-loving citizens are in contrast with popular government and should either be improved or abandoned. The life in towns is different from that on farms; therefore laws which regulate social customs differ materially in these communities. Towns and villages should have the lawful right to rule their affairs in accordance with the ideas and demands of their population. The respect for law is endangered if certain laws secretly of openly are disregarded of the execution of them is left to the discretion of an official. All citizens who agree with us are requested to join us for a lawful agitation to demand a law from the legislature at Illinois, to give the towns and villages local self-administration and the power to regulate their weekly rest day and the entertainment and celebrations of their population. On the request of Mr. Paul F. Muller of the Abendpost a Committee of eleven was choosen to recommend the names for the Executive <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0515.jpg" n="5"/>Committee. The first meeting will be held June 5 at 8 o'clock in the Sherman House. Associations, which wish to become members should apply to Secretary Massow, 94 Fifth; no fees will be charged.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
