<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
      <date when="1935-06-21">June 21, 1935</date>.
      <title level="a">An Expensive Luxury</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1182</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    
                    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
     <date when="1935-06-21">June 21, 1935</date>.</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1182.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>late Theodore Roosevelt.</p>
   <p>Carnegie, who foresaw the colossal development of the steel industry and succeeded in making money from this knowledge, was one of the greatest philanthropists that ever lived. In his opinion, it is a shame for a man to die rich. It seems that President Roosevelt intends to protect Americans from this shame by his plans for taxation. Teddy Roosevelt is today regarded as one of the patron saints and holy pillars of his party. At one time he was considered a dangerous man by the conservative Republicans. Mark Hanna once dubbed him a madhouse inmate.</p>
   <p>The President assumes the point of view that large accumulations of wealth cannot be traced back exclusively to individual initiative and skill, but that large numbers of the people co-operated to form such fortunes. The correctness of this view, for which Roosevelt cites Carnegie as witness, is self-evident. To give a concrete example: Through the Chicago World's Fair, the fact came to mind that the city was founded in 1833. At that time, lots <pb n="3"/><gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/><pb facs="5418474_2_1_1183.jpg" n="4"/>high as on an income of four thousand dollars. The rise in rate, however, ceases for incomes of over one million. How the increase of the rate for incomes of more than one million is going to affect the total tax revenue is not seen, because the number of incomes of this size is so small that, taxing them heavily would increase the governments income only insignificantly. The recommendation seems, therefore, made more for campaign, purposes than for actually adding to tax revenues. Roosevelt declares that our national life is imperiled by social unrest and an ever-deepening feeling of injustice. It is, therefore, the duty of the government to reduce fabulous incomes through high taxation.</p>
   <p>Even if one admits that the motive mentioned is good and justified, there still are doubts as to the method. Through the investigations of a senate committee, it came to light that great financiers like Morgan and Kahn paid no taxes for many years. This, a radical change of method in collecting taxes appears to be more important than an increase of rates. Many objections to Roosevelt's plan could be made on principle, but the space available in these columns is hardly enough.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1184.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It could be pointed out that, in keeping with a generally recognized theory, in the long run all taxes are paid by the consumer, and that people with large incomes who pay high taxes actually function as tax collectors for the government, getting these taxes from the great masses. It is also an undeniable fact that the exorbitant taxation of high incomes often has a damaging effect on economic life, so that not the rich man, but the poor, will have to suffer from it. And then, again, Roosevelt indulges fundamentally in a dangerous error in believing that he could apply taxation as a means for a better distribution of wealth. Taxes are levied solely to cover the expenses of government and administration. When used for other purposes, they are fundamentally and practically wrong. The ends striven for will never be attained, but bureaucracy, already appallingly large, is going to be still further increased.</p>
   <p>It should be the duty of Congress to debate thoroughly the president's proposals, for they seem to be not ripened enough. In many places, his message gives the impression of demagoguery. It lacks the solid realism that has been so characteristic of the President's previous messages.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
