<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-01-20">Jan. 20, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Germans and Poles.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 4 (Jewish)</item>
     <item>I C (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-01-20">Jan. 20, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANS AND POLES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual convention of the B'Nai B'Rith Order - a sort of Jewish Free-Mason organization - was enlivened by heated controversies, which followed the proposal to admit Polish Jews to the membership of the order. There is no doubt but that this subject will be discussed in many more Jewish circles. The decision was decidedly against the admittance of Polish Jews. The beaten minority in this case called it a reflection of the Berlin Jew baiting, and declared that it was a persecution of Jews by their own race.</p>
   <p>This is, however, an entirely false conception. The persecution of Jews in Berlin is of course a battle waged against the race, whereas the exclusion of Polish, Russian and Lithuanian Jews from membership of the B'Nai B'Rith organization is based upon different national viewpoints and also habits.</p>
   <p>This fight has brought to light one thing, namely, that the German Jews consider themselves decidedly more German than Jewish, and the Polish the same respectively. This demonstrates clearly that neither race nor religion constitutes a strong bond between them. The pet accusation of the German anti-Semites is on the whole that in thoughts and deeds they are absorbed by the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1081.jpg" n="2"/>race, while as members of a nation they remain amazingly disinterested. The heated debates during the B'Nai B'Rith convention disprove this accusation in the best way possible.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding the fact that this organization serves exclusively those identified with the Jewish race, the German national spirit, (The German-American self) was predominant at the meeting. There is no doubt that their national spirit overshadows their race and religious devotion....</p>
   <p>But the history of the Jews - all during the Middle Ages up to the present time - shows that in countries considered by Jews as their native place they build an atmosphere of exclusion and thus occasion a spirit of discrimination. However, it would be absolutely wrong to misinterpret this characteristic and to accuse the race of disregard or renunciation of that nationality, of which they are citizens.</p>
   <p>Except for the historical and religious traditions, there is no bond either between the German-Italian or the German-Polish Jews. According to statistics, France is the home of 60,000 Jews, two-thirds of whom have immigrated from Germany. And because of their contact with relatives in Germany, Stoecker and Henrici became possessed of the idea that this race is incapable of patriotism.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1082.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Then again, history shows that the Jews of Portugal and of Holland and also, to a certain extent, the English have hardly anything in common with the German Jews, whom they regard with very little esteem. The situation is almost similar to that existing between the German and the Polish Jews. The American Jewry is 75% German Jewish, who are known as German-Americans and no discrimination is made between them.</p>
   <p>... As money-makers, or in the words of Stoecker &amp; Co., who speak of them as hagglers and usurers, they do not play a more prominent part than their Yankee fellow-citizens, because one Yankee is equal to two Jews in this respect. There are few amongst our Nabobs or multi-millionaires; not a single railway promoter or industrialist is a member of that race.</p>
   <p>Thus, the arguments used most effectively to produce hatred of Jews in Germany, are of no consequence here. Their success is due to their abstinence, moderation, and thrift according to the opinion of Fr. Hecker. This disqualifies every suggestion of intellectual superiority. The only difference noticed in favor of their ability is the rapidity with which they learn the English language, and also the ease with which they adapt themselves to the American way of living, accepting the good as well as the bad.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1083.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This class can not be identified, however, with the educated Jews reared in Germany, but composes a class of its own in climbing the ladder of success. It may also be suggested that many a Germanic upstart belongs to this category. But there is not one single rule which could be applied to all. Nativity and education are great factors in many instances, and the German Jews comprise the majority in all cases.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the decision of the Grand Lodge of the B'Nai B'Rith is not at all strange. To us it seems as one of the many symptoms pointing toward a slow dissolution of the race and the assimilation of the Jews to those nations, whose subjects they happen to be. Of course, this process will require much time, in fact many generations will come and go, before the entire absorption will be completed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
