<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-08-10">Aug. 10, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Saloonkeepers, Beware of Your Enemies! (Vox Populi)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1488</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1488.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-08-10">Aug. 10, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">SALOONKEEPERS, BEWARE OF YOUR ENEMIES! (Vox Populi)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The advocates of temperance, who by no means disguise their fanaticism, are not your worst adversaries. You are confronted with another class which stealthily saps your vitality, and these enemies are the brewers, all highly prominent gentlemen.</p>
   <p>For years this class has bamboozled its victims, the tavernkeepers, by making idle promises or by a few "treats all around". During all the years in which brewers have done business with tavernkeepers, the latter have been cheated daily and have paid for something which they never have received; yet, regardless of this constant cheating, the saloonkeepers have been patient and indifferent.</p>
   <p>Saloonkeepers! How long shall you continue to endure this? <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1489.jpg" n="2"/>Wake up; fight for your interests! Follow the worthy example given by our Government, which knows how to protect itself and does not care a d--what happens to you.</p>
   <p>The Government sends its snoopers to the breweries to inspect barrels, and if any are found which contain more than the legal measure (31 wine-gallons), then the barrels are simply confiscated; but if they are smaller, then the inspectors do not care, for they obviously believe in the old proverb, "What does not concern me does not bother me".</p>
   <p>Tavernkeepers, do the same! As the Government acts whenever the measure is too large, so must you fight and see to it that the measure shall not be short.</p>
   <p>Measure your beer kegs, and if they do not contain 7 3/4 gallons, then prosecute the crooks with all the means at your command.</p>
   <p>Just as the administration compels you to give a definite measure (gallon, quart, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1490.jpg" n="3"/>and pint), so you have a right to compel the administration to see to it that you are protected against short measure.</p>
   <p>Tavernkeepers! Be united and fight your exploiters like men. Become affilicated with the Wirthsverein, defend your rights, act collectively, and work for the betterment of your calling.</p>
   <p>I hope that these few words will suffice to open the eyes of our saloonkeepers, imbue them with energy, and arouse them to action so that a few noteworthy examples may be shown to our oppressors.</p>
   <p>Peter Mueller</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
