<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-12-05">Dec. 5, 1910</date><title level="a">Bad Fruits Expressing an Attitude Toward Religion</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0866</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0866.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-12-05">Dec. 5, 1910</date><title level="a">BAD FRUITS EXPRESSING AN ATTITUDE TOWARD RELIGION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A peculiar complaint comes from Maywood, one of our suburbs. Five of their local churches closed a revival meeting, which had lasted for several weeks. The expenses of this campaign amounted to $500--, and the results--only ten conversions. It will be difficult for the layman to decide whether or not the amount spent is comparatively high. It depends entirely upon one's viewpoint and attitude toward such conversions.</p>
   <p>If a conversion means the rescue of a soul from infidelity, desperation, vice, and sin, then these ten conversions are indeed a great acheievement; it would be such a great gain that no sacrifice should be considered too high. There should be great joy among the churches in Maywood, and the leaders of this campaign should receive their sincere gratitude. Of course, this is not the case. There is no joy with words of gratitude, but rather complaints and calculations regarding the expenses coming from that suburb. This demonstrates, very clearly, that they understand conversion to be something entirely different.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0867.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The revival-campaign is considered a failure. The number of converts is not satisfactory, and there are complaints about the expenses for only ten conversions. Since the total expenditure of $500 resulted in ten conversions, only, each one of them therefore costing $50--, it is clear that the price and is too high for them.</p>
   <p>One of the leading pastors of the five cooperating churches stated, in excuse, that the revival meetings increased the interests of members for the churches, therefore, the cost could not be considered as too high.</p>
   <p>This leads to the conclusion that the revival-campaign was not for the purpose of reviving souls, but to gain members for their churches, and this explains their dissatisfaction. Each of the ten converts would have to put one dollar, each Sunday, on the collection plate, to repay their respective churches the amount expended for the, but experience has taught that it is insecure to demand upon the generosity, or the continuity, of those converted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
