<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-10-10">Oct. 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Where Are We Headed? Observations on the Development of Labor Organizations and Contributions to Their History by T. Trust</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1553</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1553.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-10-10">Oct. 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">WHERE ARE WE HEADED? Observations on the Development of Labor Organizations and Contributions to Their History by T. Trust</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[This is the third in a series of articles on this subject.]</p>
   <p>Economic Shifts</p>
   <p>It may be of interest to know that the union leaders of the old system which now exists only in the United States, were well aware of the danger of losing a sometimes unscrupulously applied power. Their antagonism toward any changes can be well understood, if one realizes the material loss which they, personally, would have to face. But their opposition only too often influences them to commit crimes which, due to prevalent political maneuvers, will rarely find judicial punishment.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1554.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We must not be surprised, therefore, that they managed to discard the new system in giant concerns like the International Harvester Company, Westinghouse, and the like, before the workers had a chance to set it up, and before the immediate advantages of this system of direct representation by the workers through factory and shop committees, as opposed to dictatorial and often corrupt representation by "business agents" and other parasites, could make themselves evident.</p>
   <p>In his testimony before the Senate Investigating Committee, Davies of New-castle, Pennsylvania, said that since 1909, the time of the last great steel and railroad strike, the United States Steel Corporation had recognized the system of direct representation of workers through self-elected committees for the adjustment of controversies. He declared that the main reason for the present steel strike was the replacement of this system by the notorious "check-off" system which all intelligent and thinking workers abhor.</p>
   <p>In 1909, Davies was among those who led the strike in New Castle, Pennsylvania, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1555.jpg" n="3"/>and who witnessed the negotiations which finally led to the settlement of the conflict. But as for his assertion that since the above-mentioned strike conditions in the steel foundries have improved considerably, let me say that actually this was true only in those shops in which the workers were able to maintain the factory representative system despite the intrigues of the union officials on one side, and those of petty factory bosses on the other. But why should the public be interested in such things. The American people can argue that no matter which of the two systems is adopted by the industries of this country, the influence on the country's economic conditions will be trivial.</p>
   <p>This argument may be justified where branches of industry and commerce are engaged in local trade only. But in cases where world-wide trade is affected by working conditions, the masses should not assume an attitude of indifference toward such problems. The whole economic life of a nation may depend on the way this problem is solved. Now, especially, the right solution is inseparably interwoven with the return to normal business conditions. In all countries <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1556.jpg" n="4"/>of the world, victors and vanquished alike, this problem undoubtedly forms the focal point of all considerations and measures. The promises which have been made to the workers during the war years, the wonderful future which was painted for them, all this has to be made good now. Will the masses, having outgrown their accustomed leadership, determine by the number of concessions made them the course of action to be taken in order to secure the fulfillment of those promises?</p>
   <p>Conflicts of interests, which in many cases seem to assume a revolutionary character, may not have originally had the overthrow of present-day society as their objective; nevertheless these clashes can unleash passions which may seek an outlet for their accumulated energies.</p>
   <p>with the aid of a vivid imagination, such correspondents as Ackerman of the Hearst press concoct whole conspiracies after the Russian pattern from <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1557.jpg" n="5"/>trifling incidents. Few persons discern behind this smoke screen the shifts which are taking place as the forces of reaction attempt to erect an apparently indestructible dam against the onrush of the currents of progress.</p>
   <p>In order to find the core of the conflict in the economic life of the nation it is necessary to study the trends more exhaustively. The attempt of many businessmen to make a clean sweep of the corrupt methods of the past, for reasons which we will occasionally discuss, should teach the public not to see an act of sedition in every strike of the workers.</p>
   <p>The economic shifts deserve our full attention. The causes are the same as those which started the World War. To give more weight to our arguments we cannot quote a better authority than the President of the United States, Woodrow Wilson. At a mass meeting in St. Louis, on September 5 of this year, the President made the following statement:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1558.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"Now, my fellow citizens, is there still a man or a woman--yes, let me add, is there still a child--who does not know yet that the germ of war in the present-day world is of commercial and economic origin? This war was a commercial and industrial war, not a political one."</p>
   <p>If these words were true, and all other declarations nothing but empty phrases designed to win the confidence of the masses and of humanity everywhere, then it is also logical to assume that the impending danger of the commercial and economic hegemony of the central European countries--especially Germany-- had to be averted, and that for this reason Germany's entire commercial and industrial capacity--which might have brought about her quick economic recovery after the war--had to be crippled in such a manner as to eliminate her as a competitor for decades to come.</p>
   <p>At the same time, care had to be taken to organize the industrial capacity <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1559.jpg" n="7"/>of the victorious nations, and to make this <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> so efficient that the headway gained by crushing Germany would not be offset by the internal strife of the victorious nations.</p>
   <p>We can truthfully say that <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> here in America can see the handwriting on the wall. This is indicated by the significant statement made by Charles Schwab, the president of Bethlehem Steel, upon his return from Europe last winter. His statement caused much comment. He said that the workers had to be conceded the right of co-operation in the new economic order; otherwise they would take it by force. He certainly would not have introduced the system of representation by the workers in his own plants if he had not taken his prophecy seriously. Therefore it is time to find out why the more intelligent and progressive employers have come to these conclusions.</p>
   <p>Above all else it was the knowledge that the mighty attempt to drive Germany into an economic chaos had failed, and that it had become necessary to find <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1560.jpg" n="8"/>in this country the more conservative influence which had preserved order and <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> collapse in that country.</p>
   <p>An impartial investigation shows (and many reports about Germany written by Farbman for the Chicago Daily News evince a profound economic comprehension) that the conservative forces were created by a system which aroused a new sense of responsibility among the workers by their participation in the management through collective bargaining in every plant and shop. The purpose of this method, to step up production in order to pay off the war debts, will certainly be accomplished. To quote Farbman: "A peaceful revolution is taking place there, the reactions of which will soon be noticeable in the economic life of the whole world."</p>
   <p>In the next article we will explain how the plan to eliminate Germany forever from the commercial and economic life of the world was bound to fail, thanks to the tremendous organizing powers and creative forces which are inherent <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1561.jpg" n="9"/>in that nation, and how the reaction to this failure will bring about decisive changes in the mutual relations between capital and labor in our own economic life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
