<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-27">Feb. 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">For Personal Liberty and the Right of Self-Determination</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0353</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0353.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-27">Feb. 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FOR PERSONAL LIBERTY AND THE RIGHT OF SELF-DETERMINATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The king is dead. Long live the king!" The primary campaign was concluded by the primary election; the campaign for regular election is beginning.</p>
   <p>It is already under way. Robert Sweitzer, the Democratic candidate for mayor, opened the campaign yesterday when he took a decided stand against prohibition--national as well as local--and advocated personal liberty.</p>
   <p>He did so in his answer to a letter written to him on February 21 by Mr. C.J. Davis, the Superintendent of the Chicago branch of the Anti-Saloon League. Mr. Davis wanted to know what policy Mr. Sweitzer would follow in regard to the enforcement of the ""Anti-Saloon" and other prohibition laws, in case Mr. Sweitzer should be elected.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0354.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Sweitzer wrote: "I am against prohibition, national and local. Had the question of national prohibition been put to a referendum vote, I would have voted against prohibition. I am for the fullest measure of personal freedom. But according to State law the people alone may decide whether the country, or a part of it, is to be "dry" or "wet". No action by a candidate before election, or of a mayor after election, can change the people's answer to the question: Shall Chicago be dry or wet? If the people expresses its will through an election, whether it be on April 1 or at any other time, then I will abide by the will of the people."</p>
   <p>That answer is clear and direct, honest and manly. It leaves no back door open and admits of no equivocation. It is genuinely democratic. The right to decide a question pertaining to the liberty of the people it reserves to the people themselves, to the persons whose freedom and privileges are at issue. That is the only procedure that is right and just.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0355.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>By taking this open and unequivocal stand against prohibition, and by courageously and strongly advocating the people's right to self-determination, he has proved that he is imbued with the truly democratic spirit. He set an example to be followed. He could not and cannot do more. The rest is within the province of Mrs. and Mr. Citizen.</p>
   <p>Never before have citizens had their duty more clearly portrayed. If the men and women of Chicago wish to prove that they are rightly called citizens of a free republic, they will go to the polls on April 1 and vote on the "wet or ary" issue. Anyone who fails to do so will forfeit his right to self-determination and declare that he is willing to permit others to make his decisions for him; that he does not want to govern, but wishes to be governed; that he does not want to do his duty as a citizen; that he mistrusts his ability to judge; that he deems himself incapable of helping to decide important issues. Anyone who voluntarily remains away from the polls on April 1, or anyone who fails to cast a vote on the "wet-dry" question, will prove that he is not worthy of his privileges and will admit that they are right who <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0356.jpg" n="4"/>believe themselves qualified to reform the "ignorant masses" and to force upon them a "salvation" which conforms to their (the reformers') conception.</p>
   <p>Robert M. Sweitzer's letter was a splendid introduction to his campaign. By his open and courageous stand he has set a fine example and thus has rendered a good service to our city, state, and nation.</p>
   <p>Now it is up to our citizens to follow the good example, and to avail themselves of the opportunity to express their will. Now is not the time to speculate, or argue about, of how much or how little use a more or less strong vote against prohibition will be. Now everybody should firmly resolve to vote on April 1, and to solicit votes everywhere--each one in his own neighborhood and among his friends--for the personal liberty of our citizens and their right to self-determination.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
