<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-01-17">January 17th, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Vereinigte Gesellschaften</title><title level="a" type="sub">(United Societies)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0493</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0493.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-01-17">January 17th, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">VEREINIGTE GESELLSCHAFTEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(United Societies)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Executive Committee of the United Societies, representing German and German-American residents of Chicago, had a special meeting last night at the Lodge Hall, 106 Randolph Street, presides over by Mr. Hermann Koelling. A resolution was adopted to call a mass-meeting of the United Societies for the coming Sunday at 3 P. M. as a protest against the use of public funds in the persecution of tavernkeepers and against the financial support of prohibition.</p>
   <p>Other massmeetings will follow during February and March, according to the announcement of Mr. Koelling.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0494.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>step to take away all our liberty. Only a strict organization can save us. We must make use of the power we possess. The next speaker was Leo. Neumann, the organizer of the society, who demonstrated that only the German press has taken up their cause, whilst a million of temperance journals are sent over the whole country each week from Chicago. Everybody individually must work for the good cause. In New York all theaters have been closed; in Chicago they started with the saloons. Every club must join the Union.</p>
   <p>Dr. John Kercher recommended to send a questionnaire to all clergymen to ascertain who are for or against them. The recommendation was accepted. The following resolution was taken: "On account of the agitation for prohibition all over the country and the provocation of the Sunday closing of the saloons, we liberal minded citizens of Chicago declare that the Sunday closing is not desired by the majority of the citizens of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Resolved, further, that we condemn the attacks of the illiberal and the</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
