<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-16">Apr. 16, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Idealism and Reality</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0216</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0216.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-16">Apr. 16, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">IDEALISM AND REALITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The law represents the voice of the people. A divine sanction hovers over it and keeps it upright. The enforcing of the law and the obedience to it may, in accordance with the nature of our institutions in this Republic, not be subject to the will of the citizens. They [laws] are rather the expression of a moral request demanding of the citizens to live in accordance with the truth. They have a spiritual significance by which the continuation or the downfall of the American ideals of self-regulation are revealed."</p>
   <p>Thus wrote President Coolidge to the conference of the Women's National Committee for Law Enforcement convening at present in the Federal capital. To judge from this, the President has a high opinion of the law and its meaning. His conception is an ideal one, in fact it is so ideal that it no longer has anything in common with reality. It may fit in with Utopian <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0217.jpg" n="2"/>conditions, but here upon earth it has no room.</p>
   <p>President Coolidge is mistaken when he contends that the law constitutes the voice of the people and that it is endowed with a divine sanction. It would be much better if, in this instance, he would leave out the Lord. For He has not as yet revealed His intentions to the Congress or to the state legislatures. And those presenting themselves as His representatives on earth are evidently not quite in accord with His intentions. This is why they founded hundreds of Sunday religious faiths, all pretending to propagate God's word. They all conceive of it in a different way, and give it as many interpretations.</p>
   <p>But the people have decidedly little to do with the creating of laws. Most laws, of course, have a purely practical significance. They are enacted to make it possible for the states, the nation or the communities to function in accordance with certain rules, and to provide them with the necessary <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0218.jpg" n="3"/>means. Other laws stand for attempts to solve a certain problem in government and administration which had arisen in the course of development. The passing of such laws constitutes, in a way, the routine work of legislative bodies.</p>
   <p>President Coolidge's disquisitions, however, seem to have reference to a different sort of law. It is, in the first place, the prohibition law which now stands in the foreground of public interest. Its defense is the aim of that woman's organization to which the President directed his message. In a further sense, the words apply to all reform laws of a like character. But even in this sort of legislation, the divine sanction is to a certain extent doubtful, and it cannot be labeled as the expression of the people's will.</p>
   <p>Everyone knows how many laws are being passed. Although we do not have an exaggerated opinion of the lawgivers' intelligence, one may concede that <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0219.jpg" n="4"/>most of them want to have nothing to do with these laws. But they are helpless. They are daily besieged by droves of hysterical women and a pack of well-paid, cunning political charlatans. By this humanitarian combination they are tortured until they finally give in. In this manner, the Eighteenth Amendment came about and was ratified by the states. To the same system the Volstead law owes its existence, as do a number of similar laws that have been passed by state legislatures.</p>
   <p>In all instances there was a small, fanatic minority, supported by skilled and ruthless political strategy, which was responsible for the enactment of the laws. The large, peaceful, industrious masses of the people are resigned to these things, knowing that these laws cannot be enforced anyway. This is how our reform laws have started. All that is, of course, known to the president and it appears rather obscure why he sent that message to the women's dry convention--a message that stood in such sharp contrast with the facts.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0220.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We may perhaps explain this phenomenon by the fact that the President, like so many others, does not react so well to mountain air. If he adheres strictly to the facts, he proves that he knows how to grasp pheomena and events and to interpret their meaning. But in the last few years he has been possessed of a futal affliction, stalking, as he does, upon a high pedestal; from there in sublime language, he proclaims to his faithful people words of wisdom pregnant with thought. In so doing he loses himself in a labyrinth of well-sounding phrases and fantastic ideas. And all this rhetoric does not fit him, typical yankee that he is.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
