<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1875-03-07">Mar. 7, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">Look Here.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1097</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1097.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1875-03-07">Mar. 7, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">LOOK HERE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago is a growth of almost an hour. From nothing of yesterday it has become today a city of nearly half a million inhabitants. Its growth has been one not alone of population, but it has included those substantial concomitants of numbers, great wealth, and a marvelous commerical supremacy. This wondrous growth has given the city a world-wide reputation, and has made it the entrepot of all elements relating to men, business, class representatives, and everything else conceivable from nearly every portion of the habitable globe.</p>
   <p>One of the consequences of this universality of supply is a population in nowise homogeneous as to nationality, religion, class, views of government, the duty of the citizen: and in fine, homogeneous in no particular of any value. Hence, no years have witnessed a substantial unity of opinion, more especially in directions involving the administration of municipal affairs. There have been frequent attempts to unite the people in the interests of reform, but seemingly without avail.</p>
   <p>The evil of this condition has been augmented if possible by a union of the foreign elements of the city's population to secure control. Without this <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1098.jpg" n="2"/>union it might be possible for the better portion of our citizens to interest themselves in local measures, to have held the balance of power. They could have united with the more worthy representatives of the Irish residents against the Germans, or with the same class of the Germans against the Irish, or with the higher elements of both these nationalities against all other classes, and thereby secured, at least, a partial success. Unfortunately the alliance of Irish and Germans effectually prevents any such results. It even goes further than this for it prevents the better classes of Germans and Irish from obtaining any considerable control. The necessities of the alliance bear down all results which might arise from the selection of the best men in a bad lot; and gives the rank and file of both wings of this foreign army the same priveleges that are possessed by the officials.</p>
   <p>Had these foreigners been pleased to give Chicago their best men, there would have been something in the dispensation to be thankful for; but, it has happened, there has been little or no choice. The men whom the foreign legion have selected to dominate in Chicago, have been always those who could command the most votes, who would make the most liberal promises in regard to the disposition of spoils. No regard whatever has been paid to fitness to hold the office; and in the very few instances where it has occurred that the men who <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1099.jpg" n="3"/>possessed at once qualifications for commanding votes, and fitness for office, such a combination has been wholly an accident.</p>
   <p>It needs no man of uncommon sagacity to comprehend that an alliance between Irish and Germans; between the predominant Roman Catholic element, and a predominant atheistic element; between the supporters of Piux IX and the supporters of Bismarck; between nationalities, who prior to this union were deadly enemies, and who now, during its existence invariably refer to each other, when not in each other's presence, in terms that are full of contempt, opprobrium - such an alliance can have no higher purpose than plunder. Such is the purpose whether one demonstrates it a priori, or from the sad and costly evidence of an experience founded upon the occurrences of the last eighteen months.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
