<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-07-13">July 13, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">The Battle in "New York"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-07-13">July 13, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">THE BATTLE IN "NEW YORK"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only a few week's back we remarked that the City of New York had in its Irish population an element of anarchy and bloody reign of terror as frightful as the Communists of Paris, and that it only needed an occasion to produce a volcanic eruption of this element... New York was on July 12th the theater of a street battle that only for one reason did not go quite to the length of the appalling July fight in 1863; namely, that the authorities were prepared, and held plenty of police and militia in readiness...Rumor spoke already in the afternoon of 170 killed and wounded...This street battle will have one regrettable and one gratifying result. The one to be regretted will be the revival of Protestant, nativist hatred against the Catholics. Not the Catholicism of the Hibernians, but their bestiality has driven them to this bloody riot. In the whole country there is not one German, or American, yes not even a single, some what educated Irish Catholic who would feel any sympathy for the two legged beasts who made the streets of New York their battle field. Especially in regard to the German Catholics, the Union yesterday in an excellent article(we surmise, from the pen of a Catholic priest) has expressed its attitude in the most unequivocal terms. However, all that will not prevent <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1143.jpg" n="2"/>the inherited hatred of the Anglo-Americans against the "Papists" to draw new substance from the events of yesterday. This is regrettable.</p>
   <p>The gratifying result is the exposure of the appalling brutality and bestial spite with which the classes that rule New York are filled. For these accursed brutes of whom, for the best of the country, as many thousands should have been mowed down as only dozens were killed, form the Guard, the elite of the Democratic Party in New York...</p>
   <p>Just at the moment when the Democratic Party had hidden her true face behind the most friendly mask and tried to insinuate itself into the favor of the people under the name of a Reform Party-just at this moment the Hibernians tear down its mask, and terrified the people with the repulsive head of Medusa that was hidden behind it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
