<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1903-10-04">October 4, 1903</date><title level="a">The First Convention State Union of Illinois of German American National Lkagut Held Yesterday Today's Great Celebration of German Day in the Auditorium.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0982</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0982.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1903-10-04">October 4, 1903</date><title level="a">THE FIRST CONVENTION STATE UNION OF ILLINOIS OF GERMAN AMERICAN NATIONAL LKAGUT HELD YESTERDAY TODAY'S GREAT CELEBRATION OF GERMAN DAY IN THE AUDITORIUM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first convention of the Illinois State League of the German-American National Union was opened yesterday afternoon by its president, Judge Eberhart. He expressed his satisfaction in the opening speech, that the meeting was so largely attended from all parts of the State. The main object is to be prepared to fight for the propagation of the principles, which the Union has written on its flag; dissemination of German manners and the maintenance of German individuality and German culture. Inseparably connected with the history of the country, is the cooperation of the German element in the building up of the Republic. A special task for the Germans is the cultivation of their language, in which everything finds expression, what is true and good in the history of a great nation. We hope, that, with earnestness and prudence the convention will finish the work before it. The organization of the Union has drawn the attention of the whole country, upon itself; through its work may it prove worthy of the elements whose representation it has accepted, and may it <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0983.jpg" n="2"/>gain the respect of the whole populace. The speaker closed by presenting the temporary president of the State Union, Mr. Charles H. Kamman, who opened the convention.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kamman expressed his thanks in the name of the out-of-town delegates to the Chicago branch, for the hearty reception given them, and gave a short sketch of the temporary organization set-up on May 23rd at Peoria, which should be strengthened and built up, so that it night be able to fulfill its task properly. The speaker regretted that because of the bad disposition of the Americans towards the extremes the temperance question has again been put in the foreground. The Union must not neglect a worthy manner, the sensible German standpoint on this question, but at the same time it has some other important problems, especially to cultivate good relations between the old and the new fatherland......</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
