<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1875-11-01">Nov. 1, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">The Meeting in Farwell Hall</title><title level="a" type="sub">To my German fellow-citizens:</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1095</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1095.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1875-11-01">Nov. 1, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">THE MEETING IN FARWELL HALL</title><title level="a" type="sub">To my German fellow-citizens:</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Allow me to give you an objective account of what happened in Farwell Hall. You all Know the bitter animosity of the nativists against A. C. Hesing, and that the two most important English newspapers, the Tribune and the Times refused to allow him space in their columns so as to dispel these prejudices. An announcement was published by the newspapers at the beginning of this week inviting the merchants and businessmen of Chicago to a meeting in Farwell Hall the purpose or the meeting was to devise means to safeguard the voting of the citizens at the coming election and to protest against the procedure of the County Commissioners in appointing poll judges. The meeting was not to be a partisan one and was open to all the businessmen of the city. For that reason I urged Mr. Hesing to attend, especially with the view in mind, that if he should be attacked, he would have an opportunity to defend himself before an entire American audience. I was convinced that no assembly of native Americans would refuse to give a man the opportunity to refute accusations leveled against him.</p>
   <p>As Mr. Hesing had received written invitations to attend even from American businessmen, after long deliberation he finally decided to go.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1096.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The two first speakers, Larner and Hoyne, spoke in a dignified and objective manner. There were many calls for Hesing to speak, but he ignored them.</p>
   <p>When Mr. Eldridge got up and read a number of resolutions, which had not been discussed nor decided upon by the assembly, accusing Mr. Hesing of being a partner of gamblers and confidence men, the supporters of Mr. Hesing felt a profound indignation. Mr. Hesing got up and walked calmly toward the platform in order to defend himself.</p>
   <p>Our expectation that Mr. Hesing would be granted the right to defend himself, by the assembly of respectable citizens, was not realized.</p>
   <p>At once cries arose: "Beat him up - Damn the Dutchman - we need no foreigners." Mr. Hesing, pushed into a corner, was unable to reach the platform. I have reached the conviction that the worst enemy of the Chicago Germans is to be found in the Christian American rabble of Farwell Hall and that the only way to defend ourselves is by our votes at the next election.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
