<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-06-27">June 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Eventually--Why Not Now?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0267</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0267.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-06-27">June 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">EVENTUALLY--WHY NOT NOW?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The legislature of the Christian, free, and progressive State of Illinois has enacted the Search and Seizure Law prepared by the Anti-Saloon League, an irresponsible, prejudiced society of reformers, and Governor Lowden, whom we regarded as liberal and independent, has affixed his signature to the document.</p>
   <p>Thus ways and means have been devised to force the (once) free citizens of the (once) free, Christian, and progressive State of Illinois under the yoke of bone-dry prohibition--to make them teetotalers.</p>
   <p>Christian doctrine knows nothing of prohibition. It not only permits the consumption of wine, but also speaks very highly of this beverage, calling <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0268.jpg" n="2"/>it a precious gift of God. In her most sacred rites the Christian Church uses wine. And the Christian nations waxed strong and prosperous, and became lords of the earth, while drinking wine, mead, and beer.</p>
   <p>The Turks are bone-dry prohibitionists--teetotalers. Prohibition is an essential part of their religion. Turkey has, or formerly had, search and seizure laws. The new Illinois law is patterned after the Mohammedan ordinance--a faithful and conscientious duplication. It imposes on the Christian, free and progressive State of Illinois all the ways and means which were devised and applied by the founders of the Mohammedan religion. However, our legislators overlooked one phase of the Turkish law. The Turks have (or did have until recently) an official "smeller," whose duty it was to sample the breath of the Moslems, to ascertain whether or not the person being tested had transgressed the law.</p>
   <p>The Illinois law makes no provision for the creation of such an office.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0269.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And that is a very queer oversight. It must be attended to, for otherwise many transgressors of the holy Turkish prohibition in Illinois will go scot free!</p>
   <p>It is to be expected that the prohibitionists will call a special session of the legislature and instruct the representatives of the people to perfect the Search and Seizure Law and make it worthy of its Turkish model by passing an amendment to establish a Bureau of "Public Smellers," with a "Chief Smeller" and a number of "Sub-Smellers" in proportion to the population of each county.</p>
   <p>One hardly need fear that the majority of legislators would hesitate to comply with this demand, or that Governor Lowden would withhold his signature. Anyone who says "A" must say "B". They who voted for the Search and Seizure Law....cannot and will not object to perfecting it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
