<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-01-24">January 24, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal of the United Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0491</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0491.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-01-24">January 24, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL OF THE UNITED SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Executive Committee of the United Societies is sending out an urgent appeal to all clear-thinking Chicago citizens to be present at the mass-meeting in the Armory of the 1st Regiment, the coming Sunday, 2 P. M. The contents of this appeal is as follows:</p>
   <p>"A dry wave is sweeping the country and has become a danger to the individual freedom of all citizens. Using religion and the Bible as a weapon, the temperance Fanatics are preaching that drinking of beer, wine and liquor on Sunday is a sin. A temperance organization "The Chicago Law and Order League" is trying its utmost to influence the Chicago courts to side with the Temperance standpoint. So far the juries at all trials of tavern-keepers have decided in favor of the saloons keeping open on Sundays."</p>
   <p>The majority of the American people is not inclined to sacrifice all pleasures on Sunday to these dogmatic fanatics, who want to chain humanity again to the rules and laws of the middle ages. As usual, these reactionary and vicious attacks on the people's freedom are finding a willing support from the wealthier <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0492.jpg" n="2"/>classes, who can afford to do without taverns and are looking at this temperance movement as a welcome opportunity to block human progress.</p>
   <p>It is up to the American people to wake up and stand together in this fight against intolerance, hypocrisy and oppression of personal freedom. Every Chicago citizen should recognize the seriousness of the situation and come to the mass-meeting in the 1st Regiment's Armory the coming Sunday 2 P. M.</p>
   <p>For the Executive Committee</p>
   <p>John Koelling, President</p>
   <p>A. J. Cermak, Secretary</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
