<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-03-09">March 9, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">[The Boers]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1003</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1003.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-03-09">March 9, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">[THE BOERS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A pro-Boer sympathy meeting, arranged by Americans of German extraction at the Auditorium Theater, March 8th, drew an audience of several thousand persons. The resolution prepared by Mr. Wilhelm Vocke was enthusiastically received and unanimously passed by that great assembly. Following is the text of the resolution:</p>
   <p>"Thus we wish to make known publicly, our deep and sincere admiration for this brave pastoral tribe the Boers, upon whom the English government has forced a bloody war. This small nation is courageously defending its sacred rights for freedom and independence of their homeland, the land which was a vast wilderness before they engaged in the transformation of same. It is evident that England is bound to carry out its policy, to enrich itself at the cost of this South African republic and of the Free State of Orange.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1004.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"We are deeply concerned about the civilized nations of Europe, and America that remain distant onlookers in this bloody war, while two helpless republics of South Africa, whose people are descendants of the noble nation of Hollanders, are being so cruelly treated by that powerful English nation, determined to take possession of the Boer's land and wealth, unearthed and brought to the notice of the world, through their hard labor.</p>
   <p>"In an urgent plea to our national government we ask, that it offer its services, as the friendly intermediary of the belligerent nations, and thus in accord with the treaty of the Haag peace conference, with the assurance of lasting independence of the South African republics, peace to nations would be restored once again."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1005.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It was an enthusiastic meeting which was attended by almost all the prominent Germans of Chicago............The address, delivered by the chairman, Mr. Jacob Ingenthron, was interrupted by stormy applause several times........Georg D. Heldmann, pastor of the German-Catholic St. Paul's congregation, said: "The European nations have a great reverence for gold, and thus they have not the slightest inclination to intervene in behalf of liberty, the price which England is asking. But, we American citizens of German extraction, can not tolerate such injustice. There is still time to avert catastrophe. As citizens of this country, heartened by the knowledge that the great heart of the American nation is in sympathy with the brave Boers, we turn to Washington with a plea that its friendly services be offered to the nations at war, thus hastening the end of this shameful warfare. The Boers must be free again........ This is our wish and our belief, and nothing whatsoever can change our attitude."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
