<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1873-02-06">Feb. 6, 1873</date>.
<title level="a">[The Sunday Closing Law]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0739</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0739.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1873-02-06">Feb. 6, 1873</date>.
<title level="a">[THE SUNDAY CLOSING LAW]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The devil's tail appeared clearly at the meeting in the Board of Trade Hall last Tuesday evening. Almost every speaker revealed a little of it, but what indicated most clearly the motive of their coming together, was the following recommendations:</p>
   <p>Resolved: "The citizens of Chicago expect and ask that the major and all those intrusted with the executing of the law, take care that the Sunday laws are strictly observed, and that after convictions for respected violation of the law, the license shall be taken away from the convicted tavern keeper and that it should never be returned to him."</p>
   <p>As far as we know, the entire trouble started because Mr. Washburn refused, as he was in duty bound, to put his innovations first before his superiors. That the partisans of Washburn made the above mentioned resolution, shows their secret motive. This meeting was called by the president of the temperance committee. The main speakers were the patron of the Y. M. C. A., John V. Farwell; the most fanatical temperance pastor of the city, Rev. Kittridge, and a few other notables of the same type.</p>
   <p>It is said of the Germans that they attack Washburn and Medill, because they have aligned themselves with the fanatics in regard to the Sunday laws.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0740.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We grant that this did not make Washburn nor Medill popular with the Germans, but we consider it as an infamous calumny if it is said that we oppose Medill in this matter on the account of his former offenses. It is better to say, that the persons who support Washburn do so because he proceeded against the Germans. How could it be explained otherwise that every speaker will knock the Germans before attacking other nationalities?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
