<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1874-01-07">Jan. 7, 1874</date>.
<title level="a">German Emigration.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1104</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1104.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Times</title>,
<date when="1874-01-07">Jan. 7, 1874</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN EMIGRATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It might be an inquiry of some value to learn why our main sources of population, are in two peoples so thoroughly opposed to each other in every particular. There is scarcely a thing in common between the Irishman and the German, except that they are impelled to seek the same destination. The Irishman comes hither cursing the government which he has left behind him; the German comes impressed with the idea that the government he leaves is the best and grandest in the world. The one never hears of a British success without a malediction; the other is tremulously alive to the honor and operations of the German government, so that the victories of William and the triumphs of Bismark are as heartily cheered and rejoiced over by the Germans of Chicago and New York as by thoseof Berlin. The Irishman is a devoted religionist and Catholic the German is just as much a free-thinker and anultra hater of pope, priest and sanctuary. Nor is the difference of temperament less marked in the two races. The one is quick, impetuous, impulsive; the other slow, calculating, and phlegmatic. The one enlists for the fun of a fight, from a desire for change and adventure; the German puts his name on the troop-roll as a matter of calculation, because there is loot, promotion, compensation in the prospect.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1105.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Some Irishmen become wealthy; far more Germans attain the same end, for the reason that the former is generous, improvident, open-handed, while the latter is close, penurious, saving. Why, then, should two peoples, thus exactly unlike in every essential as well as non-essential particular, seek the same country to an extent far greater than all other races combined?</p>
   <p>It may be that this is one of nature's tricks or designs in the direction of compensations. The two act as counterpoises of each other. Flood the country with either, to the exclusion of the other; give either unlimited control of affairs, and the result would be most disastrous. That these opposites come in quantities that so balance each other, enables the native population-- and by native we mean all those born in, and identified with, the country whether of foreign or native parentage--to hold the balance of power and to prevent affairs from gravitating either in the direction of the one or the other. This of course applies only to the first or second generations of the emigrants for the reason that the grandchildren, and often the children of both, are anxious for nothing so as to drop their ancestral line, and to regard themselves wholly as Americans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
