<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-02-24">Feb. 24, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Municipal Gas - Works</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1362</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1362.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-02-24">Feb. 24, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">MUNICIPAL GAS - WORKS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung was the first local newspaper which demanded the elevation of the railroad tracks as the only remedy for our chaotic transportation. It is the Staats - Zeitung again which many years ago, and repeatedly since, has pointed out that municipal gas works are the only solution for the abominable exploitation of consumers by the gas companies. It is gratifying that the citizens have finally awakened to see the imperative necessity for both measures. The Staats - Zeitung joyously welcomes the battle which shall be initiated tonight against the gas monopoly. It does not overlook the fact that the fight will be hard. The gas companies will defend their millions with an army of the best and shrewdest lawyers. They will not only have their own capital resources at their disposal, but also the support of the large capitalists who will not permit the dissolution of such vast capital without a struggle. The citizens in taking up this fight, must be aware that this matter will cost money - an enormous amount of money. They must elect a city council which is definitely in favor of such plans. They must fight for a law in the state legislature, which would permit special taxation for this purpose. They must engage the best lawyers to defeat their opponents. Whatever will be done will cost money.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, there can not be the least doubt in regard to the final triumph <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1363.jpg" n="2"/>if the citizens are determined to go ahead. If the city has authority to grant private concerns the right to build gas-works and to lay gas pipes, it most certainly possessess the prerogative of building its own gas works, etc. There can be no legal obstacle.</p>
   <p>In view of the above facts, three things only are necessary to make municipal gas works a reality; first, a mayor and a city council willing to cooperate; second, a legislature willing to authorizing the city to make a loan, or to devise special taxation over a period of years; and third; to raise a large campaign fund in order to procure the first and the second.</p>
   <p>Once the city has erected a gas works and has laid a few miles of pipe the old gas companies will be only too glad to sell out, ie., after they have been completely defeated in court. The campaign committee which will be appointed tonight will not have finished its task until the sale has taken place at the actual and not the ficticious valuation. The actual value may be about four to five million dollars which is about $40,000,000.00 less than the gas companies watered stock and mortgages indicate. The gas companies, undoubtedly, will make use of this predicament to arouse sympathy for their innocent victims who have bought their bonds and stocks in good faith, but they will not get very far. If a person purchases something knowing that it is worth only one ninth of the value presented, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1364.jpg" n="3"/>and that the remaining eight-ninths represent the hoped for exploiting the people, he deserves a loss on such a stupid investment.</p>
   <p>The citizens of Chicago have it in their power to liberate themselves from the gang of the bloodthirsty exploiters, the gas companies. But the people must act unitedly and with determination. Every citizen should attend the mass-meeting tonight for his own benefit as well as the welfare of the whole community. As previously inferred, the mass-meeting is held in the interest of municipal gas works.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
