<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-09-03">September 3, 1888</date><title level="a">Agitations by Sunday Saints</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0600</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <!--
                        <catRef target="#grp-scandinavian #code-III.C"/>
                        -->
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0600.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III C (Scandinavian)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-09-03">September 3, 1888</date><title level="a">AGITATIONS BY SUNDAY SAINTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the auspices of the Chicago Sabbath Association, a meeting was held yesterday afternoon at the Central Music Hall. This meeting was under the special management of Dr. Little, the most outstanding of the Sunday Saints, and was attended by men and women who are members of German and Scandinavian, Methodist, and some other Protestant churches. The purpose of the meeting was to condemn publicly that saloons are kept open on Sunday..........</p>
   <p>C. C. Bonney, a professional Sunday Saint, stated that it is most surprising and astounding to have so many Germans and Scandinavians come together in this hall to petition the "native" Americans to enforce the American Sunday laws, and to make an end to the desecrations of the Sabbath.</p>
   <p>A bishop of the Methodist church then read in German a part of the scriptures, where it speaks of keeping the Sabbath from the standpoint of orthodox beliefs. Not only the front doors of the saloons should be closed on Sunday, but also the back and side entrances.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0601.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Reverend J. Bergen then addressed the audience "in the name of the Germans" in English.</p>
   <p>"The Germans," he said, "have been accustomed in Germany to keep the laws and when they come to America and observe how the laws are trampled underfoot, they are completely astonished and clasp their hands above their heads. But many of the German new-comers in Chicago are led astray by a large, influential German newspaper (Staats Zeitung), because there are columns after columns of vile Sunday amusements advertised and glorified. In spite of this however, the majority of Germans in Chicago are opposed to this desecration of the Sabbath, and it is only a matter of time until all the Germans will arise against these sinful conditions. Those Germans who helped to build Chicago will do their part also in rescuing it from complete ruination and corruption...</p>
   <p>Reverend Barrows characterized the saloons as the curse of our communities and the breeding place of all vices and stated that it is not only his own conviction, but also that of seventy-five percent of the population. It is to be expected that all those present will realize their responsibility toward all Germans and Scandinavians in Chicago, who have a different <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0602.jpg" n="3"/>viewpoint in regard to keeping the Christian Sabbath, namely, to convince them that a picnic, a ball, or the gathering in a saloon, is a violation of the law, and leads into the abysses of corruption.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
