<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-07-22">July 22, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">False Aspects</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1585</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1585.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-07-22">July 22, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">FALSE ASPECTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As one looks a thing either through the smaller or larger end of an opera glass, it moves either into distinct nearness or into furthest dissolution. To such optical deceits is also subjected the mental view. Who, for instance looking with naked eye upon the "injunction planks" of the Republican as well as the Democratic national platform, can not detect an essential difference. Both blame only the abuse of the injunction proceedings, both betray the timid endeavor, partly not to violate the famous American legal practice, and on the other hand try to catch the workingmen's votes. Mr. Gompers is so thoroughly convinced of the excellence of the Democratic expressions, and the worthlessness of those of the Republicans, that he imagines quite seriously that the organized workmen, whom he calls "Labor," must and will vote for Bryan on a account of his "injunction plank."</p>
   <p>The objections of the labor leaders, who have just as much experience and understanding, Mr. Gompers does not seem to consider at all. It seems that he does not find it worth while to refute their views. But as not all the laborers are looking through the same glasses, it is improbable that the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1586.jpg" n="2"/>members of unions, who are Republicans, will secede from their party and join the Democratic ranks, who do not show much friendliness towards the workingman whenever they are in power. In the southern states, as is well known, there is no limit set by the law to the abominable exploitation of children and a laborer who breaks his contract may be sent to a penal colony. Mr. Hearst, as is known, organized the Independent Party, seems not to be in favor of his former bosom friend, for the reason that the Democratic platform contains a weak and unpatriotic navy program. Like President Roosevelt, he wants four powerful iron-clads built at once, without considering that there are no crews for same, that the war expenses of the United States exceed those of every militaristic monarchy, and in consequence of which a big deficit has been created. The American people cannot be influenced, as experience shows, through selection of words. But not one in a thousand will vote Democratic on account of the Republican injunction plank nor will they join the Independent Party due to the Democratic navy program.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
