<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1873-01-03">Jan. 3, 1873</date>.
<title level="a">The Mayor, the Law and the People.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0744</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0744.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1873-01-03">Jan. 3, 1873</date>.
<title level="a">THE MAYOR, THE LAW AND THE PEOPLE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The commissioners had a perfectly legal right to suspend Washburn, and the Mayor has no right to consider him Police superintendent any longer.</p>
   <p>In regard to the sentiment of the people, the Tribune asserts that it is entirely in favor of the Mayor and denies that the hatred of foreigners has anything to do with it. The Tribune specially defends the Mayor against the accusation of being a hater of foreigners. Now, we have never made any such accusation, but what we have said was that he allowed himself to be made a tool of the haters of foreigners.</p>
   <p>The main reason for the entire conflict is the Tribune knows that as well as we do the violent attack of the temperance adherents last fall, against the customs of the "foreigners" especially of the Germans.</p>
   <p>The brutal hatred of foreigners by such idiotic zealots as Kittredge and the temperance unions are the real motive for the revolt against the Police <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0745.jpg" n="2"/>Commissioners. Washburn is, for those zealots, the Samson, who must crush the Philistines, and on account of that he must be maintained in office even if illegally. For over ten years different nationalities have lived peacefully together in Chicago and the Tribune itself never objected to the manner in which the Germans celebrated their Sundays, and now it claims that it should suddenly be forbidden them. If the Tribune does not believe that nativist hatred of foreigners has anything to with the revolt against the Police Commissioners, let it send its reporters to the gambling hell called Board of Trade, and let them hear how the respectable citizens there use the words "d----d Dutch" or d----d Irish" when they speak of Police Commissioners.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
