<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1890-01-30">January 30th, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">(Prohibition) They Start Again. the Sunday Objectors Start Agitating.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0587</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0587.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1890-01-30">January 30th, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">(Prohibition) They Start Again. The Sunday Objectors Start Agitating.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What the "Sunday Closing Association" wants. (Editorial) According to the native sheet, the Daily News, we notice that the "objections" of our city who combined into the Sunday Closing Association, intend to start unusual commotions. According to our information as obtained from the above source, the encouragement they needed has been derived from all classes of the labor-population, irrespective of creed or nationality. If successful, then even the most respectably conducted saloons must close and no worker may enjoy a glass of beer among friends, after a week of effort and labor unless he is sufficiently prosperous to buy "wholesale" on a Saturday In order to give this proposal a humanitarian appeal, all factories, stores and shops must not function and to realize it, Sunday Rest Clubs are to be started in each ward, whose avowed purpose is: never to elect a dissenting alderman. All the combined objections, fraternizing under the name "Sunday Rest League" will then save the atrocious world all at once, by making it instantly sinless. Ofcourse, this crazy brotherhood promises to remain aloof from all politics but what this signifies, requires no extensive <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0588.jpg" n="2"/>elucidation. A sub-committee selected from the smartest of these world-benefactors has the thing all "fixed up" and contemplates the formulation of constitution and by-laws, at its next meeting with the general assembly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
