<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-02">June 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Away with Prohibition!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0152</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0152.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-02">June 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">AWAY WITH PROHIBITION!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Next Monday there will be an election for judges in Cook County. At the same time the voters will decide whether Prohibition is to be abolished or not. It is true the question will not be put to the electorate in this form; moreover, delegates are to be elected to a state convention in which the issue will be decided. The matter is nonetheless very simple, for the Legislature has enacted a law governing this election, and, in consequence, it is hardly possible to mislead the voters.</p>
   <p>However, we would stress the great importance of this election. All delegates to the convention will be elected "at large"; that is, every voter has the right to vote for all of the fifty delegates. On the ballot the names of the members of the two groups are placed side by side. The first <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0153.jpg" n="2"/>list of names is superscribed "for ratification," and the second list, "against ratification". In addition, a circle has been placed above each list. The voter need only put a cross in the circle above the first list; that is, in the circle on the left side of the ballot.</p>
   <p>It is altogether superfluous, and even hazardous, to place a cross before the names of the delegates, for such a procedure involves the danger of marking the ballot wrong and thus invalidating it. So much for marking the ballot. Now a word or two about the importance of the election. The Administration has made it its object to abolish Prohibition before the end of this year. This goal can be attained if the opponents of Prohibition do their duty. It may be assumed that a majority of the people of Illinois will vote for ratification. But that is not enough. The Majority must be overwhelming. The impression must be created throughout the country that the people of the state of Illinois are almost unanimous in their desire to abolish Prohibition.</p>
   <p>Elections in the larger states have great moral influence upon the states <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0154.jpg" n="3"/>in which no elections have been held. In the case of Illinois, this influence, is of especial significance, for on Tuesday, June 6, Indiana goes to the polls, and in that state the "drys" have conducted a strong campaign to obtain a majority against ratification. The leaders of the "wets" in Indiana have repeatedly appealed to the Illinois opponents of Prohibition, urging them to see to it that all their adherents go to the polls on election day, because it is known that the election in Illinois will have a profound effect upon the result of the voting in Indiana. All "wets" are honor bound to heed this appeal and to create a mass demonstration next Monday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
