<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-05-20">May 20, 1871</date><title level="a">Germans to the Front!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1148</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1148.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-05-20">May 20, 1871</date><title level="a">GERMANS TO THE FRONT!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The strangest concession which recently has been made by the American press to German spirit and solid vigor we find in an editorial of the Chicago Evening Post under the headline "The Restoration of Germany".</p>
   <p>After pointing to the elements of a higher civilization and genuine popular freedom he finds that in the newly founded German Empire, he makes the following application to American conditions"...."At last the Germans have become conscious of their strength and we hope much good from that for American politics. We are far from wishing to emphasize racial differences....however we stand just now in a crisis regarding our fate, caused by the impudent encroachment of a foreign (Irish) nationality which, brought up in ignorance and living in undisciplined sensuality, has gained, thanks to its priests and its demagogues, absolute domination over the biggest state in the Union...Now the time has come for the Germans to assert themselves as Teutons (as against the Celtic element of our population)...and to save true freedom and civilization just as their brothers on the other side of the bigpond did when they annihilated the corrupt and degenerate Caesarism of the Gaul gang".</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1149.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>According to this the Americans wish the Germans to help them to get rid of Irish mob rule, and this may very well be accomplished if only the Americans themselves will collaborate, and will exercise their right to vote. However, it is well-known that the majority of the well-to-do Americans abstain from voting and completely ignore politics. Wealth has throttled the voice of patriotism; the successive luxury and frivolity of our so-called higher (i. e. wealthier) classes has produced an enervation which abominates any exertion.</p>
   <p>The fate of New York will engulf all the cities of the Union if it is not checked while there is time. The rising of the German masses throughout the country has the effect of a tonic on the weakened American nerves - which, it is true, hardly twenty years back found themselves insulted by the smell of German sauerkraut and were irritated (in the years 1854 and 1855) to the point of an attack of "know-nothing" fever. However, we may forget this and we have long since forgiven it.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1150.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>That the inevitable antagonism of the Celtic and the Germanic races will lead on American soil, too, to bloody encounters that, at the moment, can still be doubted. But that this battle may be fought in a dignified way to the end that the Americans themselves could greatly contribute, if they will accept our counsel and introduce the German language into all public schools in this country. The removal of all sectarian elements from our free schools will further form a main fortress against the encroachments of all kinds of bigoted sects. The priests ("Pfaffen") at all times have been the first ones to weld the yoke of despotism to the neck of a free people, because the unfree spirit of the uneducated individual eagerly surrenders to the belief in a freely invented super-natural.</p>
   <p>Give us free schools and the limping devil retreats. The free spirit finds the free God without help.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
