<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-13">June 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Meager Results</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1269</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1269.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-13">June 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">MEAGER RESULTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Senate Committee investigation of the J. P. Morgan Company has been concluded. It is reported that the Senate in its next session will put other banking houses under the microscope; but if the results are no better than the results of the Morgan investigation it would be advisable for the gentlemen to save the time and money [required for the purpose].</p>
   <p>For years, very serious charges have been published against the Morgan banking house. It has been repeatedly stated that the firm exercises great influence upon the foreign policy of our country. However, nothing was said on this matter during the investigation.</p>
   <p>John P. Morgan and his business associates may justly claim that they carried off the victory in the battle. Although the Senate Committee engaged the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1270.jpg" n="2"/>services of the eminently successful lawyer, Ferdinand Pecora, it could not prove that the House of Morgan was guilty of even one illegal act. Moreover, it was forced to give Mr. Morgan and his associates an opportunity for some very effective advertising. The people who were accused were well prepared. They could prove that their securities had earned good profits for their clients, and that most of these securities were yielding dividends despite the depression, and that they were still comparatively "safe".</p>
   <p>People who have money to invest could form but one conclusion from the course of the investigation: namely, that the House of Morgan is a reliable and successful company whose securities are better than those of many other firms, even in times of economic depression. Of course, one cannot entirely eliminate the speculative element from this type of business, and losses to clients who were on the preferred list, and even to members of the firm, could not be avoided.</p>
   <p>Little or nothing was revealed concerning the international relations of the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1271.jpg" n="3"/>House. And it was just this angle that was of especial interest to the public.</p>
   <p>It is true that the whole country was "unpleasantly" surprised when it was established that Morgan and his partners had paid no income tax for two years, and only a ridiculously small one for another year. But the gentlemen could prove that they had strictly observed the law. Therefore, the results of this investigation must be considered entirely negative.</p>
   <p>Of course, the fact that the income-tax laws may stand much improvement did not escape the notice of the Senators; but the gentlemen in Congress should have thought of that before. However, one should not be unjust: this laboring mountain has brought forth a mouse. On recommendation of Senator La Follette, the Senate has resolved to make income-tax reports accessible to the public in the future. It is not clear what the purpose of this measure is. It was in force some years ago, but did not serve its purpose; and since it proved to be very unpleasant for many honorable and decent citizens, it was abolished.</p>
   <p>People who wish to evade taxes will be able to do so in the future; for the law <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1272.jpg" n="4"/>is so worded that it affords ample opportunity for evasion. Thus, the proposed improvement to be achieved by the amendment proposed by Senator La Follette is the rankest kind of bungling. It does not prevent evasion, and it only creates difficulties for honest taxpayers. The House of Morgan and Company has every reason to be pleased with the results of the investigation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
