<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-11-02">Nov. 2, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">The Sunday Question</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0884</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0884.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-11-02">Nov. 2, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">THE SUNDAY QUESTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Liberal statements concerning the Sunday question or similar issues have a twofold value when made by pastors, who, by the way, have great influence in this country. And it is exceedingly gratifying to find that such statements are increasing, both in number and in emphasis. Recently, Reverend Stebbins, one of the most prominent and influential pastors from the Pacific coast district, used as the text of a lecture: "The Son of man is Lord even of the Sabbath." He said in part:</p>
   <p>"The Jewish Sabbath, which according to Old Testament tradition fell on the seventh day of the week, was adopted by the Christian Church and transferred to the first day of the week. However, in taking this action the Christians were actuated neither by command nor recommendation from the Founder of the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0885.jpg" n="2"/>Christian Church. He did not set aside a special day, nor is there any authorization in the New Testament to observe a special day for worship. It was a matter of tradition,' of free choice. To enact a law to enforce the observance of Sunday as a religious holiday savors of a spirit of intolerance and a desire for persecution; and such a procedure is anything but Christlike. And laws which prohibit a citizen's doing as he pleases, though he in no way encroaches upon the rights of others, are null and void. There is still too much pharisaism among individuals as well as among religious denominations; for example; The City of Brotherly Love, the city of fashionable piety and gilt prayer books, enjoins the poor to pay five cents for a streetcar ride (on Sunday)--or, they may hire an equipage for ten dollars--while the rich ride in their won carriages drawn by fine horses. That is a shame! The idea that Sunday is an especially sacred day is erroneous. It is just as much a sin to steal or lie on Monday or Thursday as it is in Sunday, and it is no more a sin, and just as honorable and decent to enjoy fresh air and harmless amusements on Sunday as it is on, Tuesday or Wednesday. Morality cannot be forced by legislation; it can be engendered and fostered only by good example <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0886.jpg" n="3"/>and encouragement."</p>
   <p>Well spoken, Reverend Stebbins!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
