<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-02-04">February 4, 1896</date><title level="a">(Vox Populi) to the Editor of the "Abendpost"!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0543</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0543.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1896-02-04">February 4, 1896</date><title level="a">(Vox Populi) To the Editor of the "Abendpost"!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the general meeting of the Turner Club "Vorwaerts" on January 29th the following resolution was accepted:</p>
   <p>In regard to the fact, that at the present time an attempt is being made to close all business places on Sunday, permit us to call attention to the following; After taking a good look at the leaders of this movement, one becomes convinced that here are presented no honest intentions to procure a free day of rest and recreation for the laborer. We find here chiefly clergymen and enemies of the people, who play their game and pursue under cover of labor friendship their own egoistic purposes. The true intention of these" "Liberators" is aimed at the introduction of a puritan-religious quiet Sunday in order that they themselves can fish in the troubled water.</p>
   <p>The Sabbath shall be a day of recreation for the laborer, and therefore all places of recreation and entertainment shall be open to him. Therefore we call the attention of the public to the peril which it faces; for when this clique has once obtained a solid hold, it will expand its anti-liberal aims so that it can enforce the closing of all entertainment and recreation places by the way of prohibition laws. We feel sorry that there still exist labor <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0544.jpg" n="2"/>organizations which render their services to the work of these obscurantists. The Turner Club surely has no objection if the laborers want to win a free for themselves, but condemns it decidedly if they use such shameful methods as uniting with their own worst enemies. The Turner Club always will support a liberal movement, but deems it its duty to warn the laborers of their present allies, because their intentions indicate nothing good; further, we also warn the business people to work against their own interest and against their liberty by the signing of petitions that are put in circulation by the backers of the Sunday closing laws. Generally the Turner Club protests against all compulsion through laws, because it is contrary to the spirit of our free institutions, but it does advise the laborers to fight independently for their free day and provide for it, that on this day they are not robbed of their pleasures.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
