<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-19">Jan. 19, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Vote</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0402</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0402.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-19">Jan. 19, 1919</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="2" reason="illegible"/> VOTE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The upper house of the Illinois legislature, the Senate has adopted the Prohibition Amendment to the United States Constitution by a vote of thirty to fifteen. The lower house, the House of Representatives, has agreed to vote on it next Tuesday.</p>
   <p>The "drys" claim that they have between eighty-three and ninety votes for the prohibition amendment "in the bag," while seventy-seven votes (two thirds of the total) would be sufficient to secure Illinois' vote for Prohibition. They laugh at the assertion of the leaders of the "Wets" that the amendment will not get more than seventy-three votes and therefore will be defeated, but still they consider it wise to call for a whirlwind campaign among the "folks at home". By this means they intend to exert strong pressure on any undecided or unsafe <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0403.jpg" n="2"/>members of the house and thus prevent unpleasant surprises.</p>
   <p>Of course, that is very smart on the art of the "drys". "An ounce of prevention is worth a pound of cure and "a stitch in time saves nine". The "wets," that is, the opponents of national Prohibition, should heed the example set by the procedure of the Illinois Anti-Saloon League and do likewise. Of course it is futile to try to convert an avowed Prohibitionist by arguing justice and reason. The history of the Prohibition amendment has demonstrated that beyond all doubt. During a time when every day of delay meant great danger for the country, they spared no pains in their effort to frustrate the most urgent national legislation in order to force a victory for their bad cause and they will not relent in their determination to make the country dry if they can, even if they are given irrefutable and conclusive proof that national prohibition is diametrically opposed to the spirit of the Constitution and of democracy; that it unjustly destroys great values and is as immoral as anything could be. But it is a well-known fact that of those members of Congress who voted in favor of the amendment, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0404.jpg" n="3"/>and of those members of the Illinois legislature whose votes were counted for Prohibition, not a few were not avowed Prohibitionists at all, but merely stooges and camp followers, who fear the influence and the enmity of the Prohibition element "at home"--i. e., in their election districts.</p>
   <p>These may still be won over and saved from their cowardice, if only the liberal and really American and democratic elements "at home" would make up their minds in the eleventh hour and just once stand up for their cause as zealously and efficiently as the Prohibition fanatics and <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> have been doing all the time. They will not be able to follow the example of the Prohibitionists and hold church meetings in every town and hamlet of the state, for our denominational churches are the true strongholds of Prohibition, but at any rate they would hold meetings of businessmen and citizens, and there speak for their cause and make resolutions which should prove more effective than the prayers of hypocritical, fanatical, and self-righteous bigots.</p>
   <p>They could appeal to common sense and self-preservation. We are living in a dark <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0405.jpg" n="4"/>and perilous time. The war is over and then, again, it is not over. If a treaty of peace should be signed tomorrow, we would still feel the aftermath of the war for some time to come. So much has been said about the difficulties and dangers of the period of reconstruction that every thinking person must be familiar with this subject. And those who have not yet heard of it must be aware of it now in view of the strikes which are breaking out here and there, in view of the grumbling and discontent of the masses, in view of the shadow which the demobilization of our army of three millions is already casting before so sharply that it is noticeable to all. So far only a few hundred thousand have been discharged from the army, and already it is becoming difficult to find satisfactory jobs for these people. Many, perhaps most of them, were promised reinstatement in their former positions, but during times of great labor shortages employers learned how to get along with fewer workers, or engaged female help who, in many instances, have proved to be as good as, and sometimes better than, the old employees, with the result that their employers cannot or do not care to throw them out into the street.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0406.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>During times like these it is necessary carefuly to maintain all existing industries; to strengthen and extend them if possible, and to establish new ones whenever an opportunity occurs. In such a time common sense demands the avoidance of anything which might add to the unrest and discontent. In such a time tax values and taxing power should be increased, for the demands made upon the taxpayers are very great and will remain so for a long time.</p>
   <p>But the adoption of the Prohibition amendment--national Prohibition--would mean the scuttling of a great industry and inestimable values. It would deprive hundreds and thousands of workers of an opportunity to make a living; tens of thousands of their property and business, and <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>  of their livelihood, and the masses of those seeking employment would be augmented by the hundreds of thousands, and the number of taxpayers would be decreased by many thousands. Hundreds of thousands more would become restless and discontented, and would feel cheated by unjust and unscrupulous methods, and would lose their faith in American square dealing. To many millions all the beautiful words about <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0407.jpg" n="6"/>democracy, democratic self-determination and self-government, and democratic freedom, would seem nothing but empty phrases.</p>
   <p>If it is fair and just to tie a rock to the leg of a swimmer who is fighting a strong current, then adoption of Prohibition at a time like this may also be justified. But if, at present, it would seem advisable and in the general interest to preserve the economic prosperity of the country and to maintain calm and order, to create as many opportunities for jobs as possible and to promote and expand industry and business--then the institution of national Prohibition would be a crime, and those who vote on Tuesday in favor of the amendment, are voting against the interests of the country, the state of Illinois, and their "folks at home" and, incidentally, against their own interests, unless they have an ulterior motive.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
