<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-08-24">Aug. 24, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">The Germans and the Irish.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1069</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1069.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-08-24">Aug. 24, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMANS AND THE IRISH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Roman Catholic church as a church, and the Roman Catholic religion as a religion, are of no more concern to us than the Protestant, Jewish, the Buddha, or the Bramah religions are. The Illinois Staats Zeitung believes as does old Fritz, that it is best to let everybody be happy in his own way. But when a band of stupid Irish ruffians dare to interfere with the German Catholic element, than we feel that it is our duty to be on the job. "Blood is thicker than water". Those of the German-Americans, affiliated with the Catholic church, have held their meetings for many years past, and never have been reminded that German is their mother tongue. All of a sudden the Irish have become perturbed about it. These ruffians themselves, not born in this country, whose original language is the Celtic language have only as lashed slaves of their exploiters accepted their language: and they have the audacity to want to prohibit the German-Catholics the use of their language! And worse than that: they who were born slaves to their Anglo-Saxon masters dare to compare the German language to the grunting of swines. The Catholic Advocate in Louisville makes this insolent remark: The German language only eighty years ago, was considered as a pro-tozoic speech in Europe; just a little better than inarticulate sounds of the lowest animals. Frederick the Great detested it; the language is scoffed at by <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1070.jpg" n="2"/>other nations, and the refined circles of the German people are not proud of knowing it." What German, no matter how reverently he bows before the Irish Bishops, would not be ready with his fists when hearing such horrid remarks from an Irish scoundrel. At the time when the first German settlers came to America, the Irish language was the Celtic grunting, and now they have the audacity to tell us to abolish that language which was used for their first lessons in religion and in morals. Isn't this enough to make the blood of any sensible person boil? But they have not the courage to ask the same of the Catholics in Canada, for they feel subordinate to the French people just as much as the negro is to his master here (The slave was freed in 1853) Will the German Catholics disregard all this, just because they are Catholics? Are they going to take the insult suggesting that they become Irish instead of remaining good and decent German-Americans as the German Protestants and even pagans are. The German Catholics will very soon hold their annual meeting in Chicago, and if they don't show the Irish on this occasion that they are Germans and, as such, defend their nationality, then it would be well for them to show the Irish that they are their willing slaves, and put the prefix "Mac" or "O" to their names, as: Mac Schulze, O'Muller, etc.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
