<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-10-14">Oct. 14, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">What a Lutheran Publication Thinks of Closing the World's Fair on Sundays.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0556</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0556.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-10-14">Oct. 14, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT A LUTHERAN PUBLICATION THINKS OF CLOSING THE WORLD'S FAIR ON SUNDAYS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is interesting and important to know what a local Lutheran publication, Rundschau, has to say about the Sunday question. It writes as follows: "At the present the Sunday question is a very lively subject of discussion in World's Fair circles. It is planned to induce Congress by mass petitions to repeal the reverse clause attached to the appropriation of $2,500,000 for the World's Fair.</p>
   <p>"To have the World's Fair closed on Sunday, involves a loss to the World's Fair Society to the many exhibitors, who not only lose money but time also, and to the working classes, who are unable to visit the exhibit during the week.</p>
   <p>"Some fanatics in Congress base their claim in regard to a closed Sunday upon the concept that it is a divine law, and that the characteristic of the American Sunday must be protected. Our answer to this is, that the closing of Sunday at the World's Fair would be in the interest of saloons and brothels.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0557.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It can hardly be expected that the countless visitors will all go to church. We are of the opinion that the ennobling and improving of men can be promoted in the viewing of works of art and science. Only a few demand the repeal of the Sunday clause, because they believe that Congress has no right to make laws, which interfere with personal liberty and freedom of conscience. But is not this reason the most important in this matter? It certainly is! The Sunday fanatics want to force upon the people the wrong Jewish theory about the Sabbath, and make Sunday Christians of them by enforcing a law; just as the prohibition fanatics attempt to reform drunkards and occasional drinkers by legal measures.</p>
   <p>However, where does freedom of conscience abide? Where is personal liberty? Shall we no more decide for ourselves how to spend Sunday? Shall the State punish us for taking a walk on Sunday or to visit Jackson Park and the World's Fair? Shall the Jewish Sabbath become the American Sunday, and as such recognized by the State?</p>
   <p>"Christians know what to think of Sunday and how to observe it. It is exactly for this reason that we must vehemently condemn Sunday legislation by <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0558.jpg" n="3"/>the State. Where such Sunday laws lead to, is demonstrated by the fanatics in Tennessee, who persecuted the Adventists. Four quiet, peaceful, honest citizens were in jail in Pari, Tennessee from June 3rd until July 18th, because they observed the Sabbath, and worked on their farms on Sunday. They had disturbed none in their worship, and the neighbors respected them highly as citizens. On June 18th one of them was dismissed but the others were led through the streets with a number of colored criminals, and with chains on their feet, to work on a highway nearby. All this was done only because they were (of course, wrongly) convinced that they had to observe Saturday.</p>
   <p>"How can we be silent now, when we see, how Congress demands the closing on Sunday of the World's Fair, because the Christian idea of the American Sunday must be Preserved? Has the secular government the authority to render a verdict in regard to a day, a person, or an action, whether their specific character is Christian or not?</p>
   <p>"History of the present furnishes the proof that fanatics are ready, where they have the power to force their coercive laws upon the citizens, and to punish violators with chains and jails. Sunday legislation is an interference by the State with matters of the church. We demand, therefore, that Congress <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0559.jpg" n="4"/>repeal the Sunday clause, and pay no further attention to Sunday fanatics."</p>
   <p>We do not need to mention that we commend and admire the above mentioned publication for its manly and courageous stand in this matter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
