<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-12-06">Dec. 6, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Wirthsverein</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1479</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1479.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-12-06">Dec. 6, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE WIRTHSVEREIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Wirthsverein [Tavernkeepers' Association] held its regular meeting at Baume's pavilion yesterday. The meeting was well attended. In the absence of P. Mass, president of the association. Hermann Langenhahn, vice-president, acted as chairman. The minutes of the previous meeting were read and accepted. A new member joined the association.....</p>
   <p>Mr. H. Schule, who was summoned to court because of an infraction of the twelve o'clock closing ordinance, asked for a refund of attorney fees, a total of five dollars. His request was denied. The committee had considered the various aspects of the twelve o'clock closing ordinance and advised the association not to continue fighting the measure, as nothing could be gained thereby at present.</p>
   <p>The report was adopted unanimously. The [security] bonds offered by the treasurer and secretary were accepted.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1480.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Berger spoke about the twelve o'clock closing ordinance. He said that four policemen had watched his saloon for hours recently, although he always closed promptly. During this time a man was held up, beaten and robbed. It appeared that the police regarded the saloonkeepers as more dangerous than the highwaymen; obviously, our minions of the law were used only to watch tavern owners.</p>
   <p>P. Enders expressed his indignation and declared that Mayor Harrison placed saloons in the same category as gambling dens, which was unjust because tavern owners earn their money honestly.</p>
   <p>Peter Mueller then made a lengthy speech, in which he denounced the twelve o'clock closing ordinance. He said the measure constituted an impairment of the rights of free citizens, and he held the mayor responsible. He was in sympathy with the Democratic administration in general, but this particular issue he intended fighting with all means at his disposal. In the course of his speech Mueller urged the Democratic members of the association to form a committee to see the mayor and protest vigorously against the ordinance. Mueller became <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1481.jpg" n="3"/>increasingly excited as he emphasized various points of his topic, and finally also mentioned his candidacy, how the mayor had treated him, and the open letter wherein Mueller had given a reply to Harrison.</p>
   <p>Adolph Georg then spoke at length about the closing ordinance, and suggested that the Wirthsverein supply legal aid to all saloonkeepers who are unjustly hailed to court because of the ordinance. A long debate ensued; Messrs. P. Enders, B. Baum, Albert Ernst, Geo. Miehle and others argued the question.</p>
   <p>L. Schwuchow amended the motion, and asked that a committee consisting mostly of Democrats be appointed to see the mayor and demand an explanation. The amendment found no support.</p>
   <p>Joseph Miehle then declared that the association should defend all tavernkeepers who came in conflict with the law through no fault of their own.</p>
   <p>Mr. Georg then modified his former motion and offered it in form of a resolution:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1482.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Resolved, that the Wirthsverein defend its members gratuitously before the courts (provided that said members have obeyed all other statutes) in cases involving the twelve o'clock closing ordinance, whenever said members are found to have broken the law unintentionally, and no repetition of a voluntary transgression can be proved."</p>
   <p>Mr. Baum spoke next. He explained in great detail that the resolution could be accepted only if the association intended to make a test case.</p>
   <p>Mr. Feldkamp then criticized Harrison severely, and exclaimed that he cannot be trusted, because he favored the "drys" and was influenced by them.</p>
   <p>Peter Mueller then came to the defense of the mayor, and said that an official must always do his duty, and it behooves the mayor to enforce the existing laws. "The city council was responsible; Harrison was only the tool of that body, and I criticized Harrison only because he did not enforce the law when he came into office."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1483.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Several gentlemen, Baum, Clemens, and others, then spoke against the motion. The motion was defeated by a large majority.</p>
   <p>Baum offered a motion to nominate a committee of three to draft resolutions which should be submitted to the members. The motion was adopted and Messrs. Baum, Feldkamp, and Dieter were selected to serve on the committee. The committee deliberated, and during that period a ten-minute recess was taken.</p>
   <p>After the intermission, the committee read the following resolution:</p>
   <p>"The Wirthsverein hereby declares that tavernkeepers demand the same privileges enjoyed by hotel proprietors, and that the Wirthsverein protests against the maintenance of any saloon having a questionable reputation--irrespective of the stipulated closing hours. On the other hand, the Wirthsverein objects to the impairment of personal rights and prosecutions of respectable tavernkeepers whenever their places of business cannot be proved to be meeting places for persons of disreputable character."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1484.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The resolution was adopted. It was then decided to postpone the question of beer prices until the next general meeting, which will be held at the North Side Turnhalle (Turner Hall) next Friday.</p>
   <p>Adjournment followed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
