<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>
      <date when="1889-04-30">Apr. 30, 1889</date>
      <title level="a"/>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0589</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0589.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>
     <date when="1889-04-30">Apr. 30, 1889</date>
     <title level="a">
      <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>
     </title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>
    <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>
   </p>
   <p>A well attended meeting was held last night in the North Side Turnhalle, by a branch of the Alliance for Personal Rights. The president, <gap unit="words" extent="2" reason="illegible"/> Nettelhorst, introduced Dr. <gap unit="words" extent="2" reason="illegible"/> Cronin, who explained the aims of the alliance, and portrayed the activities of the enemies of personal liberty, the prohibitionists and others, in a most striking manner.</p>
   <p>"The people go to church where they are told that if the saloons are closed, the churches will be filled. Sunday after Sunday the clergymen preach that all misery and evil in the world is caused by alcoholic drinks, and that a large percentage of deaths and accidents are due to drunkenness."</p>
   <p>After the speaker finished, and the audience applauded, L. Nettlehorst spoke in German and stated, that for many years no other question has been asked so often as: What is the real aim of the Alliance of Personal Rights?   If a new organization is formed, a similar question is generally justified, and it is the duty of the members of such an association to explain their purpose and aims.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0590.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The Alliance for Personal Rights is fighting for the preservation of all rights, which are granted by the constitution and opposes all, who are trying to restrict the liberty of a free citizen. The Alliance attacks, chiefly, prohibition because its adherents make every effort to suppress the free viewpoints of the liberal citizens.  They are trying to force their opinions and teachings upon the moderate drinkers even by the means of a lasso. Children, too, are instructed on the supposed terrible consequences of the use of alcoholic drinks, and, thereby, are aroused to a certain contempt against their parents, who, perhaps indulge in a moderate use of alcohol. The attack of the prohibitionists is primarily aimed against the cheerful customs and habits of the Germans, and it is their duty now to be strongly united, in order to repulse the ruthless enemies. The Alliance has assumed to defend our rights, and whoever does not wish to see the good old German customs destroyed, should join our society."</p>
   <p>Mr. Nettlehorst's speech received thunderous applause. Julius <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> exhorted the audience to join the Alliance which defends our national human rights. It is important, he asserted, to prove to the prohibitionists and the "know-nothings"</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0591.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>What German culture, customs, and habits really are, and that he is convinced that victory over the bigots is certain if the Germans act in unison.</p>
   <p>After it was decided that the next meeting of the Alliance would be held on April 16th, at the same place, the meeting adjourned. Many in the audience were receivedas members into the association.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
