<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-08-26">August 26th, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">prohibition.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0456</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0456.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-08-26">August 26th, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">prohibition.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Progressive Republicans, as they like to be called, are at least in something behind the "standpatters", according to a certain magazine. They are in favor of prohibition almost without exception....It is hard to understand why that particular magazine finds it strange. Is not prohibition itself one of the retrogressive "Progresses" the reformers are aiming at? Prohibition is based upon the ridiculous assumption, that mankind can and "must" be made virtuous by means of laws and regulations according to prohibitionists, total abstinence is the greatest of all virtues and the saloons are not only the source of all vices, but also the cause of all social, industrial and political evils. Of course, the progressive Republicans are not quite so arrogant.</p>
   <p>They admit at least that there may be other causes underlying human depravity, however, they agree with the prohibitionist that perfection can be attained by pure mechanical means. If the world is not what she should be according to the ideals of reformers, it is not human inadequacy, called the" weak flesh" by theologians, but it is the result of certain public institutions. If these were amended, the millenium <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0457.jpg" n="2"/> would immediately appear.</p>
   <p>The sincerity of the progressive Republicans is not superior to the sincerity of their friends, the Prohibitionists. They simply deny all facts, which are contraty to their theories and therefore inconvenient.,..They defend stubbornly, direct legislation, although it has been proven, that the people can not possibly read all proposed legislation, much less understand the same. The "progressives" have preconceived notions and can not be tutored. Even in hypocrisy the progressives are not behind the defenders of virtue by Compulsion. We have experienced this in our own city...The leaders of the Progressive Republicans fight against the political machine, until they get hold of its control. If this is accomplished then they act the same as the so-called reactionaries. They exploit the public for selfish purposes, after they have deluded it, and supposedly laugh in their assemblies over the stupid world, which wants to be cheated.</p>
   <p>The alleged zeal to reform of the progressives should not sidetrack the liberal and, in particular the German voters. More important than anything else is the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0458.jpg" n="3"/>preservation and the restoration of liberty. In many states freedom is undermined and seriously threatened in the whole country. Despotism by a majority is not by any means more endurable, than if practised by a certain class or by an absolute ruler.</p>
   <p>Therefore we must insist, that a majority has no right to suppress and enslave the minority. Indeed, a poorly informed or artificially fanaticized majority should not be permitted to make laws without previous discussions and considerations; if the same make out of the individual citizen a poor slave or if they destroy what has been built up painfully through centuries. President Madison states in the "Federalist" that the United States shall be not a democracy but a constitutional State. The minority shall be protected against the moods, foolishness, and malignity of the majority by the constitution. If the Suprene Court had not "explained away" the constitutional rights of the individual, such a thing as the despotism of the prohibitionists would not be possible. Every thinking citizen should recognize the danger of direct legislation by a deluded mass.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
