<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-18">Feb. 18, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The City Council</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0706</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0706.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-18">Feb. 18, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE CITY COUNCIL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The City Council held a lively session yesterday evening. A host of representatives from the Tavern Keepers' Association, led by President Feldkamp, and their lawyer, Rubens, were present to observe the expected debate about the "drys'" snooping bill which was introduced the previous Monday.</p>
   <p>On the table of every alderman reposed a circular, issued jointly by the brewers, distillers and saloonkeepers, which was the report of Saturday's meeting, wherein the City Council was requested to reconsider the infamous bill.</p>
   <p>Lodding's motion to reconsider the measure did not carry, but the mayor's veto was read to the assembly instead. In his message the mayor explained why the bill should not become an ordinance, and he gave convincing reasons without placing any more stress on the temperance question than necessary.</p>
   <p>The refusal of the city's chief was accepted by the majority of the City <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0707.jpg" n="2"/>Council which, at this time, was well represented by the German aldermen--Knopf and Beidler can hardly expect to be considered German aldermen. It is hoped that the water bigots will not revive the insidious temperance question within the near future.</p>
   <p>It might be interesting to note that the mayor considered the measure entirely harmless, until the Illinois Staats-Zeitung published an editorial last Wednesday [February 12, 1879] wherein the dangerous and far-reaching consequences of the bill were exposed. A representative of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung informed the mayor, and found in Corporation Counsel Bonfield a very effective ally in convincing the city's highest official of the unavoidable perils which were bound to beset the community, should he attach his signature to the document.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
