<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-06-28">June 28, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">German-American Proposition at the Democratic National Convention</title><title level="a" type="sub">National Organization of German-American Democrats Demand Repeal of 18th Amendment</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-06-28">June 28, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN-AMERICAN PROPOSITION AT THE DEMOCRATIC NATIONAL CONVENTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">National Organization of German-American Democrats Demand Repeal of 18th Amendment</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the many propositions submitted to the Resolutions Committee of the Democratic National Convention, there is one by the National Organization of German-American Democrats, headed by Alphonse G. Koeble.</p>
   <p>The resolution begins with an explanation of the aims and purposes of the organization, which was founded in New York in 1931.</p>
   <p>The main object of the organization is to win over Democrats of German extraction so that they may participate more intensively in the activities of the party. The purpose is to win back to the Democratic Party the German-Americans who abandoned it in 1916 and to exert an influence in order to win over to the party Republicans and independents of German extraction.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0186.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Steps have been taken to keep a network or organizations, until Labor Day, in thirty states, especially Massachusetts, New York, New Jersey, Ohio, Indiana, Illinois, Michigan, Nebraska, Iowa, Missouri, Wisconsin, and California. These organizations will be then in a position to exercise an influence upon the election.</p>
   <p>The thesis of the resolution reads: "The organization is fully convinced that the Democratic Party can win back many partisans, provided they pledge themselves clearly and unambiguously to the repeal of the 18th Amendment, and thereby secure their support for the enterprises of the organization.</p>
   <p>"In the meanwhile they should demand Congress to legalize the manufacturing of wine and beer with a reasonable percentage of alcohol."</p>
   <p>As argument for the proposition of the organization, the following is mentioned:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0187.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Prohibition is contrary to the century-old habits of the German and other races residing in this country, and is furthermore, considered as a severe violation of the rights of personal freedom. The Germans have brought beer to this country. This beverage for the most part has taken the place of brandy, thereby contributing more to the furtherance of sobriety and moderation than it ever can be expected from the fatal experiment of the National prohibition act.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
