<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-12">Feb. 12, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">A New Temperance Campaign</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0709</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0709.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-12">Feb. 12, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW TEMPERANCE CAMPAIGN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The new ordinance adopted by the City Council the day before yesterday empowers the mayor, or rather, directs him, to appoint twenty special "snoopers" from the Citizen's Club to prevent the sale of intoxicants to minors. It is as nearly like a new prohibition campaign as one egg is like another. No one asserted that the dispensing of whiskey, or even beer, to juveniles might be recommendable nor would any respectable person demand noninterference in such sales; but experience had shown that "measures to prevent our youth from being led astray" are not the goal of the water wagon crew--their object is constantly to harass respectable tavern Keepers. The "drys" just want an opportunity to ensure the tavern keepers on the strength of the State law [Translator's note: At the beginning the editor said city ordinance) so that life can be made miserable for all beer vendors.</p>
   <p>One has witnessed how sturdy, bearded chaps, with all the appearance of being much older than twenty-one years, were sent to saloons for but one purpose, to <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0710.jpg" n="2"/>prosecute the bar room proprietor on the strength of the liquor law which prohibits the sale of intoxicants to minors--a charge which entails not only a fine but a jail sentence, which can be imposed upon conviction. Not only did it happen here, but the same procedure was tried in many of the larger cities where prohibitionists, on the pretext of safeguarding the morals of adolescents, resorted to the most despicable espionage system, and to the contemptible practices of agents provocateurs.</p>
   <p>No doubt, the same intentions prevail in regard to the recent ordinance passed by the City Council. Therefore, the mayor should study the matter thoroughly before affixing his signature to the document and making it a law.</p>
   <p>The possibility exists that a storm like that of six years ago is in the offing. The Republican party owes its return to power in the city to one circumstance: it hinted that the Sunday and temperance question would not become an issue again. If public confidence is undermined--if the Republicans give the "drys" an opportunity to start another crusade under the thin, transparent <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0711.jpg" n="3"/>guise of preventing the sale of intoxicants to minors--then the party now in power should remember that its actions involve the risk of returning the Democrats to control of the city administration again.</p>
   <p>"As you sow, so shall ye reap!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
