<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-11-12">Nov. 12, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">An Open Letter to Chief of Police Hubbard.</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Chicago, Nov. 12, 1888.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1044</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1044.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-11-12">Nov. 12, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">AN OPEN LETTER TO CHIEF OF POLICE HUBBARD.</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Chicago, Nov. 12, 1888.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>"The undersigned believes it to be his duty as a citizen of this "tremendous" community to inform you about certain facts which might still be unknown to you. If I am not mistaken there is a police ordinance in this city which prohibits the insulting or illegal stopping of passers-by on public roads. Such an offense has been called "disorderly conduct" up to now and has been punished accordingly.</p>
   <p>"How is it then, dear Mr. Chief of Police, that your subordinates dare to do what is forbidden to other mortals?</p>
   <p>"Was it on your order, (which I can hardly believe), that the policemen stopped and insulted the Socialists who came home from Waldheim like other decent citizens, and tried to rob them of their badges? The undersigned was a witness when a citizen, walking along 5th Avenue with a red badge, was stopped by policemen and requested to remove it. As he refused to comply <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1045.jpg" n="2"/>with their demand, one of the policemen called out loudly:</p>
   <p>"'You----! Go back to Germany to your wooden-shoe country!'" This officer of the law apparently expected some one to start a fight with him and thus to give a chance to collect some laurels.</p>
   <p>"If there is a law, dear Mr. Chief of Police, against wearing red, then what about the red handkerchiefs of the Democratic party, the red plumage on the hats of the ladies, the red neckties of the "dudes", and the red underwear of the male and female aristocracy? And why not prohibit red mustaches and whiskers?</p>
   <p>"I too, dear sir, am of the opinion that America belongs to the Americans, and I am sure that most Socialists agree with me on this point. Nativistic hate against us Germans is unjustified. Why are not measures taken to keep out the English, French, German and other capitalistic sharks who soon will own the whole country and who certainly do not follow the principle: America belongs to the Americans.</p>
   <p>"For years the Socialists have been preaching that the country belongs to its <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1046.jpg" n="3"/>inhabitants, whether in Germany or America or any other place, and not to single individuals who exploit the ones who cultivate it.</p>
   <p>"I hope, Mr. Chief, that in the future, citizens who wear red committee badges, will not be insulted.</p>
   <p>William Urban."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
