<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1925-10-11">Oct. 11, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Forge Plans against Easy Divorces</title><title level="a" type="sub">In Cook County Alone More Than Seven Thousand Divorces Granted Annually</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0812</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0812.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1925-10-11">Oct. 11, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">FORGE PLANS AGAINST EASY DIVORCES</title><title level="a" type="sub">In Cook County Alone More Than Seven Thousand Divorces Granted Annually</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The steadily growing use made of the divorce courts the country over, the particularly rapid increase of divorce suits in Cook County, Illinois, and the uncovering of quite a number of actual "divorce mills" in various states of the Union have prompted both great and small minds to occupy themselves to a greater extent with the very weighty question of how best to put a stop to a condition that is by no means a happy one.</p>
   <p>The campaign for uniform divorce laws for all states, which has been in progress for some time, is now being conducted with greater energy, and a large number of local reform organizations have, within the last few weeks, decided that this movement should be furthered and supported.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0813.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Cook County, Illinois has in Judge Joseph Sabath of the local Superior Court a cadi [this word is used in the original text] who, during his term in office, has granted more divorces than any other judge in the entire country. He can also claim the more or less beautiful glory (schoener Ruhm) that on the average more divorces are sought and granted in his jurisdiction than in any other county of the nation.</p>
   <p>It is revealed by the figures compiled by the organizations mentioned that, with one exception, twice as many divorces are granted in Cook County than in any other county of any other state. The exception is Wayne County, Michigan, to which the city of Detroit belongs.....</p>
   <p>In Cook County, Illinois, more than seven thousand divorces are granted yearly.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
