<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-04">Mar. 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Register!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Protest against Prohibition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0340</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0340.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-04">Mar. 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">REGISTER!</title><title level="a" type="sub">Protest Against Prohibition</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A number of Protestant clergymen who met in Wilken's Hall yesterday made a strong protest against national prohibition and against the attempt to make Chicago dry on April 1, two months before the Prohibition mendment becomes effective. It was resolved to ask all Protestant pastors of the city to interview all their members and friends by March 11, the only day of registration before the election, and to persuade them to register, so that they can voice an emphatic protest against national prohibition on April 1. It was also resolved, through a motion by Reverend W. Breitenbach, so send a letter to all German ministers in the city, requesting that they oppose prohibition with every means which is at their disposal and thus save what can still be saved. A committee consisting of Pastors Alfred Meyer, W. Breitenbach, and Christian Knudten, and Messrs. August Lueders and Otto Doederlein, was  elected to draw up the appeal, and will meet for that purpose tomorrow afternoon.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0341.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>About thirty pastors were present, representing the following bodies: Wartburg Synod, Ohio Synod, German-Evangelical Synod of North America, these number of laymen attended. Among them were Messrs. Henry Runkel and William Kramer, who acted as representatives of the newly organized Independent Voters' Association. Election Commissioner August Lueders served as chairman. The following men spoke: Pastors F. Wehrhahn, W. Breitenbach, Alfred Meyer, and John Traeger; and Laymen Henry C. Runkel, Otto Doederlein, and William Kramer.</p>
   <p>The majority of the speakers openly admitted that the German element and the liberal element in general had not been sufficiently watchful about the danger of prohibition, and that the acceptance of the Prohibition Amendment was directly attributable to this fact. They all called attention to the fact that the establishment of prohibition is but the first advance of Anglo-American Puritans, which will increase its endeavors to curb freedom and widen its field of operation. All German culture, the German language, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0342.jpg" n="3"/>German churches, and German schools, will become the prey of these reformers if their efforts are not strongly counteracted. The voting on the question whether Chicago shall be "wet" or not will afford the German element an opportunity to confront these Puritan schemes and to prove that the narrow-minded Puritans, who succeeded in bringing about the enactment of the Eighteenth Amendment and intend to encroach further upon the freedom of the individual, represent only a small part of the population. And though a victory of the liberal elements would have no immediate far-reaching results, the moral impression which a victory of the liberal over the Puritanic ideals in Chicago would make upon the entire country, should not be underestimated.</p>
   <p>In his address Reverend Breitenbach stated very emphatically that prohibition is contrary to the word of God and that it interferes with personal freedom; that it is the duty of Protestant ministers to oppose any movement which is not in agreement with the Scriptures; that the German community, which so often has failed to assert itself on numerous issues, did not proceed as <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0343.jpg" n="4"/>energetically and methodically against prohibition as it should have; that an immediate change in the method of procedure must be made; that all American men and women of German descent must register on March 11, the only registration day before the election in April, so that they can cast their ballots against prohibition.</p>
   <p>Reverend Alfred Meyer said, in a well-received address, that German culture in America had always served as the most important and most effective counter-balance to Puritanism, and that it must now concentrate all its power, so that its liberal ideas may overcome the narrow-minded ideas and endeavors.</p>
   <p>The Vereinigten Maennerchoere (Allied Male Choruses) held a well-attended meeting or delegates and issued an urgent appeal to all German voters to register on March 11, so that they will be eligible to vote against prohibition on April 1. The appeal, which consists of resolutions which were passed in the meeting, reads as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0344.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"The Vereinigte Maennerchoere look upon it as their duty to call the attention of all their members to the danger which will threaten German social life unless the voting on the liquor question receives sufficient consideration.</p>
   <p>"It is absolutely essential that all American men and all American women of German descent who have not registered, have their names registered at the polls, so that they may vote on April 1.</p>
   <p>"The entire country is intent upon Chicago's decision; should an overwhelming majority vote against the fanatics, then the gentlemen in Washington will recognize the will of the people and not act hastily in the matter.</p>
   <p>"Up then and be doing, you Americans of German descent, men and women! At the ballot box you can fight your part of the battle against the fanatics. Especially the American women of German descent should give this matter their <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0345.jpg" n="6"/>earnest consideration. Every vote by an American woman of German descent will make one prohibitionist vote ineffective. So do not forget the dates: March 11 and April 1!</p>
   <p>Vereinigte Maennerchoere,</p>
   <p>William Arens, President,</p>
   <p>August Lueders, Secretary."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
