<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>
      <date when="1933-04-09">Apr. 9, 1933</date>
      <title level="a"/>
      <title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0158</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0158.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>
     <date when="1933-04-09">Apr. 9, 1933</date>
     <title level="a">
      <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>
     </title>
     <title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Legal beer, which will contain up to four percent alcohol, will be available in the near future....</p>
   <p>The law permitting the manufacture and sale of beer and wine with an alcoholic content of four percent is, after all, only a temporary pacifier, and at the same time a source of <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Incidentally, there is no wine which can <gap unit="words" extent="7" reason="illegible"/> alcohol, for the lightest of wines contains <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. It is also true that only the <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> beer contains less than four percent alcohol...</p>
   <p>It is obvious, therefore, that Prohibition is, in a certain <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, still <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0159.jpg" n="2"/> with us. <gap unit="words" extent="7" reason="illegible"/>, it is imperative that thirty-six states ratify the <gap unit="words" extent="4" reason="illegible"/> to the federal Constitution, and thus annul the Eighteenth amendment. This goal must be pursued without fail. If it is to be achieved, the unity and co-operation of all anti-prohibitionist <gap unit="words" extent="8" reason="illegible"/> the principle of <gap unit="words" extent="10" reason="illegible"/> of the release of light wines and beer; <gap unit="words" extent="10" reason="illegible"/> be imperiled because of this <gap unit="words" extent="2" reason="illegible"/> attitude, <gap unit="words" extent="2" reason="illegible"/> may be defeated. It is also <gap unit="words" extent="8" reason="illegible"/> their defeat and will <gap unit="words" extent="5" reason="illegible"/> will of the majority of the people. They are still active, it is only just now the scene of their activities has shifted. <gap unit="words" extent="5" reason="illegible"/> their exclusive battlefield, because from now on the fight for the final victory must be fought in every state in the union. We must also realize that many of those states are still in the clutches of the "drys," which increases the difficulty of winning those states for the ratification of the newly defeated amendment.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0160.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The interregnum, which will last until ratification has been effected, will hardly prove an ideal period. It must be borne in mind that despite the release of beer and light wines prohibition continues in effect, as in the past. Although a slight change in the prohibition authorities' method of procedure has been observed lately, nevertheless they are still with us, and what is more, they are as bold as ever. Congress did not deem it necessary to write, with only one stroke of the pen, a "finis" to prohibition. And why not? The "drys" are here for no other reason than to molest and make life miserable for their follow men....</p>
   <p>Furthermore, it is incomprehensible why Congress still consents to make more grants for the maintenance of prohibition. After all, the Volstead Act was an exceptional law used to bring about prohibition.... why is Congress still eager, in spite of the outcome of the November elections, and in spite of the mandate received from the nation, to retain the prohibition police? And another thing, why is the wicked Jones Law--better known as the "Five and Ten Law'--still in existence five months after the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0161.jpg" n="4"/>November election?</p>
   <p>It is said that prohibition authorities must henceforth content themselves with nosing around bootleggers and illegal breweries and stop molesting citizens who take no part in the illegal manufacture of either beer or wine. This announcement brings a sense of relief and comfort, for now the nation may rest assured that no more brutal attacks will be suffered by innocent citizens at the hands of prohibition agents. At least this will not occur under the present administration. However, the attitude taken by Congress which, although practicing rigid economy otherwise, is still making grants of large sums for the cause of prohibition--after all the mischief, misery, and suffering that law has caused--is rather <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>.</p>
   <p>With the return of beer next Friday, and with the celebrations anticipated on that occasion, the public must not forget that the battle against prohibition has not yet been won, and that it may take considerable time before <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0162.jpg" n="5"/>this is accomplished.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
