<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-04-22">Apr. 22, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Prohibition Thoroughly Condemned by Rabbi</title><title level="a" type="sub">Doctor Gerson B. Levi of Temple Isaiah-Israel Delivers Inflammatory Speech against "Drys"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0202</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0202.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 2 (Jewish)</item>
     <item>I B 1 (Jewish)</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-04-22">Apr. 22, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">PROHIBITION THOROUGHLY CONDEMNED BY RABBI</title><title level="a" type="sub">Doctor Gerson B. Levi of Temple Isaiah-Israel Delivers Inflammatory Speech Against "Drys"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Doctor Gerson B. Levi, rabbi of Temple Isaiah-Israel and president of the Rabbinical Association of Chicago, yesterday denounced Prohibition before members of his congregation.</p>
   <p>"It must be admitted," he said, "that the enforcement of Prohibition during the last ten years proved an absolute failure. The barbarous methods of enforcement indicate beyond doubt that the originators of this tyrannical movement have admitted failure. Prohibition is not a fundamental law of our country; this legislation is therefore beyond the conception of the people. It is also uncivilized to put violations of Prohibition laws on the same plane with common crimes like murder, robbery, etc. The Jones <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0203.jpg" n="2"/>law was also a savage measure, as was the law in the State of Michigan which imposed the penalty of imprisonment for life for the sale of one pint of prohibited alcohol. It is therefore most gratifying that this drastic measure has been repealed."</p>
   <p>Doctor Levi also discussed the connection between the Anti-Saloon League and the bootleggers, saying:</p>
   <p>"The close friendship between the Anti-Saloon League and the bootleggers may be of great political advantage to the League. On the other hand, financial gains are the sole interest of the bootleggers. For the good of society, however, this alliance cannot be tolerated."</p>
   <p>"No person is eager for the reappearance of saloons," said Doctor Levi; "nevertheless, it cannot be denied that the sale of liquor has increased since pro-Prohibition days. Neither do we deny that saloons were here for any good purpose. But did Prohibition make any strides toward its goal?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0204.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Prohibition is a restraint imposed from without upon the public, while genuine moderation in liquor indulgence is a personal attitude, unaffected by outside influence. Another plausible reason for denouncing Prohibition is that it leads people to become scornful of the law."</p>
   <p>Doctor Levi, besides being a spiritual leader, is also publisher of the Reform Advocate. He has devoted considerable time to the study of the Prohibition problem. He is also director of the Jewish Institute of Religion, is a member of the World's Fair Committee, and is connected with numerous other public organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
