<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-09-24">September 24th, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Commercialized Art.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1010</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1010.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-09-24">September 24th, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Commercialized Art.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Art in the United States seems to be nothing else but business. But if art is compelled to beg in the land of poets and thinkers(Germany), we can not blame the artists if they choose a more practical method in this country.</p>
   <p>When I saw the first American actor I was sadly disappointed. He did not possess the least traits, of idealistic, artistic geniality, which one easily recognizes in the German actor. When ever I met an actor in Germany on the streets, I could recognize him as such at a distance of 300 feet. On his smooth-shaved face was the expression of noble dignity and sublimity, and his waving hair hung on the sides of his head in artistic locks. He was extremely well dressed compared with ordinary mortals.</p>
   <p>But what about his American colleague? The latter is in appearance by far inferior. The average American is usually well dressed but the American actor looked uncleanly and carelessly dressed. Only the really eminent actors are an exception. The average actor lacks the artistic in his personality. There is no expression of idealism in his face. He looks like a business man or a <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1011.jpg" n="2"/>travelling salesman. He is fond of the American dollar like all business men.</p>
   <p>They like to boast of their triumphs, which are usually connected with high incomes. Their chief interest is in making dollars, just like any shrewd business men.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
