<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-09-18">Sept. 18, 1935</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1171</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1171.jpg" n="2"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-09-18">Sept. 18, 1935</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>these communities to compete with private enterprises.</p>
   <p>James W. Beck, former Solicitor General of the United States, has taken charge of the suit filed in the Supreme Court against the rights granted to the Tennessee Valley Authority.</p>
   <p>Thomas N. McCarter, chairman of the Board of Directors of the Edison Electric Institute, is president of the Public Service Corporation of New Jersey, which is known to be controlled by Morgan and Company.</p>
   <p>It is evident from these facts that the holding companies consider the fight against the law to be of prime importance. The corporations are sparing neither money nor talent in order to gain their object.</p>
   <p>Reading the statement made by Mr. Thomas McCarter, one is nearly convinced that the management of the utility companies was always of the highest quality and <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1172.jpg" n="3"/>that they are unjustly persecuted for political reasons. No one can deny that the power producing companies of the United States have rendered excellent services and have done their share toward developing industry, agriculture, and commerce. Nor will anyone deny the fact that they have contributed much to the living comforts enjoyed by farmers as well as by urbanites. However, it must not be overlooked that power companies have actually had a monopoly on their product and were enabled not only to acquire the means to defray the usual cost of operation, maintenance, and improvement, but also to amass huge sums of money which was frequently used to accomplish sinister purposes. Just think of Insull and his henchmen! And recently quite a few power companies decided to lower their rates, which, no doubt, is attributable to the activity of the Government and shows that these servants of the public can get along on a smaller income.</p>
   <p>In any event, it is a fact that no other branch of industry charges prices that are so disproportionate to the cost of material and labor. Astonishingly <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1173.jpg" n="4"/>large profits are involved.</p>
   <p>At any rate, let us hope that the decision of the Supreme Court will not be long forthcoming, so that the matter is cleared up; for nothing hampers business as much as uncertainty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
