<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-01-03">Jan. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Bar</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0095</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0095.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-01-03">Jan. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE BAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question being raised at the moment is: Shall it be forbidden to serve drinks at the bar to women? It is frequently the custom to make an issue of minor matters in order to divert general attention from the major issue. The real question is not whether women are to be allowed to frequent bars, but whether it is permissible to have bars in saloons. The city ordinance provides that alcoholic beverages may be dispensed only to customers who are seated. And so seats have been placed before bars. However, few persons will doubt that this was done merely to ignore a promise made during the fight against prohibition--the promise to prevent the return of the saloon.</p>
   <p>And it was only the bar that characterized the saloon and constituted an objectionable feature. There the bartender went about his work, though he was seldom content to mix and serve, but encouraged his customers to drink. If he <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0096.jpg" n="2"/>saw that a guest was about to leave, he quickly started another "round," and thus made an additional round obligatory. A favorite trick of bartenders was to introduce one customer to another; of course it was evident that the introduction was to be followed by the invitation, "Have a drink on me". Not only was it considered an insult to decline the invitation, but it was also considered obligatory to reciprocate. This "treating" was one of the worst evils of the bar, and it will return, whether the customers are seated or standing.</p>
   <p>How did our municipal legislators picture the situation in the event of insufficient seating accomodations for all customers? Were they really naive enough to believe that late arrivals would stand in back of occupied seats and patiently wait until a seat had become vacant? In that event we would soon see more customers standing than sitting, and all would be quenching their thirst with the precious liquid. Thus the road would soon be clear for the return of the old evils.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0097.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is only one way to prevent this, and that is to do away with the bar. Then the question of serving women would solve itself. Without the bar the saloon would be a fit place for female customers. In any event, that is the way the majority of those who united in the fight against prohibition must have pictured their proposed unobjectionable saloon.</p>
   <p>It almost seems as though certain politicians place special value upon retaining the bar. No doubt they intend to use the bar again as a snare to catch voters. Unfortunately, the bar is the rendezvous of a certain element that sells its vote for a few drinks. In addition, the co-operation of the bartender or saloonkeeper is obtained in this manner, and they have great influence upon this type of customer.</p>
   <p>If the bar is retained there will be an early change in the general attitude. That would be grist to the mills of the drys.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
