<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-11-07">Nov. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Church-Sponsored Saloon</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0256</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0256.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-11-07">Nov. 7, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHURCH-SPONSORED SALOON</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Prohibition has now become a law, and, according to its sponsors, the golden era--the millenium of morality--has now been ushered in. But apparently they do not quite trust their own prophecies. The "vicious" saloon has disappeared, to be sure, but in the hearts of prohibitionists there is fear that the longing for this social meeting place will sooner or later bring about its revival. And recently they have evinced an increasing desire to create an ersatz oasis to take the place of those which have disappeared from the desert of daily routine. This is especially true of the churches, whose hopes of winning as members the former customers of the saloonkeepers, and of seeing them troop in on Sunday mornings to attend services and to fed the church kitty have only been realized to a minor degree. These places of worship are now busily trying to work out satisfactory substitutes for the pleasures of which they themselves deprived us.</p>
   <p>The Episcopal Church is announcing, these days, that she will quench the thirst <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0257.jpg" n="2"/>of the people by opening up "saloons". These are to be institutions patterned after the familiar models of the pre-Prohibition period. And it is also announced that these "saloons" are going to be made as "wicked" as possible. What they mean by "wicked" remains to be seen. The meeting places which the church-sponsored "Temperance Society" plans to open are to be located, if possible, sible, in the former palaces of sin. The interior is not to be changed at all, customers can park their foot on a brass rail just as in a "real" saloon; they may confide their little troubles to the sympathetic ear of a whita-garbed bartender, tender, and, if it will make them feel any better, they may swear to their heart's content without violating the moral code of the church-saloon. Women, preachers in clerical garb, and curiosity seekers will not be admitted. Indeed, the ersatz will not be distinguishable in appearance and other aspects from the vicious drinking emporium which the prohibitionists have so successfully abolished.</p>
   <p>But, as in the case of all other substitutes, it must be said of this, too, that "the imitation is never as good as the original". The bar counter, the bartender, the pyramids of sparkling glasses, the mirror backgrounds, the brass spittoons, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0258.jpg" n="3"/>the colored posters, and the large paintings will all help to make the patrons feel at home again, but one thing will be missing: the drink with the Kick in it. Even the permission to play cards, to smoke, and to shake dice will not enable the customers to forget that the drinks served them are devoid of this Kick. For all those outward manifestations, to which the good church brothers attribute so much importance, were only incidental to the imbibing of those dearly loved, revitalizing drinks for which there is no substitute.</p>
   <p>"The meeting places which we are going to set up," declared Dr. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>, chairman of the above named Temperance Society, "are designed to give the "old timers" a substitute for those places which they have lost through the closing of the saloons. The younger generation will grow up without having become acquainted with the saloons, and therefore they will not notice their absence. But we have to take care of the elder ones. We realize that the limitations imposed by Prohibition will create disturbances of their daily routine. We have no doubt that the former customers of the saloonkeepers will feel at home in our establishments.</p>
   <p>But we do not think it is going to work out that way. The camouflaged saloon will <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0259.jpg" n="4"/>tend to reveal the disadvantages caused by Prohibition rather than to cover them up. This case will again prove the irrefutable truth: that for lost liberty there is no satisfactory substitute....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
