<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-03-10">March 10, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The New Course. the Municipal Administration Endangers the Existence of the German Clubs. Protest Movement Starts.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0534</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0534.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-03-10">March 10, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW COURSE. THE MUNICIPAL ADMINISTRATION ENDANGERS THE EXISTENCE OF THE GERMAN CLUBS. PROTEST MOVEMENT STARTS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the meeting called yesterday by the administration of the German Citizens' Union at the Bismark Hotel, about 150 persons attended, principally, representatives of German clubs and lodges. The ways and means were discussed how to oppose the new attitude of the City Council relating to the sale of alcoholic drinks at associations' club halls.</p>
   <p>Mayor Dunne, who has the power to give special permits for this purpose has refused to give his permission since last week. He explains that it was asked by the Grand Jury and he had promised to fulfill their wishes. The mayor declared that he was very sorry that the clubs had to suffer but he can't act otherwise until the courts decide otherwise. It would be very difficult to get a judicial decision as the city ordinance gives the mayor a free hand.</p>
   <p>Mr. Wilhelm Rapp, president of the German Citizen's Union,explained at the meeting the cause and purpose, and gave the chair to Mr. John Koelling. Several speakers like Jacob Willich, Ang. Luders, Ludwig Schindler, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0535.jpg" n="2"/>Felix Buschik, Leopold Neumann, Georg Pfeiffer, etc., spoke about the danger to the German clubs from the present course of the City Council. A surprise announcement of Mr. Hoechster of the Gymnastic Club was that a criminal action was started against the manager of the Northside Gymnastic Hall because he did not follow a police order on selling alcoholic drinks last Sunday at a concert in the Turner Hall. The special permit had been refused to him by the mayor. It was proposed to engage a prominent lawyer for a mandamus action. Mr. Fritz Gloganer mentioned that these proceedings could last for years. A much better way would be to agitate in the coming elections and only vote for such aldermen who bind themselves to vote for a change in the respective ordinance. If it however should be a state law it would take somewhat longer but also here success could be obtained in the end.</p>
   <p>It was resolved to hold a mass meeting in the Coliseum. The chairman was instructed to form a committee of twenty-five persons to make all arrangements. They should be informed of their nominations in the German newspapers tomorrow and should meet Monday night at 8 o'clock at a place also to be mentioned in the press.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0536.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Koelling also should form a committee of five to get lawyers' advice as to what chance would be obtained by the courts. All those outsiders who could be of any assistance are also invited to participate.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
