<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-06-13">June 13, 1871</date><title level="a">Session of the City Council</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0774</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0774.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-06-13">June 13, 1871</date><title level="a">SESSION OF THE CITY COUNCIL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As soon as the Chairman declared the session open Alderman Schmidt presented a petition from the German citizens of the north division of the city. (This petition protests against the Sunday law, first, because it violates personal freedom and is tyrannical: secondly because it is contrary to public opinion, constantly forces thousands of good citizens to break the law, and will always remain a dead letter: and thirdly because it is contrary to certain provisions of the Constitution of Illinois establishing freedom of conscience. The Illinois Constitution is quoted: "Nobody shall be forced to attend any religious service or any place of worship against his will, nor shall the law recognize any religious association, confession or kind of worship". The legislature is therefore petitioned to table the Sunday Ordinance, and at the same time threatened with the courts. Signed: Wm. T. Wallis, 16th Ward, Vocke 16th Ward, Louis Rodmeyer 20th Ward, Ernst Mattern 20th Ward, Peter Allmendingfer 20th Ward, Adolph Schoninger 17th Ward, Charles Greiner 18th Ward, George Oertel 20th Ward, John Herting, 19th Ward, and Georg Bender 16th Ward.)</p>
   <p>This petition was first sent to the Committee of Laws. However, on a motion to that effect, it was decided to debate it immediately.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0775.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Alderman Walsh called the Sunday Ordinance a nuisance and an injustice toward the poor people who were forced to spend Sunday with six or seven people in one room.</p>
   <p>Alderman Gill said there were not only Germans in Chicago. He was not particularly fanatical about keeping the Sunday holy, "however it should not be suffered that the Germans keep a saloon open next door to a church on Sunday. The Puritans founded the Republic, established freedom, and received the Germans with open arms. The Germans should therefore refrain from wanting to introduce European mores.</p>
   <p>Schaffner declared he had nothing against the Puritans, they had been all right at their time, only that time was over now.</p>
   <p>It is McGrath's deepest conviction that the law should be repealed in the interest of public order.</p>
   <p>Gardner said he held the Sabbath holy, and the people likewise. If the inns were kept open on Sunday the poisonous Bridewells would soon be glutted.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0776.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Montgomery declares himself sick and tired of the prejudices of zealots.</p>
   <p>Batterman (German) finds it very wrong of his colleague not to believe in the usefulness of the Sunday Ordinance.</p>
   <p>Knickerbocker says if one would put the question before the American people of Chicago he was convinced they would vote the Ordinance down.</p>
   <p>McCotter engaged in a veritable sermon about the sanctity of the Sabbath, which led to interruptions and great unrest. In his opinion it was the observation of the Sabbath that made the United States great, the consequences of its nonobservation one could see in the nations of Europe. It was, among other things, responsible for the misfortune of France.</p>
   <p>Finally the motion of Alderman Gill to return the question to the Committee of Licenses was defeated by eighteen votes against fifteen. Then Schintz moved to amend the Ordinance by striking out the words: "And that he will not keep open his bar or place for the sale of such liquors.......from 12 o'clock Saturday <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0777.jpg" n="4"/>night until 12 o'clock Sunday night". This amendment of Schintz was adopted by twenty votes against twelve. With that the battle was decided.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
