<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-08-11">August 11, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">Unwelcome Guests.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1056</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1056.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-08-11">August 11, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">UNWELCOME GUESTS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The investigations carried on by Congress, in regard to the Italian immigrants, reveal very disagreeable facts. The Italian immigrants possess such a low degree of culture and education, that the American workers, accustomed to a higher standard of living, can not compete with them. It is impossible for the Americans to stoop to such low levels of existence, as has been discovered by the congressional investigators, as for instance, living on refuse,being crowded together like animals, and knowing nothing about cleanliness.</p>
   <p>There can be no advantage to this country in letting these people come here. At best, they may contribute to bring about a condition of barbarism. If, in addition to this, one takes into consideration that these half-civilized people will have the right to vote a few years hence, and thereby help to decide the destiny of this country, one can not help but shudder as to the future entrusted in such hands.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1057.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A certain Anglo-American newspaper calls the Italians the "Chinese of the East." A law against immigration from Italy seems justified on the same basis as the one against Chinese.</p>
   <p>Such a procedure, however, can not be resorted to. Actions we permit ourselves against the Chinese, will not be permissible against the Italians. Italy wants to be treated with due respect. It considers itself as one of the "Great Powers." The Italian press has plainly indicated that the Italian Government will not tolerate a similar attitude as we assumed toward the Chinese. We have to admit in justice to the Italian Government that it tries its utmost to keep its dirty sons from our shores. It made emigration laws more severe, in order to remove inducements for emigrants. It is obvious, however, what little effect these measures have, because during this investigation even Italian workers are hired by contract and transported to the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1058.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Science must retrace its steps" was fittingly stated by a certain professor. Necessity compels us to be reactionary. Any severe measures applied against undesirable immigrants may seem cruel, and is in contradiction to the old traditions, which made America appear to be the paradise of the poor. Nevertheless, necessity demands protective legislation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
