<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-10">Apr. 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Eighteenth Amendment</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0295</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0295.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-10">Apr. 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE EIGHTEENTH AMENDMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although "the Constitution" and "constitutional rights" are terms which are familiar to everyone in our country, it may safely be said that ninety-nine out of a hundred persons who use these terms are not familiar with the document which is the basis of our form of government. However, this is not true of the Eighteenth Amendment; this recent addition to our "Magna Charta" enjoys a wider circle of readers than the most popular world history.</p>
   <p>The most recent Amendment is very brief. It consists of three paragraphs of which the first is the most important. The substance of the latter is: The manufacture, sale, transportation, and importation of intoxicating liquor is forbidden in the United States. This regulation seems to be very comprehensive, and sufficiently clear in its provisions to appear entirely adequate for its purpose. But one need not be a lawyer to know that at times the simplest wording of the paragraph of a law can cause serious complications. We refer <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0296.jpg" n="2"/>principally to the fast that the Amendment does not constitute an effective law and that it will not be effective until Federal laws which make its enforcement possible are enacted. The second paragraph makes it mandatory that the laws necessary for the enforcement of the Amendment must be made in joint sessions of the Senate and the House of Representatives, and not co-ordinately.</p>
   <p>As long as a medium of enforcing the Amendment is lacking, offenders cannot be punished or prosecuted under the law. Even the legality of seizing contraband is in question since the necessary right and power has not been to lawfully constituted authorities. If the Federal officials should attempt to take possession if spirituous liquors, they could be successfully resisted on the ground that private property may not be seized without due legal procedure. Neanwhile the constitutionality of the Amendment which, in intent, is contrary to American views and traditions, is still in question.</p>
   <p>Should its constitutionality be upheld, them the Federal Government, as well as the legislatures of most states, will very likely pass laws to ensure enforcement. But this kind of legislation night serve to complicate rather than to clarify <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0297.jpg" n="3"/>pertinent issues. One of the chief difficulties will emanate from answering the question, "What are intoxicating liquors?" The State of New York intends to legalize the manufacture and sale of beer and wine, and in a bill which has been placed before the Legislature at Albany "liquor" is defined as "all liquids containing more than one-half per cent of alcohol," and "intoxicating liquors" as "all liquors which contain more than three per cent of alcohol". The Supreme Court of Oklahoma decided that all spirits which intoxicate, and all spirits which are consumed to cause intoxication are "intoxicating liquors" in the sense of the Amendment. On the other hand, the Supreme Court of Texas declares that under no circumstances is beer to be considered an intoxicating liquor, and that the sale of beer should not be placed on the same level with the sale of liquors which are intoxicants. And the Appellate Court of New York upheld this definition. However, Idaho is apparently the paradise of the "drys," for its Courts declared that even "near beer" is to be considered "intoxicating". But Georgia excludes "near beer" from the category of intoxicants. Until now, beer which contains less than two per cent of alcohol has been considered "near beer". But in most states beer is looked upon as intoxicating. A bill which characterizes <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0298.jpg" n="4"/>all drinks which contain more than three per cent alcohol as intoxicating was reported favorably to the Illionis State Legislature yesterday. According to court decisions made in Georgia and Texas, all patent medicines which have an intoxicating effect are to be prohibited. Verment even went a step further, and includes all toilet articles which contain alcohol as dissolving or heeling in-gredients. In Idaho clear alcohol is not considered a intexicant. Georgia holds the opposite view, and in Missouri the courts decided (in line with the Local Option Laws) that all liquids which contain alcohol are to be considered intoxicating.</p>
   <p>This mass of evidence is sufficient to prove that, even though the next Congress is amenable, the path of the prohibition ist forces will not be smooth. Conditions in the United States have reached such a state that a man who carries certain beverages while traveling exposes himself in one state to the punishment which is meted out to drunkards, while in the next state the "water saints" will crown him with roses as one of their own. Furthermore, we fear that the enforcement of prohibition will make conditions worse, instead of better, and that the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0299.jpg" n="5"/>issues which may arise from the contradictions of the various state laws will cause much strenuous work for the courts, and will prove to be a "gold mine" for lawyers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
