<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-09-06">Sept. 6, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">The "Drys" and the New Congress</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0720</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0720.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-09-06">Sept. 6, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">THE "DRYS" AND THE NEW CONGRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The advocates of compulsory prohibition were not successful during the last Congress, but we must admit that these fanatics have a persistence that is worthy of a better cause, and no defeat discourages them.</p>
   <p>They are now busy making ready for a new onslaught on Congress. Preparations are being made under the leadership of the well-known Quaker, William Baxter, father of the infamous temperance law of Indiana, Z. G. Wallace, female general of the praying witches, and by other equally fanatic, untiring persons who were nominated at the last state convention of the temperance forces of Indiana. Measures are being taken to induce the praying sisters--and their keepers--in other states to collaborate.</p>
   <p>Their object is to obtain a mass delegation and to send an urgent petition to Congress. The text will be as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0721.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"As the sale of intoxicating beverages is injurious, and as the Government must prevent anything which is of a harmful nature, Congress should adopt the following measures:</p>
   <p>1) A commission should investigate the effect of the sale of intoxicants in the United States upon crime and poverty; upon the health, intelligence, diligence, and prosperity of the individual; and what relation the sale of intoxicants has to taxation and the general welfare of the nation.</p>
   <p>2) Congress should prohibit the importation of intoxicants.</p>
   <p>3) Congress should absolutely prohibit the manufacture and sale of intoxicants in the District of Columbia, in the territories, and wherever the Government has sole jurisdiction.</p>
   <p>4) Congress should forbid all public officials and civil servants, also the army and navy, to consume intoxicating drinks.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0722.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At present the male and female apostles of the water wagon make no further demands.</p>
   <p>They will, of course, collect thousands of genuine and fictitious signatures, and also the names of school children.</p>
   <p>The conduct of the "drys" is, obviously, sheer insanity, as all the above demands were presented to the last Congress. Even in the Republican Congress the "drys" were only able to effect the appointment of an investigation committee; the teeth were drawn even from this measure, because Congress provided that the "respectable" drinking element should also be taken into consideration. In the Republican house of representatives the bill did not pass even with this modifying amendment.</p>
   <p>And yet the "dry" fanatics imaging that they can make some headway in the new Congress, although the House of Representatives has a great Democratic majority.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0723.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Don't the "drys" realize that the opposition, the Democratic party, won last fall--mostly because the Democrats in the various states treated the "praying sisters" with more manly rigor than the Republicans?</p>
   <p>Don't the "drys" know that consenting to their demands would be suicidal to the Democratic party?</p>
   <p>But such is fanaticism--it knows no obstacles. It is therefore expedient that we keep watch over such persistent adversaries, even if the moment appears unsuited to their cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
