<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-17">Mar. 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Illusion or Reality</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1299</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1299.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-17">Mar. 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ILLUSION OR REALITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The pitcher goes to the well once too often," and the patience of the public endures until it is overtaxed. The organizations that derive their profits from operating public utilities and the shyster politicians who act as intermediaries between the directorates of those organizations and the respective political organizations, know from many years of experience that the average American public is so long-suffering that, at best, its attitude is often comparable to the stoic equanimity of a donkey, which may be useful, but is suspected of lacking prudence. However, even a donkey will become vicious and kick, if he is systematically maltreated and abused. After all, "long-ears'" situation is advantageous, inasmuch as societies for the prevention of cruelty to animals may be found everywhere, and they force offenders to give account of themselves before a judge. But there are no societies to prevent public utilities from <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1300.jpg" n="2"/>methodically mistreating the public, and if such useful agencies really do exist, the public, the judges, and other officers who have been appointed to promote the public weal are unaware of it, and they have no influence whatever. So in this case the donkey must help himself and hick. and he shares the experience of all mules. If he does not know how to kick, if he is timid, if he has not the correct temperament, peevish attitude will not will not do him much good. He receives a boating, or his food is decreased, or some other method of forcing him into submission is applied. But if he is a mule of firm character, he will proceed systematically when his patience has been exhausted, and answer every act of abuse, and even every attempt to mistreat him, with a well-intended and well-aimed kick in the belly. All who came into contact with such a donkey will treat him with due respect and beware of offending his dignity or of ridiculing him. Such a mule is not a true mule. He has asquired a certain amount of wisdom which places his standard of living upon a higher level.</p>
   <p>Out citizens find themselves in a situation which is somewhat similar to the living conditions of an abused donkey. It is true, they are not beaten and <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1301.jpg" n="3"/>flogged, or at lost only figuratively, and that hurts but a few sensitive souls; but some persons are, so to speak, jumping around on the noses, faces, and corns of our citizens who show their dissatisfaction with such treatment in no other way save by omitting an occasional hold of protest. And the guilty ones normally treat this impotent lamenting and seelding with a calm nose and an indifference which is characteristic of their moral clearvity. Only before elections which might result unfavorably for the and cause the for their political friends some inconvenience or trouble, do they put the policy--pardon me, I mean the citizens, or rather the voters--on the shoulder, in wing after his wishes and promise to redress everybody's grievance. And then election is a matter of the past, they forget all about the promises which they have made in the heat of the campaign. But if public opinion can be quieted in no other way, they begin a long-drawn-out and tedious investigation, and the course and result of such a political investigation may well be characterized by the phrase, "Much ado about nothing". They smile at one another knowingly, and everything remains as it was.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1302.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We do not wish to inquire whether or not the brisk activity into which the State Public Utilities Commission has plunged, according to newspaper reports, has any direct or indirect connection with the coning spring election. But it is certain that many citizens of Chicago were so surprised that they nearly keeled over when they heard that the Commission had ordered the gas company to show cause why the gas rates should not be brought down to the level which prevailed prior to August 1, 1918. One would sooner have expected Good Friday to fall on Easter Sunday than that the officials of the gas company would heed the wish of the citizens of Chicago. But close observers were not surprised, for it was just fourteen days ago that the information arrived that the Commission had indicated its reluctance to grant the streetcar company's request for an increase in fare rates.</p>
   <p>Even this report seemed too good to be true; nor has it been possible to verify it. And now hope for decreased gas rates is suddenly spread among our astonished fellow citizens. That must put the voters in a good humor, for it is said that anticipated joy is the greatest joy, even if the joy promised is not realized.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1303.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The donkey we have montioned, however, who has become worldly wise, knows of no anticipated joy. Anticipation of a warm stall and a promise that he will receive his ration of hay and oats does not do him any good. He sets great value on reality and is not enthusiastic about pleasures which are shown him from a distance and prove to be nothing but an illusion when one approaches. And the hopes and expectations concerning future decisions of the State Utilities Commission may also vanish into nothingness like a fata morgana. For the first hearing on the gas rate has been set for April 7, and the Commission's decision in the increase in streetcar fares may be longer in forthcoming. The city elections, as everybody knows, will be held on April 1. They have nothing to do with the Commission's decisions. Or have they? Or does the Commission fear that its existence is in danger?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
