<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1892-02-23">February 23, 1892</date>,
<title level="a">The Republicans and Prohibition.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0574</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0574.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1892-02-23">February 23, 1892</date>,
<title level="a">The Republicans and Prohibition.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Republicans finally have decided to state their real standpoint on Prohibition by publishing the following suggestions in their press:</p>
   <p>According to the Republican standpoint, the election precincts of each county should decide, whether the liquor trade should be allowed to exist or not. If the majority of precincts should decide for prohibition, the sale of liquor must be forbidden in the whole county. But if a majority of precincts is voting against prohibition, nevertheless the latter should be kept in existence in all precincts, which have voted dry. Furthermore in the wet townships, the county court shall have the right to turn down any application for a tavern license. All existing saloons or taverns in smaller townships should pay $500. - for a license, which in larger towns and cities must cost $1,000 - per year. Any offense against police regulations should cause the lawbreaking saloon, to lose the said license.-</p>
   <p>It must be clear now to anybody, that the Republican party always will be for the existence of prohibition laws, which have been rejected by the open-minded voters in most states. It will strengthen the standpoint of the Democrats, who <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0575.jpg" n="2"/>have learned to know, that prohibition itself is the principal reactionary weapon of the Republicans, who on this issue have blindly lost 2 election campaigns.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
