<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-07-13">July 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0072</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0072.jpg" n="2"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-07-13">July 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>as the law proposed in this bill. It is revolutionary, inasmuch as it completely abandons the attitude which has been considered fundamental, with reference to games of chance, since the days when the first laws of our state were written." The Governor adds a historical review, showing that every constitution of Illinois, adopted since 1848, contained laws against games of chance.</p>
   <p>One cannot accuse the head of our state of having acted rashly or narrow-mindedly when considering this matter. His conception is merely altogether wrong, in regard to theory as well as practice; it proceeds from the viewpoint of the reformer.</p>
   <p>Governor Horner states that the fact that an innovation is involved in the bill, is no reason for vetoing it. He admits that changes in conditions are accompanied by changes in our way of thinking and acting. However, he emphasizes that such changes do not justify the lowering of our moral standard.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0073.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Horner admits that there is a general inclination to gamble. In his opinion, however, this fact does not make the practice a virtue, and he claims that there is no truth in the assertion that games of chance cannot be suppressed. Furthermore, he says that gambling has often led to embezzlement and other crimes, with bad results for the gamblers. It is not necessary to review all the reasons he advanced for vetoing the bill in question. The following sentence is most significant: "We need not worry about persons whose desires are controlled by self-discipline, but society must protect its weak members who cannot resist practices that have bad consequences."</p>
   <p>That was the pet argument of the prohibitionists, too. Again and again they declared that prohibition was not intended for people who were moderate in the use of alcoholic beverages, but for habitual drunkards. They failed to notice that they were making the exception a rule, and the moral weakness of drunkards a standard of legislation. Nor were they cognizant of depriving the overwhelming majority of citizens who consume alcoholic liquors with <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0074.jpg" n="4"/>moderation of a natural right. They merely intended to make a special law for drunkards that would apply to everybody.</p>
   <p>They also ignored the fact that there were laws against the misuse of alcohol, laws to punish people who offended their fellow citizens by becoming intoxicated and failing to support dependents. These matters are, and have been, regulated by law, and the endeavors of the prohibitionists to protect drunkards against the misuse of alcohol were entirely superfluous. All the objections mentioned may be used also to refute the arguments of the Governor. The prohibitionists, too, had a false conception in regard to the duties of the state. It is not the duty of the state to improve the morals of its citizens or to protect them against temptation. If that is Governor Horner's idea, then in order to be consistent, he would have to advocate the reintroduction of prohibition.</p>
   <p>There is still another point that is worthy of note. By his veto Governor Horner has placed himself in opposition to a great majority of our citizens. A few months ago Mayor Kelly was re-elected by an overwhelming vote of these <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0075.jpg" n="5"/>citizens, therefore, he is fully qualified to act as their spokesman. Mayor Kelly has openly and energetically advocated the bill to legalize and license handbooks. The Governor has no right to disregard the will of the majority of the citizens of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Betting is permitted at race tracks but not outside of them. Does the location where the act is committed make the act itself legal or illegal? Where is the logic of such an assertion?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
