<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-11-28">November 28, 1871</date><title level="a">Paper Victories</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1131</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1131.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-11-28">November 28, 1871</date><title level="a">PAPER VICTORIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The mouthpieces of the Third or Reform Party find cause to gloat over quite a number of victories in the October and November elections of this year. The election in New York - a victory of the Liberal Reform Party; the election of the Democrat Parker as Governor of New Jersey - a Liberal victory; the defeat of the Democrats in Wisconsin - again a victory of the Liberals... In short, whatever the outcome of any election, it was always the mysterious Third Party that determined it...All that is lacking, that the victory of the so-called "fire-proof" ticket in Chicago also would be proclaimed, is a victory of the Liberals.</p>
   <p>The "Fostschritt" (editor Ernst Schierenberg) in Jefferson City, addresses itself to the Liberals: Win a few more such victories, and then use them as the so-called Liberal Republican victory in Missouri last year was used; then every German, not only in Missouri but in the whole United States will know what to expect from you. You may be able to convince some of the Anglo-Americans that Mr. Carl Schurz carries 500,000 German votes in his pocket.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1132.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The eyes of most of then have been opened long since, and before the time of the election comes it will be shown that Schurz, in spite of his eminent talents, so far from being able to deliver 500,000 votes, cannot even pull 5,000. That he is pulling the old Democrats (whom he used to tell so many bitter truths) with him, he will not dare to assert. They, rather, are pulling him. The blind man's buff that the Republican proposes, and that the Westliche Post so zealously defends, namely the election of a backsliding Republican like Gartz Brown, through Democratic votes and for Democratic purposes, will not profit you. You have shown your cards too early, and you know that your game is lost...</p>
   <p>Perhaps there opens a chance for the Liberals to use their little strength in New York where Oswald Ottendorfer, over night, has become a great man and is reorganizing the Democratic Party. The whole wagon is to be repaired and reconstructed, repainted and refurbished that it will hardly be recognizable any longer. Driver, the Liberals could not become, but perhaps passengers. As such Mr. Schurz and his hangers-on will always be welcome to the new <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1133.jpg" n="3"/>Democrats, and if they then want to proclaim the victories of the Democratic Party as their own, nobody will grudge them the childish diversion. It will amuse them, and not hurt the Democrats.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
