<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-08-13">Aug. 13, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">Report on Second Anti-Temperance Meeting of Delegates of German Societies by H. von Langen (Secretary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0065</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0065.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-08-13">Aug. 13, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">REPORT ON SECOND ANTI-TEMPERANCE MEETING OF DELEGATES OF GERMAN SOCIETIES by H. von Langen (Secretary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following Societies were represented by delegates: Chicago Arbeiterverein: J. Bartell, J. Gruenhut, Mr. Hack, Mr. Kunze, L. Sievers.</p>
   <p>Socialer Arbeiterverein: J. Berndt, J. Lobstein, Christ Hardoe, Eduard Herbertz, Christ Schroeder.</p>
   <p>Chicago Turngemeinde: A. Erbe, J. Standau, P. Hand.</p>
   <p>Aurora Turnverein: A. Sohn, J. Michael, H. von Langen.</p>
   <p>Union Turnverein: F. Hoecken, L. Oberndorf, G. Schoefer.</p>
   <p>Turnverein Vorwaerts: Wilhelm Gottfried, F. Knepper, L. Flint.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0066.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Brewers' Association: H. B. Miller, G. Schmidt, C. Seipp.</p>
   <p>Germania Saengerbund: E. Dietzsch, T. J. Bluthardt, J. Claussenius.</p>
   <p>Mr. Bartell who was appointed chairman opened the meeting.</p>
   <p>The minutes of the previous meeting were approved as read.</p>
   <p>The committee appointed to find a suitable hall reported that Crosby's Hall was available for any evening of this and next week for $150.</p>
   <p>P. Hand moved that this hall be chosen for the mass meeting. The report amended by Mr. Hand's proposal was adopted.</p>
   <p>J. Standau moved that the meeting be held next Saturday evening, August 17; this motion was adopted.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0067.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Standau and Mr. Hertwig presented two resolutions to the committee on resolutions. The committee was instructed to confer with the chairman and the speakers to determine the contents and wording of suitable resolutions.</p>
   <p>C. Dietzsch, and H. B. Miller were added to the membership of the committee on resolutions.</p>
   <p>The speaker's committee reported that it had invited Mr. Raster, Mr. Juessen, Mr. Arnold, and Mr. Siebold to address the meeting and that these gentlemen had accepted the invitation. The report was adopted.</p>
   <p>Dr. Schmidt happened to be present and was unanimously elected to act as chairman at the mass meeting.</p>
   <p>The committee on organization proposed the following men as vice-chairman: Caspar Butz, Hans Balatka, Johann George Gindele.....[The names of thirty-three <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0068.jpg" n="4"/>additional men are listed--all of them prominent in German social, business, and professional life.]</p>
   <p>On the recommendation of P. Hand, J. Standau and H. von Langen were chosen to act as secretaries.</p>
   <p>A. Erbe moved that a committee of three be elected to engage the services of a band. The motion was adopted and the following were chosen: C. Seipp, F. J. Bluthardt, and E. Dietzsch.</p>
   <p>The delegates also resolved to ask the co-operation of the choruses of the Chicago Arbeiterverein and the Chicago Turngemeinde.</p>
   <p>The committee on organization was instructed to advertise the meeting in the newspapers and by posters.</p>
   <p>After Mr. J. Hertwig's action in publishing an invitation to the meeting in this newspaper had been approved, adjournment was noted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
