<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-07-01">July 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The King Is Dead--Long Live the King!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0263</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0263.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-07-01">July 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE KING IS DEAD--LONG LIVE THE KING!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to plan, without disturbance or opposition of any kind, war prohibition went into effect at midnight.</p>
   <p>What was held to be impossible several years ago, and was regarded as foolish only a few months ago, has actually come to pass--Chicago, which was once so "wet," has became "dry," was made "dry," through the so-called war prohibition law after the war had been formally terminated by the signing of the peace treaty. And the citizens of the metropolis, of the West, who only a few month ago voted against prohibition by a great majority, have weekly submitted to the law, which they declare to be foolish and very unjust, and which appears to be a mockery of the such-lauded American freedom, since it ruthlessly curtails the liberty of American citizens. Chicago not only submitted to the foolish and very unjust law, but, during the last hours in which it was free to drink, the city also acted as though it were celebrating a great victory and spent large sums of money to observe the dying hours of the king.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0264.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Everything is topsy-turvy. In other instances of death, mourning is usually followed by a "comforting" drinking party, which often takes on the appearance of a festive spree. But in this case the spree preceded the mourning--and today the merrymakers will feel the results. It is said that nearly a thousand citizens who once enjoyed their freedom, were arrested for drunkeness--and, no doubt, only flagrant violaters were taken into custody--and this thousand, and several more thousands who celebrated in like manner, will enjoy a good hangover. And their pleasure may help them to endure the shame which every good citizen of this country feels now that war prohibition has become a reality. The physical misery which followed their intemperance will cause them to think that there is a good reason for prohibition--the nausea caused by overindulgence in intoxicants has made many a prohibitionist.</p>
   <p>The patience of the American public was a cause for astonishment even before the War, and it has since given strong proof that it is genuine....</p>
   <p>Youth is quick to judge. It has the tendency to view only one side of a matter. There can be no doubt that the American public is patient, patient <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0265.jpg" n="3"/>as a lamb (patient as a sheep would be too harsh a term for such lovable patience). Yet the way in which Chicago took leave of King Alcohol yesterday indicates that something else entered into consideration. According to press and police reports there were thousands of mourners; all saloons were filled to capacity throughout the afternoon and evening. But the crowds were good-humored and, though much liquor was consumed, there was no thought of disturbance or violence. There was less scolding than laughing, and for every angry or threatening word, there were a hundred jokes. There was more self-ridicule than condemnation of others, and there was little mourning for King Alcohol or, as Americans are wont to call him, "John Barleycorn". Had he been justly tried, found guilty, and condemned, if justice, righteousness, and common sense had not been violated, and if the persons who stood to incur great losses had been offered adequate compensation after just deliberation on the issue and situation, there would be but a very few people in Chicago or in the whole United States who would mourn the loss of "whiskey freedom". For experience teaches that whiskey is harmful and dangerous when it is used as a beverage--and all this Chicago knows, as did the many thousands who took leave of John Barleycorn yesterday, and they said, "Away with this <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0266.jpg" n="4"/>harmful drink!"</p>
   <p>The thought that God still lives and that America will not lose her happiness nor be permantly deprived of her liberty--though matters look very dark at present--may have been, and perhaps was, a contributing factor to the gay mood of the happy throng. Life here will not become as melancholy and empty as it seems. Something else will be substituted for the outlawed John Barley-corn--if he is not resurrected; other pleasures will be enjoyed, and it would be queer if this "something" did not turn out to be an improvement, for progress is our slogan!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
