<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-05-05">May 5, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">Retaliation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-05-05">May 5, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">RETALIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As far as the "Free-traders" are concerned, the United States should be sufficiently meek and tolerant to be kicked and slapped by every other country and smile on top of it. All of Europe may refuse entrance for our most important export commodities or they may charge such excessively high rates of import duty on our goods that exporting such goods becomes nearly impossible, yet our Free-traders smile most submissively, and make a sour face toward those who demand retaliation for such malicious hostility.</p>
   <p>President Cleveland and his Secretary Bayard, have clearly proven by their weak attitude toward Canada, that they are in accord with the Free-traders in this respect, and that they rather suffer injustice than to do wrong. If the United States does not wish to become absurd and ridiculous in the eyes of European nations of even secondary rank, Congress must <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1383.jpg" n="2"/>pass a law immediately to empower the President to retaliate against hostile measures and regulations of other nations with effective counter-measures. Germany as well as France has forbidden the import of such of our farm products, which are undesirable from a competitive standpoint, and they have done so under obvious pretense. To reply to such maliciousness with modest requests and remonstrations, instead of taking stern counter-measures is nothing else but evidence of weakness and pusillanimity. As long as our Government has not the courage to regulate their foreign trade on reciprocal lines, the insolence of foreign nations toward the United States will steadily increase in regard to these matters. And why not? Whoever can not defend his own rights, can not expect anything better than lashes. Uncle Sam has taken over the role of the meek sheep, because he takes the insult of other nations with a smile, and blesses those that curse him.</p>
   <p>During the last few days Mr. Schurz had the opportunity to discuss matters freely with the Iron Chancellor Bismarck... It is very doubtful, however, if Mr. Schurz took advantage of this opportunity to tell Bismarck that his assertions of friendship towards the United States are not corroborated <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1384.jpg" n="3"/>by his deeds. Indeed, Mr.Schurz could have done more for the land of his choice than all the others, President Cleveland, Bayard, and Pendleton together.</p>
   <p>It appears that present conditions will remain unchanged, perhaps for a long time to come. We will import from Germany 70 to 80 million dollars worth of goods, and Germany will refuse to permit importation of our farm products.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
