<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-01">Sept. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Labor Day, 1918</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1582</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1582.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-01">Sept. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LABOR DAY, 1918</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Twenty-five years ago, when the unions, which had only a limited membership at the time, staged their parade, their motives were very often questioned, and the newspapers paid them scant attention. Tomorrow, however, when the armies of organized labor, now over three million strong, march in their "Win the War" parade, even those who formerly fought against the unions' objectives will cheer. This change in public opinion has been accomplished over the years by steady agitation, education, and organization, and has been considerably furthered since last year by the willingness of organized labor to enter the fight for democratic ideals.</p>
   <p>Organized labor has not been content with lip service to prove its patriotism. Its unreserved support of the Government during the present crisis <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1583.jpg" n="2"/>is the best reply to any questioning of its loyalty, and harmonizes with the attitudes of men and women who cherish republican ideals. They have all realized that if a government based on these ideals should perish, every American citizen worthy of the name would suffer a personal loss. Organized labor differentiates between a government which is subject to the whims of a single man or a small group of men, and a government of, by, and for the people.</p>
   <p>The celebration of Labor Day, 1918 will emphasize the difference between the two systems of government which are struggling for supremacy at the present time. The ideas on which these systems are based are older than any nation. Indeed, the emergence of nations is a mere incident, a stage in the struggle for human liberty and enlightenment against an obsolete theory of government such as that which is so arrogantly represented by the German Junkertum [landed Prussian nobility].</p>
   <p>Organized labor is not a peace movement. While we hope to see the day when <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1584.jpg" n="3"/>differences between capital and labor will no longer disturb our industry, we refuse to compromise our efforts by denouncing the right to strike against injustice when other methods have failed. In a broader sense, this theory can also be applied to our government when it calls for union against the principles of autocracy, which endanger the majority rule basic to our system of government.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
