<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-11">June 11, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The Governor Acts</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1276</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1276.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-11">June 11, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE GOVERNOR ACTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In some respects Governor Horner has not proved to be the strong man that a part of the electorate thought him to be. This is partly owing to the fact that he has always been a loyal member of the Democratic party, and has become used to following the party even in cases when he does not think the decisions of its leaders are right. Such a man is very valuable to the party, but the voter likes to have as Governor a man who not only can think for himself, but who also defends his ideas without anxiously considering his party when he is convinced that his own ideas will serve the public interest better than the proposals of the party. In this respect, the past administration of Governor Horner has been a disappointment to many of his followers.</p>
   <p>To then it is welcome news that he is insisting upon a reduction of utility <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1277.jpg" n="2"/>rates and that he has sent a message to the legislature demanding the enactment of a law which will grant the Commerce Commission wider powers in dealing with the utility corporations.</p>
   <p>For months, the consumers of was, electricity, etc. have been complaining that the rates are much too high is view of present living conditions; yet no action has been taken heretofore. Since the utility companies evidently wanted to see how long they could overcharge the public, it is high time that Governor Horner prod them a bit. Perhaps they will now take some voluntary action.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
