<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-12-09">December 9, 1907</date><title level="a">United Societies for Local Self-Government.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0495</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0495.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-12-09">December 9, 1907</date><title level="a">UNITED SOCIETIES FOR LOCAL SELF-GOVERNMENT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting was called by the United Society for Local Self Government, to establish the battle program for individual liberty. The propaganda made in the south by the Prohibitionists not only ruins the existence of the saloon keepers and clubs associations, but menaces the activities of all immigrants and especially the Germans. The great English press denounces already all liberals as criminals. Mr. Nicholas Michel opened the well attended meeting as chairman of the South Side Turner Hall on State Street. Mr. John Koelling, President of the United Society for Local Self Government said that we immigrated to the United States to be in a free land, in which to live an independent free life. We appealed to the liberal element of the population and the majority have joined our ranks. Our oppressors are also very active and therefore we must battle on. Eternal vigilance is the price of liberty.</p>
   <p>Mr. George Pfeiffer spoke about the fanaticism of a small minority group and the cowardice of the politicians. The closing of the saloons is only the first <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0496.jpg" n="2"/>foreigner-hating fanatics and to fight them with all our might.</p>
   <p>Resolved that we continue to demand from the legislature of the State of Illinois the repeal or change of the old fashioned puritan Sunday laws.</p>
   <p>Thanks were given to Mayor Busse for his brave cooperation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
