<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-05-15">May 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">After Twenty-Five Years</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0278</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0278.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-05-15">May 15, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">AFTER TWENTY-FIVE YEARS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tempora mutantur--times change, and man also changes. This is one of many proverbs, or figures of speech which are only conditionally true, or which set forth the opposite of that which is really true. Indeed, it is said that the people's voice is God's voice, but, good heavens, how many foolish things have "people" not already said and done! People do not actually change with conditions, but people themselves effect changes in conditions.</p>
   <p>I have lived in the United States of America exactly twenty-five years, and what men have made of this "Land of the Free and Home of the Brave" during this comparatively short period of time!</p>
   <p>When I came to this country there was still a general spirit of freedom which was enjoyed by everyone. This spirit of freedom was appreciated by everyone who had shed the narrow-mindedness of European countries. The whole viewpoint was wider and more liberal. "Live and let live" was the guiding principle at <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0279.jpg" n="2"/>that time. It was possible for laborers and middle-class people to establish their own homes, and to enjoy life; at that time the rich did not despise the poor. But how vastly different are conditions today!</p>
   <p>What has happened to the days when the laborer could afford to take a roast chicken to work in his lunch box, as he did twenty-five years ago? Where is the butcher who gave his customers the lard to fry their steak? How many workers in our day can save enough money within a few years to build a home?</p>
   <p>It is said that the accursed War is to blame for high prices. But that is not so, at least, it is only partly true. The War merely climaxed a development which began many years before the outbreak of hostilities.</p>
   <p>The true internal causes of the gradual and general increase in the cost of living may be found in the internationalization of the United States and in the establishment of great American trusts. By internationalization I mean general participation by the United States in world commerce, which necessarily resulted in the adjustment of our economic affairs to those of other countries, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0280.jpg" n="3"/>especially Europe. And by the establishment of trusts I mean the disruption of the entire economic life of our country by combinations of large corporations that grasp everything for themselves and begrudge the "little man" even a meager living.</p>
   <p>Is it not the height of insanity that one man (like the elder Rockefeller) should possess nearly two billion dollars? What possible need can he have for all that money?</p>
   <p>To a sensible person money is valuable only insofar as it will enable him to enjoy life. But this advantage is only a side issue to the capitalists; they look upon money as a means of acquiring power; they want to rule, and they have managed to attain their goal. The course of our whole political life is directed from Wall Street in New York. Our economic life is regulated and governed by the great corporations, and no bill of any importance is passed without their approval.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0281.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We poor gullible nobodies imagine that we exercise some influence upon the course of events in our country when we cast our votes! As though our election laws themselves were not formed so as to make the results of elections and the selection of candidates for political offices dependent upon the control of the "big-money men". And the primary elections, in which every businessman must declare himself for one or the other party, are fashioned to serve just that purpose. And that is what is called "secret ballot"! The regular election, indeed, is secret, but, to the individual voter the nomination of a candidate is more important, as a rule, than his election, and the nomination is not secret.</p>
   <p>How few citizens of German descent recognize the fact that the little ward clubs are the most influential of all political organizations, and that they should, therefore, support such organizations.</p>
   <p>Among the bylaws of choral groups, benevolent societies, beer clubs, card clubs, dance clubs, lodges, etc., there is usually one which bars politics.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0282.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>If I had way, all these societies would have to embody within their constitutions a rule which would make it incumbent upon every member to do his full duty as a citizen at all times--and not only at the time of the regular elections.</p>
   <p>Apparently, prohibition will soon be enforced. Well, how about changing the old eleventh paragraph to make it read: "The Attorney General of the United States of America is hereby discharged from the duty of prosecuting offenders, etc.?"</p>
   <p>Who would have thought of general prohibition twenty-five years ago? Of course, in those days, too, there were people who preached the gospel of "the water without which there is no salvation," although Doctor Martin Luther said, "It is not the water, indeed, that saves".</p>
   <p>We sympathize with the people of those days; we think that they were "queer," and that some of them had a "screw loose". I do not know just when Carrie Nation was active. Good soul, she has been resting in Heaven for some <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0283.jpg" n="6"/>years, and I hope that she is enjoying her non-alcoholic nectar.</p>
   <p>Now these "water apostles" want to make us believe that the majority of the voters in our country are in favor of dictating--in this "Land of the Free"--what their fellow citizens should drink. And an addition, which is called an "amendment," has been made to our Constitution--the Constitution which was devised by the founders of this Republic as an eternal and immovable bulwark of personal freedom and the dignity of man.</p>
   <p>Anyone who believes that this bowdlerization was not brought about through the support of great corporations is badly mistaken. They want to deprive the worker of the use of alcohol so that they may derive greater dividends from their stock. It would be most unfortunate if they were mistaken! In this connection I am reminded of a very intelligent farmer who tried to wean his horse from eating by withholding its food. Several weeks after he had begun the "cure," a neighbor asked him if it were successful. The farmer complained that just when the horse stopped eating, it died. Perhaps those of our fellow citizens who now claim to be "genuine" Americans, and who consider <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0284.jpg" n="7"/>themselves "too good" to do manual labor, will again learn to work in the mines, on the right of way of railroads, or around smelting furnaces, when the inhabitants of Southern Europe, who do not care to sacrifice their wine, decide to remain in their native countries. No more need these Yankees cry for further immigration legislation, because prohibition will protect them against "undesirable" foreigners.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, many of our honorable citizens seem to think that personal liberty and the liquor issue are identical. Give them the right to drink whatever, and as much as they wish, and they believe that they possess personal freedom in the fullest sense of the term, and so are content. Since the liquor question seems to have been disposed of, or perhaps, because the battle for the right to drink has been entrusted to a committee of lawyers, one hears practically nothing about our Associated Societies for the Preservation of Personal Liberty. Was that the only object and aim of this organization? Such an admission would be a confession of pitiable narrow-mindedness.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0285.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>It was different in bygone days. Then, great mental and spiritual alertness was fostered by the various Turnvereine (gymnastic societies); there was great eagerness to attain higher ideals. I recall with great pleasure the battle which the Turnvereine of Chicago fought against the taxation of church property. And although they were not successful, since the opposition was much too powerful, the mere attempt was a gratifying indication of spiritual activity. Today everything seems to be dead.</p>
   <p>And yet, the Turners now have a special opportunity to assert themselves. In Washington authorities are discussing the question: Is general compulsory military service preferable to a standing army of half a million soldiers? A Turner has no voice in this matter. It was just the general physical education and development of our people that the Turnvereine aimed at. By advocating general compulsory military service they are merely acting in accordance with the principles which they have adopted. But, let it be clearly stated that we advocate general compulsory military service solely for the purpose of developing the bodies of our youths, not for the purpose of teaching them the art of murdering their fellow men.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0286.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Why do we need an army of half a million men? At Paris the constitution of the League of Nations has just been drawn up, and soon the time of eternal peace will be at hand--at least so it is reported. Twenty-five years ago America was proud of having an army of only twenty-five thousand men. At the time of the Spanish-American War our imperialist policies began increasing, resulting in even more entanglements, and making a constant enlargement of our armed forces necessary.</p>
   <p>Of course our friends, the great corporations, favor a large army. As to the physical development of the people, what do they care about that? But a standing army might be of service to the citizens, when they tire of the oppression which the capitalists exercise.</p>
   <p>When I came to this country the old Germans used to tell of the time when Germans had no influence in America. That was before the Franco-Prussian War. We who arrived here after this War were astute enough to notice that in those days the respect accorded Germans in America was the result of the recent German victories. Certainly the Germans in this country had played <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0287.jpg" n="10"/>no part in the winning of this recognition. They were still unable to win it, despite the fact that they had done much for their adopted land. And now? Americans of German descent can no more bask in the glory of that once powerful empire, for it has vanished. The esteem in which they were held at one time by their fellow citizens has turned to hatred of everything that originated in German soil, and English propaganda is still busy stirring up ill will against them. Now Americans of Teutonic origin must earn that respect for themselves, unless they wish to live on in disrespect. Will they, who before the War, knew how to boast of their accomplishments, but did little or nothing to demonstrate them, now calmly sit idle, while others do their duties as citizens? Only by conscientiously performing required tasks can they hope to regain that lost prestige. If they do not set forth every effort to do so, then they deserve to be trampled upon, and people will have a right to say that Germans have no character.</p>
   <p>"Only beggars are modest," says the German poet. However, there are exceptions, as, for instance, the conscienceless bums who have the impertinence to thrust themselves upon us as leaders of Germanism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
