<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1874-01-29">Jan. 29, 1874</date>.
<title level="a">Evanston's War against the Germans.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1101</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1101.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1874-01-29">Jan. 29, 1874</date>.
<title level="a">EVANSTON'S WAR AGAINST THE GERMANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is hardly to be found in Illinois a city as saintly, as much addicted to the Bible, as pious as Evanston, If in a city wish as many churches and prayer houses, halos of saints do not as yet grow on the skulls of its inhabitants, for that, wicked Chicago is probably responsible. Sham, sanctity, and hypocrisy, secret vices, and immorality flourish in this little clean nest and the Chicago Times published last Sunday an article, telling how a Reverend was turning several virgins of his parish into young women and is now awaiting the decision of the court; but the Staats Zeitung would not pay any attention to that, for such stories and such pious dirt can be found any day in the American bible camp; but it may not be known to all the readers that many good Germans are living in Evanston and especially in the surrounding neighborhood as Rosehill and Gross Point. It is probably even less known that in Evanston a mob of fanatics is persecuting the Germans and Irish in every manner.</p>
   <p>Of course there are no saloons in Evanston, although every one there drinks his own whiskey; in the the three drug stores, brandy and whiskey can be had at exorbitant prices upon presentation of medical prescription; later the patient with <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1102.jpg" n="2"/>his biblepale face receives his drink also without a prescription.</p>
   <p>Recently, two Germans there, one of whom has a cigar store, the other a bakery and both of whom have permission to serve cider, were placed on trial on account of the paid for testimony of an American scamp who claimed that 2 glasses of this cider had made him drunk; also two saloon keepers from Gross Point are on trial under the same circumstances.</p>
   <p>As the so called university in Evanston, independently passed a law that no saloons were allowed within a circuit of 4 miles, the saloon keepers are persecuted in every manner. This stupid law or charter is of course void. Then the saloon keepers who have their taverns in Rose Hill and Gross Point had them before the university of the fanatics was ever built.</p>
   <p>Let him who wants to know about the Evanston saints inquire at the Chicago Wholesale Liquor Stores. There he will find out what a tremendous business is done with Evanston. One can state that no where does the secret whiskey drinker flourish more than in Evanston. May parents consider seriously before sending their children to a school where nothing is done scientifically and where the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1103.jpg" n="3"/>dangers of secret vice are so close.</p>
   <p>One of the heroes of the Evanston saints, is a little paper, the Evanston Index which is nothing but a spitoon of the Reverends.</p>
   <p>It is to be hoped that the Germans there will get together, start a club and fight their enemies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
