<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-07-01">July 1, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Rear Guard Action</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-07-01">July 1, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">REAR GUARD ACTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Military strategists claim that a [well organized] retreat is the best criterion of an army commander's ability. If this also holds true in the field of political strategy, then the leadership of the "drys" has been grossly overestimated. When the voting on repeal began (or, more correctly, at the time of the elections to the state conventions), the Honorable James Cannon, Methodist Bishop, general chief of staff of the "dry" forces and coregent of the former president, declared that the first election returns did not mean anything, and that only the results in Indiana would indicate the trend of things. Dr. F. Scott McBride, field marshal of the "dry" armies, was of the same opinion.</p>
   <p>The election returns in Indiana indicated grave defeat for the "drys" in that state. Whereupon their leaders belittled the importance of the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0141.jpg" n="2"/>returns from Indiana, and pointed out that the state of Iowa would really reveal the sentiment of the people. When there, too, the election favored the anti-Prohibitionists, Bishop Cannon staked his hopes on the election in West Virginia, only to experience another disappointment. Now these good fellows are concentrating on Arkansas. They will do this same thing with every state in the Union before they get through.</p>
   <p>It is evident that these events will undermine their reputation as prophets. However, their strategy is not quite as stupid as it would seem. They are covering the whole country all right, but a good old German proverb says: "Mit dem Hute in der Hand Kommst Du durch das ganze Land" (With your hat in your hand, you can bum your way through the land). In this case, too, the hat is the main thing. As long as there are states left which have not yet voted on the repeal, the generals of the "dry" army can pass the hat and collect money for the Eighteenth Amendment and the holy cause of abstinence. That is their main purpose, anyway.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0142.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The other wing of the "dry" army is made up of the Women's Christian Union, which has its headquarters in our neighboring city of Evanston. Now Evanston used to be a highly moral community, but since the City Council there has given beer the legal status, the city has lost that reputation.</p>
   <p>The Temperance ladies at least display courage. They have dared to enter the lion's den by holding this year's National Convention in Milwaukee, which was the stronghold of the brewing industry during the pre-Prohibition era, and which is now making great efforts to regain that reputation. But then again it could have been a sort of grim sense of humor which prompted the "dry" sisterhood to convene in the beer city.</p>
   <p>The ladies disapprove of President Roosevelt and his administration. They were painfully shocked when the President openly favored repeal of the Eighteenth Amendment and even asked Democratic politicians to go to bat for the success of the repeal campaign. By this act, according to the sisterhood, the President far exceeded his constitutional prerogatives.</p>
   <pb n="4"/>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0143.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>They did not demand exactly that he be removed from office and sent into exile, but they made it quite clear that they would hail such proceedings with great rejoicing.</p>
   <p>They probably lost track of the fact that the Democratic party has incorporated the repeal of the Eighteenth Amendment in its platform, and that the President, as the titular head of his party, was morally obligated to keep this promise. They also criticize the administration for dismissing a part of the Prohibition enforcement personnel, although this was done only to conform to its program of economy. According to their opinion, the administration may econimize on everything except expenditures for the enforcement of Prohibition.</p>
   <p>In former years the conventions of the "dry" ladies receivd much attention in the press, and detailed accounts about the proceedings were published. THis year the convention of the Christian Temperance Union is grievously ignored. The newspapers act as if Prohibition were already dead and buried<pb facs="5418474_2_1_0144.jpg" n="5"/>and they are right, because it really makes not the slightest difference what the "dry" leaders, male and female, have to say or resolve. They simply do not possess any talent for leadership. Since the passing of Wayne B. Wheeler, who for years was the real head of the "dry" movement and the shrewdest politician of his time, all that the "dry" leaders can do is travel around with a collection plate and a lot of big talk. And the public is not interested in that.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
