<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-02">Sept. 2. 1918</date>.
<title level="a">On Labor Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1579</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1579.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-02">Sept. 2. 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ON LABOR DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Labor Day 1918" belongs to all the world. It will be celebrated not only by the three million members [in the ranks]of organized labor in this country, but [also by the workers]in all other countries where the armies serving industry and commerce have attained recognition and respect for themselves. Especially for the thirty-five million workers in the United States will Labor Day have a new significance.</p>
   <p>The first Labor Day was celebrated on September 5, 1882, and the small number of men and women who originated it could hardly have realized the influence the parade they established would have in the course of time..... Since that day, thirty-six years have gone by, and where once twenty thousand marched, today hundreds of thousands will fall in line. The principles of true democracy, for which our sons in arms are fighting <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1580.jpg" n="2"/>today on European battlefields, find among the men in uniform, who were former laborers, their most ardent and zealous champions, since in the ranks of organized labor there was at no time a place for discrimination against race, religion, or nationality. Its principal motto always has been: "One for all and all for one." That is why we find in the ranks of labor the fullest approval and understanding for the aims and objectives that the American people are striving after in the present war. They have enthusiastically offered to serve the government that adheres to the maxim: "The most satisfactory government is the one in which an unjustice to the individual is an injustice to all."</p>
   <p>Labor Day has long since become a national holiday and this [i.e., that it is a national holiday]is especially true of the one we are celebrating today. It will demonstrate in a most convincing manner the unity of the American people, whether its sons are fighting over there with arms or over here with hammer and shovel. They all belong to the same army and everyone of them is fighting for the welfare and liberation of mankind from brute force and oppression. In this spirit, Labor Day 1918 is a <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1581.jpg" n="3"/>milestone on the road of human progress, and countless multitudes are passing by it with a silent prayer in their hearts for an early peace, then to return to the factories and work shops, or to face the trenches on the battlefields, in order to make "peace on earth" a reality in the near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
