<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-05-08">May 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Snooping Law before State Legislature</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0288</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0288.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-05-08">May 8, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">SNOOPING LAW BEFORE STATE LEGISLATURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the coming week and the one following, a great battle will be fought in Springfield, and the outcome will decide the legality of the old English adage "A man's house is his castle". On May 14 or 21, the lower house of the state legislature will vote on the notorious bill which provides that homes may be searched for spirituous liquors, and that, if found, the liquors may be seized. If this bill is passed, the citizens of this state will be deprived of more of their personal freedom. For then nobody will be safe against having the peace of his home disturbed by whisky or beer snoopers. The law itself opens the door for them. The emissaries of those narrow-minded clergymen will be able to enter homes upon mere suspicion, at any hour of the day or night, and slanderers will have full sway. There is still hope that the legislators in Springfield will not consent to a measure which so seriously interferers with the private lives of the people. They must remind themselves <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0289.jpg" n="2"/>that an overwhelming majority of citizens would never agree to such a proposal, and that their resentment will be shown in the coming state elections. However, in view of past experiences with the present senators and representatives, there is not much hope. Yet no stone should be left unturned in an effort to inform the legislature and the Governor of the will of their electors. It is bad enough for the people to be ignored when such steps are taken, and the people as a whole not to be given an opportunity to take a stand. The representatives of the people should not be left in ignorance concerning public resentment of such concessions to "whiskey snoopers" and narrow-minded preachers.</p>
   <p>Two other bills which should be passed because of present conditions are to be voted on when this notorious proposal comes up for decision. According to one bill, intoxicating beverages are to be defined as beverages which contain no more than three per cent of alcohol, and the other bill provides that saloonkeepers, brewers, etc., who suffer property losses through the enforcement of prohibition are to be compensated, and that such compensation is to be paid by the respective communities. Since an anti-liberal attitude prevails in the legislature, it seems that there is hardly any hope that these bills will be <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0290.jpg" n="3"/>accepted. Nevertheless, we should try to convince the legislature that it is necessary to enact pertinent laws.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
