<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-13">June 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Meager Results</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1274</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1274.jpg" n="2"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-13">June 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">MEAGER RESULTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>preferred customers were in a position to balance the scales in favor of the House of Morgan, with reference to credit or loan extensions. And banks usually earn a pretty piece of money through such transactions. So one can readily imagine that the system of preferred customers has proved to be very profitable to J. P. Morgan.</p>
   <p>One may also assume that this practice will be continued; for Morgan and Company vigorously defended the system of preferred customers only last week. There are no legal means to abolish this practice, and it is very doubtful if laws against it will ever be enacted. Since banks have found ways and means to remove all hindrances to the successful execution of their machinations in the past, they will also find a method of evading legal prosecution in the future. It has ever been easy for them to avoid legal responsibility.</p>
   <p>The banks will not be disturbed in the least by the congressional provision that all income tax declarations are to be published. Juggling of balance sheets creates many possibilities of getting around the statutes. If the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1275.jpg" n="3"/>Morgan partners have paid no income tax during the past years, they will certainly be able to prove to the courts by written documents in the future that they do not owe any taxes. They surely will take such precautions. And even though they are liable, it will be impossible to prove it.</p>
   <p>This leads to the conclusion that legislatures are quite helpless against the objectionable practices of banks. Perhaps especially zealous congressmen will now attempt to devise new laws with the intention of abolishing these undesirable practices; but it is not very probable that they will succeed in their efforts. Laws exist to be transgressed....</p>
   <p>In this case, legislators face a brick wall, which is possibly the strongest in our entire economic system. The fault lies in the system. So it will be necessary to change the system in order to eliminate the evil. It is useless to fight it by intricate laws. This is the lesson which the Morgan investigation teaches our people, Congress, and Federal Government.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
