<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-03">Sept. 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Democracy on the March</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1574</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1574.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-03">Sept. 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">DEMOCRACY ON THE MARCH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Labor Day 1918" was the most remarkable holiday that organized labor has ever celebrated, and for a long time to come it will probably be remembered as the most outstanding. It will be talked about in future years.</p>
   <p>Labor, especially organized labor, replied to the call of the President to speed up war production as much as possible by holding parades and meetings, thus indicating that it pledged all its strength and power effectively to support the government in its [the government's] endeavor to conclude the war quickly and victoriously. That means the working masses reaffirmed their loyalty and patriotism, and clearly showed that they realized the great problems of the day. They have earned appreciation and gratitude--merely by doing as a matter of course what was in their very own interest.</p>
   <p>If loyalty to the government and the administration--to the elected representatives and officials, who are entrusted with the fate of the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1575.jpg" n="2"/>republic--should always be the proper thing and a natural obligation assumed by every good citizen in the interests of all, regardless of his political credo during peace times, then in this war only the most faithful co-operation with the government, the most effective support of its war measures and war aims, will serve the particular interests of labor especially organized labor--and [such co-operation and support]should absolutely be a matter of course. For organized labor will reap the greatest benefits by a successful liquidation of the war, which in the last analysis is labor's war: the war of the liberation of the masses from the oppression of the classes--the military, the bureaucratic, and the social [classes]over there and the plutocratic over here--and the war of democracy against inherited or usurped power and privileges.</p>
   <p>The present government of the United States, headed by President Woodrow Wilson, is the leader and protagonist of this democracy, which is fighting against any class rule and all class privileges and for the emancipation of labor--i.e. the masses--all over the world. And all this was known not merely since yesterday, when it was proclaimed to the workers of the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1576.jpg" n="3"/>country, not merely since the first declaration of the war aims. Everybody knew it--at least everybody that followed the occurrences in Washington with some degree of attention and political understanding--as far back as the autumn of 1913. Organized workers knew it--or should have known it from their own experience. That can be clearly realized from the incomparably better position labor finds itself in today [as compared with its position prior to 1914].</p>
   <p>Organized labor, which only a few years ago was looked upon askance and treated in a condescending manner by the press of the country and by the powerful interests, today is flattered by the press and is regarded by those self-same interests, at least outwardly, as being just as powerful and having the same rights [as these interests]. Today the question is not: Do the workers have the right to organize, and, by so organizing, to combat the unfair practices of organized capital? but: How will organized labor apply its great power? Will it remain moderate in its demands, or will it use its strength, as organized capital used to do, to unjustly encroach upon the rightful interests of others?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1577.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Like organized labor, productive labor of all kinds has made immense gains during recent years. Wages are much higher and the laborer is appreciated more than ever before. Today the productive worker is looked up to and admired; he has become an important individual, like the rich consumer of former days. It has not been so long ago--to the older ones among us it seems like "yesterday"--that, more than anything else, inherited wealth used to command the greatest admiration and could strut around in a proud and arrogant manner. Next in importance came those that managed to live by their wits or those that became rich quickly; they were regarded as superior citizens, who thought quite a lot of themselves and felt they could look down on the farmer, who tilled the soil by the sweat of his brow and sometimes could not pay the interest on his mortgage when it was due. Today the plain hired hand is regarded as more valuable than the parasite that is living on his inherited wealth. Those who are today called parasites are those charming people who once used to brag that they never had fallen to that level where they had to work for a living. And the independent farmer of today is a prince, whom even the government treats with kid gloves. The "hick," who was once the butt of jokes, has become a respectable and honorable person.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1578.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>And he will remain so. And where he isn't [considered respectable] he is going to be; wherever the worker has not yet reached the status of a member in American trade union, he will of course attain that status--as fast as this war for democracy is concluded. For the end of the war can only mean: victory of the democratic idea--better conditions for the worker, increasing influence and power of the producing masses all over the world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
