<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-06-19">June 19, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">Italian Immigration.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1060</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1060.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-06-19">June 19, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">ITALIAN IMMIGRATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In recent times the Italian Immigration into the United States has rapidly increased. The emigrants from Italy, as well as from other south European countries, naturally prefer Brazil and the La Plata states, but of late years it has been observed that a considerable portion have been landing in the northern parts of the United States. But now it has become a very serious matter, and even alarming. The increase of Italians in New York and vicinity since January 1 amounts to over 30,000 persons.</p>
   <p>What shall become of these people? Their sphere of activity is very limited. Most of them remain near or in the city where they landed because of their poverty which has become almost proverbial. They help to swell the number of proletarians, who live from "hand to mouth", or they fall in line with the large army of the unemployed. Without depreciating the value of the "cheap" Italian man-power, it is impossible to ignore the danger connected with such en masse immigration. Although they have contributed largely to the erections of public buildings, railroads, streets, etc, in this country, but they do not in particularly adapt themselves to agricultural activities, and are not desired by the American farmer. Since <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1061.jpg" n="2"/>they are therefore dependent upon the large cities for employment, it must be discovered, if the present condition of the labor markets are favorable for them or no. This must be answered with a definite no, because we laready have more Italian workers than we can steadily employ. A great many of these new-comers will face a serious winter, full of worry and misery.</p>
   <p>It appears that a large number of Italian immigrants is being directed to the United States deliberately and for a selfish reason. We seem to be justified in assuming that immigration agents in Italy have expanded their soul-selling activities immensely. The steamship companies pay a fee of $3.00 for each steerage passenger. Taking into consideration that the prospects for Italian laborers are not at all favorable, the steadily increasing stream of immigrants is indicative of unscrupulous action by the agents. There is no other explanation. This abuse could not easily be rectified by the American government, but it is the duty of the Italian government to warn its subjects of the dangers connected with a thoughtless or hasty migration to the United States. Finally, the Catholic clergy, here and there, could also do something to ward off the misery. <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1062.jpg" n="3"/>It is certain that many of the Italian immigrants will suffer greatly, if this affair is permitted to run its natural course.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
