<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-13">Mar. 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Liquor Consumption--</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0327</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0327.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-13">Mar. 13, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">LIQUOR CONSUMPTION--<gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/></title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Advocates of prohibition usually attempt to justify their zealous endeavors to make America "dry" by pointing out that it is in the interest of humanity to put a stop to the ever-increasing drunkennness. But has inebriety really increased during the past decades, centuries, or even during the last two thousand years? A study of chronicles and other historical material which we have before us impels us to answer this question negatively. At the time of the Roman emperors good manners dictated that one drink to excess,and the festivals which were observed in honor of Bacchus, Venus, and Saturn, were marked by such gross debauchery that it would disgust even the most immoderate tiplers of today. Julius Caesar, a habitual drunkard, while intonicated gave the driver of his war chariot $80,000 as a gratuity, and thereby established a record which undoubtedly is still unsurpassed. What is a twenty-dollar bill, given by a drunken war profiteer to his chauffeur, in comparison to Caesar's sip?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0328.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Even a hasty reading of general history teaches us that Philip of Lacedonia was a drunkard. His son, Alexander The Great, imbibed no less. It is said of him that sometimes he did not recover from a drunken stupor until after sixty hours. He died as the are of thirty-two years--as a result of his immoderate use of intonicants. Dionysius, the Tyrant of Sicily, often went on a three-month spree. Liguor blinded him. Nero also was drunk hearly every day during his reign. Many of the other Roman emperors were drunkards; Tiberius, for instance, whom his soldiers dubbed "Biberius," that is, "toper"; Claudius, Caligula, Vitellius, Lucullus, Verres, etc. And the habits, morals, and styles of the rulers of those days were emulated by their subjects. Drunkenness was so general and widespread among the Thracians, Iberians, Celts and Scythians, that a man who did not overimbibe every day, or every other day, was considered an oddity. Romans and Greeks, triumvirs, consuls,and emperors, legionnaires and gladiators, looked upon intoxicating liquors as necessities of life, and would have understood the admonitions of a modern "dry" preacher as little as they would have understood a dissertation on perpetual motion.</p>
   <p>During the Middle Ages, too, there was unlimited drinking. Nobles, courtiers, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0329.jpg" n="3"/>lords of manors, townsmen, and farmers set no bounds to their efforts to quench their thirst, and history shows that the intoxicants of those days were of such strength, and were consumed in such quantities, that later generations were astonished. King Henry VIII, an archetype of King Blue Beard, was intoxicated nearly every day, and English historians mention this as an excuse for his polygamy, which he made possible by divorcing, banishing, or executing a wife when he tired of her. And Queen Elizabeth, Queen Bess, could hold up her end at a drinking party. In Germany, Italy, Spain, and France, spirituous liquors, such as wine, beer, and mead, were every day drinks, and in several of these countries it was legally prescribed how much of such liquids was to be given to servants.</p>
   <p>Although drunkenness has never been considered to be a characteristic of the American people, of late the United States has offered a far greater variety of spirituous liquors than could be purchased in other countries. Nature has endowed the "Land of the free and the Home of the Brave" with manifold fruits, from which a potent potion may be made, and during the good old days of yore alcoholic drinks were prepared from plums, pears, apples, apricots, etc; these drinks were hardly any weaker than stored bourbon whiskey. Many of America's <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0330.jpg" n="4"/>prominent men enjoyed alcoholic liquor without losing any mental power, or their good name. Webster, Clay, Calhoun, Daniel, Douglas, and other great men of our country liked a little glass. Even in the capitol at Washington there is a room in which an array of battles is kept, so that senators may refresh themselves after making an address, or during long discussions. If anybody and recommended as recently as five years that this arrangement be abolished, the members of the "most signified parliamentary body of the world "would have voted him down as a crazy reformer.</p>
   <p>Although the quantity of liquor consumed by the American people, whose numbers are are increasing very rapidly, has greatly increased, the amount consumed by the individual has undoubtedly decreased considerably. Again, it must be taken into account that government control over the manufacture, sale, and use of spirituous liquors was constantly grown stricter, and in consequence the quality and whole-someness of alcoholic drinks is better, We must also consider that the evil results of overindulgence in intoxicating liquor are well enough known today to impress upon our people the expediency of being moderate. Thus no argument <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0331.jpg" n="5"/>appears to be less sound than the statement that it is necessary to protect the American people against drunkenness by coercive laws.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
