<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-01-30">Jan. 30, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">Vicious Anti-German Propaganda.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1040</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1040.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-01-30">Jan. 30, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">VICIOUS ANTI-GERMAN PROPAGANDA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The English American newspapers have recently been full of anti-German agitation. The most malicious slander, as well as most assinine notions of the French press, are presented to their credulous readers as undeniable facts. Every action of Germany, of its government, and of its leaders is maliciously distorted, and no scandalous story is too absurd not to be copied. Due to the general circulation of these defamations, prejudice is being aroused among the Americans against the Germans, and it makes itself felt among the German Americans in a most unpleasant manner. It can be safely assumed that this aroused prejudice is partly responsible for the anti-German sentiment which has manifested itself in different cities in this country, as for instance the suppression of German instruction in public schools.</p>
   <p>If we investigate the reasons for publication by the Anglo-American press of these slanders, we find the cause in the so-called "Special Cablegrams" of the New York newspapers.</p>
   <p>This worthless trash of which in almost all cases, not one word has been cabled, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1041.jpg" n="2"/>is put together by Irish press "gyps" in New York. Because of their desire to make that trash as sensational as possible, and because of their intense and almost insane hate of the Germans they gather this "news" almost exclusively from French newspapers, which they receive by mail. Of course, these French papers try to surpass one another in printing the most slanderous and absurd stories against Germany.</p>
   <p>This worthless trash, calculated for the Irish in New York, and for which the newspapers in New York pay only a small amount to the Irish press "gyps", is then peddled for a few dollars per month to the English-American papers in this country. In this way the New York papers are compensated for the few dollars they pay to the infamous Irish cablegram manufacturer.</p>
   <p>These falsified New York "Special Cablegrams" were also offered to us for a low price, but we refused to accept the offer, because the "news" contain only a few old reports besides the already mentioned scandals from French newspapers, which no decent paper can afford to publish.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
