<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-07-20">July 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">One Half of a Job Done</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II E 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-07-20">July 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">ONE HALF OF A JOB DONE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before it can become a law, the Twenty-first Amendment, which calls for the repeal of Prohibition, must be ratified by three fourths of all the states. That is a long way to go and it is generally supposed that it will be several years before thirty-six states decide whether or not to ratify the latest amendment to the Federal Constitution. But the way things are going now, it will take considerably less time. Last Tuesday another two states, Alshama and Arkansas, cast majority votes in favor of the Twenty-first Amendment, which means that now we are at the halfway mark, because Alabama and Arkansas are the seventeenth and eighteenth states which have decided for repeal of Prohibition.</p>
   <p>These two states, in particular, were of great importance to the prohibition issue, because they were numbered among those which were already "dry" at a time when nobody in the country thought it possible that Prohibition would ever <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0134.jpg" n="2"/>become a Federal law in America. The dream picture of Prohibition was much more beautiful than the reality. If it was necessary to furnish additional proof that Prohibition did the greatest damage to the intrinsically sound idea of temperance, then these two Southern states, by joining the "wet" camp, have certainly supplied that proof. Without this noble experiment these states would probably still be "dry" today. This practical test has cost the temperance advocates not only their good reputation, but also their political power. And the way they have been using this power is precisely the reason why nobody in the land feels sorry for them. Their concepts of morality, and they themselves, are through. And that is a good thing.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, one cannot say the same of that vile by-product of Prohibition, the bootlegger. He is still going strong; he still has his distilleries, breweries, and speak-easies. The reason for this is simple enough: As long as Prohibition is in force, we will also have political corruption which enables the "booze peddlers" to make an easy living. It is true that the number of bootleggers has decreased, because they find it a little more difficult to make</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0135.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>profits now, since beer has been legalized. But they are still with us and will remain so until the Eighteenth Amendment is repealed by the Twenty-first Amendment. These considerations should play a decisive role wherever a favorable or adverse decision on Prohibition has not yet been made.</p>
   <p>Nothing has had a more demoralizing effect on the American people than Prohibition, with its incredible corruption and scandals; and, to a great extent it has undermined the citizens' respect for the law. The spirit of Prohibition cannot be made to disappear--public authorities cannot be cleansed of corruption--until the thirty-sixth state has pronounced judgment on the most stupid and frivolous experiment ever perpetrated in a country of free peoples.</p>
   <p>And still another aspect merits consideration: The drinking habit of minors, which before Prohibition was unknown in America, and which must also be charged up as a direct product of Prohibition, will continue as long as the consumption of alcohol is legally prohibited. Forbidden fruit has always tasted good, especially to young people. After reflecting on this problem of health and</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0136.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>education, the remaining eighteen states should not find it hard to declare themselves in favor of the adoption of the Twenty-first Amendment. The whole country will breathe a sigh of relief when that time comes. The first half of the job is done; the rest, we hope, will not take long.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
