<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-09-17">Sept. 17, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">Anent the Temperance Movement</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0060</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0060.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-09-17">Sept. 17, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">ANENT THE TEMPERANCE MOVEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our friends in Aurora sent us the September 12 issue of their Beacon, in which there is a detailed report of a meeting which was held on September 1 by the advocates of temperance. We cannot say that the report offers anything new or original. It is the old story, although the "mourning brigade" was not represented. It is interesting to learn that the apostles of bigotry and hatred still persecute us Teutons as "diabolical opponents of the most salutary reform the world has ever heard of". Since these so-called reformers are still active, it is up to us Germans to unite with the enlightened English-speaking citizens in making war on a common enemy.</p>
   <p>The main speaker in the aforementioned meeting was the Honorable Charles Button.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0061.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Who are they," asks this clergyman, with the righteous indignation of an Old Testament prophet. "Who are they that organize 'beer conventions' in opposition to our efforts to reform our fellow men? Who are they that lend their hand to overthrow the institutions of this great Republic and refuse to support any candidate for public office who does not promise to do everything within his power to abolish all Sunday laws? They are our German fellow citizens. They are trying with might and main to undermine the Christian religion, and therewith the very foundation of free government. They threaten to bring about the defeat of the Republican party unless that political body advocates free whiskey and free beer.</p>
   <p>"The Germans rendered valuable services; they fought very bravely in the late War, but they have no right to force upon the New World the unrepublican and immoral principles which they brought with them when they came here from the old country. Beer gardens and desecration of the Sabbath was against morality and cannot be tolerated. The Germans speak of their rights, but <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0062.jpg" n="3"/>are they the only citizens of American who have rights? Have the adherents to religion and the advocates of law, order, and temperance no rights?"</p>
   <p>We need not tell our readers, and especially our friends in Aurora, that this is all bosh. This good man, like all his "brethren in the Lord," is laboring under the foolish notion that this great continent was created solely for the benefit of a few thousand New England "saints," and that all other nationalities are nothing but helots who are subservient to the whims of fanatical puritans. And as to the desires and ambitions of Germans and their attitude toward liberty, justice, and equality--well he knows as little about them as a blind man knows about colors. Were this not so, he would not prate about "Teutonic endeavors to overthrow the institutions of this country, and to transplant to America unrepubliean and inmoral principles". Indeed, this country would be much better off if none of its inhabitants were more unrepublican and immoral than the Germans are. There is no other nation that is less disposed to encroach upon the rights of <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0063.jpg" n="4"/>others, and it was not until the Germans came to the United States that they learned to appreciate and to cling to the rights that are guaranteed all Americans in our precious documents, the Declaration of Independence and the Constitution of the United States. However, the advocates of temperance are acting in the manner of all fanatics. While they still have stolen goods in their possession, they cry, "Stop thief!" And while they are endeavoring to convince others of the excellence of their narrow-minded bigotry, and would have the state force their unjust measures upon others, they complain of attempts to deprive them of their constitutional rights. There is no remedy against such blindness, and, as we all know, we cannot expect to get anything but beef from an ox.</p>
   <p>Mr. Young who spoke after Mr. Mutton, I mean Button, is a very crafty person. He said, among other things, that "the best way to enforce prohibition laws is to grant women the right to vote," and that he was "not in favor of permitting flunkies who had all their possessions wrapped in a handkerchief when they <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0064.jpg" n="5"/>came over here, to frustrate the will which women voice at the polls".</p>
   <p>Is there anything else that bothers you, Mr. Young? Have you any other pains? It seems you would deprive German immigrants of the right to vote, and grant women that right, and, as the press informs us daily, women frequently employ very radical measures to gain their objects.</p>
   <p>We hope that our friends in Aurora will give this impudent scoundrel, who is supposed to be of German descent, a good piece of their mind. They have a good opportunity to do so, for this fellow is a job hunter, a candidate for representative to Congress. [Translator's note: It is not clear whether the author refers to Mr. Button or Mr. Young in this paragraph.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
