<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><date when="1919-03-02"> Mar. 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Are There Harmless Liquors?</title><title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0346</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0346.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><date when="1919-03-02"> Mar. 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">ARE THERE HARMLESS LIQUORS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A reader of the London Daily Hail asked this question and that newspaper answered thus:</p>
   <p>"No alcoholic liquor can be said to be harmless. But just as little can it be claimed that colored carbonated waters which are commonly known as 'temperance drinks' are harmless. These gaseous liquids often damage the organs of digestion and contain undesirable admixtures.</p>
   <p>"Tea and coffee contain poisons which disturb digestion, cause symptoms of nervousness, interfere with the action of the heart, and are often productive of sleeplessness and headache. Used intemperately, tea and coffee may cause gastric catarrh.</p>
   <p>"Many are the evil results which are attributed to the use of spirituous <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0347.jpg" n="2"/>liquors. A great number of physicians condemn even a moderate use of them. One cannot overlook the fact that no palatable drink can be said to have absolutely no bad effect on health. However, there is quite a difference with reference to the degree of harmfulness. This becomes evident when we compare beer and light red or white wines with liqueurs, cocktails, and other fluids of strong alcoholic content. It is very probable that there is less risk connected with consuming a pint of beer or a half pint of red wine than there is in drinking a pint of strong tea."</p>
   <p>It has been proved beyond the shadow of a doubt that alcoholic liquors used moderately at mealtime aid digestion. Tea, when used with a meal of meat, fish, or eggs, undoubtedly hinders digestion. Although there is poison in every mug and in every cup, whether the contents contain alcohol or not, yet we need not permit anyone to order or forbid us to use any particular drinks. The people who ascertain which foods and drinks are agreeable to them are the healthiest. Since it is certain that no drink is above suspicion, we should select those which we have found to be the least harmful and <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0348.jpg" n="3"/>which produce a feeling of comfort. English prohibitionists who recommend tea as a substitute for spirituous liquors perhaps do not know that tea increases the blood pressure, stimulates the action of the heart, and causes somewhat deeper breathing. It restores waning muscular power--for a time. Its main disadvantage is that it disturbs digestive activity. As stimulants beer and light wines are to be greatly preferred, especially during old age.</p>
   <p>When people are told that they need nothing but water to quench their thirst, there is grave danger that their bodies will suffer from insufficient fluid matter; drinks, as well as food, should correspond to the taste.</p>
   <p>On the coming election day, April 1, Chicago will declare her stand on local prohibition. Let no one fail to vote against the proposed "drying-up" of our city. [Translator's note: This last paragraph is printed in bold type.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
