<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-08-03">Aug. 3, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">Anent the Sunday Question</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0792</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0792.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-08-03">Aug. 3, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">ANENT THE SUNDAY QUESTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a recent editorial entitled "Reasonable Opinions" we said that our English- speaking citizens are becoming more enlightened and more liberal in their views on religious matters. The local Post (issue of August 1) is a pertinent example. Christian Times and Witness, a local religious periodical, published a fulminating article, sustaining the statement made by Dr. Schaff and his henchmen in the meeting held at Crosby Opera House, "that a widespread and well organized conspiracy exists for the purpose of desecrating the Sabbath, breaking down public morals, fostering crime and vice, and undermining the very principles which all Americans esteem very highly", denouncing the Germans as the chief tools of this conspiracy, and accusing the liberal press of setting the value of the German vote above that of religion and morality. In answer to this article the Post writes, August 1:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0793.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"It is not difficult to enact a good law and to place it on the statute book, but it is impossible to enforce a law that is not in agreement with the opinions and desires of the majority of the people of a community.</p>
   <p>"Who is to blame if honest German workers prefer spending a part of the Sabbath in a beer garden to visiting the stylish temple of the Reverend 'Creamcheese,' there to endure the suspicious glances of elegantly attired 'Christians,' or attending services in the house of worship presided over by Reverend 'Zealot' where thunderous anathemas are cast upon him from the Old and New Testaments?"</p>
   <p>If modern Christianity has nothing to attract the great class of citizens, the workers, to its houses of worship on Sunday, why should Christians be surprised to find that workers look elsewhere for recuperations from the effects of daily toil?</p>
   <p>To accuse all who do not go to church on Sunday, and who drink beer on the Lord's Day, of "intending to undermine the civil and religious institutions of our <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0794.jpg" n="3"/>country," is foolish and unjust.</p>
   <p>It has never occurred to these peace-loving and law-abiding citizens to encroach upon the religious freedom of others, nor do they have the least thought of conspiring against liberty, when they drink beer on Sunday; and though they were in the wrong, they certainly cannot be persuaded to do right by the ridicule and lies which are hurled at them by some so-called ministers.</p>
   <p>We often thank God that time of religious persecutions has passed; but we forget, at the same time, that in some of our churches today there prevails an attitude of intolerance which would condemn to death at the stake a man who commits the awful crime of drinking a glass of beer on Sunday, and would execute all "evil-doers," were it not for the fact that such drastic measures are forbidden by law.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
