<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><date when="1919-03-25">Mar. 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Prohibition Via the Rear Door</title><title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0306</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0306.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><date when="1919-03-25">Mar. 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">PROHIBITION VIA THE REAR DOOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The New York World, a newspaper which, according to general opinion, reflects the attitude of Washington relative to important current questions, lately made this statement in an editorial on prohibition:</p>
   <p>"The suit which was brought in Federal District Court assures a rigorous investigation into the constitutionality of the prohibition clause contained in the law of November 21, 1918, which relates to an appropriation for agriculture. It is high time that our people know what they may expect in this matter. Millions of law-abiding persons are firmly convinced that the present situation has been brought about by underhanded dealings. It is worth while to ascertain whether or not these people have retained any rights. If their complaints are just, they are entitled to immediate redress."</p>
   <p>Congress was induced to pass the prohibition law as a war measure. But that <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0307.jpg" n="2"/>was a misrepresentation, for the War was formally concluded, and the armistice was already signed. The American people have never taken prohibition seriously. They never considered it a possibility, for they were never consulted on the matter. The law was passed slyly, by making it a rider to a proposal for an appropriation.</p>
   <p>At that time there was not the least doubt that our people would consent to make any sacrifices which would be necessary to win the victory. They were willing to do without food, and drink, and other necessities, if the situation demanded it. The prohibitionists thought they could take advantage of this sentiment to execute their plans, and even after the armistice had been signed and the time for stringent measures had passed, and there was no prospect that they would again be necessary, these reformers insisted upon enactment of the coercive law.</p>
   <p>War prohibition had its inception in dishonesty. It found its way into our legal code by deception. Common hypocrisy, disguised under a mask of loyalty <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0308.jpg" n="3"/>during war, forced it upon the people. And the originators of prohibition boasted about the cunning manner in which they had cheated the public. Irrespective of whether the courts consider the prohibition clause to be constitutional or not, the fact remains that the procedure used to secure its enactment will stand out as one of the blackest pages in the history of American legislation. [Translator's note: Since the author failed to use quotation marks, it is impossible to ascertain the exact point where the quotation from the New York World ends.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
