<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1873-05-02">May 2, 1873</date>.
<title level="a">General Order No. 20.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0729</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0729.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1873-05-02">May 2, 1873</date>.
<title level="a">GENERAL ORDER NO. 20.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The general order, No. 20, revealed yesterday by Elmer Washburn has caused a sensation everywhere. It came suddenly, without any warning, a May present of the trio, Medill, Tuley and Washburn, to the city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The first point of the order commands the policemen to spy, to do, what had been forbidden them by the general order five months ago. At that time Washburn instructed the policemen through their captains, not to loaf around backdoors, not to stand on barrels, in order to look through the windows, that they had to report only those violations they encountered while on their beats.</p>
   <p>And Today? Policemen are ordered to enter saloons frequently on Sundays, if they have a suspicion that drinks are sold there, so as to be witnesses.</p>
   <p>Mr. Medill will have the distinction to have been esteemed as highly, and later to have been esteemed as little, as no one has else previously. He complains that he is attacked by everyone. He is solely responsible for it. Can he expect <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0730.jpg" n="2"/>consideration, if he hurts the feelings of thousands of the best citizens? Or are not the Germans the best citizens? May he tell us if we do not answer the following questions correctly.</p>
   <p>Who is it one does not find among the tax dodgers? The Germans. Which nationality gives the least work for the Relief and Aid Society and to the County agent? The Germans.</p>
   <p>Have the Germans complied until now with the oppressive law, without any direct resistance? Yes.</p>
   <p>And the mayor still dares to complain that the Germans attack him in their meetings and in the press. The policemen are driven to a conflict with the saloon keepers. Let us hope that no blood will flow.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
