<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1890-11-02">Nov. 2, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">Franz Amberg Defended</title><title level="a" type="sub">Harsh Criticism, for the Committee of One Hundred.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1027</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1027.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1890-11-02">Nov. 2, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">FRANZ AMBERG DEFENDED</title><title level="a" type="sub">HARSH CRITICISM, FOR THE COMMITTEE OF ONE HUNDRED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung yesterday contained a violent denunciation of the Sons of America, the Deputies, and the British Americans, as attempting to revive the Know-Nothing spirit and opposing candidates of German descent for no other reason than that they are Germans. It charges that the organization are fighting not only the Catholics but the German Lutherans as well, "although the Protestanism of the latter is a thousand time better than their own"</p>
   <p>With reference to the ticket issued by the Committee of One Hundred, this paper says:</p>
   <p>But just as hostile (as against Raab) this horde shows itself against Franz Amberg although he is a Republican. In his place it has made Edward S. Wilson its candidate.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1028.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>True Amberg was a citizen of this country when many of these Know-Nothings were still in the cradle. But has committed the crime of having been born in Germany. Hence the Know-Nothing horde prefers the long fingers of Mr. Wilson, which once reached into the County Treasury at Robinson in Crawford County, to the clean fingers of Amberg. True Amberg fought as a brave soldier for the American Republic when many of these Know-Nothing knaves were yet unborn. But he commits the crime of being not only a good citizen of this Republic, but also a faithful conservator of German customs and language. Hence these scapegraces who continually bear the word "American" on their lips prefer the hand which at Ofney, in Richland County, wanted to lay itself on land titles that justly belonged to others to the manly German hand which wielded the saber in many a battle for America...</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
