<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1891-12-14">Dec. 14, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">The Illinois Staats-Zeitung and its Compositors</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1891-12-14">Dec. 14, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">THE ILLINOIS STAATS - ZEITUNG AND ITS COMPOSITORS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For sometime back a misuse has been made of my name, and words have been put into my mouth, which I never uttered, I ask the indulgence of the community for a few moments that I may offer a word of explanation.</p>
   <p>Typographia No. 9 and its official organs, the Agitator and the Arbeiter-Zeitung, have for weeks indulged in a wholesale and indiscriminate abuse of me, which I hereby brand as infamous, and without one single word of truth. I openly declare, that every single charge made is a bold outrageous lie, and I defy any man to confront me and make these charges verbally in my presence.</p>
   <p>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung considered all negotiations closed, as far as Typographia No. 9 was concerned, until the Messrs Schilling and Madden requested a personal interview with our compositors which was granted. This committee misrepresented the desires of the Staats - Zeitung to the compositors. I corrected the false statements made by the committee, whereupon the compositors manimously voted to reject the propositions submitted by Typographia No. 9</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0035.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>through the committee. Is it any wonder that these propositions were rejected? For by the grace of Typographia No. 9 only 25 of our entire force were to be allowed to remain in our employ, while the rest were to be sold like so many slaves by Typographia No. 9 to any second-hand job office or to some newspaper which has bankruptcy staring it in its face. In other words: faithful and honest employees, who have been with us for nearly a quarter of a century, were to be sent wherever a few hot-headed anarchists might dictate. This resolution on the part of our employees was communicated to the committee of the Typographia by our foreman, Mr. Krumme, in a respectful manner.</p>
   <p>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung believes in the eight hour law. It has always paid the highest prices for labor. It complies in every respect with conditions existing between the English Typographical Union No. 16 and the English papers. The Illinois Staats - Zeitung believes in labor organizations and is an advocate of the principle expressed in "In Union there is strength". It interferes in no wise with the right of any man in its employ to join any union or organization, (and if any of our employees desires to join any Typographical union they have a perfect right to do so); but we can not and will not dismiss an old employee <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0036.jpg" n="3"/>simply because he will not do what some cranky outsiders, who desire to ruin our business, dictate. It appears to me that the time has come to cry "halt" and that the honest, hardworking and thrifty laborer should separate himself from those, who are constantly plotting strife and trouble, in order to magnify their own self-importance, and at the same time profit thereby. This is a free country. The laborer is worthy of his hire and must be protected. No organization has any right to interfere with him. No union must attempt to dictate what he shall do, at what price, nor where he shall work. When his personal liberty is interfered with, when he loses his right to act as his free moral agent, then the law must be appealed to.</p>
   <p>The compositors of the Staats - Zeitung can join a union or not; that is their business and not ours. If, however, they do not wish to associate themselves with law-breakers and hair-brained anarchists they will be allowed to remain at their cases in the future just as in the past. If they decline to be ruthlessly torn from work they have been accustomed to perform for many years in order to be sold into servitude, then the Illinois Staats -Zeitung will protect them. The honest laborer will always find the strong arm of the Staats - Zeitung raised in his behalf; he will always find it a defender against the arrogance of mischief-makers and against the interference of meddling political schemers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_3_1_0037.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If our men at any time desire to join the Union, I say, "God speed". If they believe in "letting well enough alone", they shall be protected in that belief.</p>
   <p>Washington Hesing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
