<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-07">Feb. 7, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Arizona</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-07">Feb. 7, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">ARIZONA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The treasurer of the Chicago Mining and Hilling Company informed that body at a meeting yesterday, that enough bonds had been sold to warrant energetic procedures. It was decided, therefore, to attend forthwith to the procurement of machinery for the proposed reduction plant [Globe District, Arizona]; to send for Mr. Weberling, mining engineer and metallurgist whom Mr. [A. C.] Hesing engaged in San Francisco; and to let him [Weberling] superintend the construction of the machinery. Mr. Weberling studied at the Mining Academy at Freiberg, Germany; he is an experienced metallurgist and as such was active in the best-known mines of California and Arizona; he was highly recommended to Mr. Hesing by the silver king, Senator Jones. As Mr. Weberling is particularly familiar with the peculiarities of the ores found in Arizona, he is especially qualified to design suitable reduction works and superintend operations.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's resolutions of the executive board of the Chicago Mining and <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1419.jpg" n="2"/>Hilling Company [founded by A. C. Kesing, and controlling twenty mines] marked the beginning of actual operations; presumably all bonds will be sold in a short time. The demand for then has increased greatly in recent days and capitalists from other cities show a strong inclination to be affiliated with the Corporation. Almost every day gentlemen from New York and Boston visit Mr. Kesing to obtain information about the mines and, if certain deals are consummated, large blocks of bonds will be disposed of.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: In conjunction with this article, Illinois Staats-Zeitung published the court proceedings involving the bankruptcy case of the Germania Insurance Company which was founded by A. C. Hesing, is also the promoter of this mining venture.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
