<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-09-16">September 16, 1907</date><title level="a">Its Real Meaning.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0500</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0500.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-09-16">September 16, 1907</date><title level="a">ITS REAL MEANING.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After the grand demonstration arranged yesterday by the United Associations for Local Self Government", nobody will dare to assert that they only represented the liquor interests. So many societies would not have undertaken the trouble and expense of a gigantic demonstration, and ten thousand voters would not have defied the heat and dust storm. The so-called "ignorant foreigner" has shown those self styled "real Americans", that they know their political rights only too well and are willing to defend them with great sacrifice.....Even if the Charter scheme would have been so much better than it really is, it would yet possess the fundamental error, that it was effected without the real people of Chicago, and consequently disregards the views, habits and wished of three-quarters of the population. When the attention of the Charter convention of the United Societies was called to it, it even knew how to recommend two more bills, besides the Charter, to the legislature, that would at least assure to the people a free Sunday and maintenance of their harmless recreations. But as these bills, in some respects, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0501.jpg" n="2"/>were regarded as a patched up apendage, the legislature thought they were not meant seriously, and meant little or nothing. This view was eventually endorsed by the English-American cosmopolitan press, and by other sponsors of the charter. It was asserted that the "foreigner" could very well be satisfied with the tolerance which they enjoyed till now. They should not be so impudent, persisting in their attitude against the charter, only because the legislature wouldn't even consider their demands. When they, solely from caprice, stand in the way of "progress" they will be effectually chastised.</p>
   <p>But these attacks had a different effect, which was not expected by the cosmopolitan press, and the Republican leaders. Instead of being intimidated, the "stranger" will now more than ever, assert himself through the ballot. They are thoroughly tired of being regarded as hangers-on. In their own opinion they are not an inferior, unchained mob, but full-fledged citizens, who have as much a share in the progress of the city as the natives have had, and hence insist that they receive the consideration due them. The immigrant <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0502.jpg" n="3"/>voters, who with their immediate descendents by far make up the majority, will not accept a city charter which was drafted by the "upper classes" to promote their own interests only. This is the real meaning of the movement against the proposed charter, that is to be decided by a vote. We hope its defeat will be so enormous that it will be impossible to misunderstand it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
