<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-01-10">Jan. 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Wall Street</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1245</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1245.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-01-10">Jan. 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">WALL STREET</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many of the reports which are read about Wall Street indicate that the men of finance have not yet agreed on an attitude toward the plans of the Federal Government. When we consider how sensitive and presentient the money barons were under former administrations, how they fairly smelled what was in the air, we wonder why their incredible sense of smell is no more active. Have their noses lost their ability to detect and distinguish between odors, or did their ears, perhaps, sharpen their sense of smell in former times?</p>
   <p>Anybody who formerly followed the rates of exchange on the market from day to day, was often astonished at the tendency of the exchange rates suddenly to change, shortly before the close of the market, although incoming telegrams <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1246.jpg" n="2"/>revealed no reason for the change. Then after the close of the market the newspapers published reports to justify the tendency of the exchange rates to change. Then, of course, there was admiration for the ability of Wall Street to read the future. However, if, on the next day, a small speculator wished to buy or sell on the basis of the proceeding day's reports, he was too late, of course. The report has already been discounted on the market the day before, and in most cases the rates were a rain moving in the opposite direction. Thus the fact that the rates fall when good reports are made known, and that they rise when unfavorable views are published, has become a proverb on the market.</p>
   <p>Since President Roosevelt has taken office, the large speculators' power of presentiment has declined greatly; indeed, one might say that it has caused to function. The reason for this may be found in the fact that President Roosevelt was very careful when he selected his co-workers, and sought only men who had no connection with the unscrupulous financiers, or, at least, were under no obligation to them. Thus the fine connections between the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1247.jpg" n="3"/>Government and Wall Street were severed, and so the large speculators lost their supernatural sense of smell.</p>
   <p>It is to be hoped, and nobody has any reason to doubt, that it will remain thus under the present Administration. By adhering to this principle, the Government has removed one of the many evils of Wall Street, for it is no exaggeration to say that speculators are less interested in knowing whether or not certain plans of the Government will redound to the welfare of the nation, then they are in the use of the plans of the Government for their own selfish interests.</p>
   <p>Nor is it wrong to assume that the large speculators are opposing the Administration on the inflation question chiefly because they could not find out what course the Government intends to pursue in the matter. They would be only too happy to know and use that knowledge to make a lot of money.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1248.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Perhaps the Administration will not be content to do away with this evil only, but is also planning to remove others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
