<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-04-17">Apr. 17, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[The Temperance Movement]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0788</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0788.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-04-17">Apr. 17, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">[THE TEMPERANCE MOVEMENT]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fruits of the so-called People's Movement of the 18th of November, 1869, begin to make themselves very strongly felt. Mayor Mason and Mark Sheridan have hitched themselves together before the temperance wagon and try to pull it forward. The Staats Zeitung has said it a hundred times when the Mayor was nominated that he is a temperance man even though one cannot say much else against him. The Staats Zeitung has warned that the so-called Reform and People's Movement was endangering German interests, that the whole was only a disguised attack against the German influence. This indictment now has been proven true.</p>
   <p>On Saturday afternoon, a meeting took place at the Mayor's which was attended by the three police Commissioners, 19 Aldermen, some obscure gentlemen from temperance circles and Mr. Drake, Proprietor of Tremont House. Of the German Aldermen only one, Herr Schaffner, was invited. That he gave the other gentlemen a piece of his mind in good German fashion needs hardly to be mentioned. The meeting was so secret that doors were locked. Reporters were not admitted. We are able nevertheless to give an almost verbatim report.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0789.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mayor Mason explained the reason for the meeting. Something has to be dome to carry municipal decrees and the Sunday State Law into effect. He asked Alderman Schaffner to take the word. Herr Schaffner declared that while being an American citizen with his whole heart in this question he had to represent the views of his German fellow citizens. He and his countrymen regarded the attempts the made by the temperance people as encroachments on their rights. He made his conviction clear in no uncertain terms that the Sunday Law could not be made to function, that the Germans would not stand for it and that he was afraid the attempts to enforce it would lead to unpleasnatness and possibly worse.</p>
   <p>Alderman Me Cotter: The Germans must submit themselves. It is really impudent considering that they came here poor and in order to make moneys and that afterwards they always want to be considered Germans only. Alderman Schaffner protested, saying he was just as good as Americans as Me cotter even if not so big a Know-nothing.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
