<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Abendpost</title>
      <date when="1919-01-18">Jan. 18, 1919</date>
      <title level="a">For Liberty and Justice</title>
      <title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0397</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0397.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Abendpost</title>
     <date when="1919-01-18">Jan. 18, 1919</date>
     <title level="a">FOR LIBERTY AND JUSTICE</title>
     <title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is reported  that the distillers are resolved to continue the fight against prohibition, particularly against the Prohibition Amendment to the Constitution, and to take any steps that promise results.</p>
   <p>This resolution is commendable and merits the recognition and gratitude of all good Americans and democrats (democrats in the general sense of the word, not adherents to partisan politics).</p>
   <p>For, although the distillers may have only their own financial and commercial interests in view, and although they may have decided upon this final fight in the hope of averting greater losses in the future, nevertheless, they are, or will be, champions of natural human rights, of the American Constitution, of American democratic principles, and of the entire Aerican democracy.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0398.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since thirty-eight state legislatures have ratified the Prohibition Amendment, and legislatures of states which were always considered strongholds of the "wets" are among them, some people infer that the majority of the American people favor national prohibition. Even if this inference were correct, it could not alter the fact that the Prohibition Amendment, in its very nature, and in the manner in which it was presented and accepted, is a grave injustice, a violation of the Constitution, and a several blow to American democracy.</p>
   <p>However, the inference is wrong. When the legislatures of the various states ratified the Prohibition Amendment in such great haste that they nearly tripped over one another's feet, each one vying for the first honors, they did not do so because they were convinced that prohibition would be conductive to the welfare of the country. Various reasons for their action are possible. They may have wanted to gain the good will and support of the powerful organizations which demanded prohibition; or they may have been ignorant of the gravity of their error; or they may have hoped that the Supreme Court would declare the amendment unconstitutional, and thus prevent</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0399.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>the great injustice, the violation of the Constitution; or they may have been unscrupulous enough to deny that they were elected to guard and preserve the liberties of the people, and thought: "Apres nous le deluge!"; or they may knowingly and intentionally have used the Constitution, which was conceived and written for the protection of minorities against the tyranny of majorities, to diminish the rights of the people, and to suppress the majority through the tyranny of the minority; perhaps they were autocrats at heart and enemies of American ideals and principles, and not democrats, not genuine Americans.</p>
   <p>The last possibility will likely be accepted by only a few people, but the other possibilities will certainly appear plausible to any one who is familiar with the nature and ways of American politics. The first possibility is the most acceptable, that the legislators who voted for ratification of the Prohibition Amendment did not realize what they were doing; they were not aware of the fact that the ratification of the Amendment was a violation of human rights which are guaranteed by the Constitution.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0400.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>When a great majority of the people favors such an encroachment upon the personal liberties of citizens, an amendment to the Constitution is not necessary; a mere law is sufficient. If the citizens of the thirty-eight states which ratified the Eighteenth Amendment to the Constitution wanted prohibition, it was entirely within the province of their legislatures to enact a prohibition law for their respective states. The objection that prohibition could not be enforced as long as  some states were "wet" and permitted interstate traffic in alcohol was rendered untenable by late Supreme Court decisions, which make the traffic in liquor in even nominal quantities impossible.</p>
   <p>The Eighteenth Amendment to the Constitution is in itself a violation of the Constitution and should be opposed by all true Americans, by all who are democrats by conviction. The distillers, as has been said, may be actuated by their personal interests, but apparently they are the only ones who are willing to take up the fight which is necessary for the general welfare. Therefore, they should have the support of all liberal, all truly <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0401.jpg" n="5"/>democratic, all American citizens.</p>
   <p>At present, they are the ones who are the champions of liberty and justice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
