<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-09-20">Sept. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Perils of the Liquor Trade</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0102</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0102.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-09-20">Sept. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">PERILS OF THE LIQUOR TRADE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Edward P. Mulrooney, chairman of the commission for liquor control of the State of New York, has issued an order that all persons who are engaged in the sale of beer to restaurants or retail stores, and who are in the employ of a brewery or of a wholesale beer house, must submit their photographs and fingerprints to the authorities. This order affects all local salesmen, traveling salesmen, collectors, beer truck drivers and their aids, whether they draw wages or work on commission. Mulrooney's action is indicative of a deep insight.</p>
   <p>The purpose of his action is explained by Mulrooney in the following manner: "This order is not going to disturb honest people who work for breweries or who sell beer as representatives of wholesale dealers. Its chief aim is to eliminate convicts and 'muscle men,' if there are such in the beer industry." It <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0103.jpg" n="2"/>must be quite bad in New York if the liquor control commission sees the need for such radical procedure.</p>
   <p>To file photographs and fingerprints of criminals is general practice. During the war, enemy aliens had to submit to this procedure, which has always been regarded as unpleasant and humiliating in this country. If the New York liquor commission has decided to issue that order, it must have had compelling grounds to do so.</p>
   <p>As soon as beer was legalized, there was a fear that professional criminals and racketeers would take hold of the industry and introduce into it the same methods they used in the illegal liquor trade. Now, every brewery must secure a permit from the federal government. The government seems to scrutinize every application thoroughly, but it is still possible that criminal elements may find their way into the industry by incorporating their breweries through "straw men".</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0104.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It seems that the liquor commission of the State of New York has verified the fact that these elements seek to seize the beer trade. That may not be so difficult, because the traders need no federal permit. At any rate, the attitude of the commission indicates that there is danger for the liquor trade. Here we see one of the results of prohibition, which placed in the hands of criminals the whole of this enormous and profitable business. The country will suffer for years the consequences of that noble experiment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
