<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-03-02">Mar. 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Streetcar Fare</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-03-02">Mar. 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">STREETCAR FARE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A proposal by the Surface Lines to increase the fare from five to six cents has been before the State Public Utilities Commission for some time. The Commission is taking ample time to render a decision. When the elevated railroads requested an increase in the rate of their fares, the answer of the Commission was not long in forthcoming, it suggested a compromise. The elevated roads asked for a seven-cent fare; the Commission allowed a six-cent fare. But even this slight increase caused the riding public to enter a strong protest, and the general indignation may have given the State authorities food for thought, although they probably pay little or no attention to public opinion. At all events, they do not appear to be so ready to grant the request of the streetcar companies.</p>
   <p>It is true, the case of the streetcar company differs from that of the elevated roads. The latter operate their lines to the general satisfaction of the public. Of course, there is room for various improvements in the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1310.jpg" n="2"/>transportation which they offer. But the public, which uses the elevated day by day, feels that the elevated companies, as well as their employees, have the will to do their part in making transportation as good as possible. With reference to the Surface Lines the public has often had reason to doubt that they have good intentions. Or does it not recollect the great promises which the company made when the renewal of the franchise was up for consideration? Or does the public not remember the scandalous watering of stocks--the chief cause of the present mess? Did it not witness the recent endeavors of the company to direct the funds which the city is gathering for the purchase of the streetcar lines to some other purpose? Is it not known that the franchise of the company will terminate in eight years, and that officials of the Lines are doing everything they possibly can, either to obtain an advantageous renewal of the franchise, or to get as much money as they can from the riding public during the eight-year period?</p>
   <p>Bad blood was created when the elevated roads' request for a six-cent fare was granted; greater indignation will result from an increase in streetcar fares. For the public is convinced that the transportation which the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1311.jpg" n="3"/>streetcar companies furnish at present is not worth even five cents. It may be that their income is not sufficient to cover their costs now, a thing they no doubt wish. But that is by no means a reason to expect the public to pay an increase of forty per cent. In those years when the streetcar companies enjoyed a very good income, they gave no thought to returning a part of their large dividends to the users of their lines. Why then should the riding public now be burdened with an increase in fare--just to restore the dwindling dividends of the corporations to their former amount? "What-soever a man soweth, that shall he also reap." The streetcar companies, too, will find that that is true. The time when our citizens permitted themselves to be fleeced without objecting, and perhaps were amused by the cunning of the fleecer, is gradually passing.</p>
   <p>There is a rumor in local financial circles that the State Commission will reject the proposal of the streetcar companies and will suggest that they make up for the deficit which has accumulated during the past few years by using a part of the so-called "renewal fund," for which three million <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1312.jpg" n="4"/>dollars are reserved every year, and which at present is supposed to amount to nine million dollars. That would not be a bad solution, for the streetcar companies have made no renewals worth mentioning during the past few years, and if the franchise is not renewed the companies will hardly spend three million dollars a year for renewals during the remaining eight years. And a rumored restriction of transfer privileges would be such an evident retrogression that it should not be even thought of.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
