<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-30">Dec. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Divorce Mills</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0822</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0822.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-30">Dec. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE DIVORCE MILLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to a recently published annual report about the activities of our courts, 12,895 petitions for divorce were filed in 1917, against 9,895 of such cases in 1916. During the current year this figure may be as large as 15,000. At present, 5,000 pending cases grace the calendars of our Superior and County Courts.</p>
   <p>This is not a pleasant picture, and it sheds a bad light on the matrimonial ethics of our metropolis, even if we have the dubious consolation that in other parts of the country the situation is no better in this respect.</p>
   <p>A law which has been suggested by our professional reformers, to prohibit marriages between persons under twenty-five years of age, would be <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0823.jpg" n="2"/>nonsensical and against the laws of nature. It would meet with about the same success as those decrees in some European states during the last century, which made it impossible for any couple to marry legally unless they possessed a certain amount of earthly goods. Since the poor did not have this amount of property, they used to live together, without the sanction of the law, as long as both parties desired. This created complications and legal problems about the welfare of the children. The courts were overburdened and standards of morality suffered in those countries. Consequently more reasonable matrimonial laws had to be enacted.</p>
   <p>A law requiring that a person be twenty-five years old before he could marry would create similar and more vicious conditions in this country. The age limit in itself would not be very bad were it not for the fact that we have no uniform marriage laws in the United States. If a young couple found obstacles in one state they would just move to a neighboring state where the laws were not as strict; and unscrupulous officials <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0824.jpg" n="3"/>can always be found to unite the young people for a fee even if they are scarcely more than children and do not know what life is all about. The parents are then often confronted with an accomplished fact to which they are compelled to give their blessing, out of fear of the consequences.</p>
   <p>If, instead of the numerous state laws, we had a uniform federal law for marriages; a law that included a residential requirement, that is, a law which provided for a certain period of residence in a locality for at least one of the parties; a law, furthermore, which placed officials or clergymen under strict regulations--then divorce suits would very soon be on the decrease.</p>
   <p>These unhappy marriages are also due, to a large extent, to the wrong kind of education, to pampering a child's bad temper, which makes him wilful and leads to a lack of respect for his parents, and this lack of respect for his parents is also closely related to the unfortunate lack of moral teaching in our schools.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
