<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-03-26">March 26, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The People Rise! Thousands Tried to Get Admission after 2:30 in Vain.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0521</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0521.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-03-26">March 26, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE PEOPLE RISE! THOUSANDS TRIED TO GET ADMISSION AFTER 2:30 IN VAIN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the pretext of fighting vice and crime, which are detested by all law abiding citizens, war has been declared in Chicago upon the most honorable unions of a social, educational, and benevolent character. They are compared and considered equivalent to the lowest types of dancing halls and criminal vice dens and they are deprived of their old and undisputed rights to dispense wine and halt beverages to their own members and friends. We are of the opinion that the laws and ordinances against vice dens never have been made to be utilized against social clubs of the people. We contend that social gathering of the young people and their parents should be developed and promoted and not forbidden. Vice and crime will only be advanced if these young people are driven to the pleasure, in which their parents do not participate. We do not have the wish to criticize the views of others, but claim the right to describe for ourselves, which kind of creation and social entertainment is best for our children. We therefore protest in a mass-meeting against any attempt to rob us of our right to amuse ourselves in our own way and we demand from the city <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0522.jpg" n="2"/>Council a change in the saloon license ordinance of the kind that the Mayor of the city is empowered to give: Special licenses for the temporary sale of wine and beer at all real social 5 th rings of a lawful and honorable character. We also ask the Legislature of Illinois to give the towns and villages the absolute right to regulate the customs and pleasures of their inhabitants in their own way and repeal all laws, which are opposed to the natural rights of the people in the execution of decent entertainments.</p>
   <p>Those are the resolutions made yesterday by one of the largest protest meetings ever having taken place in Chicago composed of clubs, associations, lodges, individual citizens, etc. The Mayor and States Attorney were not present and only five of the seventy council members had accepted the invitation. More than a million citizens have joined in the protest against the interference of a small group of hypocrites in their time-honored customs of life. Never before in Chicago has there been such a parade of law abiding citizens of all nationalities. From all directions of the town they marched with their music corps and flags to the Armory Hall. At 2 o'clock every seat was taken. The first club marching in with music and flags, numbering about a thousand men was the Mutual Aid Association of <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0523.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago. All other associations, clubs, and lodges followed. The Gottfried Brewery on their Brewery had the words: Michel make Up", which net with much applause.</p>
   <p>The meeting had no political aspect. It was the intention of a small minority to force their ideas on the majority of the people. Mr. John Koelling then introduced Emil Hoechster, speaker of the Chicago Turner Club, amid great applause. He spoke about the motto: " The German Michel Has Awakened." He was followed by the president, Wilhelm Rapp. He welcomed the audience in the name of personal liberty and human rights. The next speech was by Lebowsky. He said eternal vigilance is the price of liberty. The English press has suppressed public opinion. It is not the sale and enjoyment of alcoholic drinks that is responsible for crime and vice, but pure hypocrisy. The cause cannot be found in innocent pleasure meetings of law abiding citizens, but more so in large corporations, which, under a moral cover plant the seeds for future crimes. Prof. Joseph O. Kral said, that in Russia every host, who invites some private friends and guests to a drinking party, must have the permission of the police, but in the free State of Illinois, if a lodge will entertain some friends no permission is given at all.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0524.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"The Bohemian song, gymnastic, and welfare clubs which I represent consist of law-abiding citizens, mostly workingmen who are not found in prisons and poor houses and who love liberty. Citizens you have the power in your hand by not voting for the enemies of liberty, but rather vote for the Socialists; then you are sure of the preservation of your liberty. Mr. Samuel Alshuler declared that the meeting is non-political but only for independent citizens of all classes. He also said that the American Constitution assures liberty and independence and equal rights for all classes. There is no connection between the citizens assembled here and the criminal element. We are all for the obedience of the laws, but not for such laws which are against the liberties of law-abiding citizens. We are for the individual right of everyone who wishes to amuse himself in his own way as long as he does not interfere with the rights and the liberties of his neighbor."</p>
   <p>Council member Werno said that there never was a protest meeting of that importance and that magnitude as the present. He thinks that this protest will be successful.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
