<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
      <date when="1935-07-17">July 17, 1935</date>.
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    
                    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
     <date when="1935-07-17">July 17, 1935</date>.
    </bibl>
   </div>
   
  </front>
  <body>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1174.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>to gain control over a great number of gigantic enterprises which greatly influence the economic life of the whole country--and thus the welfare of millions of people.</p>
   <p>It is evident that this problem will have to be solved some time.</p>
   <p>The President, however, has acquiesced in the present situation, at least for the time being. Perhaps he sees that the people have not yet been sufficiently informed on this matter. Perhaps he hopes to attain his end in some other way. It is also very gratifying to know that he did insist upon passage of the bill to tax large incomes and inheritances. It was generally presumed that the plan involved was premature. That assumption proved to be correct.</p>
   <p>Perhaps Henry Ford should be given credit for opening the eyes of the administration with reference to this point. He emphasized that he had little or no wealth of which his heirs could pay a part to the Government in the form of an inheritance tax. It is plain that this statement is correct. Ford is <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1175.jpg" n="3"/>perhaps the world's most important industrialist; but it is evident that he has no large sums of cash on hand. What would he do with it? He needs only enough cash to pay for raw materials and labor. The greater part of his wealth is in the form of factories, railroads, mines, and gigantic sales organizations.</p>
   <p>Thus, if at Mr. Ford's death the Government demanded a large portion of his wealth in the form of an inheritance tax, his heirs would, of course, have to get the money from banks, and would be obliged to mortgage their inherited property in order to secure the loan. Even the first inheritance tax could possibly place the business in the hands of the bankers. A second death would certainly put the enterprise under the control of the "money men". [Translator's note: The sentence lacks clarity. No doubt the writer meant to say that the death of one of the heirs, or rather the tax due upon the death of one of the heirs, would have disastrous results]. This is just what the President wishes to avoid.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1176.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The planned inheritance tax is based on the erroneous assumption that wealth consists chiefly of cash money. However, cash is but a small fraction of our wealth. The greater part consists of tangible securities and would gradually come under the control of money lenders, if the planned inheritance tax law was enforced in its original form. In this connection we might call attention to the agricultural inheritance laws which are now being enforced in Germany. It is only through these laws, which give the oldest son "special" preference when an estate is divided, that the independence of farmers is maintained. Otherwise, all rural property would have come into the hands of bankers long ago.</p>
   <p>Now the President has declared that he is willing to put the Inheritance Tax bill aside until the next session of Congress. Probably it is possible to enforce a law providing for a larger tax on great wealth. However, the law in its original form could not be enforced. Any decided attempt to enforce it would be followed by catastrophe, as Ford showed. By the way, it is very significant that the Secretary of the Treasury, Henry Morgenthau, did not <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1177.jpg" n="5"/>say a word in answer to the objections voiced by Mr. Ford.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
