<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-11-24">Nov. 24, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">American Servility</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0995</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0995.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-11-24">Nov. 24, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN SERVILITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the most repugnant features of the so-called high-class English-Americans is the way they cringe before European royalty and members of old aristocratic families. To get an audience with or bow before royalty is their highest ambition. Should the English or the German royal courts deny them this privilege, a potentate of even the most insignificant little domain on the map will do, so long as it is a king to whom they bow. And when all attempts to bow to a sovereign prove hopeless, then they insist on being presented to members of some aristocratic family. This, however, is not the worse; this same spirit of servility is displayed by many American newspapers.</p>
   <p>The papers of Cincinnati are at present overwhelmed with joy because Miss Zimmerman, the daughter of a local millionaire, who married the Duke of Manchester, is being escorted home by her bridegroom. The Times-Star, one of the important daily papers published in Cincinnati, printed <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0996.jpg" n="2"/>in large and heavy type and article from which we translate the following:"Cincinnati will pay due tribute to its own native born duchess; and as for the Duke of Manchester, a royal reception is planned by all the clubs of the city."</p>
   <p>How shameful and disgusting is this cringing and bowing before European nobility. There is no doubt that this worship of titles on the part of some citizens of this great Republic will not be appreciated by the duke of Manchester. Although of royal blood, he is a full-fledged and conscientious journalist, a career which he entered after he spent the money left him by his family. He has thus proved to be a man of fine character, who prefers honest work to any position at the royal court.</p>
   <p>It is reported that in the near future the duke and duchess of York will visit Canada and the United States. It would be unnecessary to add, that a certain class of our citizens dream already of grand receptions, and of royal favoritism. The English-American press pursues the same policy.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0997.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is regrettable that Mr. Choate, the American Ambassador to England, who, in accord with the advice from Washington kept strict silence for a considerable time, has resumed the royal lick spittling. The occasion was his recent Lincoln lecture in Edinburgh, which, by the way, was a credit to him, when he recalled with feeling and simplicity the many letters Lincoln addressed to the mothers of those soldiers who had given their lives for their country. At the close of the lecture, he could not refrain himself from showing his worship of the English crown and said: "Your own gracious sovereign could not find more tender words of comfort for the mothers of those boys, who, while serving in Her Majesty's army, lost their lives on the battlefield." Drunk with servile ecstasy, this Choate was evidently not aware of the outrage which he committed against the fallen heroes of the Union, when he put them on the same pedestal with "Tommy Atkins," the infamous mercenary of the English army. Neither was it common good sense when he compared our sacred war, fought for the preservation of the Union, with the atrocious war England was waging against the Boers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0998.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>High above this cringing, servitude was that true American Benjamin Franklin, who amidst the stupendous splendor of the French court never hesitated to display his pride and manliness before the royal Throne. He was the image of a simple but great Republican.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
