<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-22">June 22, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">An Expensive Luxury</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1178</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1178.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-22">June 22, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">AN EXPENSIVE LUXURY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A special senate committee, entrusted with the investigation of the much-disputed system of subsidies from which private steamship companies are supposed to have derived enormous sums as loans and direct financial contributions to keep them going, has just published a report in which it supplies date that may lead to sharp debates in both houses of Congress.</p>
   <p>The report designates the payment of subsidies to ships, as it is done under the present system, as a "very expensive luxury on the part of the American government". These payments may seem patriotic, but, by and large, their aim is nothing but the enrichment of the ship companies in question.</p>
   <p>As a particularily crass example, the report brings the fact that the International Kercantile Marine Company, in which Vincent Astor is deeply <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1179.jpg" n="2"/>interested financially, received subsidies totalling $1,700,000 for the steamer Leviathan at a time when the ship was no longer in service. Many have protested against the paying of these subsidies, but they have been paid all the same.</p>
   <p>The report of the Senate committee lays special emphasis on the fact that there has never been an effective government control over the system of subsidies. The navigation authorities have been paying millions of dollars under certain contracts, the illegality of which is beyond all question.</p>
   <p>"Any business undertaking," the report continues, "which receives subsidies from the government, expects from the latter the necessary capital for its operation and overhead, either all or nearly all in cash. With its subsidies, the government covers all or most of the financial losses of that business undertaking, but has absolutely no voice in its management. The latter is wholly under the control of private persons. Our government may have supplied more than half of the entire capital invested in the undertaking, but has <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1180.jpg" n="3"/>less to say about its management than private stockholders."</p>
   <p>The committee sums up the results of its investigation with the words: "The existing system of subsidies is a sad and miserable blunder. Many of its proponents have proved to be persons who, directly or indirectly, have profited (or still profit) financially from the system."</p>
   <p>The committee then recomends that the entire American merchant fleet and its management be taken over by the government. That that could be done easily is evident from the fact that, in 1927, at a time when their management was entirely under the control of the government, the United States Lines showed a net profit of $404,017.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding the example cited, one cannot help having doubts as to the applicability of the recommendation, especially when one is reminded of the costly experiences the government had, during the war years, with the management of the railroads. But it cannot be denied that something is <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1181.jpg" n="4"/>quite wrong with the present system of paying subsidies. All further assaults upon the pocketbooks of the taxpayers should be quickly and permanently stopped.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
