<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-21">Jan. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A Necessary Supplement</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0391</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0391.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-21">Jan. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A NECESSARY SUPPLEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>B. Hartmann of Belleville, Illinois, a subscriber to the Abendpost, makes the following noteworthy recommendations as a supplement to the Eighteenth Amendment:</p>
   <p>"The United States of America can be proud of its legal morality, and it and its democracy may serve as an example of virtue for the whole world. But we, as citizens of this country, must go a step further, since morality can be enforced only through laws. Therefore we move that the following laws be proposed in Congress or in the Legislature:</p>
   <p>'Whereas immorality is spreading, not only among men, but also among women, and</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0392.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>'Whereas this evil condition will in time bring ruin upon our country if the law does not immediately interfere,</p>
   <p>'We, therefore, make the following proposals:</p>
   <p>'1. No pharmacy of any sort shall be permitted to exist in any part of the United States, dating from the day when this law becomes effective.</p>
   <p>'2. It shall be unlawful to sell of give away any medicaments or patent medicines through merchants or private persons, dating from the day when this law becomes effective.</p>
   <p>'3. It shall be unlawful for merchants or private persons to sell or give away surgical instruments or any instruments which can be used on the human body for any purpose, dating from the day when this law becomes effective.</p>
   <p>'4. The articles named in paragraphs 2 and 3 shall be administered by <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0393.jpg" n="3"/>authorized physicians only; every medicine and every instrument must be promptly recorded, as must also the name of the recipient.</p>
   <p>'5. All physicians shall be under the control of the State. The State shall appoint examiners who shall inspect the books and laboratories of physicians four times a year at unannounced hours.</p>
   <p>'6. Physicians or other citizens who prescribe medicines or provide instruments which are harmful to, or kill an unborn child, shall be looked upon, and punished, as criminals. They shall serve from five to twenty-five years in the penitentiary.</p>
   <p>'7. Women who are guilty of abortion shall be guilty of first-degree murder.' "The reason for these proposals? It has been proved beyond any doubt that druggists and peddlers are selling medicines and instruments which are used <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0394.jpg" n="4"/>to cause abortion and for other crimes. Thus there is grave danger that the negroes will soon outnumber the white people in the United States. As far as our women in general are concerned, they have ceased to be Christians, for the command of God, 'Be fruitful and multiply,' is not only generally disregarded but also circumvented by the killing of the foetus. Furthermore, doctors, druggists, and peddlers are selling poisons, patent medicines, and instruments, which are often used to commit murder or suicide. It is hardly necessary to enumerate all of these poisonous medicines, such as opium, morphine, cocaine, hashish, and so forth, the use of which often results in insanity or death, and which are especially dangerous because they are generally used in secret. The above laws should, therefore, be strictly enforced in order to preserve the morality of our people, especially that of our women."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
