<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-12-20">December 20, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">A King of the German Sort.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0978</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0978.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1908-12-20">December 20, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">A KING OF THE GERMAN SORT.</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many of our esteemed fellow citizens of the Anglo-Saxon race view the strong immigration of the foreign speaking population of the country as a danger to American institutions. Especially, do they think, even if it is not expressed in plain language, that the danger is from the Germans. We must not misconstrue their meaning. If we want to judge them by the proverbial German justice, we must say that they are right. It would not be honest and a little cowardly, if we denied, that we actually have damaged some of the so-called American institutions, openly fought them, and are endeavoring to retard others.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0979.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If, in many places, the quiet Puritanical Sabbath is lively, and, in other localities, had to give way to the more or less wet Sunday, one must thank the Germans for it. Prohibition, another would-be American institution, can sing the same song. Wherever their power is disputed, wherever there is fighting against them, the Germans are to be found in the foreground.</p>
   <p>The other foreigners are but following, so to speak. It is the same in many other spheres. The strong influence, Which the Germans exercise upon American Institutions, can be observed most clearly in the winter months. Whoever looks around in those December days, and possesses just a little intelligence, must say to himself, they are right, positively right, with their fear of the Germans, their worry about American institutions.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0980.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The most distinguished of all American institutions is the democratic republic, yet, it is true that for almost four weeks in every year, a King rules here, and the free American people humbly bend their knees, before this King, and acknowledge his reign unconditionally. Where did this King come from? The Germans brought him over, and he himself is in all his actions and looks so unmistakably German, that he could not deny his origin if he tried ten times. We all know him, and we know how he looks. The children especially know him well. He has a good-natured, benevolent face, which is framed by a long, white beard, other-wise, there is no sign of old age. On the contrary, it speaks of enjoyment, of life, and harmless pleasures, and hearty eating and drinking. Whether he still has plenty of hair on his head, nobody knows. An elderly gentleman, a well known German of Chicago, passed a few children lately, who nudged each other, and said: "Look, here goes the Christman Man, but he is not dressed up yet."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0981.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>He did not have any hair on his head. He had the typical the merry beard,the merry and benevolent eyes, and the red checks, which are so characteristic. Otherwise it could not have happened to him. The hair is not important to our King. because it can't be seen anyhow, as he is continually wearing a crown. A strange crown; nothing else but a comfortable cap, pulled over the ears. This head piece, does not have a very kingly effect, but in very practical in rainy, snowy and frosty weather, and those usually occur during the winter. Also the other piece of his official costume, show is practical sense, although they approach somewhat the regulation of a king's costume.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
