<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-03-06">March 6, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">Negro and German</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1071</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1071.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-03-06">March 6, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">NEGRO AND GERMAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whoever would have predicted 26 years ago, at the time of James Buchanan's presidency, that the next Democratic President would give the preference to a Negro before an old tried white Democrat at the nomination to an important office in the Federal District, Columbia, would have been called crazy. But it has happened under the first Democratic President since Buchanan. On this fact alone, the extent of the revolution can be measured that took place since in the conditions of this country. But of course there is another side to this affair.</p>
   <p>One of the best offices in the District of Columbia is the one of Recorder of Deeds. President Grant was noble enough to put this office like many others into the hands of a German of the District, namely of Mr. Simon Wolf, who occupied the position during both terms of Grant.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1072.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>President Hayes replaced him by another white man from New Orleans, by the name of Sheridan. President Garfield turned over this office to a resident of the District, namely, the famous Mulatto Frederick Douglass, who is a real estate owner there. President Cleveland kept the Mulatto for an entire year in undisturbed possession of the office. On January 5, 1886, in a grateful letter to the President, Douglass proposed his retirement from this office on March 1.</p>
   <p>The great majority of the Negroes of the District of Columbia owns no property and therefore it was expected that an able white man of the District would become the successor. Such a man was found in the prominent German Democratic resident Louis Schade. He was highly recommended to President Cleveland, but now this old Democrat experiences the painful disappointment to see himself pushed back by a Democratic President behind a Negro, whom he picked up somewhere in New York State.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1073.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Cleveland's nominee, James C. Matthews, is not like Douglass, a national celebrity, but a shyster lawyer and local politician in Albany, N. Y.</p>
   <p>By preferring a third-rate Negro to a "Schade", or the Negroes in general to the Germans, Cleveland brings ladness to the old corrupt circle in Washington, that" Schade's Sentinel" was fighting for years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
