<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1918-12-08">Dec. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">After the Saloon--What?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0408</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0408.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1918-12-08">Dec. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AFTER THE SALOON--WHAT?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>National Prohibition, if it ever becomes a permanent institution, will bring about a thorough change in our habits in more than one way. In their crusade against the saloons, the apostles of abstinence are guided primarily by the assumption that men visit saloons only to satisfy their craving for alcoholic beverages. But this is only partly true.</p>
   <p>In the daily life of ever the best-trained husband there are moments which he cannot spend at home, and even the busiest business man occasionally has some spare time or needs some hours of recreation. Since man is a creature of habit, it seems quite natural for him, at such times, to visit places where he can hope to find congenial people. The saloon was of importance to the male sex not so much as a drinking place but as a meeting <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0409.jpg" n="2"/>place. There a man was able to meet his business friends and to act as their host without the outlay of much cash; or to pass the time away while waiting for the return of a customer who was unexpectedly absent; or to hang around during bad weather. The saloon was not only the "club of the little fellow," but who also frequented by well-to-do people. Its disappearance will leave a gap in public life that will be hard to fill, and something will have to take its place. The devising of a substitute must be left to the American public and to the tastes and desires which they will manifest under the new conditions. It is possible that the cafe, of the Paris or Vienna type, which is open to both sexes, will come into favor; or perhaps the Spanish bodega will be preferred which, over there, serves simultaneously as saloon, restaurant, delicatessen, wineshop, and place of gossip, and which is visited by men and women alike.</p>
   <p>The disappearance of beer and intoxicating liquors will saddle the barons <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0410.jpg" n="3"/>and kings of our beverage industry with the task of manufacturing fluids which can be consumed in great quantities without deleterious effects, and which are refreshing and wholesome at the same time. The soda water which has been dispensed in this country for more than Fifty years lacks various qualities which would make it a suitable substitute for the beverages now prohibited. Besides, it is primarily a summer drink. Then, too, as they are now set up, the places where soda fountains are to be found will hardly do for public meeting places. They are designed merely for the quick consumption of soft beverages and give almost no opportunity for private conversation. Besides--and this fact is emphasized even in a magazine favoring Prohibition--even first-class soda water "emporiums" could not stand any comparison with first-class bars as far as cleanliness, service, and comfort are concerned. The man who tends such a bar would not dream of putting unappetizing drinks before his customers; his glasses must sparkle and his uniform and laundry must be white as snow. In the clean glass he is offering his guests, delirium tremens may be lurking, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0411.jpg" n="4"/>but, on the other hand, the dirty glass of the soda clerk may contain the germ of a deadly disease.</p>
   <p>In the United States, as in England, women's associations and organizations founded by clergymen have tried to interest the workers and the so-called little man in coffeehouses and teahouses especially designed for them. But nearly all such enterprises were forced to close their doors due to lack of customers. This failure must be attributed largely to the dislike of the average American for anything that looks like regimentation or charity, especially when he is willing and able to pay for his needs with cold cash.</p>
   <p>The problem, "After the saloon--what?" will be solved sooner or later. In order that this solution may be satisfactory for the great majority of the people, a place has to be created where the man who is waiting for a friend or a train may find warmth, comfort, cleanliness, and <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0412.jpg" n="5"/>wholesome refreshments; a place which is half way between a cheap restaurant and an expensive one; where the guest feels neither too shabby and cheap nor too extravagant and pompous; a place which has neither the hurried atmosphere of a soda fountain nor the comfort of a club; neither the viciousness of the saloon nor the cold formality of a church-sponsored coffeehouse, but embodies the advantages of both. And maybe this new type of place will eventually enjoy the same popularity as the "saloon", which today is pictured by its adversaries as a place of damnation and iniquity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
