<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-04-05">Apr. 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Trial Conducted in German</title><title level="a" type="sub">Judge Sabath Conducts Entire Divorce Proceedings in German language.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0814</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0814.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-04-05">Apr. 5, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">TRIAL CONDUCTED IN GERMAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">Judge Sabath Conducts Entire Divorce Proceedings in German language.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the first time in a very long while, a court trial held in the County Building was conducted in German from beginning to end, as Mrs. Emma Pflaum of 1204 North Avenue, Maywood, appeared before Judge Sabath to ask for a divorce from her husband, Henry Pflaum.</p>
   <p>Neither the plaintiff nor the witnesses could speak English. It also seemed that not one of the attorneys had sufficient knowledge of the German language to overcome their clients' handicap and to bring about an understandable presentation of the case. Judge Sabath, who is known to speak eight languages other than English just as fluently as he does the latter, cut the Gordian knot by immediately undertaking to personally conduct the questioning of the plaintiff and the witnesses, using the German language only.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0815.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mrs. Pflaum stated that she married Henry Pflaum on February 21 of this year after he had told her that he had been divorced from his wife whom he had left behind in Germany. But when she asked for documentary proof after the wedding had taken place, it turned out that Attorney Jeffe, at the behest of Mr. Pflaum, had merely instituted divorce proceedings, and that a divorce had not yet been granted. For this reason Pflaum is still undivorced.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Pflaum based her claim to a divorce on this fact, stating that she married Pflaum in the belief that he was divorced, but that in view of the above findings their marriage had not been legally consummated. Asked by the judge whether she intended to charge Pflaum with bigamy or whether she would remarry him after the dissolution of his first marriage, the plaintiff remarked that she had not yet made up her mind about her future attitude in the matter.</p>
   <p>After the questioning of the witnesses was concluded, Judge Sabath ordered the annulment of the marriage between Emma Pflaum and Henry Pflaum.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
