<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-02-09">February 9th, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Unexpected Change. United Associations Intend to Convert the Signers of the Petition.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-02-09">February 9th, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Unexpected Change. United Associations Intend To Convert The Signers Of The Petition.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, 25 writers were entrusted with copying the 74806 signera and addresses. The petition is not to be contested by the United Association, said Alfred S. Austrian, their attorney; Our only object is to mail them campaign literature. Mr. Austrian in speaking to a representative of the Abendpost gave this explanation. We will not attack the petition of the "Anti-saloon League," not even if an accurate examination shows that it contains 20,000 names of persons who are not legally qualified to sign. This affair is to be definitely settled. To enable the copying of this petition, the board of election officials, divided it into 25 equal parts. Superintendent James K. Shields, of the Anti-Saloon League dissented strenuously but his objection was denied. However, he will have two if his agents watch the proceedings. The United States Manufacturers and Merchants Association concluded yesterday, to join in the fight for the maintenance of personal liberty. This afternoon, a meeting will be held by the executives of the saloon-keeper's Association, where campaign plans will be discussed. The Anti-Saloon League and Associated temperance <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0476.jpg" n="2"/>Societies will have a meeting to-morrow evening, at Willard Hall to prepare for the fray. W. A. Brubaker, chief of the Prohibition-party leaders in this county, issued a challenge to Pres. George B. Pfeiffer of the United Associations, to meet him in a debate on the saloon closing question.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
