<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1929-01-27">Jan. 27, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The German Society of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0914</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0914.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1929-01-27">Jan. 27, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN SOCIETY OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Society was originated in 1905 by Dr. Carl Beck, Carl Schurz, Franz Boas, Dr. A. Jacobi, Herman A. Kudlich, Dr. Willi Meyer, Edward Uhl, Herman Ridder, Edward S. Adams, and Everett Wheeler as a national organization of persons who were interested in the advancement of cultural relations between German speaking countries and the United States. Its object is to create, especially among Americans not of German descent, an understanding for the new Germany and Austria by means of lectures, publications, and other tactics. This aim shall not be attained either by politics or propaganda, but merely by means of education.</p>
   <p>The supporters of the German Society are well known personalities as: Ferdinand W. Lafrentz, Dr. Lit. Ferdinand Thum, Julius P. Meyer, director of the Hamburg - America Line, Charles Nagel of St. Louis, the well known attorney and secretary of Commerce under President Taft, Oswald Garrison Villard the proprietor and publisher of the Nation, Professor Franz Boas, Dr. Hugo Lieber, Dr. Carl Schmidt, Eberhard Faher, Rudolph Pagenstecher, Edgar Uhlein, and others.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0915.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The German Society, among others makes it possible to continue the publication of the Year books of the German-American Hostorical Society, edited by Professor Julius Goebel. The society also donates prizes for the best translation of German literature into the English language, it arranges lectures, and supplies German and Austrian libraries with American books and periodicals.</p>
   <p>The society annually bestows scholarships to American professors to enable them to attend German universities. But the most important work of the German Society consists of their recommendation of the reintroduction of the German language into American high schools. Considering the fact that in view of the still existing prejudice of parents and pupils and the lethargy of the school administration the German lessons have so far not been introduced to their fullest extent. The complaints of American professors in regard to the inability of their students to make the desired progress, because of lack of the absolutely necessary knowledge of the German language in medicine. chemistry, national economy, and history, the German Society through Prof. W. Heuser of Columbia University arranged a circular questionnaire to a number of prominent Americans of all professions, to investigate <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0916.jpg" n="3"/>the sentiment in regard to the reintroduction of German lessons in the high schools of America.</p>
   <p>The result of this circular was extra-ordinarily favorable. Not a single negative answer came. On the contrary, the majority expressed a desire to restore the German lessons to their rightful place in accordance with its importance....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
