<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-13">Dec. 13, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Struggling Speakeasy</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0176</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0176.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-13">Dec. 13, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">STRUGGLING SPEAKEASY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A rough estimate of Chicago's speakeasies would put their number at about five thousand, and all of them do a thriving business. They sell alcoholic beverages such as wine, beer, or liquor, which they manufacture or import illegally.</p>
   <p>They are, as a rule, places of business operating without a permit from the city, and from profits they are making, they do not have to pay one cent in taxes to the city's treasury. You can easily put yourself in their place, knowing how well they must feel. They are now threatened by Mayor Cermak with a war of extinction. All speakeasies are to vanish.</p>
   <p>The mayor explained a plan which this week will be submitted to the city council for approval. The police captains were instructed to round up all <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0177.jpg" n="2"/>speakeasies in their districts and to close them. He has in mind to have the various police districts controlled by especially trustworthy secret service men. If it should turn out that his orders are not obeyed implicitly, then he will make the police captains personally responsible, and treat them accordingly.</p>
   <p>On first sight this plan of the mayor, who is a determined adversary of prohibition, is somewhat strange. But he will be agreed with all the same. Taking into account that the legalized sale of beer is a matter of the near future, it will be easy to conceive that the five thousand illegal beer joints will enter into unsavory competition with the licensed distributors, unless they are put out of existence before beer becomes lawful. It is, therefore, no expedient to save prohibition as planned by Mayor Cermak; it is rather a protective measure for the legitimate restaurants which are being licensed by the city and which have been paying their license fees into the city's treasury even during the period of prohibition, although they sold only <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0178.jpg" n="3"/>lemonade and beer, which was beer in name only. Theirs is a rightful claim for a full protection against dishonest competition on the part of the speakeasies and, from the looks of things, they are going to get it. The illegitimate sale was a substitute planted during the time of prohibition. In case beer and wine again become legal, this substitute will have to disappear. On the one hand to leave legitimate business unmolested, on the other hand to get in the taxes which is only fair and just to expect from the legalization of beer and wine. That bootleggers are taxpayers of no great value is a known fact. To put them out of commission as quickly as possible is a public duty. It is to be hoped that, in doing so, a speedy and thorough job will be accomplished in Chicago and in the whole country. Considering the close friendships existing between bootleggers and influential politicians, it might not be so easy to winnow them out.</p>
   <p>Mayor Cermak further plans an increase in the license fee paid by all restaurants in the city selling lemonade and near beer. To press the increase would be, at the moment, a burden on small businesses, because there would be immediate <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0179.jpg" n="4"/>profits for them from the elimination of the speakeasies. It would be quite different if the increase should take place after the sale of wine and beer becomes legalized. Then, naturally, business in restaurants will rise, and it will be an easy thing for them to pay higher taxes for their permits. Care and foresight are just as necessary as the ruthless annihilation of the speakeasies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
