<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-27">June 27, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Hugh Johnson's Plans</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1260</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1260.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-06-27">June 27, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">HUGH JOHNSON'S PLANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Hugh Johnson, the director of national industry, has begun to carry out the plan for industrial revival. He states that the plan is not based upon complicated or narrow ideas, but that it is really very simple. He points out that untold numbers of houses in America are vacant, while millions of people have no place to live, because they cannot pay rent. Much more food and clothing are produced than we are able to consume, although prices are much lower than they have been for years. At the same time, there are many people who cannot buy even the most immediate necessities.</p>
   <p>Johnson thinks that these conditions are absurd, and that there must be a solution to the problem. He would solve it by shortening working hours and increasing wages. When industrial corporations made large profits in <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1261.jpg" n="2"/>former years, they used these profits not to decrease working hours or to raise wages, but, in many instances, to enlarge their factories or build new plants, in order to increase production. Johnson considers this policy to be one of the chief causes of overproduction and the resulting depression.</p>
   <p>He thinks that there is a correlation between prices, wages, and production, and that it must be maintained at a certain balance. If one of these factors is increased or decreased in too great a degree, then industry as a whole is thrown out of balance, and there result economic crises such as we are experiencing now. This is a new view. Undoubtedly it is correct, and for many years the Socialists have advocated state ownership of all means of production as a remedy against such crises.</p>
   <p>But Johnson does not want to go that far. Private business is to remain, but the state, or rather the Federal Government, wants to exercise great influence upon the shaping of industry. In the final analysis this idea, too, is socialistic. Johnson figures on a work week of thirty-two hours <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1262.jpg" n="3"/>and a minimum wage of forty-five cents an hour. He considers these working conditions adequate for the cotton industry. The workers would thus receive $14.40 per week. That is a very modest wage. In the South, where living is comparatively cheap, an unmarried man or woman might possibly get along on it. But for a man with a family it would be a "starvation wage".</p>
   <p>But industry does not want to go even that far. It has proposed a weekly wage of ten dollars for the South, and eleven dollars for the North. Of course it would be desirable that Johnson's plan be adopted. But even then, there would be another problem to solve. First, it would have to be determined whether or not the cotton industry could continue to exist under this plan. If the industry could not survive, then Johnson would have to raise the price of its products proportionately. And that, again, would necessarily create another problem: Could industry compete in the world market and in the domestic market if it raised its prices?</p>
   <p>The Government has little or no control over prices in the world market, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1263.jpg" n="4"/>but it could regulate prices in the domestic market in such a way that industry could meet competition. But then two other problems would promptly present themselves. The Government would have to grant the industries which buy the products of the textile industry special price dispensations. Otherwise, they could not survive. The chain is endless, and ultimately the entire economic life....of the country would be placed under the control of the Government.</p>
   <p>And that was very likely the purpose of the Industrial[Recovery] Act from the beginning. But it is very doubtful that such a plan could be carried out. The Industrial Act would necessarily lead to economic dictatorship: there can be no doubt about that. Thus the matter is not as simple as Johnson claims. The aims and fundamental principles are clear and simple, but putting the plan into practice involves many complications. Of course, it must not be overlooked that the plan is to be executed only if industry consents. Thus industry still has a certain amount of freedom.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1264.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The plan is to be in operation for only two years. It would probably be better for the entire economic life of the country if conditions in general would soon improve to such an extent that the Government would not carry out the plan in detail, but would confine itself to mediating between individual groups, and to offering them information and advice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
