<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-07-23">July 23, 1892</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1607</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1607.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-07-23">July 23, 1892</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Abendpost and the Fire Presse, German daily newspapers, were unionized yesterday so far as the printers are concerned. There was great rejoicing as it means that all type on daily papers in Chicago will now be set by union labor. The strike began April 24. The settlement favorable to union labor was achieved by Committeemen M. H. Madden, James A. O'Connell, and George Shilling, of the Trade and Labor Assembly. The terms of settlement are: Seventeen of the present forces are to be taken into Typographical Union No. 9. The scale is to be reconstructed on the basis of Typographical Union No. 16, with an arbitration clause to be inserted in the agreement. Both sides are satisfied. The men are to be taken back according to their senority of employment.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1608.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The publishers will, it is said, retract statements made throwing suspicion on the men for injuring the machinery. The men will retract personal statements made against employers in the heat of the strife. The Committee of Master Printers Association called yesterday morning at the headquarters of the Printers District Council to ask that the difference between the Council and Master Printer McCarthy and Emil Wight who signed the Union scale and then receded from it, be settled. The conference continued behind closed doors until 3 p. m. Nothing was accomplished.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
