<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-03-21">Mar. 21, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Mighty Mass Protest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0461</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0461.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-03-21">Mar. 21, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">MIGHTY MASS PROTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In response to the assault against the personal liberty of Chicago's inhabitants as perpetrated by the nativistic and fanatic temperance element under their advertising poster "Local Option," the German citizens were called to appear at the Auditorium, as requested by the executive of the local branch of the German-American National Association. The upper gallery doors should have been open for admission, since the spacious hall was overcrowded--heads were virtually wedged against heads. Many would have been content to use the upper seatd, when entrance was denied them for lack of available space. A fact which was unprecedented was the union of male chourses--clubs who previously never functioned as a combined unit. It showed German solidarity and created an imposing impression, especially among those who are more intimately conversant with German affairs. Mr. Wilhelm Middel Schulte, that capable and excellent master, arranged an organ concept especially for this occasion.</p>
   <p>Mr. Harry Ruben declared in his speech: "The ambition to influence the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0462.jpg" n="2"/>activities of a lifetime, the customs, yea, even the religious belief, by the application of compulsory laws, is as old as the world's history. The wearing of expensive apparel was equally prohibited in ancient Greece, as in puritanic New England. The Greeks granted exceptions only to the fallen. Soldon created a law forbidding opulent feasts and ornate funerals. Ancient Rome even prescribed to its citizens now many guests they were allowed to invite to a meal.</p>
   <p>During the period of Edward III of England, it was legally forbidden to enjoy more than two courses at a dinner, with the exception of important holidays when three constituted the limit. Just as it was attempted to control the habits of the gluttonour ans the vain, so for centuries a great many were afflicted with the delusion that the use of tobacco would be eliminated by legal means or by the terror incident to the Pope's ban. The Pope's Urban VIII, and Innocent IX, proclaimed with thundering anathema against the weed.</p>
   <p>King James I, of England, zealously opposed to tobacco, described and compared it to the vapors of Hades in his Counter Blest to Tobacco. A Turkish Sultan, <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0463.jpg" n="3"/>Amuret IV, provided an especially cruel death penalty for all smokers. In Germany, church and state were united to fight the "vice" and in Russia, even as recently as the year 1634, if anyone was cauent while smoking then his nose was amputated.</p>
   <p>In connection with this it will surely interest you to know that the American prohibitionists are even now contemplating to take away the poor man's pipe. The national convention of the Prohibition Party, which met on July 3, 1884, declared itself to be opposed to tobacco. In its platform it demands the abolition of the Governmental tax on the grounds that this "vice of humanity" is not a suitable subject for taxation.</p>
   <p>The Compulsory Laws</p>
   <p>The history of compulsory laws against the consumption of alcoholic beverages can also be traced to remote times. In the 11th Century F. C., a Chinese emporor resorted to the extreme method of naving all grane vines destroyed, in the celestial empire. The German people have also ample experience in <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0464.jpg" n="4"/>the realm of such legal manifestations; nevertheless, in honor to their sane mentality we must admit that these laws were not so much concerned with the use of such spirituous beverages as with their abuse. Thus, Karl the Great decreed that monks and preachers must not visit taverns; drunken soldiers were given severe punishment; he prohibited brotherly lodges, where drink was regarded as a statutory duty, and compelled the counts to attend court sessions only when sober. As the habits of "toast-drinking" and rounds of drinks tend to increase intemperance, a great many imperial proclamations were issued to control this evil. As far as I can ascertain, legal prohibition was obtained only onece, after the Thirty Years' War, but then prohibition was concerned only with liquor. The German ruling officials have always been sufficiently educated scientifically and historically, so they do not look for a suitable medium in the form of compulsory litigation as an effective means to eliminate the drink evil. what has been achieved by prohibition in the United States in the United States is too well known to require further elucidation here."</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the speech, Professor Midcel Schulze played the National Hymn of American on the organ, with the combined voices of the chorus on the <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0465.jpg" n="5"/>stage and the assembled audience. More speeches, songs, and finally the resolution.</p>
   <p>All Germans, man for man, use the power of the ballot on April 5. Shame upon him who fails in his duty!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
