<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-03-02">Mar. 2, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[Mass Meeting to Protest Actions of Railroad]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-03-02">Mar. 2, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[MASS MEETING TO PROTEST ACTIONS OF RAILROAD]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night a mass meeting took place in the very large hall of Mr. Friedrich Koch, 584 S. Halsted Street. It was attended by Germans, Irishman, Bohemians and other inhabitants of that part of the 8th Ward which is threatened by the land robbers of the La Salle and Chicago Railroad Company. Alderman Bailey presided, and Alderman Clowrey, together with Messrs. Walsh, Fraser, Gelis and John Reiser (who, living 26 years in Chicago, was called on to make a speech, but excused himself), drew up a set of resolutions for the City Council.</p>
   <p>Mr. Carl Gelis, 596 S. Canal Street, made a speech, in German. He said, he had lived 22 years in the district and owned two large plots at the corner of Stewart Avenue and Meagher Street, and at Stewart Avenue and Wright Street. This district, he said, was largely populated by "foreigners" probably more densely than any other part of the city, and as dear to those who live there as their marble palaces to those who live on Michigan Ave.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1425.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When Henry Greenebaum was alderman of the ward he voted for the grant of the right-of-way on one side of Stewart Avenue to the Chicago, Fort Wayne, and Pittsburgh Line, on condition that the company would keep the other side of the avenue in good repair. This, however, has not been done. Now the other side is to be given to another company. If the companies want the the streets, they should buy the plots. The speculators and monopolists are well able to pay for everything at its full value.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
