<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-09-16">September 16, 1907</date></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0503</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0503.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-09-16">September 16, 1907</date></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Impressive Demonstration Against the Anti-Democratic Charter - Arranged by the Associated Societies" - A Wind-up of the Campaign that Will Be Spoken of in Later Years - Full Agreement Among the Polyglot Foreign Population of Chicago - German Turners and Singers, war Veterans and Lodge Members Demonstrate unitedly as do Also the Bohemians, Danes, Italians, and many other Races-The Proposed Charter is Criticized by Many Prominent Speakers.</p>
   <p>The popular demonstration, planned by the election committee of the United Societies for Self Government, was achieved without much preparation. Most of the member groups had not even had time to decide in a regular way as to their participation in the demonstration. If, despite the encountered difficulties, so large a crowd, at the lowest estimate, about 35,000 - then this may be considered as the best proof of the general antagonism of the masses against the charter plot. Therefore the desired purpose of the planners of the huge assembly has been fully achieved. The boodling politicians and their backers, who aimed to cheat the public with the dastardly charter, know already, that their plan has miscarried scurried, and is doomed to failure, through the vigilance of the United Societies................</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0504.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At 3 PM the main parade, composed of the German Section, formed and was headed by the Kretlow Band, and led by G. von Massow, marched down Washington Street to the Park...................</p>
   <p>About 10,000 arrived thus, many women among them. Almost instantly the large area was nearly filled, so that the speakers with difficulty reached the improvised speakers' platform, - express trucks draped with bunting. New swarms arrived constantly, the Swiss, Italians, Danes, Belgians, Poles, Croatians and, at the end, the Bohemians, who considered it a special honor to have marched all the way from their distant local headquarters, located on the far southwest side.</p>
   <p>In addition to banners, numerous lodges also carried signs with inscriptions, pointing ironically to the ignorance with which the plotters of the charter had re-prosched the "foreigners."</p>
   <p>About 3:15 the national hymn was played by the Kretlow Band. Then Mr. Gloganer in the first address said;</p>
   <p>"The purpose of this demonstration is a double one. we wish to protest against the charter, which is to be foisted upon us, and we also desire to refute the infamous lie that it is only the saloon interests that oppose the charter.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0505.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Here, as elsewhere in the country, it is always the reactionary element, the enemiesof the people, whose tactics it is to cast suspicion on the opposition and to decry its attitude as the result of the wretched "foreigners" ignorance, who without judgement, follow the leadership of the brewers and saloonkeepers. The fact remains that they are trying to suppress us with the charter. We were not consulted in its planning. They insolently rejected our two amendments and now we are also using our rights to reject the bill. If they still maintain that it is the saloon interests to whose standards the people here have rallied, very well, may it be so. The majority of the population then are behind these interests, and it will be shown that it is still the majority, not only in Chicago, but also in Illinois, who decide the issue."</p>
   <p>"Now I introduce to you as the speaker, Judge Barnum:-</p>
   <p>"I will be brief and limit myself only to advising you - Vote against the Charter! Many important reasons weigh against this measure, which originated in such an undemocratic manner. They dared to reject our amendments, which should have been adopted as the unanimous decision of the charter convention of the Associated Societies". By these amendments, there would have been a sensible and legal <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0506.jpg" n="4"/>regulation of the Sunday question, respecting our inherited customs....</p>
   <p>The legislature went out of its way, even to order the reapportioning of the city words, so that the majority will be partly disfranchised, if they wish to enforce their demands. The membership of the council was to be reduced to fifty, so that the minority could elect the majority of the aldermen. The charter reduces the controlling influence of the citizenry and increases that of the ordinary official.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was former Congressman Noonan.......</p>
   <p>"I have conscientiously and thoroughly reviewed the entire charter and I can assure you that it is from top to bottom a betrayal of the citizen's interests. It is a plan to promote the interests of the large corporations and the grafting politicians.......</p>
   <p>From this day, the city of Chicago will owe the "foreigners" its everlasting gratitude, because of the worth of their services in this important demonstration.. The new charter forms a part of the constantly growing danger, which threatens to change our republic into an oligarchy.".......</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0507.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The next speaker, Secretary of the Campaign Board, of the Associated Societies, spoke in German..........."The management of the city park, which concerns us all, is important. Under the new Charter, the Council reserves the power to squander at its will, the beautiful park to the highest bidder, while at present the Park Board may only sell an acre of park land by order of the District Court, provided no objection has been raised by the citizens.... It also delivers the city streets to the mercy of the large corporations. Under the present Act, the City Council has no right to give the railroads any privileges, without the consent of the majority of the property owners affected by the transaction; nor has it the right to lease the city streets to the company for as long as 99 years. The new charter is loaded to the brim with such pitfalls."</p>
   <p>Mr. Otto D. Schiff, the Socialist Speaker, said:</p>
   <p>"As it is well known, the new charter was planned by members of corporations, or those in their employ. Hence, for this reason, we must vote it down"...</p>
   <p>Congressman A. J. Sabath addressed the Bohemians, calling attention to the proposed increase in taxes which will be heavy burden on the middleman and the workers. The shameful attempt by the Republicans to change the election districts so as to disfranchise the masses, must fail.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0508.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>John C. Cervenko also spoke in Bohemian -</p>
   <p>"The income from taxes should be used to benefit the working class as well as the wealthy classes. It should be used for building boulevards and improving the principal business sections."</p>
   <p>The Polish speakers were Mr. N. S. Budzban and Alderman John S. Derpa. (They also criticized the high taxation.)</p>
   <p>Mr. Pesza spoke in Croatian, pointing to the autocratic power of the mayor under the new charter, which must not be tolerated.</p>
   <p>John Ch. Kantor, in a lengthy speech elucidated on the many incongruities of the new charter. He spoke on the autocratic power the mayor would receive. He would have in his hands 25,000 jobs, thus exposing the civil service to danger.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
