<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-05-25">May 25, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">Mass Meeting in Worker's Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1445</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1445.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-05-25">May 25, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">MASS MEETING IN WORKER'S HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following resolutions were adopted in a mass meeting which was held in Worker's Hall last evening:</p>
   <p>1)Resolved, that a safety committee consisting of five members be appointed to aid and advise all German depositors who wish to recover their bank deposits, either by employing friendly tactics, or, if necessary, through lawsuits, and to supply the means necessary to accomplish the purpose. This committee shall have authority to call a mass meeting if it deems it feasible.</p>
   <p>2) Resolved, that we condemn the banking systems which are employed in the United States, and especially the one in vogue in Illinois, as unstable and tending to enrich a few persons, while doing harm to the public in general, particularly to laborers.</p>
   <p>3) Resolved, that gold and silver are the only reliable and valid mediums <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1446.jpg" n="2"/>of exchange, and that there is enough gold and silver in this country to meet the demands of all business.</p>
   <p>4) Resolved, that bankers are obliged by all principles of law and morals to pay depositors the full amounts deposited, and that a refusal to do so is a grave breach of confidence.</p>
   <p>5) Resolved, that we are greatly at the conduct of the German bank of Hoffmann and Gelpcke, which refuses to pay German citizens the full amount of their savings-accounts.</p>
   <p>6) Resolved, that we ask this bank to meet it's obligations in full, and to withhold no discounts from depositors.</p>
   <p>7) Resolved, that it is not our intention, illegally or unnecessarily, to incite the public against the bankers, and we regret to hear that German citizens are applying to the Commissioner of Police for protection for private <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1447.jpg" n="3"/>persons who should have no reason to be afraid of appearing in public and trying to justify their actions.</p>
   <p>8) Resolved, that it is unnecessary and suporfluous that the Commissioner of Police engage special policemen to quell a disturbance that does not exist.</p>
   <p>9) Resolved, that we, the German inhabitants of Chicago, assembled in mass meeting, will recognize only metal as a meding of exchange in doing business with anyone in the future.</p>
   <p>10) Resolved, that from this day on, we will place all existing representative currency, be it issued in this or in other states, on the same level with all other goods which we consider valueless.</p>
   <p>11) Resolved, that the German residents of Illinois are hereby requested most earnestly to indorse and adopt these resolutions.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1448.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The following men were appointed to the committee by the assembly: A. C. Hessing, John G. Gindele, J. C. Kersten, L. Brentano, and Fred Letz.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
