<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-05-16">May 16, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Extending Depression</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1194</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1194.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-05-16">May 16, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">EXTENDING DEPRESSION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A Person who observed the goings on in Congress might suspect that this body had made it its duty to show the world the inferiority of the parliamentary and democratic form of government. If Musselini Hitler and other dictators wanted to convince their dissatisfied subjects that they had nothing to complain about, they would only need to point to what is going on in the Capitol in Washington. There Congress has been in session since the beginning of this year and has an yet taken no action except about the big emergency appropriation bill and the bonus bill. And yet it has on its agenda a whole series of bills, all of which are extremely important, with regard to the economic life of the nation.</p>
   <p>A masterly piece of Legislative bungling was done by the U. S. Senate lately when, with a sudden burst of energy that was as unprecedented as it was violent, it passed a bill prolonging the NRA for another nine months....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1195.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The NRA should remain in force for a few years in its present form, should be changed in a few important particulars, or should be discarded altogether. Such action should have taken place a long time ago: then industry would have known what to expect after June 16, when the law expires. It is generally known that the building industry is the least prosperous section of our national economy. By the NRA the wages of most workers in the building trades have been considerably increased. As long as firms and corporations do not know whether the NRA will remain in force after June 16 or not, they are also unable to tell how much the buildings which they have planned will cost. Consequently they are holding up the awarding of contracts.</p>
   <p>It is undesirably true that industry is prepared to award contracts amounting to billions of dollars, which would bring about a great improvement in business conditions. But industry is delaying this because it does not know what Congress is going to do. The NRA has done much that is good, but it has also done harm. To give only one example: It almost tripled the wages of unskilled workers in the South. On the other hand, it did not triple the income of these workers, almost all of whom are Negroes.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1196.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The sole result is that the Negroes who used to work an average of two to three days per week, now work only one. They get about as much money as they used to receive for two or three days' work. This satisfies them completely and gives them an opportunity to devote six days a week to sweet idleness and the enjoyment of alcohol. The result is that the foremen and white skilled workers cannot make any headway; it takes longer to put up a building, and the cost is increased correspondingly.</p>
   <p>It is obvious that such measures do not tend to increase building activity. Nevertheless, those who wish to build, and are obliged to, would make some arrangements to do so if it were not for this unfortunate uncertainty. One might declare without fear of being charged with exaggeration that, if Congress adjourned today, there would be a big increase in building activity within a few weeks. The plans are completed, the funds are on hand and the contracts could be awarded immediately. But the contracts will not be awarded because the country does not know what Congress is going to do. The worst trouble is not that Congress enacts bad laws, but that it wastes time <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1197.jpg" n="4"/>and leaves the country in uncertainty. Of this obvious truth the people in Washington have plainly not the slightest understanding.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
