<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-11-01">Nov. 1, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Der Wirthsverein</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1485</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1485.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-11-01">Nov. 1, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">DER WIRTHSVEREIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular semimonthly meeting of the Wirthsverein [Tavernkeepers' Association] was held yesterday afternoon at Baum's Hall, Cottage Grove Avenue and 22nd Street. The minutes of the previous session were read and accepted.</p>
   <p>A lengthy debate ensued on the question of whether the Wirthsverein should buy a one-hundred-dollar bond of the Turngemeinde (Turner Association). Some believed that the Wirthsverein, as an association, would not have the right to buy a bond, but that the members would be justified in subscribing on their own accord, since the Wirthsverein was organized for one purpose only: "To fight prohibition!" Others in the assembly had a more liberal attitude. However, all agreed that the Turnhalle (Turner Hall) should be supported. The most convincing argument in favor of the Turnhalle was that the Turngemeinde was "always on the job" when action was needed to fight prohibition. The Turners and tavernkeepers were allies. Finally, the motion was passed that the Wirthsverein should buy a $100 bond, and likewise should recommend that <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1486.jpg" n="2"/>the members assist the Turngemeinde.</p>
   <p>M. Wassermann then made a speech, showing that Sidney Smith espoused prohibition in 1874 and that the Illinois Staats-Zeitung opposed him at the time. Others thought, he might have changed his mind. A. George declared that it was highly improper for the Wirthsverein to play politics in such a manner.</p>
   <p>Philip Maas, president of the Wirthsverein, then remarked that the election, in this instance, would not affect the tavernkeepers--at least not appreciably--and Adolf George replied that it was too late to investigate whether Sidney Smith still was affiliated with the temperance movement; besides, the assertions made were insufficient as a basis of action prior to the election. The motion to nominate a committee of three to investigate the status of Smith was tabled.</p>
   <p>The committee which was appointed at the last session to ascertain how Senator Johnson regarded the prohibition question was dismissed, since several members <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1487.jpg" n="3"/>gave satisfactory explanations.</p>
   <p>A debate on the question of whether another meeting hall should be chosen ended without a decision. The meeting was not well attended; only thirty people out of a possible 500 were present. The next meeting will be held Friday at the Vorwaerts Turnhalle.</p>
   <p>It is evident that the tavernkeepers are intent on helping the Turngemeinde in its distress, since the several members at the hall subscribed liberally, and a much larger amount, perhaps three times as much, could have been obtained had more people been present.</p>
   <p>The list: Philip Maas, $25;....[Translator's note: Eight German names; two English.]</p>
   <p>The total amount subscribed was $250.</p>
   <p>Good Work!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
