<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-10-02">Oct. 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Vox Populi</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0905</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0905.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H (Polish)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-10-02">Oct. 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">VOX POPULI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Editor of the Abendpost</p>
   <p>(This newspaper is not responsible for any opinions sent to this column, etc. . . . . Contributions must be free from personal aspersion.)</p>
   <p>In regard to "Submitted by H. A. M." (An Observation and a Question), I subscribe to everything the contributor said about the Eckener donation. The amount thus far received is almost more humiliating than the sum obtained for the Hindenburg celebration.</p>
   <p>What then is the underlying cause for all these failures? As far as I am concerned, I contributed for the Hindenburg collection and also did my <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0906.jpg" n="2"/>share towards the German World's Fair group, but I must add that since I participated in the latter I have been bombarded with all conceivable assortments of literature to induce me to buy bonds and other securities.</p>
   <p>I consider this exploitation on the part of the treasurer's office as tactless, to use a mild expression. Are there no Germans willing to function in this capacity without seeking private gain? That alone would suffice to rebuild public confidence.</p>
   <p>I do not care to be further involved in the matter, although it is about time that this boil of Chicago's Germanism be lanced by experienced hands, because I do not believe that such inane covetousness has been tolerated by Chicago's Germans during the last seventy-five years. Seemingly, no improvement is in sight. Respectfully, A Reader.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0907.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>To the Editor of the Abendpost</p>
   <p>I am not a German citizen of the empire, my hometown is a small German city (Zwittau in Maehren, birthplace of Oswald Ottendorfer), and I am unimportant, politically. I am twenty-nine years old, have traveled throughout the United States and Hawaii, as well as Panama, and would like to express my sentiments about the $10,000 Eckener contribution, the accomplishment of Chicago's Germans. It is nothing to be proud of, to the contrary.</p>
   <p>That we Germans have become estranged in this land by the spirit of the times is proved by our lack of interest for German aviation and its greatest exponents, men of our blood. As an example, I mention only the Polish people.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0908.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In order to attain an aerial trans-Atlantic crossing by Polish fliers, the Poles in this country spent $100,000, irrespective of the success of the venture.</p>
   <p>But here Dr. Eckener realized a task which virtually was regarded with bated breath by the entire World.</p>
   <p>The Chicago visit of the Graf Zeppelin in its journey around the world was a singular experience for all, an experience which cannot be expressed in words. This master accomplishment of German engineering skill deserves more than ten thousand dollars from an appreciative Chicago with a population of millions.</p>
   <p>And, since the collection has been started, the main problem now is to bring it to a successful conclusion, to make the donations commensurate with the perfect work of the great man.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0909.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Next Saturday I shall send another contribution. I work as a machinist, yet the two dollars which I gave appear to be a very small amount to me.</p>
   <p>Very respectfully Yours,</p>
   <p>Frank Patzbold</p>
   <p>852 Sheridan Road.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
