<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-04-29">April 29, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Appeal for Permanent Organization Convention of May 22Nd at the Northside Turner Hall at 2 P. M.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0517</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0517.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-04-29">April 29, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">APPEAL FOR PERMANENT ORGANIZATION CONVENTION OF MAY 22ND AT THE NORTHSIDE TURNER HALL AT 2 P. M.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a large meeting the people of Chicago on March 25, 1906, declared: "While we do not criticize or limit the views of others, we reserve the right for ourselves to decide which ways of recreation, pleasure, and entertainment are the most suitable for ourselves and our children.</p>
   <p>"We also demand from the Legislature of Illinois to give the right of self-determination to the towns and villages of the State to organize their popular festivals is and entertainments, and to renounce all laws which are in contrast with the natural claims of the people for decent and moral entertainments. The greater part of the population in the industrial centers leads a very nervous and strained life and is in need of recreation different from those of the farmers. Past laws do not fit in with modern times. Especially in Chicago, the ordinances of the City Council differ materially from those of the State as regards the observance of the Sabbath. The change of these obsolete laws would give the municipal administration the power to regulate their popular festivals and entertainments on Sundays and other days.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0518.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The enforcement of obsolete laws which are not in accordance with the wishes of the people can lead to drastic, consequences. The population of towns does not interfere with the rural entertainments of the country folks. They only demand the extension of the principles of local self-determination. The State should give the right to every town, village, or market place to organize their public places of entertainment, licensed public houses, and to consider the demands of the majority of the people as regards their observation of the weekly rest day, the privileges of decent clubs, permission for theater performances, concerts, and public plays. In a democratic republic no law can be maintained permanently which is not in accord with public opinion. A free population cannot be forced into obedience with the police club. We, therefore, ask all associations, clubs, ledges, social unions, organizations, etc., which agitate for a lawful justification of moral entertainment of the people, to send their delegates to a convention to take place May 22, at 2 o'clock, at the Chicago Turner Hall, N. Clark street near Chicago avenue. This convention will work out a plan for a permanent organization and energetic action to submit to the Legislature the wishes of the people of the State of Illinois."</p>
   <p>The Organization Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
