<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-07-25">July 25, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Judge David, Eloquent Orator, Condemns Prohibition</title><title level="a" type="sub">Speaks at Mass Meeting of Shrewd "Drys" at Camp Desplaines</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0180</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0180.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I B 2 (Jewish)</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-07-25">July 25, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">JUDGE DAVID, ELOQUENT ORATOR, CONDEMNS PROHIBITION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Speaks at Mass Meeting of Shrewd "Drys" at Camp Desplaines</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is indisputable that, regardless of time or place, Joseph B. David of the Superior Court steadfastly maintains his identity. Whether he presides in his court, where lawyers of high intellect are quite frequently subjected to his sarcastic remarks, or whether he engages in open debate with an opponent--in either situation, his audience is never in doubt as to his views on the particular subject under discussion.</p>
   <p>This was again manifested on yesterday when, in a rather lively debate on Prohibition, he spoke at Camp Desplaines before approximately one thousand prohibitionists. His opponent was Professor Andrew A. Bruce of North western University, a former member of the Supreme Court of North Dakota. In the course of his denunciation of Prohibition, Judge David exclaimed:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0181.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"I can give you a piece of really helpful advice on how to accomplish within sixty days the miracle of enforcing Prohibition throughout the nation. Compel those liquor-drinking but "dry"-voting hypocrites in Washington to pass a law which provides that the purchaser of intoxicating beverages shall share the fate of the dealer! If such a measure would be adopted, then, of course, fifty per cent of our population would wind up behind prison bars."</p>
   <p>Neither did Judge David neglect to emphasize the much-discussed violation of those rights of the citizen that are guaranteed by the Constitution and are now being trampled upon as a result of the partiality shown in the enforcement of the Eighteenth Amendment. He also asserted that the transfer from State to Federal courts of cases involving Prohibition agents accused of the murder of peaceful citizens--a change resulting in almost every instance in the acquital of the defendant--does not encourage respect for the administration of justice.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0182.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As one might have expected, his speech was frequently interrupted by loud, ironical remarks. In reply, his opponent reproached him for a display of words which lacked content. This, however, did not upset the equilibrium of the champion of personal liberty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
