<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-03-26">March 26, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">The Infamous Swindle.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1388</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1388.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1883-03-26">March 26, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">THE INFAMOUS SWINDLE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The State of Illinois counts amongst its laws one that limits labor's working hours to an eight-hour work day. It is a well known fact that this law has been adopted only to pacify the dissatisfied working element, in other words, sand was strewn into their eyes. Nobody abides by this law and nobody has to. Labor in seeking employment has to submit to longer hours. But another thing which is still more absurd and infamous than the supposed Illinois eight-hour day law, is the mining inspection law. This law was also created to pacify the worker who demanded, a law determining liability for injuries by accident for protection of health and life of those working in mines. A law containing grand phrases was drawn up, but to render it more ineffective, the respective counties were entrusted with the execution of this law. Each county where mining was in progress was requested to employ a mining inspector, but is by no means forced to do it. The State requirements for a mining inspector call for a $1,000.00 bond as guarantee, for good behaviour and execution of duty, but the State does not make any provision whether or how this inspector shall be remunerated. Aside from that, the paragraphs of this law are inconsistent. For instance, the mining inspectors are supposed to give an annual report to the governor as to the state of the mines, but do not mention any provision of funds for such reports which require time and printing matter connected with it. They are required to know the use of all the scientific and technical instruments, they are supposed to draw plans of the mines in their <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1389.jpg" n="2"/>districts, test the air in the mines, examine steam-boilers and machines. In case of accidents they are to investigate, indict the offender and be ready with suggestions for the legislature, how to avoid such accidents. But for funds necessary for all these, they have to depend on the mercy of the county executives. No sane person can believe that a mining inspector with as numerous duties as those mentioned and the high qualifications required and besides in a position to give a $1,000 bond, can be had for an annual salary of $90.00 including travel expenses. And this means a county with an average of 29 mines with 1,500 miners.</p>
   <p>County Warren with forty-eight mines pays its inspector $60.00 annually, and Scott county pays its inspector the grand sum of $4.50 annually. This is the worst swindle and mockery to which labor has ever been submitted. And this is called the law for the protection of labor! This is an explanation why crippled and exploited old miners are chosen for this duty, for they are dependent on their exploiter, and therefore, have to take it and like it. This is the kind of legislation America affords its labor for protection of health and life. This piece of legislative rascality accounts for the tragedy and the impunity of the crime at Braidwood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
