<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-03">Jan. 3, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Trusts Without End</title><title level="a" type="sub">Liveries and Undertakers Combine</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_1474</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-17">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1474.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-03">Jan. 03, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">TRUSTS WITHOUT END</title><title level="a" type="sub"> Liveries and Undertakers Combine</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The North side is usually progressive and in the lead, giving us both good and bad examples for emulation, but as a matter of variety it now supplies the latter. The livery owners and undertakers have formed a trust, and their first official transaction revolved about a mere matter of price. The rates for coaches have been increased from 4 and 5 to 5 and 6. During the last decade the customary change was 4 for the ride to Graceland or Bonifacious cemeteries, and 5 to all others. But now the gentlemen of the trust consider this an insufficient remuneration. Horses, coaches, harness, feed, and wages have risen, so according to their opinion, one need not look frantically for suitable pretext to justify the increase. The new "trust" has been organized as follows: Charles Burmeister, President; A.M. Schillo, secretary; W.A. Hinkins, treasurer.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_1475.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Burmeister declared the general price increase in the aforementioned items raises the maintenance const of every coach; livery owners must shell out an additional $80 per year. The world has become more exacting in so far as funerals are concerned; the people demand the most modern equipment, imposing horses, immaculate drivers in uniform, and all that sort of stuff; money really is no object. Since the funeral coaches are mostly rented from livery owners, and as these gentlemen are adamant, we the undertakers obviously must comply.</p>
   <p>The permanent organization will be considered sometime next week. And thus the jacked up price does not affect the dead, but the living who are obliged to pay the bill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
