<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-12-24">December 24, 1910</date><title level="a">Christmas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0864</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0864.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-12-24">December 24, 1910</date><title level="a">Christmas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Christmas is the very heart of our family festivals. It gathers together the members of the family around the Christmas tree, around the manger of the Christ Child - the freely-giving, self-sacrificing love. Children, the care and the joy of the home, have confiscated this beautiful festival and it is for children in particular, that the table is overloaded with gifts of surpassing love.</p>
   <p>Real Christmas depends upon the frame of mind, the spirit in which the gifts are prepared or presented, and not upon the abundance or material value of the gifts. It is indeed fortunate for the child that it can feel this spirit. In the light of the Christmas Tree our own childhood looms up again, even if we do not desire to be children again. Husband and wife discover in the midst of the severity and struggle of life the child in themselves again. That which they had almost forgotten, the charm of Christmas touches it again. It is in particular painful at Christmas, if a member of the family circle is missing. Whoever is unfortunate enough to be without family connection at Christmas must beware of a too sentimental emotion.</p>
   <p>Christmas has for us Germans a double meaning and value, because it points so clearly towards the light. Our forbears celebrated "equinox" at this time.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0865.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Although months would pass before spring would come, they knew that then everything would change. In these days we are united with our farthest ancestors in a deep and primitive emotion, which can not be eradicated by modern tendencies and achievements. This thought is mysterious and deep, and if one desires to conceive a purpose for the history of the world, here is the opportunity to do so.</p>
   <p>The fragrance of the evergreens, the Christmas Trees brings us intouch with nature, and out of the unsearchable depth of our subconsciousness arise reminiscences from those ages, when our ancestors believed to feel the august presence of God in the rustlings of the forests. This great festival of nature is at the same time saturated with the spirit, presented by the Christ-child of Bethlehem.</p>
   <p>Christmasis the feast of mutually giving and taking, childlike joy, happy participation, and sweet memories. Happy is he who can look at Christmas Eve in the glowing eyes of children. Who can look back without remorse into the days of his own childhood! But those who are unfortunate enough not to have a home, can bring happiness into the life of a stranger or into the home of destitutes, and thereby he will make his own life happier and better.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
