<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-22">Jan. 22, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[Prohibition More Dangerous Than Bolshevism] (Letter to the Editor by Fr. Kra)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0389</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0389.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-22">Jan. 22, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[PROHIBITION MORE DANGEROUS THAN BOLSHEVISM] (Letter to the Editor by Fr. Kra)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Much that has been said and written about the wearing of a nightcap or dunce cap by the German Michel is undoubtedly true. And though I have not heard people say much about the sheeplike patience of free Americans, I have read much about it, and have come into contact with it many times. It is especially in evidence at this time, when a few fanatics have decreed that the constitutionally guaranteed liberty of the individual is to be curtailed;for many millions of citizens are to be deprived of their personal rights through the ratification of the Eighteenth Amendment to the Constitution. I think this is much more dangerous to the Government than Bolshevism because, prohibition is to be brought about and enforced by people (representatives) who have been elected by the nation to uphold and defend the Constitution. Ratification of the Eighteenth Amendment is equivalent to illegal confiscation of private property and the destruction of work and the opportunity to work: and the Constitution expressly protects citizens against these acts of violence.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0390.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Should the Prohibition Amendment become law through ratification by the necessary number of states, then the original intent and purpose of the Constitution, namely, to protect citizens against tyranny and oppression, would be nullified. And to force this Prohibition Amendment through the various state legislatures at a time when the entire country is kept in constant excitement by the after effects of the war is, in my opinion, not patriotism but downright Bolshevism.</p>
   <p>Finally, there is the money question. I have spoken to several "drys" about it, suggesting that all who voted for prohibition be made responsible for all property damage and for all money which would have accrued through the sale of liquor licenses. I think that a petition to this effect is in order. I also recommend that all the cellars of the "drys" be drained by the "wets," since they are well qualified to perform that task.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
