<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-03-06">Mar. 6, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">"Reconcilitation Trip" under the Direction of F.O. German Institutions in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_2_1_0890</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-16">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0890.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-03-06">Mar. 6, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">"RECONCILITATION TRIP" UNDER THE DIRECTION OF F.O. GERMAN INSTITUTIONS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under Frank Orman Beck's guidance, the participants of the excursion which was held yesterday afternoon under the name of "Reconciliation Trip", visited German institutions of Chicago. The headquarters of these trips are in Evanston, 2000 Sheridan Road.</p>
   <p>The trip first led into the building of the Abendpost, which is the only German daily newspaper in the City. The visitors inspected the different departments. the start was made with the editorial offices, where they were welcomed by the publisher, Paul H. Mueller, and the editors, P. Kaemmerling, and P. H. Ortmann. The latter gave the desired information in regard to the purpose and work of a newspaper which is not printed in the language of the Country, but which has set as its high purpose to make good American citizens of the immigrants, with the understanding, however, that they shall not forget their old homeland, and that they are keepers of cultural achievements which they have brought along with them from Germany. The compositors' room and the large press were inspected later.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_2_1_0891.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In accordance with the programme they afterwards went to the Bismarck Hotel, a caravansary of world fame, a creation of <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> Brothers. The Red House at Germania Place came next-this cheerful restaurant with its Bavarian characteristics. The Germania Club, just opposite the Red House, with its many attractions, principally with its ballroom of the "Schlaraffia" was the next object.</p>
   <p>A small detour thorough Lincoln Park to Lincoln's Monument; a glance at the new building of the Chicago Historical Society; the new Moody Church; and the place of the old Relic House led to the St. Paul's Church, a creation of Pastor Rudolph John, and now served by the Pastors <gap unit="words" extent="5" reason="illegible"/> Scherger, who gave a hearty reception to the visitors while Mr. Erich Paul told about the German youth. St. Paul's is the German Protestant Church, which is well known through out the City. The supper was partaken in its drawing rooms, where the ladies of the congregation had served a tasty meal prepared according to German recipes and German style of cooking. The participants in the trip were satisfied to see their trip ended here. "Goodbye" was said to the charming hostesses and pleasing memories were carried home from the "Reconciliation Trip" which had brought the participants into German institutions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
