<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Skandinaven</title>,
<date when="1909-03-12">Mar. 12, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Danish Home for the Aged</title><title level="a" type="sub">Anniversary Celebration at Wicker Park Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5410780_2_1669</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1669.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Skandinaven (Daily Edition)</title>,
<date when="1909-03-12">Mar. 12, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">DANISH HOME FOR THE AGED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Anniversary Celebration at Wicker Park Hall</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The celebration of the eighteenth anniversary of the founding of the Danish Home for the Aged, held at Wicker Park Hall, was a greater success than any previous anniversary celebration held by the Home. Many friends of the Home were present, friends who have stood by during the years and supported the good cause. Many new faces were also to be seen, among them the Danish manufacturer Waldemar Michaelsen, president of the Illinois Paint Manufacturing Company. Mr. Michaelsen has of late shown much interest in the Home. This was the first anniversary celebration of the Home that he has attended.</p>
   <p>Contrary to custom there was no entertainment prior to the anniversary celebration. On the other hand, the committee on arrangements had secured H. C. Schmidt's excellent orchestra, which provided continued opportunity for dancing throughout the evening, and by means of its brilliant music helped to make the evening pleasant for those who were not dancing. During the evening <pb facs="5410780_2_1670.jpg" n="2"/>Johannes Herskind, the actor, sang several songs which were greeted with much applause.</p>
   <p>The supper arranged by the committee was served in the small hall, which was tastefully decorated. The supper....was excellent, and the enthusiasm prevailing in the dance hall was matched by that...at the tables. From every side favorable comments were heard concerning the supper, which, by the way, is likely to yield a considerable surplus to the Society for the Home for the Aged.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
