<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende og Revyen</title>,
<date when="1925-07-10">July 10, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Shall the Danish Information Bureau Be Closed?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5410780_2_1724</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1724.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende og Revyen</title>,
<date when="1925-07-10">July 10, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">SHALL THE DANISH INFORMATION BUREAU BE CLOSED?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Danish Bureau (Foreign Language Information Service) has been in existence for seven years. On an average, ten Danes have visited the Bureau every day for legal aid, advice, and help of all kinds. Every week thousands of other Danes have received advice in articles which the Bureau sends out through this and other Danish papers. Those who know this office and its mission agree as to its value and importance. Shall this work continue, or do the Danes wish the office closed?</p>
   <p>The Bureau's services, which have saved our countrymen thousands of dollars, have been furnished free of charge. A few hundred Danes have donated just about enough for postage. The balance of the $7,500 needed to keep the office <pb facs="5410780_2_1725.jpg" n="2"/>going has been contributed by Americans.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the Foreign Language Information Service is to help and advise newcomers. A hundred thousand immigrants arrive every year from Mexico, while the number of arrivals from Denmark is much smaller. Mexico has no information office. The directors of the Foreign Language Information Service have decided to open a Mexican Information Bureau and to finance this by abolishing the Danish office.</p>
   <p>Upon my request they have agreed to keep the Bureau open on the condition that we shall contribute $2,000 to help defray expenses this year. We must also <pb facs="5410780_2_1726.jpg" n="3"/>contribute $5,000 in the year 1926. After 1926 it is expected that the Danes will take care of the matter themselves.</p>
   <p>Is the office worth so much money to the Danes in America? I, for one, think that it is. A simple proposal which was sent from this office to the Danish government saves $10 for every American citizen of Danish birth who takes a trip to Denmark, the amount which he formerly paid for his passport. It also saves him $10 more which it formerly cost to have the passport visaed. These savings will amount at least to $25,000 a year. The annual saving in cost of legal services and of other assistance furnished gratis by the Bureau may conservatively be estimated at another $25,000.</p>
   <p>A short time ago we learned of the case of a young Dane who was accused of <pb facs="5410780_2_1727.jpg" n="4"/>violating the immigration laws. A lawyer had offered to settle the case for $1,000. The Danish Bureau in ten minutes adjusted the matter without cost to the defendant.</p>
   <p>An immigrant had met with a serious accident. This office was instrumental in securing for him $5,000 in compensation. A lawyer would doubtless have retained half this amount for his services.</p>
   <p>The Bureau helped an old man gain an inheritance of $5,000 after he had given up hope of receiving anything, and it did not cost him a cent.</p>
   <p>Another of our important duties is to find missing persons. A detective bureau would usually charge $100 for one of these cases. The Danish Bureau <pb facs="5410780_2_1728.jpg" n="5"/>has handled more than eight hundred and has traced and found more than half the missing persons. If this work was paid for at the regular rate, it would amount to more than it takes to keep the office in operation.</p>
   <p>George Fernstrom told me last week that the reason why the Bureau has received so little support from the Danes was that I was too modest and did not advertise what we were doing.</p>
   <p>"Beat the big drum," said he, "and you will arouse the interest of the Danes in the cause."</p>
   <p>I hope that he is right; so I am asking every one who reads this to send me <pb facs="5410780_2_1729.jpg" n="6"/>a donation for the maintenances of the Bureau. There are 300,000 Danes in the United States. Are there not among you two hundred who will contribute $5 or $10 each and a thousand who will contribute $1 a year? This is all that is required to keep the office going for 1925 and 1926. But this help must come at once; otherwise the office will be closed.</p>
   <p>Viggo C. Eberlin,</p>
   <p>Danish Bureau F. L. I. S.,</p>
   <p>222 Fourth Avenue,</p>
   <p>New York City.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
