<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1914-03-07">Mar. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">New Danish-American Sports Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5410780_2_1251</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1251.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1914-03-07">Mar. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">NEW DANISH-AMERICAN SPORTS CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Danish American Athletic Club is the name of the latest organization for the promotion of sports among Danes in Chicago.</p>
   <p>It has been established by young countrymen, many of whom have recently arrived from Denmark, where they have starred in many branches of sport, and they possess the will and the courage to go to bat for the Danish colors and traditions on this side of the ocean.</p>
   <p>The president of the club is the long distance runner Christian Christensen, who came to Chicago several years ago, and has won many 10- and 15- mile races; he has also placed first on shorter distances. Up to now he belonged to the Norwegian club Sleipner.</p>
   <p>The vice-president is John Steen, who at one time held the middle-weight <pb facs="5410780_2_1252.jpg" n="2"/>boxing championship of Europe, and also was a member of the Danish Olympic track team in Stocholm last year.</p>
   <p>The secretary of the new club, Steen Rasmussen represented Denmark at the last Olympic marathon race, and has also competed successfully in indoor races here, even though he had been accustomed to outdoor races only.</p>
   <p>Rudy Hansen has also won laurels as a runner in Denmark, where he was known by the nickname "the banana," due to the fact that he, like Christensen and Steen Rasmussen, is a vegetarian.</p>
   <p>The club already has about one hundred members, some of which are passive and not of Danish nationality, but according to its laws all officers must be Danes. The first issue of a monthly club publication is just off the press.</p>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1253.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The management is soon to decide on a permanent meeting place and training facilities, and plans are already under way for the acquisition of a clubowned home and gymnasium. The most optimistic souls within the club are looking for a membership of one thousand within a short time.</p>
   <p>The D.A.A.C. will make its first appearance before Danish Chicago at the National festival in Riverview Park next summer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
