<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende og Revyen</title>,
<date when="1925-05-22">May 22, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Silver Wedding</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5410780_2_0913</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_0913.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende og Revyen</title>,
<date when="1925-05-22">May 22, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">SILVER WEDDING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Tuesday evening Mr. and Mrs. Bunck celebrated their 25th anniversary of married bliss with a great host of friends at the Atlantic Hotel. "Sam Smiles" was master of ceremonies. A great number of speeches were made, all extolling the popularity of the Bridal Couple with the"Colony." It is in particular the Danish Old People's Home, which so often asked so much from this popular couple. Mrs. Bunck has been on the House Committee for many years, and Mr. Bunck has been president of the Society for three years, during which time, the membership was doubled. He was particularly active on the Chicago Committee for the World's Fair in San Francisco, and served in many places in the interest of his countrymen.</p>
   <p>When Mr. Bunck assumed a duty, one could rest assured it would be carried out in the most faithful manner.</p>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_0914.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A few friends presented the Bridal Couple with a handsome Silver Cup, as a token of esteem and good comradship. The Old leoples Home Society sent a beautiful flower decoration presented by Mrs. James Henriksen with a good speech. A beautiful bouquet was sent by the Danish Old Peoples Home together with a poem written by M. A. Thorsager. A huge basket of flowers was received from Mr. Bunck's business concern, as a token of the good understanding between the "boss" and his workers. More than forty telegrams were received, and among them were from: General Consul Beck, Vice Consul M. Hemmingsen, Holver Jacobsen, Ivar Kirkegoord, James Madison, Frank Philipson and A. J. Nielsen in California; The Danish Pioneer and Danish Times. Songs written by Mrs. Chas. Andersen, Anton Kvist and Casino were sung.</p>
   <p>All in all it was a beautiful celebration, which will long be remembered by both the honored couple as well as the others present.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
