<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1921-10-01">Oct. 1, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Danish Times Staff</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5410780_2_1047</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1047.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Danish Times</title>,
<date when="1921-10-01">Oct. 1, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE DANISH TIMES STAFF</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We present to our readers the staff of the new paper, Danish Times. It is a step forward in Danish-American journalism:</p>
   <p>Jens Toft, our business manager, was born on the island of Mors in "Linfjorden," thirty-three years ago. After receiving his education in England and Canada he connected with several newspapers for several years in Denmark in the capacity of editor. In the last few years he has been secretary for the Personliga Friends Van, an organization of over one hundred thousand members.</p>
   <p>Einar Olalsen, our artist, has only lived in America a few months. The American artists have agreed that he is an able artist. He will draw pictures of prominent men and women for every issue of the Danish Times.</p>
   <p>Casper Hasselriis, one of the most able Danes in Chicago, came to Chicago fifteen years ago. He was, for a long time, secretary of the Danish-American Society. He was also, at one time, connected with Transatlantic Company.</p>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1048.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>P. B. Nelsen, a partner in the firm of Dufres, Buckingham, and Eaton, is well known in the Danish colony. He was born in South Jutland, and came to America with his parents when he was four years old.</p>
   <p>Chris D. Hagerty is an American and our reporter. He was one time ace reporter for the Chicago Tribune. He is the only correspondent who interviewed President Madero in Mexico during the revolution. He was foreign correspondent during the Boxer rebellion in China, and during the Russian-Japanese War. Last Year, he was president of the Chicago Press Club. It is a great honor for the Danish Times to have a man of this type on its staff. Miss Anna Grabow is our Canadian correspondent. Mrs. M. Madsen is editor of our "House and Home" section. Orla Juul, an actor, is the editor of the music section. Claus Jensen is editor of the special section for lodges, fraternal organizations, etc. Mr. Snollelev (pen name) is our humorist. Anton Kvist is the writer of poetry. Ole Knudsen is our dramatic editor. He is also director of the Danish Theatre. Martin Andersen Nexo is our correspondent in Denmark, and is also one of the greatest living Danish authors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
