<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende</title>,
<date when="1925-10-23">Oct. 23, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">The Good Fellowship Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5410780_2_1738</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1738.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende (Danish Times)</title>,
<date when="1925-10-23">Oct. 23, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">THE GOOD FELLOWSHIP CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Good Fellowship Club is made up of male members of St. Ausgar's Church, and a meeting was held last Wednesday in the church in which sixty members participated. A turkey dinner was served, and later the visiting Danish composer, Sextorph Mikkelsen, entertained with his songs and his marvelous lute accompaniment. He was greeted with enthusiasm and applause not only for his performance but also for his true interpretation of something distinctly Danish, which of course appealed to the audience in particular.</p>
   <p>Then Mr. Davis, Superintendent of the Better Government Association, gave an excellent lecture on conditions prevailing in the judicial branch of the Chicago municipal government, expressing himself rather strongly in favor of reorganization for the purpose of improving the judicial system, which appears to be controlled by undesirable elements in our community. He pointed out that it was <pb facs="5410780_2_1739.jpg" n="2"/>an absolute necessity to check the trend of court procedure if we expect to avoid a state of lawlessness.</p>
   <p>The lecture was received with much interest, and several members of the audience declared themselves ready to take an active part in this effort.</p>
   <p>Mr. John M. Pedersen, president of the Club, expressed his thanks and his appreciation of the excellent entertainment and lecture and voiced his hope that some results would be attained.</p>
   <p>The Good Fellowship Club is organized for the purpose of extending aid, particularly to newly arrived immigrants who are in need of help to get a start in their new surroundings.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
