<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>, (The Review)
<date when="1909-09-18">Sept. 18, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">[Danish Brotherhood Discusses Old Age Benefit Plan]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5410780_2_1475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>, (The Review)
<date when="1909-09-18">Sept. 18, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">[DANISH BROTHERHOOD DISCUSSES OLD AGE BENEFIT PLAN]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2.col.5...... The proposed establishment of the old age benefit fund is being thoroughly discussed, with many contributions to Revyen's open forum on the subject. (A) claims that the D.B.S. is strong enough, numerically and financially, to establish such a fund and offers as proof that to data the D.B.S. has met all obligations (nearly a million dollars) promptly and in full and still has a large treasury balance. (B) says D.B.S. should absolutely have such a fund. The old age benefit is preferable to entry into an old peoples home. Old people prefer it to being "put on the shelf" in an institution and financially the benefit plan would bring about a saving in actual funds. Comparison of the outlay of the two plans are convincing. On the home plan side $500,00 or $1,000.00 paid the home at time of death vs old age benefit paid monthly to the aged member who gets the benefit of every dollar paid out, as against splitting the amount to cover running expenses of the institution. In addition - a person entering the "Home" at the age of sixty-five <pb facs="5410780_2_1476.jpg" n="2"/>carrying a$1,000.00 policy obligates the lodge to pay to the institution the amount named in the policy even though the policy holder died within a year or two; under the benefit plan the member would have more freedom and live his normal life and at death the expense to the ledge would end; a saving well worth considering as a means of greater benefits to the aged still living.</p>
   <p>The battle goes merrily on and the outcome is unpredictable.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
