<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-01-28">Jan. 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[Dania's Banquet]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5410780_2_1461</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1461.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1911-01-28">Jan. 28, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">[DANIA'S BANQUET]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2.4-6..........Dania (Chicago's oldest Danish Lodge) enjoyed a pleasant social evening at their hall on Sunday January 22. Guests numbering 125 were seated at the beautifully decorated tables literally loaded with the usual tasty and plenteous good things on a Danish banquet board. A number of the guests attended a Danish-American affair for the first time and with the ice broken through such an auspicious occasion we can safely predict their continued association and a hearty co-operation with this particular group. Photographers were on the job and excellent pictures of the gathering may now be obtained as a memorial of a really enjoyable evening with their own countrymen.</p>
   <p>The service was perfect and the food as well from soup to cigars. The main dishes were baked trout, and roast turkey complete with the accompaniment of Port and Rhine wines, Akavit, Cheese, Ice Cream, Cake, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1462.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Among the speakers were Attorney Bastrup for Denmark, Consul Beck; Danes in America, Otto Christensen; America and M. Houlberg for "Dania." The nice part of the speeches was that they were short and precise, not the tiresome long brand so common at a banquet. There was no trace of the usual monotony of speech making as the speeches alternated with solos and the ensemble singing of both Danish and English songs in the livelier mood.</p>
   <p>The enthusiastic crowd then made short work of clearing the floor for dancing that was enjoyed until 1:00 A.M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
