<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>, (The Review)
<date when="1909-02-06">Feb. 6, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Carl Hansen Appeals for Danish-American Unity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5410780_2_0932</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_0932.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>, (The Review)
<date when="1909-02-06">Feb. 6, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">CARL HANSEN APPEALS FOR DANISH-AMERICAN UNITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2.col.3-4......Today's issue carries a one and one-half column appeal to all Danish-American organizations and individual groups for more Dane co-operation in Chicago and its surrounding territory. The most prevailant excuse for the lack of this seems to be that the Danes are divided into so many groups, lodges, clubs, choruses, etc., that it is difficult to bring about an agreement to any degree.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hansen cites the fact that about ten years ago a central committee had been appointed,but because of petty jealousy and independence of various leaders, the chairman of the committee became disgusted and resigned and the committee disbanded. But he suggests that every Danish-American organization in Chicago send a delegate to a convention so that a league of Danish-American organizations may be formed <pb facs="5410780_2_0933.jpg" n="2"/>that can and will show Chicago and the world that there are Danes that are capable of working together to preserve their adopted country, as well as to further the culture and traditions of the country of their birth or ancestry. A league of that type can do much to bring about a better understanding between groups in all parts of Chicago, and to get them together for the celebration of a common Danish holiday to say nothing of putting the Danish-American people on the map of Chicago in the celebration of our own U.S. holidays. Our fellowcitizens will wake up to the fact that there is a country by the name of Denmark that has thousands of her children and grand children, who are becoming good citizens of Chicago and the U.S.A.</p>
   <p>Danish-American Chicago has been assembled in the past, and with the proper spirit and leadership this can be done again. We were proud of ourselves at the unveiling of the Hans Christian Anderson Statue and at the Constitution Day Festival in 1899.</p>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_0934.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The latter was the world's greatest gathering of Danes outside of Denmark. We demonstrated conclusively that Danes could celebrate the Drachman Festival and the 100th anniversary of the birth of H. C. Anderson, which resulted further in the initiative of Danish-American organizations and also resulted in the establishment of the beautiful Danish Children's Home. This built, in no small part, by contributions collected by the H.C.Anderson committee.</p>
   <p>We Danes have ably demonstrated the possibility of uniting for a common cause. Let us now concentrate upon forming a committee to bring about a Danish Day in common, without religious or political barriers, where old organizations can be renewed, new friendships established and a combined support from Danish-American institutions can be brought about.</p>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_0935.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We especially appeal for united efforts on behalf of our Old Peoples Home in Norwood Park and the Orphanage on Evergreen Avenue. Let us, for example, make June 6, a prominent annual event in Danish-American History and show Chicago and the country at large that our people here are more than an insignificant group, and are to be highly respected.</p>
   <p>Every Dane in Chicago and vicinity is urged to attend the 60th anniversary of Constitution Day. We urge you to come with the firm conviction that in showing an interest in the old land you are better citizens of the land of your adoption.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
