<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1909-10-09">Oct. 9, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">[Kund Peterson Vs. the Terrible Turk]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5410780_2_1287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Revyen</title>,
<date when="1909-10-09">Oct. 9, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">[KUND PETERSON VS. THE TERRIBLE TURK]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2.col.5.......The club house of the Austin Athletic Club (48th Avenue and Erie Street) was filled last night, the occasion being a wrestling match between the Danish-American favorite, Knud Peterson (Austin) and Hamid Kalla Pasha (The Terrible Turk). The"Turk" has vanquished many of the country's best wrestlers including the Danish-American champion, "Bull" Olsen. The "Turk" had engaged to pin Petersen twice in thirty minutes of wrestling and won the first fall in thirteen minutes. He had learned, during these minutes that he had a worthy opponent and this seemed to anger him to such an extent that he forgot the better in his makeup and started a lot of dirty work that brought a volume of boo's, hisses and catcalls from the entire audience of lovers of clean sport. The disapproval of the crowd did not make him feel any better nor did it call forth an exhibition of reserve, strength or skill and the alloted thirty minutes came and went; Petersen was still unthrown for the second time and he was declared winner of the match. As victor he was given the purse of $100.00 <pb facs="5410780_2_1288.jpg" n="2"/>plus about twice that amount as the winners share of the gate. Petersen was given a rousing cheer and was carried to the dressing room on the shoulders of his admirers.</p>
   <p>Peterson lived for some time at the Danish Young Peoples Home on the West Side and on a number of occasions gave a good account of himself in the Humboldt Park ice skating races.</p>
   <p>On Tuesday Oct. 12, Petersen with his wife and children are sailing to Denmark where he is scheduled to meet the Danish middleweight champion, John Grover in Copenhagen on November 5. Revyen wishes him a happy trip and a decided victory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
