<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende og Revyen</title>,
<date when="1924-02-29">Feb. 29, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Danish Old Peoples Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5410780_2_1628</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1628.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende og Revyen</title>,
<date when="1924-02-29">Feb. 29, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE DANISH OLD PEOPLES HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4........We often hear complaints from many quarters about the lack of interest shown by our countrymen and women in the most worthy undertaking, and how difficult it is to obtain sufficient funds to properly care for our old ones at the "Home," and now, when a committee is hard at work trying to raise enough money to enable them to build an addition to the home, one is met with almost insurmountable obstacles.</p>
   <p>I am willing to concede that the Danes' interest in this cause is rather lax; when we consider the number of Danes in Chicago as well as the large membership list of the Danish Old Peoples Home Society, the lack of interest is self-evident; but what can be the reason?</p>
   <p>First I must ask: Is it not the purpose to extend to all old and needy Danish - men and women help in their last years, remove their economic worries and try to make their last days as sunny and cheerful as conditions will permit - or is the <pb facs="5410780_2_1629.jpg" n="2"/>Danish Old Peoples Home an Institution, where well-to-do Danes in a respectable manner and for a few hundred Dollars can place their patents, when "the old folks" are getting a little in the way in their respective homes?</p>
   <p>If the first part of my question is the aim and purpose of this institution, and this is carried out, I am certain, it will not be difficult to arouse the interest among the Danes, and receive both their moral and financial support, is, however, the opposite in the case, that the home is sort of a private institution for the privileged class, when they upon the payment of a nominal amount gain admission to the "Home," it is easily understood why interested people keep aloof.</p>
   <p>It has been said that the Danish Old Peoples Home is no poor-house, where people who have not saved anything, but spent their money as fast as they made it, can be admitted, but a place for worthy respectable old Danes, true enough, worthiness should probably be considered, but it is possible to find competent unbiased judges, who possess the ability to draw the line between the worthy and the unworthy; it is doubtful if such judges were ever born.</p>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1630.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is my opinion that the many of our countrymen and women, who are unable to support themselves and without any means, should be entitled to first option on any vacancies at the "Home" and not young able-bodied people as the case is today. I have been told there are those who have resided at the "Home" for seventeen years; even though they paid down three or four hundred Dollars at their admission, it does not mean much, as the first two years would have eaten this up, it is then up to the Society, its management and its committees to get busy and work early and late to raise means for the further support.</p>
   <p>In recent years we have had an "Assisting or Help Committee," which has worked unselfishly with the few means at its disposal, it has taken many a heavy life and done a blessed work; out of every Dollar this committee handles, one-hundred cents go to the needy, there are no administrative expenses, every penny received is paid out. If this committee had more to work with, the applications for admission to the "Home" would be materially reduced, perhaps the proposed new building, which again will tax our donors, would not be necessary.</p>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1631.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It seems to me that this committee together with the house-committee chould work hand in hand, a better understanding and co-operation should be brought about, in order to do a more widespread and effective work. Perhaps the purchase of old dwellings in the Danish quarters which in turn could be turned over to the needy frequently, thereby, encourage self-help and at the same time avoid moving many old people from their known surroundings.</p>
   <p>This I think should be considered and carried further for the benefit of many more of our needy countrymen than the limited number which can be accomodated at the Home, even with the addition of the proposed new building.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>Lauritz Olsen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
