<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende</title><date when="1925-10-09">Oct. 9, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Danish Children's Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5410780_2_1556</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.D.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1556.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende, (Danish Times)</title><date when="1925-10-09">Oct. 9, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">DANISH CHILDREN'S HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In his office at Danish Children's Home the Rev. A. W. Anderson greets us with his friendly smile, happily accomodating us in our desire to learn about the acitvity of this institution in which he holds the office of protector.</p>
   <p>Starting out on our inspection trip through the building we notice a collection of pictures on the walls of the reception hall, portraying men whose work has been of benefit to the institution, such as the Rev. A. S. Nielsen, founder of the home and faithful sponsor of its activities from 1884 to 1898; Pastors Helvig, Peter Eriksen, H. C. Rordam and others who have dedicated time and efforts for the benefit of Danish Children's Home. We pass through the classrooms, dormitory, play-rooms and sewing-room and emerge on a spacious balcony overlooking the playground and the beautifully landscaped garden. We also peep into the hospital department, but fortunately - this department is vacant most of the time - according to Rev. Andersen.</p>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_1557.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Order and cleanliness are rules, strictly adhered to in every department. In the dormitory the small beds are arranged in straight rows neatly made up, and opening a drawer of a tiny dresser, we find that the eight year old owner has her dolls and playthings neatly arranged as everything else in the room.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, our little friends whom we would like to meet, are attending school and must not be disturbed. Only a couple of four years of age are busy in the sandpile underneath the balcony. Seeing Rev. Anderson the forget their play and pester their "father" for a story. He escaped the job only after pleading with them at length.</p>
   <p>The kitchen is modernly equipped, and in the dining-room the children are taught proper table manners.</p>
   <p>Returning to the office we have a final conversation with Rev. Andersen: "Am I tired of the work? No, on the contrary:" says Rev. Andersen. "This work is a blessing to the children as well as to those who perform it. Our children <pb facs="5410780_2_1558.jpg" n="3"/>are all good boys and girls, and the fact that we are able to accomplish so much is sufficient evidence of the interest our countrymen have in the work."</p>
   <p>When the children reach the ages of fourteen and fifteen they leave the home but are under our observation until we think they are able to take care of themselves."</p>
   <p>Rev. Andersen has been the protector of Danish Children's Home since 1914. He deserves the appreciation of all Danes in Chicago for his unselfish work, and we hope he will continue it for years to come.</p>
   <p>If you have time, you ought to pay a visit to this institution to see what is being done for unfortunate little ones, and if you are able to spare a few dollars to promote its course, they will be accepted with appreciation. Remember, such donations cause more happiness than you probably imagine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
