<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende</title>,
<date when="1935-11-01">Nov. 1, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">An Absurd Situation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0205</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0205.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Dansk Tidende</title>,
<date when="1935-11-01">Nov. 1, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">AN ABSURD SITUATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The hog raisers of Middlesex County, who last year were paid three hundred and sixty-five dollars [each] for cutting hog production, have voted unanimously to accept the government bounty in 1956.</p>
   <p>Naturally they would. Many of them in this way have received small fortunes in the past two years, besides profiting immensely from the great rise in hog prices. The public is paying high taxes to make these men comparatively rich.</p>
   <p>The Massachusetts hog farmers get the cream from this hog-control scheme. The hogs they raise are small but they get as much money for not raising an eighty-pound hog as western hog farmers get for a two-hundred-and-fifty or three-hundred-pound hog.</p>
   <p>Western farmers raise corn-fed hogs. The higher the price of corn, the more it <pb facs="5410780_2_0202.jpg" n="2"/>costs them to raise a hog. But our local hogs are garbage-fed hogs. Few of them see any corn. The stuff fed to them costs the hog farmer no more than the cost of transportation. Yet, the raiser of garbage-fed hogs gets as much for his hogs in the market as the raiser of corn-fed hogs.</p>
   <p>This year the price of hogs soared to three times the price the hog farmer received in 1934. So did the bounties he received, for he got three times as much for every hog not raised in 1935 as he did in 1934.</p>
   <p>We are facing the greatest hog scarcity in fifty years. As all housewives know, the price of park products is rising tremendously. It will be impossible for the hog raiser here to supply the demand in the coming year, and the supply must be augmented by importations from abroad. The Bureau of Agricultural Economics, in Washington, declares that prices for pork products are likely to go very much higher this winter.</p>
   <p>In view of all this, the idea of continuing to force production cuts for 1936, <pb facs="5410780_2_0203.jpg" n="3"/>and paying out huge sums to hog farmers, who will probably make twice as much money next year as this year, seems fantastic.</p>
   <p>When one hog farmer, here, who is an alien, can get a twenty-thousand-dollar bonus in 1934, a nine-thousand-dollar bonus in 1935, and a probable nine-thousand-dollar one in 1956 for a farm worth not more than seven thousand dollars--and in addition make the biggest profit in all his farming history--the ordinary farmer here who gets no bonuses, and sometimes is forced to sell produce at a loss, must be amazed at such windfalls for hog farmers.</p>
   <p>And the housewife is paying for all this. Could there be a more absurd situation than housewives paying processing taxes in order to increase the cost of the food they buy? Even when costs rise so high that consumers are protesting forcibly the order goes forth from Washington to jack them up a good deal higher.</p>
   <p>All this reminds us of an enterprising Danish real-estate operator who advertised as follows: "Dandy way to make money: Buy this thirteen acres for hog raising.</p>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_0204.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Sign up with the government not to raise, say, five hundred hogs. It will pay you one thousand dollars. That will pay for the farm and you will still have some money left."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
