<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title level="a">Danish National Committee, Aksel Nielsen, Teacher of Danish Folk. Dancing, Chicago</title>, <title>World's Fair Year Book</title>, <date when="1933">1933</date>, p. 55 and 107.
<title level="a">The Origin of Danish Folk Dancing</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420780_2_0912</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   
   <change when="2012-11-22">Mapped 2010 transcriptions of 5420780_2 images to 5410780_2</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420780_2_0912.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title level="a">Danish National Committee, Aksel Nielsen, Teacher of Danish Folk. Dancing, Chicago</title>, <title>World's Fair Year Book</title>, <date when="1933">1933</date>, p. 55 and 107.
<title level="a">The Origin of Danish Folk Dancing</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In writing about folk dances, there is no particular system or group of dances that is more outstanding than others, because a nation's folk dances represents its culture, and has become a means of expressing the inner feelings of that people. These old folk dances show typical temperaments of the various nations.</p>
   <p>The Danish folk dances differ from most others in their soft and carefree movements and are symbolical of Denmark, its people and nature. There are, however, dances that are typical of other nations as well.</p>
   <p>When the common people gathered in the olden days, it was through dancing they expressed their feelings--it was the spiritual language, understood and loved by all, through which the moods and strifes of their daily lives found experssion. Typical are the Shoemakers' Dance and the Weavers (Weaving Wadmel). The dance that occurs most frequently in all folk dancing is the waltz, which took form in the 16th century in France.</p>
   <pb facs="5410780_2_0892.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Polka, a Bohemian national dance, was first danced by the peasants, but during the 18th century it gained popularity in many other countries. The Gallop which is a Hungarian dance is also very old. The Quadrille was danced all over Europe in the 16th century. The Polonaise and Mazurka are Polish and Russian dances. From these, many other dances, have been created.</p>
   <p>In Denmark, the old folk dances have relinquished their popularity in favor of the more modern ballroom dancing, a mixture of everything and not much of anything with the exception of such specialty dances as the tango and, of course, the waltz. The "Society for Promotion of Folk Dances in Denmark" has successfully undertaken to gather up the old Danish folk dances and melodies in order to preserve the culture, they represent. In every hamlet in Denmark these dances still hold sway both for their wholesome fun and their cultural value, and is considered by the people as a precious possesion to be handed down to future generations.</p>
   <p>Also in America have we folk dances. This country has come to value and <pb facs="5410780_2_0893.jpg" n="3"/>appreciate their cultural influence. Many minor schools as well as universities practice folk dancing. Among the Danes in America, folk dancing is a natural feature at gatherings and festivities. There are at least fifty different groups throughout the states who enthusiastically strive to promote folk dancing.</p>
   <p>Our dances are, no doubt, best suited for the American schools because they are easy to learn and understand and are as light and carefree as the typical American.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
