<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-06-26">June 26, 1929</date><title level="a">Greex Public Receives the Greek Press with Approbation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1033</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
                    
                    
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    
    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1033.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-06-26">June 26, 1929</date><title level="a">GREEX PUBLIC RECEIVES THE GREEK PRESS WITH APPROBATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The reception accorded to the first issue of the Greek Press, by the entire Greek community of Chicago was very phenomenal and extremely pleasing to the publishers.</p>
   <p>Not even the wildest of our dreams and expectations could come anywhere near to what actually took place. It is not an exaggeration to state, that the Greek of Chicago welcomed the first issue of the Greek Press, in a spirit of pleasure and with satisfaction.</p>
   <p>For the first time, in the memory of all those who have made Chicago their home during the last generation or so, the Greek colony heralded the appearance of a publication with great fervor and if we may venture the remark--with enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>People that we have known for years, and many others that we did not know, called in to see us; to congratulate us upon the elegant appearance of the Greek Press, and to express to us their whole-hearted cooperation, for its success and its ultimate triumph.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1034.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many others have brought in their advertisements, unsolicited, an unprecedented occurence in the annuals of a new publication. Readers, as well as advertisers, are rendering their support to the Greek Press gladly, openly and unreservedly.</p>
   <p>The soul and the brain of the sons and the daughters of this virile race have spoken and responded in unmistakable terms. They have given their verdict of approval for the manner in which we print and edit our paper.</p>
   <p>Moved, as we truly are, by the sentiments expressed and voiced in all the Greek centers and Greek homes, we are not letting ourselves be carried away with premature enthusiasm to recline in comfort and contentment.</p>
   <p>Thankful as we are for the Greek public's approval, we are not unmindful of the fact that our work is hardly begun, that the task of publishing and editing a newspaper calls into action all the faculties and every fiber of the human body.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1035.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Greek Press, week in and week out, will be improved and bettered in every way. It will register faithfully and accurately all the social events of the Greeks of Chicago. Its policy will be constructive and upbuilding, cooperative and elevating, fair and rational, sound and logical. All activities, business as well as social, will be looked at through the small end of the telescope.</p>
   <p>In size and appearance, the Greek Press will, in the course of time, become larger and better, in order that it may more forcefully serve its readers and benefit its advertisers. It will strive and will succeed to become the sine qua non of every Greek home and all business establishments.</p>
   <p>No efforts will be spared to reach the desired end. With all the powers at our command we shall go on and on, with an undaunted will and determination to build a Greek and American newspaper that will be representative and characteristic of the enviable qualities of the Greek, the Greek-American and the future American.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
