<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Program, Dated Chicago, Ill.</title>,
<date when="1923-05-07">May 7, 1923</date><title level="a">Owned by C. Mammon, 208 S. La Salle St.</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Hellenic Festival Dionysia</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Program, Dated Chicago, Ill.</title>,
<date when="1923-05-07">May 7, 1923</date><title level="a">Owned by C. Mammon, 208 S. La Salle St.</title><title level="a" type="sub">THE HELLENIC FESTIVAL DIONYSIA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Drama League of America believing that the beauty of ancient and modern Grecian art should receive more recognition, has arranged for a festival of the Grecian arts of music and dancing with cooperation of a distinguished committee. The performance will be in the hands of foremost professionals but will be supplemented by the talent of distinguished amateurs and groups of singers and dancers from the Greek societies and churches.</p>
   <p>The program will be in three sections each covering a different period of Grecian art:</p>
   <p>1. Ancient Greece, illustrated by a Procession of Dionysia, several group and solo dances, together with the rendering of the Ancient Hymn to Apollo, recently unearthed at Delphi.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0461.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>2. Byzantine Greece, shown in the dance and"choro-dramas,"The Emperor's Bride and Kasiane eleborately costumed according to plates by Charlotte Markham and utilizing a large group of actors, dancers, singers, and concluding with a brilliant solo dance.</p>
   <p>3. Modern Greece, in peasant songs by a native Greek choir, Cretan dances, national Hellenic dances and a colorful Festival of May. The professionals appearing are pre-eminently the leaders in Greek art.</p>
   <p>Vassos Kanellos, the foremost dancer of Greece, who unites the true spirit of the ancient are with those of Byzantine and the vitality of modern Greece, introducing Hellenic and Byzantine music and peasant melodies for the first time in America.</p>
   <p>Charlotte Markham Kanellou (Tanagra), the Decorative Painter, designer of the costumes and stage settings of the Dionysia, is strongly allied with the modern movement in art.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0462.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Her dance pantomine, studied in Paris and America, is full of creative charm. Her love and understanding of Greek art makes her interpretations very inspiring.</p>
   <p>The Ballet Ensemble for the Ancient Greek dances has been selected with the cooperation and courtesy of Mr. Adolph Bolm, the Ballet Master of the Chicago Civic Opera and from his School of Dance.</p>
   <p>The dancers for the Byzantine Chorodrama are from the School of Mme. Young. The Choir of forty voices will sing rare Byzantine music entirely new to Chicago, as well as peasant songs and some of the little-known Greek Church music. A native chorus of thirty will dance peasant dances.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
