<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1904-04-01">April 1, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Grocers against Greek Peddlers Judge Hurley Heaps Insults on Greeks - Greek Consul-General Inquires - Judge Retracts His Statements</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0323</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0323.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1904-04-01">April 1, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO GROCERS AGAINST GREEK PEDDLERS JUDGE HURLEY HEAPS INSULTS ON GREEKS - GREEK CONSUL-GENERAL INQUIRES - JUDGE RETRACTS HIS STATEMENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2- A committee of Chicago grocers last week declared war to the finish on Greek vegetable and fruit peddlers, accusing them of being the parasites of the trade and requesting the city council to prohibit peddlers from selling merchandise in streets and alleys or to impose a heavy license-fee on them so that they may quit acting as leeches.</p>
   <p>So great was the effect of the grocers' war on the Greeks that Judge Hurley from the bench cast wantonly violent insults right and left at Greeks in general as he delivered his judicial decision to the six Greek defendants (newly-arrived immigrants) who were before him for disobeying a police ordinance.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0324.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Greek Consul-General, Dr. N. Salopoulos, who is distinguished for his academic learning, dignity, and sanity, has written a letter to the American Jurist calling its attention to certain facts and pointing out that the accusations against the Greeks were wholly unjust. The Consul's letter, which was published by the press of the city, brought results, and His Honor publicly retracted his statements.</p>
   <p>That closes the incident of the insult to Greeks, which was absolutely unwarranted; but the grocers want the Greek leeches off the streets. The war is on against the poor unorganized Greek peddlers. The grocers are organized, and consequently their voice is the louder.</p>
   <p>Of course the Greeks, who are determined to make an honest living, are not so easy to deal with. Their argument is that they, the Greeks, facilitate buying for housewives, and these in turn are in favor of the Greek peddlers and their strictly fresh and seasonable merchandise, which is also according to the housewives, much cheaper.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0325.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If logic means anything, I am inclined to believe that the housewives will win. The Greeks are cultivating the good will of these, their daily customers.</p>
   <p>On the other hand the poor grocers are to be pitied because they are losing business, and something ought to be done before these Greeks ruin them. The way is open for the grocers; let them compete with the Greeks, and the better man shall win. That is the clean, pure spirit of business, honest competition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
