<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-07-29">July 29, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Tomorrow's Lecture at the Professional Men's Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1469</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1469.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1926-07-29">July 29, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">TOMORROW'S LECTURE AT THE PROFESSIONAL MEN'S CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- Chicago's Greek community is distinguished not only for its progress in business but also for its educational activities.</p>
   <p>For some time, indeed, lectures have been given one after another in rapid succession, and now again the Greek Professional Men's Club is preparing a pleasant surprise for tomorrow's meeting.</p>
   <p>As we have announced before, Mr. M. Iatrou will lecture tomorrow, Friday, at 8 P.M. in the Sherman Hotel on the eminently original and instructive theme, "Prometheus, Fire, and the Gods." However, because of the opportune visit of Mr. Nicholas Papantonopoulos, formerly a member of our community and now a professor at the Athens Dental School, the Professional Men's Club is enabled to present more. It has begged Mr. Papantonopoulos to come to tomorrow's meeting and to give his impressions of Greece, so that the Greek community in Chicago may hear from him about conditions there.</p>
   <p>This idea of the Professional Men's Club is praiseworthy because through this invitation to Mr. Papantonopoulos, who is a prominent compatriot of <pb facs="5422062_3_1470.jpg" n="2"/>ours and well liked in our community, our fellow-Greeks will have the opportunity to obtain highly valuable information, information which only an American Greek residing in Greece and one endowed with the knowledge and the perception of Mr. Nicholas Papantonopoulos could give us.</p>
   <p>The lectures, it is understood, will be free to all who desire to attend, and we have no doubt that many will benefit by this educational treat, in which besides the lecture given by Mr. M. Iatrou we shall hear much about Greece - highly valuable and exceedingly interesting information.</p>
   <p>Mr. Papantonopoulos, as we have been informed, will leave us in a few days. On this account his lecture is announced somewhat suddenly in conjunction with the meeting of the Professional Men's Club, since, unfortunately, there is not time enough to arrange properly for a special lecture and to inform the entire Greek community. The Greek Daily, however, intends to publish the details of his lecture for those who are unable to attend.</p>
   <p>Antilogos (The Contradictor)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
