<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1933-09-30">Sept. 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Day at the Fair--Musical Bedlam</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0732</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0732.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1933-09-30">Sept. 30, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK DAY AT THE FAIR--MUSICAL BEDLAM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The tenth of September was appointed as Greek Day at the Fair. This celebration will be remembered forever by all who were present and by those who listened to it by radio as a day of humiliation for the Greeks of Chicago.</p>
   <p>It seems that the destiny of Greeks is always to fall short of what is expected of them because of the foolishness and selfishness of some egotistical Greeks who disregard the interests of the general public and seek to gratify their personal ambitions, which are either to display themselves or to make a profit, and usually both.</p>
   <p>The Greeks of Chicago and of the near-by towns came in crowds to honor our beloved Greece's day at the Fair. The Greek ambassador was expected to be present.</p>
   <p>More than ten thousand Greeks assembled before the Science Building, where the program was to be presented. Long before the appointed time the entire <pb facs="5422062_3_0733.jpg" n="2"/>space was filled, and all seats were occupied by an audience eager to listen to the program and to watch the arrival of various celebrities.</p>
   <p>About three o'clock preparations for the performance were complete, and pictures were taken. This consumed considerable time, but at last the orchestra opened the program by playing the American and the Greek national anthems.</p>
   <p>Bishop George Kallistos, accompanied by the Reverend Father Ereneos Tsourounakis, chanted a prayer in Greek fairly well, but the number which followed, "Hypermacho Stratego" (a Byzantine hymn to Mary), was the beginning of real musical bedlam, as it was very aptly called by a certain friend of ours. The major part of the program thereafter produced the worst possible impression on the audience and on all those who listened to it by radio.</p>
   <p>If the impressive Cretans had not been present with their music, seconded by two or three other good numbers on the program, the whole performance would have been a total failure and an absolute calamity for the self-styled super-patriotic committee which organized the affair.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0734.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The choir, which had practiced for months under the direction of a capable director, who was not, however, a Greek, made a very good impression, and so did sweet-voiced Bertha Floros with her solo. She is an excellent artist.</p>
   <p>But the music of the Kalamatianos dance was practically butchered, as was that of Tsamico and of the dance of Zalongo.</p>
   <p>The music presented as lately discovered airs of classical times was poor, unimpressive, and without color. In general the public, which overcrowded the space allotted to spectators of the performance, was enthusiastic because of the immense multitude in attendance, even though the program was very poor and badly rendered, measured by the usual standards of Greek affairs; and this is especially to be deplored because it was presented at the World's Fair.</p>
   <p>Just praise is due to the young men and women who composed the choir. For months they had practiced untiringly and had incurred no little expense to present some really good music and to display a magnificent spectacle of <pb facs="5422062_3_0735.jpg" n="4"/>Greek costumes on this Greek Day at the Fair. Among the numerous choristers were the sweet-voiced prima donna Miss Bertha Floros, Miss Katina Costouros, Miss Margarita Costouros, Misses Pauline, Stella, and Amalie Karamihas, Miss Irene Solopoulos, Miss Roxy Dessyla, Miss Anna Dedakis, and Miss Susan Jidvanes.</p>
   <p>In our humble opinion the failure to present a far better and more genuinely Greek program was due to the fact that the direction was assigned to a musician who is not a Greek and who does not have the requisite feeling for the Greek music which was so badly butchered.</p>
   <p>If the direction of the performance had been entrusted to any of our good Greek maestros--and we have some very good ones, among them, Messrs. Grechis, Spiros Bekatoros, and Eddy Varzos--a really Greek program might have been presented, and the music of the Greek dances especially, very badly mutilated by the orchestra, would have been played much better.</p>
   <p>We might also remark that it did not seem very tactful of the committeemen to present the dance of Pan, performed by ladies almost nude, before our <pb facs="5422062_3_0736.jpg" n="5"/>good and pious clergymen, who in our humble opinion should not have been forced to witness so ridiculous an affair.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
