<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-05-07">May 7, 1931</date><title level="a">Theodora to Be Presented at the Studebaker Theatre</title><title level="a" type="sub">Sunday, May 24th</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0600</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0600.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-05-07">May 7, 1931</date><title level="a">THEODORA TO BE PRESENTED AT THE STUDEBAKER THEATRE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Sunday, May 24th</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- What purports to be one of the most magnificent spectacles ever presented in Chicago, will be the presentation of the historical play, "Theodora", written by Mr. Demetrios A. Michalarios, at the Studebaker Theatre, May 24th, 1931, under the auspices of the local chapters of Ahepa. The plot of this play revolves around the most momentous crisis in the life of the famous Byzantine Empress "Theodora", wife of Justinian, the celebrated lawgiver.</p>
   <p>It was during the Nika riot that this resolute empress displayed her marvelous power and determination, by saving the throne for herself and Justinian, and by preserving the unity of the powerful Byzantine empire.</p>
   <p>This incident then constitutes the central theme of the play, around which several historical and ficticious situations have been woven to make of it a dramatic whole.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0601.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To produce a historical play which deals with the above period is not an easy matter, and the committee which has undertaken to do this work, has been busy for several weeks trying to devise all possible means to make the presentation as magnificent as possible.</p>
   <p>The entire cast will be furnished by the Hull House players, and it is expected that at least seventy persons will be on the stage.</p>
   <p>A most important feature of the entire presentation will be the music, pure Byzantine music, which will be furnished by direction of Mr. Demetrios Pappageorge.</p>
   <p>This Byzantine choir has already sung on the air through radio station W.G.N. on two occasions with great success. The music has been expecially arranged for this play. It is expected that more than sixty mixed voices will be mustered by this choir. Another pleasant feature of the production is the scenery. Mr. Economos, chairman of the committee for the production of the play, has secured gratis appropriate scenery worth over $10,000.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
