<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1905-09-08">Sept. 8, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Pan-American Marathon Race--A Greek Runner to Participat</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1610</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1610.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1905-09-08">Sept. 8, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">PAN-AMERICAN MARATHON RACE--A GREEK RUNNER TO PARTICIPAT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.3--On September 23, a Marathon Race will take place in Chicago to which the principal athletic clubs of America will send members for participation. The Pan-Hellenic Club of Chicago will be represented by L. Lambrakis. A committee composed of Dr. John Volicos, N. Protopappas, and Ch. Vlachandreas has been appointed by the Greek club to follow Lambrakis in an automobile and assist him in case of need.</p>
   <p>Lambrakis, who is 23 years old and has lived here for the last ten years, was born in Koniditsa, Sellacia county, Lacedaemon, Greece. In spite of his small stature he possesses tremendous power and endurance. Although he is to compete with twenty other runners who are considered perfectly well qualified to win the race, many of his American friends have already proclaimed him as winner.</p>
   <p>The Pan-Hellenic Club will be represented at the grand stand of the Washington Park Club by Messrs. Karavelis, Printezis, and Demetracopoulos and <pb facs="5422062_3_1611.jpg" n="2"/>by the already chosen committee of three which will follow the young Greek racer. The route of the twenty-five-mile race is as follows: on Saturday, September 23, at 2 P.M., from the Evanston Golf Club grounds, the startingpoint of the race, by Sheridan Road, Lake Shore Drive, Lincoln Park, Lake Shore Drive, Chicago Avenue, Rush Street and Rush Street Bridge to Michigan Avenue; by Michigan Avenue, Garfield Boulevard, and Washington Park Speedway to the Washington Park Club. Greeks and a great many Americans who know Lambrakis have placed heavy bets on him. Lambrakis will be the only alien in the race; the other nineteen runners are Americans. Can he win? Let us see!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
