<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1924-10-11">Oct. 11, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Lappas in the Concert of the St. Catherine Society for the Benefit of Poor Children.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0366</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0366.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1924-10-11">Oct. 11, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">MR. LAPPAS IN THE CONCERT OF THE ST. CATHERINE SOCIETY FOR THE BENEFIT OF POOR CHILDREN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 8 - In the program of the concert given by the influential St. Catherine's Society of Evanston, Illinois, for the benefit of poor children, two operatic stars were included.</p>
   <p>At the magnificent Orchestra Hall last Tuesday the Greek Adonis, Ulysses Lappas, tenor of the London and Chicago Operas, and Mrs. Thurston, another concert star, delighted the big audience with their fascinating voices. The spacious hall was packed with more than three thousand people of the elite of society, among whom were the Cardinal, bishops, judges, bankers, the Mayor, and other prominent persons.</p>
   <p>The program, which consisted of Italian, American, and Greek pieces (because of the insistence of Mr. Lappas, who said that he would sing only if Greek songs were included), was executed to perfection. Miss Zarokosta, dignified and graceful, accompanied Mr. Lappas, who, aroused prolonged applause whenever he appeared on the platform. His impressive appearance, his voice, and his technique captured the audience and he was called back again and again.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0367.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He sang two Greek songs not included in the program.</p>
   <p>Not only the Greeks but the entire audience displayed great enthusiasm for the Greek songs and justified Mr. Lappas' Epirote courage and national pride in refusing to sing unless there were Greek songs on the program. He made the foreigners admire the songs although they did not understand them.</p>
   <p>We extend our sincere congratulations to the great Greek operatic star for his spirit in upholding Grecian ideals and spreading the knowledge of Greek art among foreigners. May God promote his success!</p>
   <p>All the American newspapers printed many complimentary things about the voice and the appearance of Mr. Ulysses Lappas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
