<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-02-12">Feb. 12, 1931</date><title level="a">Marika Cotopouli in "Karagiozis" as Seen in Her Performance</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Nick John Matsoukas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0421</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0421.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-02-12">Feb. 12, 1931</date><title level="a">MARIKA COTOPOULI IN "KARAGIOZIS" AS SEEN IN HER PERFORMANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Nick John Matsoukas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 6.- A social satiric drama in three acts by Theodore Synodinos was presented at the Studebaker Theatre, Monday night, Feb. 9th, at 8:30 P.M., by Marika Cotopouli and her company.</p>
   <p>Modern Greek intellectualism, fortunately or otherwise, tends to borrow from our immediate friends, namely the genteel French, the Tartar Russians, the reincarnated Hellenes, the Germans, the sturdy Scandinavians and sometimes from the business like minded Anglo Saxons. Our modern literature, is somewhat afflicted with the curse of plagiarism. There might be a reason for that, some seem to be believe. But in the case of "Karagiozis" it proves that it exists.</p>
   <p>Theodore Synodinos is a clever writer. He also seems to be more clever in his attempts to amalgamate dramatic formulas. "Karagiozis", branded as a contemporary Greek social satyric drama, has its skeleton borrowed <pb facs="5422062_3_0422.jpg" n="2"/>from Ibsen's "Pillars of Society" and "Ghosts" by the same dramatist who seems to have supplied the spiritual motif of the play. For flesh and blood it has been handsomely filled in by good Greek common sense and its phraseology has been reduced down to a level where a ten year old child can understand it. Synodinos knows how to use words. Words in turn express idea. A living drama necessitates both. These he has arranged and served properly to the one hundred year old skeleton.</p>
   <p>The legendary character of Karagiozis, with his cynical sense of humor and deformed body, plays havoc with the play to such an extent that I wasn't so certain whether I was in Chicago or at the Royal Theatre in Stockholm.</p>
   <p>But what did Madame Cotopouli do to "Karagiozis?" As an answer I will say to you, what did Michalangelo do to painting when he took it up? She put forth a "Karagiozis" that thrilled me physically and spiritually.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0423.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A balanced dose of humor and bitter cynicism was the result. Just as the audience was getting ready for a good hearty laugh you were being forced to subside in your own misery and say to yourself, "Get rid of that wench, Nicho Paganis." But "Karagiozis" would answer, "It is fruitless. Crooks and vagabonds, are humans and humans are petty. So why should one excite himself over pettiness." The only objection that some Greeks in Chicago might have about the play is that Karagiozis, Evgale T'aplita Sti Fora (Exposed Another's Dirty Linen). But what of it? That is fruitless, too. Unlike any other actress that I have seen Madam Cotopouli is one Thespian artist that is just as much at home with heavy tragedy as she is with social drama.</p>
   <p>Characterization and mimicry reach their zenith with her. Let us go to see her at the Civic Opera House a week from Saturday. There you will see "Eratocritos" that immortal Cretan epic poem of the Seventeenth Century which Synodinos has transferred into a play.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
