<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-12-09">Dec. 9, 1930</date>, p. 1.
<title level="a">The Sons of Pericles</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0609</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0609.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-12-09">Dec. 9, 1930</date>, p. 1.
<title level="a">THE SONS OF PERICLES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The stage presentation by the young Greeks of the Sons of Pericles at the Eighth Street Theater last Sunday night, we can only call a national night.</p>
   <p>The efforts and labor exerted for the successful performance of Esme must be extolled and just praise must be tendered to those who undertook the task and accomplished it.</p>
   <p>We must confess that the task of preparation for the performance of such a drama was not easy, considering the fact that most of the boys and girls who participated in the play did not know how to speak Greek very well. And for this reason the performance is to be considered a grand success and an accomplishment of importance for our race. For the Lord Byron Lodge of the Sons of Pericles succeeded in teaching its members to speak Greek and inspiring them with Greek sentiments and national pride; because they are Greeks and speak Greek, despite the fact that they were born in America.</p>
   <p>The first part of the program consisted of church hymns sung by our youth, and <pb facs="5422062_3_0610.jpg" n="2"/>various speeches by the officials of Ahepa, which might have been omitted in order to carry away an integral impression of the children of the new generation with their pure and genuine feeling for what is Greek and their assurance on oath that they will maintain this feeling for life.</p>
   <p>The second part consisted of the performance of the play, which, considering the linguistic difficulties and stage inexperience, was perfectly presented and aroused the emotions of the large audience.</p>
   <p>The third part of the program was the exhibition of Greek social life by dances and songs. The children danced so rhythmically and sang so melodiously, that their performances were applauded and repeatedly encored by the enthusiastic audience.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
