<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-06-18">June 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Loxias' Third Year</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1157</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1157.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-06-18">June 18, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">LOXIAS' THIRD YEAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- Today, June 18, Loxias starts its third year as a newspaper. We are proud to say that we have not sunk down to the level of the other Greek newspapers in America which are hypocritical, false, and deceiving. We have always tried to look out for the best interests of our countrymen. We have given them suggestions; we have argued with them; and we have chided them--all for their own good.</p>
   <p>We are not rich and we are not poor. We don't print material because it will bring in subscriptions, but because it is the truth and should be known by all. We have been in the journalistic field for ten years and are proud of our record of clean, unbiased truth.</p>
   <p>We have been constantly aware of what is going on around us, and many times have we warned our unsuspecting countrymen of some danger or peril unforeseen by them and the other newspaper men. Sometimes we have been <pb facs="5422062_3_1158.jpg" n="2"/>thanked for the warning, sometimes cursed, but it is a pleasant feeling to know we have done our duty.</p>
   <p>Sometimes we have been a little harsh in our criticisms. This was because our words could not penetrate the thick skins of some Greeks any other way. Forgive us, because we are striving for the benefit of every Greek in Chicago, not for ourselves alone.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
