<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-02-24">Feb. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Performance by Kanellos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0498</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0498.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1917-02-24">Feb. 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">PERFORMANCE BY KANELLOS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Thursday, the sixteenth of this month, Mr. Basileus A. Kanellos gave a dance exhibition. His program consisted of ancient Greek dances and small parts of ancient Greek dramas.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kanellos is a well-known exponent of the ancient Greek dances. He succeeded in accomplishing his purpose of putting on a finished and artistic performance through persistence and patience, despite the fact that he had no financial backing, and little artistic support. He worked so hard with the amateurs who assisted him in his dances that they did not hinder his artistic performance as much as had been expected. The dancing of Mr. Kanellos is fine, and it seems as if his body had been especially moulded to interpret this ancient Greek art.</p>
   <p>We are sad to say that the audience was noisy and unappreciative, and continued to murmur and rattle paper long after the performance had begun. Since the theater is very small the disturbance was doubly annoying.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0499.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The program was successfully carried out and the Greek ballet "At the Time of the Flower Festival of Dionysus" was especially good; as was also the "Sacred Dance of Orestes".</p>
   <p>While the performance as a whole was well carried out, there should have been more variety in the dances. Their sameness bored the audience (whose artistic appreciation was prectically nil). We also wish to comment upon a rule which is customary at many Greek performances; that is, playing the Greek National Anthem at the beginning of a program. First of all, it is neither necessary nor correct to play the Anthem at all public affairs; and if it is considered indispensable, then the American National Anthem should be played first. Since we live in America and not in Greece, it is necessary that we show our respect to our adopted country.</p>
   <p>Congratulations are extended to Mr. Kanellos and Miss Kanellos, and also to E. Eleftheriou, T. Harilaou and....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
