<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-03-09">March 9, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">The Duty of the Greek Press in America Hellas Revokes its Announcement-Pleasing Occurence</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1208</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1208.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-03-09">March 9, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">THE DUTY OF THE GREEK PRESS IN AMERICA HELLAS REVOKES ITS ANNOUNCEMENT-PLEASING OCCURENCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are very happy to read that Hellas, our sister Greek paper in Chicago, in plain and unequivoral language revokes its announcement regarding the purported request of the Greek Minister of the Interior, who according to this Chicago Greek publication had delegated Hellas to compile statistics of our fellow-Greeks residing in Illinois and in the State of California. The Star in previous issues urged its sister paper for the sake of journalistic principle, to abandon such forms of deception. Our suggestions were accepted, our logic was heeded, and with real joy we read the withdrawal of the announcement in the column of our sister paper. This ends the discussion of the matter, and we call it felicitous ending.</p>
   <p>The Greek press in the United States, in our conception, has a sacred duty to perform. That duty is above material gain and above anything else. The duty is to guard and to guide our fellow-Greeks in America and to exalt the honor of the Greek name. By doing that we not only benefit enormously the Greek element of our population, but we also automatically become patent factors in benefiting our adopted country. The real prosperity of a country depends upon the enlightement of its citizens. And here in America, which is called because of its heterogeneous masses the international <pb facs="5422062_3_1209.jpg" n="2"/>melting-pot, the future citizen of Greek extraction, who will ultimately be an integral part of the whole, needs much more guardianship and guidance than he would need in any other country.</p>
   <p>The duty of the Greek press is to illumine the minds of the greenhorns, the frantics, the uniformed, the deluded, and all others that need enlightenment, teaching them that Americanization is not in the same category with Bulgarization or Turcofication but is a real liberation of the individual. It means freedom and justice. Many of our fellow-Greeks, extremely conscientious also extremely but narrow-minded, live in perpetual dread because of their lack of understanding. The thought of forsaking his beloved Greece and his traditions and becoming a citizen of the United States tortures the mind of the uniformed Greek.</p>
   <p>It is the duty of the press to disabuse the minds of those so afflicted and to prove by systematic explanation what Americanization means.</p>
   <p>In order to command the respect of the public and to accomplish its journalistic purpose, the Greek press in America must be guiltless of any desire to deceive and true to its own principles, an example to guard and to guide our fellow-Greeks in <pb facs="5422062_3_1210.jpg" n="3"/>America. If we desire to perpetuate the immortal Greek leaven in the American bodies and souls of our future generation, we must keep a vigilant eye on the welfare of the Greeks in America and on the sacredness of the Greek name.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
