<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-10-02">Oct. 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Young Ladies' Dance.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0930</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0930.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-10-02">Oct. 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE YOUNG LADIES' DANCE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Friday evening, the Young Women's Literary Club of Chicago gave a dance which exceeded our wildest expectations. Their patience and hard work have been rewarded because the dance was a huge success. Everyone felt at home due to the hospitable ways of the charming president, Alexandra Tulupan.</p>
   <p>At the door we were greeted by Nina Perdikes who pinned a rose on each and ushered each one of us into the salon. There we were greeted by a bevy of beautiful girls, all eager to welcome us. Among the beautifully dressed women were: Mrs. Maria Vatsinea, Martha Roussi, Mrs. Ligeri Marantis, Mrs. Chronopoulos, Mr. P. Lambros (wife of the editor of the Greek Star), Mrs. Papatheodore, Miss Mitou, Miss Miller (Milias), Miss Papanicholas, Miss Cokins (Kokkinou) Miss Raftis, Miss Lempesis, Miss Geormbas, Lenia Fournarakis, Miss Calvert (Kalabritinou), Miss Bouloukus, Mrs. Katina G. Stauropoulus, Mrs. Ntinas. Nicholopoulos, Mrs. Sikokis, Mrs. Minagiotou, Mrs.Basilopoulos, the Misses Diangelis, Mrs. Chrisous, Mrs. Kameas, Mrs. Evanthia Tsakidou, Mrs. Meronis, Mrs. Zambraki (wife of the doctor), the Mrs. P. and G. Nicholopoulos, and many others.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0931.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We congratulate the girls who did so much to make this dance a success. Below are the names of the members:</p>
   <p>Officers:</p>
   <p>Alexandra Tulupan- President</p>
   <p>Virginia Floras- Vice-president</p>
   <p>Liberty Vournazou-Secretary</p>
   <p>Harriet Licouris- Rec. Secretary</p>
   <p>Sylvia Calvert- Treasurer.</p>
   <p>Directors: Nina Perdikes, Galateia Hajon, Bertha Floros, Pearl Souyoul, Lulu Giorma.</p>
   <p>Members: Magda Cokins, Muriel Columbos, Lenia Fillmore, Eleanor Gianaeopoulos, Antigoni Gianakutsu, Mary Gianakutsu, Nina Hajon, Angeline Laris, Helen Laris, Kathryn Licouris, Anna Mary Maras, Lila, Maras, Phyllis Rioniotis, Despo Sotiniadou, Bessie Tarantelis and Mary Votsis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
