<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-04-23">April 23, 1931</date><title level="a">Melange</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Nick John Matsoukas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0603</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0603.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-04-23">April 23, 1931</date><title level="a">MELANGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Nick John Matsoukas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- Here are some great news for you. A certain young lady, member of the Young Ladies Philomusical Hellenic Society, informed me that the society intends to do justice to its name. They have decided to take up lessons in the art of harmonica playing. Can you picture the situation; a recital by the Y.L.P. (?) H.S. with harmonicas?</p>
   <p>The Knickerbocker had somewhat of a fair attendance last Sunday. The "400" did not appear in body, only in spirit. We saw a few children sleeping on the chairs and a male couple dancing together. Imagine that these people were not informed that this dance was for blue blooded ones-----</p>
   <p>One good thing about the dance last Sunday is that I met an exceptionally clever Greek girl, Miss Christine Limberis. She is in charge of an office at the Transportation building rendering service to outgoing and <pb facs="5422062_3_0604.jpg" n="2"/>incoming immigrants. Her clientele is varied. From Irene Bordini, the French musical star down to Tony (Mops) Volpe, famous gangster who is about to be deported. The young lady is selling service at reasonable rates. This is not an advertisement for her office. It is merely an appreciation for the efforts of a young Greek lady who has originated an idea and goes ahead alone trying to put it over. She assists immigrants in entering and leaving U.S. In her business routine she encounters many funny incidents. She related that the other day she asked a German lady the color of her complexion and her customer showed her transformation. Another one she asked as to the existence of any birthmarks and he was about to show her his appendicitis operation. Such misunderstandings are common among foreigners who are ignorant of the language. Such tales have their charm.</p>
   <p>When I heard them they reminded me of the time when I played my first game of baseball some twelve years ago, two years after I landed in America. Accidentally I hit the ball over the yard fence. The boys yelled, "Run for home Nick." Taking the command literally, I started like lightning, homeward bound. Up to this day my sister does not know why I come in the house so completely out of breath, on that afternoon.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0605.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And now that the dance season is over something worthwhile is springing up. After much deliberation, the "big shots" of the Ahepa were finally convinced that "Theodora the Empress" by Demetrios Michalaros is something worthwhile to see. They are presenting the Hull House players who will stage the play sometimes in May at the Studebaker theatre.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt that even Ahepans are susceptible to learning if something is presented properly to them. The results from the Ahepa decision will be most beneficial to the Greeks. A play of exquisite beauty will be staged. It deals with the period of Greek history, 6th Century A.D., the epoch that left such an impression upon our present ethnic make up that we can freely say that Theodora and her times are the days when the Greeks were young.</p>
   <p>The play is to be preceded by a whole week of Byzantine revival, in which time there will be an exhibition of Byzantine art for the first time in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0606.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Byzantine Choir will offer its services free of charge in participating at this play. Pageantry, beauty that is entirely Byzantine and an interpretation of a historic character that is entirely comprehensible to the modern mind, are the outstanding features of this Ahepa festivity.</p>
   <p>Michalaros, I take my hat off to you. Bravo! Since I am in charge of the exhibition, I request from all of you that in case you come across with an ikon or a relic that is of age and possesses beauty, to notify me. I shall be up to see it and request that it be lent to this cause. Come on. Let us show the Americans the treasures that we have in our ikonastasia.</p>
   <p>Read next week's "Melange". An important announcement is about to be made. Now in the meantime, if you have any contributions to make, see that they get in with the next mail.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
