<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-08-31">Aug. 31, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Ahepa Forms Greek School in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-08-31">Aug. 31, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">AHEPA FORMS GREEK SCHOOL IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The twenty-first division of the Ahepa, which is under the leadership of Mr. D. Parry, well-known Greek lawyer of Chicago, held a meeting a few weeks ago. At this meeting it was decided to form a Greek school. It will open in the Loop in September.</p>
   <p>The Ahepa has sponsored many lectures and affairs which have contributed to the culture and pleasure of the Greek people in Chicago. One of its aims is to enlighten and educate the Greek people. By organizing this school the Ahepa, will fulfill its purpose as set forth in its constitution: "to rebuild, rekindle, cultivate, and enrich the finer and higher ideologies of true Greeks."</p>
   <p>The school is to be in complete charge of Mr. N. Papanickopoulos, who will <pb facs="5422062_3_1310.jpg" n="2"/>be allowed to follow any program or method of teaching he may deem advisable. This man was the principal of the well-known Greek-American School, "Koraes," and he put into practice there his pedagogical and educational training. It is quite certain that the students of the Ahepa School will achieve a good command of the Greek language because it will be taught according to the new American method, which is effective and simple.</p>
   <p>An examination of its prospectus, Subject and Course Program, shows that there are four divisions in the school. In the first three divisions the following subjects will be taught: modern Greek philology; Greek history, ancient and modern; Greek political science; analytical study of Greek religion; and the geography of Greece. In the fourth division; first year high school Greek grammar, syntax, and literature, including philology; and the history of contemporary Greece (1912-1933); Asiatic catastrophes and Greek democracy; etc. [sic]. The last division will be open to all pupils who have graduated from a Greek-American grammar school, or to all those who can pass the <pb facs="5422062_3_1311.jpg" n="3"/>the required entrance examinations.</p>
   <p>This program shows, beyond a doubt, that the Greek School of Ahepa is founded upon much higher standards than the average school, and the list of students is already considerably long.</p>
   <p>A Series of Free Open Lectures</p>
   <p>We have been informed that Mr. Papanickolopoulos will present a series of lectures during the first of the present school year. These lectures will be bi-weekly and the topic will be: "The Effect of Greek Philology upon Europe during the Period of the Renaissance." [The transitional period in Europe between the medieval and the modern, marked especially by the revival of classical influence.] These lectures will be especially designed for the understanding of high school graduates.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1312.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Any information desired concerning the School or its curriculum can be obtained from the nearest Ahepa chapter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
