<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>St. Constantine Parish News</title>,
<date when="1934-04-29">Apr. 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Chapter of Daughters of Penelope Organized</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1651</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1651.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>St. Constantine Parish News</title>,
<date when="1934-04-29">Apr. 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO CHAPTER OF DAUGHTERS OF PENELOPE ORGANIZED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For some time the mother Lodge of the "Daughters of Penelope" of San Francisco deemed it wise to extend its membership scope to all parts of the United States, so they proceeded to nominate deputy organizers for each of the larger cities.</p>
   <p>Mr. Mark Mamalakis, former president of chapter #46 of the Order of Ahepa, was chosen as deputy organizer of this city. He called a first meeting on Thursday evening, April 17, at the Hotel La Salle, and about fifty women attended. Assisted by Mr. George Spannon and Mr. D. Parry, he explained to the assembled group that the purpose of the organization was an attempt to uphold Greek idealism in the hearts of the Greek people.</p>
   <p>Later in the evening possible candidates were nominated by the women present. Since it was too late to hold elections, the meeting was adjourned with the expressed hope of the chairman that the new members would seriously consider the eligible nominees.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1652.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the next meeting the elections were held with the following results:</p>
   <p>Mrs. Mary Pofanti, an unusually active woman in all South-Side Clubs, was elected president. Miss Barbara Petrakis, who will graduate from Mandalein College in June, was elected vice-president. Mrs. Mary Spannon, wife of the well known South-Side lawyer, was elected secretary. Mrs. Athena Pittas, who for many years has held several responsible positions in women's organizations, was elected treasurer; and Mrs. Fotini Varounis, head-teacher of Koreas School, was elected governor.</p>
   <p>The Parish News feels sure that with such competent leadership, the "D. of P." will progress courageously and take their rightful place among the recognized Greek clubs of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
