<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-01-16">Jan. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Greek-American Bank</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0175</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0175.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-01-16">Jan. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEK-AMERICAN BANK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All who have believed the statements found in various other Greek papers, and who have doubted the statements made by Saloniki, are asked to read this column very carefully.....</p>
   <p>As we have previously announced, the property of this bank was sold at auction last Tuesday. No offers were made for the furniture and fixtures of the bank. Mr. Alafouzos offered $2,500 for the 758 safety deposit boxes, but he was refused.</p>
   <p>The lease of the bank building, which expires April 30, 1922, was bought for $5,700 by N. Kyriakopoulos, C. Tampari, and John Varella. They also bought the real estate on the corner of Kedzie and Irving Park Boulevard for $5,250. Mr. Bousios bought the lease on the store at 622 South Halsted Street for $150.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0176.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The buildings at 625, 734-736, and 738 Blue Island Avenue were sold to Mr. B. Doukas after he paid the mortgage of $1,500 on the property. Mr. Kyriakopoulos bid $10,000 for the building on the corner of Elston Avenue and Montrose Boulevard but his bid was not accepted.</p>
   <p>Mr. Grossman's bid of $450 for the property in Euclid Park was accepted. Theodore Sperison bought the three lots at 77th and West Hudurn [sic] for $1,000. Three other lots at the same location were purchased by Mr. Mylonas for $450. A house, located at Humphrey Avenue and Van Buren Street, was purchased by Mr. Mylonas for $1,125.</p>
   <p>Thus it is evident that the poor depositors will not receive even one dime for each dollar they have deposited. In fact, after the court expenses are deducted nothing will be available. In this manner the Greeks of Chicago have been robbed of their savings; moreover, the accomplices to the crime <pb facs="5422062_3_0177.jpg" n="3"/>are the Greek and American papers which have covered up the true state of affairs.</p>
   <p>Saloniki was the only newspaper who fought for the rights of the poor laborers who had placed implicit faith in the integrity of the Greek bankers. The bankers and their friends have proved themselves to be exactly what we have been calling them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
