<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-06-08">June 8, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">To the Officials and the Members of All Chapters of Ahepa</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1720</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1720.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1930-06-08">June 8, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE OFFICIALS AND THE MEMBERS OF ALL CHAPTERS OF AHEPA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 6- The supreme vice-president wishes to announce to all brothers that since he is alertly conscious of his duty to take cognizance of the spiritual and mental attitudes of all members, and since he is aware that for certain reasons things have been in a state of unrest for a number of years, he has seen fit to send the following telegram to the Most Reverend Father Damaskinos, Metropolitan Bishop of Corinth, now on board the S. S. Byron, approaching our shores:</p>
   <p>"Ahepa greets and cordially welcomes Your Reverence and without hesitation offers to you its moral support, hopeful of Your Reverence's happy solution of our questions pending.</p>
   <p>P. G. Sikokis,</p>
   <p>Presiding Vice-President."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1721.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are all aware of the purpose of this special mission of the Most Reverend Bishop Damaskinos, and that he comes to us intrusted by the Ecumenical Patriarchate and by the Holy Synod of the Church of Greece with plans for the amelioration of conditions and the pacification of discordant elements in our local churches.</p>
   <p>Your presiding vice-president believes that these glad tidings will inspire and fortify you all. To deny the existence of an abnormal situation which requires a beneficent and pacifying agent would be to act the ostrich's part, and to refuse our moral support would be an act of injustice to our families too grave to pardon.</p>
   <p>Surely and unavoidably a situation which greatly upsets an individual's mind and heart will affect and hinder his progress and consequently his contribution to humanity in general and to his nation in particular.</p>
   <p>But although this is an indisputable fact, the telegram above cited and this letter should not be misconstrued. There is not the slightest intention of exciting any member of Ahepa nor of conveying to him the faintest hint that he should deviate from his course heretofore pursued.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1722.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We are not interested in the individual nor in personal ambitions and motives. We are interested in the principles and the high ideals which created our organization and will hereafter enlarge it and the members who compose it.</p>
   <p>But when under such circumstances and after careful and diligent observation the government of a nation, the Ecumenical Patriarchate, the Head of that Orthodox Christianity to which a large majority of our members abide loyal, and the Holy Synod of the Church of Greece have all decided upon the mission of the Most Reverend Father Damaskenos, Metropolitan Bishop of Corinth, then whatever his instructions, his authority, and his mission may be, we ought not to hesitate to accept the solution offered by him to this abnormal situation which for many years has kept in suspense half a million of our compatriots.</p>
   <p>We suggest that this circular letter be read in our meetings for one month or at least in two meetings, and that it be widely published in Greek journals if such exist in your vicinity.</p>
   <p>Fraternally yours for a better future,</p>
   <p>P. G. Sikokis,</p>
   <p>Presiding Vice-President.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
