<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-05-02">May 2, 1931</date>, p. 3
<title level="a">Plans for the Chicago Jubilee Grow-Greeks of Chicago Will Participate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0787</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0787.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1931-05-02">May 2, 1931</date>, p. 3
<title level="a">PLANS FOR THE CHICAGO JUBILEE GROW-GREEKS OF CHICAGO WILL PARTICIPATE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>May 10th. to 20th. will be a period of celebration and festivity in Chicago. During this period the Chicago Jubilee will take place, which will mark a political and ecomomic revival in Chicago, and is designed to show the rest of the world that Chicago is not the kind of a city most people think it is.</p>
   <p>In this Jubilee, which is sponsored by the Chicago Association of Commerce, the Greek people of this city will contribute their share.</p>
   <p>They will be represented by the Byzantine choir, which recently sang over radio station, W.G.N, with great success. It is planned that they will be grouped on a striking float of Byzantine design from which they will sing various Byzantine hymns, under the directon of Mr. Demetrios Papageorge.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0788.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Beside participating in the huge parade which will probably take place Monday night, May 11th. the Byzantine choir will also be heard on various other occasions throughout the Jubilee.</p>
   <p>The committee in charge of the celebration is issuing a special medalion as a souvenir of the event. They will be sold at the Churches and at various society meetings. Every one buying one of these madalions may contribute whatever he wishes, and the money thus collected will be used to cover up the expenses of the float.</p>
   <p>In this way it is planned to have the expense paid by a large number of people, each contributing a little, and thus avoid leaving the burden to fall on a few who would have to contribute a large sum.</p>
   <p>In order to enhance the effect of the float by the largest number of voices in the choir, it is requested that anyone who wishes to participate do so by applying to Mr. Dem. Papgeorge, the Director, or Mr. Nick Matsukas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
