<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-06-13">June 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">[Italy Outlaws the New York Times]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0987</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0987.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-06-13">June 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">[ITALY OUTLAWS THE NEW YORK TIMES]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From personal observation we know that nearly all the readers of this column also read the editorial comments of American papers which we reprint in the Greek Press....The selection of these articles is made very carefully, with one and only one idea in mind;--to show the trend of prevailing opinion as revealed in the American press concerning national and international problems. In our regular browsing around in order to cull what we consider the most appropriate article to be reprinted, we have often made use of editorials from the New York Times. The Times, admittedly one of the cleanest papers in America, is being widely quoted as representing sound, conservative, and rational American opinion. Going through its editorial columns of last Monday's issue, our eye caught an editorial entitled, "Baldwin and Mussolini". Finding it very constructive in its comments and more than logical in its conclusions, we turned it over to our linotype man. As this is being written, we read in <pb facs="5422062_3_0988.jpg" n="2"/>the Chicago Daily News that the New York Times has been barred from circulation in Italy, due to that particular article.</p>
   <p>This action on the part of Mussolini proves conclusively the truth of the arguments set forth in this column--to the effect that Mussolini is nothing less than a low type charlatan and a tyrant. If articles such as the New York Times' editorial--which we recommend for their consideration to our readers--offend Mussolini, then one can easily judge the mental caliber of the man who wants to create an Italian empire in Africa.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
