<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-08-09">Aug. 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Miracle</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1913-08-09">Aug. 9, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A MIRACLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If the 25,000 Greeks of Chicago would become subscribers to Saloniki, of which this is the third issue since it first appeared in our Greek community three weeks ago, it could undoubtedly be published ten times a day. This is an hypothetical "if" which flatters us greatly.</p>
   <p>It was with such miracles, suppositions, and fond hopes that such Chicago Greek newspapers--now defunct and of blessed memory--as Thermopyle, Pan-Hellenic, Hellas, The Immigrant, The Daily Mail, as well as many other insignificant publications, expected to survive and grow.</p>
   <p>According to the great New York Greek daily, the Atlantis, all the publishers and editors of these "most remarkable news organs" were nothing else but pretentious and uncertain adventurers. Since there were many different types of adventurous writers and publishers, naturally there were as many different publications. Traveling salesmen for these papers used all sorts of <pb facs="5422062_3_1137.jpg" n="2"/>tricks to get subscribers. One fellow said that when he wants a young man in the shoe-shine parlor to subscribe, all he has to do is smile at him. Then the boss of a store can be persuaded to subscribe by a mere wink of the eye. The subscription problem is thus easily solved in this way by some publications. Such methods will not be used by every newspaper, however.</p>
   <p>We would like to tell our readers all about our newly published Saloniki, about its assets, its aims, and its general policy. Because we lack space, however, we will not give an account of ourselves in this issue. we only wish to remind the Greek public that Saloniki will resort to no tricks in soliciting and gaining subscribers. We sell for what we are worth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
