<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Invitation, Dated Chicago, Ill.</title><date when="1923-04-24">April 24, 1923</date>,
<title level="a">in possession of M. C. Mammon 208 S. La Salle Street.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0463</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0463.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Invitation, Dated Chicago, Ill.</title><date when="1923-04-24">April 24, 1923</date>,
<title level="a">in possession of M. C. Mammon 208 S. La Salle Street.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Drama League of America in the interest of</p>
   <p>The Festival of the Greek Arts to be held at the Auditorium Theatre, May Seventh requests your presence Tuesday morning, April 24th, at eleven o'clock at the residence of</p>
   <p>Mrs. Frederick D. Countiss, 1524 Lake Shore Drive. Mr. Vassos Kanellos will speak on the Greek Dance and exhibit authentic Greek costumes. Other speakers will include M. Constantine Mammon (Prince Paleologos). M. Trigetas, the Greek Vice-Consul, and Mr. Lorado Taft, Chairman of the Festival.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0464.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Greek Festival Committee</p>
   <p>Lorado Taft, Chairman, Mrs. Edward R. Fifield, Vice-Chairman Constantine Mammon, Treasurer, Mrs. William Cleff, Tickets</p>
   <p>Patrons</p>
   <p>Mr. Arthur C. Aldis</p>
   <p>Mr. Graham Aldis</p>
   <p>Mrs. Richard Barnitz</p>
   <p>Mrs. Jacob Baur</p>
   <p>Mr. John Borden</p>
   <p>Mrs. Walter F. Braun</p>
   <p>Mrs. Julius C. Benedict, Mrs. Walter Brewester, Mrs. William Bush, Mrs. Harry E. Byram, Mrs. John Alden Carpenter, Mrs. Joseph Coleman, Mrs. Frederick Countiss, General Charles S. Dawes, Mrs. George Dixon, Mrs. Edward Warren Everett, Mrs. Kellogg Fairbanks, Mrs. Henri Farre, Mrs. Henri Fish, Dean Roy C. Flickinger, Miss Mary Glenn, Mrs. Claude Hopkins, Mrs. Clarence Hough, Mrs. Milan Hulbert, Samuel Insull, Mrs. Henry Pratt Judson, Mrs. Charles Kohl Sr., Mrs. Edward Leight, Mrs. L. Hamilton McCormick, Mrs. Rockefeller McCormick, Mrs. Russell Matthias, <pb facs="5422062_3_0465.jpg" n="3"/>Mrs. John R. Mauff, Mrs. Arthur Meeker, Miss Olga Menn, Mrs. Edward Morris, Mrs. Francis Neilson, Mr. Francis Weilson, Mrs. Potter Palmer, Mrs. Augustus Peabody, Mrs. Charles S. Peterson, Mr. Charles Peterson, Mrs. M. B. Pitman, Mrs. Harrison B. Riley, Mr. Carroll Shaffer, Mrs. Paul Shorey, Mr. Paul Shorey, Mrs. Gustavus F. Swift, Mrs. Frank M. Taber, Mrs. Lorado Taft, Mrs. Russell Tyson, Mrs. Margeret Williamson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
