<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1919-05-17">May 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Performance in Auditorium Theater</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0669</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0669.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-05-17">May 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">PERFORMANCE IN AUDITORIUM THEATER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Filled with national pride, I dare to write about the successful and touching performance of "The Dance of Zallogou" last Sunday night.... I will not be able to describe with mere words the poignant, heartbreaking drama, and the fine acting of the children of "Socrates," who took part.....</p>
   <p>Before the performance began, Mrs. C. Kantzou, their teacher, spoke to the audience as follows: "What are we all waiting for with such anxiety? It is the performance of 'The Dance of Zallogou' which has brought so many of us here tonight. Not skilled artists, but little school children are to take part in this drama. School! It is the holiest and finest word which can be formed by human lips. School! It is the finest institution ever founded by culture and religion. School! It is the basis of patriotism and religion, for within its walls are taught the essentials of both..... School! It is the sun on earth, by whose rays everything that is fine and good is brought to light...." These were the words of the teacher, whose voice trembled with <pb facs="5422062_3_0670.jpg" n="2"/>emotion and ardor, as she asked the support and aid of the community in behalf of the schools.</p>
   <p>Then the curtains parted to disclose one of the loveliest scenes ever witnessed by an audience. Thirty boys and girls wearing the beloved Foustanella (kilts) and the costume of the Souliotisses [women of Souli] were grouped on the stage, looking like a painting by Raphael or like pieces of sculpture by the famous Phidias. Do not ask me to describe what happened then. The rafters of the theater rang as they never have before with the applause, the "zitos," and the enthusiastic voices of the audience. The orchestra under the direction of Mr. Spiros Becatoros, who is an honor to the Greek name, played the American and the Greek anthems while the audience stood and cheered. Then the curtain dropped and the lovely scene disappeared.</p>
   <p>Slowly the curtain rose again. The first one on the stage to speak was little Andrew Sellas, who played his part as the villager with naturalness and dramatic ability. Other actors participating were Pilios Gousis, Bill Mihos, G. Limberopoulos, E. Zoganas, Peter Movzakeotis; and the mother of "Drakos" <pb facs="5422062_3_0671.jpg" n="3"/>was played by A. Hondromaras.......</p>
   <p>The famous Greek actresses, Kotopouli, Kiveli and Beroni, must stand aside as a little Sarah Bernhardt passes. Ten-year-old Georgia Priovolou certainly is following in the footsteps of that great actress. Her performance as "Froso" was one of the finest that I have ever witnessed. She is a born artist, and her farewell to Peter Varzos, who played the part of her son, was so touching that it brought tears to the eyes of the audience.</p>
   <p>Then came the dance of Zallogou: one by one those brave women danced over the cliff. Finally all were gone, and the curtain dropped. Flowers were thrown upon the stage and the theater rang with applause. A violin and piano duet by Peter and Edward Varzos, who are ten and seven years old respectively, followed.</p>
   <p>The children and their teacher are to be congratulated for this fine performance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
