<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
"<title level="a">Statement of the Ownership, Management, Circulation, Etc., Required by the Act of Congress of Aug. 24, 1912</title>," <title>New Era</title>, Chicago, Ill.,
<date when="1921-06-01">June 1, 1921</date>, p. 27.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1233</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1233.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
"<title level="a">Statement of the Ownership, Management, Circulation, Etc., Required by the Act of Congress of Aug. 24, 1912</title>," <title>New Era</title>, Chicago, Ill.,
<date when="1921-06-01">June 1, 1921</date>, p. 27.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is a statement of the Ownership, Management, circulation, etc., required by the Act of Congress of August 24, 1912, of the New Era Magazine, published semi-monthly at Chicago, State of Illinois, County of Cook, for April 1, 1921.</p>
   <p>Before me, a notary public in and for the state and country aforesaid personally appeared George B. Lewis who, having been duly sworn according to law, deposes and says that he is the Business Manager of the New Era Magazine, and that the following is, to the best of his knowledge and belief, a true statement of the ownership, management, etc., of the aforesaid publication for the date shown in the above caption, required by the Act of August 24, 1912, embodied in Section 443, Postal Laws and Regulations, printed on the reverse of this form, to wit:</p>
   <p>1. That the names and addresses of the publisher, editor, managing editor <pb facs="5422062_3_1234.jpg" n="2"/>and business manager are:</p>
   <p>Publisher - Nea Zoe Greek Publishing Co., Inc. 600 Blue Island Ave.</p>
   <p>Editor - George Halepas, 600 Blue Island Ave.</p>
   <p>Managing Editor - George Halepas, 600 Blue Island Ave.</p>
   <p>Business Manager - George B. Lewis, 600 Blue Island Ave.</p>
   <p>2. That the owners are:</p>
   <p>Nea Zoe Greek Publishing Co., Inc. 600 Blue Island Ave.</p>
   <p>George Halepas, 600 Blue Island Ave.</p>
   <p>Alex. Sousanis, 600 Blue Island Ave.</p>
   <p>3. That the known bondholders, mortgages, and other security holders owning or holding 1 percent or more of total amount of bonds, mortgages or other securities are: None.</p>
   <p>4. That the two paragraphs next above, giving the names of the owners, stockholders, and security holders, if any, contain not only the list of stockholders and security holders as they appear upon the books of <pb facs="5422062_3_1235.jpg" n="3"/>the company but also, in cases where the stockholder or security holder appear upon the books of the company as trustee or in any other fiduciary relation, the name of the person or corporation for whom such trustee is acting, is given; also that the said two paragraphs contain statements embracing affiant's full knowledge and belief as to circumstances and conditions under which stockholders and security holders who do not appear upon the books of the company as trustees, hold stock and securities in a capacity other than that of a bona fide owner; and this affiant has no reason to believe that any other person, association, or corporation has any interest direct or indirect in the said stock, bonds, or other securities than as so stated by him.</p>
   <p>5. That the average number of copies of each issue of this publication sold or distributed, through the mails, or otherwise, to paid subscribers during the six months preceding the date shown above is .....(This information is required from daily publications only).</p>
   <p>(Sign) George B. Lewis.</p>
   <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this 16th day of April, 1921.</p>
   <p>(Sign) C A. Esslin</p>
   <p>(My commission expires July 29th, 1923.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
