<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1926-05-08">May 8, 1926</date><title level="a">The Mind of the Curriculum.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1230</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1230.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>SALONIKI</title>,
<date when="1926-05-08">May 8, 1926</date><title level="a">The Mind of the Curriculum.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2. Under the above title, a monthly publication made its first appearance last week. "The Mind of the Curriculum" is a periodical published by the Greek school, Socrates.</p>
   <p>It is intended that the pupils of the school shall be the editors of the publication. Each pupil shall reveal his mind through the paper. Five hundred pupils would tell their parents and the rest of the Greeks, what is on their mind. Each pupil will read and criticise the ideas of other pupils in this way. This publication is the first of its kind to make an appearance amongst the Greek schools of this city. Pupils of the other Greek Schools of Chicago, as well as of other cities, are invited to participate in this innovation of revealing their minds, by publishing similar periodicals. In this way the Greek language would be learned quicker and more effectively. Pupils all over the country would exchange views and ideas and acquire acquaintances and friendship through their respective publications. The "Mind of the Curriculum" will bring the Greek youth of the New Generation closer to each other through these media of intellectual, educational and social commonication.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1231.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The staff of the publication is composed entirely of pupils under the supervision of Mr. Lambrinopoulos, who is a teacher of the School Socrates and the initiator of the publication.</p>
   <p>The pupils through their editor, Athanassios K. Giannias ask the public not to be too critical if they should not be able to write as correctly as educated grown up people do.</p>
   <p>Athanassios K. Giannias, Editor.</p>
   <p>(pupil of the 5th grade.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
