<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1908-06-17">June 17, 1908</date><title level="a">A Friendly Notice to the Chicago Saturday Evening Herald</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1173</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1173.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1908-06-17">June 17, 1908</date><title level="a">A FRIENDLY NOTICE TO THE CHICAGO SATURDAY EVENING HERALD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.- It is to be regretted that gentlemen so shrewd and well informed as the editors of the Saturday Evening Herald should have momentarily relaxed the vigilance which has heretofore characterized the management of their paper, as to give publicity to the article classing Nicholas Papadakis as the only lawyer of the Greek Community of Chicago. So far as we know for N. Papadakis from an advertisement of Messrs. Lamborn and Cuernsey, lawyers, in the Greek newspaper, Athena, of Chicago, he is a student yet without any diploma, calling the attention of the Greeks to visit the offices of the above esteemed lawyers for finding there the best interpreter, N. Papadakis.</p>
   <p>The only Greek lawyers in Chicago, whose names are heard among the Greek colonists, are Messrs. N. Kyriakopoulos of Oxford University and Andrew Vlachos of Athens.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1174.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Another story in this article is that, among the doctors whose clientile is recruited from Americans as well as their own countrymen and who boast of practises running way up into the thousands, are doctors C. Theodore, C. Petroulas, John Volicos, and A. Sanichas. In the City of Chicago, except the above, there are in the heart of the Greek colony three more doctors, very well known and experienced at Paris, namely, Gregory Papaeliou, Gust Galliontzis, and John Papageorge.</p>
   <p>Another story is that in the City of Chicago there is a newspaper with the circulation of ten thousand copies and is supported by the advertisers and subscribers among the Greeks, by name Hellas, the principal organ of the colony. This information lacks any truth, as in the City of Chicago there are published three more papers, namely, The Star, The Athena, and the Loxias. The Star, to say the truth, has a larger circulation than the Hellas and Athena combined, delivered to 2,300 subscribers. The Star also carries more advertisements than the other two combined.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1175.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Next Arabian story is that Mr. Fotis Papadakis is the Secretary of the Greek Community. Not he, F. Papacotsos is the secretary.</p>
   <p>Arabian Night stories are much more interesting and quite as truthful as anything above told and stated.</p>
   <p>Our interest in this matter is not to show the public how our friends of The Saturday Evening Herald have, unwillingly, we do not doubt, been led to place a false statement before their readers. They are gentlemen of business acumen and quite able to take care of their own interest. The purpose Loxias has in view in calling attention to this untrue matter is to place the managers of other journals on their guard against the practise of some outside writers of passing "gold bricks" off on honest and unsuspecting members of the general community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
