<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Evening American</title>,
<date when="1919-11-11">Nov. 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Speed Lands Greek Trade Envoy.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0072</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0072.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Evening American</title>,
<date when="1919-11-11">Nov. 11, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO SPEED LANDS GREEK TRADE ENVOY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A bit of Chicago hustle has landed for the city's merchants and manufacturers one of the big fish of the foreign trade puzzle in the person of Miltiades Rezos, who a few days ago reached New York with letters of credit and orders for vast stores of American goods.</p>
   <p>President Harry H. Merick of the Chicago Association of Commerce heard Rezos was coming and sent Paul Demos, President of the American Society of the Greek Community of Chicago, to the seaboard to get him. As a result Mr. Rezos, with his letters of credit still intact and his order book blank, reached Chicago today.</p>
   <p>Advance reports said Mr. Rezos had backing from the National Bank of Greece for $20,000,000. The Greek envoy would not quote figures.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0073.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"I am well armed to take care of everything that is needed", was his way of putting it.</p>
   <p>"Why do I come to Chicago? Well, partly because Chicago came down to New York and got me. But I really prefer to come to Chicago for several reasons.</p>
   <p>"I am mostly interested in cereals and foodstuffs, and Chicago is the center of the food market of America.</p>
   <p>"Then I prefer Chicago's method of business. You are quicker and more up to date than in the East. Your business methods suit me better. And now that I have come,I want to say I am not going back empty handed."</p>
   <p>Mr. Rezos said the Greek merchants had decided that business which before the war was done with European houses should hereafter come to America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0074.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This trade before the war was $100,000,000 annually.</p>
   <p>Mr. Rezos has a contract with the Greek government for 100,000 tons of coal and with private interests for 500,000 tons, and has the money to pay for it. But Bah! these American strikes! He can't get the coal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
