<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Herald and Examiner</title>,
<date when="1934-06-25">June 25, 1934</date><title level="a">Greek Classios Live Again at Dedication Envoy Expresses Amazement Over Country Century of Progress Hellenic Pavilion Is Opened</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0721</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0721.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Herald and Examiner</title>,
<date when="1934-06-25">June 25, 1934</date><title level="a">GREEK CLASSIOS LIVE AGAIN AT DEDICATION ENVOY EXPRESSES AMAZEMENT OVER COUNTRY CENTURY OF PROGRESS HELLENIC PAVILION IS OPENED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Fair attendance at 9 P.H. yesterday</cell>
     <cell>111,345</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Attendance to date</cell>
     <cell>2,376,007</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Thirtieth day 1933</cell>
     <cell>115,006</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Attendance first thirty days of 1933</cell>
     <cell>2,404,831</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>In a ceremony as ancient as classic dancing and as modern as radio broadcasting, Hellenic and American civilizations met yesterday at the dedication of the Greek pavilon at Chicago's 1934 World's Fair.</p>
   <p>Preceding a program of Grecian music and ballet centuries old, Charalambos Simopoulos, Greek minister to the United States, broadcast concerning the world's interest in America's economic fight.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0722.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Envoy Broadcasts</p>
   <p>Witnessing the ceremony in the court of states, 15,000 Chicagoans of Greek origin cheered minister Simopoulos' statement:</p>
   <p>"Every visitor looks with amazement and admiration at the progress accomplished by your country, the achievement of your industry and your development of the sciences.</p>
   <p>"We all follow with the utmost interest the fight of the American people and its government against the world crisis and we look to America as the leader to world prosperity."</p>
   <p>Points to old Glories</p>
   <p>Pointing to the efforts of various nations to unearth the glories of ancient Greece, he added:</p>
   <p>"Greece welcomes this international collaboration, inspired by the idea that the treasures of the classical period constitute a precious heritage for all humanity."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0723.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>John D. Dritsas, acting Consul General of Greece, praised the accuracy with which the beauties of Greece had been reproduced for the fair exhibit. Sounding the welcome and appreciation of the exposition was President Rufus C. Dawes.</p>
   <p>To be welcomed with booming guns and military honors this morning will be Wilehelm Morgenstierne, Norwegian minister to the United States, who arrived in Chicago last night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
