<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-10-01">Oct. 1, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">What Union Means</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1152</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1152.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-10-01">Oct. 1, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT UNION MEANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Someone once said "Make as many enemies as you wish; they are less dangerous than disputes among friends."</p>
   <p>This old saying could easily have been written about the present day Greeks in America and especially about the leader of these Greeks - the Greek press. Hellenism of America has always followed the dictates of the press. But now something is happening. The press is just a little too eager to point out the faults and mistakes of our countrymen and they are quick to resent it.</p>
   <p>This is causing much trouble for every reader believes what he chooses to believe and consequently there is jealously and suspicion everywhere.</p>
   <p>The Greeks of America do not know what union means. They do not yet realize the value of cooperation; they do not know that "In Union there is Strength."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1153.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Years ago the press was only used for local incidents and trifles which made up current gossip. Nowadays, when everyone expresses his own ideas, the papers are full of editorials and articles from various sources, full of the problems that confront each one of us. Our editors, in their attempt to outdo each other, are ruining our chances of uniting and making a name for ourselves in America. We must become united! Let us overlook these little criticisms and stick together. If Hellenism in America is to be preserved, we must unite!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
