<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1937-01-15">Jan. 15, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Actors and the Stage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0409</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0409.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1937-01-15">Jan. 15, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">ACTORS AND THE STAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1- Next to the pulpit, the press, and the public platform comes the stage as a medium for the moral education of society.</p>
   <p>However, there are indications in recent years that those engaged in the actor's profession have gone astray, and the authorities have intervened, exercising strict censorship on those plays which affect the integrity and the morals of society.</p>
   <p>This evil has been noticed mostly in localities under control of local authorities. Sometimes it escapes the attention of the latter, either because of lack of complaints or because of lack of alertness and enforcement of the law.</p>
   <p>For these reasons foreign actors and sometimes charlatans, exploiting the misunderstood freedom of this country and its hospitality and pretending ignorance of the law, lapse into indecencies on the stage in defiance of law and morality.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0410.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>So those who attend the theater for edification come away disgusted with the bad taste of the performance.</p>
   <p>Such purveyors of filth have come in times past from Greece to America, where they have made their fortunes, returning to Athens with American dollars and there insulting the Greeks of America for their hospitality and their patronage.</p>
   <p>And so the Star urges the Greeks of America and especially those with families not to patronize performances of plays of suspicious origin and not to attend stage productions which are detrimental to the morals of Greek communities.</p>
   <p>The theater is the supplement of the public platform and the press, for it teaches virtue and portrays human life in all its good and evil aspects, with its conflicts and its hardships, and so the stage has its own mission.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0411.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The stage has no mission whatever if it is not founded in morality and does not portray reality to the eyes of its audience.</p>
   <p>Many actors come to America under pretence of presenting good plays, but what is uppermost in their minds is to make money, and they are not concerned about society. The actor must be primarily a polite, dignified gentleman, a man who respects society, so that men and women who go to the theater with their children may be sure of seeing and hearing something good and instructive, not ballyhoo and profane language!</p>
   <p>The more brilliant the stage appears, the brighter the electric lights shine upon it, the more insidious is the reaction in the hearts of spectators when immorality and disrespect play their role to the detriment of the audience and of society at large. Plays differ according to social conditions in the countries where they originate, but all the actors in the world are one in regard to morality and respect for society. The theater without morality is Hades, and its performers are demons!</p>
   <p>Away with immoral plays and bad companies! Bad companies and immoral plays are like coals in which the fire is extinguished. They do not burn, but they blacken when they are touched. Keep away!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
