<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-06-05">June 5, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A Merciless Beating</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-06-05">June 5, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A MERCILESS BEATING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 1. Mr. P. Simades, publisher of Arcadia, was mercilessly beaten yesterday in the Byzantion Coffee House by Dr. George Karaflos. Dr. Karaflos asserted that Mr. Simades had insulted him.</p>
   <p>Journalism's Parasites.</p>
   <p>We have remarked on another occasion that just as in other occupations which are invaded by parasites, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> in the profession of journalism various parasites intrude - persons, in other words, who do not belong in the profession and who by publishing libelous and offensive articles, attack the honor of individuals and even of families.</p>
   <p>Against such parasites public opinion often bursts out, and a merciless beating is the result. In spite of the fact that thrashing originated in Paradise and that there are occasions when it has a beneficial effect, it is nevertheless advisable that physical force be avoided and that legal means be used. The law provides heavy penalties for persons who write libelous articles.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1060.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is unfortunate that a paper should be published here by an illiterate wretch behind whom the real offender may hide, using this wretch as a tool to satisfy his spite and mania for abuse.</p>
   <p>These anonymous writers are those who deserve to be spat upon and even to be beaten, for they have not the courage to come out in the open. Instead, they let the publisher be maltreated, who persists in representing himself as a journalist even though he gets thrashed.</p>
   <p>Let us hope, however, that things will improve and that the lesson gained from this experience will be of benefit to those who have not learned not to intrude where they do not belong.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
