<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1919-09-20">Sept. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Greek Day at All-American Exposition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0919</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0919.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1919-09-20">Sept. 20, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK DAY AT ALL-AMERICAN EXPOSITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Despite the lack of patriotic interest on the part of those who were financially able to accomplish much, the fine efforts of Mr. George Kambas, a violin teacher, and Mr. S. Achillidou, made Greek Day a tremendous success from an artistic point of view.</p>
   <p>The program began at 3 P. M. Mr. C. Palaeologos served as master of ceremonies. He introduced Mr. Kambas, who played "The Star-Spangled Banner". Little Danny Varzos played a beautiful composition on the piano. He and his brother Eduard, who plays the violin, performed a fine duet. The two children were loudly applauded by the large and attentive audience.</p>
   <p>The well-known N. Salopoulos then gave a speech in the English language that was very well received. He in turn introduced Mrs. Kambas who was attired in the ancient Greek dress. Her fine stature and attractive face gave her the appearance of one of the marble caryatids carved by an old master. She sang selections from "Il Trovatore", and her lovely voice was enthusiastically applauded.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0920.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then to the tune of martial music the pupils of Socrates School made their appearance, wearing the national costume and ready to dance the "Dance of Zallogou"....The first one to lead the dance was little Helen Tsirimbi. The pupils performed the dance with which we are so familiar, since it has been performed by the children at various places. The applause was loud, and became even louder when Mrs. Kambas reappeared upon the stage to sing "Gero-Dimos" and "Favorita".....</p>
   <p>Mr. Kambas is to be congratulated upon his fine program, for the performance should be judged by the ringing applause it received. Congratulations also to Mr. N. Salopoulos, Mr. C. Palaeologos, Mr. C. Salopoulos, Paul Demos, George Kambas, Mrs. [Constantine] Hadzidimitriou, Mrs. C. Kantzou, and Mrs. G. Vatsinea. Heartiest thanks to Mrs. Kambas, and to all the boys and girls of the Socrates School.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
