<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1929-10-12">Oct. 12, 1929</date>, p. 4
<title level="a">Greek Musical Club in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0546</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0546.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1929-10-12">Oct. 12, 1929</date>, p. 4
<title level="a">GREEK MUSICAL CLUB IN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Music is inseparable from the Greek mind and soul. Music elevates the mind and soul to their proper heights. Music is divine, the whole of nature expresses rhythm and harmony. No Greek gathering or festivity past or present could take place without music.</p>
   <p>It is said in Homer's Odyssey that Ulysses, with his companions passing through the straights of Messina, commanded them to close their ears with wax in order that they should become voluntary slaves of the Syrens, who with their beautiful songs and sweet melodious voices allured those who happened to pass through the straights.</p>
   <p>Later, when Christian religion spread, Byzantine music was the center of attraction. The Czar of Russia, (Russia being a Christian country) wanting to give his people the best religious music, sent delegations to all Christian countries to find fitting and melodious music for the 160 millions of Russians. The result was Byzantine music was offically adopted.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0547.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Unfortunately here in Chicago, inspite of the Greek love for music, our sweet and melodious religious music is neglected and is bound to lose its charm and effectiveness. Thousands of dollars are spent for the acquisition and upkeep of bishops and archbishops. We raise money for Greek cemeteries, orphanages, hospitals and educational institutions in order to perpetuate our language and religion, but for our ecclesiastical music we don't want to spend anything worthwhile.</p>
   <p>For that reason, we, the undersigned founded the Chicago Greek Musical Club, and we are requesting those who wish better music in our churches, to become members of the club. Geo. Depastas, Constantine Paleologos, T. Valos, A. Marantes, K. Haralambidis, I. Gikas, G. Karaflos, Rev. Tsourounakis, D. Paulakis, Geo. Grant, Geo. Kokinos, D. Dokos, G. Kantaras, P. Vasilogeorge, A. Bouras, K. Serriades, K. Agelopoulos, P. Kilavos, M. Laskaris and Leo. Kilavos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
