<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
"<title level="a">Critical Review</title>," <title>New Era</title>, Chicago, Ill.,
<date when="1921-02-01">Feb. 1, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">[Young Musician's Concert Slighted]</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0377</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0377.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>"Critical Review," New Era, Chicago, Ill.</title>,
<date when="1921-02-01">Feb. 1, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">[YOUNG MUSICIAN'S CONCERT SLIGHTED]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This article is written for the professional and educated Greeks of Chicago.</p>
   <p>A young Greek musician, a violinist, only seventeen years old - his name is Leon. Methinetes, but that does not matter - gave his first nusical concert. Very few Greek people were seen there. The incident isn't important except that the Greeks found it unnecessary to attend a brilliant violinist's first concert. They are following their usual custom and tradition. We are not idolaters of this young man's talent because we know nothing of the beauty of music.</p>
   <p>We can excuse the poor and ignorant Greeks for not taking advantage of the opportunity of hearing something wonderful, because they can't afford it or because they know no better. This excuse, of course, cannot apply to the well-to-do, the educated, the professional Greeks.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0378.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Any one can tell us that the Greeks are the only race in the world that has no music appreciation whatever. Even the Indians appreciate music better than we do. Our Greek songs are mostly of Italian origin.</p>
   <p>The Greek professionals and the educated people should consider it an honor as well as a duty to attend a seventeen year old Greek maestro's first concert. Some day he may bring glory to the Greek name. Then we all will take notice of him, won't we?</p>
   <p>The Greeks should take a little kindly advice. If you have two loaves of bread, sell one and buy a flower, for the soul wants to eat as well as the body.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
