<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1936-06-18">June 18, 1936</date><title level="a">Beyond Tomorrow</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Graeco-Americanus</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0980</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0980.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1936-06-18">June 18, 1936</date><title level="a">BEYOND TOMORROW</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Graeco-Americanus</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- Readers of this column, as well as those that read the contents of this paper written in the Greek language, whether they look through its pages to see what is happening in the Greek colony of Chicago, or whether they peruse the paper's editorials, its "dactylografimata", Mr. Halepas' or Pipida's column, or the numerous other contributors to the Greek Press, little realize that this publication has rolled up seven years of its history.</p>
   <p>Its advent in the field of Greek journalism in America in June 1929 was hardly expected by any one to be of any more significance than just another Greek newspaper. Its history, however, tells of another story.</p>
   <p>The Greek Press, in this short span of time, has made itself an inseparable part of the lives of the Greeks in America in general and those of Chicago in particular.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0981.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Its inauguration of modern journalistic methods has endeared it to the hearts and souls of so many thousands of Greeks of Greek descent, that it can now proudly boast as having become an institution--indispensable to the Greek community of Chicago and the rest of the Greek colonies of America.</p>
   <p>Several years of hard mental and bodily labor have fully justified the aims and ambitions of the founders of the Greek Press, now that its efforts have been crowned with success and its future is brighter than ever.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
