<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-11-06">Nov. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Value of Advertising</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0118</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0118.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-11-06">Nov. 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE VALUE OF ADVERTISING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We desire to make public certain information before we proceed to enter into a discussion about advertising.</p>
   <p>Greece has a natural monopoly of Corinthian raisins which are well-known in all Europe to be the best obtainable. Yet here in America they are practically unknown, and are considered to be greatly inferior to the California product. This in the face of undisputed reports of experts that the Corinthian raisins are unexcelled by any.</p>
   <p>The blame for this condition can be put upon the lack of advertisement of the product. A small part of the condition, it is true, has been caused by the unattractive packaging of these raisins. They did not satisfy the mental picture of what packaged raisins should look like. Nevertheless, even if they <pb facs="5422062_3_0119.jpg" n="2"/>had been packaged in a more appealing manner, they would still not sell in large quantities. Why? Because the California raisins are nationally advertised to be the best and most wholesome raisins on the market. The public is greatly influenced by what it reads, and has been taught to prefer advertised products. This enables the California producers to sell very inferior grades of raisins as being the very best; and they also sell at such low prices that they force out all other competitors. They also influence the tariff, and fight to make them higher, in order to discourage all foreign imports.</p>
   <p>In order to improve these conditions, a Union of Raisin Producers has been organized in Atlanta, Georgia. We believe that this organization will soon send an application to the Greek Commercial Club of Chicago, in order that both clubs may work together to advertise and aid Greek business and commerce.</p>
   <p>Raisins are only one of many Greek products that are as yet unknown in America. For instance, the cognac of Greece is famous throughout Europe and Asia, and if advertised would find even a greater market here in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0120.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This is true of all other Greek liqueurs and wines, also.</p>
   <p>The olive oil of Greece is the best and purest in the world--especially that from Mani, Kranidou, and Kalamon. A few unscrupulous salesmen sold the American buyers inferior oil, hoping that it would not be detected--and so they lost American confidence. That is why the Italian olive oil is preferred by the American people.</p>
   <p>The most important commodity of Greece is, of course, tobacco. Greece today controls and owns the tobacco fields of Kavala and of eastern Macedonia where the most aromatic tobaccos of the world are raised. Yet the American people still have it presented to them as Turkish tobacco under such names as Murad, Fatima and Hasan cigarettes.</p>
   <p>One good advertisement would expose this unfair and misleading propaganda. Systematic advertising would halt this use of Turkish names, and would also give the Greeks a chance to become wealthy. We deserve this opportunity <pb facs="5422062_3_0121.jpg" n="4"/>because the tobacco is a Greek product and Greeks should, by right, profit from it.</p>
   <p>The supremacy of the Greeks in the confectionery, candy, restaurant, and other enterprises of a similar nature would be indisputable if Greek men would unite and advertise. In unity there is strength; and in advertising there is fame, power, and success.</p>
   <p>We have expressed our ideas about the importance of proper advertising,and the reason for the lack of spectacular success of Greek products in America. Now we invite you to send us your opinions. We appeal especially to those interested in the commerce and progress of the Greeks of America in the business world.</p>
   <p>Please make your replies concise and to the point. All those considered to be of value will be published in future issues of Saloniki.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
