<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1916-02-05">Feb. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">100,000 Soldiers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) by Christ Damascus</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1107</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1107.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1916-02-05">Feb. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">100,000 SOLDIERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) by Christ Damascus</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The political editorials continually being presented to the readers of these columns, have been written with a definite purpose. Today, we feel that it is time to state this purpose. In doing so, we shall endeavor to answer the inquiries of our readers by stating the beliefs and aims of this newspaper.</p>
   <p>The editorials of any newspaper are written with a definite purpose in mind. They are concerned with some policy or some matter that the paper wants to put before the reading public. Naturally a series of editorials on a pertinent subject will influence the opinions of many individuals.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1108.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Newspapers that print articles on ephemeral subjects, and have different opinions for each day of the week, are like a ship in mid-ocean without a rudder. Not only is it buffeted about by every wave, but it is also a danger to any passenger who happens to be on board.....</p>
   <p>The newspaper is a powerful instrument in the world of today. A yellow or unethical publication can cause more trouble than a raging fire. And so we say for all to hear, that the political editorials printed in these columns have had only one aim--a sacred and patriotic aim. This aim was: to send 100,000 Greek-American soldiers to fight on the tragic battlefields of Macedonia.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately we failed. There were too many newspapers publishing editorials that were intended to make the Greeks turn deaf ears to the pleas of their motherland. These newspapers succeeded because there were a large number of them, and because they wrote clever, hypocritical articles that completely misled their readers.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1109.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The editorials of certain Greek papers were so deceptive, so unpatriotic that they even included fanatical accusations against the King, Venizelos, and the Cabinet.</p>
   <p>They created so much chaos in the minds of the Greeks of America that whole communities were divided, and homes were broken up. The worst part of it was that the potential army of Greeks--100,000 soldiers--were discouraged and became indifferent to the plight of Greece.</p>
   <p>If our fight had been successful, this army would now be on the fields of Macedonia, defending their country's honor; and at the same time, living up to their glorious tradition.</p>
   <p>Protected by a distance of a thousand miles of water, they[these newspapers] wrote degrading accusations against the Greek government. They succeeded in severing all the spiritual and patriotic ties between Greece and America. They deafened the ears of 100,000 Greeks in America to their country's call to arms.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1110.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Of course, it would be easy for us to cast aspersions on the government of our motherland. We too could imply things about Venizelos and could criticize the King. We could, if we desired, create antagonisms in order to have our subscribers spend money on stamps, in order to write us their opinions on the subject.</p>
   <p>However, as true journalists, who know our duty to our motherland, we have refrained from using such tactics. We do not care to have such a stigma placed upon the name of our paper. We had a definite goal, and we did our best to reach it.....</p>
   <p>We estimate that at least 100,000 Greeks would have left America months ago, and would have taken up arms in defense of their country. At the beginning of our campaign, over fifty thousand Greeks, from one end of America to the other, began to make preparations to cross the ocean.</p>
   <p>Immediately, the poisonous articles written by hypocritical, unethical <pb facs="5422062_3_1111.jpg" n="5"/>writers began to pour their venom into the minds of the people, and as a result, these volunteers changed their minds and turned deaf ears to their country's call.</p>
   <p>A second appeal was made by the King, and lucrative offers were made to all who would enlist in the Greek Army. Not one of the 100,000 responded!</p>
   <p>Where can the blame be placed? Can it be placed upon a lack of patriotism, or upon the lack of courage of Greek men? Or is heedlessness to blame?</p>
   <p>The whole world is well aware of the profound patriotism of the Greeks. It is known that a Greek will fight like a superman for his country. So the lack of response cannot be blamed upon a lack of patriotism. It must have been due to misinformation; and this misinformation was undeniably instigated and nurtured by the various yellow, so-called Greek papers.....They succeeded in smothering the[fire of]Greek patriotism.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1112.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We try to believe that these editors were not even aware of the evil they had wrought upon the Greeks of America. The results are evident. They hindered and discouraged thousands of Greeks from going to the aid of their motherland.</p>
   <p>We tried our best to bolster up the cause. We tried to bridge the chaos of division caused by the exophrenic[frenzied]articles appearing in the other newspapers. We tried to steady the Greeks and teach them to have faith in their government, hoping to make them return to their Greek regiments.</p>
   <p>This alone was our purpose, and we appeal to the other papers to forget their differences, and to unite to help our country.</p>
   <p>Let us start a Preparedness campaign in behalf of Greece. Today, our country is in terrible danger and all the Greek papers must unite their forces to send aid.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1113.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Behold, this is a noble goal for all the Greek papers--a goal of unity and patriotism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
