<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-05-17">May 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Greeks Must Create Propaganda for the Greek Exhibit at the Fai</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0724</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0724.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1934-05-17">May 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">GREEKS MUST CREATE PROPAGANDA FOR THE GREEK EXHIBIT AT THE FAI</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The main topic of interest and conversation to the Greeks of Chicago, and, in a lesser degree, to all the Greeks of America, is the Greek participation in the Chicago World's Fair. One of our readers wrote to us as follows: "Now, that there is to be a Greek Exhibit at the Fair I am going to go to see it, despite the fact that I live in Patterson, N. J. My son is coming along so that he may see a few of the beauties and marvels of Greek art and culture." Many letters of this nature have convinced us that all the Greeks are intensely interested in their country's exhibit. They will, therefore, directly and indirectly, do everything in their power to make it a finer and more enviable one.</p>
   <p>News from Greece speaks of the enthusiasm and co-operation on the part of government officials and businessmen. They realize that a priceless opportunity has been given them to exhibit their products and prowess to the peoples <pb facs="5422062_3_0725.jpg" n="2"/>of the world. All this has been made possible because of the courage and generosity of a Chicago Greek--Mr. John Mantas. He is the one who should receive the thanks and plaudits of the Greek exporters and producers. He has given them an undreamed-of chance to advertise their Greek products.</p>
   <p>Officially, Greece and all other interested groups have done all that has been expected of them. It remains for the Greek importers and merchants of America to do their duty by an advertising propaganda in the interest of Greek products. Such action will be of great benefit to themselves as well as Greece. They understand the value and importance of advertising even more than the merchants of Greece. The great Greek business firms in America are fully aware of the worth of advertising, and need no arguments in its favor.</p>
   <p>Every dollar spent by producers for exhibit purposes at the Fair will be multiplied many times over in profits.</p>
   <p>Now, that Greece has entered the Fair, and that the large Greek firms are doing <pb facs="5422062_3_0726.jpg" n="3"/>their utmost to give the Greek Exhibit the characteristics of a "pangyric", it still remains for the average Greek-American to take his share of responsibility. The Greeks of Chicago, especially, are duty-bound to assume a large part of it. From now until October, one thing should be uppermost in our minds--the creation of propaganda for the Greek Exhibit. It is imperative that we carry on a systematic campaign, in order that the American people may know the value and names of Greek imports, and be able to sample, look at, and buy them at the Chicago Fair...We have the interest of the Greek people, already. What we are now interested in, is the American buying public.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
