<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-10-09">Oct. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">[Unification of Greek Salesmen and Businessmen]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0129</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0129.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-10-09">Oct. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">[UNIFICATION OF GREEK SALESMEN AND BUSINESSMEN]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The previous article which appeared in the last issue of the Saloniki, and concerned the Greek representatives of large American concerns, aroused a great deal of discussion. We are proud to say that the comments were favorable to the ideas presented in the article. The unification of these salesmen into some form of commercial organization or club was the most popular idea of all. In fact, the Greek salesman have already taken steps to write a constitution for such an organization.</p>
   <p>Aside, from the Greek salesmen, whom we have designated with the title of "Advance Guards of Greek Business in America", all the other Greek businessmen are giving serious consideration to the suggestion made by the Saloniki. They, too, are beginning to believe that only through the organization of such a society can Greek business become unified and as a result--powerful.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0130.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Such an organization would serve as an instrument of education and progress. The representatives of American concerns are the most experienced ones and therefore the best equipped to educate the Greeks in the accepted codes of American business. They can teach better business methods, and can give much valuable advice because of their long and varied experiences in the American business world.</p>
   <p>The Greek bank officials likewise, can, instruct the businessman in the methods of extending credit and in the checking of his accounts; and they can also advise him where to invest his money to the best advantage. This in itself will be a valuable service, for sadly enough, too few of our business men know how to make use of the banking services offered to them.</p>
   <p>In the same way the Greek people can be benefited by an organization composed of Greek salesmen from large stores, such as Marshall Field and Company, and from a similar unification of representatives of manufacturing concerns. This would consist of various divisions, and would help the thousands of <pb facs="5422062_3_0131.jpg" n="3"/>Greeks who make such purchases as furniture and store fixtures. This group of buyers, in particular, is in need of advice. They continually complain of the high prices they are forced to pay and of the high rates of interest they are charged; and they know, through bitter experience, the value of being able to get competent advice, that is so necessary when a business is being opened for the first time.</p>
   <p>Of course, the experiences of the veteran businessmen are of value to those who are making a start in the commercial world for the first time; but the average human being has a way of being unable to learn from the experiences of others, who have already gone through the same kinds of troubles as he is now experiencing. An individual is more apt to listen to the advice of some one he knows in an entirely different line of business. The Greek salesman is the most qualified to give the needed advice.</p>
   <p>It is imperative that an organization of Greek salesmen should be formed immediately; because such an organization is sorely needed by every Greek <pb facs="5422062_3_0132.jpg" n="4"/>businessman in Chicago. The organization will receive the utmost co-operation from all Greek businessmen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
