<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1914-12-05">Dec. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Business Unification</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0186</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0186.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-12-05">Dec. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">BUSINESS UNIFICATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are impatiently waiting to see the formation of the much needed commercial union of Greek business. This union--important from any point of view--will imbue our already established enterprises with new and vigorous life. It will be conducive to rapid and successful progress.</p>
   <p>In the commercial world, it is undeniable that the system of co-operation, as followed by corporations and partnerships, has been of tremendous value. However, these organizations have so far been purely local in character. Despite their great numbers we have not felt any nation-wide benefit as a racial group. The local partnerships and commercial clubs do not fill the needs of the Greek people all over this country.</p>
   <p>Many commercial organizations that exist today, are not capable of serving any social need because they are improperly organized. They are not able to give <pb facs="5422062_3_0187.jpg" n="2"/>advice to the members because they know nothing about the business conditions outside of their own small community. This makes it evident that the time has come to change the present methods, and to adopt more comprehensive and efficient ones.</p>
   <p>We must form business clubs which are capable of advising and educating the Greek businessmen. The economic horizon will be enlarged if the Greek men realize the importance of such a move and will see that it is done.</p>
   <p>Such a step must be taken as it is definitely a forward one.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
