<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1929-04-18">April 18, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Daily Items - Our Organizations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1758</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1758.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1929-04-18">April 18, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">DAILY ITEMS - OUR ORGANIZATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.- The Greeks of America have felt, from the very early years of their immigration to this country, the need of organizing for different purposes.</p>
   <p>These organizations were divided into three classes:</p>
   <p>The Communals, having as their purpose the founding and managing of the churches and schools.</p>
   <p>The National or Patriotic for the support of different national aims.</p>
   <p>The Locals for objectives in the different towns or villages from which their members come.</p>
   <p>There were also many occupational organizations established, of which very few succeeded.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1759.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In our community many organizations are functioning toward the above purposes. Of these three groups the Locals outnumber the others and are the most successful.</p>
   <p>The reason why the Local organizations are most progressive and successful is that all their members, being from the same native town, they have more nearly the same point of view in regard to the amelioration of the social and economic conditions of the poor in their native village.</p>
   <p>With the aid of these Local organizations many social activities have been performed in the different towns and villages of Greece and large sums of money have flowed into Greece.</p>
   <p>Thus these organizations have offered and continue offering an inestimable service to Greece, for the various social activities in each and every town or village. Most important of all, they have kept undiminished the patriotic feeling and maintained closely the strong of affection bonds between the Greeks of America and the Greeks of Greece.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
