<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-10-23">Oct. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Commercial Club</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Triumph for the Greek Salesmen of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0124</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0124.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-10-23">Oct. 23, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">COMMERCIAL CLUB</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Triumph for the Greek Salesmen of Chicago</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The foundation has been laid for the organization of the Commercial Club of Greek salesmen of Chicago. The work is progressing more favorably than the Saloniki dared to hope.</p>
   <p>The organizing committee is composed of George Bambakaris, Basilopoulos, N. Sarantakis, P. Damascis, C. Spirakis, D. Sarantakis, C. Giannia, A. Apostolou, John Agriostathis, and Th. Theodoropoulos; and these gentlemen laid out the purposes of the club very efficiently, as follows:</p>
   <p>1. To be a brotherhood of Greek salesmen.</p>
   <p>2. To support and aid Greek representatives in their dealings with their concerns.</p>
   <p>3. To teach and enlighten the Greek businessmen concerning their dealings <pb facs="5422062_3_0125.jpg" n="2"/>with American business firms.</p>
   <p>4. To develop good salesmen, and then to see that each American firm that is patronized by Greek stores has at least one Greek representative.</p>
   <p>5. To promote a closer and friendlier spirit between the Greek and American businessmen.</p>
   <p>6. To increase the strength and influence of the Greek salesmen, by teaching the Greek businessmen to demand Greek salesmen and to patronize firms that do have them.</p>
   <p>These purposes and aims pleased the assembled salesmen. These purposes were commented on and critisized until all those present were finally satisfied.</p>
   <p>Mr. N. Salopoulos honored the meeting by making a short speech, and he was followed by Mr. Wilson, advertising manager of the Saloniki. Mr. C. Damascus, <pb facs="5422062_3_0126.jpg" n="3"/>Mr. Bambakaris, and the Reverend Hadzidimitriou also spoke.</p>
   <p>Among the salesmen present were G. Arvanitis, J. Agriostathis, C. Agrios, C. Giannias.....</p>
   <p>Saloniki is proud that it has the right to take the credit for the idea of forming such a necessary organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
