<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title level="a">"Ahepans of Chicago to Hold Ancient Greek House Party,"</title><title>Ahepa Herald</title>, (Official Organ of District No. 21, 77 W. Washington Street, Chicago, Illinois),
<date when="1934-05-01">May 1, 1934</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0730</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0730.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title level="a">"Ahepans of Chicago To Hold Ancient Greek House Party,"</title><title>Ahepa Herald</title>, (Official Organ of District No. 21, 77 W. Washington Street, Chicago, Illinois),
<date when="1934-05-01">May 1, 1934</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A midweek house party for the Olympian gods, demigods, Nymphs, Muses and Nereids is being planned by the Ahepans of Chicago, a Greek organization for Wednesday night, May 2nd, at the Aragon ballroom.</p>
   <p>In the name of charity the Olympian deities have accepted the invitation sent out by Demetrios Parry, governor of the Ahepa in Chicago. The occasion is just an ancient Greek "house party" known to antiquity as "Anthesteria" (the sacrifice of flowers).</p>
   <p>Prominent in this parade of deified personages of the "Golden Age " of Greece will be Aphrodite, Goddess of Love; the muse Terpsichore, Goddess of the Dance, and Goddess Demeter. They will be impersonated by three of the most beautiful Greek girls living in Chicago, who will be chosen by the committee on arrangements, of which Arthur Peponis is the chairman.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0731.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The festival of Anthesteria is the most beautiful of ancient Greek rituals," said Mr. Parry. "Essentially a grand sacrifice of flowers to Mother Earth and the gods of Mount Olympus, the celebration of Anthesteria to the classic Hellene was just as fascinating as the Eleusinian mysteries. It marks definitely the beginning of mild weather." More than 5,000 persons are expected to attend the festivities. Presidents of the nine lodges of Ahepa in Chicago have been named on the committee of arrangements.</p>
   <p>Gov. Horner, Mayor Kelly and other state and city officials have been invited. The head of the Greek church in the Middle West, the Rt. Rev. Callistos, has accepted, and John Dritsas, acting consul of Greece in Chicago will attend.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
