<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-03-09">Mar. 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">For the Ladies</title><title level="a" type="sub">The "Happy Family"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1361</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1361.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-03-09">Mar. 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE LADIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">The "Happy Family"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many changes have occurred since the appearance of the first Greek immigrant in Chicago. Fortunes have been won at the cost of hard and ceaseless labor, and then lost within a comparatively short time. Practically everything in our life has reached a climax and an anti-climax, as a result of present-day conditions. Nearly all has been lost.</p>
   <p>The courage of the young is the only thing that has not been vanquished; for youth gives one fearlessness and staying power. We hope that our boys and girls will hold tenaciously to this courage throughout their lives. They have just begun to face life and its problems--especially trying in this period of depression.</p>
   <p>Courage and an active brain can bring happiness and success to most people. Our community is filled with people who, lacking these two qualities, are <pb facs="5422062_3_1362.jpg" n="2"/>unhappy and bewildered. There is only one group of people among us who are happy and content--like a "happy family."</p>
   <p>As a result of the efforts of the Professional Club, we have had in Chicago during the last few years a large group of people who are like a happy family because they are using their minds and their material means to achieve spiritual rest and growth. The members of this fine group come together in various kinds of meetings. Lectures are arranged, and topics of social importance are discussed. Socials and parties are an important part of the program of this group because they tend to create better mutual understanding and appreciation. Its members talk, laugh, exchange ideas on controversial subjects, and, by forgetting for a little while the troubles and cares of their daily lives, receive renewed impetus and a fresh outlook upon life. Worries tend to lower man's morale, unless he finds solace and encouragement from some source. If people are financially embarrassed, or have personal problems on their minds, these gatherings provide them with a temporary haven where they can find mental relaxation.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
