<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-06-13">June 13, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">A Creditable Display to Students of the Progress of Greek-Americans</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1387</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1387.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-06-13">June 13, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">A CREDITABLE DISPLAY TO STUDENTS OF THE PROGRESS OF GREEK-AMERICANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1--Last Sunday the Church of St. Constantine was host to a group of American professors and students of sociology who desired to study the manners, customs, and characteristics of the Greeks in America. The leader of this group was Professor Frank Orman Beck of Northwestern University.</p>
   <p>Committees composed of women of three Greek societies, St. Helene's, Nea Genea (New Generation), and Cretan, took charge of the reception and the preparation of delicious Greek food and pastries and also appointed the day for the exhibit.</p>
   <p>In spite of the fact that all preparations were made in an impromptu fashion, the large reception-hall of St. Constantine's Church was converted <pb facs="5422062_3_1388.jpg" n="2"/>on one side into a display-room in which artistic samples were exhibited of elaborate embroidery work done by skillful Greek women and on the other side into a luxurious dining-room in which were seated more than a hundred American and Greek guests. These guests were highly pleased with the flavor of the Greek food and pastries prepared by Mmes. P. Djovani, M. Petrakis, Stergiou, Konstandoudaki, Pappas, and Dzathas and Miss Mitou. The following young ladies served: Misses Stamos, Petrakis, Floutha, Matzarake, Andritopoulos, Sifiake, Vrouna, Mavromichalaki, and Constanntinopoulos.</p>
   <p>Mr. Andrew Vlachos, assistant State's attorney, who had been appointed master of ceremonies, described for the American guests, with that facility of speech which is a natural gift of his, the progress of modern Greece, which recently entered its hundredth year as an independent nation, and also the progress of the Greeks in America.</p>
   <p>Miss C. Melia spoke of the Greek-American girl--her progress in higher education and other activities.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1389.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Reverend H. Demetri and the Reverend M. Petrakis also gave talks on the Greek Orthodox Church.</p>
   <p>The entertainment portion of the program was very elaborate and is worthy of mention. More than fifty Grecian girls, dressed in the classical costumes of ancient Greece, who had been well trained by Mr. N. Tsoukalas, an eminent authority on Greek classical dancing, presented a dance taken from the Antigone of the tragic poet, Sophocles.</p>
   <p>A few beautiful Greek arias were sung by Miss Stamos and Mr. Demopoulos.</p>
   <p>Professor Beck spoke a few words, expressing his admiration for the progress of the Greeks in America, who in his opinion are far ahead of other nationalities. He also expressed on behalf of his group their hearty thanks and appreciation for the wonderful reception and for the exhibit of handicraft.</p>
   <p>Heading the list of those who were responsible for the success of this reception was Mrs. Stella Petraki, assisted by Mmes. H. Stathoudaki, H. Anagnostopoulos, <pb facs="5422062_3_1390.jpg" n="4"/>E. Papadouraki, M. Demopoulos, and B. Mavromichalaki. Miss Mitou was in charge of the group who displayed Greek handicraft.</p>
   <p>These women, who so heartily devoted themselves to the task of preparing this exhibit to depict the progress of Hellenism in America for the group of American professors and students of sociology, are worthy of thanks and praise, and their efforts were crowned with success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
