<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1905-09-29">Sept. 29, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">The Chicago Marathon Race-Lambrakis Wins.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1607</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1607.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1905-09-29">Sept. 29, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHICAGO MARATHON RACE-LAMBRAKIS WINS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2-Last Saturday the marathon race of Chicago took place under the auspices of the Illinois Athletic club. Twenty runners participated in the race; eighteen Americans, members of various clubs, one Frenchman, and Lambrakis, the Greek, representing the Pan-Hellenic club of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Lambrakis, aided by his American friends, came in first and won the race, thus honoring the city of Chicago, his friends, the club which he represented, and himself. The Pan-Hellenic club of Chicago and the Greek community are proud of Lambrakis's victory.</p>
   <p>The comments of the city press were numerous and complimentary. Every daily graphically described the Greek's victory and his tremendous endurance.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1608.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A group of Lambrakis's American friends, who had followed him all the way along the twenty-five mile route, being convinced in advance of the outcome, filled the air with deafening cries of "Hurrah for Greece! Hurrah for Greece!" Lambrakis, after making the circuit of the grand stand three times to comply with the rules of the executive committee, cut the ribbon as victor and unaided and in good physical condition went to his room, changed his clothes, presented himself to photographers, and then departed with his American friends, who carried him away on their shoulders.</p>
   <p>Several hours later a sumptuous dinner was served at William Trebilecok's residence in honor of the Greek's victory.</p>
   <p>Among numerous Americans who were interested in Lambrakis's achievement the following persons were kind enough to give us their names: William Trebilecok, John Kenny, H. Harrison, O. Allstrom, O. E. Vogelsang, E. C. Reece, Carl Heim, Joe Fitch, E. Drock, and Will and John Dunbar.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1609.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The victorious Greek appeared next day before the committee and received the gold and diamond award in a brilliant ceremony.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
