<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-03-05">March 5, 1931</date><title level="a">Greek Olympic Club Boys Go in for Heavy Harvest of Victories</title><title level="a" type="sub">Olympic Games Their Goal by Nick John Matsoukas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1555</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1555.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-03-05">March 5, 1931</date><title level="a">GREEK OLYMPIC CLUB BOYS GO IN FOR HEAVY HARVEST OF VICTORIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Olympic Games Their Goal By Nick John Matsoukas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 6.- The rise of the new Greek is not only in business, the humanities and other professions, but also on the horizon of athleticism, pugilism being one of the major forms. Boxers of the Greek-Olympic Athletic Club for the last ten years have been reaping laurels in the pugilistic world.</p>
   <p>Last week, Jimmy Eliopoulos, a crack fighter of the 112 pound weight, knocked out Joe Falk in the second round at the meet held in the gymnasium of the Medinah Athletic Club. Knocking out Falk, Eliopoulos encountered a victory over a man that has to his credit 32 knockouts.</p>
   <p>In the first round it seemed that Eliopoulos would have a tough time putting Falk to sleep. Like a baby lion, Eliopoulos sent Falk down and out with a terrific right cross to the chin.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1556.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Another boy that is a credit to the Club on the West Side, where Greeks are Greeks and the others are aware of it, is Nick Flambouras. He whipped Ernie Parker, who for some time has been reigning supreme ruler over the North Side rings with fighters of the 130 weight. Meeting Flambouras proved to be Parker's Waterloo. It was a game battle that Parker put up. Some heavy punching was offered, involuntarily accepted and sent back C.O.D.</p>
   <p>Nick disregarded the heavy punching that came from Parker. He went after his opponent with hammer and tongs-and there lay Parker. Speed and cleverness of delivery is Nick's outstanding virtue.</p>
   <p>Tom Petros, promising 160 pounder, made his second appearance in the ring by whipping Fred Cooper, a tough negro chap, whose punch has always been feared. From the start as soon as the gong spelled "go", Petros went after his man, never for a second letting down on his heavy artillery attack.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1557.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Groomed for Olympic Games!</p>
   <p>Now let me tell you something, you ring side seaters.</p>
   <p>George Curtis, instructor of bosing at the Greek Athletic Club, is grooming these boxers and few others for the Olympic Games in 1932, and if no accidents occur, they are going to be tough competition for the other boys that are going to meet at the great big gathering of 1932. Now, isn't that reason enough why you should help the Greek Olympic Club? Imagine a champion coming from Chicago! "Ain't" it something?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
