<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1915-05-01">May 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Bankrupt Greek-American Bank Pays Up</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0164</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0164.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-05-01">May 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">BANKRUPT GREEK-AMERICAN BANK PAYS UP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The celebrated Greek-American Bank, the founding of which was greeted with uncontrolled enthusiasm, is now breathing its last. The closing of this bank has become one of the major scandals of our community.</p>
   <p>Although Saloniki had repeatedly warned the depositors and investors of the uncertain status and rumored insolvency of the Greek-American Bank, no one at the time thought that such a "prosperous" bank could fail. About eight hundred hard-working Greek laborers have lost their hard-earned savings overnight. As yet, there is very little hope that the poor depositors will get any of their money back.</p>
   <p>Last week, one hundred depositors of our nationality gathered around Monadnock Block to hear Mr. Eastman, the State bankruptcy official, announce the decision of the court on the case of the Greek-American bank. Mr. Eastman told the crowd that there was no use wasting money for carfare <pb facs="5422062_3_0165.jpg" n="2"/>in order to find out whether the bank will return some part of the total deposits. He informed the Greek depositors that only two cents on the dollar remain from the assets of the much lamented bank.</p>
   <p>So, the case has closed. Any further comment is useless and hopeless. Saloniki fought desperately to protect the interests of the Greek depositors. It was the only Greek newspaper that did its duty. The Greeks of Chicago may well be proud of its gallant efforts to prosecute the bank and to liquidate the remaining assets of the bank. The work is not finished, however. The Federal courts will now tackle the case. For this reason, all the depositors are requested to meet and decide their next course of action, in the hope that they may obtain some justice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
