<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-07-13">July 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">What Is the Duty of the Press?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1067</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1067.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-07-13">July 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS THE DUTY OF THE PRESS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If a child is to develop properly toward a worthy manhood, it must have kind and competent teachers as well as affectionate and understanding parents. It is at home and in school that the child acquires the first elements of schooling and proper breeding, without which he may easily be diverted to a course of criminality and ruin. It is the duty of the good parent to keep himself in physical, moral, and mental health, thus setting a good example for his children, and to send his children to school in order that they may obtain the best possible education.</p>
   <p>It is well known that bad company corrupts the morals of youth, while good company makes for good character. So, just as parents who are interested in <pb facs="5422062_3_1068.jpg" n="2"/>the future of their children must follow the aforementioned suggestions, similarly a good society and community of people, such as our Greek community of Chicago, which has evolved from small beginnings to a position of importance, must see to it that its members receive the enlightenment and guidance which they need. Only thus will the community be able to occupy a place of honor in the society of man. Therefore, a good teacher is needed to educate the general public.</p>
   <p>Who is that good teacher? What is that indispensable element in every modern society? It is an honest and decent press. The press is a storehouse for the ideas of the most intelligent and industrious members of society. The citizens of any community are developed and guided by its opinions and advice. It is the guardian of the rights and interests of all men.</p>
   <p>But the press may also become a destructive force. It can ruin as well as <pb facs="5422062_3_1069.jpg" n="3"/>benefit. It can raise men to the highest offices, but it can also kill reputations and cause powerful men to lose all influence.</p>
   <p>In the formation of political policies its influence is of vital importance. Emperor Joseph of Austria-Hungary, Bismarck, Gladstone, our own statesman Koumountouros, Deligianis, Tricoupis, and many others, all used to arise early and read the newspapers, from which they often derived political ideas highly useful in the development of their countries' policies.</p>
   <p>This, in short, is the significance of the press. Its mission is of the highest order. But, if the press is to maintain its prestige, newspapers must contain serious instructive and constructive material. Articles must be clearly and correctly written. Consequently, the publisher, the editorial staff, the correspondents, and the reporters must all be true journalists. In this way, we can have a good press, and with a good press we can have a good society <pb facs="5422062_3_1070.jpg" n="4"/>and state. Therefore, every society must use great care in selecting its organs of public opinion. It must do away with the cheap yellow press by which the public is misled and corrupted. But as no good is gained without hard work and sacrifice, so a community must expect to make some slight financial sacrifice in support of a worth-while enterprise. Many people spend five or ten dollars for cheap carnal pleasure which may be short-lived. Should they not be willing to spend three to five dollars annually for intellectual pleasure? There is so much profit in reading a good newspaper. Is there any greater satisfaction than the one derived from meditating upon national, political or social problems?</p>
   <p>Think about this and judge for yourselves. The problem of the press is a social problem which demands a solution from you, the reading public. If you want an intellectually alert and constructive social organ, you must be prepared to sacrifice a few dollars and subscribe to the best newspapers. Without a sincere <pb facs="5422062_3_1071.jpg" n="5"/>and reliable press you will all become intellectually blind and will be led to a dangerous precipice. Everything depends upon you. Think and act accordingly. [Saloniki editor's note: True translation filed with the Postmaster of Chicago on July 13, as required by the Act of October 6, 1917.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
