<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-03-10">Mar. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A Great National Event.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0493</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0493.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-03-10">Mar. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A GREAT NATIONAL EVENT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3.. Last Monday about thirty women of wealthiest families in Chicago were invited by the Drama League of America, one of the aristocratic societies, to meet at 10:30 a. m. at the residence of Mrs. Frederick Countess, 1524 Lake Shore Drive, to discuss the introduction of the Greek and Byzantine art, drama, and dances in America. This movement was encouraged by Mr. and Mrs. Vassos Kanellos. Mr. Kanellos is well known among the Greeks in America and also among Americans; he is an instructor in ancient Greek dances.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Hoff presided at the meeting and in a few words introduced Mr. Kanellos, who made a very elegant speech describing the Grecian and Byzantine eras, exalting the grandeur of those epochs; he attired himself in beautiful Byzantine royal costumes which made a deep impression upon the audience.</p>
   <p>After this Mrs. Fifield spoke. She expressed her admiration and her astonishment at learning that in Chicago there are more than forty thousand successful and progressive Greek citizens.</p>
   <p>The ladies present then adopted a resolution to recommend the introduction of <pb facs="5422062_3_0494.jpg" n="2"/>Greek and Byzantine master pieces and also to solicit the support and the active participation of the local Greek population.</p>
   <p>After this Father Constantine was invited to speak, and he guaranteed that the Church as well as the Greeks of Chicago will gladly support this movement. Thereafter the organizer of the Drama League of America, Mrs. A. Starr Best of Evanston, spoke and explained her economic program.</p>
   <p>Mr. Paleologos was invited to make the closing speech, and he thanked the League and the ladies present for the interest which they have shown in the introduction of a knowledge of Greek and Byzantine civilization in America. "It is true," he said, "that ancient Greece was the mother of the world's civilization and that the Byzantine Empire was the seat of European civilization in the middle ages.</p>
   <p>"Your work, mesdames," said Mr. Paleologus, "is of great significance and honors our race. Here in Chicago we have an organized Church, many professional men, men engaged in industry, and three Greek newspapers. I can assure you <pb facs="5422062_3_0495.jpg" n="3"/>that all these persons and these institutions will offer their assistance in support of your project, which will introduce our adopted country and our generation to the classical life of ancient Greece.</p>
   <p>"Greeks have always displayed a generous spirit, and you may depend on the work which they will accomplish in the course of time. Then you will all be persuaded that the things which Mrs. Fifield has said about my countrymen are true."</p>
   <p>After Mr. Paleologos' speech the meeting ended, and the majority left full of enthusiasm. The executive committee remained to confer about the time when the first performance will take place in the Auditorium.</p>
   <p>It remains for us Greeks here to plan how to help a great nationalistic movement which will lay for us a new foundation for action, honor, and interest. In the near future a special invitation will be issued to all Greek associations, newspaper reporters, and professional men to attend a general conference and through a representative committee to co-operate with one another <pb facs="5422062_3_0496.jpg" n="4"/>to promote this project.</p>
   <p>May the Lord, who never abandons our race, guide us and teach us how to show ourselves worthy of so truly great a nationalistic enterprise!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
