<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-04-28">April 28, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Statement</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1010</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1010.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-04-28">April 28, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">STATEMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Of the Ownership, Management,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois, for April 1st, 1932.</p>
   <p>Act of Congress of August 24, 1912,</p>
   <p>Of Greek Press published weekly at Chicago, Illinois, for October 1st, 1931.</p>
   <p>State of Illinois, County of Cook</p>
   <p>Before me, a Notary Public in and for the State and County aforesaid, personally appeared Paul Javaras, who, having been duly sworn according to law, deposes and says that he is the Editor of the Greek Press and that the following is, to the best of his knowledge and belief, a true statement of the ownership, management (and, if a daily paper, the circulation), etc., of the aforesaid publication for the date shown in the above caption, required by the Act of August 24, 1912, embodied in section 411, Postal Laws and Regulations, printed on the reverse of this form, to wit:</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1011.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>1. That the names and addresses of the publisher, editor, managing editor, and business managers are: Name of Publisher, Greek Press Publishing Co.; Post office address, 188 W. Randolph St.; Editor, Paul Javaras; Managing Editor, Paul Javaras; Business Manager Geo. P. Marshall.</p>
   <p>2. That the owner is: (If owned by a corporation, its name, address must be stated and also immediately thereunder the names and addresses of stockholders owning or holding one percent or more of total amount of stock. If now owned by a corporation, the names and addresses of the individual owners must be given. If owned by a firm, company, or other unincorporated concern, its name and address, as well as those of each individual member, must be given.)</p>
   <p>Greek Press Publishing Co., 188 W. Randolph St.</p>
   <p>Paul Javaras, 1145 N. Harlem Avenue, Oak Park, Illinois; Louis George,</p>
   <p>188 W. Randolph St.; George P. Marshall, 4022 N. Kedvale.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1012.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>3. That the known bondholders, mortgages, and other security holders owning or holding 1 per cent or more of total amount of bonds, mortgages, or other securities are : None.</p>
   <p>4. That the two paragraphs, next to the above, giving the names of the owners, stockholders, and security holders, if any, contain not only the list of stockholders and security holders as they appear upon the books, of the company but also in case where the stockholder or security holder appears upon the books of the company as trustee or in any other fiduciary relation, the name of the person or corporation for whom such trustee is acting, is given; also that the said two paragraphs contain statements embracing affiants' full knowledge and belief as to the circumstances and conditions under which stockholders and security holders who do not appear upon the books of the company as trustees, hold stock and securities in a capacity other than of a bona fide owner; and this affiant has no reason to believe that any other person, association, or corporation has any interest direct or indirect in the said stock, bonds or other securities than as so stated by him.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1013.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>5. That the average number of copies of each issue of this publication sold or distributed, through the mails or otherwise, to paid subscribers during the six months preceding the date shown above is (This information is required from daily publications only).</p>
   <p>Paul Javaras, Editor, sworn to and subscribed before me this 5th day of April, 1932.</p>
   <p>(Seal) Constantine A. Alexopoulos.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
