<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-05-02">May 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Tripolitans Give Affair with Double Purpose</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1644</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1644.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1935-05-02">May 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">TRIPOLITANS GIVE AFFAIR WITH DOUBLE PURPOSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Due to their great amount of advertising the Tripolitan Lodge of Chicago succeeded in keeping last Sunday for themselves, for no other affairs were scheduled for that day. Two reasons caused the dance to receive wholehearted community support. The Tripolitans celebrated the birthday of Theodore Kolokotronis, who fought for Tripoli during the War of 1821, in an impressive liturgy conducted in the Holy Trinity Church by Bishops Callistos. Mr. J. Giannes, the consul general, honored the Lodge with his attendance. After the service, Mr. Andrew Vlachos, prominent Chicago lawyer, spoke of the honored dead who had fought for the freedom of Greece.</p>
   <p>Before these services, the members of the Lodge had gathered at 722 Blue Island Avenue and arranged themselves in parade formation. Behind them came sections of other Greek societies, carrying banners and flags. Preceded by an American Legion band playing funeral marches, they <pb facs="5422062_3_1645.jpg" n="2"/>proceeded to the Church.</p>
   <p>Following the services there was an intermission for rest before the evening celebration, held at the Amalgamated Center, 330 South Ashland Avenue. This affair was for the benefit of the Evangelismos Hospital of Tripoli.</p>
   <p>It is useless to give the details of the evening celebration because we are all familiar with the enjoyable Tripolitan social affairs....All the Greeks of Chicago seemed to be there, for who can resist a Tripolitan glendi [party], especially when it is for such a worthy cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
