<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-12-04">Dec. 4, 1930</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Melange- by Nick John Matsoukas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-12-04">Dec. 4, 1930</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">MELANGE- BY NICK JOHN MATSOUKAS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Esme" is to be presented by the Lord Byron Chapter of the Sons of Pericles at the Eighth Street Theater, next Sunday night, Dec. 8th. It is a play, as you all know replete with dramatic intensity and full of Roumeliotiki romance that will thrill even the Greeks who might have been born in Alaska. Peter Matsoukas and Gregory Monemuasites are the directors of the play. American publications have been buzzing with news about this dramatic event. Why shouldn't they? Take a look at the list of dignitaries:</p>
   <p>Senator Elect James Hamilton Lewis</p>
   <p>George E. Phillies, Supreme President of the Ahepa</p>
   <p>His Excellency, George Depasta, Consul General of Greece.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0612.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Most Reverend Exarch, Damaskinos, that big man, from Greece, (almost seven feet) and a few others.</p>
   <p>Business might be bad, but when it comes to social life for the Chicago Greeks, then we have a different story. It will take more than one Hoover with his prosperity to stop these Hellenes from making whoopee next Monday night, Dec. 11. At that time the Aragon Ballroom will open it doors to receive the thousands who are planning to see Miss Aliki Diplarakou, "Miss Europe," for whom the hall is being given, by the ladies of St. Andrews Church. What is a dollar when one can see "Miss Europe?"</p>
   <p>To the winds with Hoover prosperity!</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0613.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>You know, that what our old folks were telling us is that, if you stick to something you are bound to get it finally, is true. In Chicago we have the poet, Demetrios Michalaros (writes in English), who has been a slave to the literary art for some years. Now he has emerzed with two other books. "The Grove" (a translation from Polomos's original), and "Sonnets of an Immigrant," (Altogether original).</p>
   <p>Halsted Street has gone society. In other words those inhabitants who frequented the coffee houses, are now in great demand by society ladies to teach them Tavli (Bachzammon).</p>
   <p>John Vassos, the greatest book illustrator since Beardslay has just published his fifth book. "Ultimo" is the name.</p>
   <p>It seems that Hoover prosperity has scared many citizens away from the gentle occupation of handling money. At the election of the north Shore Ahepa, nobody wanted to run for treasurer.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0614.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Yet the chapter is solvent, and has more cash on hand than any other chapter in the Union. Those nominated and who refused the honor, must have thought that hard times are certain to come. The present treasurer, Peter Kondominas, was relected.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
