<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1911-05-13">May 13, 1911</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Greek Restaurant Keepers Association Hermes-To the Greek Restaruateurs in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0215</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0215.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1911-05-13">May 13, 1911</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">GREEK RESTAURANT KEEPERS ASSOCIATION HERMES-TO THE GREEK RESTARUATEURS IN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The object of this letter is to induce every Greek in the City of Chicago, who is engaged in the restaurant business, to come together in one body so that we may all plan how we can render our connections mutually beneficial. We must act, work, progress and prosper as a united body and not as individuals. In union there is strength. The Poles, Swedes and Germans, have strong unions, strong organizations, and the result is they are strong and powerful, politically, socially and commercially.</p>
   <p>The restaurant trade, in this great city of the West, is in the hands of fellow-Greeks but we are not strong as far as organization is concerned. We are not immigrants any more, we are established here in the land of the free people, and the land of progress and prosperity.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0216.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Let us forget petty differences and animosities and be united in one big and strong association, thus not only serving our interests, but the interest of our Mother-Greece and our Adopted Country, which expects us to go along with the life of the country.</p>
   <p>Let us come together and together decide how we can better the restaurant business and prove once more that we are not backward people, but progressive ones and worthy of our name.</p>
   <p>J. Kokkalis, President</p>
   <p>B. Constantakis, Secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
