<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-02-17">Feb. 17, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Successful Business.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0040</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0040.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-02-17">Feb. 17, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">SUCCESSFUL BUSINESS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5-The Greek restaurant corporation of John Raklios, that which maintains twentyfive restaurants in busy sections of this city, last week leased for a number of years, space in the building at 59-69 West Madison street, contracting to pay rent amounting to some five hundred thousand dollars. The amount of the annual rental is not yet known, nor the length of time for which the lease was written.</p>
   <p>We have been reliably informed, however, that the rental is the highest ever paid for an equal space on Madison street.</p>
   <p>The Raklios corporation intends to spend seventy thousand dollars in decorating this new restaurant and in making it one of the best of its kind.</p>
   <p>The Raklios Company, which has operated for many years under the direction of the well-known Greek, Mr. John Raklios, has been highly successful, and about three years ago it was made a corporation.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0041.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since that time it has increased its number of its restaurants and by the introduction of a really American system has rapidly progressed. The president of the Company is Mr. John Raklios, the vice-president is Mr. Vasilios Kotsonis, and the secretary is Mr. Andreas Chronopoulos or Chronis.</p>
   <p>The negotiations to secure the above lease were successfully completed by Mr. George Tsagouris, who has maintained a real estate office since 1908 and has done many a service to Greek businessmen in selecting and leasing for them proper locations. Although Mr. Tsagouris had to face some opposition on the part of American companies which were also interested in leasing in the above-mentioned property he succeeded in overcoming these obstacles and accomplished his purpose.</p>
   <p>Chicago is considered to be the modern Babylon, where all nationalities compete with one another. We therefore feel that this is a good omen for the progress and the success of our fellow Greeks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
