<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-05-26">May 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Tragedy "Iphigenia in Tauris" to Be Presented by the Socrates Greek School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0654</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.A.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0654.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I A 2 b</item>
     <item>I A 2 c</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-05-26">May 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE TRAGEDY "IPHIGENIA IN TAURIS" TO BE PRESENTED BY THE SOCRATES GREEK SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Wednesday, May 30, 1923, at 8:15 P. M., the pupils of the Socrates Greek School will present the classical Greek play, "Iphigenia In Tauris," in the Chicago Auditorium, Congress Street and Wabash Avenue. In addition to this drama they will also present several comedies.</p>
   <p>We believe that it is unnecessary for us to urge our beloved countrymen to attend this play, for they all understand the high purpose of its presentation and the national and social benefits which we expect to derive from our children who are trained in the Greek school.</p>
   <p>What we must emphasize is that this school has been established, enlarged, and supported by the dances and other entertainments given by Holy Trinity Church, and by the subscriptions of its members and a few others among our countrymen.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0655.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These young students are now seeking, by their own efforts, to obtain funds for the support of their school, in order that they may learn the language spoken by their forefathers in that country which they have never seen, but of which they hear their parents say many beautiful things.</p>
   <p>Sould this not touch our higher feelings? Should it not arouse our enthusiasm? Should it not inspire us to make sacrifices? Is the price of a ticket too much to pay to see our children act? Should not the acting of these children please us more than the performance presented in any other theater?</p>
   <p>Let us all attend the play to be produced by the Socrates School on May 30, 1923, thereby performing one of the most sacred of our duties. Without the school, the church cannot exist, and without the church and worship of God the Christian cannot live.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
