<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-10-09">Oct. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Guilty Are Absolved</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1915-10-09">Oct. 9, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE GUILTY ARE ABSOLVED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Never before have the Greek people of Chicago found themselves faced with a situation similar to the present one, caused by the bankruptcy of the Greek-American Bank.</p>
   <p>The eight hundred depositors who lost their savings in the bank were so disgusted, so disheartened and miserable, that not one of them appeared against the four bankers at their trial yesterday, with the result that the four exploiters were declared innocent of the embezzling charges.</p>
   <p>People who were merely followers of the progress of the matter, said that the bankers were not afraid, since they knew the type of people they had to contend with. Others gave all the credit to the bankers, because they were smart enough to fool the same people twice, and felt sorry that they did not get the chance to steal a larger sum of money.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0134.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These people, however, are very wrong for harboring such ideas. By doing so they are helping to kill the faith the Greek people have in each other.</p>
   <p>These eight hundred depositors who lost their savings were not lawyers, doctors or businessmen; they were merely laborers working in railroad gangs: Of these eight hundred, two hundred and eighty have not as yet received notice of the bank's closing, and are probably unaware of the bankruptcy. Of course, there were a few professional men who lost their money, but they were the ones who muddled the affair the most. Their concern seems to be for the side of the bankers.</p>
   <p>And so the poor workers, the unprotected, ignorant people who struggle for an existence are left to their fate. They could not raise a penny for their defense, so they were thought to be dumb and indifferent by the rest of the Greek community--a community so without conscience that it went so far as to give credit to the bankers for their ability to exploit these people.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0135.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This can only be called a bestial irony in the face of so much unhappiness; this is the death blow to Greek co-operation and brotherly feeling among the Greeks of America.</p>
   <p>The entire Greek community of Chicago should have hurried to the active defense of these eight hundred people. But this did not happen. So today we see the four scoundrels declared innocent and receiving congratulations from the community.</p>
   <p>Let them or anyone else seek the faith or support of the Greeks. They shall never get it and justly so!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
