<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-28">Sept. 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Eddie Varzos</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Hamlet</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0339</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0339.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1933-09-28">Sept. 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">EDDIE VARZOS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Hamlet</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I first knew him as a little lad carrying his father's musical scores to the theater every Sunday for the Varzos Orchestra. He was rather thin and tall, with eyes that revealed the artistic nature of the boy. His hands were well formed and his nails well kept, not revealing the tedious hours of hard work they performed in an effort to conquer the intricacies of the violin. This boy attracted one by his shy, quiet, manner, his hesitant speech, and his fine character. This was Eddie--the musically-trained and talented son of Varzos.</p>
   <p>After a short while instead of Edward, I saw the youngest son carrying the scores for his father. What had happened? Eddie had been promoted to the first violin in the orchestra; and a short time later he had become its conductor. At the Greek theaters and dances the orchestra of Eddie Varzos was <pb facs="5422062_3_0340.jpg" n="2"/>always present, by popular request. Then Eddie and his orchestra were invited to take an engagement at the famous Trianon Ballroom in Chicago.</p>
   <p>This gave our fellow patriots much to talk about. Most of them did not hesitate to say that Eddie was given this engagement only because of the kindness of its Greek owner, Mr. Karzas. Others credited it to mere chance. Finally they accomplished what they wanted, and Eddie played no longer at the Trianon. Then they really did talk. They said: "The star has fallen; he, too, was a comet; we knew he wouldn't last." And yet, some of us knew that Eddie's star was a bright one that had not dropped out of the firmament.</p>
   <p>Were we not justified? In spite of the fact that there was an economic tightness and that a pitiful situation existed in the music-making and music-selling world, Eddie not only retained his leadership and his orchestra, but he even made considerable amounts of money. At present, he has one of the finest and most popular orchestras in Chicago. Just as he was the chosen one of the Greek <pb facs="5422062_3_0341.jpg" n="3"/>community of Chicago in the past, so he became the chosen one of the American aristocracy of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Last year he was engaged by the most exclusive and famous clubs and dining places of Chicago; the Maisonette Russe, the Club Petroushka, and at present, the Paramount Club. John Lawson of the Daily News wrote about the appearance of Faith Bacon at the Paramount, saying, "....even more brilliant than the dancing was the music of Eddie Varzos. There is no doubt in my mind that Varzos will achieve national popularity in a short time. His five-piece orchestra plays Argentine tangoes that are as sweet and light as a breeze".</p>
   <p>This is a far cry from the little fellow carrying his father's musical notes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
