<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-09-26">Sept. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Truth Is Being Smothered</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1118</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1118.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-09-26">Sept. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">TRUTH IS BEING SMOTHERED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Greeks of America, especially Chicagoans, are reading the columns of Saloniki to see if we have made any response to the insults heaped upon us by other Greek papers. We are referring to the organs which are supporting--and being supported by--the notorious bankers of the Greek-American Bank.</p>
   <p>Greeks of America are anxious to discover if this bank actually has gone into bankruptcy, as we have announced in our paper. They want to know if the sudden poverty of Rifakis, the flight of Koustoumbos, and the wasteful spending of $400,000 by these gentlemen are facts worthy of public attention. Greek people are skeptical of this information because as yet no other Greek newspaper in America has made any reference to these events. Not only do these papers refrain from printing the truth, but they even try to hide it. They feel that the longer they can keep Greeks in ignorance of the true facts, the longer they (the papers) will receive the support of the bankers.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1119.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Saloniki loudly and frankly proclaims that the Greek-American Bank of Chicago has gone into bankruptcy. The sum of $215,000 has been lost! Rifakis has gone into bankruptcy after stealing $150,000 belonging to Greek laborers. Koutsoumbus has fled with $20,000. These are proven facts and must be told to every Greek in America.</p>
   <p>The insults and slurs cast upon Saloniki by these men and their friends are being ignored. We do not condescend even to answer them.....</p>
   <p>Saloniki has never taken part in personal insults and defamations..... It has refrained because we know that Greeks of America are intelligent enough to distinguish between good and evil; thus only a review of past occurrences is necessary in order for them to know which paper is telling the truth.</p>
   <p>The other papers have tried to embroil us in arguments and trouble in order that we would have neither time nor space to devote to exposing the activities <pb facs="5422062_3_1120.jpg" n="3"/>of certain people. If we had fallen into their trap, any subsequent accusations we might have made would have been regarded merely as more of our argumentative articles. As a result, the truth would have been smothered and the culprits would have been allowed to escape without punishment.</p>
   <p>We will say no more about the individuals involved in order that we might not give our enemies ammunition to be used against us and the truth for which we are fighting. We will try to explain the relationship between the lying bankers and the newspapers which are supporting their lies.</p>
   <p>All Greeks have read the advertisements of this bank in the newspapers that are now fighting us. These "ads" were well paid for and involved thousands of dollars. These editors accepted money in return for advising the hardworking Greek worker to invest his few dollars in the Greek bank. These thousands have bought the silence of all the Greek newspapers--except Saloniki.</p>
   <p>Saloniki has the right to print anything it chooses because it has never <pb facs="5422062_3_1121.jpg" n="4"/>accepted bribes from these bankers. We have taken no part in the deeds that have caused hundreds of Greeks to grieve, and we are proud of that fact. What good does a paper do if it shouts its patriotic feelings and points to funds and programs it has sponsored in behalf of the fatherland, but, at the same time, permits Greek-Americans to be robbed?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
