<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1933-10-31">Oct. 31, 1933</date><title level="a">Mr. Euripides Kehayias and the Auction Sale of the National Herald</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0999</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0999.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Proodos (Progress)</title>,
<date when="1933-10-31">Oct. 31, 1933</date><title level="a">MR. EURIPIDES KEHAYIAS AND THE AUCTION SALE OF THE NATIONAL HERALD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is now several weeks since the daily Greek newspaper the National Herald and all its equipment, including the editorial staff, became property of the wealthy Greek, Mr. Euripides Kehayias, through an auction sale.</p>
   <p>Or rather, as somebody said in jest, Mr. Kehayias became the property of the Herald.</p>
   <p>We do not want to express our opinion on the subject, but it is a common secret that Mr. Kehayias was the real owner of this immense enterprise all along as he was the one who paid the bills.</p>
   <p>The thing that arouses the curiosity of the public now is the fact that just as soon as the legal title of this enterprise was transfered <pb facs="5422062_3_1000.jpg" n="2"/>to Mr. Kehayias an intense campaign was started to proclaim his ability as a clever publisher and a great leader of Greek journalism, with many flattering predictions as to the future of the enterprises under his dynamic direction.</p>
   <p>And it will not be surprising to see a new Hearst of Grecian descent in the field of Grecian journalism!</p>
   <p>About the ability of Mr. Kehayias to make money there is no doubt, because all the people who bought shares in his Standard Commercial Tobacco Company are waiting with anxiety for the first dividends.</p>
   <p>We think that the burning of too much incense at the picture of Mr. Kehayias as an important person in Greek journalism here is a <pb facs="5422062_3_1001.jpg" n="3"/>farce and is not becoming the dignity of true journalism. And furthermore it gives the impression of the promotion of a suspicious commercial enterprise.</p>
   <p>Fortunately or unfortunately, there is not plenty of money among our countrymen and so we believe there is no fresh field in which to cultivate the sales of stocks of such a commercial enterprise.</p>
   <p>Also the visit of Mr. Kehayias to Chicago, and the establishment of branch offices of the paper here is an indication of the commercial ability and vision of the new management of the paper which discarded the founder of that paper, Mr. P. Tatanes, who for many years was advertised as the Titan of the Greek journalism despite his ignorance of it.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1002.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The showing of this new trader as a new journalistic titan does not create any new impressions, with the exception that the columns of the paper are full of letters of praise written by various important and insignificant individuals.</p>
   <p>The success of the new policy of the office staff, and if it will be lucky enough to prove the well-wishers right, is a matter for the future to decide but we are very skeptical about it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
