<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-06-19">June 19, 1930</date><title level="a">School Holiday in Evanston</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1313</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1313.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-06-19">June 19, 1930</date><title level="a">SCHOOL HOLIDAY IN EVANSTON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5.- Last fall, a group of prominent Evanston men headed by Messers. Kokkala and Georgousis, conceived the idea of providing a Greek education for their youngsters. They decided to rent a building to serve as a school, but due to the small number of Greek children in Evanston, this proved impractical.</p>
   <p>They succeeded in obtaining a room donated by the ashington Public School bo be used from 4 to 8:30 for this purpose. The great kindness of the school board comes through F. W. Nichols, president, and Miss E. G. White, superintendent.</p>
   <p>As soon as the meeting place for the children was arranged, Miss Basiliki Chrisos Thenou took over her duties as teacher. Twenty seven children were enrolled last November and were promoted last Sunday. These children, who could not speak Greek a year ago had progressed so rapidly that they <pb facs="5422062_3_1314.jpg" n="2"/>were able to recite poems, dialogues and recitations in Greek with the greatest ease.</p>
   <p>Guest of honor at the assembly were F. Nichols and Miss White. Mrs. Nichols and Miss White were given beautiful bouquets of flowers. Mr. Georgousis presented flowers to the girl students and Mr. Kokkalas presented Greek and American flags to the boys.</p>
   <p>Miss Chrisosthenou thanked the parents, the guests of honor, Messers Kokkalas and Georgousis and also Miss Soula Diaggelis for accompanying the songs on the piano. Refreshments and coffee were served after the program.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
