<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-06-19">June 19, 1929</date><title level="a">The Greeks of Chicago a Powerful Element</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1055</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1055.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-06-19">June 19, 1929</date><title level="a">THE GREEKS OF CHICAGO A POWERFUL ELEMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the long list of newspapers and magazines, published in the United States, exclusively for Greek readers, is added the Greek Press. This issue is its first number.</p>
   <p>The Greek Press, as the reader will readily see, is printed principally in Greek but also contains a number of columns in English. Sometimes there will be more columns of English and at other times less, for the benefit of those of its readers, who find it easier to read in the English language.</p>
   <p>The major portion of the Greek Press will be printed in Greek, for beside the fact that most of its readers are natives of Greece and will naturally prefer to follow the local, national and international events in their mother tongue, it is the conviction also of the publishers that the Greek tongue, being itself from the Gods, will elevate anyone who will become acquainted with its nobleness, whether he be a Greek or otherwise.</p>
   <p>On the above point writers and thinkers, the world over, agree and they never let an opportunity pass without emphasizing the value of the Greek language.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1056.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>None excells the sentiments expressed by General Garfield, however, who make the following statement:</p>
   <p>"Greek is, perhaps, the most perfect instrument of thought ever invented by man, and Greek literature has never been equaled in purity of style and boldness of expression. As a means of intellectual discipline its value can hardly be overestimated. To take a long and complicated sentence in Greek; to study each word in its meanings, inflections, and relations; to build up in the mind, out of these polished materials, a sentence, perfect as a temple, and filled with Greek thought which has dwelt there two thousand years, is almost on act of creation. Such an effort calls into activity all the faculties of the mind."</p>
   <p>In making its appearance, before the Greek public, the Greek Press feels that it is duty bound to state its aims and principles.</p>
   <p>The publishers of the Greek Press have made Chicago their home for the last quarter of a century. During all these years they have followed and watched the growth of the city itself; the advancement and betterment of its Greek population.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1057.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The time was not very far distant when there was but one Greek church in Chicago, when the number of stores owned by Greeks was less than one hundred and when there was not a solitary property owner.</p>
   <p>Now what have we to show in the short spasm of less than a generation? Nine churches, instead of one, Fifty times as many stores and thousands of property owners.</p>
   <p>This expansion of the Greeks, in the business and social world, is truly remarkable and noteworthy. They merit all the praise that is due to their industry, frugality and sagacity.</p>
   <p>Presently the Greeks of Chicago possess a number of publications, all actively promoting the interests of the Greeks in America and ardently expounding the Greek ideals.</p>
   <p>The Greek Press will not claim that it comes to fill a long felt want, that had it not been for its appearance, a noble cause would have been lost, or that a glorious battle would not have been won.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1058.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It simply feels that this thriving group of 75,000 people within the metropolitan district of Chicago, needs, and will support a paper which is more fitted to the times we are living in, one that will seek their activities and accomplishments, pure and unalloyed.</p>
   <p>To this purpose of serving our compatriots, in broadening their spheres of influence, in enriching their own values with what America has to offer of its best, we will give of what there is best and pure in us, contented with the thought that he who serves best gets most.</p>
   <p>Publishers of the</p>
   <p>Greek Press.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
