<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-01-08">Jan. 8, 1931</date><title level="a">Dinner Party Given by Mr. Dem. Megalides in Honor of Miss Diplarakou ("Miss Europe")</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0793</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
                    
                    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0793.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1931-01-08">Jan. 8, 1931</date><title level="a">DINNER PARTY GIVEN BY MR. DEM. MEGALIDES IN HONOR OF MISS DIPLARAKOU ("MISS EUROPE")</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4.- In front of a fireplace, 40 feet high, burning three mammoth logs big enough to start a real war in any village in Greece, the guests were waiting. This fireplace was not on any farm or ranch-house but in a luxurious and aristocratic building.</p>
   <p>In this home, a part of the splendid and aristocratic Edgewater Beach Hotel, the following were waiting: Constant Mammon (Paleologos), Paul Demos, Paul Javaras, Editor of the Greek Press, with his sister, Paraskevorila, Mr. &amp; Mrs. Efstration Pofanti, with Mrs. Pofantis' brothers, John and Athan Tsoumas, George Spanon and Peter Lambros, Editor of the Greek Star, with his son and two daughters.</p>
   <p>In due time our host Demosthenes Megalides, of the National Bank of Greece, arrived with Miss Diplarakou ("Miss Europe") and her mother for the dinner to be served, in the main dining room. The dinner, in honor of "Miss Europe", started at 8 P.M. It consisted of a well selected and prepared menu and delicacies.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0794.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>While everybody was dining, the band leader in the next hall informed the hotel guests--that "Miss Europe" was in the next hall, so they rose, and with cheers demanded to see the beautiful Greek girl, who from a platform greeted them. The guests thanked Mr. Megalides for the wonderful time they had, departing at midnight.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
