<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1921-03-05">Mar. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Brilliant Lecture on Language Problem</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1482</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.B"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1482.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>V B</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1921-03-05">Mar. 5, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">BRILLIANT LECTURE ON LANGUAGE PROBLEM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday afternoon in one of the halls of Hull House, a lecture was given concerning the language problem of the Greek people. It was sponsored by the Greek Students' League.</p>
   <p>Mr. D. Eftaxias, one of the first Greek journalists to come to America, was asked by the League to speak on this subject.</p>
   <p>The theme was of major interest to the large group of men and women who attended. Mr. Eftaxias spoke for three hours, during which he explained and propounded his theme so well that he held the undivided attention of his audience.</p>
   <p>There had been, he said, no language problem in Greece, because the Greeks <pb facs="5422062_3_1483.jpg" n="2"/>preserved faithfully the language of Korais, and the other great minds of the preceding centuries.</p>
   <p>This language was banished through the efforts of Russia; tsarist Russia having as a program the taking of Constantinople, and making all the Balkans one state, found the pure Greek language a hindrance in the unification of these groups. Therefore a system of propaganda was introduced, causing poems, translations of Homer, and books, to be printed in a language having the Greek forms but interspersed with various Slavic words. Gradually there evolved a language which although it sounded Greek, was not the language the ancient Greeks had striven so hard to keep pure.</p>
   <p>"It is our duty", Mr. Eftaxias said, "as Greek people to lift the veils of darkness, to repair the tattered fragments, and to soothe this wounded language of ours."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
