<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-12-06">Dec. 6, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">A Trial for Libel</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mr. James Kominakis Sues the Newspaper Hellas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-12-06">Dec. 6, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">A TRIAL FOR LIBEL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mr. James Kominakis Sues the Newspaper Hellas</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As has been known for six years now, an insignificant Greek newspaper by the name of Hellas is being published in this city. It has a wide circulation in the Greek quarter around Halsted Street and Blue Island Avenue. One of the main attractions which this news organ offer the public is its advertisement of the famous Harem cigarettes. Besides this, it is engaged in advertising the laborer and servant employment agency of Karavelis and Bomsoulas, who own the cigar store on South Halsted Street near the offices of our Greek bankers and brokers, Messrs. Giocaris and Stamatiadis. (Trans. note: no initials were given).</p>
   <p>This small paper is being published in the office above the Hellas saloon. Most of the articles in the paper are written by one Nick Printezis, who is also one of the principal owners of the paper.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1186.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A series of articles and items containing libelous and defamatory remarks against Mr. James Kominakis appeared in Hellas during the period from April to August of this year. This gentleman was called a notorious, disreputable character and a dirty dog, worse than those that roam the streets of Constantinople. It is difficult for us to mention the filthy language which was used, because we do not wish to offend the public's sense of decency. This unfair, sycophantic, and rude conduct of the owners and publishers of Hellas forced Mr. Kominakis to have recourse to the courts of justice. He has the sympathy and support of the Greeks of Chicago in his fight against the malicious accusers.</p>
   <p>So, legal action was instituted before a jury in the court of Judge Houston. The trial lasted three days, during which all the filthy accusations and shameless libels against Mr. Kominakis were translated into English. The unspeakable language and the shameless insults which were examined by the jury resulted in the conviction of the owners of Hellas, who were forced to pay the sum of $400 to Mr. Kominakis for unjustifiable libel and defamation of character.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1187.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Of those convicted, Mr. Eustathios Karavelas is in Athens, Greece, and consequently we doubt that he will share any guilt in the case. The other defendant, Mr. Soterios Bousoulas or Lieos from Stouras, Karystos, may also be absolved from all responsibility in the case, for only a few days ago, he testified before Judge Facke that in May, 1907 he sold the newspaper Hellas to Mr. Printezis for $800, $400 of which was paid in cash, while a promissory note was signed for the remaining amount. He said that he did not record the sale in the newspaper's books, nor did he mention anything about the sale at the time. Therefore, he claims that he is not responsible for the actions and policies of the newspaper. If we assume that the testimony of Bousoulas was truthful, then Mr. Printezis will have to answer to the law for the conduct of his newspaper.</p>
   <p>We deem it unnecessary to comment on the evasive attitude and the legal technicalities employed by the defendants of the case in question, because the public has formed some opinion about them from their behavior in the past. Fortunately, in spite of all their efforts, they have been unable to shake the foundations of truth and justice, nor have they succeeded in <pb facs="5422062_3_1188.jpg" n="4"/>influencing the just opinion and verdict of the jury, who by their irrevocable decision have smitten the head of the Lernaean hydra, that is, the falsities and malice of Printezis and company. A serious blow has thus been struck in the American courts against Greek journalism in Chicago.</p>
   <p>We are really very sorry that we have to publish these terrible facts. Permit us to say, in passing, that those gentlemen have shown the depth of their depravity and social degradation.</p>
   <p>The plaintiff, Mr. Kominakis, has been one of the oldest and most respectable and progressive members of the Greek community of Chicago. He fought bravely in the Greco-Turkish war of 1897, and is today an active officer of the patriotic National Macedonian Society.</p>
   <p>We fervently hope that the healthy and sober-minded press of our community will continue to defend and protect the interests and good name of our good <pb facs="5422062_3_1189.jpg" n="5"/>Greek citizens, not only in Chicago but in the entire United States. Those news organs that are not fit to perform their duties properly and decently must be destroyed and prosecuted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
