<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-04-02">April 2, 1910</date><title level="a">The Gree Press in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-04-02">April 2, 1910</date><title level="a">THE GREE PRESS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- The Greek Press in America should be severely scolded. Why aren't the 350,000 Greeks in America more concerned about the welfare of their native land? Is it their fault or is it the fault of the press? The press should record all possible news about Greece. The press should write about political positions and point out dangers that confront the Greek people. Why doesn't it do this?</p>
   <p>Many think they have done their duty by contributing the $40,000 to Matsoukas. Eighty thousand dollars would only have been a drop in the bucket. We should be able to raise $400,000.00 if we truly wish to help our countrymen. From the total amount collected we would say that the 350,000 Greeks of America gave an average of twelve cents apiece. That is the patriotic enthusiasm we show for our native land.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1160.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are always holding large celebrations with speeches, songs, etc., emphasizing our love for Greece. These are of no help to our brave homeland. They will not scare the Turn away. The Greeks are very generous with their money. They give it away. To whom? To the priests and their hirelings who are not interested in your welfare or the welfare of Greece.</p>
   <p>You are not to blame, Greeks of America. Your press is to blame. Your press should be the organ of the people, the adviser, the guide, the informer. If the press fails to live up to these duties, the readers should give it a poke to get it started again. A properly organized newspaper can be very powerful if handled correctly. Give it a poke, Greeks of America, start it again.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
