<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-08-15">Aug. 15, 1926</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Music and the Greeks.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0553</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0553.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1926-08-15">Aug. 15, 1926</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">MUSIC AND THE GREEKS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Taking a trip to the largest Greek community of Chicago, one feels that he is going through some great hall of music. Eating stores, coffee houses, hotels, taverns, groceries and what not all have musical entertainment. Music everywhere and of all kinds. The Greek knowing that at birth he was touched by the musical scepter of the muses believes in music as his ancestors did.</p>
   <p>Can you imagine the world without music, without melody, or harmony? Music in some form is so intimately entwined with our daily life that it becomes a part of us. From the mother crooning a lullaby, to the grand orchestra, or grand opera, music is essential to the enjoyment of life, to health and happiness. The ancient and modern Greeks knew that music is seen in the child struggling to utter words he does not yet know. The beautiful realm of sound is all about us, and each of us may find the form of music which please us most.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0554.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In order to enjoy the pleasures afforded by music, one need not know the technical secrets.of making harmonious sounds. It is both in the listening and the performing. Those who listen, lose themselves in feeling.</p>
   <p>The musical instruments used by the Greek players in some stores around "Greek Town" are odd looking, as for instance, a "Bouzouki" nevertheless the player and the listeners enjoy the harmony. Music, the magic kingdom, is the utterance of life, the symphony of nature. Music, the magic rhythm, harmony and order. Rhythm is soothing and pleasant to the body and soul.</p>
   <p>The nerves are rocked and lulled into acquiescence by the strains of soft music, that is why mothers rock and sing babies to sleep. You will notice that when a mother sings her baby into slumber, she sings softly and monotonously. It has a relaxing effect.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0555.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Music, as an accompaniment to any activity is at once pleasurable and stimulating. It creates moods and heightens the impressions received by the eye. Music at dinner hour produces cheerful thoughts and improves digestion, by prolonging the meal. To the normal person music is a diversion, it effects the mind keenly and is, therefore, employed as a stimulant in religion and war.</p>
   <p>Leonidas with his 300 Spartans at Thermopylae before the battle with the Persians, took out his flute and made stimulating melody. The forerunner of the Persians, who came to demand their surrender, was astonished with the musical diversion of the Greeks. Music helped to arouse the super-human courage of the 300 immortals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
