<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-09-11">Sept. 11, 1929</date><title level="a">The Paleohoritans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1755</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1755.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1929-09-11">Sept. 11, 1929</date><title level="a">THE PALEOHORITANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the largest clubs in Chicago is that of the Paleohoritan community. The Paleohoritans are among the first Chicagoans to organize themselves and carry out their purposes and endeavors successfully. We all know that wherever we turn, we will see a Paleohoritan with his own establishment, if not owning the entire building in which his business is located.</p>
   <p>With all this progress, they have not forgotten their native land. Their organization has done many things for their "home town" and will continue to do so.</p>
   <p>With this in mind, they gave their annual picnic last Sunday at the Polonis Grove. Naturally, the picnic was a success. We never realized there were so many Greeks in Chicago; men and women born in Greece and the younger generation born in America.</p>
   <p>For hours the Greek orchestra played our beloved songs and the Paleohoritans danced with their wives and friends and sons and daughters. Four dance circles were necessary to give everyone a chance to dance. The <pb facs="5422062_3_1756.jpg" n="2"/>enthusiasm which the boys and girls showed for Greek dancing was an unexpected but pleasant surprise. The Paleohoritans have every right to be proud of their Greek children.</p>
   <p>The success of the picnic was due chiefly to the efforts of P. Courlas, president; G. Lempesis, vice-president; N. Economos, secretary and N. Gianakakos, treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
