<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-11-01">Nov. 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">A Perverted Newspaper</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1190</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1190.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-11-01">Nov. 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">A PERVERTED NEWSPAPER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Any regular reader of The Semaia, another Greek newspaper in Chicago,.... will have observed that its editorial writer, Mr. Fasoularides, suffers from an inexplicable mania which embraces nagging, insults, superficiality, indecency, and every other evil affliction. To our great misfortune, such a man presumes to be a teacher and leader of our community.</p>
   <p>Because of these peculiarities of his, Mr. Fasoularides has not refrained from attacking and insulting this newspaper. For some time now, he has been freely hurling all sorts of insults against many other respectable people without even considering the rules of decency and courtesy. In vain has he been preaching these "noble principles" in a stentorean voice from the columns of his newspaper.</p>
   <p>As if this were not bad enough, he has now directed his venomous arrows against <pb facs="5422062_3_1191.jpg" n="2"/>our distinguished and highly reputed Greek banker, Angelis Giocaris, accusing him of having spoken against the interests and the honor of our fatherland. In regard to this incident, we have made an appropriate answer, and have considered that the whole case was closed after the necessary explanations were made. Mr. Fasoularides, however, will continue his nagging until he succeeds in getting permission to advertise for the Giocaris and Stamatides banking, real-estate, and brokerage house. With these same methods, he succeeded in getting the advertising of the white-slave and smuggling racket, which brought so much disgrace to the Greek name. When someone speaks to him of this scandal, he remains as silent as a fish.</p>
   <p>Such a journalistic policy not only detracts from the dignity of a true newspaper, but reduces it to the level of the gutter. There is then no hope left for decent and independent journalism.</p>
   <p>We do not wish to embitter and antagonize the oldest Greek journalist in <pb facs="5422062_3_1192.jpg" n="3"/>America with these remarks, but, as members of the same profession, we wish to suggest that Mr. Fasoularides cease making derogatory and violent personal attacks. Otherwise, he will be classed among the empty-headed, simple-minded, and backward pseudo journalists. Furthermore, let the publisher and owner of The Semaia refrain from heaping on us all the calumnies in the world, and from accusing us of stirring up trouble with the staff of Hellas, another contemporary.</p>
   <p>As for our opinions and written attitudes on the question of the proposed Panhellenic Order--they remain unchanged. The Semaia cannot say that we are hindering the progress of the Order. In this matter, as in all others, we have taken a courteous and dignified stand which cannot be affected by the perverted minds of our enemies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
