<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1923-05-05">May 5, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A Great Artistic Performance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0912</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0912.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-05-05">May 5, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A GREAT ARTISTIC PERFORMANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Greek Festival at the Auditorium Under the Auspices of Chicago Society Women</p>
   <p>For the first time in the history of the United States an artistic Greek festival has been organized and will be soon held. It will be a reproduction of the life of the ancient Greeks who under the sponsorship of Apollo, the god of music, and the Muses of Helicon brought the fine arts to ideal perfection.</p>
   <p>For the first time also the life of the Byzantine Greeks will be reproduced, who for several centuries led the world in the fine arts and the sciences and incoiliization and was a mighty maritine power.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0913.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first part of the program consists of the Dionysia, a festal procession depicted on ancient Greek vases. The god of wine, Dionysus, followed by satyrs and other mythological creatures, leads the procession, which winds up in a festival at which aromatic wine flows freely, while the satyrs perform elaborate dances in honor of Dionysus and Aphrodite.</p>
   <p>The second part of the program is an imposing Byzantine drama "The Emperor's Bride," of which the scene is laid in the Byzantine palace near the shore of Bosporus. Byzantine magnificence and Byzantine costumes with their rich and variegated colors make a marvelous spectacle.</p>
   <p>This presentation is of great nationalistic importance because besides its main purpose, the revival of Greek art it will contribute to the social and commercial uplift of the Greeks of Chicago, who will undoubtedly be present with their American fellow citizens to pay their respects to glorious and immortal Greece.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0914.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Saloniki, considers it a sacred duty to work for this high cause. It remains for the Chicago Greeks to show that they are worthy of their Greek descent.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
