<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1930-01-04">Jan. 4, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Biography of Constantine Salopoulos, Editor of Saloniki</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. C. P. Kaliontzis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1018</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1018.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1930-01-04">Jan. 4, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">BIOGRAPHY OF CONSTANTINE SALOPOULOS, EDITOR OF SALONIKI</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Dr. C. P. Kaliontzis</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.- "Those who love God are righteous," Paul said.</p>
   <p>The life of the deceased Constantine Salopoulos was as Paul described. He loved God and consequently he was just. He never in his mind or heart entertained an evil thought or any iniquity. His justice was natural and hereditary. His father, Dr. Athanasius Salopoulos, was just and pious and never became indignant when an injustice was done him.</p>
   <p>Constantine Salopoulos was the prototype of a just man, he was good as a friend, honest family-man, good citizen, excellent patriot and eminent professional man. With these virtues he performed his duties to the end of his life.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1019.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Great men are not only those who distinguishes themselves in war, but also those who, in time of peace, distinguish themselves in justice and benevolence. War is an episode in our life, while peace is the continuous prosperity of people. Peace has the blessing of God, and those who in peace are in the front rank are great men.</p>
   <p>Owing to my friendship with the deceased,I have found him, for the last twenty-five years, to be virtuous and just. He never permitted himself to become irritable, although he was vexed when iniquity was at any time practiced in the family circle, community affairs, affairs of the state, or in journalism. On one occasion I recollect when both of us were invited to a mutual friend's house, who was celebrating his name's day. Constantine, upon seeing a certain individual among the invited, was very careful to avoid him and not to sit close to him. When I suggested that the certain individual never meant any harm to him or to his family, Constantine said, "He who does evil to others, soon will do evil to me. He must be shunned."</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1020.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He regarded friendship as a religious devotion. The abuser of friendship was classified as a sacrilegious person by the deceased. He knew and practiced the immortal friendship of Damon and Pythias. He was very careful in choosing his friends. Once he said to me, "It would have been a blessing if all of us were careful to choose our friends." He was a man of few words and a very brief writer and very much disliked blabbing orators and speakers. He knew and practiced the adage "Let not the tongue go before the mind." He never spoke without thinking first. His publications were balanced by logic and his writings were just.</p>
   <p>Exercising his political franchise was a part of his religion; and his convictions regarding anybody he voted for, were of the highest kind. As a fellow Greek he always fought for the purity of the Greek language, ideology and tradition. He was a symbol of activity, energy and straight forwardness in our Greek community in Chicago. As Chairman of various committees and societies he never deviated from righteousness. Flattery and diplomacy were things strange to him.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1021.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>My dear friend, Constantine, came to America in 1903, right after he graduated from the University of Athens, at which institution he majored in chemistry. Soon he got his professional license and opened up his drug store, which was the first Greek drug store in Chicago. It was the Mecca for the Greeks of Chicago. I was one of the first Greek doctors who listened to his counsel and opened an evening office in his drug store in 1904. That marked the beginning of our friendship, which lasted until his death. Being his friend and having my evening office in his drug store, did not turn him from his helpfulness and wise counsel to the many Greeks who flocked in his store for advice and medicine. And only when his profession did not permit him to go any further in his ministration of medicine, would he send people to my office inside the drug store.</p>
   <p>I, as a friend and the Greek community in general, regret the loss of the deceased Constantine Salopoulos, whose deeds and memory will remain with us for ever.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
