<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-04-23">April 23, 1910</date><title level="a">By-Laws of the Greek Restaurant Association of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0235</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0235.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1910-04-23">April 23, 1910</date><title level="a">BY-LAWS OF THE GREEK RESTAURANT ASSOCIATION OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.- Art. 1. The Greek restaurateurs of Chicago, Illinois, United States of America, have met together on March 1, 1910 and organized the Greek Restaurant Association of Chicago, for the better development of restaurants.</p>
   <p>Art. 2. All Greek restaurateurs are elegible for membership.</p>
   <p>Art. 3. Before becoming a member the restaurateur must fill out an application and have it signed by the secretary of the club.</p>
   <p>Art. 4. He must take an oath of allegiance to the organization.</p>
   <p>Art. 5. Members will enjoy all privileges granted by the organization unless otherwise specified.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0236.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Art. 6. The Association will take care of all grievances and complaints.</p>
   <p>Art. 7. The Association will lend money to borrowers under specific rules and regulations.</p>
   <p>Art. 8. The committee will work at all times for the benefit of all. They welcome any criticisms or suggestions at all times.</p>
   <p>Art. 9. No business dealings can be done with a restaurateur of another city or another nationality without the consent of the association.</p>
   <p>Art. 10. The committee will consist of 18 members: 1 president, 1 vice-president, 1 treasurer, 1 assistant treasurer, 1 secretary, 1 recording secretary, and 12 committeemen. These will constitute a board of directors.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0237.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Art. 11. (Duties of the President)</p>
   <p>Art. 12. Vice-president takes the place of the president upon his absence.</p>
   <p>Art. 13. (Duties of the secretary)</p>
   <p>Art. 14. (Duties of the recording secretary)</p>
   <p>Art. 15. (Duties of the treasurer)</p>
   <p>Art. 16. (Duties of Assistant treasurer)</p>
   <p>Art. 17. Checks are to be signed by the president and the treasurer.</p>
   <p>Deposits will be made by the treasurer only.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
