<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. C. Mammon</title>, 208 S. La Salle St., Chicago, Ill.
<date when="1923-05-16">May 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">(Letter sent to C. Mammon by the "Drama League of America")</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0457</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   <catRef target="#source-correspondence"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0457.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Correspondence of Mr. C. Mammon</title>, 208 S. La Salle St., Chicago, Ill.
<date when="1923-05-16">May 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">(Letter sent to C. Mammon by the "Drama League of America")</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I was greatly disappointed in not having the pleasure of seeing you the evening of the performance but I seemed to be much needed in back of the stage and unable to get out in front to enjoy the result of all our labor. I hope that you were as pleased with the beauty of the performance as the rest of the audience seemed to be and feel that it was worth all the time and effort put into it.</p>
   <p>I realize, of course, that the entire success of the Greek side of the movement is due to you and your personal efforts. Without you and the doctor we could have done nothing and I shall never forget the generous cooperation and unlagging enthusiasm which you have given throughout the entire undertaking.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0458.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It has been a tremendous pleasure to work with you, and even though we may not make very much money out of the undertaking, which is more or less a disappointment, yet the artistic success is so great that we hope that the lasting influence and better relation between the Greeks and the leading Chicago people may be of enough value to repay us all for the time and energy and enthusiasm which we have put into it.</p>
   <p>In any event it will always be a lasting pleasure to have had the opportunity of working with you and becoming acquainted with you and Dr. N. Salopoulos.</p>
   <p>I trust that we may be able to continue our project for promoting interest in Greek things and shall hope to meet you again before very long to discuss the matter further.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0459.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>May I take this opportunity, therefore, of sending you my personal thanks for all the help and kindness which you extended us during the undertaking.</p>
   <p>Marjorie A. Best. (Mrs. A. Starr)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
