<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1914-08-22">Aug. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[Safety of Investments]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1125</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1125.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-08-22">Aug. 22, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[SAFETY OF INVESTMENTS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Greeks have for, the moment, lost all interest in the European war. Their minds are filled with thoughts of their lost savings.</p>
   <p>The Saloniki has repeatedly printed articles which have advised the Greek people where and how to invest their money. Great care has always been exercised in order that these [recommended] investments should be made in reliable concerns. We have never accepted the advertisements of dubious or untrust-worthy banks. This care has been taken because we earnestly try to help our fellow citizens. For that reason, we have never accepted misleading advertisements which would fool the public.....However, we are not supposed to be writing eulogies about ourselves.</p>
   <p>We are publishing this article for all the Greeks of America--not just for those in Chicago. The Greeks are advised to make haste and to put their savings into secure banking houses. The United States Postal Savings Bank is an <pb facs="5422062_3_1126.jpg" n="2"/>especially safe place to bank your money. Use this bank so that no more of you will lose your hard-earned money in banks run by thieves.</p>
   <p>Statistics show that Greek people have deposited over $500,000 in banks that have a capital of only $20,000. That is a peculiar situation. It seems our advice goes to waste. Greek people always listen to the one who tells them fancy stories. They are never impressed by plain, simple truths.</p>
   <p>But, for once, take our counsel. See that your money is safely invested, or you will weep bitter tears later on.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
