<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-08-11">Aug. 11, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Purchase of a New Building by John Raklios through George Chiagouris's Real Estate Agency</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0035</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0035.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-08-11">Aug. 11, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">PURCHASE OF A NEW BUILDING BY JOHN RAKLIOS THROUGH GEORGE CHIAGOURIS'S REAL ESTATE AGENCY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John Raklios is a well-known businessman and president of Raklios and Company, Incorporated, the organization which maintains some very good restaurants in the Chicago Loop. Mr. George Chicagouris is the head of the well-known real-estate office which has been operating very successfully for a number of years and has rendered many services to the Greek businessmen of Chicago. It is the oldest Greek office of its kind.</p>
   <p>Mr. Raklios is an expert in the art of making money, and Mr. Chiagouris is an expert in changing money to property and property to money. Their first mutual transaction resulted in the successful acquisition of a long-term lease involving more than half a million dollars.</p>
   <p>Their second business venture was the purchase by Mr. Raklios through the agency of Mr. Chiagouris of a three-story building located at the corner of <pb facs="5422062_3_0036.jpg" n="2"/>Wells and Division Streets, with a frontage of a hundred feet on one street and sixty feet on the other.</p>
   <p>Although the value of the lot and the building exceeds $140,000, they were purchased for only $75,000 as the result of Mr. Chiagouris's expert handling of the transaction. There are many indications that a subway station will be located at this corner. Mayor Dever has been making efforts to get the subway started.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
