<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-01-27">Jan. 27, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The New President of the Atlas National Bank.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0042</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0042.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1923-01-27">Jan. 27, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW PRESIDENT OF THE ATLAS NATIONAL BANK.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 3-Yesterday the shareholders of the well-known Atlas National Bank elected a new board of directors and chose as president of the Bank Mr. Peter Gregor, who by his intelligence, sincerity, progressiveness, and industry has qualified himself for office.</p>
   <p>Mr. Gregor is the first Greek immigrant to the United States, to be elected president of a national bank. He was born in the village of Zeugalatio in Mantinias in the year 1884. He graduated from the gymnasium of Tripolis and in the year 1902 matriculated in the school of Philogogy of our National University in Athens. Since he was naturally fond of travel and of leading an adventurous life, he discontinued his studies about a year later and migrated to the United States, coming to Chicago and beginning his career as a simple wage-earner.</p>
   <p>About the year 1907 he took an active part in the foundation of a Greek colony in the State of Alabama, a project conceived by Mr. Jason Malmpis.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0043.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This colony was named Dafni and made astonishing progress, developing into a small city which challenges the admiration of Americans and has been made the subject of study by American socialogists.</p>
   <p>Later Mr. Gregor visited Japan, where he engaged in commerce and acquired a thorough knowledge of the Japanese language. About the year 1918 he was appointed to a position in the Atlas National Bank.</p>
   <p>After a year's service he was elected vice-president, and yesterday he was chosen president to succeed Mr. Healy, who was elected president of the board of directors.</p>
   <p>Saloniki warmly congratulates Mr. Gregor and feels pride the progress of our Chicago Greek colony.</p>
   <p>Directors of the Atlas National Bank for the year 1923.</p>
   <p>Daniel M. Healy, chairman of the board, attorney and banker.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0044.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Peter Gregor, banker</p>
   <p>John Raklios, restaurateur</p>
   <p>Peter A. Rusetos, manufacturer of ice-cream</p>
   <p>George C. Papageorge, physicians</p>
   <p>John Gallanis, confectioner</p>
   <p>Peter Frankos, commission merchant</p>
   <p>T. Frank Quilty, civil engineer and engineering contractor</p>
   <p>M. F. Schiavons, realtor</p>
   <p>Salvatore Sisco, confectioner</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0045.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>B. Pastorelli, merchant</p>
   <p>Officers for the year 1923.</p>
   <p>Peter Gregor, president</p>
   <p>M. F. Schiavons, vice-president</p>
   <p>B. M. Blankenheim, cashier</p>
   <p>Peter Malakates, vice-president</p>
   <p>E. T. Nordholm, assistant cashier.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
