<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-06-06">June 6, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">To Our Brother Ahepans and to Mr. D. Michalopoulos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1696</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1696.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1931-06-06">June 6, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">TO OUR BROTHER AHEPANS AND TO MR. D. MICHALOPOULOS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. D. Michalopoulos, in response to our previous article captioned "To Our Brother," has expressed to us in writing his thanks for our publication of the facts, which proved the lack of organized support to assure the success of Mr. Michalaros's play "Theodora," recently presented on the American stage. On the other hand, however, he attempted in his reply to refute the statement which we had made in the aforementioned article:</p>
   <p>"The majority of the Ahepans failed to realize that as long as all the local chapters of the Order of Ahepa had sponsored the presentation of this play on the American stage, it was their duty to accord their support to make the performance a success."</p>
   <p>Mr. Michalopoulos continues by stating that the officers of the Order of Ahepa are responsible for this lack of co-operation, and that the members are <pb facs="5422062_3_1697.jpg" n="2"/>more than anxious to show their interest and to co-operate, but lack of proper leadership, etc.</p>
   <p>But Mr. Michalopoulos should understand that the outside world, those who are not members of the Order of Ahepa, judges the purpose of the organization by actual results and does not stop to discriminate between the leaders of the order and their lay brethren.</p>
   <p>How the officers of Ahepa are chosen, and how much more progress would have been made if others had been elected, are private matters which should be determined among you, Brother Ahepans.</p>
   <p>When you introduce to the outside world your supreme president, supreme governor, archon megistos, guard, or any other of the distinguished incumbents of your numerous titled offices, it accepts them as such and judges the merits of your Order by their policies and their actual achievements. As the popular adage expresses it, "Like father, like son".</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1698.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>You are asked to give a reason for your selection of these leaders whom you allege to be the cause of the lack of proper co-operation in your organization, but you fail to give a [satisfactory] answer. We can answer that question for you. You elect them because you have no alternative; you have no others to choose from.</p>
   <p>We do not agree, however, that your leaders are responsible for all your errors, or that they are inefficient and incompetent, and I still abide by my simple opinion that outsiders [attach credit or] blame to the Order itself for what it does well or ill, and that it is not the outsider's duty to decide whether it is the fault of the leaders or that of the lay members. The outsider simply blames the organization itself.</p>
   <p>Your contention that "the Ahepans did not arrive from heaven, nor did they attend a special school of learning, and they are of the same origin as any other Greeks," has no bearing on the subject under discussion, which is the organization, for we know that every large [national] organization springs <pb facs="5422062_3_1699.jpg" n="4"/>from the bowels of one race, and that its members are therefore of the same origin as others of that race. But the organizers and founders of good fraternal orders must first be imbued with a spirit of idealism, profess noble principles and high standards, and formulate programs to realize these aspirations with those whom they have chosen as their collaborators, by diligent co-operation achieving the success of their plans and their policies.</p>
   <p>Do we find this true in the Order of Ahepa? Do its organizers profess any principles, ideals, or platform? Do they select the leaders whom they consider fit for the execution of the policies of their organization from the entire mass of the Greeks in America? Do they choose devoted and trusted adherents who ultimately will become the proper leaders of their order?</p>
   <p>You, my dear people, merely take the first fellow who is desirous of becoming an Ahepan, have him undergo certain trials and ordeals at his initiation, when most of you laugh at the candidate's expression of fear and suspense, have him brought before your altar, where he takes an oath to keep inviolate <pb facs="5422062_3_1700.jpg" n="5"/>your fantastic secrets, deck him with a fez, and pronounce him "brother". Then what? In due time you present him with a title such as "captain of the guards," "supreme governor," or "supreme president," and finally you tell us that your shortcomings are not the fault of the Order but are due to the incapacity of its officers! Are the officers to blame when without forethought you bestow upon your members the titles of "marshal," "megistos," and so on down the list?</p>
   <p>Your reference to the Order of Ahepa as an organization of which the members may be classed as lions, and the officers as donkeys, has not the slightest bearing on the topic under discussion. On the contrary, it proves that the Order of Ahepa has neither purpose nor leadership. Who does the enlisting of the lionhearted Ahepans? Some of the older members, certain leaders; and what are their motives?</p>
   <p>Here lies the solution of the mystery of your grievance and our misunderstanding, the grievance of those members of the Order of Ahepa who earnestly desire <pb facs="5422062_3_1701.jpg" n="6"/>to see Ahepa conceive, and carry out a definite program, and the misunderstanding likewise of those outside the Order who believe that the organization does have a fixed goal or aim.</p>
   <p>When the time arrives, however, when every one realizes that the Order of Ahepa is devoid of principle or purpose, then matters will arrive at their normal status, and the misunderstanding will cease to exist.</p>
   <p>By your final contention, Mr. Michalopoulos, that the Order of Ahepa is still young, that it has not been long since the organization was established, and that it should be given more time, you demonstrate that you are under the impression that the Order is a mere infant. Permit me to say to you, Mr. Michalopoulos, and to the other Ahepans that your Order has already graduated from the period of infancy, and that it is already time that it be shelved. It would have had before this numerous offspring in the way of results if it had possessed a consort, that is, a purpose. As a matter of fact, it did have a consort, but the consort has disappeared. By that I mean that at the time <pb facs="5422062_3_1702.jpg" n="7"/>of the foundation of the Order, it did have an aim which was popular to all, namely, to defend its members from the assaults and the persecution of the Ku Klux Klan. However, after this danger was averted, the Order was left without a purpose, and ever since it has been trying to discover one, and hence the misunderstandings both among members and among those outside the organization.</p>
   <p>Do not blame the short term of its existence for the lack of proper leadership; blame the fact that the Order is without principle or purpose.</p>
   <p>Therefore I do not agree that you have not the proper leadership; the fact is that you have no definite purpose. Every individual Ahepan, every group of Ahepans, has a different conception of the purpose of the Order. Be also assured that it is not definitely determined even among the members themselves whether Ahepa is a Hellenic institution aiming at the support of Greek ideals or an American institution aiming at the support of American ideals. Every individual member is desirous of having the organization abide by his own <pb facs="5422062_3_1703.jpg" n="8"/>standards and methods of conduct. But hard as you may attempt to disguise your Order as a Greek organization, and the majority of its members still believe it to be such, Ahepa is an American institution, for at the time of its foundation it was such, and it still continues to be such.</p>
   <p>We will discuss the reason why Ahepa is devoid of definite aim or purpose further in our ensuing article, and we welcome any refutation of our contention by any of our readers.</p>
   <p>In conclusion we wish to state to our dear Ahepans that by our contention that Ahepa has no goal or purpose we do not mean that the Order must cease to exist. On the contrary, we have always been staunch supporters of the organization. By what we have written in our columns in the past, judge the assertions which we have just made, and in what we shall write in the future we aim to clarify certain matters which remain a mystery both to the members and to non-members of the Order of Ahepa, and we hope that by our doing so the organization will be improved.</p>
   <p>The Contradictor</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
