<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1930-03-15">Mar, 15, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Tatanis in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1016</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1016.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1930-03-15">Mar, 15, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">MR. TATANIS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The prominent members of the Greek community in Chicago vie with one another for the honor of entertaining the distinguished visitor from New York, R. Tatanis, Publisher of the National Herald, a Greek daily of New York, reaching every state and city of America.</p>
   <p>The popular and prominent lawyer, Paul Demos, gave a dinner in honor of Mr. Tatanis at the Hamilton Club. John Raklios, president of Raklios and Co., gave a symposium at the Medinah Club, and John Papanastasiou entertained in his palatial residence.</p>
   <p>Others gave sumptuous dinners. Among these were Nikitas Nomikos and William Karzas.</p>
   <p>At the various symposiums the elite of the Greek community participated. Some of them are Messrs. T. Chamalis, A.Karagianis, A. Johnson, Basil Kotsonis, Mike Cherigos, K. Theodorou, Nicholaos Ganas, Andrew Chronis, Th. Valos, Geo. Becharas, Paul Javaras, P. Bougas, Nicholas Vasilopoulos, D. Michalopoulos, S. Partheniou,K. Granias, G. Kontos and the publisher of Saloniki.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1017.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The distinguished visitor, whose patriotic and philanthropic famous articles are read by 500,000 Greeks in America, left the city very much impressed by the social and commercial progress of the Chicago Greek Community. He expressed a sincere desire to make a longer stay the next time he came.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
