<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-02-16">Feb. 16, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Exposure of a Greek Publication in Chicag</title><title level="a" type="sub">Deceiving the People for Gain</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1211</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1211.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-02-16">Feb. 16, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">EXPOSURE OF A GREEK PUBLICATION IN CHICAG</title><title level="a" type="sub">Deceiving the People for Gain</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2- In its last issue the other Chicago Greek newspaper, Hellas, publishes something which shows very clearly the incompetence of this publication. It says, "The Greek Minister of the Interior ( called Secretary in the U. S.' Government has requested Hellas to compile statistics of the Greek element living in the States of Illinois and California. We therefore request all fellow-Greeks, especially businessmen of the two aforesaid States, to report to our offices their names, their addresses, what kind of business they are engaged in, how long a time they have lived in America, and what part of Greece they came from."</p>
   <p>The Star, as guardian of the Greeks in America, has applied its common sense to the consideration of this unusual, unpractical, and anomalous procedure with the following results. According to Hellas's statement the Minister of the Interior has undertaken to function as Minister of Affairs (Secretary of State), a thing which it is not proper for the <pb facs="5422062_3_1212.jpg" n="2"/>Minister of the Interior to do. We also observe that the Greek Minister of the Interior did not, as he ought to have done, address the Greek consuls of the two States, who are the proper persons and the officials duly qualified to compile the statistics requested. You see the anomaly of the whole affair. Our common sense tells us that such procedure is unusual, improper, and without precedent.</p>
   <p>In order to confute our reasoning and to compel the Star to discontinue its commonsense method of procedure, our sister journal is asked to publish the purported request of the Minister of the Interior. This will never be done, for no such request was sent to the Chicago Greek newspaper by any constituted authority in Greece.</p>
   <p>And we venture to say, again applying our common-sense logic, that our sister journal is fishing for business, hastening to add that this is a very poor journalistic method of doing it. The Star for the sake of decency urges Hellas to discontinue such methods of deception, for otherwise its disqualification as a reliable newspaper will ensue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
