<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-12-26">Dec. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Greek-American Bank Fixtures to Be Sold at Auction</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0178</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0178.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1914-12-26">Dec. 26, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">GREEK-AMERICAN BANK FIXTURES TO BE SOLD AT AUCTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was decided by Judge Eastman and Mr. Zibell that the tangible property of the Greek-American Bank of Chicago should be sold at auction. The notice of sale was posted on the door of the bankrupt bank on the corner of Halsted and Blue Island Avenues.</p>
   <p>A week ago a different notice was attached to the closed doors. It announced to the public that the bank and all its fixtures were for rent--if anyone felt capable of opening another bank for the Chicago Greeks. It seems, however, that no one has evinced any desire to enter the banking business, and for that reason the rental sign has been displaced by a "for sale" sign.</p>
   <p>To become a banker a large capital is necessary; and we know of no one, except our four banker friends, who owns enough to become one.</p>
   <p>However, even these gentlemen have abandoned the profession. Mr. Rifakis has <pb facs="5422062_3_0179.jpg" n="2"/>left the banking business forever, and Mr. Geokaris has opened magnificent offices on Dearborn Street, where he sells travel tickets as an agent for the Greek Steamship Lines of New York City.....</p>
   <p>Therefore there is no one left to reopen the Greek Bank. The action of the court was very wise under the circumstances. The Greeks of Chicago are quite relieved to know that they no longer have bankers and banks to worry about.</p>
   <p>Of course the loss is a great one. We are very sorry that the committee of depositors--which presented such an impressive plea--was not able to force the bankers to keep the bank open, in order that the depositors could receive all their money back. The Atlantis published a statement defending the integrity of these four men, who said that they would repay dollar for dollar the money deposited in the Bank. Both we and the Atlantis were aware of the falseness of this statement. We exposed these men--but the Atlantis published their statement in order to fool the public. It is obvious that the integrity of this newspaper and that of the bankers is cut from the same cloth.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0180.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Now let us cease our consideration of the bankers and the deceitful newspaper editors who help them, and see what can be done to correct the wrongs already committed. Of course some of our readers will laugh, others will sneer, and still others will criticize us for daring to cast aspersions upon such fine citizens and such respected journalists.</p>
   <p>We do not care. Each person has a right to think just as he chooses. And we reserve the right to print the truth about these bankrupt money grabbers and the journalists that defend them. This is not done to insult any person or to get revenge. It is merely an attempt to tell the common people the true facts, which are being hidden from them.</p>
   <p>Of the eight hundred depositors who lost their savings, seven hundred and ninety are hard-working laborers. They had gone to the Greek Bank because of their limited knowledge of English, and felt safer when they heard and spoke their <pb facs="5422062_3_0181.jpg" n="4"/>mother tongue. It is these poor people whom the Saloniki desires to help.</p>
   <p>If the eight hundred investors had been businessmen who were familiar with the language and laws of this country, the matter would be entirely different. Then the Saloniki would not be the only one to raise a protesting voice. If these people were influential a deafening clamor for justice would be heard on all sides. Unfortunately they are simple, poor people and no one takes very much interest in their sad plight.</p>
   <p>The shame of it is that the few educated depositors went around making speeches to their fellow depositors and influenced them to sign releases. They were aided by certain unscrupulous journalists who hid the true facts; and as a result the bankers have been declared innocent. In fact they complain of the ill usage which they have suffered.</p>
   <p>If the educated Greeks of Chicago had taken a greater interest the situation would not be so intolerable. Nothing can be done now because on January 12 <pb facs="5422062_3_0182.jpg" n="5"/>the property goes under the auctioneer's gavel.</p>
   <p>We shout our accusations in the ears of those who declared that every dollar on deposit would be returned intact. What do they think now? How about the depositors who persuaded the more ignorant to sign papers which they did not understand?</p>
   <p>We have not given up, despite the hopeless aspects of this situation. As soon as the auction takes place we shall again take up the cudgels and fight for justice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
