<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1906-08-24">Aug. 24, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">A Word to the Greek Confectioners of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Star</title>,
<date when="1906-08-24">Aug. 24, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD TO THE GREEK CONFECTIONERS OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One out of every four Greeks living in Chicago is in business of some kind, but the Greek confectioner predominates among Greek business men with the restaurateur second.</p>
   <p>The great majority of our Greek business men have never been in business before. Practically every line of business in which the Greek is now engaged is new to him. But his innate spirit of progressiveness has made it easy for him to open his eyes and learn a lesson or two from the American business man. Because of the Greek's facility in learning his incomparable assiduity and persistence he soon makes himself noteworthy in the business world. This is all very well.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0298.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Greek has acquired from the American business man certain ideas conducive to prosperity, but either because of his eagerness for accomplishment or because of his arrogance he has failed to adopt the wonderful system of the American business man, which includes incessant publicity, honesty in all transactions, both with customers and with business houses, and the establishment of credit. This does not imply that the Greek business man is not honest. Far from it. He certainly is honest. But his honesty is not known to business houses, and his credit is not established with the Business Men's Credit Association with the exceptions of a very few Greek merchants.</p>
   <p>The majority of Greek business men buy for cash. Their names are not registered in the credit departments of business houses. And worst of all they frequently give evasive answers and refuse to declare the value of their concerns to the investigators of the Business Men's Credit Association lest the facts become known to their competitors. What foolish notions they cherish! They avoid the thing most useful for expanding their business.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0299.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Greek confectioners in Chicago because of their great numbers and the tremendous business which they do have untold power in their hands, whether they know it or not. Such power and such influence, if properly and wisely used, will bring honor and credit to them and to the Greek community and will enhance the reputation of Greeks in general. And the way to use this great power properly and wisely is very simple: Americanize yourselves, your thoughts, and your system of conducting your business! Very simple, if you are willing to do it. Add to the gifts which you already possess the three simple but effective elements of the American system; advertising, honesty in all dealing, and establishing credit in the commercial world so that everybody will known who is who.</p>
   <p>Those confectioners who are not as yet members of the recently organized Association of their trade will help themselves and the Greek community by joining it, attending its meetings, and inviting eminent American business men to deliver lectures to this young organization.</p>
   <p>You Greek confectioners, have great power at your command. Use this power wisely.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0300.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Captains of industry and of business and all others will salute you if you will add to your equipment for business the three things needful , above mentioned.</p>
   <p>It is absolutely necessary to live to think and to act as Americans while you live in America and make your living among American people.</p>
   <p>Establish your credit, pay your bills promptly, advertise your business, mingle with American business men, attend their lectures, and plan for the future. Then nobody will be able to compete with you in your business.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
