<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-11-24">Nov. 24, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Greeks and Americans Will Appreciate the Byzantine Ensemble</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1273</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1273.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1932-11-24">Nov. 24, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">GREEKS AND AMERICANS WILL APPRECIATE THE BYZANTINE ENSEMBLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Starting Sunday, November 27th, at 4:00 P.M. over Station WIBO radio fans will hear something novel and unique, yet as ancient as Rome and Greece.</p>
   <p>The Byzantine Ensemble, under the musical direction of Marion Schroeder Booras will begin a series of seven week half hour broadcasts over W I B O, thus instituting what is called by the managers of the Station "A Radio Music Carnival of Byzantine Peoples".</p>
   <p>At each one of these afternoon musical radio concerts, a representative from one Byzantine nation will appear to talk for a three minute period. The first one is the Honorable George De Pasta, Consul General of Greece.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1274.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Outside of the general music festivities that the Byzantine Ensemble is preparing for the radio fans, it will also present a most novel and unique instrument, being the only instrument used as accompaniment to the weird and sensual music that they sing and at the same time the oldest instrument known to the music world.</p>
   <p>Sanduri is the name of this 140 string instrument and Spiro Stamos, Musical Arranger for the Byzantine Ensemble, plays it.</p>
   <p>The Byzantine Ensemble was founded by Nick John Matsoukas who for the last two years has been working on the nation that the Olympian Gods have decreed that even Midwestern Americans should get a touch of their gift to the world, their music. He is also the manager for this group.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
