<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1918-03-23">Mar. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Gala Greek Artistic Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0380</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0380.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-03-23">Mar. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">GALA GREEK ARTISTIC CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, March 31 at 8:30 P. M. the brilliant and famed young Greek tenor, Mr. Andrew Petropoulos, or Andrew De Parry, will give a musical concert in the magnificent Kimball Hall, 308 South Wabash Avenue, at the corner of Jackson Boulevard. Mr. De Parry has done honor to the Greek name in Egypt, America, and elsewhere. A descendant of the great historic Bokos family, members of which were naval commanders during our Sacred War for Independence, he is the son of the well-known captain of the Panhellenic Steamship Company. He studied in Italy, and he gives vocal music lessons here. He is not related to Constantine Petropoulos, so let there be no confusion in regards to the two names. Although he is proud of his Greek origin, he has adopted the name De Parry. In this concert he will be accompanied by the well-known pianist in the musical world, Dr. Balatka. He will have other violinists and vocal artists of the opera with him.</p>
   <p>Admission is one dollar; many tickets have been disposed of among our people as well as among the American public.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0381.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>So the occasion will be highly interesting and a patriotic one if we rally to hear him presenting his excellent musical program. By attending this affair we will be entertained and will support an able young man worthy of every consideration. Thus, we are also supporting our musicians.</p>
   <p>Saloniki congratulates Mr. De Parry and wishes him success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
