<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1927-02">Feb., 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Minutes of the Twenty-Eighth General Meeting of the Greek Club Pontus of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1462</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1462.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Democrat</title>,
<date when="1927-02">Feb., 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE MINUTES OF THE TWENTY-EIGHTH GENERAL MEETING OF THE GREEK CLUB PONTUS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2.- This brilliant and educational meeting took place at the residence of the past president, Mr. Nick Mason, at 1746 Lawrence Avenue, January 9, 1927, at 4 o'clock in the afternoon, under the chairmanship of the president, T. M. Bishop.</p>
   <p>Disposing of the business part of the program first of all, the president then introduced Mr. G. A. Kyriakopoulos, a prominent attorney and assistant prosecuting attorney of our city, to the members and guestsas the speaker of the day. Mr. Kyriakopoulos spoke very efficiently for a whole hour on the subject of "The Kingdom of Pontus."</p>
   <p>Once again Mr. G. Kyriakopoulos proved to be a born historian. He held his audience in such a fervor and astonishment that they expressed the desire of having him join the club and enjoy the privilege of his companionship.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1463.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The speaker was good enough to answer all questions asked following his speech.</p>
   <p>The club was also honored with the presence of the following guests: Messrs. John D. Morton, Th. Kalpakis, and Christ J. Pallas, all from the AHEPA, North Shore Chapter No. 94.</p>
   <p>The following were then officially initiated for membership: Messrs. E. Castritsis, S. Photiades and J. Sphondouris.</p>
   <p>After the singing of the Pontus Song, the meeting was then adjourned and refreshments were served by the hostess.</p>
   <p>T. M. Bishop.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
