<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-06-23">June 23, 1928</date>, P. 1
<title level="a">The Lecture of Mr. G. Frankoudes.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1452</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1452.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1928-06-23">June 23, 1928</date>, P. 1
<title level="a">THE LECTURE OF MR. G. FRANKOUDES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. G. Frankoudes gave a lecture, the other day, under the auspices of Ahepa, to a select audience.</p>
   <p>Mr. A. Pantelis acting as chairman, introduced Mr. Frankoudes. The subject "The Regeneration of Greece" whose fate it was to die and to rise again from its own ashes was wonderfully developed.</p>
   <p>Mr. Frankoudes related in a brief review how Greece was subjugated by the Romans how it was regenerated in the Byzantine Empire, and after having been enslaved by the Turks, was reborn through the struggles of 1821.</p>
   <p>He touched briefly on the Asia Minor catastrophe, offering one point of consolation only: the concentration of all Greeks within the boundaries of Greece, the results of which is the complete Hellenization of Macedonia.</p>
   <p>He dwelt at length on the political madness of Greece which he attributed to lack of education and training. He blamed all government administrations for negligence on this question.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1453.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He pointed out as the only hope of salvation, the establishment of a large political school for the building up of character first, and for the instilling of the ideals of Hellenism,secondly.</p>
   <p>This school, must not be under the management of the State, if it is to prosper and fulfill its mission.</p>
   <p>In spite of the political maladministration in Greece, Mr. Frankoudes is optimistic for its future. "It will suffice", he said, "for the citizens to rise in a peaceful revolution, not against the status quo, but against corruption and the methods used by the politicians there."</p>
   <p>This necessity must be felt deeply by every Greek who should reform himself and show greater interest in politics.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
