<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Greek Star</title>,
<date when="1907-11-22">Nov. 22, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">The Greeks of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1489</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1489.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Star</title>,
<date when="1907-11-22">Nov. 22, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREEKS OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, a lecture series, which had been previously announced, was given in the splendid auditorium of Hull House. This patriotic lecture series was sponsored by the rapidly expanding and progressive Greek Macedonian Society. The affair was a complete success.</p>
   <p>There was a brilliant galaxy of speakers, all of whom were enthusiastically applauded by the great crowd. Some of the speakers were: Messrs. John Palamaras, Doctor Nicholas Salopoulos, who illustrated his talk with motion-picture projections, Attorney George Kyriacopoulos, George Matalas, Demosthenes Eutaxias, the brilliant journalist, and Van Gregoropoulos, a distinguished man of letters from Athens, who is visiting with us. The latter recited a dialogue in verse entitled, "Hellas-Macedonia". The poem was rendered in a dramatic and inspired tone of voice characteristic of a true poet. Because of lack of space, we cannot publish the text.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1490.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are greatly pleased to write about the success of this lecture. And we are in the enviable position to praise the remarkable zeal and enthusiasm of those who organized this splendid intellectual treat. The spontaneous response of more than four hundred of our countrymen who supported this cause must also be highly commended. We hope that the time is not far distant when we will give more evidence of the patriotism and loyalty of the Greeks of Chicago.</p>
   <p>This newly established organization, the Greek Macedonian Society, is the sacred altar and the holy tabernacle of the Greek Community of Chicago, before and in which we must pay humble homage.</p>
   <p>For the benefit of those who did not attend the lecture, we would like to inform the public of the nature of subjects which were discussed. Mr. John Palamaras presided over the symposium. The Greek Consul, Dr. Nicholas Salopoulos, spoke about the fallen heroes of Macedonia, giving a wonderful and inspiring account of the heroic exploits of Greece's guerrilla bands fighting against the <pb facs="5422062_3_1491.jpg" n="3"/>Bulgarians. The picture slides which were projected on the screen were very interesting. Mr. George Kyriacopoulos gave a sweeping and thrilling account of the long and adventurous history of the Byzantine Empire. Mr. George Matalas spoke on the history of Macedonia from the time of Alexander the Great to the present, when Greece, Serbia, Bulgaria, and Turkey have racial and historical claims on this important key Balkan area. Mr. Demosthenes Eutaxias spoke on the subject of "Oaths and True Greek Patrotism". As we mentioned before, Mr. Van Gregoropoulos offered several excellent patriotic recitations.</p>
   <p>Let us hope that the Society will establish a precedent by arranging educational and patriotic lectures on many subjects, which will undoubtedly benefit the people of this community. Our educated classes, the members of the professions, and our numerous intellectuals should contribute to the cultural and educational advancement of our people by means of frequent lectures.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
