<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1911-02-04">Feb. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Many Mistakes of the Greek Press in America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1143</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1143.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1911-02-04">Feb. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE MANY MISTAKES OF THE GREEK PRESS IN AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Greek Community of our city acquitted itself admirably last Sunday at the reception given for Spyros Matsoukas. We had been waiting for him a long time, and, when he finally came, our enthusiasm was unquenchable.</p>
   <p>More elated were we when we heard that he has sent, in his 18 months, here, over $103,000 home to Greece. He raised $103,000 from the Greeks of America and he sent $103,000 to Greece. He is working, without any personal gain to himself, for the cause of Greece.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1144.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Greek press in America has dubbed him a thief, a liar, a usurper, etc., but if this were so, would he send $103,000 of the $103,000 to Greece? Wouldn't he keep a goodly portion for himself? Would he be working so hard among so many obstacles if he weren't the genuine thing?</p>
   <p>That is only one mistake of the Greek press. Among our Greek newspapers the Atlantis collects $70,000 annually from subscribers, the Pan Hellenic collects $40,000, the Athena $5,000, and Immigrant $2,500, making a total of $117,500 a year or $235,000 in two years' time.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1145.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Greeks of America, we are throwing $235,000 away every two years to worthless newspapers. Of that $235,000, how much was sent to Greece? How much was used to improve the Greeks of America? How much was used to preserve Hellenism? None!</p>
   <p>The press says that it does much good for the Greeks of America and should be paid accordingly. What has the press done?</p>
   <p>1. Has it cooperated to solve the immigration problem?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1146.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>2. Has it shown the young people how to become systemized in their occupations?</p>
   <p>3. Has it ever helped the church?</p>
   <p>4. Has it been used to find employment for our countrymen?</p>
   <p>5. Has it ever tried to build a hospital for the ignorant Greeks who cannot speak English?</p>
   <p>6. Has it explained the Greek religion to its readers so the common people can understand it?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1147.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>7. Has it told the 3,000 Greek merchants how to unite and become more progressive?</p>
   <p>8. Has it said anything about church officials who rob the poor of their last cent by promising them a holy blessing?</p>
   <p>9. In a community of 25,000 Greeks, has it tried to establish a gymnasium, or club rooms, or a school for the younger people?</p>
   <p>10. Has it tried to explain American politics and the duty of voters to the uneducated Greeks?</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1148.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>11. Has it told them what patriotism and duty is?</p>
   <p>12. Has it tried to naturalize them?</p>
   <p>These are only twelve mistakes of the Greek press in America. $235,000 bi-annually is a lot to pay to people who make such costly mistakes. Wake up, countrymen!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
