<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-03-23">Mar. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Real-Estate and Investment Business Among the Greek People of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1918-03-23">Mar. 23, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">REAL-ESTATE AND INVESTMENT BUSINESS AMONG THE GREEK PEOPLE OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Saloniki is proud of the business and financial genius and activities of those of our nationality who are engaged in industry or business. From time to time we will endeavor to write about the progress and attainments of the most important and noteworthy Greek commercial, industrial, and financial establishments. The extent and development of our economic life in America, and in Chicago in particular, is an index of and must of necessity precede any cultural, educational, religious, and generally social accomplishments and degree of prosperity.</p>
   <p>Today we are happy to give a short account of the real-estate and investment company of George P. Chiagouris and Company.</p>
   <p>This company is one of the first and oldest Greek companies of its kind. On arriving in America some years ago, Mr. George P. Chiagouris conceived <pb facs="5422062_3_0091.jpg" n="2"/>of the idea of organizing a business and financial concern, similar to the American real-estate and investment companies of offices, which would meet the needs and requirements of Greek business. He foresaw the rapid and marvelous expansion of Greek enterprise and business activity and forthwith began to sell and buy real estate of every kind, to rent properties, and engage in nearly all the various financial activities.</p>
   <p>The most important departments of this real-estate and investment company are the following:</p>
   <p>1. The Rental Department where buildings, stores, shops, and homes are rented.</p>
   <p>2. The Sales Department where business properties, stores, shops, homes, apartment houses, and lots are sold.</p>
   <p>3. The Loan Department--in this department loans are made by mortgaging properties, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0092.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>4. The Building and Repair Department where nearly every kind of building and store is built or repaired.</p>
   <p>5. Managing Department where all sorts of tangible property are managed for a small fee.</p>
   <p>6. Insurance Department where any kind of insurance is issued in cooperation with the greatest insurance companies of America.</p>
   <p>7. Bond and Mortgage Department.</p>
   <p>8. Legal Department where any type of legal service is given in regard to bills of sale, mortgages, leases, notes, partnership agreements, trusts, etc.</p>
   <p>This company transacts business with all the real-estate, investment, <pb facs="5422062_3_0093.jpg" n="4"/>and insurance companies in the Loop, and employs many able and experienced American salesmen, brokers, and real-estate experts.</p>
   <p>The George P. Chiagouris Real-Estate and Investment Company is located at 127 North Dearborn Street, suites 1611-1616, in the Unity Building.</p>
   <p>We congratulate Mr. Chiagouris and his partners and sincerely hope that the Greek businessmen, investors, and property owners will avail themselves of the services of this fine company.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
