<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1929-09-21">Sept. 21, 1929</date><title level="a">The Picnic of the Stereoladitans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1753</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1753.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1929-09-21">Sept. 21, 1929</date><title level="a">THE PICNIC OF THE STEREOLADITANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 6.- The Stereoladitans of our community long ago organized themselves into a Society. They held their first picnic last Sunday, at which they presented to us, in the most emphatic way, a native festival.</p>
   <p>"Fustanella" (white Greek kilt) and sandals and fez with tasels, and peasant dresses with aprons of blue and green colors swayed this way and that during their dances, while the "Splin-Andero", "Cocoretsi," and the tender milk fed, roasted and barbecued lambs were beckoning the appetites of the numerous visitors present at the picnic in which such national expression of our people took place.</p>
   <p>The good weather with which the picnic was favored, the presentation of dances in native costumes, the repayment of their obligation in the form of a visit on the part of "Moraitaes" to the "Stereoladitans", so helped to gather a large crowd that "Cocoretsi" and "Splin-Andero" ran short quicker than was expected. But the abundance of roast lamb and especially <pb facs="5422062_3_1754.jpg" n="2"/>the hearty welcome of the organizers, and the ladies dressed in peasant costumes were helping to make the picnic a pleasant one.</p>
   <p>The Greek Dances</p>
   <p>The Greek dances were given with much grace and the women and men were competing in the skill of dancing. The spectacle, especially of the ladies dressed in Greek costumes, incited the admiration of all.</p>
   <p>Among the many who were present at this beautiful picnic were Mr. Manos and the attorney-at-law, Mr. G. Gikas, wearing their Greek "Fustanellas". The President of the organization, with his Counselors, A. Patrinos and B. Bouramas, welcomed the crowd.</p>
   <p>The picnic of the "Stereoladitans" left the best of impressions and it will serve as the best example to other Greek national organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
