<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1908-07-22">July 22, 1908</date><title level="a">The Greek Restaurants</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0275</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0275.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Loxias</title>,
<date when="1908-07-22">July 22, 1908</date><title level="a">THE GREEK RESTAURANTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.- This week we have decided to write on the Greek restaurants in our city which certainly need a little help if they wish to maintain and enlarge their position. They must learn to have "system" in their business or all their efforts will be lost.</p>
   <p>The first thing needed in opening a restaurant, of course, is capital. That is not hard to get, but once a man gets it all his worries begin. In opening a restaurant, he must know his business, be always on the job, and in years to come he may make a successful living in this land to which Fate has brought him.</p>
   <p>This doesn't sound hard or complicated and it isn't, if there is a system in the way a store is run. The proprietor must be careful of waste and overhead expense.</p>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0276.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In Chicago there are many Greek restaurants. They have lights, meats, vegetables, stoves, tables and chairs, but they do not seem to progress. This is because they lack something--system. The Greeks are far behind in this respect. On Monday their bill of fare reads: Steak, 25¢; on Tuesday it is 20¢, and on Wednesday it is 15¢. This is no way to do business.</p>
   <p>Why should a restaurateur make such a loss on Tuesday and Wednesday, when he sells the same steaks he sells on Monday? Why should he work hard day and night just to meet his expenses? There seem to be plenty of customers in all the restaurants for the proprietors to make huge profits.</p>
   <p>Although not in the restaurant business, we believe the answer is simple. A restaurateur does not relax. If he goes home to nap for an hour, he finds that his competitor across the street or next door has lowered prices and taken away his business. Why do they do this? Do they think <pb facs="5422062_3_0277.jpg" n="3"/>that by lowering prices they can make more money? Can't they see that they are ruining their own chances along with their neighbors?</p>
   <p>The other nationalities in Chicago are laughing at this child's play the Greeks are conducting. They will keep on laughing until the Greeks wake up and put system in their business.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
