<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-07-16">July 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Founding of a Greek Medical Association.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Need of Co-operation Among Greek Professional Men. (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_0976</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_0976.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Greek Daily</title>,
<date when="1927-07-16">July 16, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE FOUNDING OF A GREEK MEDICAL ASSOCIATION.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Need of Co-operation Among Greek Professional Men. (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.. The Greek physicians of our community got together the day before yesterday to found a Greek Medical Association for the purpose of exchanging scientific information and clinical observations, a step which proves that our professional men do not confine their attention to their practice but keep in touch with the progress of science, closely watching all new developments pertaining to their professions.</p>
   <p>But the most pleasing inference to be drawn from the organization of this society is that since this is the first time that Greek doctors have even got together in co-operation, much good may be expected to accrue.</p>
   <p>Co-operation among Greek physicians will result in a more exhaustive study of the problems which confront them. Moreover, such co-operation, such a manifestation of mutual helpfulness, inspires the respect of the public not only <pb facs="5422062_3_0977.jpg" n="2"/>for the Greek physicians but for all Hellenism. Greek professional men in all fields would do well to follow their example.</p>
   <p>It is about time for our fellow-countrymen, many of whom patronize professional men who are not Greeks, to realize that trained men of Greek origin are fully as competent as those of any other nationality. In fact, we do not hesitate to say that to judge by some of the professional men of other races who are retained by our compatriots, Greek professional men are even superior to many others from the scientific point of view. More than that, the Greeks serve their clients more conscientiously and invite the informality and frankness which are possible only among people of the same nationality.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, however, many of our fellow-countrymen nevertheless continue to remain in the dark as to the real worth of Greek men with professional training. They prefer strangers, imagining that Greeks lag behind in scientific knowledge and in expierience.</p>
   <p>This belief is without foundation in fact but it has been current for many years. It is a great misfortune that nothing has been done to combat it. We believe that it is about time to explain the facts of this matter to American-Hellenism, inasmuch as the Greek professional men themselves have never sought <pb facs="5422062_3_0978.jpg" n="3"/>to intrude upon their compatriots not to advertise the fact that instead of lagging behind those of other races they are often superior to them. Highly competent Greek physicians are found in all branches of the medical profession; able surgeons, heart specialists, throat specialists, and chiropractors offer their highly skilled services to all their fellow-countrymen who require medical attention.</p>
   <p>Congratulations to our doctors for founding their scientific association, and we wish them success in their aims! By their co-operation they inspire greater confidence in our fellow-countrymen and thereby offer stronger inducement for employing their professional services.</p>
   <p>S. Kotakis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
