<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Saloniki-Greek Press</title>,
<date when="1922-09-02">Sept. 2, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Coraes, Greek-American School on the South Side</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422062_3_1318</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-greek #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-20">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422062_3_1318.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GREEK</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Saloniki</title>,
<date when="1922-09-02">Sept. 2, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE CORAES, GREEK-AMERICAN SCHOOL ON THE SOUTH SIDE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Registration at the Greek-American School, Coraes, begins on September first and continues until the fifth of September. Regular classes start on the next day. This year the school will operate under a new plan and new methods.</p>
   <p>There have been several radical changes. In our endeavor to make our school comparable to the American schools, we have spent a considerable amount of money to establish and equip a children's school library. We have also ordered various school apparatus and instruments. The rich collection of school books with which our new library is equipped will arouse the children's interest and provoke initiative in reading instructive as well as entertaining books.</p>
   <p>Among the school instruments, the powerful electric picture and screen projector will make instruction in geography, physics, biology, etc. <pb facs="5422062_3_1319.jpg" n="2"/>most attractive and interesting.</p>
   <p>New and important subjects, such as hygiene, ethics, civics, etc., have been added to the curriculum.</p>
   <p>We have hired an American teacher who is a University of Chicago graduate and an experienced pedagogue. These innovations are attributed to the special efforts and ability of the new school principal, Mr. George Papanicolopoulos, who has specialized in and studied education at the University of Chicago. He intends to deliver a series of lectures to the parents.</p>
   <p>Evening classes, from 7:00--9:00 P.M., will be offered to the older pupils who are attending American schools during the day. The night school will be carried on on the basis of new methods in curriculum and teaching technique. Registration opens on September 1.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
