<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-03-08">March 8, 1899</date><title level="a">Flase Prophets Editoria:</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0478</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0478.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-03-08">March 8, 1899</date><title level="a">Flase Prophets Editoria:</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the first year's office tenure, President Grant suggested the annexation of Santo Domingo, and he knew more about it, than do our present Imperialists in regard to the Philippines. And, irrespective of this knowledge, he erred in his judgement. It is worth while to peruse these former statements as it shows the true value of the assertions we hear today - and interesting, to note the arguments, which furnished the foundation for the annexation plans at that time.</p>
   <p>Grant's written message to Congress: "Santo Domingo is a small power; it has less than 120,000 inhabitants, yet it is one of the richest regions under the sun, a territory where ten million could live in plenty. The people of Santo Domingo are incapable of supporting themselves under present conditions, and it must seek foreign assistance. They are desirous of sharing the protection of our free institutions, progress, liberal laws and civilization. Should we deny it to them? According to information which I consider reliable, it is said that a European power is prepared to pay Two million dollars for the possession of Samana Bay, if we should decline it. What rights have we (after such a relinquishment) to prevent a foreign nation from acquiring such a valuable prize?"</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0479.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Undoubtedly, Grant wrote in accordance with his belief. Now, nearly three decades have elapsed and every word proved to be a fallacy. The people of Santo Domingo have been neither anxious nor willing to be annexed; it required no foreign support; no foreign nation clamored for the precious prize or offered a single cent. If, in spite of all the predictions, the weak people of Domingo with their limited culture, maintained their independence and self-sufficiency, then what will prevent the Cubans, the population of Porto Rico, the Filipinos, from acting similarly and govern according to their own discretion?</p>
   <p>T he empty, inane assumption, that we must reach for it, otherwise others will grab it, deserves no more serious consideration today than it required formerly. And William McKinley is not a prophet, nor the descendant of one, He belongs in the same category as Ulysses S. Grant.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
