<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-08-04">Aug. 4, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Sewer Gas</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0919</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0919.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-08-04">Aug. 4, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">SEWER GAS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the time of the scarlet fever epidemic, two years ago, when so many died in Chicago, we called attention to the badly constructed sewers, which permit seepage and escape of sewer gas into even our finest homes. The board of health has been very active in ameliorating conditions by compelling property owners to make the needed repairs or improvements wherever sewer gas was apparent. However, it seems necessary to go to the root of the evil.</p>
   <p>As the city has authority to enforce building specifications, it is obvious that certain regulations can be drafted to prevent faulty sewer construction. No permit for a new building should be issued unless a sewer plan is submitted. A competent official should then make an investigation, and inspect the pipes before they are put into the ground.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0920.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Only in this manner will it be possible to avoid a repetition of the awful experiences we have had.</p>
   <p>Pipes which were badly connected caused entire blocks to become fever breeding places and, when basements were dug into, it was found that the soil was contaminated--just a filthy mess. Badly constructed sewers cause the gas to seep into even our finest homes, bringing sickness and death. The old story about looking the barn after the horse is stolen ought to be a thing of the past.</p>
   <p>It is not improper for the authorities to interfere in building construction in order to prevent sickness or pestilence.</p>
   <p>The plumbers to whom the installation of sewer pipes is usually entrusted are a conniving lot, and whatever labor they perform is usually hidden by the subsequent work of the carpenters or bricklayers; if no thorough inspection is required, the temptation to be careless is almost irresistible. If sloppy work merely caused constant repairs and expense, then the problem could be left <pb facs="5418474_6_0921.jpg" n="3"/>to the property owner, but when the health, and even the life, of the community are jeopardized, then it is just as much of a duty for the city to act as in the case of unsafe buildings.</p>
   <p>Ventilation is also an important matter, and should be subject to inspection. It was shown recently that the cold air intake of a residential building was improperly located, so that, when the furnace was in operation, sewer gas circulated through the building.</p>
   <p>That the law permits such criminal negligence and fails to protect the public is an outrage. Heavy fines should be assessed, and the power of the state should be called upon to prevent recurrences.</p>
   <p>The commissioner of the board of health would be delinquent in his duty if he failed to present the facts to the council, and did not urge that body to pass an ordinance on sewers and ventilation which provided for inspection of buildings during construction.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
