<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-23">July 23, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Wages and Tips</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-23">July 23, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">WAGES AND TIPS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The eight-hour question has arisen in the city administration, and presents a strange aspect.</p>
   <p>The council, at its last session, decided that city work, such as sewer construction, laying of water pipes, etc., shall be done on an eight-hour basis, and that the daily wage shall be two dollars.</p>
   <p>Commissioner of Public Works Waller declared that he cannot follow the dictates of the council, because, in an opinion given by the corporation counsel, paying of the new and higher rate would constititute a violation of Waller's official duties, or, at the very least, a waste of public money. All public <pb facs="5418474_6_0200.jpg" n="2"/>improvements are made according to contract, and $1.75 is paid for ten hours' work; that would be $1.40 for eight hours. To pay more--when the workingmen did not even ask for a raise--would be equivalent to giving a tip of sixty cents to every man. The council has no right, and Commissioner Waller has still less authority, to do that.</p>
   <p>If Congress and the states are not empowered to impair the validity of contracts, surely a city council can be no exception.</p>
   <p>The distinction which Waller draws between wages and tips may perhaps be explained by the council in calling the workers "officials", and their wages salaries. In that event, the council's right to raise official salaries cannot be disputed.</p>
   <p>But, in that event, official salaries would be of little importance, so far <pb facs="5418474_6_0201.jpg" n="3"/>as the eight-hour labor question is concerned. The money which the aldermen would give to city workers, the sixty-cent tips, would not come out of the aldermanic pockets; the additional funds would come from the taxpayers, and the taxpayers, regardless of their occasional braying, are good-natured asses who will bear the heaviest loads. It is somewhat doubtful, however, that any of the councilmen would pay two dollars for eight hours' work, instead of $1.75 for ten hours, if these gentlemen were to hire a laborer. Not one of the aldermen would do that. They are very liberal with other people's money, but if they would have to defray the expense, that would be another story.</p>
   <p>If the city council, in one way or another, circumvents the opposition of Commissioner Waller, all city workers, in comparison to other laborers, will be a preferred class.</p>
   <p>It can happen, of course; we even have had a precedent in New York, where <pb facs="5418474_6_0202.jpg" n="4"/>Bill Tweed created a preferred class of workers, city workers, who receive a higher rate of pay, at the taxpayers' expense, of course. The tips these workers received in addition to their regular salary were a sort of reimbursement for the dirty work which had to be performed for their political party.</p>
   <p>Our Democratic council now follows the example given by Tweed, but that our aldermen--the majority of them--should adopt such a resolution because of a belief in the eight-hour principle, is something that not even the Socialists will believe--they are not so foolish.</p>
   <p>By the way, Waller is a Democrat, and his argument with the council is there-fore a family row. The costs, whatever the outcome, will be paid by the taxpayers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
