<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-01-11">Jan. 11, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">"Carl Wolfsohn's Third Trio Concert"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1657</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1657.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-01-11">Jan. 11, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">"Carl Wolfsohn's Third Trio Concert"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>was enjoyed by a large audience which is proof, that the desire for good music is steadily increasing. Mr. Wolfsohn also showed talent in the selection of compositions for these concerts which fascinate his audiences, and the clever arrangement of the program keeps the listeners keenly interested in the performance throughout the evening. Mr. Wolfsohn was supported at last night's concert by two Chicagoans, well known artists, Messrs. Marum and Hess, in whose praise we can hardly add anything. The opening number played by the trio was that lofty composition in B by Volkmann, and following was the trio in F by Godard. Both compositions were played with the highest skill. Mr. Wolfsohn, as the first soloist of the evening, played four compositions by Schumann, "Romanze", "Arabeske", "Traumerei" and "Novelette". This rendition was undoubtedly the most brilliant performance of the evening. The artist understood how to enrich these compositions with so much poetic beauty, it was not easy to identify them, or we should say rather, that for once we were able to identify them again, after they have been played by every student of music everywhere. Fred Hess gave us also an exquisite exhibition of his art when he played the "Adagio" by Bargiel. Last evening's vocalist was Miss Elena Varnesi, a gifted singer displaying a well trained voice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
