<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-06-08">June 8, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">The Inequality of Woman.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0784</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0784.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-06-08">June 8, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">THE INEQUALITY OF WOMAN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mrs. Rawson's complaint that she did not receive justice in our courts furnishes us with something about which we should think.</p>
   <p>To the average mind this complaint seems incredible, but to the keen observer of human nature it is perfectly clear that women are not on an equal basis with men in any relationship pertaining to life. Women possess an entirely different range of thoughts and emotions. They look at the world and at human affairs from a vastly different viewpoint, irrespective of what they themselves and men may say to the contrary. Some very excellent men are trying to bring about the equality of both sexes, but it is this very difference which prevents the achievement of that ideal condition of human society.</p>
   <p>Men and woman can not meet on an equal plane discussing matters, except in very rare cases and under exceptional conditions. Men and woman can not be friends in the sense that women are with women and men with men. The difference of sex will always be present and a different solution will be presented to every problem. Women will always claim a certain consideration, and perhaps rightfully so, <pb facs="5418474_6_0785.jpg" n="2"/>because of their sex. This consideration will have the tendency to work out to their advantage or their disadvantage, but never in perfect equality. In some cases they gain more, and in other cases they lose more than they deserve.</p>
   <p>Women arouse either unusual sympathy before our courts, or unusual diversion. The result in both cases is injustice. But this is human nature, and what can be done to overcome it? The women are treated either with extreme mildness or unusual severity. And this will continue until men and women are made of different stuff.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
