<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-01-05">Jan. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">German Bank of Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">Formal Reception Today and Tomorrow</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1132</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1132.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-01-05">Jan. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN BANK OF CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">Formal Reception Today and Tomorrow</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recently founded German Bank, chartered under the laws of this State, and therefore under its supervision, is holding a formal reception today and tomorrow in its ornate bank building, corner Clark and Division Streets. It has been a source of satisfaction to many who already visited the establishment, that Chicago now also possesses a German bank, similarly to other large cities in this country, and particularly an institution which prides itself in conducting its business transactions with typical German thoroughness and conscientiousness. A reporter of the Abendpost made a personal investigation and finds that the commercial and savings accounts have grown commendably, regardless of the bank's recent origin.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1133.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The majority of the merchants in the northern section of Clark Street and adjacent neighborhoods are Germans who displayed a particular interest in the organization of this bank, and therefore readily entrusted their business to the new corporation. Not only the commercial element but also employees in divers kinds of human endeavor, brought their savings trustingly to the new bank, and, as Mr. Gustav F. Fischer assures us, deposits show a constant growth.</p>
   <p>In consideration of the present reception days, the interior has been converted into a veritable garden, since the host of friends and well-wishers of this venture expressed their greetings by sending flowers. The officials received the numerous visitors in a cordial manner, showed the bank's interior, and readily gave all desired information. The bank has a bonded capital of $200,000 and $20,000 surplus.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1134.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Its motto, which is also prominently displayed on its circulars, is summarized in these four words - "Secure, Conservative, and Sound." In conformity with this formula, the following gentlemen have pledged their service: Gustav F. Fisher, President; Harry H. Keyes, Vicepresident; Jacob R. Darmstadt, Cashier.</p>
   <p>Directorate: Albert F. Madlener, Gustav F. Fisher, William F. Juergens, Fred Klein, William H. Rehm, Louis Mohr, Rudolph S. Blome, Edward Levy, Henry C. Brummel, Richard E. Schmidt, John G. Graue, and Harry H. Keyes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
