<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-09-26">Sept. 26, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Attitude Toward Trades in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0564</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0564.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-09-26">Sept. 26, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE ATTITUDE TOWARD TRADES IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the approach of good times we hear again the old complaint that it is very difficult to find American workers who know a trade. The Scientific American states that if any one inserts an advertisement in an American newspaper and asks for an office boy or a delivery boy, he is sure to get hundreds of applications; but if one wishes to hire an experienced man who knows his trade, then only two or three apply. Other papers also have considered the problem and have tried to find an explanation; none deny the condition which confronts us, and they reluctantly admit that Americans show little inclination to learn trades. However, nearly everybody is willing to become a clerk, because clerks merely sit, stand, or walk, and that is deemed the only sensible way to get a start in life; much preferable, regardless of the ridiculously low wages, to performing useful, productive <pb facs="5418474_6_0565.jpg" n="2"/>labor which requires physical as well as mental exertion. And so our American youth is willing to eke out an existence behind a counter.</p>
   <p>Why? Have not the last six years shown what a helpless lot these youngsters are? Thousands, tens of thousands of them have been doomed to utter failure, --have been forced to become tramps. But experience is not heeded, and every day one becomes aware of an ever increasing antipathy to work; fewer and fewer Americans show an inclination to learn a trade, that is, anything else than some such pursuit as bookkeeping.</p>
   <p>A father who has six sons has tried to give an explanation in a letter to one of our Chicago papers. It appears to him that the primary cause is the foolish ambition to become a prominent office sheik.</p>
   <p>These stylishly dressed fellows would consider it a disgrace if their dainty <pb facs="5418474_6_0566.jpg" n="3"/>hands were to show calluses or other traces of useful labor. And of course, when you work, your hands will show it. These young men are aware that the girls whom they associate with would be horrified if their male friends worked with hammer, file, plane, or saw instead of a golden pen or at most a yard-stick. Loafers of this kind on the fringe of society are simply hopeless.</p>
   <p>"But," he continues, "there are also thousands of parents who are indifferent to society, people who want their sons to become proficient in some trade, and here, too, little is accomplished. Why? Because they are Americans. Our factories with few exceptions are owned by foreigners, and the men, the workers, are mostly immigrants who make life unbearable for any American apprentice. I have been successful," continues the writer, "in inducing two of my sons to learn a trade. I have also tried to persuade my other children to do so. As a result of my endeavors, one son wanted to be a carpenter, but the Bohemian workers made life so unpleasant for him that I could not let him continue. This is only one instance; I could enumerate <pb facs="5418474_6_0567.jpg" n="4"/>many others. A factory owner promised me definitely to hire one of my sons so that he could learn a trade but later told me that it was impossible to give the lad a chance because the factory workers objected to teaching the trade to an American."</p>
   <p>Does this condition prevail elsewhere? We believe that the problem is serious. Many labor unions object to apprentices on general principles, not merely to Americans. Quite often strikes have been threatened when employers have hired more apprentices than the men cared to have, or even when any helpers at all were employed.</p>
   <p>Of course one might ask the Americans: Why are so many industries owned by foreigners? They were not here in the beginning. During the first sixty years of the Republic the foreign element was not so numerous as to crowd out the American workers. Why did not Americans take control of the <pb facs="5418474_6_0568.jpg" n="5"/>various trades at the time when factory production was still in its infancy?</p>
   <p>The answer apparently must be: In the main, the Americans showed as little inclination for learning a trade in those times as today. Americans were either farmers or merchants, and since the latter vocation was more respected and was considered much more dignified, all farmers' sons who cared not for the soil showed an inclination to become loafers. Among the sparse population adventure and the prospect of gain with the comparatively little effort proved much greater attractions than the modest but secure income derived from working at some trade. A fortune suddenly acquired without too much effort is a goal which can be attained only by business transactions, and so Americans showed no interest in trades and the plodding connected therewith. Even when machinery increased production, and trades became industries, the interest of Americans was concentrated on the business end. The American planned and managed the enterprise and sold the merchandise wholesale, and the immigrants, Germans, French, Bohemians, Swiss, or <pb facs="5418474_6_0569.jpg" n="6"/>Scandinavians, did the work.</p>
   <p>These conditions existed in the beginning and will probably continue for some time,--at least for the next ten years.</p>
   <p>As better times approach, there will also be a proportionate increase in opportunities of a speculative nature, and then the American chase for the almighty dollar will come into full swing again,--and that means good-bye to all good resolutions and to learning trades which provide a reliable livelihood!</p>
   <p>Only after our population increases to such an extent that speculation is virtually eliminated--when a modest but regular income appears to be the most desirable--will Americans show an interest in learning trades.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0570.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Conditions in crowded European countries are the main contributing factor why most of our trades in America are controlled by foreign workers; natural inclination or an acquired liking for certain pursuits has had little to do with this phase of our labor problem.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
