<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-14">May 14, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">[Doubtful Terror Agitation]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0266</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0266.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-14">May 14, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">[DOUBTFUL TERROR AGITATION]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fear of riots by the proletariat is immense. Dispatches from the foreign newspapers read as follows: "Chicago Communists are ready for action on July 4th 1879, the Authorities are taking precautions for safety." All the capitalistic newspapers express their indignation over the proposed introduction of the 8 hour work day for American labor which is planned for the 4th of July. Of course, the fact that the miners whose deplorable working conditions and small wages will give this movement their whole hearted support is not to be question. The mere thought of a general strike, fills one with horror. But, that even the rough element, has to a certain extent a right to an education which, by virtue of the long working hours and starvation wages, is denied to them, is the reason which compels labor to take such a step. Some time ago the Ill. Staatz Zeitung began its investigation and the Westliche Post followed in their foot steps by saying, "An eight hour working day has been decided upon by the leaders of the working organization. It is not a bad plan but, who will pay,the same wages for eight working, as formally for ten? No matter how this question will be solved if the price of <pb facs="5418474_6_0267.jpg" n="2"/>living necessities should rise; what will the worker have gained by that?</p>
   <p>As to the question who will pay, we answer work pays for itself. With the shorter working hours, the wages should not lessen but, to the contrary should increase, for the number of the unemployed will decrease. With the exception of a few capitalists, nobody would suffer any disadvantage, as a result of the shorter working day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
