<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-25">June 25, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Right to Bear Arms</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0255</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0255.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-25">June 25, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE RIGHT TO BEAR ARMS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The assertions of the communists that no state has a constitutional right to ban armed organizations, other than the state militia, cannot be well sustained, when viewed in the light of the wording of the Constitution. With respect to the second article in the amendments to the Constitution. "A well-regulated militia is necessary to the security of a free State; the right of the people to keep and bear arms, shall not be infringed."</p>
   <p>This addition was proposed by the first congress to meet after the adoption of our present Constitution, and was accepted by three-fourths of the states then in existence.</p>
   <p>The text plainly shows that it was desired to obtain a necessary, armed militia; now, note well, a regulated militia to protect the state. And that was the underlying motive of the proponents of the amendment--that in the <pb facs="5418474_6_0256.jpg" n="2"/>absence of a powerful national army, it becomes necessary to have a strong militia for the security of the state.</p>
   <p>Anybody in congress at that time would have been regarded a fool if he had asserted that armed organizations should be premitted to exist in opposition to the state. And if anyone in that congress had claimed that that constitutional amendment permits irresponsible military organizations to shoot people at random, then such a persons mental status would have been questioned.</p>
   <p>An attempt to quote the Constitution for the purpose of justifying the existence of armed organizations other than the militia, organizations holding military parades and making threats against the present order, is crazy.</p>
   <p>The right of the individual to carry arms for lawful purposes is not taken away by the new militia law of Illinois, The law fully considers the dictates of the Constitution and lives up to its spirit; therefore, it only makes it unlawful for associations to exercise with arms and to carry weapons while <pb facs="5418474_6_0257.jpg" n="3"/>parading.</p>
   <p>It is the sworn duty of the Governor of Illinois to uphold this law, which goes into effect on July 1, and we do not believe that any high tribunal will regard this statute as unconstitutional.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
