<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-08-07">August 7th, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">Proclamation.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0587</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0587.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-08-07">August 7th, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">PROCLAMATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following was composed by the German-American Republican Club "Address to the German American Voters."</p>
   <p>"Fellow Citizen! On the eve of a Presidential election which in importance only could be compared with those of 1860 and 1864, and in which the fate of this country is going to be decided for many years to come. the Society of the German-American Republicans regards it as its duty, to appeal in earnest words to the German speaking voters, especially in the city of Chicago and in the State of Illinois.</p>
   <p>"This time, the Democrats of the Southern states stand against us in their full strength, united as in Pierce's and Buchanan's times with their political fellow-believers in the North, and encouraged by advantages gained at the ballot boxes two years ago in consequence of a wide dissatisfaction over evils existing in the country they are now trying through alluring promises and deceitful delusions to win from our lines some votes, without which they could not expect any success.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0588.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is not our task, to explain the development and achievements of the Republican Party; but one might be mentioned. The Southern Slave-holders in 1861, in company with their confederates in the North started the most warranted of all civil wars known in history. Its ourpose was to destroy the great work, which crowned the struggle for independence of the Colonies against great Britian, destroying the Union, through which the United States, originally a small community had become a great commanding-respect Republic. They tried to ruin the union because they could not control it any longer. The Republicans Party had to accept the challange and carried it victeriously through at the sacrifice of wealth and life. And at last, after more than four years of fighting, the victory was accomplished, there were no military courts instituted to wreck revenge, no prisons were filled with political prisoners and no boats left their harbors in our country with deportations. The Republican party had a difficult task to accomplish; the union had to be reconstructed and safe guarded against the repetition of violence attacks on its confirmed existence. Abrahman Lincoln's greatest and immortal deed, the liberation of four million slaves had to be preserved. The Republican <pb facs="5418474_6_0589.jpg" n="3"/>party courageously marched forward on the path entered by its great leader, and guaranteed the freedom of the former slaves by constitutional and lawful protection;but as our Vice Presidential candidate William Wheeler correctly says: "The mission of the Republican Party cannot be considered as completed, as long as the American citizen cannot enjoy without discrimination because of the color of his skin, whether in the cane marshes of Louisiana or on the banks of the St. Lawrence River his civic, political and public rights."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
