<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-04-30">Apr. 30, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Loewenbrauerei</title><title level="a" type="sub">M. Brand and Company's Imposing Brewery</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-04-30">Apr. 30, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE LOEWENBRAUEREI</title><title level="a" type="sub">M. Brand and Company's Imposing Brewery</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The new brewery of M. Brand and Company, successors to the Busch and Brand Brewing Company....is now completed--and, it is hoped, the scientific methods and improvements which have been incorporated in the new structure will produce an even better beer than the Company produced heretofore.</p>
   <p>The Loewenbrauerei (Lion Brewery) is situated a few blocks north of Fullerton Avenue, between Elston Road and the North Branch of the Chicago River, which provides excellent transportation facilities, and the Company intends to take full advantage of these opportunities, including the water route. Elston Road is in good condition for traffic of all kinds, and the river is navigable as far as the brewery, so that raw materials such as coal, malt, hops, and so forth, can be delivered cheaply and quickly.</p>
   <p>The exterior of the brewery is imposing; the frontage is on Elston Road.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1298.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Architecturally, the structure shows harmonious lines, and as far as the interior is concerned, the brewery may be regarded as one of the most excellent and exemplary establishments of its kind. Everywhere it is apparent that science and experience were the deciding factors in the construction; this manifests itself particularly in the relative locations of the mash vats, boilers, cooling tanks, fermenting chambers, ice cellars, etc., as well as in the general arrangement. The mash vats are equipped with excellent machinery, and have a capacity of 400 bushels of malt. The two large boilers have a capacity of 300 and 150 barrels each; the Kuehlschiffe are of large dimensions: one of them is 100 by 20 feet in size; the other, now near completion, measures 240 by 30 feet. Power is supplied by a 68 H. P. engine and transmitted to various machines. Facilities for filling and bottling are excellent.</p>
   <p>In planning the brewery, particular attention was given to fermenting chambers and storage cellars. There are two fermenting chambers, each 130 by 18 feet. The ice cellar is divided as follows: One compartment, 180 by 16 feet; nine <pb facs="5418474_6_1299.jpg" n="3"/>compartments, each 130 by 18 feet; the ceilings are 18 and 22 feet high. The arrangement is of such a nature that beer can be stored at a constant temperature, regardless of season.</p>
   <p>To attain this, it was necessary to obtain ice in sufficient quantities regardless of unfavorable weather conditions, and this constituted the chief reason why the brewery was erected in such a far outlying district. M. Brand and Company, by selecting that location, were enabled to obtain ample space for their buildings and, in addition to the site of the buildings, bought an additional plot of twenty-one acres contiguous to their present holdings. On this site, west of the river, ponds were constructed which cover eight acres. Water for the ponds is obtained from an artesian well which the Company has had drilled; in this manner, crystal-clear ice can be produced during cold weather; machinery is used for cutting and conveying. Aside from the storage chambers, 16 feet high, above the ice cellars, the company has a separate building, 264 by 24 feet and 26 feet high, which holds a reserve supply.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1300.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is therefore quite apparent that, if that storage space is filled (and that was readily accomplished during a favorable winter last season, when not less than 27,000 tons of ice were harvested), ice will never be lacking during any summer, or even two summers.</p>
   <p>The brewery also has a large malt house (sixteen floors, 24,000 bushel capacity) and a storage space for hops connected with their cooling chambers; a very desirable arrangement because hops will keep better and will not turn rosinous if exposed to a low temperature.</p>
   <p>M. Brand and Company make their own malt; hence their old brewery on Cedar Street has been converted into a malt house. Here, also, the most scientific methods have been adopted.</p>
   <p>While the highly suitable cellars of the brewery serve in maintaining an even temperature for malting and sprouting, the drying of the malt is now accomplished by circulating hot air, and not by an open fire as formerly; also, sheet metal <pb facs="5418474_6_1301.jpg" n="5"/>trays have been dispensed with, and slabs are now used in the kiln drying process. Obviously, this procedure produces a better malt and, no doubt, only European malt houses can be compared with this installation.</p>
   <p>The equipment in general shows the same high standards. The office is located a short distance north of the Division Street bridge, at 287-293 Hawthorne Avenue. Large barns for the Company's teams, and wagon sheds, are near the office. Here also is located an ice house for the temporary storage of beer before it is delivered. A wharf on the river serves as a convenient loading place for the Company's own, specially built steam boat, the "M. Brand," which is used to deliver beer to the ice house near the office, and to transport empty barrels as well as all raw materials used at the brewery. Telephone connections with all parts of the City prove of inestimable value.....The brewery, in all its phases, including business management, is under the supervision of our well-known fellow citizen, Michael Brand, whose activity and diligence were the chief factors in the rapid growth of the establishment. F. C. Dewes is in charge of the office <pb facs="5418474_6_1302.jpg" n="6"/>and financial matters, and Rudolph Brand is the superintendent of the brewery.</p>
   <p>.....California malt and hops only are used, thus producing the clearest, best beer available in the West.....The Company now has available 40,000 barrels of lager beer, and therefore need not brew much during the summer months. This explains why the Company built such large storage cellars and ice houses; it was desired to produce a properly seasoned beer throughout the year.</p>
   <p>Tomorrow, May 1, it will market its bock beer; within a few days the Company's famous Utah Lager Beer is scheduled to make its appearance--undoubtedly to the credit of the brewery and the gratification of the discerning consumer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
