<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-19">May 19, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Loisch's Benefit Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1707</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1707.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-19">May 19, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">LOISCH'S BENEFIT CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Georg Loesch's concert, arranged by his friends and given at the North Side Turnhalle last evening, was a decided success, regardless of its mixed obstacles. An explanation may be in order: Some of the musicians who appeared at the final rehearsal did not show up for the performance; (much better than not to have been at the final rehearsal and appearing for the performance) and then, there was difficulty in securing the ABT club, because a large number of the club's members belong to church choirs and sang at religious services that evening [Sunday], while a few objected to singing on a Sunday in such a "Godless" place as the North Side Turnhalle.</p>
   <p>This explains why the opening was so long delayed and why the orchestra consisted of only twenty-eight men, instead of forty as announced; it also accounts for the small number of singers present.</p>
   <p>Whoever might have objected to the late beginning was fully rewarded, however, <pb facs="5418474_6_1708.jpg" n="2"/>by the truly brilliant performance of the orchestra. When one considers that the musicians of Loesch's orchestra in the main are not of the highest type, and that only a few skilled and talented individuals were present, the orchestra's performance was astounding, and gave proof of what our musicians can accomplish under excellent leadership. If one speaks highly of Thomas' orchestra, particularly of the great control which that conductor has attained, then Mr. Loesch deserves oven more credit, because Thomas' orchestra is composed of the best musicians available--many deserve to be called artists.</p>
   <p>That the orchestra was not as large as originally announced did not prove too detrimental, as it was more than sufficiently powerful to fill the hall. It is to be regretted that the audience was not as large as it might have been.</p>
   <p>The first number, Meyer Beer's "Facketanz in B flat", arranged for military <pb facs="5418474_6_1709.jpg" n="3"/>band by Mr. Loesch, showed in a well trained orchestra and only in a few passages did one note an insufficiency of string instruments. The presentation showed exceptional exactness, and it almost appeared as if Mr. Loesch desired to show (by his abrupt endings and sudden starts) how well he could control his musicians.</p>
   <p>Weber's "Jubel Ouverture" made a great impression; in its rendition the composer's ideas were well interpreted. Mendelssohn's "Nocturno," however, lacked softness, and the musicians showed less confidence than in other numbers played.</p>
   <p>The next number was a double quartet, "Ein Frisches Lied im Walde", sung by members of the ABT club. Although the club's best singers were not present, the rendition was excellent, and the gentlemen were given deserved applause.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Loesch deserves public gratitude; he has organized an excellent military <pb facs="5418474_6_1710.jpg" n="4"/>band....which....will do much for the furtherance of music in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
