<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-02-17">February 17, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">What Mr. Mc Kinley Wants.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0480</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0480.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-02-17">February 17, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT MR. MC KINLEY WANTS.</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The politics of the administration ought to be fully known to the president of the United States, but if we draw conclusions from Mc Kinley's public speech at Boston, then it appears that he is just as unfamiliar with the intricacies of his office, as any other mortal. According to his conception "the future of the Philippines lays in the hands of the American people," but its obscure fate is still obvious. "At this hour I know no one, who has sufficient intelligence or is so correctly informed, that he can proclaim, which form of Government is best for their and our interests, most beneficial for their people and ours. If we could be omniscient by inspiration- and sometimes I think there are people who believe this applies to them but not to us- then we could dispense with learning, but fortunately, most of us are not favored with such an enviable endowment. The entire problem is now presented to our congress, and after all the senate constitutes the voice, the conscience and the judgment of the American people."</p>
   <p>Everybody, after considering the significance of these words, must admit, <pb facs="5418474_6_0481.jpg" n="2"/>that Mr. Mc Kinley is exceptionally modest; incidentally he has a high regard for our Congress. The majority of the House of Representatives however, has no presumptuous opinion of its own members but professes high esteem for the president, which prompted them to acquiesce in all the executive's requests, without ascertaining his reasons or purposes. It may surprise them somewhat, that the executive authorizes a war with the Filipinos, for unknown reasons and that he desires to increase the numerical strength of the army to 100,000 soldiers. Although the president does not profess to know, just what form of government he should give to the Philippines, on the other hand he is adamant and convinced that the natives themselves dont know what they want, nor what form of leadership is best for them. If we had shown indifference towards them, after the evacuation of the Spaniards, and left them to their own devices, then they would have been devoid of any Government and be compelled to exist in an environment of anarchism. Our object was not one of territorial acquisition, trade or imperialism but to consider the interests and destiny of a race, whose future was placed into our hands, unsought and without volition on our part... If we are able to bestow benefits upon this distant people, who then can raise objections? Despite <gap unit="lines" extent="1" reason="missing from image"/>
    <pb facs="5418474_6_0482.jpg" n="3"/>does and hold them in high esteem. He says: "Since we did not ask them whether we could liberate them, it is evident, we need not inquire, if they will permit us, to make them happy. Can anyone tell me, how their consent may be procured before peace and order have been restored! It is not an auspicious time for the liberator to ask important questions of the liberated, while the latter shoot their protectors." According to this evidence, it appears, that the telegrams have not expressed the truth, when they stated, that Mr. Mc Kinley demanded that the Filipinos should submit to absolute dependence upon the United States before even Congress authorized the declaration of peace, and that our troops killed thousands, of the natives. Mr. Mc Kinley is the lamb, and Aguinaldo the wolf.</p>
   <p>In closing his remarkable speech the president quoted a fact, which at one time was very popular among the slave-owners. These gentlemen assured us, that the Negro, while in the care of the cotton plantation owners, was better off than in the African wilderness, likewise Mr. Mc Kinley exclaims. "It is my inalienable belief, that the inhabitants of the Philippines will be benefited by our Republic; that they will have a more benevolent administration <pb facs="5418474_6_0483.jpg" n="4"/>under our leadership, and that we will help them realize their goal, to develop into a respected and self-governing people is as true, as the belief of the American population in its liberty and stanch adherence to its own government and institutions."</p>
   <p>Ergo, it is best for the Philippines, if our battleship guns now them down and we burn their villages. Not for our, but for their sake we must subjugate then. Identically the same expressions were uttered by the Spaniards, when they ravaged Mexico and Peru with fire and sword, because the Indians were unwilling to accept Christianity and refused to work in mines and fields for their saviors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
