<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1884-06-02">June 2, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">Grand Opera House, Nenendorff's Opera Company, a "Trip to Africa."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1672</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1672.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1884-06-02">June 2, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">GRAND OPERA HOUSE, NENENDORFF'S OPERA COMPANY, A "TRIP TO AFRICA."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If the beautiful Georgina Januschoffsky cast a glance at the throng which filled all the chairs and benches of the Grand, she must have told herself: "See, these Chicago Germans are better people. Give the children what they are crying for," comic operettas, and they will not fail to be on the spot." The audience last night consisted of at least one-half Germans and they laughed till the tears ran down their cheeks, and they applauded as if they had been paid for it (although the privilege cost them $1.50 each.)</p>
   <p>But it was for a good purpose, and according to the proverb, "The crown to the meritorious." The "Trip to Africa" is a piquant opera, and that is what all the papers, both German and English, write about it; and we do not hesitate to endorse their opinion, in spite of the fact that we were only able to see the first act. The first act introduces the main character actors to advantage and is, as we are told, the leading act, because its basic musical ideas are continued and developed in the other parts of the operetta.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1673.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Miss Von Januschoffsky sings and plays the role of "Titania" with charm and grace; she has, as is well known, a delightful stage appearance (figure) and understands how to increase the effect through elegant costumes. She is a piquant actress, who quite often rises to the heights of artistic productions. She is the best-singing soubrette who has ever appeared on the American stage. The charming role of the "Titania" could not find a better representative than Miss Januschoffsky. W. H. Fessenden was liked as "Maradillo," George W. Travner (Prince Antarfid) was an excellent baritone, Miss Lillie West shone more as a dancer than as a singer.</p>
   <p>We reserve the exercise of a more detailed criticism. The choir of the troupe--45 people with as many excellent voices--is well trained and sings with precision. The orchestra, conducted by Adolph Nenendorf personally, has done very well. The scenery, supplied by the Grand Opera House, was beautiful and evoked repeated plaudits. The star and the performance were received by the audience with great cheering. The "Trip to Africa" will be repeated today, and every following evening, also Wednesday and Saturday afternoon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
