<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-03">Oct. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Funeral Services for Emanuel Gall Friday Afternoon</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1052</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1052.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-03">Oct. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">FUNERAL SERVICES FOR EMANUEL GALL FRIDAY AFTERNOON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Emanuel Gall, honorary president of the Schwabenverein (Swabian Society) and of the Gesangverein Harmonie (Harmony Singing Society), died yesterday afternoon at the ripe old age of eighty years. Funeral services for the deceased will take place Friday afternoon at two o'clock in Linn's funeral chapel at 3415 North Clark Street, and the burial in Graceland Cemetery will follow. The societies mentioned above will furnish the pallbearers, for in these two societies the deceased took a special interest, although he did take an active part in almost every German movement of the last half century.</p>
   <p>Emanuel Gall was born September 19, 1854, in Affalderbach, Wuerttemberg. After attending school there he entered his father's business as an apprentice, and learned the stonecutter's trade.</p>
   <p>He was not yet twenty years old when he came to America and joined his <pb facs="5418474_6_1053.jpg" n="2"/>brother in Chicago. His brother at that time had his own business, a stonecutting shop, in Lake View not far from Graceland cemetery. For about two years the brothers were partners, until Emanuel Gall took the business over in 1875. For fifty-three years, the deceased carried on the business successfully, until he retired, about six years ago.</p>
   <p>In 1877 he married Louise, who survives him. The marriage was happy, and there were four children; a son George, and the daughters Kitty, Flora, and Pauline, who join with the grieving widow, with two sisters who live in Germany, and with a large number of other relatives and friends in mourning the passing of this highly respected man.</p>
   <p>Only a few weeks ago Mr. Gall celebrated his eightieth birthday. Unfortunately the condition of his health at that time was such that the Schwabenverein and the singers had to forego a public celebration for which they had made plans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
