<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-03-16">Mar. 16, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Natural Course of Events</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0075</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0075.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-03-16">Mar. 16, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE NATURAL COURSE OF EVENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"In unity lies strength," and "the price paid for liberty is constant alertness." When the liberal element of our citizens had discovered that liberty and the right to home rule were jeopardized, they realized the truth which lies in these words, and hastened to strengthen their fortification, culminating in the founding of the United Societies for local home rule. An Executive Committee was then appointed, into whose care the governing of these societies was entrusted. To watch and guard the interest this precious thing called liberty was the principal duty of that committee.... Faith played a prominent part in the organization of the United Societies. They placed faith in the men whom they elected as their representatives. These delegates, in turn, depend upon the faith of the Executive Committee, etc., all of whom are working toward one ultimate goal. The structure of the United Societies rests upon the faith in each other.... Liberty <pb facs="5418474_6_0076.jpg" n="2"/>was well guarded under the watchful eye of this organization; it was the supporting pillar of liberty loving people....</p>
   <p>And it worked excellently, but not indefinitely. While the organization remained true to the principle upon which it was founded, all was well, and the Association became powerful and influential beyond the limits of its own city. This resulted in the pronounced anti prohibition attitude throughout the State.</p>
   <p>However, the faith placed in certain members of the Association was grossly misused. They have now formed a minority group, a faction of their own, and, therefore, are politicians just the same. Spoil politics and office huntings, now replaced the unselfish spirit of the local liberal home rule. While all this was undermining the organization's splendid reputation, it gave the prohibition advocates a good chance to gain considerable ground, although <pb facs="5418474_6_0077.jpg" n="3"/>victory is still far off. The "drys" have beaten the "wets" in two ballots, in the lower House of Legislature in Springfield, yesterday.</p>
   <p>The success of the Prohibitionists is the direct result of the deviation from the principle of the United Charities upon which it was built. The change of their political view point is regarded as a breach of confidence, and jeopardizes the whole structure of the organization. Furthermore, if it continues upon the path of its present political attitude, the absolute collapse of that structure is inevitable. Their opponents, well acquainted with this deplorable condition, draw added vigor from this inconsistency, which is largely responsible for the decrease in popularity of the Association. An organization which permits its managing force to become involved in Party and faction politics, cannot expect to defend its original stand successfully, and hope to obtain a hearing by the opposition Party.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0078.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>An organization which permits its officials to become active in faction politics, resulting in a profitable compensation, must, as a consequence, loose prestige and influence, not only with the opposing Party, but with the Parties of its own standard, as well. When an organization fails to fulfill its mission, a complete collapse is unavoidable, and only a matter of time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
