<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-01-29">January 29, 1887</date>,
<title level="a">Election Rights for Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0789</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0789.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-01-29">January 29, 1887</date>,
<title level="a">ELECTION RIGHTS FOR WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Federal Senate has voted against the bill, which was to entitle every women reaching the age of maturity to cast her vote. Among the minority (23 men) in favor of the bill was the new Senator of Illinois, Mr. Chas B. Farwell... Women anxious to participate in political activities may be numerous, but they were doubtlessly gifted with a good mouthpiece, which explains of course, why "Statesmen" like these are in favor of women in politics. These Statesmen have to resort even to such tactics, in order to strengthen their position. According to Cady-Stanton, Susan Anthony and others, the principal reason for introducing women into politics is, that women would have an ennobling and moralizing influence upon politics. This is one of the silly phrases for which people,who preferably let others think for them, would fall, without questioning the other side of it.</p>
   <p>It is quite surprising that an English-American paper(The Local Daily News) has the courage to point out the reverse when it says: "The women who have a beneficent influence on social life, are not the same women who demand the <pb facs="5418474_6_0790.jpg" n="2"/>right to vote... Very much is said about the charitable and noble influence of good women, while it is entirely overlooked what the influence of the low and indecent woman can be. What would be the result, if women of Chicago would obtain the vote? Would the virtuous and noble, highly educated women, or the morally low, heartless, and uncultured woman make use of this privilege?</p>
   <p>We hear so much about liquor taverns at times of elections; but the influence of occupants of houses of ill-fame is still worse. The franchise would never be exercised by the decent women, who never yearned for it, but by 7000-8000 indecent, immoral and uneducated women. What if these women, like those 8000 mentioned in Chicago, 10,000 in Philadelphia and 16,000 in New York, altogether about 120,000 throughout the United States would take part in elections? Of their influence would have to be reckoned with in nominating candidates? The election turmoil which is now carried from tavern to tavern would then be carried from one house of ill-fame to the other. The election day would furnish us with scenes of indecency never seen before. The decent and modest woman would not <pb facs="5418474_6_0791.jpg" n="3"/>venture to rub elbows with this element and therefore would abstain from voting...the shame and disgrace brought on the country by the women suffrage, would be fatal to the country."</p>
   <p>It rarely happens, that an English-American newspaper goes as far as taking a stand against the "ladies" and telling them frankly the truth. We fully agree with the attitude of the news, for every word this article contains, breathes pure truth... No matter what changes the 20th century may bring, general suffrage for women at least will not become constitutional during the 19th century.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
