<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-04">July 4, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Fourth of July</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0246</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0246.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-04">July 4, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE FOURTH OF JULY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Republic of the United States is one hundred and three years old today. In the first year of the nation's existence, Congress provided that the flag of the United States should consist of thirteen alternating red and white stripes, and that the Union should be represented by thirteen white stars on a blue field. On the present flag, only the thirteen stripes remind one of the original thirteen states which formed the Union; the blue field now contains thirty-nine stars instead of thirteen; and our eight territories give promise of developing into additional states, so that some of our readers will live to see forty-five (sic) stars in the blue field of our banner.</p>
   <p>The flag, which at one time represented a small republic of farmers and planters, is today the emblem of the mightiest and freest country on earth. Our Constitution enables anyone to improve his position, and entire classes of the population <pb facs="5418474_6_0247.jpg" n="2"/>are given tremendous leeway, as far as laws are concerned.</p>
   <p>The worst place for the red flag, emblem of the social revolution, is therefore next to The Star-Spangled Banner, because the latter presents no obstacles, even to the discussion of the most radical questions, and provides for a peaceful, gradual solution of all problems by due process of law.</p>
   <p>The great majority of our local knights of the red flag seem to realize this, because, regardless of the agitation of the several leaders, the demonstration for the eight-hour day will be a peaceful, lawful affair. Not only will any tilt with the law be avoided, but the arrangers of the parade even give assurances that the demonstration in no way represents an introduction to a general strike; the mass movement is merely adopted to make impressive the insistence of labor for shorter working hours.</p>
   <p>Reports received from other cities also show that the demonstrations scheduled for the Fourth of July are only in furtherance of the eight-hour workday--a <pb facs="5418474_6_0248.jpg" n="3"/>principle of labor--and the parades on that day are no forerunners of general strikes or violence.</p>
   <p>Communist newspapers in the East threatened a general uprising only a few days ago, and predicted other fearful events. But it appears that the labor unions taking part in the demonstrations have the upper hand, and most members prefer The Star-Spangled Banner to the red rag.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
