<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1924-06-08">June 8, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Democracy and the Party System</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0420</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0420.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1924-06-08">June 8, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">DEMOCRACY AND THE PARTY SYSTEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One often hears the remark that the old political parties have outlived their usefulness. This assertion reveals a lack of understanding of the nature of a party. A party as such cannot outlive its usefulness, because it is primarily a theoretical creation, given importance and significance by its members. One should rather say that the members of a party no longer follow its principles, that they misuse the organization to further certain aims which do not coincide with its true purposes, thus giving rise to contradictions. This is not the party's fault; these contradictions must be attributed to its members.</p>
   <p>Democracy means government by the people, and without parties such a form of government is inconceivable. It is impossible for a citizen to be politically active unless he is affiliated with an organization which reflects his views. Such an organization we call a political party.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0421.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The will of the masses is expressed by the majority party which controls the government, and logically enough, the minority party always forms the opposition.</p>
   <p>In keeping with the spirit of democracy, the entire population must participate in the nation's political life through the medium of the different parties. If large groups of people take no interest in politics, then the government will not be a democracy in the true sense of the word. The United States is now faced by this problem [of political lethargy]. During the last presidential election, there was an exceptional popular response; yet one-half of the qualified voters, both men and women, did not go to the polls.</p>
   <p>At that election President Harding received far more votes than any candidate in our history. But if a third candidate had appeared who could have obtained the support of this inactive element, then he, and not Harding, would have been in office. This consideration makes perfectly clear the extent to which our indifference has grown. It has therefore often been <pb facs="5418474_6_0422.jpg" n="3"/>suggested that citizens be compelled to vote, legal penalties to be meted out to those who are delinquent in their civic duties. But such a proposal would actually be tantamount to a declaration of national insolvency with respect to our democracy.</p>
   <p>What then would be gained by forming new parties? Of course, it is a fact that the progressive Republicans are nearer to the progressive Democrats than they are to their conservative colleagues, and the same is true for the progressive and conservative Democrats. But would a regrouping of the parties mitigate the evil of nonparticipation in voting? Would it be more advantageous for the people if we had Conservatives and Progressives instead of Republicans and Democrats?</p>
   <p>Probably not; after all, the public has had the opportunity to select conservative or progressive candidates ever since primaries were instituted. But the people have failed to take advantage of this opportunity. The primary elections are often decided by five percent of the voters, and <pb facs="5418474_6_0423.jpg" n="4"/>this fact makes a farce of our democratic form of government. Nor do reforms achieve their purpose. True democratic rule is possible only when the entire populace is politically minded.</p>
   <p>It is easy to understand why the critical observer has concluded that the parties have deviated from their original principles. Yet it would be unjust, for example, to compare the Republican party of today with its counterpart of Lincoln's time. We were then living in a heroic age, and consequently the political organization also took on that aspect [of heroism]. But the study of history brings to light an inexorable fact, namely, that the brief heroic episodes in the history of a people are followed by an era of mediocrity. This is an inflexible rule which brooks no exceptions, and men must bow to it.</p>
   <p>Even in our times parties have their uses. We cannot eliminate them since they are indispensable. But they can only fulfill their mission when all the people represented by the party are politically active. The leaders do not guide the party; it is the people who are supreme. The rulers can <pb facs="5418474_6_0424.jpg" n="5"/>be dethroned if the majority does not tolerate them. These are rather self-evident facts. Nevertheless it is occasionally necessary to restate them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
