<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-16">Mar. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Opinions</title><title level="a" type="sub">Prominent Real Estate Firms Speak of German-Americans as Home Builders and Owners</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1135</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1135.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-16">Mar. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">OPINIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Prominent Real Estate Firms Speak of German-Americans as Home Builders and Owners</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. McCollan of McCollan &amp; Kruggel:</p>
   <p>"As home owners, Germans, Poles, Bohemians, and Scandinavians head the list of nationalities represented in this country. The desire to own a plot of land and live under their own roof seems to be closely connected with their concept of a true family life. Our experiences with German-American customers have been highly satisfactory. Whenever we advertise new subdivisions, our German customers carefully appraise their values and chances for future development, and do not purchase with the idea to double their invested capital in a few months. They prefer moderate returns from their investments to a risk in speculation. Obligations which they assume are conscientiously observed and duly discharged."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1136.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Niles of H. O. Stone &amp; Co.:</p>
   <p>"It has been our experience that, in their adopted country, the Germans display the same enterprising spirit, diligence, and thrift that have gained for their native land such a prominent place in all phases of commerce, industry, and finance. Germans arriving here from the old country are almost without exception well educated and proficient in their vocations, and therefore capable of earning a good living as merchants, skilled workers, and artisans within a short time. They consider it a good investment to purchase real estate and to own their homes. The percentage of German-American real estate buyers far exceeds their percentage of the total population of the city."</p>
   <p>Mr. B. J. Nichols of L. A. Kinsey &amp; Co.:</p>
   <p>"The German-American makes a thorough investigation before selecting any lots offered for sale, but once he has made up his mind, he'll make his <pb facs="5418474_6_1137.jpg" n="3"/>property his permanent residence. He not only keeps his home in good repair and the exterior in excellent condition, but adds to the value of his property by planting gardens and trees around it."</p>
   <p>Mr. Bartlett of Bartlett &amp; Co.:</p>
   <p>"Our experience with German-American customers have been highly satisfactory. Not only do they conscientiously fulfil their obligations and keep their homes spotlessly clean, but, by their civilized and law-abiding behavior, manage to lend an otherwise poorly regarded neighborhood a character of respectability and desirability."</p>
   <p>Mr. Jones of E. Cummings &amp; Co.:</p>
   <p>"According to my experience, there is no doubt that the Germanic races appreciate the value of a home of their own most highly. Germans and <pb facs="5418474_6_1138.jpg" n="4"/>Scandinavians are foremost as home owners, with Bohemians and Poles coming next. There is no more pleasant sight than a German-American residential district with its well-painted houses and front yards in full bloom, while vegetables and chickens are raised in the back yard. The German home owner can serve as a shining example for all other nationalities."</p>
   <p>Mr. Wm. Bond of Wm. Bond &amp; Co.:</p>
   <p>"In my opinion, there is no doubt that the desire for a home of their own is much stronger with the Germans than with any other nationality. In making a selection, they always keep their financial capacity in mind because they like to have their property free of mortgages as quickly as possible. Even a man of moderate means would rather own a modest little home of his own than pay rent for a swanky apartment. German people give any neighborhood an air of respectability and substantiality."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1139.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Mr. Collins of Collins &amp; Gauntlett:</p>
   <p>"Citizens of German descent have not only taken a prominent place in various phases of Chicago's development, but have contributed to the establishment of residential sections of our city. If we find today solid rows of pretty dwellings and beautiful garden plots, where once existed swamp lands and sandy stretches, we must give credit for the most part to the German-American element of our population. The Germans' concept of a home is inseparably connected with the acquisition of a piece of ground which they can call their own, on which they can raise a lawn and flowers or otherwise make improvements. As purchasers of lots and houses, the Germans make excellent customers."</p>
   <p>Mr. John Heim:</p>
   <p>"The prominent role which the local German assumes as a home owner in the community is not only characterized by his building activity, but by his <pb facs="5418474_6_1140.jpg" n="6"/>acquisition of ready-built houses as well. The reason for this is that building lots are becoming scarce in some sections of the city and that the erection of wooden structures has been restricted because of present high building costs. Brick buildings in good condition are therefore preferred by many Germans who want to have a home of their own, which sometimes saves them a lot of money. But there are still many Germans who like to build a home according to their own specifications and, according to estimates, their number exceeds that of any nationality as buyers and builders of homes for personal use."</p>
   <p>Mr. Zander of Koester &amp; Zander:</p>
   <p>"German neighborhoods always attract other nationalities, Bohemians, Poles, and Swedes, who prefer their own communities. German orderliness and the care which they give to the surroundings of their homes is evident, and is the principal reason why their real estate increases so quickly in value.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1141.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The greater portion of my customers is German and nothing speaks more for their conscientiousness than the fact that in the various subdivisions which I have opened up, most building lots have been sold to Germans, and every one of them has taken care of his obligations within the specified time."</p>
   <p>Mr. Wm. Zelosky of Zelosky &amp; Co.:</p>
   <p>"Among my customers, the Germans assume the most prominent place. It seems unnecessary to me to praise their honesty and integrity, since these are German national characteristics known the world over. According to my experiences, which takes in many years and innumerable cases, the desire for a home of their own is nowhere so prominent as among the Germans. A house which they have bought is, to them, not a temporary abode, but a permanent dwelling place which they leave to their children, who in turn leave it to the next generation. That is why the German characteristics of of many neighborhoods is perserved for decades, while other nationalities <pb facs="5418474_6_1142.jpg" n="8"/>come and go. The number of home owners on the North Side should have an exceedingly high percentage of German-Americans."</p>
   <p>Mr. Rueter of W. F. Kaiser &amp; Co.:</p>
   <p>"Although we American citizens share equal rights and common interests, it is true nevertheless that the adopted [naturalized] citizen is loath to suppress character traits based on tradition, as well as certain inclinations. Two of the best characteristics of the German-Americans I can think of, and which are worthy examples for his fellow citizens, are his family spirit and his conscientiousness. As soon as he has become acclimated to American conditions, his efforts turn to the acquisition of a home of his own, which provides protection and shelter for his family after his earning power is gone. Nearly everyone of our German customers, many of whom had a hard time making the first down payment on a piece of ground, has fulfilled his obligations so promptly that he could start building a home at the time planned.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1143.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>In this respect the German-American undoubtedly stands first."</p>
   <p>Mr. McCluer of McCluer &amp; Cochran:</p>
   <p>"I am sure that my business colleagues have had so much praise for the German-American as property owner and tenant," said Mr. McCluer, "that all I should do, really, is to agree completely. But I do not want our many hundreds of German customers to gain the impression that I do a lot of talking only when I want to persuade them to buy, and that I cannot open my mouth when it comes to give them their just due as citizens of Chicago. Without belittling any other nationality, I can truthfully say that the German is the best home builder of them all. Even if I hadn't said that, the official statistics will reveal this fact. But what they don't tell you is that sensible economy, together with a healthy enjoyment of life, loyalty among their family members, and unceasing hard work have enabled citizens of German descent to become home owners in most cases. On such a <pb facs="5418474_6_1144.jpg" n="10"/>foundation you can well build, and if German-Americans like to avail themselves of the services of my firm, we will be only too glad to accommodate them."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
