<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-05-20">May 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Haydn's "Creation."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1576</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1576.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-05-20">May 20, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">HAYDN'S "CREATION."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Friends of classical music were once again taken back into the period of classical music of German origin when an appreciative audience listened spellbound to the performance of Haydn's "Creation" at the Orchestra Hall, last night.... Although this composition is indicative of times long past, Haydn did not indulge in chaotic music. According to the Bible, chaos reigned supreme, but serenity was the outstanding point in his interpretation of the "CREATION". Soft and melodious tunes becoming increased to a mezzo forte, when he painted the musical picture of the raging elements. We listened to the interpretation of the development of nature, flowers, trees, and the sweet murmur of the brooks; to the creation of animals and finally, of man. Thus Haydn revealed to us his sunny disposition and deep religious sentiment.</p>
   <p>If Haydn could have witnessed yesterday's performance, there is no doubt <pb facs="5418474_6_1577.jpg" n="2"/>he would have clasped the hand of Mr. Boeppler, and of every member of the orchestra, in grateful appreciation for the elegant and masterly performance of his great work. But, the Chicago Singing Society accomplished still more; namely, it drew a capacity audience, which is one of the rarest things on such occasions. "The Creation" has been performed in Chicago previously, but years have elapsed since it was presented in German. For this reason, and because the Chicago Singing Society enjoys an excellent reputation, it draws a capacity audience to Orchestra Hall which follows its performances with intense interest. If this society continues its splendid work, offering classical masterpieces of German musical literature, it will earn the gratitude of all German music lovers of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The choir was at its best. Mr. Boeppler must have derived pleasure indeed, directing singers whose vocal qualities and musical understanding turn performances of that type into a musical feat. On the <pb facs="5418474_6_1578.jpg" n="3"/>other hand, without a director of the type of Mr. Boeppler, a masterly performance like yesterday's "Creation" could not have been achieved. The soloists were: Mrs. Hannah Butler, and Messrs. John B. Miller, and Albert Boroff, professional concert singers, all of whom are Chicagoans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
