<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-02-03">February 3, 1914</date><title level="a">Personal Liberty</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0458</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0458.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-02-03">February 3, 1914</date><title level="a">PERSONAL LIBERTY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To be an American is not indicative of one's race or religion. It simply means to have a living faith in American ideals and principles, which is a part of the American citizenship.</p>
   <p>American ideals include very much, but one of the most important is the freedom of the individual. The Puritans came here to worship God according to the dictates of their conscience. The English Catholic came here and established Maryland for the same purpose. German Revolutionaries came to find political liberty, for which they fought in vain in their Old Country. The Irish came to escape feudalism. The Italians came to seek and to cultivate liberty, which guarantees better results for individual efforts. The Bohemians came to seek larger opportunities for their energies. The same is true of the Russians, the Poles, the Lithuanians, and others. They left the Old Country to escape the oppressions of the ruling classes.</p>
   <p>All these, in a certain sense, were Americans, before they arrived here, because of their adherence to American ideals. To this they added political or national citizenship, by becoming naturalized American citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0459.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The English who came from isolated farms, were accustomed to living alone with their families, and they introduced this system in the United States. But the continental Europeans lived in villages, around which their farmland was located. Social life was a necessity for them. The desires, tendencies and habits which he developed by reason of his social activities, he brought to America and to participate in social activities, is necessary for his well-being. The various clubs and societies have been organized to create opportunities for social gatherings...</p>
   <p>In all these things there is nothing which is un-American. A man, who is considered as one of the most typical Americans, none less than Theodore Roosevelt, has declared that "intemperance is mostly the result of isolated farm life, and is characteristic of farm helps and subordinates." Again he said: "The clearly recognizable satisfaction in many farm districts is in itself true evidence of social incompetence and degeneration." The movement, which he initiated, to open up the vast stretches of land in the West for farming purposes is planning the settlement in villages, for the definite <pb facs="5418474_6_0460.jpg" n="3"/>purpose of cultivating social life and activities.</p>
   <p>In such a speech in 1907, Mr. Roosevelt, then President of the United States, made this statement: "We have gained things which the Puritans did not have.... We have recaptured a joy of living, which was lost, but which is an excellent thing to possess and to cultivate for any nation."</p>
   <p>However, at the present time there is developing a tendency to make an end to this innocent and beneficial part of life. This tendency hides behind an attack upon a part only of our social life, the use of alcoholic drinks. But the attempt to enforce prohibition is only a part of the general ambition, namely the suppression of all social life with the exception of that part only, which is customary among the posterity of the English Puritans...." Prohibition is in direct opposition to personal liberty. But back of prohibition is the enslavement of all social and religious life. Prohibition has been inaugurated, and is being supported by the intolerant faction of our population, which calls itself typical American, but which is in reality, in regard to its ideals and <pb facs="5418474_6_0461.jpg" n="4"/>principles, entirely un-American. Prohibition is the forerunner of a movement against everything foreign, with the exception of Protestant principles of English origin. The spirit back of prohibition is the spirit of ignorance, racial prejudice and religious intolerance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
