<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-10-09">Oct. 9, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">Let Each Citizen Serve His Country</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0699</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0699.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-10-09">Oct. 9, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">LET EACH CITIZEN SERVE HIS COUNTRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An English language publication justly complains that in many districts congressmen and senators spend the time when Congress is adjourned attending to their private affairs, and that they fail to show the slightest interest in the cause which is dear to the heart of every patriot.</p>
   <p>It is apparent that this conduct deserves a sharp reprimand. On account of his position, every member of Congress who possesses ability and a sense of patriotism can do much in his district to further the good cause; furthermore the people who elected him have a right to expect that he will be concerned about the interests of the public and the welfare of the nation. Pretty or forceful speeches made in Congress are praiseworthy, and they <pb facs="5418474_6_0700.jpg" n="2"/>merit the gratitude of the country; but the duties of a representative of the people do not end therewith; he must also seek to successfully use his ability and influence outside the confines of Congress; and it is his special duty to use every means to furnish his constituents with aid. This is especially true during a crisis, at a time when all that our country stands for and everything that we esteem highly, is at stake.</p>
   <p>Recruiting must continue, since the Government needs many more troops, and many more subscriptions must be obtained to make the national loan a success. There is, generally speaking, much work to be done, and the ability of senators and representatives to organize and lead can be very useful; we hope that the people's representatives will not continue to neglect their duties. We refer especially to the Kentucky congressmen, about whom the newspapers of that state complain bitterly. Let them follow the example of their colleagues who have entered the army or organized regiments, and who have promoted the good cause of the Union by word and deed. When a ship is in <pb facs="5418474_6_0701.jpg" n="3"/>great danger the captain issues the command: "All hands on deck!" This command has been heard also on the good ship "Union," and everyone who does not wish to be looked upon as a coward, or who wishes to avoid being branded a traitor to his country had better do everything in his power to keep the good ship "Union" afloat!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
