<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-01-15">Jan. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">German Teachers' Association</title><title level="a" type="sub">Kruetgen Makes Address</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0972</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0972.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-01-15">Jan. 15, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN TEACHERS' ASSOCIATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Kruetgen Makes Address</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the monthly meeting of the Deutscher Lohrerverein [German Teachers' Association] which was held last night at the Bismarck Hotel, Mr. Ernest J. Kruetgen, the newly appointed member of the Board of Education, was among those present. In a brief speech he declared that it was his intention to give special care to German turn [gymnastics] instruction in the schools of Chicago. He also emphasized the necessity of co-operation among his colleagues and the advantages which the individual teacher would derive from it. He asked the German teachers always to remain loyal to their Association and not to pass up an opportunity for further education when they had the chance to do so.</p>
   <p>Later Dr. [Joseph] Philippson [Jewish], professor at the University of Chicago, gave a lecture, "Pedagogic Meditations on the War". He stressed the point that ignorance of German conditions on the part of Americans, including <pb facs="5418474_6_0973.jpg" n="2"/>educated people, and even among his own colleagues was appalling. He said that only due to the fact that surprisingly few Americans had a clear picture of Germany's geographical position and history, was it possible for the lying British propaganda press to find a gullible public which could be incited to hatred for Germany. The speaker suggested that his listeners arrange their class work so that the pupils could not only learn the German language but could also gain some comprehension of the German spirit, German history and geography, and the nature and philosophy of the German people.</p>
   <p>The question of whether the Teachers' Association should arrange a performance in the German theatre was discussed in detail but was finally referred to the chairman for consideration. Several new members were inducted into the Association which has about one hundred members altogether.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
