<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-05-08">May 8, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Bach Chorus</title><title level="a" type="sub">Concert in Orchestra Hall; Four Works Never before Heard in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1514</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1514.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-05-08">May 8, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO BACH CHORUS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Concert in Orchestra Hall; Four Works Never Before Heard in Chicago</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It will be hard for the Bach Chorus, under the baton of Dr. Sigfried Prager, to surpass the excellent performance it gave yesterday.</p>
   <p>This celebrated chorus sang with a degree of perfection it never had reached before. The program consisted of four cantatas which never before had been heard in Chicago. The chorus, strengthened by a boys' choir of sixty-four voices, sang with such a precision and above all, with such a devotion, as to animate the already extraordinary performance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1515.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But the soloists also kept themselves at the height of the chorus. By this is meant that although they sang in German, their diction was free from a disturbing accent.</p>
   <p>The soprano Else Harthan Arndt deserves first rank this time. She sang "Aria of the Christmas Cantata," "Sweet Comfort," and "My Jesus Comes." Her renditions at the piano turned out to be a great success.</p>
   <p>The tenor Erwin Kemp sang as he had never sung before in a Bach concert, and the basso, Mark Love will remain for a long time in the memory of many for his performance in the aria of the Lenten Cantata, which was accompanied <pb facs="5418474_6_1516.jpg" n="3"/>at the oboe obligato. Then Dr. Prager, as pianist as well as conductor, played the Brandenburg Concert # 5 in D major. It was more than an enjoyment, just as if Bach, amidst serious times, wanted also to have his carnival, but of his own style. The trio made up by the pianist, Dr. Prager, the flutist A. Liegl, and the violionist, Mr. J. Creicher, with the orchestra, was singularly beautiful. The orchestra, which consisted of members of the Chicago Symphony Orchestra, played with its well known perfection, accompanied on the organ by Tlanley Seder and on the piano by Philipp Warner.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1517.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The concert was well attended and the artists received hearty applause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
