<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-08">July 8, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Saint Paul's Penny</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0222</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0222.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-08">July 8, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">SAINT PAUL'S PENNY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The rumors which the communist leaders spread during recent months,predicting a universal strike--a great movement which might include anything, even a counterpart to the French revolution--had a very practical purpose, and served to advertise the picnic of the Fourth of July, an affair which lasted three days. During that time, many a St. Paul's penny was collected. The name of the communists' local "pope" is Paul, and the pennies gathered from the faithful are intended to provide a comfortable living for "Pope Paul". If a wag should say that the Swiss live mostly on strangers, then it may well be said that the communists thrive on dunces.</p>
   <p>Opinions differ as to the amount of pennies realized from the three-day picnic, but none of the estimates is high. As a speculation, the affair <pb facs="5418474_6_0223.jpg" n="2"/>seems to have been a fizzle. But then, every little helps, and anything is better than nothing. Just like the declaration in Lumpacivagabundus: "And if everything is gone, then we start again!" The begging then starts all over again--not by exhibiting one's clubfoot, but just by passing the hat; you must remember the old German proverb:</p>
   <p>"With hat in hand,</p>
   <p>You can travel throughout the land."</p>
   <p>Now that the nonsense has come to an end, and the revolution against existing laws has been avoided, the next problem is to see what can be done for the great mass of people who are not piece-workers--the common laborers. To claim that certain factions are definitely opposed to the demands of labor is just plain malice, but the assertion helps to collect many a penny. As soon as most people are convinced that a shortening of the workday would be <pb facs="5418474_6_0224.jpg" n="3"/>of benefit to everybody, necessary laws will be passed without much ado. But not before!</p>
   <p>To convince most of the people is not a simple problem, not as easy as bulldozing,of course; but reason is far more effective in the long run, and is the surest way to reach the goal. Bulldozing is contrary to the prevailing sentiment in the northern states--but attempts to influence public opinion by appealing to reason will produce favorable reactions.</p>
   <p>If the pennies,collected by the communists are used for propaganda purposes, that is, to convert citizens to the communistic faith, then no one can object.</p>
   <p>But the labor leaders must remember that screaming, denouncing, lying, and threatening do not convince, and even the most patient of listeners will <pb facs="5418474_6_0225.jpg" n="4"/>eventually be aroused, and reply in the same manner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
