<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-04-23">April 23, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">[Dr. Felix Behrendt Passes Away]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0987</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0987.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-04-23">April 23, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">[DR. FELIX BEHRENDT PASSES AWAY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Felix Behrendt died in the prime of his life, having reached the 36th year. He succumbed to an attack of Bronchial catarrh, at his home, 612 Orchard Street. He has been a highly honored physician who found true inspiration in performing his duties. His pure character and benevolent deeds which proved such a blessing to many will always be recognized by his host of patients and friends who will always remember him with esteem and gratitude. The news of his unexpected, untimely death created profound regret everywhere; perhaps the numerous expressions of condolence may console the grieved widow somewhat during the hours of a relentless fate.</p>
   <p>Dr. Felix Behrendt was born on his father's large farm at Dammerau in Western Prussia, graduated from Highschool at Neustadt and Konits, studied medicine at Berlin and passed his examinations at the University of Wuerzburg in the year 1886. Thereafter he entered the Colonial service of Holland, then the German and was transferred to Zanzibar.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0988.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After completion of his two-year service as doctor of the Imperial German Marine, he became assistant to Dr. Stelzner at Dresden, for the purpose of acquiring further experience in special branches. From there traveled to the United States, where he acted for a time as assistant to Dr. Schneider of Milwaukee, and then moved to Chicago. Within a very short time he succeeded in acquiring an extensive private practice, as a specialist in all diseases affecting the respiratory organs, which induced the Alexian Brothers Hospital to secure his valuable services. A profitable, pleasant future, was envisioned for him, when grim death suddenly tore his from the blessed field of his activity. May he rest in peace.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
