<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-06-04">June 4, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">[Babor and Patriotic Parade]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0180</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0180.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1888-06-04">June 4, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">[BABOR AND PATRIOTIC PARADE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We wonder if the generals and colonel of the Grand Army of the Republic, who marched so proudly through the streets last Decoration Day, knew of the death of the abolitionlist, John Glazebrook, who died after making the statement that all his spending of time, money, etc., to liberate the slaves in the south was in vain.</p>
   <p>What does it matter if the slave-drivers know that the conditions of the negroes are worse than before, that thousands of lives were sacrificed in vain, and that slavery is now taking a hold on the white race.</p>
   <p>While thousands join the money-bag parades, other thousands cast their glances towards Waldheim, where men, who sacrificed their lives for the liberation of the slaves, are buried.</p>
   <p>The wreaths sent from near and far, for that historic grave, came from people who knew that the emancipation of slaves was not completed, and this showed the spirit of Decoration Day among the working class of the United States.</p>
   <p>At this moment in Washington there is a life and death fight being made by one of <pb facs="5418474_6_0181.jpg" n="2"/>those veterans, who is idolized by the American people.</p>
   <p>General Phillip Sheridan was one of the leaders of the army, the adversary of the rebel-leader, Lee, who was forced through Sheridan to capitulate to Grant.</p>
   <p>Sheridan's march of victory left a trail of blood and devastation, he knew nothing of Garrison's noble achievements. He was a sergeant of the Prussian type, who looked at the war game as his trade.</p>
   <p>The world will not lose anything by his death.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
