<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-03">Nov. 3, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Charles H. Wacker and the Chicago Plan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-03">Nov. 3, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">CHARLES H. WACKER AND THE CHICAGO PLAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago plan may be well regarded as one of the most genial creations in the field of city planning. Chicago is indebted to it for a rapid expansion, a growth which astounded the world and which resulted in elevating our "Windy City" to the ranks of the leading cosmopolitan centers.</p>
   <p>This plan and the ceaseless energy to bring it to fruition are attributes of our city with which the name of Charles H. Wacker will forever be associated.</p>
   <p>The plan to provide a definite design for our city, the striving metropolis of the Middle West, commenced to shape itself definitely at the time of the Chicago World's Fair, in 1893.</p>
   <p>The chief engineer of the World's Fair, Daniel B. Burnham, and his assistant, <pb facs="5418474_6_1081.jpg" n="2"/>E. H. Bennett, were the original advocates of the plan, according to Charles H. Wacker. This modesty is one of the typical virtues of Wacker. Although he has been deeply involved in the plan, which no one doubts, he shows a certain self-effacement and gives unstinted credit to others, although he has labored fully as diligently as any other man affiliated with the venture.</p>
   <p>But in providing this plan, only the foundation for Chicago's future was laid.</p>
   <p>After all, it was the realization, the execution of the plan that gave us the deciding factor for the development of the city.</p>
   <p>And here, there is only one name, only one man who deserves the credit for the achievement which required considerable diplomacy, energy, and much patience in bringing this plan to culmination; and that is Charles H. Wacker.</p>
   <p>The History of the Plan</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1082.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The ideas of Burnham, Bennett, and Wacker at the time of the Chicago World's Fair, in 1893, were often discussed in the Commercial Club of Chicago and also at the Merchants' Club.</p>
   <p>In 1906, a committee was appointed to consider it. Charles D. Morton, president of the Merchants' Club, nominated its members. A year later both clubs combined and appealed to Fred Busse, Chicago's mayor at that time, to appoint a commission to consider the planning of a greater Chicago.</p>
   <p>The mayor acquiesced, and within a year the commission was created with due concurrence by the city council.</p>
   <p>Wacker was a member of it from the very beginning.</p>
   <p>The members of this commission, so it was agreed, were the elected mayor, the members of the city council, the department heads of our diverse city administration, and to this a suitable number of citizens were added. Of <pb facs="5418474_6_1083.jpg" n="4"/>the latter, they chose those who were particularly adapted through their economic and social position to properly represent the interests of the public.</p>
   <p>The first president of the Chicago Plan Commission - that was the name of the new commission - was Charles D. Norton. He retired from this position two years later. Charles H. Wacker accepted it, remaining in that post fully fifteen years. He worked with an enthusiasm and energy which has seldom been equalled in this country because after all, no emoluments were attached to this office.</p>
   <p>In 1927, however, ill health compelled Wacker to resign from the Commission. Valuable support was given to Wacker by the administrational director, Walter S. Moody, and his successor, Eugene S. Taylor.</p>
   <p>What is the Chicago Plan?</p>
   <p>In Wacker's own words the plan comprised four definite principles in controlling <pb facs="5418474_6_1084.jpg" n="5"/>Chicago's future building developments: Uniformity, orderliness, conformability, and suitability.</p>
   <p>As Wacker described it, it was a definite ideal, something intangible which we cannot grasp, akin to the sailor who watches the storm-tossed waves of the ocean. We follow indications, trends, and finally reach the goal.</p>
   <p>The first object of the plan was to provide diagonal arterial highways of sufficient width to provide unhampered traffic to the main business section of the city, and this was particularly important in view of the transportation problems at that time. Next were a sufficient number of connecting links and enough bridges of modern design to be practical in giving adequate relief to the ever-increasing traffic and congestion. Furthermore, the architectural designs were to be of such a nature as to be a fitting ornament to the city, besides complying with utility in general.</p>
   <p>The public did not always give unanimous approval to the suggestions of the <pb facs="5418474_6_1085.jpg" n="6"/>planning commission and this proved mostly detrimental to our citizenry.</p>
   <p>Here, for instance, one may give a glaring example: the projected widening of Halsted Street.</p>
   <p>At the time when the Commission broached this subject, the landowners and merchants objected on the grounds that the high cost of such improvements would make it prohibitive. They would not be able to bear the cost.</p>
   <p>Halsted Street remained narrow, much too narrow for its natural traffic. Many years later the property owners of the street appeared before the Chicago Plan Commission, requesting that the street be widened. But it was too late then.</p>
   <p>The mounting costs, particularly the payments for condemnation, had risen so much that the project had to be postponed indefinitely.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1086.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Similar difficulties confronted the Commission in its attempt to widen Michigan Boulevard. Endless law suits ensued and had to be settled before the city acquired the legal right--whereby the Plan Commission was finally enabled to proceed in giving the city a thoroughfare, commensurate with the traffic demands.</p>
   <p>Today the landowners on this street are more than glad that they lost their law suits. Not only was the widening of Michigan Boulevard a dire necessity, but the widening of this thoroughfare greatly increased property values.</p>
   <p>Aside from the widening of Michigan Boulevard, the creation of the Outer Drive and Lake Shore Drive, all instigated by the Chicago Plan Commission under Wacker's leadership, one must mention above all the changes of South Water Street, that historical road, Chicago's oldest street.</p>
   <p>Here Wacker would not rest until this neglected street became a double-deck, modern thoroughfare.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1087.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>This road now bears the name of its creator, Wacker Drive.</p>
   <p>The Future Plans</p>
   <p>Among the future plans that are supposed to be realized within the next few years, and which represent the far-reaching vision of Wacker, is a new depot to replace the antiquated structure of the Illinois Central Railroad, on Park Row and Michigan Boulevard. The new depot is to be located south of the present station. Particular stress is laid on one point, that it shall conform architecturally to the classical lines of the new Field Museum, and the new Aquarium. This will decidedly improve the appearance of the city.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, a large connecting bridge between the Southern and Northern Outer Drive has been contemplated. This will greatly facilitate and speed up northern and southern traffic.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1088.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Thirdly, the eastern part of the Chicago River, between Eighteenth Street and Polk Street; is slated for changes, in order to lengthen La Salle Street in a southerly direction. The old river bed will have to be filled in and a new one will have to be built. Small wonder that such gigantic plans were often regarded as "dreams" and were even rewarded with ridicule.</p>
   <p>A new Post Office is to be erected. According to indications, it will cover six acres and the estimated cost is twelve million dollars, in round figures. Here also the Plan Commission's opinions will be the deciding factors. Their dictum provides that aside from the standpoint of utility it must also have architectural value as befits a modern public building.</p>
   <p>Also a new Union Depot has been regarded by the Chicago Plan Commission as a necessary adjunct of the city. Many other improvements have been listed, too numerous to be enumerated here.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1089.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>Wacker fought with incomparable energy for the aims of the Chicago Plan Commission. We do not overrate his efforts by attributing Chicago's large growth and planned beauty to his efforts.</p>
   <p>Did Not Rule - Convinced</p>
   <p>According to Wacker's opinion it would have been useless to inaugurate these far-reaching plans of the Chicago Plan Commission by resorting to municipal decrees. He did not intend to rule, he desired, above all, to convince. He wished to obtain the confidence of the masses by showing the evident benefits and proving the necessity of the proposed changes and additions.</p>
   <p>Propaganda was, and had to be, resorted to. The spoken word, written matter, and even films did their share. And this publicity even permeated the schools. From here the children brought the news to their elders, and, consequently, there is not a person living in our Chicago who does not know what the Chicago plan represents and why one or another improvement is a civic necessity.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1090.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>All Chicago is fully aware today that these diverse labors not only beautify our city, but that they solve the technical problems of our complex traffic. More than that the plan anticipates future needs. In connection with this, one need only point to the hopeless traffic snarls of outer city streets, the so-called automobile routes, during evening hours.</p>
   <p>Here human vision has provided a far-reaching plan, at present premature, but the only feasible means to give Chicago an opportunity to grow - as befits a world metropolis; at least, it facilitates matters.</p>
   <p>Fully convinced that he was fighting for a worthy cause that benefits the people and brooks no regression by tiring and lagging efforts, Wacker wrote the following words in 1927:</p>
   <p>"Finally, permit me to declare: All who are involved in the beautification of Chicago, draw their inspiration from a historical retrospection of our city.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1091.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>I earnestly implore every individual citizen to heed this inner call--it is an enthusiasm that leads to the performance of future deeds. As he looks into the past, he will perceive examples of united labor, united plans, intertwined by faith and a belief in the future of our city. Before his inner eye, his subconscious mind, appear dreams leading to reality. When the spirit of 1871 and 1893 rules our younger generation, then we, the pioneers, can confidently entrust our burden to our sons."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
