<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-09">Dec. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A Dreadful Chicago Ruin by the Reverend C. A. Koenig</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0870</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0870.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-09">Dec. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A DREADFUL CHICAGO RUIN by The Reverend C. A. Koenig</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In old Europe we have seen many beautiful and picturesque ruins. They are placed in a romantic setting, on the Rhine, or on a high cliff, "looking proudly over the lands," as the poet has so beautifully described it in the poem, "The Singers' Curse".</p>
   <p>These ruins in Germany and other countries are landmarks of olden times. Once they were castles "proud and defiant," but now they are dilapidated, destroyed, for the most part, during the everlasting feuds of knighthood and medieval warfare, in the peasant wars and the Thirty Years' War (1618-1648).</p>
   <p>In Italy, too, we saw ruins dating back to the time of the Romans, in Verona, Rome, and other regions, and in Tuscany, even some prehistoric ones.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0871.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All these ruins were beautiful in a romantic sort of way, covered with ivy and moss, melancholy and historically interesting, calling to mind the true saying: "World history is world judgment."</p>
   <p>In Chicago, too, one can view a ruin, right in the center of one of the most populated neighborhoods of the metropolis. Thousands of people pass by there every week. This ruin, however, is not romantic and sublimely beautiful, but is ugly in the truest meaning of the word. It is located at South Ashland Avenue, on the east side of the street, between 13th Street and Washburn Avenue, and covers almost an entire block between these last-named streets. This large ruin has existed for over three years.</p>
   <p>All the windows in this great two-story building are broken. Refuse of all sorts has collected around this disgraceful spot. Rats as big as young cats walk in and out. At the second story, eight balconies, or porches,--or whatever you want to call those old wooden stalls--hang far over the side-walk. After a rain, black and brownish drops fall on the hats and clothes <pb facs="5418474_6_0872.jpg" n="3"/>of passing pedestrians. It is the water that has collected on these filthy balconies. The sidewalk itself has sunk in several feet, and has been surrounded, for three years, by a patched-up wooden fence, which bears the legend: "Bureau of Streets, City of Chicago".</p>
   <p>This ruin is really worthy of inspection--for thirty-six months it has been the target of youthful rowdies, a rendezvous par excellence for shady characters, a breeding place of contagious diseases, a daily effrontery aesthetically and a blot on the beautiful city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The other day we asked a question of a servant of the holy brotherhood of Irishmen, in other words, a policeman, in this poetic manner: "Whence will salvation come unto this citadel?" Whereupon he made the prosaic reply: "I don't know, sir; probably never, for this citadel belongs to Mr. Carter Harrison." . . . . .</p>
   <p>Strange! When, in this year of 1918, the Bureau of Streets called our <pb facs="5418474_6_0873.jpg" n="4"/>attention to the fact that our sidewalk showed two sunken spots before our church and parish, we had the sidewalk repaired immediately for a cash outlay of seven hundred shiny U. S. dollars.</p>
   <p>Carter Harrison? "Stop, peasant, this is something else again," we used to say in our Swabian home district.</p>
   <p>Last week, in the Daily News, Mr. Carter Harrison described his impressions and experiences in northern France. On this occasion he also described the ruins of towns and villages there, which were the work of the "Huns". At any rate, German as well as Allied aerial bombs and cannon--according to the luck of war--have contributed to the wrecking. We certainly feel sorry for those poor people who now find their beloved homes in ruins. We are in favor of complete reconstruction of these damaged homes.</p>
   <p>Just the same--we found the description of the ruins as given by Mr. Carter Harrison somewhat curious. How about that dreadful ruin on Ashland Avenue? <pb facs="5418474_6_0874.jpg" n="5"/>Isn't our shirt closer to us than our coat? Maybe the owner of this civilization-defying ruin is saying to himself: Why not? Only Jews live there! Before God, before every right-thinking person, and before the law, a Jew is just as good, and just as good a citizen as a Christian, a heathen, or a Mohammedan. Our politicians of the Tenth Ward, of the city and of the state very much appreciate our "Jewish" votes at election time.</p>
   <p>Besides, Christians also live in the neighborhood of the dreadful three-year-old abomination. In the immediate vicinity there are two beautiful German churches, the Zion Evangelical Church and the (Lutheran) Immanuel Evangelical Church. There is, furthermore, the beautiful Ashland Boulevard and the new and widened Twelfth Street. But the whole thing, especially the well-known Ashland Avenue, with its heavy traffic, is fearfully disgraced by this big, hideous ruin. Again--"When will salvation come to this spot of shame?"</p>
   <p>If Mr. Carter Harrison has such influence that he can afford to let this <pb facs="5418474_6_0875.jpg" n="6"/>dangerous, large, and ugly building stand for some time to come, then all we can do is to "hide in the bushes" for another three or ten years and exclaim, with Martin Luther: "Our power is for naught and soon we shall be lost." [Translator's note: The last is a quotation from Luther's church hymn "Ein' Feste Burg ist Unser Gott"]</p>
   <p>But, then, we are equally convinced of the truth in the saying:"There is something rotten--in the city of Chicago."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
