<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-12">Feb. 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Our Building Activity</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0040</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0040.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-12">Feb. 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">OUR BUILDING ACTIVITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Building, at least for private purposes, is one of the industries which came to an almost complete standstill during the War. Lack of men and materials, and transportation difficulties, as well as the economic uncertainty of the immediate future, were the chief causes for the curtailment of building long before the time when the Government saw fit to place legal restrictions on private building. Then again, the drafting of thousands of marriageable young men into war service did great damage to the real-estate business. Building was costly and afforded little profit. Many tried to dispose of their property because of the change in economic conditions, and there were but few buyers who acquired lots with the intention of erecting a home for themselves. Since the War has now been successfully concluded, the Government has lifted the restrictions which it once placed upon building, and we may look forward to a general and rapid revival of this industry.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0041.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>According to the estimates of real-estate experts there is a great lack of homes in America at the present time. This lack does not appear uniform in all localities; it is prevalent chiefly in the cities. About 320,000 new homes will be needed in the United States every year, according to carefully compiled statistics. Hardly any new homes were built last year. As a result about 700,000 new homes are necessary immediately, and building activity should increase greatly and rapidly as soon as mild weather can be looked for.</p>
   <p>It is true, there is no superabundance of building material on hand at this time. The materials which we had in stock were used for war purposes. But present supplies should be sufficient to meet the immediate demands, and additional supplies will very likely be forthcoming in the near future. The lack of workers, too, can quickly be remedied. Among the soldiers who are returning to civil life there are many mechanics who will gladly avail themselves of the opportunity to earn good wages, for wages are higher today than they were before the War. Salaries are higher than they ever were. Of course, the cost of living has also advanced, but we may hope that the limit of the rise in prices has been reached, and that no further <pb facs="5418474_6_0042.jpg" n="3"/>increase need be feared. In the coming spring and during the coming summer there will be a general drop in prices, and next winter's prices for food and other necessities will be much lower, than those now prevailing.</p>
   <p>At all events, economic conditions will be stabilized, and we will view the future with fewer misgivings. The young people who are returning from the War will be thinking of establishing homes for rearing families. Our citizens are accustomed to live in their own homes if they possibly can, and have an innate dislike for renting living quarters, whether these be called "tenements," or are known by the proud name, "apartments". Morality and sanitation make the one-family home preferable to duplex homes, which destroy all desire for individuality and deprive human beings of air, light, and rest. Much can be said against "apartments," and precious little for them. Above all, we should encourage workers, thousands of whom, for obvious reasons, live in dirty barns in which a respectable farmer would not house even his animals, to establish their own homes. They (the workers) will be rewarded for their efforts by physically and morally clean children.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0043.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>And it is more economical to live in one's own home than it is to rent living quarters. Acquiring a home encourages thrift and is often the foundation of subsequent wealth.</p>
   <p>To those who are without means, building and loan associations, which are established on the principle of reciprocity, are a great help in financing a home. Many people have acquired homes in this way. This system could be greatly expanded with the aid of the Government. Much would be gained, if builders of homes could borrow money at the low rates at which farmers may obtain capital. The Federal Government is working on such a plan at the present time. If the plan proves to be workable, the one-family house will play a more important part in the life of our country than it does now, and that would be a great blessing to our people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
