<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-01-27">Jan. 27, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Soldiers' Pension Law</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0302</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0302.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-01-27">Jan. 27, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE SOLDIERS' PENSION LAW</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Hayes has been found wanting, as might have been expected, considering his weak character. He did not veto the bill which was passed under the rotten pretext of "Justice for the Nation's defenders," but the purpose of which is the looting of the Treasury. Instead of returning the document unsigned to Congress, he affixed his signature--and thus the bill becomes a law.</p>
   <p>The moral cowardice involved in the President's action becomes quite apparent when compared to the intrepid courage of ex-President Grant, who twice vetoed the measure and thus protected the Treasury and National credit from Congressional depredations.</p>
   <p>Even if Grant had practiced nepotism to a higher degree than the virtuous civil service reformer Hayes, still the decided difference in Grant's conduct in respect to the "bounty equalization" (sic) would have far outweighed Hayes' lamentable <pb facs="5418474_6_0303.jpg" n="2"/>acquiescence in the proposed plundering plan.</p>
   <p>Instead of preventing this raid on the Treasury by a decisive veto Mr. Hayes apparently prefers to let Congress shoulder the responsibility. He knows that there is no money available to make the law effective: the twenty-nine million dollars appropriated for the fund apply only to the regular pensions provided in former sessions. If Congress intends to have this law enforced, then a new appropriation should be authorized. If the money thus advanced in accordance with our existing financial statutes exceeds our revenues, then it is the problem of Congress to raise sufficient capital and yet maintain a balanced budget by increasing taxes or devising new levies.</p>
   <p>Congress will probably look askance at this attitude. To be regarded as benevolent and liberal to the "country's defenders," and then to hold the Administration accountable for any deficit resulting from such generosity, would be a pleasing prospect for our lawmakers. But to assume responsibility for the <pb facs="5418474_6_0304.jpg" n="3"/>destruction of the "Democratic reputation for economy" so laboriously built up in the last two years, or to incur the public indignation which would result from an increased tax load--for which the elation of the pensioners would be no substitute--is another matter. Therefore it is quite possible that, in view of the approaching end of the Congressional session, the essential appropriation will not be acted upon. And thus the Democratic members of the next Congress will be obliged to eat the sour apples which will create bad prospects for the Democratic party in 1880. It is not unlikely that the crafty members of Hayes' Cabinet who advised the President to adopt the bill based their calculations on the logic of dyed-in-the-wool ward politicians instead of on the principles worthy of honest statesmen.</p>
   <p>One of the amusing incidents of the debate on the subject [pensions] is the following proposal (as it appeared in the Cincinnati Enquirer): That Congress add an amendment to the bill whereby all payments under this law should be made in silver dollars. This would be a new attempt to compel the restoration of that "much-abused and timid child"--the "dollar of our fathers".</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0305.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Suppose that a man who was discharged from the army in perfect health fifteen years ago now suffers from a liver complaint or gout--the origin of which some obliging physician ascribes to the ordeals of the war. If such a "veteran" were given fifteen or sixteen hundred dollars as a retroactive pension he would accept it, even if it were a burdensome, one-hundred-pound ingot of solid silver. After all, beggars must not be choosers. And it is just as likely that this unexpected windfall of silver which is to be received by the postwar"wounded" will go into circulation, and will be squandered like the bundles of greenbacks which were paid the army in 1865. Whether such measures will make silver money more popular or less is an open question. The experience of the past indicates the latter.</p>
   <p>It is difficult to find a single businessman who would not prefer the most soiled ten-dollar bill to ten silver dollars which any sub-treasury is willing to give him in exchange for it.</p>
   <p>In view of all this, opponents of the coinage of silver may come together in <pb facs="5418474_6_0306.jpg" n="5"/>an open alliance on this proposal which, would in effect, circulate twenty to thirty million silver dollars through small trade channels. This would create difficulty for all those holding heavy, clumsy cartwheel dollars. It would seriously affect the gentry who, a year ago, screamed themselves hoarse in the quest of silver, because they had hoped to cheat their creditors out of fifteen per cent with the aid of silver dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
