<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-03-12">Mar. 12, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Henry Marchetti Dies</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Tyrolean Men's Chorus Loses its Founder and Conductor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1509</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1509.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-03-12">Mar. 12, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">HENRY MARCHETTI DIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Tyrolean Men's Chorus Loses Its Founder and Conductor</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After a long illness, Mr. Henry Marchetti died yesterday evening at his home, 2146 Irving Park Blvd. With him passes away one of the best known German-Americans of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Marchetti was born in 1878 in Scharwitz, Tyrol. His inborn musical talent drew him to the peasant theatre, with several troupes of which he traveled throughout Germany.</p>
   <p>In the year 1910 he came to America with a peasant group from Oberammergau. This group, which visited most of the large cities in the country, is still no doubt in the memory of the oldest German-Americans. Its performances were greeted everywhere with great enthusiasm and applause. After two years <pb facs="5418474_6_1510.jpg" n="2"/>with the group, Mr. Marchetti and Ferdl Nagel took over its direction.</p>
   <p>The Oberammergau actors traveled all over the country. Twice they went as far as the Pacific coast, and in 1915 the Company played under Marchetti's direction at the exposition in San Francisco. Later the group, reorganized under his management, traveled through the South, Texas, and New England. It even visited with success the Northeastern part of Canada.</p>
   <p>Finally, getting tired of wandering, he longed for a home and a fireplace. After living in New York for a while, he settled in Chicago, where he was engaged as a Zither player at a place on North Avenue. When the place was closed on account of the prohibition, Mr. Marchetti took over the position of conductor at the Vienna Ball Room, and in later years played in Marie Hillebrand's "Munchener Kindl." He was also co-founder and for <pb facs="5418474_6_1511.jpg" n="3"/>many years a conductor of the Tyrolean Mens Chorus, the rapid and successful development of which must be placed to his credit.</p>
   <p>His passing away is mourned by his widow, Martha Marchetti, and a son by his first wife, Christoph Marchetti.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
