<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-29">July 29, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">A New Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0792</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0792.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-29">July 29, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About thirty ladies and gentlemen attended a meeting at 13 South Halsted Street yesterday evening to found the Working Woman's Industrial Protective Union. Mrs. Anna Schrock opened the meeting in a lengthy, well-prepared address, wherein she stressed the suffering and the low wages which are the lot of women, and that only an organization can mitigate the evil.</p>
   <p>Mrs. F. B. Kingsbury said that a similar association exists in California, and is very successful.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Mills remarked that an alliance with labor unions and co-operative enterprises would bring quicker results.</p>
   <p>The chairman declared that the most important matters at present were the election of officers and the membership drive. Any workingwoman can become a member by paying twenty-five cents, and dues for the year amount to only <pb facs="5418474_6_0793.jpg" n="2"/>one dollar. The income of the association is to be used to pay hall rent and other expenses. If the organization is successful, several rooms will be rented and furnished to shelter women and children in need. Perhaps even a school may be added later. An employment bureau is also to be organized as soon as possible. It is the object of the association to help all women earn better wages.</p>
   <p>At the end of Mrs. Schrock's speech, a gentleman arose and nominated Mrs. Anna Schrock as president of the new association. The gentleman proved to be Attorney Marcus Monroe Brown, whom Arabella McLaughlin tried to shoot some time ago....</p>
   <p>Mrs. Schrock was elected president; Mrs. Kingsbury, vice-president; Mrs. Barnum, treasurer. Mrs. Mills, secretary; but Mrs. Mills declined, because she did not share Mrs. Schrock's views. Then the "protector of poor widows," M. M. Brown, was nominated secretary by the president. In the interim, <pb facs="5418474_6_0794.jpg" n="3"/>rumors spread concerning Brown's character, and his election did not arouse enthusiasm by any means, but he considered it proper to give a speech, in which he declared that the success of the organization was assured.</p>
   <p>One of the ladies present suggested that the members attend the meetings of the Working Women's Union [another organization] which are held every two weeks at Uhlich's Hall, where labor questions, and women's problems in labor matters in particular, are discussed.</p>
   <p>The president did not like that remark at all. She said that she had her own ideas on how to ameliorate the conditions confronting women, and that she had a high goal in mind. She felt grieved when thinking of the thousands of poor girls leading a life of shame, and who could be saved by such an organization as the present one. She has had to endure persecutions because of her views, but expressed determination to continue her efforts. Whoever was not willing to help her, should not be affiliated with the organization. <pb facs="5418474_6_0795.jpg" n="4"/>After that, about a half-dozen names were entered on the membership list, and an equal number of quarters collected, whereupon the assembly adjourned until next Monday evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
