<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-01-25">Jan. 25, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Kreisler Concert.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1542</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1542.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-01-25">Jan. 25, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">KREISLER CONCERT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An appearance of Fritz Kreisler is always one of the events of the season. This is proven by the fact that he dares to give his concert in the Auditorium, where others have to be satisfied with small halls and are glad if they are filled. Only Paderewski can attract such a tremendous audience.</p>
   <p>In what lies Kreisler's almost unprecendented popularity? It is not this certainly highly-eminent virtuosity alone. In our era we have large numbers of great violinists produced by Leopold Auer in the last decade. With Kreisler it is something additional. Every German heart is beating for him, for his wonderfully generous labor of love during the war, in whose services he placed his great art. For this reason his Austrian compatriots love "our Fritz" and none of them will miss a concert when he comes.</p>
   <p>And it is the same with the other Germans. But only half of his listeners are German, the other half consisting of real Americans. Because nothing causes them to respect him more than the manly courage, which he displayed when he was surrounded by a howling, abusing, foaming crowd, he, an imperial Austrian officer, firmly drew his bow across his violin. For all these <pb facs="5418474_6_1543.jpg" n="2"/>reasons, love and respect are his rewards. Besides, he is a great artist.</p>
   <p>He appears more mature today. This is proven by his program - all classical compositions including the Vieuxtemps concerto which does not offer many opportunities for glamour. But cheap virtuoso pieces are not Kreisler's affair. Beautiful, serious holy art! How manly sounds his Beethoven (C Minor Sonata), how full and rich his Bach (E Minor partita); "LaFolia" by Corelli, pleased me best.</p>
   <p>The enthusiasm of the listeners was tremendous. They did not want to leave until he played some additional pieces. In conclusion we want to mention the excellent piano-accompaniment by Carl Lamson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
