<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-08">Jan. 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Warning for Over-Zealous Settlers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0849</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0849.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-08">Jan. 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">WARNING FOR OVER-ZEALOUS SETTLERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After the opening for settlement of a large part of Oklahoma several years ago, a venture which was exceptionally successful, preparations are now being made to make additional tracts available, lands which the redskins relinquished.</p>
   <p>A well-meaning German farmer of Union County, Oklahoma, gives sensible advice to prospective homesteaders.</p>
   <p>"I consider it imperative to give timely advice to friends and to those who contemplate settling in this region. The journey should not be made until the prospective farmer has made his selection and is prepared to take possession of his acres. Thus far, many ambitious settlers arrived here without sufficient funds to live on. Such people find themselves in a deplorable position, because there is no opportunity at present to <pb facs="5418474_6_0850.jpg" n="2"/>earn money. The territory is well populated, but during the winter the farmers are not very busy; aside from this, even with the best of intentions, strangers find it impossible to obtain jobs.</p>
   <p>"I believe it is my duty to inform my compatriots that this conglomerate of impecunious people who arrived here in quest of homesteads, must suffer considerable hardships and even want ere they realize their expectations. Many sleep in wagons, or even under the bare sky, as they have no means to find a better shelter. Months will pass before the designated sections are available for entry. Of course, the aforesaid does not apply to those who have enough money to tide them over.</p>
   <p>"In connection with the above, I might mention that, according to the latest information, the opening date has been postponed. Originally, it was scheduled for May, but unforseen circumstances intervened and it had to be postponed for several months. Until the officials have allocated new <pb facs="5418474_6_0851.jpg" n="3"/>lands to the Indians, farms to which they are legally entitled, it will be impossible to open the district to the White settlers. The deals with the Indians proceed slowly, exceptionally so, due to rampant contagious diseases, which broke out lately. It is said that the President may delay the opening proclamation until the Fall.</p>
   <p>"Furthermore, the pioneers do not receive this land gratuitously. It is acquired under the Homestead laws; upon proving up, a payment of $200 for every Quarter Section [160 acres; 1/2 mile long and 1/2 mile wide. Transl.] must be made to Uncle Sam.</p>
   <p>"However, title to the land can be obtained within 14 months, if a person is able to make the $200 payment to the Land Office at the end of that period, and provided that he lived on it and cultivated the ground according to the legal requirements."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
