<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-02-14">February 14, 1890</date><title level="a">To the Editor German Apothecary Diploma in Illinois.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1019</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1019.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-02-14">February 14, 1890</date><title level="a">TO THE EDITOR GERMAN APOTHECARY DIPLOMA IN ILLINOIS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American "Doctor" - title is not recognized in Germany. However, the possessor of such a diploma is on a par, or rather is classified and has the same rights, as a medical student who has graduated from a German gymnasium (high school). He has the choice of displaying his doctor- diploma in a frame, or leaving it in his trunk. He may look at it whenever he feels inclined and exclaim: "I am an M. D. after all."</p>
   <p>What different experiences a prescription clerk of a drug store, duly supplied with a German diploma, finds here! Not only is it entirely ignored, but he is not permitted to make up a prescription without the supervision of a "registered clerk" or the regular druggist!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1020.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In order to be eligible for registration, he must first serve for a certain period as apprentice in the state of Illinois, gain his knowledge by washing windows, bottles, and make himself generally useful by selling patent-medicines. Anyone who passed his examinations before the Board of Pharmacy, is a registered pharmacist, or a senior clerk.</p>
   <p>Now then, what does such an examination consist of? It is made up of the trickiest questions which the examiners can gather from all conceivable books and which they, themselves, are not able to answer- without looking into the various volumes. Questions which are as useful to a drug dispenser as sauerkraut is to a canary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1021.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Lately, three German pharmacists appeared before the Board of Pharmacy. All of them are experts in their vocations, recognized, and more capable than any of their examiners. (The German element is not represented any longer on the Board). What was the result? The Germans failed. Why? - Because they answered the silly questions and showed too much intelligence. A few examples follow:</p>
   <p>"What is the difference between odorless (deodorized) and ordinary (simple) tincture of opium?" One of the German gentlemen gave this answer: "Deodorized tincture of opium should be free of narcotin, according to the pharmacopoeia but," he added, "during the ten years I have been in the United States, I have not found an opium tincture which is free from this ingredient." This was correct but evidently it heaped insult upon the apothecary gentry.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1022.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Another question: "What are the symptoms of poisoning from digitalis and its derivatives and what antidotes would you use?" Here we have it! Men who do not know how and where to find the human pulse-beat, ask toxicological-pathological questions. It is all very good, that a drug-clerk or even a layman should know something about toxicology, (science of poisons), but would he dare treat such a case on his own initiative, without being a physician?</p>
   <p>The next question was about the compounding of a pharmaceutical preparation. The answer broke the candidates neck; since, after his reply, he could not refrain from adding, that a practical drug salesman should always consult the pharmacopoeia, as cursory memorizing of its general contents, is not practically applicable and will inevitably lead to constant errors. He was absolutely correct, but then, no one asked him for his opinion.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1023.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>How well the applicants answered their questions, I know from personal investigation, yet, they failed. Why? Because the answers they gave, with their annotations, were scratched and considered as insufficient.</p>
   <p>The examination consisted of 150 questions. If one fills out the questionnaire, with or without help by looking at one's cuffs, which have been previously inscribed with gentle reminders and one is 75 per cent correct, that is, in the sense of the examiners, then the registration will be certified.</p>
   <p>Whether the examinee is capable of preparing a prescription or any preparation, lege artis, is immaterial. Of what benefit, then, is the German's diploma? Well, he may hang it in his shanty to cover up a few dirt spots or hide a bedbug nest, but to indulge in that introspection: "After all, I am a pharmacist," that is an untenable consolation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1024.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The writer knows many American clerks and pharmaceutists who do not know, that natrium and sodium or calcium and potassium are the same thing, who would not accept a prescription written in Latin, because they could not read "Dutch," who looked in a half a dozen books for aqua fervida and aqua frigida (hot and cold water) and then sent to a "German pharmacy" for some of that "imported stuff" - since they had sold their available stock. May science long live:</p>
   <p>Kendelhof.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
