<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-09-21">Sept. 21, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Progress</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1266</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1266.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-09-21">Sept. 21, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">PROGRESS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>German industries are making progress. A noteworthy example is the copper and iron manufacturing concern of Conrad Kattentidt. The factory, built of brick, covers an area of 50 by 100 feet, and there are barns and wagon sheds in addition. The buildings were erected in July and August under the supervision of the architect, F. W. Wolf. The masonry work was done by the contractor Fred Hausser; the woodwork by Andrew Katz. The forge and machinery are in the basement. The office, the assembly room, and the stock room are on the first floor.</p>
   <p>A copper boiler of 320-barrel capacity is now under construction, designed by A. Dehne and Company of St. Louis. The boiler is being built for Anhaeuser's brewery in St. Louis.</p>
   <p>The second floor is used as a workshop for lighter wares. The entire building <pb facs="5418474_6_1267.jpg" n="2"/>is well illuminated and ventilated. From 75 to 100 people are employed.</p>
   <p>Conrad Kattentidt learned his trade in the largest factories in Germany and is an experienced coppersmith. He built up his trade to such an extent within a dozen years that he eliminated Eastern competition and made all the boilers and copperwork for the breweries in the West,--the largest breweries in the United States.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kattentidt will be pleased to show his factory to prospective customers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
