<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-16">Aug. 16, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">But If!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0558</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0558.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-16">Aug. 16, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">BUT IF!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As we are writing, very alarming reports about President Garfield's condition are being published; one of the sheets, anxious to make a few extra pennies, even announces that the president is dying. Up to the present this statement is false, but a turn for the worse is possible before press time. It may be that the excessive number of doctors may well cause Garfield's death, since none of these surgeons has dared to do the proper thing at the proper time, so that Garfield's tombstone might well bear the inscription:</p>
   <p>"Died with the aid of Dr. Bliss, Barnard, Woodward, etc."</p>
   <p>How would so tragic a result affect political conditions? The people would be profoundly affected, although not to the same degree as if the President had died on July 2 [the date of the assassination] because in the last six weeks most people have become aware that death may ensue. Nevertheless all the <pb facs="5418474_6_0559.jpg" n="2"/>emotions aroused after the first news was received on July 2 would manifest themselves anew; grief, fury, and dismay would vent themselves a thousandfold. All the newspapers would print eulogies, and as in all cases of such a nature, the characteristics of the departed would be distorted because not only the statements of the daily papers but also the chroniclers who write for more enduring publications would give more glowing accounts than in the case of a man who had died after the completion of his official term, when everything that he did would have been colored by party hatred. And of course great sympathy would be expressed for the President's bereaved family, fully consistent with the American people's kindness of heart.</p>
   <p>However, the effect of the President's death upon our economic life would be only of short duration. Fortunately the fate of the country does not depend upon the life or the death of an individual, not even of that of the highest official. Undoubtedly during the first few days the gamblers on the stock exchange would try to exploit the disaster, and the stocks and bonds of large corporations might fluctuate, but only for a few days. Afterwards matters <pb facs="5418474_6_0560.jpg" n="3"/>would continue in the usual manner.</p>
   <p>The most important effects of Garfield's death would be in the field of party politics. How Arthur would act as President, that is a problem concerning which many opinions prevail. Would he show more tact and common sense than heretofore, as many people now assert, or would he follow the precedent set by Andrew Johnson? Would Arthur consider himself Garfield's [political] successor and the administrator of his policies, or would the new President surprise the world by his ungratefullness toward his former master, Conkling, as Prince Felix Schwarzenburg comported himself in his sudden anti-Russian attitude in Europe? Would the new President keep the present cabinet in the main, or would he fulfill the intentions of Guiteau [Garfield's assassin] , in other words, make Conkling the ruling spirit and thus become a Stalwart of the Stalwarts? These are questions which no one can answer at this time, perhaps not even Arthur himself.</p>
   <p>But even if the answer were ever so unsatisfactory, a country which could endure <pb facs="5418474_6_0561.jpg" n="4"/>a Tyler and an Andrew Johnson without permanent injury might even get along with Arthur. After all, what does it matter if several hundred government jobs are given to one group of Republicans or to another contingent of--Republicans? Has not even Garfield ousted a number of highly capable Republican officials and replaced them with others of lesser quality? Whether Peter or Paul is postmaster or tax collector who need worry, so long as neither one pilfers? Illinois, in particular, would not experience any considerable change in political matters if Guiteau's bullet changed the leadership in Washington, since Garfield already has given political jobs to that section of the Republicans which fought him most at the convention, the clique to which Guiteau, the murderer professes to belong, or wants to be regarded as belonging.</p>
   <p>But the fact that a crazy person, a murderer, can make a change in the highest public office will undoubtedly provide food for thought and will make all parties more prudent, so that in the future no opponent of a President will be made Vice-president, for that is equivelent to putting a premium on murder. Just as <pb facs="5418474_6_0562.jpg" n="5"/>Guiteau tried to change the fortunes of the Stalwarts by using a revolver, so some one else may do the same thing under similar circumstances in the future. Then our form of government would be a counterpart of the Russian monarchy, concerning which the Marquis Cuestine wrote:</p>
   <p>"It is hereditary despotism, mitigated by clandestine assassinations!"</p>
   <p>Finally, if Garfield dies, what will become of Guiteau? Will he be executed like a common murderer on the gallows? The friends of Leo Hartmann will undoubtedly protest vigorously:</p>
   <p>"Is not Guiteau a man of honor, just like the Russian?</p>
   <p>"But aside from this, it will be difficult to obtain a conviction because according to the laws of the District of Columbia no one may serve as juror who has read anything about the case or has already formed an opinion. But where, throughout the whole land, not to mention Washington, can one find twelve men <pb facs="5418474_6_0563.jpg" n="6"/>who have not read anything of Guiteau's despicable deed or formed an opinion about it? It is said that where there is no plaintiff, there is no judge. Here the opposite might be stated: when there is no juror, there cannot be a plaintiff!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
