<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-09-28">Sept. 28, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">A Laborer</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0498</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0498.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-09-28">Sept. 28, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">A LABORER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In one of the countless speeches delivered after Garfield's death one finds this terse comment, which summarizes the practical application of his life principle:</p>
   <p>"He was not too proud to work."</p>
   <p>This is a lesson which should be heeded by hundreds of thousands of our American-born loafers; but it is also suitable for several hundred specimens of the imported German variety who instead of working prefer to "get along" by arousing labor and teaching the doctrine of the new worker's gospel, collecting a few dimes here and there and thus making a fair if not an honest living.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0499.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Garfield's life proves that in spite of all the clamor about "capitalism" in America success still depends on honest, ceaseless labor, the kind which is mixed with a good measure of ambition and enables us to start on a rung [of the ladder] far below an apprentice's and still come out on top. With what disdain would not some socialistic tailor or shoemaker have looked at the barefoot youngster, thirty-five years ago, muleteer of a canal barge, who worked for starvation wages--two dollars a week; [Translator's note: That's good money; the mules received less--which proves that the more you work, the less you earn.] He, a laborer? The socialists have pride. They would never recognize an unkempt farmer's boy, mule skinner, or worker on a canal barge as a laborer; only men who have learned a trade are entitled to such an appelation.</p>
   <p>Granted! Garfield was one of these workers, far below the social standard of our socialist tailors, shoemakers, and carpenters who want to make the world a better place to live in. But he did not intend to stick to that job forever, consider it his life's work, kick about it or complain about the cruel <pb facs="5418474_6_0500.jpg" n="3"/>world which provided nothing better, vent his fury on the "despicable capitalists", and finally seek solace in drink and in ranting about business conditions in general, which had condemned him to such an existence. No--that was not Garfield's way. He worked instead, took what jobs he could find, and was diligent and reliable even in the lowliest calling. And the less he earned, the less he drank to arouse his passions against the "damnable possessing class". [Translator's note: I don't see how he could have got drunk on two dollars a week. The editor is inconsistent.] He saved enough for an education. And instead of wasting time and going around with a chip on his shoulder he worked hard to earn money, and this enabled him to acquire knowledge and to rise in life. From mule driver on a canal to country schoolteacher--then college--a man of letters--that was his accomplishment! When the financial question arose in the late sixties and became of extreme importance, he resolved to study it. He found that many of the most important works [on finance] were written in French; so he decided to learn the language, and because of his incomparable diligence he succeeded in reading these scientific works in the original language and in understanding them, <pb facs="5418474_6_0501.jpg" n="4"/>and he could even converse in French. In a similar way he mastered German, in which he became just as proficient as in Latin and Greek, which he had previously studied. It is not saying too much if we declare that the poor farmer's son, who was born in a log cabin,the mule driver, far excelled in knowledge any of his colleagues in Congress.</p>
   <p>And he was indebted to no one. Since early childhood he had looked upon honest labor, tasks faithfully performed, as the only means to progress; and his entire life bore evidence of staunch adherence to this principle and proved that he was right. He bore no envy toward those who happened to have "more" of the world's goods than he had. What he was, what he intended to be, he wanted to achieve through his own efforts, and he never thought of appealing to the state or to any one else to protect him against the "damned capitalists". Whether he used his hands or his head, it was always his own work which shaped his destiny. And so through his own efforts he reached the highest office and the greatest honor which a free people can bestow.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0502.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Thus we find that Garfield's life is a glorification of honest labor and conscientious endeavor, far different from the lives of rancous-voiced toughs who wish to turn workers into ferocious beasts. Garfield was a worker--the personfication of an ideal. And this laborer's death was mourned by a hundred million people, including emperors, kings, sultan, and pope. The world's history will remember him, and his name will endure for centuries. [Translator's note: But the financial question which the editor so casually interjected is still a red-hot issue!]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
