<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-03-23">Mar. 23, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Successful Concerts Presented by Two Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1506</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1506.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-03-23">Mar. 23, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">SUCCESSFUL CONCERTS PRESENTED BY TWO SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday the Nord-Chicago Maennerchor prepared a program to be held in the Social Turner Hall. This chorus, led by its conductor, Mr. Tanner, will participate in the program along with other choral groups. This custom is very praiseworthy, for it provides variety for the concert. This variety was noticeably lacking on yesterday's program, for no orchestral numbers were included.</p>
   <p>The Nord-Chicago Maennerchor presented a number of gay songs, and they received rich applause from the audience. The upper Austrian folk songs seemed to please especially well. But even the Maennerchor's very first number "The Hermit in the Night" was well shaded and splendidly performed. As guests, the Damenchor Deutsch Unterstuetzungs-Bund sang, and displayed their excellent Tanner schooling. The concluding number of the concert was performed by Nord-Chicago Maennerchor singing in unison with the Excelsior, the Damenchor D. U. B., and the Swiss Men's chorus. The selection was "The Spring on the Rhine and the <pb facs="5418474_6_1507.jpg" n="2"/>blended voices rang through the Hall, and at the conclusion of the number the audience responded with deafening applause.</p>
   <p>The conductor showed his ability in his selection of soloists. A young singer, George Eckardt sang "Songs to the Lute"; Mr. and Mrs. Ewald Latkow provoked storms of laughter with their "Musical Marriage"; Felix Glasneck, a member of the Excelsior Maennerchor, displayed a wonderful voice. The "Two Hearts in Three-Quarter Time" is a welcome selection on any program. The accompaniment to most of the solo numbers was performed by Mr. Tanner.</p>
   <p>The stage of the Social Turner Hall provided a pretty picture; a make-believe forest provided a background for the society's president, Frederic Gehen, during his welcoming address.</p>
   <p>The following persons served on the reception committee: Henry W. Thomas, Georg Hecht, August Barth, Fred Dickmann, Paul Sonnemann, Erich Gustafel, and several others.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1508.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The evening was concluded with a ball for which Tanner's orchestra provided the inviting dance music. Both old and young accepted the orchestra's invitation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
