<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1890-02-19">February 19th, 1890</date>. (Not in Chicago)
<title level="a">Editorial on Equal Suffrage.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0774</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0774.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1890-02-19">February 19th, 1890</date>. (Not in Chicago)
<title level="a">Editorial On Equal Suffrage.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Lathrop, Mo., the "ladies" are rebelling and considered it eminently proper to rid the locality of saloons on their own accord and initiative. One of the tavern proprietors, whose supplies, were emptied on the street, whose furniture has been demolished and even home broken into, took recourse to the County Court to issue warrants against the mob-leaders. As a result, the sheriff fared forth, prepared to arrest 16 ladies and 3 ministers, which were present during this deplorable mob-demonstration and functioned virtually as the leaders. Insinuations were made to the officials, that he would meet with resistance. Now we must wait and surmise, whether the sheriff intends to protect the sanctity of the law with force, of if it reaches extremes, whether the Governor of Missouri will supply the militia just as readily and gladly against the rioters in petticoats, in the identical manner as is customarily done, on the least provocation, when striking workers are concerned. Law is "law", and people who wantonly disregard our statutes, should surely not be given more lenient treatment, than man, who have been driven by "desperation" to disregard law and order. Women and girls who find it so diverting to demolish a Canteen-keepers property, as did the "jovial" students who occasionally broke street lanterns and, for good measure thrashed the nightwatchman, ought to be at least "cooled off." After such a display of toughness, they cannot demand exemption on account of sex.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
