<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-08-16">Aug. 16, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Tavernkeepers' Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1276</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1276.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-08-16">Aug. 16, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE TAVERNKEEPERS' ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Tavernkeepers' Association held its regular fortnightly meeting yesterday at Baum's Park Place Pavilion, Cottage Grove Avenue and 22nd Street. A fair sized crowd was present; J. Feldkamp, president of the Association, presided.</p>
   <p>After the minutes had been read routine matters had been attended to, the following gentlemen were accepted as members: H. Pickard, Charles Richter, A. Wieschendorff, and H. Light. The bond of P. Mueller, trustee, was accepted.</p>
   <p>Mr. Engelmann, of the committee on legal matters, announced his resignation, which was accepted with regret. Selection of another member of the committee was postponed because the regular election will be held soon.</p>
   <p>The special committee which was nominated at the last session to confer with the brewers on measures and shortages submitted its report. The committee <pb facs="5418474_6_1277.jpg" n="2"/>declared that the brewers had arranged a meeting for next Tuesday to settle the question, and the members added that the reception given them by the brewers was friendly in every instance. One of the proposals, considered to be the most reliable means of settling the difficulty, provided for the selling of beer according to weight. This would give assurance to the tavernkeepers, as well as protect the brewers against confiscation of barrels, because the government confiscates all barrels which are oversize, in order to enforce the revenue laws.</p>
   <p>P. Mueller remarked that the contents of a quarter-barrel should weigh sixty-eight pounds and, according to present prices, a pound of beer would cost three cents.</p>
   <p>A general discussion followed, and nearly everyone present was in favor of selling beer by weight instead of by the barrel.</p>
   <p>Mr. Baum wanted to go even further to make the tavernkeepers independent of <pb facs="5418474_6_1278.jpg" n="3"/>the brewers, and suggested a co-operative brewery with tavernkeepers as sole stock owners. All speculators should be excluded from the corporation and only bona fide saloonkeepers should be connected with the enterprise.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cortes had doubts, and believed that a venture of the kind would very likely be doomed to failure, as was a Philadelphia brewery which was financed by a stock issue.</p>
   <p>Mr. Baum, however, was very positive in his opinion, and declared that, if speculators were excluded and the brewery sold to its own investors, success would be assured from the very beginning.</p>
   <p>It was decided, however, to await the brewers' conference before proceeding in the matter.</p>
   <p>President Feldkamp then said that he had heard that the mayor desired an opinion from the tavernkeepers on the question of prohibiting music in saloons <pb facs="5418474_6_1279.jpg" n="4"/>after 10:30 or 11 o'clock at night.</p>
   <p>Mr. Baum was definitely opposed to consideration of the mayor's plan. What the mayor wants can only be a measure to control disreputable places--and that has nothing to do with legitimate tavernkeepers. It is the mayor's duty to close all dives, but he cannot expect respectable saloonkeepers to do this work by resorting to a curtailment of their own rights in order to make the noisy places less conspicuous. If the mayor really wants to clean up the saloons, why does he not close all places which are but entrances to dives and use bad music merely to attract customers? But instead of that he [the mayor] plays politics and has permitted King and Jerry Monroe to operate their saloons again, after bragging that he had closed them in the interests of public decency. About the only thing the Tavernkeepers' Association can do in giving an answer to the mayor would be to pass a resolution condemning his policy of permitting saloons to reopen after their licenses have been revoked, wherever such revocation was based upon misconduct.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1280.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Association finally decided not to express an opinion on the mayor's question, since Association members never will consent to be put into the same category with keepers of common dives.</p>
   <p>Before adjournment, the assembly decided to arrange an outing, within the near future, to visit Cortes' saloon, and a committee (P. Mueller, chairman), was appointed to take care of the details.</p>
   <p>The next session will be held in three weeks at the Vorwaerts Turnhalle.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
