<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-01-21">Jan. 21, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Miss Rehberg's Concert.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Young Cello Artist Captivates Her Listeners.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1550</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1550.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-01-21">Jan. 21, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">MISS REHBERG'S CONCERT.</title><title level="a" type="Sub">Young Cello Artist Captivates Her Listeners.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Miss Lillian Rehberg, the daughter of the well known choir director, H. A. Rehberg, played yesterday before a large crowd of music lovers in Kimball Hall and earned great laurels. She played as a perfect artist, with a brilliant technique, and with a full understanding for the difficult music of the masters whose works filled yesterday's program. We cannot count her today among the youthful, who will become somebody some day, because she is already an artist, whose name must be mentioned among the great ones.</p>
   <p>The evening started with the Allegro Non Tropp of Saint Saens "Concerto in A Minor". Here it was noticeable, that Miss Rehberg displayed a certain melancholy in her playing which was advantageous and touching. Also in the lively Allegro molto and Allegretto con moto there was a certain depth, which caused the listeners to express their gratitude to the artist through warm acclamation. "Melody" by Gluck and the "Meunett in G" by Beethoven, received an ovation from the audience, and the young artist had to play additional pieces. The "German Folk Song", after Abt's melodies arranged by Miss Rehberg was pretty and produced through its simplicity a great effect. Schubert's "The Bee" gave Miss Rehberg <pb facs="5418474_6_1551.jpg" n="2"/>the opportunity to prove her cleverness with easy teasing play. In the "Concerto in B Minor" by Dvorak she let her instrument sing once more. "The Hungarian Rhapsody" by Popper, brought the evening to a close and Miss Rehberg can look with pride upon it. It means for her a further climbing on the rungs of the ladder of well earned success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
