<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-12-25">Dec. 25, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Metropolitan Opera in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1595</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1595.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-12-25">Dec. 25, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE METROPOLITAN OPERA IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Neither the adverse weather conditions nor the customary Christmas eve gift presentation interfered with the splendid attendance at last night's opening of a cycle of opera performances at the Auditorium Theatre.</p>
   <p>The presentation was Verdi's "Aida." it demonstrated again its power to attract lovers of opera, and the performance justified to a certain extent the good reputation heralded in advance of the company's arrival.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1596.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The laurels for last night's success go to the soloists of the evening. The title role was impersonated by Miss Strakosch whose voice lacks sweetness when striking the middle or lower register. But Miss Strakosch compensated us richly with her great dramatic talent combined with a vivacious temperament. Mother nature has endowed her with an "Aida" personality. And when she combined the beauty of her voice with the three foregoing factors, as in the rendition of the great aria "O Patria Mia," she scored a genuine triumph.</p>
   <p>Displaying equally as much dramatic emotion was Miss Louise Meisslinger, the possessor of a clear and voluminous voice, I wish I could have <pb facs="5418474_6_1597.jpg" n="3"/>bestowed upon her the honor of being mentioned first, but due to the secondary role - that of "Amneris" - this was impossible. She arose to colossal heights in the scene exhibiting jealous frenzy, and then again in the opening scene of act IV with "Radames." Judging Miss Meisslinger by her last night's interpretation, great things might be expected of her in the role of "Ortrud."</p>
   <p>Of Philipp Brozel, the "Radames" of the evening, better singing and protrayal of the role was expected. At times however, he surprised us most pleasantly.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1598.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Ethiopian king Amonasro found a splendid exponent in the person of Mr. Paull. Somewhat civilized, nevertheless, he displayed a sufficient degree of barbarism to be convincing. He possesses a well-trained voice, as well as dramatic talent.</p>
   <p>Mr. Whitehill was excellent in the role of"Ramfls." His wonderful voice added much to the performances. Relative to Mr. Carr, he was an acceptable king.</p>
   <p>The chorus, did not meet our approval. Frequent dissonances and negligible indifference were exhibited throughout the performance. The male chorus was very unsatisfactory, in the singing of "Spiro del Nume." To be lenient, we will, at this time, refrain from criticism of the ballet.</p>
   <p>The orchestra was equal to its task.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
