<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-01-21">Jan. 21, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">"K-Bread;" Not for Sale at the German Labor Aid</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1128</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1128.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-01-21">Jan. 21, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">"K-BREAD;" NOT FOR SALE AT THE GERMAN LABOR AID</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The war or "K-Bread" has recently come into general use in Germany. ["K," first letter of the German word Krieg meaning war. Transl.] The composition is one of the highlights in the research laboratories of the baking industry. The belief prevails that "K-Bread" consists of 50 per cent potato flour, and that anyone can bake it. This is not the case, although the ingredients and proportions are simple enough: 60% best rye flour, 30% wheat flour, and 10% potato flakes, but the baking process is a matter of applied science. The nutritive value of "K-Bread" exceeds all heretofore known bread products and besides, it has a fine flavor.</p>
   <p>The sales price in New York is 25 cents loaf. This geniune "K-Bread" is now obtainable in Chicago. It is made by German bakers, and it sells for 10 cents. The product was introduced in our city by <pb facs="5418474_6_1129.jpg" n="2"/>the German Worker's Aid, an organization which endeavors to combine true American citizenship with German skill and thoroughness in the peaceful pursuits of labor. Unemployed, experienced men, Americans or those who intend to be citizens, have found jobs in large numbers where they produce implements of peace.</p>
   <p>In order to help such workers, who are temporarily out of work, home industries have been created and their activities manifest themselves in ever widening fields. Posters of Washington, Lincoln, as well as of the new Archbishop Mundelein, are being prepared, and the manufacture of "K-Bread" also represents an industry designed to benefit the working class.</p>
   <p>The bread can be bought at the Bureau of the German Workers Aid, 154 W. Randolph Street, Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1130.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>[Note: The article gives no information whether the German Workers Aid is a society, club, or co-operative institution. It only mentions organization. A reprint appears in the issue of January 24, 1916, and six additional places where "K-Bread" can be obtained, are listed. Transl.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
