<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-11">Apr. 11, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">A Strict Investigation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0101</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0101.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-11">Apr. 11, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">A STRICT INVESTIGATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A committee shall be appointed to investigate complaints brought against the County Hospital.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hanberg, president of the County Board, announced yesterday that he has decided to appoint a committee whose task will be to investigate the alleged cruelties to which patients of that institution are subjected. The majority of the members of this committee of nine, will not be selected from among members of the County Board, in order to avoid any suspicion that politics governs the investigation. Mr. Hanberg's intention is to invite various organizations to assist him in the task of appointing members for the committee. Invitations for participation in the actual appointments will be sent to the following organizations: the Commercial Club, the Municipal Voters League, the Citizens Association, the Civic Federation, the Chicago Medical Association, and others.</p>
   <p>The County Board will be represented by three associates only; furthermore, to ascertain absolute exclusion of politics, two of these members will represent the Democratic party and one the Republican.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0102.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The accusations referred to are of course of a rather serious nature; therefore they must be thoroughly investigated. Whether or not there is any foundation to these accusations, Mr. Hanberg is not in a position to tell. "Nevertheless, one thing is beyond any doubt", said he, "namely, that some persons become actually horror-stricken at the very thought of having to seek medical care in the County Hospital." Now he wants to know the truth.</p>
   <p>The accusation by the Mizpah Lodge No. 768, A. F. and A. M., in regard to their member Mr. H. W. Boulton, has received space in this newspaper already, but the latest accuser of the County Hospital staff and their conduct is James O'Neill, a male nurse in the hospital in 1897. He said that patients there are submitted to a most barbaric treatment by the inhumanity of which he was prompted to give up his job after only five months. Poor unfortunates in a state of delirium, as a result of high fever, are the ones mistreated the most. Furthermore, any patient uttering the slightest complaint would be promptly declared temporarily out of his mind and treatment is then meted out accordingly, that is, a severe beating administered by an orderly until the <pb facs="5418474_6_0103.jpg" n="3"/>patient responded in the expected manner. Although patients who face an operation deserve the greatest sympathy, no less than eight of them are wheeled into the operating room at one time, thus being forced to witness the surgical procedure,- a drama developing before their very eyes while waiting for their own turn to come.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
