<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1895-01-07">January 7th, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">A German House</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1171</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1171.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1895-01-07">January 7th, 1895</date>.
<title level="a">A German House</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Through the complaint is justified, that the Germans allow themselves to be pushed back in Political life and that they do not maintain the position they are worthy of, because their intelligence and number, it must however, be admitted, that in the business life of our country they take first place. This position has caused the envy and hate of some citizens not of German descent.</p>
   <p>It is not always easy to identify German enterprises, as they are often hidden by English names. An ample proof of the above is afforded by the great printing and publishing house, "The Werner Co," who have their factories in Akron and their head offices in Chicago. Agood German, Mr. Paul E. Werner who immigrated in 1868, at the age of 18, is the founder and the head of this enterprise, which today works with a capital of more than $4,000,000.00 and is one of the largest printing establishments and publishing houses of the world. It is a German house, which has Americanized the great English "Encyclopedia Britannica" and made it accessible through cheaper production to the great American public. The sale of this great work in all parts of the U. S. A., Canada, Mexico and South America exceeds for several years the amount of $2,000,000.00. This great success was possible by the <pb facs="5418474_6_1172.jpg" n="2"/>easy methods of payments, so that everybody was in the position to acquire this wonderful work, as a steady adviser in his home, in all phases of daily life. The Werner Company also publishes "Pictorial Wonderful", "Glimpses of the World" by John L. Stoddard and the World's Fair portfolios. 200,000 copies of the "Glimpses of the World" have been sold in the form of books and 9 millions in the form of copy books. The millions of books sent yearly to all parts of the world, are manufactured in Akron, Ohio, where they possess 9 buildings each of 2 floors together occupying a space of 1255 feet in length and 40 feet in width. The machinery occupies 30,000 square feet. They have a photo atelier, a wood cutting department, a drawing and painting atelier, a large book binding department, large type setting rooms and all necessary departments and offices for printing.</p>
   <p>They occupy about 1000 persons and several hundredsare busy in Chicago in the Rand Mc Nally Building. They have over 5000 agents and salesmen all over the world. They have branches in London, Paris and Berlin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
