<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-23">Nov. 23, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Agriculture and Industry</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0813</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0813.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-23">Nov. 23, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">AGRICULTURE AND INDUSTRY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Oscar Johnston, a cotton planter from Mississippi with a prominent position in the A. A. A., is an advocate for equality of agriculture with industry, to be achieved by the Government. He contends that ever since the Civil War the Government has been largely influenced by the industrial East to the detriment of agriculture. This contention is to some extent justified, although as a matter of fact the Federal Government has spent more money for the advancement of agriculture than to aid industry. However industry has received its share in an indirect way, namely, by way of high tariffs which has enabled it to keep foreign competition at a distance from the American market and so to make exorbitant profits.</p>
   <p>Originally the policy of a protective tariff was fully justified, because only by this means was it possible to develop and build up American industry. <pb facs="5418474_6_0814.jpg" n="2"/>In the course of time, however, this policy completely degenerated. Now Johnston demands a radical revolution in agricultural politics. As an initial step, the Government should not extend further credit to the farmers, for through this credit it becomes easier for them to get farther and farther into debt. He further takes exception to the fact that one department of the Government restricts production, while at the same time another opens new stretches of land to production. He finally demands that on making new business treaties the exportation of agricultural products should be taken into consideration.</p>
   <p>It is remarkable that the latter demand was made only a few days ago by the national chamber of commerce. This policy has also been followed by the Government for some time, but the settlement of trade treaties is progressing so slowly that their effects are not felt as yet. That the other two demands are right and should be carried out has been repeatedly pointed out here and emphatically stressed. To give his demands more emphasis Johnson wants to unite the population of the South and the Middle West into a sort of <pb facs="5418474_6_0815.jpg" n="3"/>agricultural block, as their interests are essentially the same.</p>
   <p>This idea is not new. Only a few weeks ago Governor Olson of Minnesota suggested the formation of an agricultural block of the North West. This suggestion may not have been formal, but it was actual. Therefore Johnston's suggestions and demands seem to some extent superfluous, and yet it is remarkable that the man from the South has stepped out before the public with his plans. These plans are not radical; they do not express ideas of a farm agitator but of a practical farmer who also happens to occupy a Government position.</p>
   <p>The Government has strayed into a blind alley with its agricultural policy. The farmers will have to learn that no group of producers is ever benefitted for long by a policy of gift giving and by artificial restrictions of production. The sooner the Government makes up its mind to reconstruct its farm policy from the bottom up, the better.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
