<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-04-17">Apr. 17, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">No Grand Opera for Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1605</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1605.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-04-17">Apr. 17, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">NO GRAND OPERA FOR CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The impresario, Maurice Grau, announced the other day that Chicago opera lovers will not be given a chance to shine by their absence next season. Chicago will not be included in the guest performances of his opera company's coast to coast tour. Chicago, he contends, does not appreciate grand opera. This was shown plainly enough, by the terrible deficit during his company's engagement there.</p>
   <p>Once before, we were in a position to advise Mr. Grau and point out certain shortcomings in the presentation of these performances. And we still insist that as long as Mr. Grau pays unreasonably high salaries to a dozen stars of his company and continues to underpay the members of the chorus, the financial success of the company will always be a doubtful one.... The impresario thought to produce a certain jealousy among Chicago music lovers, when announcing the other day the names of the stars engaged by him for the next winter season. If credence could be given to the statement that his company will include such stars as Mmes. Melba, Nordica, Baumeister, Adams, Strong, Homer, Bridewell, Gadski and Olitzka, and Messrs. Prindle, the de Reszke brothers, Flangon, Deppel, Muhlmann, Campanary, Scotti, etc., the company will in our opinion be forced to dissolve long before the coast to coast tour is ended.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1606.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Chicago will manage to get along without opera for one season. It will try to satisfy its want for good music by attending those ezquisite Thomas concerts and other musical productions scheduled to take place here during the next winter season. Chicago is blameless, for not liking to pay exhorbitant admission prices to hear the special characters impersonated by the greatest of operatic stars, while the chorus and scenery are of even less than mediocre quality. Grand opera requires also a ballet, but Mr. Grau's opera performances were not produced so elaborately. The scenery in the "Walkure" for instance, was beyond any criticism.</p>
   <p>Mr. Grau does not know Chicago people well enough, when resorting to such measures, to obtain a guarantee, against future deficits. Chicago is willing to make sacrifices, but then, it does expect to get the best which music can offer. And this is the reason why Theodore Thomas and his splendid orchestra was acquired for Chicago - an orchestra which is second to none in the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
