<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-02-25">Feb. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Northwest Side Association of Commerce</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1149</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1149.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-02-25">Feb. 25, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE NORTHWEST SIDE ASSOCIATION OF COMMERCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two hundred Chicago businessmen situated on the Northwest Side of the city met at Gerstens Hall last night with the purpose of founding a society for the protection and furtherance of the interests of the citizens of those districts. The association will be known as "The Commercial Association of the Northwest Side." According to the statutes of this organization, the society must follow a non-partisan policy and remain strictly neutral in the nomination of candidates for any office. It also provides that no public official shall become a member of their executive committee. This area has a population of approximately 446,000, all of whom shall derive benefits from this association. Numerous committees with various duties shall be formed, interested exclusively in the improvement of streets, parks, boulevards, schools, Police Department, Fire Department, water and many other worthy causes. Following is the list of the officials of this new organization: R. J. Terwilliger, president; Otto Schulz, Edward Ahlswede, Horitz Bendheim, vice-presidents; Jens <pb facs="5418474_6_1150.jpg" n="2"/>C. Hansen, treasurer; and George L. Maccarron, secretary. Richard Carrol, John S. Edwards, Iver L. Quaiss, Thomas F. Deuther, A. C. Sievers, Joseph R. Noel, F. A. Maurer, Charles Lang, Paul Dryzmolski, and Charles C. Breyer are directors of the society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
