<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-01-21">Jan. 21, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">New Food and Drug Act Proposed</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0862</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0862.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-01-21">Jan. 21, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">NEW FOOD AND DRUG ACT PROPOSED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new draft of a law governing the sale of unadulterated foods and drugs is now before the United States Senate. When a previous bill was discussed in committee last month, manufacturers voiced strenuous objections. They considered its provisions too strict. Many of the provisions which were objected to have not been embodied in the new bill. In its present form, the proposed law does not give the public the same degree of protection against fraud and adulteration that the former bill offered; nevertheless, it is a great improvement over the present law.</p>
   <p>Anybody who has visited the Government Building at the Century of Progress, and has seen examples of adulteration of food and drugs, and has noted the ingredients of which they actually consist, can readily understand, why the <pb facs="5418474_6_0863.jpg" n="2"/>various sections of the existing act should be thoroughly altered; for the Government could not institute proceedings against the manufacturers and vendors of the products which were exhibited, because the pertinent paragraphs of the present Food and Drug Act are too lax. At the Fair people were especially warned against the use of one of the exhibited products, which at that time was not only openly sold in Chicago, but was also extensively advertised by radio. Apparently the authorities could not interfere, although, in their exhibit, they expressly designated the product as harmful.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, the proposed act does not prescribe that the component parts of this highly recommended product, or medicine, be recorded on the label; but it does prohibit advertising remedies for about fifty kinds of sicknesses, which are enumerated, unless these remedies are expressly prescribed by a physician, since they might prove harmful to the health of the patient when not taken under the supervision of a doctor. That, at least, is a great step toward progress. Moreover, an advertisement is to be considered false if it <pb facs="5418474_6_0864.jpg" n="3"/>is only misleading in any respect. According to the original bill, the Secretary of Agriculture would have authority to set a standard of quality for various foods. The present bill merely grants him power to establish a minimum standard of quality.</p>
   <p>Of course, those who like decreases of authority are harmful to the purpose of the law. However, since the act, in its first form, could not have passed, it is desirable that Congress enact it in its present form. A bird in the hand is worth two in the bush. The provisions of the present law are entirely inadequate. Since there is apparently only a choice of retaining it, or replacing it by the proposed act, the latter should be enacted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
