<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-01-22">Jan. 22, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">German Mutual Fire Insurance Company of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1182</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1182.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-01-22">Jan. 22, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN MUTUAL FIRE INSURANCE COMPANY OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Mutual Fire Insurance Company of Chicago held their annual meeting last night in the Folz Hall, Larrabee and North Ave. Of the more than 1,700 members of the old and reliable insurance company which was established in 1867, almost 500 of them attended the meeting.</p>
   <p>The financial condition of the company is very excellent. Its officers have been with the company for many years: M. Schmitz, President, 16 years; F. Becker, Vice-President, 7 years; C. Zuber, Treasurer, 7 years; J. H. Epnst, secretary, 19 years.</p>
   <p>The insurance policies in force or the liabilities of the company, amounts to $2,935,800.00; and the assets consist of $62,138.35 in cash which is nearly all invested in city and county bonds, and $220,185.53 which is outstanding in premium notes.</p>
   <p>During the last six months, from July 1, until December 31, 1891, the company paid only $896.00 for losses by fire.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1183.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The president, secretary and treasurer were re-elected. Mr. J. Seilheimer was elected Vice-President. The president also appointed members to the Finance-Committee and others to the Election Committee.</p>
   <p>The members of the German Mutual Fire Insurance Company are exclusively owners of real-estate property of the North and Northwest side. Only owners of real-estate property are accepted as members, and only such buildings are insured against fire, which are located on such property. The rates are very low and amount to $1.20 per $100.00 for the first five year period. For the following five year periods the rates are reduced to only 70 cents per $100.00 Factories and storage-houses are not insured by the company.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
