<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-05-09">May 9, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Musical Performances in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1692</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1692.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-05-09">May 9, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">MUSICAL PERFORMANCES IN CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The gala concert, performed yesterday at the Turner Halle by two excellent orchestras, was indeed a musical treat. The two amalgamated orchestras, formerly known as the Rosenbecker and Liesegang respectively, competed against each other all during the past season but demonstrated at yesterday's concert that each member was an accomplished musician. The audience on the other hand, demonstrated its appreciation of an afternoon concert, played by accomplished musicians. Regardless of the oppressive atmospheric conditions, the hall was filled to capacity. The first part of the concert was directed by Mr. Liesegang, who was enthusiastically greeted upon his appearance on the stage.</p>
   <p>The opening number on the program was the "Kaiser March," by Wagner. This difficult composition could be referred to as the stepping stone of every musician, nevertheless, the orchestra delivered it with utmost exactness, proving thereby its unquestionable ability of perfect reading.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1693.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The allegro and the andante from the "Unfinished Symphony," by Schubert, was simply a brilliant execution of that composition for which, both the conductor, as well as the orchestra, deserves high praise. The acme of the evening was reached by the rendition of Beethoven's violin concerto. The performing artist was Mr. Rosenbecker. Although, technically a most difficult composition, Mr. Rosenbecker, surpassed himself yesterday. The prolonged acclaim was spontaneous. The concluding number of the first part of the program was the "Leonora Overture No. 3," by Beethoven. It is obvious however, that Mr. Liesegang was unaware of the acoustical shortcomings of the hall, therefore, some of the most beautiful music of that masterpiece was lost to the audience in consequence by taking the pianissimo too softly.</p>
   <p>The first number of the second half of the program, directed by Mr. Rosenbecker, was the well known overture "Roman Carnival," introducing the second act of the opera "Benvenuto Cellini" by Berlioz. In this <pb facs="5418474_6_1694.jpg" n="3"/>extremely genial tone-picture, the composer depicts the rustle and bustle of a Roman carnival. It is in every sense an instrumental masterpiece, demanding of the artist utmost exactness. For the excellent reading of the composition, the conductor and the orchestra alike, are to be commended. The concert continued with the "Serenade" by Volkmann, followed by the characteristic piece "Nordic Folk Songs" by Soedermann. The originality and the changing color of this composition gave another opportunity for a brilliant exhibition by the highly talented Mr. Rosenbecker, and his musicians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
