<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-07-02">July 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Our Constitution</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0379</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0379.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-07-02">July 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">OUR CONSTITUTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All civilized nations live under some form of a constitution. In some cases the constitution is written; in others the will of the ruler who issues orders to his subjects is equivalent to a constitution. We in America have a written constitution, and it is one of the oldest existing documents of its kind. It was adopted 146 years ago, so it dates back to the period of the oxcart, as a prominent man recently expressed it. It is evident that many fundamental changes have occurred in our political, economic, and social life since the days of Washington, Madison, Hamilton, Marshall, etc. And so it may be that our Constitution, which was drafted to meet the demands of a small nation, is no longer adequate to meet the needs of our large country, and must be changed.</p>
   <p>President Roosevelt apparently had this in view when, in his chagrin at the <pb facs="5418474_6_0380.jpg" n="2"/>nullification of the N.R.A. by the Supreme Court, he spoke of a change in the Constitution. It is certain that the document can be changed, but only if the people desire it. Neither the president nor Congress, nor the Supreme Court has the authority to alter it. That authority is vested in the people. And Washington had better keep that fact in mind. If the present administration is convinced that our Constitution has outlived its usefulness, that it needs a revision, or that it should be supplanted by a new one, there is only one way of effecting a change or a substitution--by appealing directly to the people. They adopted the Constitution, and they alone have the right and the power to alter it, or to adopt another in its stead.</p>
   <p>Some advisors of the administration have given vent to their anger at the decision of the Supreme Court on the N.R.A. in another way. They upbraided the high tribunal and demanded that Congress deprive it of the right to declare acts of Congress unconstitutional. This attack was uncalled for <pb facs="5418474_6_0381.jpg" n="3"/>and very careless, for it disclosed that certain advisors in the White House have very little respect for the Constitution. It is true that the Constitution does not state that the Supreme Court has such authority; on the other hand, there is nothing in the Constitution that could possibly be interpreted to mean that Congress has any power whatsoever over the Supreme Court. Moreover, it expressly states that the government consists of three branches--legislative, executive, and judicial. These three branches are subject to the provisions of the Constitution. That is, Congress has no right to enact laws that are contrary to the Constitution; the president has no authority to sign such laws; likewise, the Supreme Court may make no decisions that are contrary to the Constitution. Thus, if a citizen appeals to the Supreme Court for redress from a judicial decision, it is the duty of the Supreme Court to adjudicate the matter.</p>
   <p>No one can dispute this fact. The authority of the Supreme Court, as outlined above, has never been questioned during the one hundred and fifty years that our Constitution has been in force, and if anybody expresses doubt regarding <pb facs="5418474_6_0382.jpg" n="4"/>the power of the Supreme Court today--well, he's rather late. In any event, neither Congress nor the president has the right or the authority to curtail the functions of the high tribunal. It has been proposed to give Congress or the president the power to remove those members of the Supreme Court from office who render unfavorable decisions. That, too, could be done only by amending the Constitution; it would constitute an intended unbalancing of the three branches of government. When judges lose their independence, justice must disintegrate. The American Constitution is so well worded and balanced that each of the three branches of government is controlled and kept within its bounds by the others, and no branch can assume greater powers than the others have. The attempt to make the members of the Supreme Court subservient to the will of the president or of Congress is, in effect, an attempt to overthrow the Constitution. The attempt is not made by the use of permissible, legal means. Anyone who recommends such a procedure, certainly does not have the backing of the majority of the American people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
