<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-09-27">Sept. 27, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Dust to Dust</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0503</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0503.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-09-27">Sept. 27, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">DUST TO DUST</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American people have buried their President and in the last rites they honored him as probably no mortal man has been honored heretofore. Dust became dust again, but the great spirit which once animated the body will continue to live in the memory of generations to come. The people whose best characteristics he embodied will think of him as part of the nation's history. A splendid man has gone to seek eternal rest, but he continues to live in the minds of millions and will become a guiding star, so we ardently hope, for thousands of young, ambitious men whose goal is achievement and honest endeavor. The example of such a life is bound to bear fruit.</p>
   <p>Garfield's life gives us proof that even in times like these, in a land where crass materialism rules, and the chase after the Almighty Dollar <pb facs="5418474_6_0504.jpg" n="2"/>principally interests us--because of the luxuries which it provides--we can nevertheless achieve "immeasurably greater and more lasting success" by devoting ourselves to science and to unselfish labor for the common weal; and his life also demonstrates that our reward will be far greater than any results which can possibly be obtained by any insane haste to acquire possessions. What are the proud robber barons of our railroads, our oil kings and our mine owners, who toy with millions as children do with an abacus, compared to the everlasting glory of the martyr-leader of this nation! Garfield was a poor man, according to American conceptions, but they buried him with regal splendor. How many Vanderbilts, Goulds, Scotts, and Mackays would it require to measure up to a Garfield? And how many men of this wealthy category could be murdered without arousing a hundred-thousandth part of the sympathy which a land of fifty million people feel for Garfield!</p>
   <p>A sorrow more intense than any sympathy which ever was accorded to a crowned head grips an entire nation and reveals to us the deep-rooted sentiments of <pb facs="5418474_6_0505.jpg" n="3"/>the American people--a profound consolation for all sarcastic aspersions [on Americans] made in the past. In view of the prolonged tension and uncertainty throughout the eleven weeks during which the President lingered it would have been natural to expect that the people would eventually become apathetic. But the opposite happened. It was wonderful to behold this sudden unity throughout the country--how national mourning obliterated class distinction, irrespective of the social standing, vocations, national origin, party affiliation, or creed of the various factions. Even before official requests could be issued, millions of houses were decorated with symbols of mourning. At the railroad tracks thousands and thousands of people gathered to see the train which bore the last remains of the great leader, and flowers were strewn in profusion along the right of way. There was no community, no district, club, or lodge which did not express its sorrow. By unanimous consent on the day of the funeral work was suspended; the event was observed as the Germans abroad mourn the death of the founder of the Christian religion. Wherever processions were held--and this custom <pb facs="5418474_6_0506.jpg" n="4"/>does not appeal to everybody--tens of thousands of people came and regarded it as their duty to express their sentiments by their presence.</p>
   <p>Other lands even, such as England, France, Belgium, Spain, and Austria, did much to enhance the impressiveness of the occasion by sending notes of condolence. Probably at no time has the death of the highest official of a republic evoked such general sympathy in Europe as has been observed in this instance.</p>
   <p>Lincoln was assassinated at a time when the passions which had been aroused by our civil war (especially in England and Canada) had not yet entirely subsided. Many were still friendly to the Confederacy, and the death of the President of the Northern States did not strike a responsive chord. When Garfield's death occured, these views had disappeared--even in the Southern States. And this made it possible for the queen of that very England the ruling class of which had looked with sardonic satisfaction on the disintegration of the United States twenty years before to telegraph a message <pb facs="5418474_6_0507.jpg" n="5"/>of consolation to Garfieid's widow, send flowers, and order mourning for the British court. The kings of Belgium and of Spain followed this example, although their subjects are by no means so closely related to us as the English people and the German. After news of these notes of regret had filtered into Germany, Emperor Wilhelm and Prince Bismarck also decided to send letters, which will be presented in Washington by Mr. von Schloezer, according to a cablegram received from London, today. The letters may be expected to arrive about two weeks after the funeral.</p>
   <p>Better late than never, but in this case only if the date shows that the letters were written prior to the time when American newspapers published the telegrams which had been received from London, Brussels, and Madrid. [Translator's note: Why didn't he simply say: "Typical German bureaucratic procrastination?" or "Red tape"?] "It is better to leave the skeleton in the closet than to try to explain its presence."</p>
   <p>All that could be done to prove the people's regard for the assassinated <pb facs="5418474_6_0508.jpg" n="6"/>President has been done. The nation returns to its accustomed normal life, in accordance with the laws of nature. Even individual men cannot forever remain beside the graves of their beloved. But men will regard this final resting place as sacred and often return to it to abide in silent reverence. In this manner the place, the bit of earth, where they buried the great leader yesterday will become a national shrine, like the graves of Washington and Lincoln.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
