<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1875-06-13">June 13, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">A Chicago Industry</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1424</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1424.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1875-06-13">June 13, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">A CHICAGO INDUSTRY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Among the various branches of industry and commerce which have made our city into the thriving metropolis of the Northwest, the manufacture of furniture has by no means taken a subordinate rank. Our furniture manufacturers have commercial connections with the entire United States, not only with the comparatively poor South, which lacks industrial enterprises, or with the distant West, but even with the East, so that furniture made in Chicago is generously represented on the New York market.</p>
   <p>Certain branches--the sewing-machine industry, for instance--procure most of their supply of wood furniture from Chicago.</p>
   <p>It is, therefore, quite evident that this branch of industry is of tremendous importance to Chicago's commerce. Not only is it a considerable item for our lumber trade in so far as the more valuable woods are concerned, but it also provides profitable and constant employment, a claim which <pb facs="5418474_6_1425.jpg" n="2"/>most other industries cannot make.</p>
   <p>It is gratifying to note that our German compatriots again play a prominent part, as in most industrial branches. Their achievements are due to diligence, intelligent saving, thoroughness, and business ability, qualities which have brought them to the fore in commerce in all American cities.</p>
   <p>A few details about the most prominent establishments in the furniture industry might be of interest to our readers.</p>
   <p>Louis Schultze</p>
   <p>Mr. [Louis] Schultze's furniture factory, at 274 and 276 Milwaukee Avenue, is one of the most flourishing and continuously operating establishments in the city. He would be justified in feeling proud of his success and ability in bringing this establishment to its present position--quite aside from his other excellent qualities as a man and citizen, by reason of which <pb facs="5418474_6_1426.jpg" n="3"/>he is regarded as one of the most outstanding Germans of the West Side and, in fact, the city. Even if his rise depended in great measure upon the faithful and responsible performance of their duties by co-workers whom he secured--such as Wm. Meatens, his foreman, for instance, and his bookkeeper and business manager, August Gruetter--nevertheless the chief credit belongs to Mr. Schultze, because of his energy, vision, thorough business experience, and capable leadership. To go into further details of the large factory is hardly necessary, as it is so well known among Germans.</p>
   <p>The factory proper and the storage space in the buildings on Milwaukee Avenue are commensurate with the size of the business. The machinery is driven by a twenty-five horsepower steam engine. The factory provides constant employment for seventy-five people throughout the year.</p>
   <p>In the course of time the wholesale business reached huge dimensions, but it must not be forgotten that Mr. Schultze also gives careful attention to retail sales. All varieties of furniture for home use are available at <pb facs="5418474_6_1427.jpg" n="4"/>Schultze's retail division. The designs provide beauty and comfort, as well as solid construction, at most reasonable prices. We highly recommend this firm to German families.</p>
   <p>John Monzel</p>
   <p>John Monzel, 264 and 266 State Street [Translator's note: Whether North or South State Street is not indicated] enjoys a reputation among the local public for making fine and luxurious parlor, bedroom, and dining room furniture, as well as furniture for libraries. He was the first of our Chicago manufacturers to make this type of furniture, which had previously been secured in the East.</p>
   <p>Being experienced in the practical phases of the work, he personally supervises all stages of the manufacture, and thus is able to give purchasers adequate guarantees of the quality of the products. John Monzel provides us with a splendid example of a self-made man, the type which <pb facs="5418474_6_1428.jpg" n="5"/>only America can produce.</p>
   <p>Mr. Monzel's financial resources are such that he can buy for cash, which in turn insures reasonable selling prices. He is a director of a local bank, which enables him to command sufficient funds for a business of such magnitude.</p>
   <p>Spiegel and Cahn</p>
   <p>The furniture house of Spiegel and Cahn located at 222 Wabash Avenue, with its rapid turnover represents the type of store which can only be found in Chicago. In its mighty four-story building it displays a splendid selection of the finest parlor, home, and kitchen furnishings to satisfy every taste. Good, solid merchandise at reasonable prices, in keeping with present conditions, built up a large clientele, so that today this comparatively new establishment is considered one of the first in its line. Among the firm's specialties are ornamental, decorative articles, such as small fancy tables, <pb facs="5418474_6_1429.jpg" n="6"/>chairs, easels, bookcases and music cases, vase stands, etc., which are available in such profusion in no other city except New York.</p>
   <p>Mr. Spiegel has had years of practical and technical experience in this type of business. He supervises buying and selling while Mr. Cahn's entire attention is centered on routine business and clerical matters.</p>
   <p>All who have patronized the store even once are unanimous in proclaiming their complete satisfaction.</p>
   <p>H. and M. Neuberger</p>
   <p>This old firm has been in the furniture business here for the last twenty years, and has thus had ample opportunity--more than any other furniture concern--to learn all about the various branches of the business. Since last March, H. and M. Neuberger have occupied the five-story stone front building at 167 East Randolph Street. Since the establishment burned <pb facs="5418474_6_1430.jpg" n="7"/>down for the second time during the last great fire, on July 14, 1874, it is now supplied with an entirely new assortment of modern furniture, which provides the greatest choice of parlor, bedroom, and dining room furniture as well as the usual home and office furnishings, at prices which range from the most reasonable to the highest levels. We suggest, therefore, that anyone who is in need of furniture or upholstery should visit this firm. The prices are the most reasonable in the city and the quality is guaranteed; this ought to convince anyone that the articles conform to the representations made by the company.</p>
   <p>A. J. Neuberger and Brother</p>
   <p>This firm, located at 78-80 Randolph Street, was founded in 1865 and has one of the largest and most varied assortments of furniture in Chicago. It carries a complete line, from the most elegant parlor, dining room, bedroom, and library furnishings to the common everyday variety of household furniture. Such a large assortment is available that even the most <pb facs="5418474_6_1431.jpg" n="8"/>fastidious tastes can be fully satisfied. All the furniture is manufactured by the firm under the special supervision of Mr. [A. J.] Neuberger, thus the firm is able to provide its customers with goods of sufficient quality and at reasonable enough prices to satisfy anyone. It is one of those firms which deserve full confidence, as every buyer may be certain that he is obtaining good merchandise at a commensurate price.</p>
   <p>Colby and Wirts, 217-219 State Street</p>
   <p>Colby and Wirts not only manage a large furniture house with a wide variety of beds, upholstered furniture, and other merchandise of this sort, but also employ more than seventy people in their upholstering department, where custom orders of every description are taken care of.</p>
   <p>J. F. Rapp, 744 [South] State Street</p>
   <p>All of the older inhabitants will surely remember this firm, as our esteemed <pb facs="5418474_6_1432.jpg" n="9"/>friend is one of the oldest--if not the oldest--German furniture dealers in the city. He has always maintained a reputation for great reliability and reasonable prices. Forced to leave Lake Street because of the great fire, he established himself in the southern part of the city and, since that time, has had a flourishing business.</p>
   <p>A. P. Johnson and Company, 233-251 North Green Street</p>
   <p>The firm A. P. Johnson and Company, consisting of A. P. Johnson, Alderman Borgmeier, and N. Johnson, is highly rated among our local furniture manufacturers, although the concern has been in existence only a short time, since 1868. This rise within such a short period is in itself proof of capable management. Johnson and Company's chief products are chairs, dressers, and washstands. Its output reaches 2500 to 3000 chairs, 250 dressers, and 350 washstands per week. The demand for the company's products may best be indicated by the fact that its business connections extend far beyond the boundaries of our state, into Iowa, Nebraska, and<!--pb facs="5418474_6_1433.jpg" omitted--><pb facs="5418474_6_1434.jpg" n="10"/>Minnesota, and even into California and the Territory of Washington. For the convenience of its customers the company publishes an illustrated yearly catalogue.</p>
   <p>The firm is very careful to use properly seasoned lumber. Hence it always keeps a supply of lumber on hand--from one million to one and one-half million feet.</p>
   <p>McDonough, Price and Company</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Since the firm does not have a German name, the description is condensed. Items of German interest only are given.] This firm located at 290-294 South Canal Street,....ships to many states.... About seventy-five people are steadily employed, including many Germans. German artisans are well represented, particularly in the upholstery department, since their thoroughness is everywhere appreciated....It....is quite commendable....that the firm....succeeded <pb facs="5418474_6_1435.jpg" n="11"/>in securing German patronage. The German is a prudent, careful buyer, frequenting those places where he obtains good, substantial merchandise at reasonable rates. Consequently, a large German clientele is an excellent recommendation for any firm....</p>
   <p>Patzack and Schulz</p>
   <p>The above firm specializes in sewing-machine furniture, that is, the modern elegant wooden mountings and parts connected with sewing machines. This shows how huge enterprises may develop from very modest beginnings, if proper diligence is applied to the task. The business is owned by the partners Patzack and Schulz; it was founded in 1868. For a year the small, modest factory was located in rented quarters on West Erie Street, but the space soon proved inadequate and the company moved to its present location, 193 and 201 West Superior Street, where it occupies three two-story buildings covering a piece of land 96 feet wide by 100 feet long, which is owned by the company. The venture proved prosperous, <pb facs="5418474_6_1436.jpg" n="12"/>and the company was able to retain its full force of sixty-five men throughout the winter, in spite of the depression. Messrs. Patzack and Schulz can well be proud of their accomplishment. During the most dismal times they were able to pay their men promptly and in cash, an achievement which other manufacturers--even though they had the best intentions as far as their workers' welfare was concerned--did not always find possible.</p>
   <p>On the lower floor of the factory are the cutting departments and workshops proper; on the upper floor, the finishing and storage rooms, as well as special rooms for oiling, polishing, etc. The factory is also equipped with a steam and drying house where lumber, from 10,000 to 12,000 feet per week, is subjected to a drying process. Adjacent to the factory is a warehouse for seasoned lumber; at this writing Messrs. Patzack and Schulz have a larger supply of block and walnut lumber than any other factory in Chicago. The most trivial details are under the personal supervision of the owners. As far as this specialty is concerned, the company's sales are not surpassed by those of any other company in the West.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1437.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>Eduard Warnecke, 46-54 Huron Street</p>
   <p>This firm also specializes in sewing-machine furniture. The factory is one of the largest, if not the largest, of its kind in the city; it was founded in 1864 and proved such a successful enterprise that Mr. [Eduard] Warnecke's partner, Mr. Haller, was able to retire a few years ago and return to Germany, where he now lives in affluence. Mr. Warnecke, who continues in the business with ever increasing success, is a cabinetmaker by trade, of the thorough, German type, and therefore has the proper qualifications for a superintendent who takes a personal interest in his extensive factory.</p>
   <p>Aside from this, he is an old resident of our city, honored and respected as a businessman. He has secured such an excellent reputation for his products that many of the leading sewing-machine manufacturers have all their wooden parts made by him. The building--Warnecke's factory--is quite indicative of the extensive business it serves, covering an area of <pb facs="5418474_6_1438.jpg" n="14"/>75 by 80 feet. About ten thousand to twelve thousand feet of cabinet wood are used every week. The excellent quality of the factory's output is due, in great measure, to the care which Mr. Warnecke exercises in the selection of his employees. No one finds permanent employment there unless he meets the exacting demands of Mr. Warnecke, who, as an experienced cabinetmaker, is fully able to judge the ability of his men.</p>
   <p>Mr. Warnecke is not only concerned in producing good merchandise, but he endeavors also to sell it at a reasonable price. Consequently no one will begrudge him his success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
