<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1892-12-03">December 3, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Technical Club "Chicago".</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1000</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1000.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1892-12-03">December 3, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Technical Club "Chicago".</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The technical association "Chicago" held its monthly meeting recently which on account of the fast growing membership of the association, was very well attended. Engineer Haller as representative of the German Government to the Worlds Fair, has been made a member of the association by acclamation. Mr. Haller also represents the German Engineer's and Architects Association, which will visit next year the Worlds Fair by the thousands. After several important matters had been discussed, Prof. Dr.T.E.Siebel, member of the technical association "Chicago" was asked by the president Mr.H.Wallmann, to make his announced speech about"Dr.Mehners chemical Motor and the Second thermodynamical law".</p>
   <p>This chemical motor which has been described by its inventor Dr.Mehner the first time at a meeting of the Franklin institute, effects the transformation of atmosphere warmth into work, and is therefore as admitted by the inventor, a contradiction of the second law of thermodynamics. This, however, should be no reason to reject his invention and he refers to great scientific authorities and the thermodynamic experts of the Patent office in Washington. Dr.Siebel has made it his business to investigate the probabilities of the said motor without the acceptance of such a law and, as it seems, has solved the problem completely. The speaker analyzed the transformation of the heat in the various stages of the Mehner's system and proved in an ingenious and convincing manner, that the physioynomy of the chemical compounds of sal ammonia and liquid ammonia used in this process are contrary to the theoretic <pb facs="5418474_6_1001.jpg" n="2"/>possibilities of the system. The question that if taken for granted, that the motor was possible theoretically, the danger of the formation of chlorine nitrogen would make the use of the motor impossible was answered by the speaker as follows: Though this danger of a chemical nature of related substances does not prevail there are serious difficulties for the practical use of such a system. In a further discussion it was stated, that the Mehner system should be regarded as a perpetuum mobile and for this reason alone should be impossible. Dr.Siebel explained that the Mehner motor is no perpetuum mobile in the real sense of the word, that is no mechanism with which work without power could be produced from nothing. The Mehner motor presents a conservative system, which though in continous movement does not produce work on the outside without equivalent on the other side. Such a system also had been declared by the most eminent scientists as a perpetuum mobile but was deficient to the resolution of the French academy of science made 100 years ago for rejection. Several members of the association participated in the discussion as Dr.Bernard, Dr.Weingaertner engineer Wallman, engineer Neuert, engineer Kandeler, Pres.Wellman thanked Dr.Siebel for the scientific speech and asked the members arise.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
