<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-01-10">Jan. 10, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Thomas Brisch Dies.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1109</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1109.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-01-10">Jan. 10, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THOMAS BRISCH DIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A well known and highly respected business man, Thomas Brisch, president of the Brisch Brick Co., was suddenly called away by the reaper Death, from the circle of his family and friends. A heart attack made an end to his restless activity. Mr. Brisch fell to the ground when he left the building of the Chicago Title &amp; Trust Company and died in a taxi while on the way to the Iroquois Hospital.</p>
   <p>The deceased, numbered among the successful business men of the city, played a prominent part in German circles. Wherever it was necessary to place men with a devoted heart and open look at the top, he was always among those chosen.</p>
   <p>Brisch was born on the Mosel at Reil, emigrated 35 years ago with his brothers to America, and owing to his activity, his business acumen and his honesty, he was greatly esteemed and accumulated a great fortune. He established himself with his brother Michael in the building and real estate business and founded the brick factory, whose president he was until his death.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1110.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He occupied a number of honorary and confidential positions, among others those of director and treasurer of the German Old Peoples Home, treasurer of the Silver Leaf Building and Loan Association, director of the Guardian National Bank, and the Crawford State Bank. He was a member of the Knights of Columbus, and belonged to the German Club. In addition he was a delegate of the Catholic Casino to the United Men's choruses, member of the German Society, of the Germania Club, and a number of other societies.</p>
   <p>He was unmarried and lived with his sister Catherine at 3441 Douglas Blvd. Another brother, Andreas, is a contractor in Oak Park. The funeral will take place Tuesday forenoon, at half past nine o'clock at the Bonifacius cemetery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
