<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-09-07">Sept. 7, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">The Protest of the Chicago Brewers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1385</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1385.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-09-07">Sept. 7, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROTEST OF THE CHICAGO BREWERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, August 29, we reported that the local revenue collector requested the brewers not to use more than two and one-half bushels of malt for each barrel of beer. He demands a tax of one dollars for every two and one-half bushels in excess of this quota. Let us assume that a brewery produced 1,000 barrels of beer and paid the revenue tax thereon, but instead of 2,500 bushels of malt, found it necessary to use 3,000 or 3,500 bushels. In that case the revenue collector wants an additional two hundred, or four hundred dollars.</p>
   <p>The brewers held a meeting and formulated the following protest:</p>
   <p>To General J. D. Webster,</p>
   <p>Revenue Collector, Chicago, Illinois:</p>
   <p>"The undersigned brewers of Chicago have been informed that you have received instructions from Washington to tax the quantity of malt used whenever it is <pb facs="5418474_6_1386.jpg" n="2"/>in excess of two and one-half bushels per barrel of beer. We wish to protest against this regulation. Our objections are based on the following reasons:</p>
   <p>1) This tax is illegal; Congress has passed no law which covers this subject.</p>
   <p>2) Such a tax is unfair and unreasonable, as it would destroy the brewing industry.</p>
   <p>"In regard to the first reason above we would like to submit the following:</p>
   <p>"We hear that the Revenue Department in Washington based this tax on the communication of Commissioner D. W. Douglas, dated July 15, 1874, and published in the Revenue Record on August 10, 1874. This communication is as follows:</p>
   <p>"'Mr. M. Simpson,</p>
   <p>Collector of the Eighth District,</p>
   <p>Lafayette, Indiana.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1387.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"'In reply to your letter regarding taxation of brewers, in which you ask how much material may be used for the manufacture of one barrel of beer, you are informed that, according to circular 18, if the books of a brewer show that two and one-half bushels of malt, or its equivalent in making beer, does not equal the above proportion [i. e., two and one-half bushels of malt per barrel of beer], then, according to circular 23, said brewer shall be reported for taxation. You will then give all details on your blank, circular 23, and this office will decide whether the tax is to be collected or not. Series number 6 is still in force. Respectfully.</p>
   <p>J. W. Douglass.</p>
   <p>Commissioner.'</p>
   <p>"You will see by this that the former commissioner does not propose to collect a tax but merely desires information, and his office will decide whether a tax should or should not be collected.</p>
   <p>"The fact that such a tax was collected only once during the period when <pb facs="5418474_6_1388.jpg" n="4"/>former Commissioner Douglas was in office appears to be sufficient proof that he realized that this tax would not be upheld by the courts.</p>
   <p>"The federal revenue law requires that a brewer report how much beer he has brewed, the amount sold and how much material has been used; and requires that he pay a tax of one dollar for every barrel which contains thirty-one gallons of beer.</p>
   <p>"Whether the brewer produces lager beer, ale, porter, or some other fermented beverage (see paragraph 3339, revised statutes), the tax rate remains unchanged--one dollar per barrel. The alcoholic content of the beer--the percentage of alcohol--does not affect the tax rate. Whether more malt is required to produce ale or porter, or less malt is needed to brew lighter beers, is immaterial, since the tax in either case is the same.</p>
   <p>"Congress never intended to tax beer according to its percentage of alcohol; otherwise Congress would have passed a law similar to the liquor laws.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1389.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"In regard to whisky, Congress empowered the tax commissioner to tax the distilleries in all cases where the commissioner is convinced that the percentage of distilled products, as reported by the distiller, falls below eighty percent of the distillery's capacity.</p>
   <p>"In regard to fermented liquids, no such powers have been given to the commissioner. He has authority to collect the tax imposed by Congress but cannot add or collect additional taxes on his own accord.</p>
   <p>"For this reason we believe that this questionable tax can be recommended only on the ground that we cheated, and brewed additional beer in direct ratio to the amount of malt consumed, and that we sold beer without paying a revenue tax.</p>
   <p>"If such an accusation is contemplated, then we hereby record our emphatic denial, as we consider such an accusation unjustified and unfounded, and we <pb facs="5418474_6_1390.jpg" n="6"/>demand a thorough investigation; in fact, we promise to give the officials of the Internal Revenue Department every possible assistance.</p>
   <p>"In regard to the second point, that the tax is unfair and unreasonable, etc., we respectfully submit the following facts:</p>
   <p>1) To stipulate by law that only two and one-half bushels of malt may be used for one barrel of beer, is tantamount to demanding that the brewer make beer of only a certain strength, irrespective of whether the consumers will be satisfied. Furthermore, such a law would entirely ignore the fact that malt is not always of the same quality. A certain kind of malt will often produce twenty-five per cent more beer than other varieties of malt. Malt costs from $1.00 to $1.75. At least three and one-half bushels of malt are needed for one barrel of beer, if the one-dollar malt is used, whereas,with the higher-priced malt two and one-half bushels will be enough.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1391.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Should the brewer who uses the cheaper grade of malt--because he believes in buying cheaper supplies and using an inferior article--pay a higher tax? Would that be sensible and just? Or can the Government dictate the quality of the malt as well as the quantity?</p>
   <p>2) The brewers of Chicago and the entire West use barley almost exclusively, whereas in the East substitutes are used for malt, such as grape sugar, Indian corn, and rice. As it is very difficult to say what quantities of such substitutes are equivalent to one bushel of barley malt the brewers in the East find it very simple to limit their malt to two and one-half bushels per barrel of beer.</p>
   <p>3) The brewers of Chicago and other Western cities make a [considerably] stronger and better beer than the Eastern breweries, because the consumers demand it. To satisfy their customers, the Chicago brewers must produce a malt which--according to the saccharimeter--measures <pb facs="5418474_6_1392.jpg" n="8"/>twenty-four pounds per barrel, and to obtain such a specific gravity from Western barley it is necessary to use more than two and one-half bushels of malt per barrel of beer.</p>
   <p>The Western brewers can readily make a better and stronger beer than Eastern brewers, because malt made of Western barley can be obtained at a lower cost and, secondly, because beer in the West sells steadily at ten dollars per barrel, whereas in the Eastern states the price is often lower.</p>
   <p>4) If the Government insists that not more than two and one-half bushels of malt shall be used for one barrel of beer, and that the quality of malt is not to be considered, such a measure would be a sort of temperance law, because a lighter grade of beer would result.</p>
   <p>This would be an indirect usurpation of state rights, and the states have belabored the brewers often enough. Such a Government law, as <pb facs="5418474_6_1393.jpg" n="9"/>has been said, would not only be detrimental to the brewers, but it would also restrict revenues considerably.</p>
   <p>If this principle is to be enforced, then ale and porter should not be taxed at the gallon rate, but according to the strength of the beer.</p>
   <p>5) The beer of Chicago brewers is of almost uniform strength, and the difference in the amount of malt used is due to the use of various kinds of malt. A beer of Chicago strength can be made with less malt by using the best grade of Western barley, but more malt will be required if the brewer buys barley of grade 2 or 3. And, when making mash of good California or the best Canadian barley, the ratio of malt to one barrel of beer is decreased still further.</p>
   <p>6) There is another reason why no brewer can predict the actual amount of raw material needed: No brewer knows what his percentage of loss <pb facs="5418474_6_1394.jpg" n="10"/>will be. Usually the loss is twenty per cent from the time the beer is brewed to the time when it is ready for sale. Accidents, mistakes, or inexpert workers may cause a decidedly greater loss.</p>
   <p>"In submitting these incontestable facts and the deductions drawn from them, we believe that the we have offered irrefutable proof that the threatened tax is unjustified.</p>
   <p>"We know, of course, that the Revenue Department, though it does not have legal power to enforce such a tax, does, nevertheless, have authority to assess and collect the tax. An injunction against the Department's action cannot be obtained. We can be compelled to pay the tax under protest, though we may then seek a refund from the commissioner. This involves a waiting period of six months to a year before his decision is made known. In case he refuses to refund the money paid, our only recourse will be to the courts. This, in turn, means one year of waiting before the case is even accepted.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1395.jpg" n="11"/>
   <p>"We desire to avoid such unpleasantness and we doubt that the Administration will compel us, in view of the evidence which we have submitted, to pay a tax which is neither due nor legal.</p>
   <p>"We also do not believe that it would be good statesmanship on the part of any administration to fill the Government treasury with large sums which may have to be returned at the behest of a petit jury.</p>
   <p>"We have confidence in the justice of our cause and expect that the question-able tax will not be assessed.</p>
   <p>Bartholomae and Roesing</p>
   <p>Peter Schoenhofen</p>
   <p>Schmidt and Glade</p>
   <p>F. Binz</p>
   <p>Bartholomae and Leicht</p>
   <p>Downer and Bemis Brewing Company</p>
   <p>Matthaeus Gottfried</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1396.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>Busch and Brand Brewing Company</p>
   <p>Conrad Seipp</p>
   <p>Edmund Juessen, attorney."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
