<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-18">Feb. 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Canadian Migration Problem</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0843</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0843.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-18">Feb. 18, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE CANADIAN MIGRATION PROBLEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last few years, at least 100,000 young American farmers emigrated to Western Canada. The majority were from Iowa, Nebraska, Minnesota, and other agricultural states of that section in the United States. Within the last decade, it is said, about one million have settled in the Dominion.</p>
   <p>These numbers are destined to arouse some apprehension among our agricultural population. Such a quantum represents a serious economic loss, particularly to the agricultural regions. This emigration cannot be readily counter-balanced by a large immigration from Europe, which at present is likely to be curtailed or suspended entirely as a result of nearsightedness and restrictive laws.</p>
   <p>It is very detrimental to us because this contingent represents our young American-born farmers; hence, men who have learned their calling under the <pb facs="5418474_6_0844.jpg" n="2"/>watchful guidance of their experienced, successful fathers; and in availing themselves of the exceedingly liberal inducement provided by the Canadian homestead laws, they become the most desirable influx to Canada. But to us, they are irretrievably lost, since the English statues require them to swear allegiance to King George V of England before they may acquire any land.</p>
   <p>Of course, several thousand young farmers returned within the last few weeks. They fled, fearing the ominous specter of general military servitude, which is a recently inaugurated English product. They were not inclined to market their staunch and healthy osseous frames for re-inforcements of the King. Their English assimilation was still superficial, regardless of oaths of expatriation and subservience to George V, and they preferred prudence to valor.</p>
   <p>But what benefit is derived by the few who return when compared to the hundreds <pb facs="5418474_6_0845.jpg" n="3"/>of thousands remaining and becoming bona fide Canadian citizens? Can the European immigration give us a fully satisfactory substitute for this valuable young people obsorbed by Canada? The German and Scandinavian farmers, always our most desirable element, will find such favorable conditions in their own country, after the war, that they won't have any inclination for migration towards our distant American West to make our wilderness amenable to culture; at best a very laborious task.</p>
   <p>Aside from that, our West has lost its attraction. All valuable agricultural land is in private possession. Homesteads of 160 acres for one family, free as of yore, are not available any more.</p>
   <p>Of course there are large areas in the West which are offered for settlement; 260 million acres of government land. Thus four fifths of the State of Nevada, two thirds of Utah, half of Wyoming, one fifth to one third of Oregon, Idaho, Montana, Colorado, California, and New Mexico may be had. But no one only <pb facs="5418474_6_0846.jpg" n="4"/>slightly familiar with the local topography and agriculture, cares for it. Although Uncle Sam claims that about half of it (130 million acres) is suitable farming land, nobody places much reliance on this assertion. Arid land, stony and sandy; tufts of grass occasionally, which serve as meager pasturage for cattle and sheep; it is not tempting.</p>
   <p>Several land bills were recently submitted to Congress. One provides for a unit of 640 acres for grazing land homesteads. That much would suffice to support a family, but the cattle rangers of these parts, who enjoy free and unrestricted use of wide stretches of government land, do not cherish the prospect of seeing this vast territory cut up into fenced farms. They declare, quite brazenly, that not even forty head of cattle can be maintained on 640 acres; it requires more than 1,280 acres. But as these gentlemen have "special interests," it does not behoove us to accept their verdict at face value. Nevertheless, these districts are infamous due to the sanguinary feuds between cattle raisers and sheep herders; surely not very desirable from the settler's <pb facs="5418474_6_0847.jpg" n="5"/>standpoint, when Canada is so near, where the best wheat land can be had for the asking, and other practical inducements are given to the homesteader; benefits which are unobtainable elsewhere.</p>
   <p>Uncle Sam who would like to keep his young farmers on his own soil, finds this a serious problem. Canada has an advantage which he cannot equal, regardless of any number of homestead laws. Neighbor Canada entices with her wheat fields, and is simply superior. After the war, the Canadian advantages will be more apparent than ever, and emigration from the United States will take on a very noticeable increase.</p>
   <p>What shall our Nation do about it? Look on with equanimity how our best blood is drained from us for evermore, or pass a law against emigration to Canada? Hardly.</p>
   <p>There is a solution exceedingly, yea, frightfully simple: annexation of <pb facs="5418474_6_0848.jpg" n="6"/>Canada by the United States. Under an English George, - the third to be specific, - England had to relinquish part of her American holdings. Why not finish the work which started so successfully 140 years ago? Let it be completed under George V, so that the rest of this colonial territory may be ceded to the United States, which is, after all, "the nearest," historically and geographically. It will not create a very Raucous dispute. Just now the world map is being subjected to considerable "changes," and if we revise our Northern boundry just a little, it would not amount to much more than a "moping up," Would the Canadians object very much? Only recently they assured us of their friendship based on "racial solidarity and homogeneousness." Now let them be serious and express their sentiments through action.</p>
   <p>It is easily accomplishable now. Uncle Sam need not issue two proclamations to obtain 500,000 tried and experienced soldiers, who would revel in making the command a reality. Ere long the problem must be solved; why not now, when the operation would be short and almost painless? Just a little courage!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
