<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-15">Dec. 15, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Old Heidelberg at the Next World's Fair</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mayor Cermak Makes Speech of Laying of Cornerstone This Afternoon</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1064</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1064.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-15">Dec. 15, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">OLD HEIDELBERG AT THE NEXT WORLD'S FAIR</title><title level="a" type="sub">Mayor Cermak Makes Speech of Laying of Cornerstone This Afternoon</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the site of the World's Fair there took place, this afternoon, the laying of the corner stone for the Old Heidelberg Inn; it was attended by many outstanding personalities. It is the structure intended to contain a restaurant with a rathskeller erected by the brothers Max and Robert Eitel. We are told that this structure is going to be the largest building to serve such purposes at the World's Fair.</p>
   <p>Robert Eitel addressed the guests witnessing the laying of the corner stone with sincere words. But, owing to cold weather, he made it rather brief and concluded by giving expression to the hope that at the time the inn is open for business there will be a possibility to sit in the restaurant or in the rathskeller and peacefully enjoy a glass of beer.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1065.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mayor Cermak followed Mr. Eitel with a brief address, in which he congratulated those who undertook and planned the structure, and expressed the hope that "Old Heidelberg" might become a token of the return of the former days of personal liberty. Then he drew the attention to "Old Heidelberg" and to its seeming destiny to occupy a place of honor at the World's Fair. It will also maintain that place just as the Brothers Eitel, who in the year 1893 made a favorable reputation for the same field at another World's Fair.</p>
   <p>The mayor looked forward to being one of the first guests of "Old Heidelberg" at the opening of the World's Fair, not only to enjoy reminiscences of former days, but gratefully to remember the pleasant days he spent in Germany during the past summer months.</p>
   <p>Besides Mayor Cermak, there were at the laying of the corner stone the following guests of honor: the German consul general, Dr. H. F. Simon; Ernst J. Kruetgen, chairman of the German group of the World's Fair and vice-president <pb facs="5418474_6_1066.jpg" n="3"/>of the city's board of local improvements; Ernst Buehler, Swiss consul and member of the city's board of education; Dr. O.L. Schmidt, Ludwig Plate, A. C. E. Schmidt, Fred Haake, Oscar Mayer, Jr., Edward H. Landsberg, Mrs. Emma Eitel, Emil Eitel, Paul H. Mueller, editor of the Abendpost and Sonntagpost, Rufus Dawes, Mr. Whitfield, and Dr. Moulton.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
