<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1862-02-10">Feb. 10, 1862</date>.
<title level="a">The Rights of Immigrants at the Constiutional Convention</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0670</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0670.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1862-02-10">Feb. 10, 1862</date>.
<title level="a">THE RIGHTS OF IMMIGRANTS AT THE CONSTIUTIONAL CONVENTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last campaign we insisted that the Germans be represented in the Constitutional Convention of the State of Illinois; we emphasized that our need for recognition was the only reason for our recommendation for a suitable candidate to be present at the meeting at Kingsbury Hall, and we stated that we were not in the least interested in conferring a well-paying county office to a mere political job chaser. It was our intention to protect our rights to vote, for a change in the Constitution might involve a restriction or an expansion of this right. And we note from the official report on the proceedings of the Convention (January 29) that our German delegate, Mr. John Henry Muehlke, made the following proposal, which was adopted:</p>
   <p>Resolved, That the Committee on Elections and Franchise consider the feasibility of granting the right to vote to all foreign-born residents of this state who volunteered to serve in the army or navy during the present Rebellion and who <pb facs="5418474_6_0671.jpg" n="2"/>have been honorably discharged, or who will serve in the armed forces of the Union during this War and receive an honorable dismissal, if such persons are not disqualified for any reason save that they are not citizens of the United States.</p>
   <p>From the very beginning of the campaign we did not hesitate to give Mr. Muehlke our full support; and as far as we have been able to follow his activity to date, we do not doubt that not only the Germans of Chicago, but also of the whole state will look upon their choice with great satisfaction.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
