<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-01">Feb. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Josef Schneider Becomes Citizen</title><title level="a" type="sub">German Captain of Industry Inventor of the Ball Bearing</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1120</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1120.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-01">Feb. 1, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">JOSEF SCHNEIDER BECOMES CITIZEN</title><title level="a" type="sub">German Captain of Industry Inventor of the Ball Bearing</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Having passed a second examination before Circuit Court Judge Barrett, thirty-four Germans and seventeen German-Austrians and Bohemians received their citizenship papers yesterday. The Austrians were required to abjure allegiance to Emperor Karl, and the Germans were required to abjure allegiance to Emperor Wilhelm. Mr. Stephan Schneider was one of those who were naturalized. [Translator's note: In the heading, Mr. Schneider's Christian name is given as "Josef".]</p>
   <p>He resides at 2016 Sedgwick Street and is the owner of the Schneider Ball Bearing Company, on Berteau Avenue. Nine years ago he emigrated from Silesia, Germany, and founded his company. He furnished England with war material during the entire time of the war.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1121.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"It is my wish that the United States win every war," he said, "and I would have sent my son, had he not been but seventeen years old. During the war I employed forty-eight men, and now I have forty working for me. All my interests are centered in this country."</p>
   <p>Later, Mr. Schneider told a representative of the Abendpost that he worked many years as a mechanical engineer in Berlin, and became independent after having invented the ball bearing.</p>
   <p>The export of his product to America increased to such an extent that he found it expedient to emigrate to this country nine years ago. Here he opened his business with one employee. After a short time, he built the three-story factory at Harrison Street and Clarence Avenue, and founded the United States Ball Bearing Company. He was president of the organization. A. A. Strom was vice-president, and Paul Schulte was secretary and treasurer.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1122.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In 1913 he sold his interest in the business, intending to return to Germany, but before he could carry out his plan, war broke out, so he opened a new factory. In the old factory he employed 1,100 men.</p>
   <p>He has obtained eighty patents; one or more in every civilized country of the world, and twenty-two in America. In the monthly magazine published by the Illinois Manufacturers' Association, he is pictured as one of the captains of industry.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
