<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-02-19">Feb. 19, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">Seventh Ward Seward Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0714</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0714.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-02-19">Feb. 19, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">SEVENTH WARD SEWARD CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following resolutions were unanimously adopted in a meeting which the Seventh Ward Club and the Seward Club held Saturday evening, February 16, 1861.</p>
   <p>Whereas, Several Chicago meat packers and grain merchants are doing everything they possibly can during the current week to support the compromisers in the Senate and the House of Representatives, by stating that nineteen twentieths of the Republicans of Chicago are in favor of compromise; therefore be it</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we consider honesty to be a prime virtue in business as well as in politics, and that we deem it a great injustice that those gentlemen want to barter free territories to slavery, and that they approve of such bartering because now they probably are not able to buy as much pork and flour as they were wont; further</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0715.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That those gentlemen are guilty of an infamous lie when they claim that they represent nineteen twentieths of the Republican party of Chicago; for in the Seventh Ward alone there are more than twelve hundred Germans who are affiliated with the Republican party, and thus far we have not heard of a single one among them who approves of such an ignominious compromise as the Kellogg Compromise; further</p>
   <p>That we are firmly resolved to a bide by the Chicago platform and to oppose any and every compromise which cedes even an inch of free territory to slavery, and will hand over those of our representatives who barter free territories to slavery to the scorn and contempt of the present and future generations.</p>
   <p>The gentlemen speak of a dictatorship which the Tribune is trying to exercise over them, but to which they will not submit. And they wax angry, very angry, indeed. Poor Tribune, you had better tremble--for didn't you adhere to and defend the principles of the Republican Party?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0716.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, the gentlemen referred to apparently do not know that the Rebels have insulted our flag and stolen our forts, our ships, our money, and our weapons--that they have heaped shame upon our flag and humiliated it in the sight of the world; these acts seem to be of no consequence to these men whose sole honor and distinction seems to consist of making money. The Southerners have long had the privilege of making and ridiculing the North, of tarring and feathering the opponents of slavery, and as a reward for such acts we are to donate the free territories to them; for they are our dear, dear brothers of the South! Do you not notice a trace of dictatorship in their conduct? Therefore, be it further</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we declare the proposed compromise of Mr. Kellogg treason to the Republican party and openly comdemn it.</p>
   <p>In conclusion we would say that these resolutions will be published in the English language and German language newspapers, and a copy will be sent to each of our congressmen. We ask all German Republican clubs of Chicago <pb facs="5418474_6_0717.jpg" n="4"/>to voice their opinions on this matter.</p>
   <p>H. Hett, President; C. Scheef, Secretary; Seward Club Philipp Wetzel, President; E. Kaeseburg, Secretary; Seventh Ward Club</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
