<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-04-29">April 29. 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Our Latest Disgrace.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-04-29">April 29. 1914</date>.
<title level="a">OUR LATEST DISGRACE.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The South American diplomatic peace conference which undertook to iron out their differences, has found no base for action, and the duodecimo diplomats are forced to recognize that Huerta is prepared to give the United States every satisfaction desired, but as a counter demand he wants recognition for his government. Don't laugh. Huerta possesses political logic which is sadly missing in our government. The Alpha and Omega of our government's demands was from the beginning the unconditional retirement of Huerta. Now that our national honor has been fully outraged after Americans have been killed in war and by the hands of assassins, after our flag has been trodden into the mud and our consul general has been dragged to jail, and now that our land and sea forces have been mobilized, and now that the American people, in one voice, are crying for war comes Mr. Huerta and promises satisfaction, but only in case America humbles itself and recognizes him as the head of the Mexican Republic. Huerta has a right to insist upon recognition. He has been, regardless of Washington, already recognized. He has been recognized by our entering into diplomatic negotiations with him. What else but recognition can such a report mean, as that the government in Washington as well as Huerta's government has been requested to set forth their claims after which the claims of Huerta will be laid before President Wilson, and the latter's demands will be submitted to Huerta? Meanwhile a conference between Villa, who has flirted <pb facs="5418474_6_0451.jpg" n="2"/>with us, and Carranza who has negotiated with us with results to which we can not remain indifferent. The two generals to all appearances have buried the battle ax and have resolved to act energetically against Huerta. But it is a question whether this means opposition against Huerta only. Carranza, in a message to Wilson, has demanded the evacuation of Mexican soil. President Wilson has refused. Carranza might consider this a declaration of war, and turn against the United States, for whom he has never shown much love, and whom he hates the more, because Washington has prohibited the export of Arms to Mexico anew. The United States has made Mexico its enemy regardless of the pilot at its helm.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
