<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost, (Sunday edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-07-01">July 1, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Parent Country of the United States</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0400</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0400.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost, (Sunday edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-07-01">July 1, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE PARENT COUNTRY OF THE UNITED STATES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Next Wednesday the United States celebrates the anniversary of the Declaration of Independence. On this day, all Americans, whichever party they belong to, or whichever nationality they come from, will be mindful of their unity. One may, through all the 364 days of the year, have, on his tongue, dissatisfaction with this or that national development, with this or that Congressional resolution, with the political aims and methods of the parties or of the President, and one may let his dissatisfaction escape through his lips, but on this day all are as one in the pride of belonging to this nation which evolved from small beginnings to a great power commanding universal respect today.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0401.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Owing to a misinterpreted tradition, the world is used to referring to the American people as to an Anglo-Saxon nation. The American people is only in part, and not in its greatest part, composed of Anglo-Saxons. Foreign countries are misled by the fact that English is the language of the country, and by the further fact that a sizeable number of American family names mark their bearers as Anglo-Saxons. That English is the language of the country results from the circumstance that the thirteen English colonies, situated on the Atlantic coast, were originally owned by the English crown at the time the States emancipated themselves from Europe. Had they, at the time, been under the sovereignty of Holland, France, or Spain, it is likely that the language of the country would have become Dutch, French, or Spanish. Even in those early days, the colonies were not exclusively inhabited by Anglo-Saxons. Many Dutchmen, Germans, Frenchmen, and Scandinavians lived among them, and all these nationalities played a part in the War of the Revolution. No one should be deceived by the preponderant number of Anglo-Saxon names!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0402.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A considerable part of those who immigrated from Europe dropped their old names, because they were difficult to pronounce by others, by either anglicizing them or exchanging them for English ones. This is a quite natural procedure, encountered in all countries having a large immigration.</p>
   <p>As the immigrants became absorbed in their work and in their business, and since it became necessary to utilize all one's energy to make a living for oneself and family, and since they pretty soon came in touch with American politics (which tended to make their Americanization complete), there was scarcely any time left to maintain contact with their old homeland which, because of great distance, became increasingly difficult. Their eyes were fastened upon the new homeland in which they took root, where their children were born, where their own and their children's future lay. So it came that after two or three generations there often remained but a hazy reminiscence of the family's land of origin, and even that finally vanished. This was hastened by marital unions with other nationalities. Think of the <pb facs="5418474_6_0403.jpg" n="4"/>case of a German who came to America and here married an Irish girl. Their son in turn, later married a girl of French Canadian descent. What nationality is the product of this marriage supposed to belong to? To the German? Scarcely! The ties which bind him to Germany through his grandfather are indeed weak in the face of the fact that his grandmother was Irish, and his mother of French descent. He regards himself neither as German, Irish, nor French but merely as an American whose original German family name, if it was not suited to the English tongue, had probably been Americanized beyond recognition, unless his grandfather had left him a name that sounded more like Irish or English.</p>
   <p>This "melting pot" process, which for years went on in the United States, the future will be able to alter but very little. What has entered the melting pot of the American Union comes out again, perhaps after a hundred years, in the shape of a grandchild or great-grandchild who is just another American without the least vestige of origin. Whether the cradle of his <pb facs="5418474_6_0404.jpg" n="5"/>people once stood in England, Ireland, Germany, Russia, Italy, Spain, or elsewhere will eventually make no difference. Certain traits of his character may be manifest which will bear witness to the origin of his family. Since, on the other hand, the third or fourth generation of an immigrant rarely keeps its national purity, his entire character will have undergone corresponding changes. At any rate the grandchild or great-grand-child of an immigrant is a pure American, even if his original name had undergone no change in the meantime.</p>
   <p>It is therefore absurd to speak of America as an Anglo-Saxon nation. In our days, there are just as few Anglo-Saxons as there are Scandinavians, Germans, or Frenchmen. The people were no longer exclusively Anglo-Saxon at the time independence was declared. For among the signers of the Declaration there were sixteen of non-British origin, and eight whose cradle had stood in a foreign country. The "parent country" of the United States was not England alone, but Europe in general. It is well to bear that in mind from time to time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
