<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-01-19">Jan 19, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">A Chemical Motor for Operating the Street Cap System</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1209</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1209.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-01-19">Jan 19, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">A CHEMICAL MOTOR FOR OPERATING THE STREET CAP SYSTEM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The inventive spirit of a German engineer was praised yesterday by a large number of our fellow citizens who during the noon hour saw with astonishment two unknown street - cars travel to the barns of the Chicago Passenger Railway Company on Centre Avenue. The company had imported the two cars from Germany and wanted to demonstrate them to the public in a few days. On the insistance of two marine engineers who are here from New York, the officials felt obliged yesterday to arrange a test ride. This type of car has been used for some time in the outskirts of Berlin and have proved very satisfying. The driving power that causes its locomotion is produced in a kettle filled with caustic soda. The power is so strong that by a single heating of the kettle, it can drive the main car, that carries the kettle and which looks like our ordinary cars, and also, two additional passenger cars over a distance of more than 40 miles. The new "chemical" car is 11 feet long and 7 feet wide. One of the advantages of the new motors is that by means of opening a valve the entire car can be filled with hot air. The brakes are very easy to operate. Only one man (both conductor and motorman is needed for its operation. The unnecessary noise, caused by horse drawn and cable cars is abolished and the cost of operating is extremely cheap. A new motor cost between $2,000 and $2,500.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Passenger Railway Company will within a short time outfit its entire service system with the new motors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
