<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-01-01">Jan. 1, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">The Wm. Schmidt Baking Co.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1194</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1194.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-01-01">Jan. 1, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">THE WM. SCHMIDT BAKING CO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Germans can look with justifiable pride upon one of the greatest business ventures of its kind, which had a very modest and small beginning in 1874, when it was brought to life by a very capable German. It stands today, an astounding monument to the success of an able, enterprising, and progressively spirited, business man. We refer to Mr. Wm Schmidt, or rather as his firm is now known, to the Wm. Schmidt Baking Co. In the beginning, about 1870, Mr. Schmidt functioned as the worker. The daily receipts after its initial opening, were less than one dollar. Within fifteen years his income mounted to $800,00 or $900,00 per day. To obtain such an expansion, requires excellent business sagacity, an untiring energy, and that rare talent of giving a hand when needed. Mr. Schmidt was well versed in the lore of success; he made his establishment a model to be emulated. It is an excellently appointed store with the best and most select merchandise, a comfortable office, gigantic storage space, immaculately clean baking rooms, packing and machinery halls which are wonders of the trade, in fact, wherever one glances the beholder is confronted with proofs of constant progress and business energy which elicit admiration. During the month of March, however, at a time when Mr. Schmidt was away on an extensive business trip, he suffered a severe misfortune. His</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1195.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>splendid establishment was completely destroyed by fire, a mere remnant of dust and ashes, but on October 3rd, like the mythological Phoenix, it grew anew and today the officials of the organization, and Mr. Schmidt in particular, look upon the past year as a successful one, in spite of the calamity that confronted them. Mr. Schmidt is a highly esteemed member of many German clubs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
