<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-18">Jan. 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Keep Your Government Insurance Policies!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0056</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0056.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-18">Jan. 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">KEEP YOUR GOVERNMENT INSURANCE POLICIES!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nearly all of the many thousands of young soldiers who are now returning home have insured their lives with the government on very favorable terms. The majority of them are young; they are in their so-called best years, and, when they answered the call of their country, they had not yet established their own homes, perhaps had not even given that matter any thought. Still they subscribed for insurance--in most instances because their superiors, or friends, or relatives, urged them to do so, since it was very possible that they might not return from the war; and it was a source of consolation for them to know that their loved ones would be cared for in the event that they should meet death on the battlefield.</p>
   <p>Now that the war is over, some of them may think that there is no necessity <pb facs="5418474_6_0057.jpg" n="2"/>for keeping up their insurance. They are hale and hearty and give no thought to death. They expect to support their dependent relatives by working, consider insurance superfluous, and let their policies expire.</p>
   <p>Warnings against such thoughtlessness cannot be too forcible. No one knows how long he will live. The next hour may be the last. Even the strongest, even the seemingly healthiest, may very suddenly and very soon fall a prey to the grim reaper. Every year thousands upon thousands lose their lives by accidents against which they could not protect themselves. Even the youth who to-day boasts of his abundant strength may be a helpless victim of disease tomorrow, and soon thereafter a corpse. What comfort could he not derive in his last hours from the knowledge that his dependents would not suffer from want after his departure! The sooner he begins to provide for his dependents the smaller the cost will be....No private company would have assumed the risk which the government assumed when it sold its insurance to the nation's soldiers. Only the <pb facs="5418474_6_0058.jpg" n="3"/>fact that the wealth of the entire nation served as security enabled Uncle Sam to sell his soldiers insurance on such favorable terms. Anyone who drops his government insurance, thinking that he can obtain insurance on similar terms at any time, is acting very foolishly. Prudence dictates that every owner of a government insurance policy pay his premiums very promptly, for thus he earns the privilege of converting his war policy into a regular government policy without submitting to a medical examination.</p>
   <p>The Government intends to issue various kinds of life-insurance policies, regular policies, annuity policies, twenty-year endowment policies, and others. Present policyholders may choose any one of these, and in choosing may avail themselves of the experience which the Government has had in the insurance business. Government insurance is attractive for another reason, namely, that the Government operates at less cost than other insurance companies. Then again, the premiums paid for Government insurance <pb facs="5418474_6_0059.jpg" n="4"/>are invested for the benefit of the nation, while the private companies let the enormous sums which they accept from their clients flow into Wall Street, whereby the power of the barons of finance is steadily increased. Investigation affords ample proof that much of the money which the worshippers of gold lose through speculation in lower Manhattan's temples of Mammon, or through extravagance and dissipation, comes from the pockets of policyholders. It would be a severe blow to these plutocrats if government insurance should become a permanent public institution, a legal obligation--and sooner or later it will. For this reason these gentlemen are opposed to such an institution. They know that their income from premium payments would cease, and the power which they have over the people would wane. They did not earn the contents of their coffers. These are filled chiefly with the savings of the common people, and the "bears" and "bulls" use these savings for their speculation on the market.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
