<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-06-07">June 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">A Disgrace to Humanity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0138</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0138.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-06-07">June 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">A DISGRACE TO HUMANITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It cannot be denied that very essential improvements have already taken place in our penal and reform institutions, in our insane asylums, and in our houses for the poor. However, there is yet much to be done before conditions in these institutions will be such that the work "scandalous" will no longer describe them.</p>
   <p>Although it is not a pleasant task to criticize our own affairs, we shall proceed to do so; and for this purpose we shall make use of the report made by the Charity Organization of our state. This report unfolds a very clear picture of the prevalent conditions in the poor-houses, and, above all, in the County jails of our state.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0139.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All this leads anew to the conviction that as soon as a virtue,in itself commendable, is carried to excess, it becomes a vice, and its effects are the opposite of what was originally intended. This excessive economizing in the respective institutions causes the county and the state increasingly larger expenses, because our jails and poor-houses can be justly called criminal factories.</p>
   <p>The conditions prevalent in these institutions, have not been a secret for a long time, but the above mentioned report of the Charity Society of the state has called attention to it again. The conditions at Dunning, one of our county institutions, are well-known. Just recently the report of the grand jury pointed out that the supply of water is insufficient, and that the sewerage system is faulty. The <pb facs="5418474_6_0140.jpg" n="3"/>first evil would increase the danger in case of fire, and the second is a continuous threat to the health of the inmates. Undoubtedly, these serious conditions would have been ameliorated long ago if the county officials had not been robbed of the necessary means by unwise economy.</p>
   <p>The report critizes especially the conditions in our jails. These institutions are, almost exclusively, far below what they should be. They are dirty, full of vermin of all kinds, and they lack sufficient light, ventilation, as well as suitable heating systems. The food for the inmates is also very deficient. Therefore, the jails are designated in the report as being a disgrace to humanity.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0141.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the jail of Pope County, the bedding of the prisoners lies on the floor of the cells. There are no chairs, or any other furniture; and the inmates must either stand or lie on the floor. During the winter, they are forced to seek protection against cold weather in these cells, even in the day-time, because there is no provision made for a heating system, and very little sunshine can enter the building.</p>
   <p>In regard to the jail in Union County, this is stated: "The building is like a vault for the dead; it is dark, damp, and its system of ventilation and heating is defective. Common sense demands that these scandalous conditions be remedied, even if there is no sympathy for <pb facs="5418474_6_0142.jpg" n="5"/>the inmates of these institutions. The behaviour and morals of the criminal elements cannot be improved by keeping them in such institutions for shorter or longer periods of time; on the contrary, they will suffer greater injury, and become worse morally.</p>
   <p>The National Society for Prison Reform will hold its conference in Chicago in the near future. It is most advisable that the lectures to be given by the Society, receive unusual attention and a hearty response. It will contribute materially to the amelioration of the serious conditions that we have pointed out and described.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
