<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-01-17">Jan. 17, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Symphony Concerts</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1696</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1696.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-01-17">Jan. 17, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">SYMPHONY CONCERTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not many years ago a symphony concert on Sunday afternoons would have seemed quite impossible, although the price of admission may have been within the reach of almost everybody. Compositions of the lightest nature made up our Sunday afternoon concerts until recently. It is also true that orchestra leaders had no confidence in the musical appreciation of their audiences.</p>
   <p>However, the Thomas Concerts given in the Fair building during the summer of 1877 are accredited with awakening the public's desire for finer music. . . . Several attempts were made thereafter to establish regular symphony concerts but these proved futile. The musical offerings by such renowned musicians and orchestra leaders as Adolph Liesegang, Rosenbecker, and S. G. Pratt were appreciated, nevertheless none of these orchestras was given the necessary financial support. Consequently, the organizations were forced to disband.</p>
   <p>Mr. Liesegang was persistent however, and formulated plans to give Chicago <pb facs="5418474_6_1697.jpg" n="2"/>symphony concerts at a moderate admission price, hoping to create a general interest for the higher type of music. In the rendition of the second series of concerts yesterday, he and his musicians deserve the highest praise and encouragement.</p>
   <p>The first number on the program was Mendelssohn's symphony in A major, better known as the Italian symphony. This work enjoys the distinction of being the most melodious and pleasing among symphonic compositions. It may be stated that this performance could be favorably compared with the presentation of the work of Thomas's orchestra. We shall not indulge in criticism of the somewhat faulty technique, because we were more than compensated by the enthusiasm of the musicians. Beethoven's brilliant "Septet," opus 20, was undoubtedly the most impressive number on the program, as was attested by the applause of the appreciative audience. "The March of the Riders" by Schubert was the least satisfying rendition of the evening. The rhythmic beauty of this composition was lost by insufficient force of expression. In contrast to this, Weber's "Invitation to the Dance" was in every detail delightfully shaded. The inspiring overture to "Figaro" concluded the concert.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
