<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-08-14">Aug. 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Farmers' Week</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0817</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <!-- 5418474_6_0816 omitted, duplicate of 5418474_6_0817 -->
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0817.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-08-14">Aug. 14, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">FARMERS' WEEK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Farmers' Week at the World's Fair brought not only the farmers to Chicago but also the politicians, who proclaim the saving of agriculture as their aim. Two of the latter, Senator Elmer Thomas of Oaklahoma and Chester C. Davis of the A. A. A., made use of Farmers' Week to submit their saving plans to the country. Thomas is generally looked upon as the leader of the inflationist group. He, however, emphatically denies that he or his associates aim at unlimited inflation. Rather it is his contention that they want nothing but to lower the price of gold to the status it had in 1926. They have chosen 1926 because, in their opinion, most of the present debts were contracted at a time when the value of gold was approximately that of 1926. It can also be said that the prices for agricultural products should be raised to the level of the year 1926. Thomas wants to achieve this end by having the President, by executive order, raise the price of gold an additional eighteen per cent.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0818.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This would automatically decrease the gold content of the dollar by eighteen per cent.</p>
   <p>One may, contrary to this argument, contend that the Government sometime ago reduced by forty per cent the gold content of the dollar, without increasing prices to any noticeable degree. The prices of agricultural products began to soar when, because of the drought, these products became scarcer. Senator Thomas maintains that price formation depends entirely upon the exchange value of money. This view point is a false one.</p>
   <p>Every Chicagoan knows that all rents have been reduced by fifty per cent during the last five years. There were two reasons for this. First, so much had been built during the preceding years that the supply exceeded the demand. Second, tenants have had to cut their expenses because of the depression. These two deciding factors cannot be undone by inflationary measures and, as a matter of fact, the decrease of the gold content of the dollar did not result in a rise of rents.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0819.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Prices of agricultural products, in the same manner, are not determined solely by the exchange value of money. The latter depends largely upon the ability of the domestic and foreign markets to absorb these products, as well as upon nature, which sometimes lavishes abundant crops upon the farmer and at other times bestows poor crops.</p>
   <p>All these factors are omitted in Thomas' views, and his arguments are thus of no practical value. The contentions of Mr. Davis, who attempts to defend the artificial reduction of agricultural products, make no claim to serious consideration in the face of the poor crops expected this year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
