<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-07-28">July 28, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Our Drinking Water</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0865</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0865.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-07-28">July 28, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">OUR DRINKING WATER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whenever the summer heat gets us in its grip, our Commissioner of Water Works complains about the inconsiderate waste of water. This at least, is given as an explanation for the deficit which crept into the water budget lately, a deficit which needs annual bolstering in the form of loans. Whether these increased appropriations have become second nature or are merely indulged in to convince the city of the water work's capacity, is something which has not been fully ascertained as yet. Undoubtedly, if matters continue the way they are, the water department's money-raising ability will soon exceed its water-lifting efficiency. Even today the financial force is greater than the water pressure, which anyone may note by opening the kitchen faucet. This condition is a regrettable feature and, it is claimed, it can only be eliminated by installing water-meters in all buildings. The officials proclaim that the citizenry of our city <pb facs="5418474_6_0866.jpg" n="2"/>are hopeless squanderers as far as the precious liquid is concerned, and that if equitable taxation, according to use, is resorted to, a fair measure of frugality can be attained.</p>
   <p>They may he right at that. It has been claimed for many years that our Chicago uses more water than any city on God's wide, wide world. Remarkable though, that we do not notice where all the nice liquid dissappears. But this crime, - if it is one, - may be interwoven with extenuating circumstances, and thus the terrible prospect may not be quite as fearful as it originally appeared. Now, assuming one could produce statistics proving our Chicago mothers do wash their youngsters oftener than New York's, whose economy is given to us as an example, or showing that Chicago's sandy subsoil is more absorbent than the terra firma of other cities, and that, obviously, our sod needs more aqua pura, or, incidentally, that we have more lawns to beautify, - then the local sinful tendencies for more water would be forgiven.</p>
   <p>Very likely, prohibition has much to do with the unprecedented use of the <pb facs="5418474_6_0867.jpg" n="3"/>antidote for universal dryness. The human body is for the most part composed of liquid, and it requires infiltrating dampness to maintain it. Beer, wine, and whiskey have been abolished and with much conniving we enticed mortal man to mount the monstrous water wagon. He has no alternative but to share the trough with the peaceful, domesticated quadrupeds. If three million people on a torrid summer day quench their thirst with our famous (my pen slipped almost into "infamous") lake water, it is natural that the drain be noticeable at the pumping stations.</p>
   <p>It is actually phenomenal that neighboring states, bordering on Lake Michigan, have not complained years ago to the War Department that Chicagoans are gradually guzzling up the lake. As a matter of mundane justice, Chicagoans deserve commendation for their subservience to the Eighteenth Amendment instead of punishment in the form of higher taxes for water. Furthermore, the abnegation required to drink our chemically disinfected water, is almost akin to the martyrdom of legendary saints. At least every imbiber should be given a Carnegie medal for proved heroism whenever he cools his parched throat with <pb facs="5418474_6_0868.jpg" n="4"/>this beverage. If chemically purified and sanitary water tastes like our pipe line drinks, then mankind was born with a perverted taste. It is so reminiscent of - no, not chlorine, that would be bearable, - muck and rotten fish, that partaking of it ought to be included in the ordeals of hell. If Tantalus had been stationed in our water conduits, he would have had an enviable position. The elusive refreshment would at least have evaded him whenever he sought to gulp it down, and that represents a diminution of one half of his tortures. He would have lost all desire for it. Of course, during that era human appetite still had natural tendencies.</p>
   <p>Could that deplorable palatability of our water be attributed to its source, the lake, with its gradual contamination by an increasing population? Hardly. Most cities depend upon highly polluted rivers for their supply and their product is not nearly so miserable. The reason, then, must be sought in our purifying method; perhaps in the mains. Either our City's bacterial-killing process is inadequate, or the conveying fixtures need cleaning.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0869.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>That a metropolitan city like Chicago countenances this without rebellion, bespeaks of a serene, angelic patience; a splendid testimonial to its inhabitants. But there is no justification in being proud about it. Chicago pays stupendous sums for its "underground plumbing" and therefore should be entitled to obtain an unquestionable thirst quencher. It could have it if it owned a proper filtering plant.</p>
   <p>The fact that our inland sea drops taste better in some sections of the city, leads one to the obvious conclusion that the supply pipes are in bad condition, possibly choked with mud. This at least should be attended to.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
