<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-03-28">March 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">New Publications of Schurz</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0491</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0491.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-03-28">March 28, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">NEW PUBLICATIONS OF SCHURZ</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new and interesting contribution to the history of polities will be made by C. Schurz. He is writing a book entitled. Reminiscences of Public Men and Events. Those who know his book about Henry Clay and his writings about A. Lincoln, will look forward with intense expectations.</p>
   <p>The Boston Herald states in regard to Schurz, that no American author writes more excellently about history than Schurz, but they are under the erroneous impression that Schurz writes his books originally in German. Schurz thinks and writes English, and it seems strange that he expresses himself more fluently and intelligently in English than in German. His English writings are full of understanding and fire.</p>
   <p>Indeed, Schurz is master of the English language. He devoted his first years in the United States to the study of it, not being required by necessity to seek employment for his livelihood. Even Schurz' enemies in the Senate had to admit that he spoke better and more classical English than they.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0492.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The assertion of the Boston Herald that Schurz is a better writer of American history than all American authors can only have reference to his contemporaries, because Sohurz will not think himself above the great American historians, Prescott and Motley. However, there is this difference! the American-born historians wrote foreign history, but America's adopted citizen is writing American history.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
