<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-05-08">May 8, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">[The Wirtsverein]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1239</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1239.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-05-08">May 8, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">[THE WIRTSVEREIN]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Wirtsverein (Innkeepers' Association) held a meeting yesterday afternoon in Baum's Pavilion, corner Indiana and Cottage Grove Avenue, under the chairmanship of president John Feldkamp. After the minutes of the previous meeting were read and adopted and several new members admitted, the committee which was appointed to be present at the Beer Brewers' meeting, [Translator's note: See article of May 3] reported that they had not been admitted to it. It was learned, however, that the brewers were not in accord regarding the raising of beer prices. One of them had declared the first aim should be that all brewers demand and get eight dollars a barrel, which had not been the case so far, since many allowed a discount from ten to fifteen per cent.</p>
   <p>There was great indignation among the members about an article published in Inter-Ocean which stated that a barrel of beer cost the brewers themselves seven dollars. After a motion, a committee of three was appointed, consisting of Messrs. Peter Mueller, J. Miehle and C. Heiser, which was to issue a public reply</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1240.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>to this article. It was further resolved to hold meetings only every first Friday of the month, in the Hall at 7 South Clark Street.</p>
   <p>Then a letter from Kankakee, addressed to President Feldkamp, was read in which it said that the innkeepers of Kankakee County had organized; some suggestions were also made regarding the Wirts' (Innkeeper's) Convention.</p>
   <p>The justice committee reported in regard to the sale of liquors (mostly poor quality) in drugstores, the proprietors of which naturally did not have licenses; the investigations had fully justified the complaints made. Then the fact was mentioned that bottled beer was sold in some restaurants without licenses. This matter, also, was referred to the justice committee.</p>
   <p>The president was given power to call a special meeting at any time he considered it necessary. [The meeting] adjourned [shortly thereafter].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
