<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1862-02-18">Feb. 18, 1862</date>.
<title level="a">Concert for German Unionists Who Were Driven Out of Missouri</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0667</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0667.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1862-02-18">Feb. 18, 1862</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERT FOR GERMAN UNIONISTS WHO WERE DRIVEN OUT OF MISSOURI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Freie Saengerbund (Liberty Chorus) has the honor of being the first organization to act in behalf of our countrymen who were driven out of Missouri. Last Thursday's issue of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung brought the news that four German families who are true to the Union had arrived in Chicago after having been expelled from Missouri, and hardly had we requested the local German societies to devise ways and means of providing for these unfortunate people--martyrs to the cause of liberty and the Union--when the Saengerbund took steps to arrange for a concert, the proceeds of which were to be devoted to the support of these refugees from Missouri.</p>
   <p>Hans Balatka, director of music, all members of the Light Guard Band, and the orchestra of McVickers Theatre, immediately offered to help the Saengerbund; the Board of Management of the German House furnished the hall gratis, the German newspapers donated the necessary advertising space, the German brewers and <pb facs="5418474_6_0668.jpg" n="2"/>and wine merchants sent beer and wine, and German grocers contributed coffee, sugar, and milk.</p>
   <p>The brewers mentioned were Lill and Diversey, John Huck, Schott and Metz, Busch and Brand, Ludwick and Martin, Seip and Lehmann, Mueller Brothers, and Siebert and Schmidt. Wine merchants who contributed were: Baer, Koeffler, Suess, and Kronfuss. Grocers named were: Arnold Breuer and the Kirchhoff Brothers. Milkman: Schaub.</p>
   <p>While Mrs. Puetz, Mrs. Adolf Mueller, and Miss Therese Diehl served coffee and refreshments, the well-known host, his brother, the former mayor of Guttenberg, Mr. Georg Diehl, and Mr. John Mayer were kept busy at the bar.</p>
   <p>Although there was very little time to make and carry out arrangements, and though the weather invited outdoor activity, the Hall was filled to capacity by the elite of our German citizens. It was a great satisfaction for those present to note that the first call to aid oppressed citizens was answered both <pb facs="5418474_6_0669.jpg" n="3"/>by those who were willing to give of their art and their talents, and by those who had their pocketbooks wide open.</p>
   <p>The success was unexpected under prevailing conditions. A total of $119.54 was given to the families who were driven out of Missouri.</p>
   <p>It is reported that other organizations are now making arrangements to outdo the Saengerbund. We say: Full steam ahead!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
