<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-22">Apr. 22, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Intrusive Words.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0884</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0884.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-22">Apr. 22, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">INTRUSIVE WORDS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Physical exercises are an excellent preventive, of spinal curvature.</p>
   <p>A splendid article on this subject, written by Mr. Heinrich Suder, physical director of public schools here, appeared in the April issue of a magazine published by the Turner Society Harmony. The wording of the article reads as follows:</p>
   <p>A thorough examination of each pupil in regard to posture would disclose an amazing large percentage of spinal curvature. For instance, among pupils of advanced classes, from fifth grade upward, one third or even more are victims of spinal curvature. In an interview, granted me by a principal of a school, she volunteered the information that according to the advice of the physicians <pb facs="5418474_6_0885.jpg" n="2"/>who have conducted the examinations, sclerosis has already developed in fifty per cent of children of the lower grades.</p>
   <p>If this statement is correct, it definitely shows that the weakened condition of the spine was already present when the child became of school age. It is a condition which cannot be cured by sitting in school rooms. Before school days, a healthy child enjoys out-of-door activities. On entering school, he is compelled to spend several hours each day in close school rooms, with only ten-minute relaxation periods in the forenoon and in the afternoon. However, the introduction of physical exercises in the lower grades of public schools signifies progress in the school system, and according to indications, the physical welfare of our children will still further improve as time goes on. The first signs of bad posture of a child are drooping head, flat chest, and drawn up shoulders. Warnings of good posture follow then. The child straightens, only to fall back into an indolent posture as soon as it feels free <pb facs="5418474_6_0886.jpg" n="3"/>to cater to its own inclinations. The child is then forced to accept the agony of posture braces, although this is not the proper procedure in correcting this condition. Nothing but physical exercises taken regularly would prove a successful corrective. However, curvature of the spine is a hereditary disease, a fact which must not be disregarded. Nevertheless, the most frequent cause is an indolent posture while at work in school. There is also another type of curvature, in which the spinal column is twisted to one side, but which is not easily detected either by parents or by teachers. This type is caused in early infancy. Mothers and nursed are unaware of the fact that they are the responsible parties causing this condition, since they do not alternate the use of the arm upon which the infant rests.</p>
   <p>Another great mistake is to encourage early walking. If the infant does not show any tendency to walk, it signifies that the muscular structure is not strong enough to balance the body. Every child's ambition is to walk, and <pb facs="5418474_6_0887.jpg" n="4"/>it will, without coaxing, in due time. Muscle-building exercises are of course imperative, and it must be accomplished before the child becomes of school age, since a child's spinal column is exceedingly flexible up to then. The so-called school disease commences with school age, denoting itself by a lop-sided posture.</p>
   <p>In most instances, however, the corrective prescription by physicians would call for physical exercise, except in complicated cases under the direction of an experienced gymnastic teacher. Athletic instruction in public schools promotes good posture, and is also an excellent muscle builder, especially under the direction of an experienced instructor. But, I repeat, that time allotted to physical culture in public schools is absolutely insufficient to prevent or cure spinal curvature.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
