<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-02-11">Feb. 11, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to German and German-American Women</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0773</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0773.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title><date when="1892-02-11">Feb. 11, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO GERMAN AND GERMAN-AMERICAN WOMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All readers of the Staats - Zeitung who are interested in higher education for women and who desire to contribute something towards its promotion, are requested to join the recently organized association. This organization is a branch of the "Universal German Teachers Association" under the leadership of one of the most prominent women in Germany, Miss H. Lange, Berlin. It is trying to shape public opinion in Germany in favor of higher education for women, to erect colleges for girls, and to secure permission from the government to permit women to attend the universities.</p>
   <p>The members of the American section of the Universal Association of German Teachers hope to be in a position to assist German women morally as well as financially and to serve the best interests of their German-American sisters. Hundreds of American women have addeep desire to attend Germany's great universities but only the victory of the women in Germany will make it possible.</p>
   <p>To join the American section of this association involves no further responsibility than the payment of annual fee of seventy-five cents. Every woman teacher may become a regular member, and every woman interested in higher education for her sex may become a special member. Requirements are alike for both.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
