<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-08-04">Aug. 4, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Unwelcome Aid</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0824</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0824.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-08-04">Aug. 4, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">UNWELCOME AID</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The distress of the American farmer, which was greatly aggravated this summer by the drought and insect plague, is so well known that it is not disputed by anyone who is at all acquainted with existing conditions.</p>
   <p>It is just as indisputable that the Federal Administration has, in the current year, done everything in its power to alleviate the suffering of the rural population. It has already spent many millions for this purpose, and more millions will follow. Those farmers who suffered from the dreadful drought have received generous assistance, and they will continue to receive it. Henry A. Wallace, Secretary of Agriculture, declared only recently that the Agricultural Administration will buy from four to seven million cows from such farmers as would otherwise lose their cattle because of the drought; and <pb facs="5418474_6_0825.jpg" n="2"/>the same holds true for the other livestock which could not survive the winter for lack of fodder and water. These measures of assistance are fully appreciated by the farmers in general, even if, among the more radical farm organizations, expressions of discontent can be heard at what has been done for agriculture. Still, the criticism does not seem entirely unjustified. If we consider, that, of the $130,000,000 which should have been paid last January to the farmers who limited their cultivated land and reduced their livestock in accordance with the wishes of the Agricultural Administration, only about $14,000,000 has been paid so far, we must admit that there are good grounds for dissatisfaction. Therefore, one cannot take it amiss if it is as ked how long it will be before the total amount appropriated for this purpose is paid out.</p>
   <p>The Government's plan for enabling hard-pressed small farmers to move into better areas met with unexpectedly sharp criticism and even direct opposition. From South Dakota comes the report that the farmers there whom this measure <pb facs="5418474_6_0826.jpg" n="3"/>was especially intended to assist, are fighting with all their might against having to abandon their farms and move to other states. The governor of this state has therefore found it necessary to devise ways and means for creating new settlements for the distressed farmers within the borders of the state. At the same time, he intends to ask the Federal Agricultural Administration to support this plan, because all other resettlement plans meet with insurmountable resistance.</p>
   <p>Taken as a whole, this resistance is not surprising. The farmer clings, with every fibre of his being, to the soil which has been a home to him and his family, even if it has supported them only meagerly. The Agricultural Administration will do well if it takes into consideration the farmer's attachment to the soil, with which he has inseparable ties; and does not insist upon the carrying out of plans for relief which are not desired, even if they are well meant.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
