<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-04-28">Apr. 28, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Benefit Concert for Rosenbecker</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1712</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1712.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-04-28">Apr. 28, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">BENEFIT CONCERT FOR ROSENBECKER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A large, select audience attended yesterday's benefit concert for Professor Rosenbecker of the Chicago orchestra, at the Northside Turnhalle. Much was promised for the occasion, and it is gratifying to report that all pledges were fulfilled. A pretentious program was announced, a credit to the audience as well as the musicians; to the latter, because the selections given required solving of considerable difficulties and, in so far as the public is concerned, a proper understanding of the offerings necessitated considerable knowledge of music. The presentation was exemplary, and the beneficiary in particular deserves praise for the extensive rehearsals given under his direction, and for the many new numbers which, due to his efforts, were presented in such a highly satisfying manner.</p>
   <p>Of course, one might criticize considerably in so far as Mr. Rosenbecker's conception of several passages is concerned, but one must recognize his <pb facs="5418474_6_1713.jpg" n="2"/>courage in presenting his own interpretations, which elicited admiration even from those who did not favor the orchestra leader's rendition.</p>
   <p>For the opening number, the Overture to the "Flying Dutchman", one of Richard Wagner's earlier works, was selected. The composition is almost equal to the "Tannhaeuser" Overture.....</p>
   <p>The conductor and musicians cooperated exceptionally well, and the performance therefore was one of the best presentations ever given by a Chicago orchestra.</p>
   <p>After the Overture, "Rondo with Variations", by Wieniawski, was offered, and Mr. Lewis played the violin part in the true manner of a virtuoso. As an encore, the artist selected a Mazurka by Chopin. Both numbers have been played here by Wilhelm and Remenyi,thus a comparison of these masters with Mr. Lewis is therefore quite possible. As far as technique is concerned, Mr. Lewis, <pb facs="5418474_6_1714.jpg" n="3"/>of local fame, need not feel any apprehensions, but his tone lacks the loftiness--that dignity of expression and unerring pitch--which Wilhelmy attains on his magic instrument.</p>
   <p>The next number was the "Andante" from Haydn's "Kaiser Quartet". The entire orchestra's group of violinists and cellists, sixteen members, played the composition in a very acceptable manner. Evenness of tone and gradation may have been lacking at times, but these shortcomings were insufficient to detract seriously from the general impression created by the rendition.</p>
   <p>After a short intermission, the Overture to the "Roman Carnival", by Berlioz, was given--an entirely new number to Chicago. In this composition the genial Frenchman gives proof of his mastery in instrumentation as well as rythm, providing thereby a true characterization of the jovial carnival spirit of Rome....Under Mr. Rosenbecker's leadership, the orchestra played the effective <pb facs="5418474_6_1715.jpg" n="4"/>overture in an excellent manner, as was shown by the highly attentive and animated attitude of the audience. The orchestra, in this instance, deserves especial recognition; there are few compositions requiring greater attention on the part of the conductor and the individual musicians than this work.</p>
   <p>Beethoven's classic simplicity, as exemplified in the Adagio movement of the "Prometheus Ballet," gave a fitting contrast to the previous number, proving especially interesting, because the daring construction of the French composer's work is actually a development of the musical perceptions which animated the gigantic Beethoven in his characterization of the mythological Prometheus. In the excellent presentation of that even, splendid Adagio, Mr. Eichheim deserves particular commendation; he played the cello part in a manner fully befitting the serenity of the melody.</p>
   <p>Then followed Wagner's colorful "Walkueren-Ritt." The orchestra lacked power <pb facs="5418474_6_1716.jpg" n="5"/>to do justice to this titanic tone-picture, but maybe it was fortunate that volume was not available; it might have proved catastrophic if the Walkuren-Ritt had been played with genuine Wagnerian intensity. Jarring, not to say hair-raising, are the attributes one must resort to in describing the harmonies--if a succession of dissonances can be called that--which Wagner applies in this instance. But regardless, one may perceive beauties therein, after listening to it often enough, so that one may feel inclined to do homage to the great Wagner eventually, only the good Lord created but few humans with sufficiently resistant ears and adequate nerves to listen to Wagner's music often enough to understand this Babylonian tonal confusion.</p>
   <p>The closing number of the highly successful concert--or, impressive up to this point--was Beethoven's so-called "Battle Symphony". Were it not definitely established as a creation of Beethoven, it would have been forgotten long ago, but it shows that even a great man can produce inferior work. The orchestra tried its utmost to save the composer's reputation, and the only <pb facs="5418474_6_1717.jpg" n="6"/>reproach one can express involves the mistake in having made such an unfortunate selection in an otherwise excellent concert.</p>
   <p>A ball was given after the concert.....The proceeds of the benefit concert were fairly large, and the recipient donated the entire amount to the library fund of the orchestra. The results, due to this gift, will become apparent next Winter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
