<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-09-07">Sept. 7, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">One Hundred and Fifty Years Ago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0409</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0409.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-09-07">Sept. 7, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">ONE HUNDRED AND FIFTY YEARS AGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A century and a half have gone by since the treaty was signed in Paris which marked the end of the American Revolution, officially recognizing the surrender of Cornwallis at Yorktown which had taken place two years before. The wearisome negotiations, which had lasted for months and had been conducted by Benjamin Franklin, John Adams, and John Jay on behalf of the American colonists, came to a successful close. The colonies received certain fixed boundaries and became at last free and independent.</p>
   <p>Vincennes, in the State of Indiana, was destined to memorize [the anniversary of] this event in a special manner, whereas in the other parts of the country it remained without very much notice and in most cases went by without leaving any trace in the memory of the people. A new bridge across the Wabash River near Vincennes marks the spot at which George Rogers Clark with his hand <pb facs="5418474_6_0410.jpg" n="2"/>of half-starved volunteers traversed the river. The foundation stone of the new bridge preserves documentary evidence of the exploits of this brave leader of the Revolution in the valley of the great Mississippi.</p>
   <p>It was on September 3, 1783, that the treaty was signed, actually marking the birthday of that half of the Middle West which lies east of the Mississippi. The treaty of Paris brought the entire Northwest Territory of those days under the Stars and Stripes. Later, preliminary arrangements were completed for the states of Illinois, Indiana. Wisconsin, Michigan, and Ohio, and they were included in the North American Federation of States.</p>
   <p>That the heads of the States of Illinois and Indiana lent by their personal participation an official aspect to the memorial festival of Vincennes will bring nothing but honor to the two States which they represent.</p>
   <p>A hundred and fifty years are in the history of mankind only a small space of time. Yet it seems that we of today live in an age that rushes on so fast <pb facs="5418474_6_0411.jpg" n="3"/>or is so much wrapped up in itself that we remember only superficially historic events of such monumental importance as the signing of the Treaty of Paris.</p>
   <p>There are certain elements which are eager to keep the American people in the dark with respect to their own history and would like to make them forget the hardships and the oppressions which cost their ancestors much wealth and blood. It should therefore be the aim of our so-called patriotic organizations to take care that the American people shall always be cognizant of the struggles of their forefathers who prepared the ground for their liberties to come. Besides, to call attention repeatedly to their patriotism and their sacrifices for the independence of the Union is the more proper because there are many dangers that threaten us still and are essentially worse than what had to be overcome by the contemporaries of the American Revolution.</p>
   <p>They are worse because they threaten not so much from without as from within.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0412.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This threat comes from elements that are the more dangerous because they operate under the cover of patriotism. They know so well how to camouflage their real aims that the principles laid down by our forefathers in the Constitution of the country are pushed into the background without any opposition. In this manner these principles become like dead letters, deprived of their dignity by wanton mischief.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
