<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-28">Apr. 28, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">Richard Wagner</title><title level="a" type="sub">Guest Performance of the German Grand Opera</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1648</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1648.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-28">Apr. 28, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">RICHARD WAGNER</title><title level="a" type="sub">Guest Performance of the German Grand Opera</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Grand Opera Company has been appearing in the Chicago Opera House for the last eight days. The cast is composed of such well-known artists as the following: E. Fischer, Madlinger, Alvary, Mrs. Kelisch-Lehmann, Miss Straubman, and a score of others.</p>
   <p>The performances have been confined exclusively to the compositions of Wagner. Society has been certainly right in calling this event a really big one. One does not have to be a Wagnerian in order to pay tribute to that genial composer. Wagner has gained immortal merits in the sphere of operatic music.</p>
   <p>Regarding operas, up to the present time the mistake has always been made that the music was degraded to the purpose and the drama itself to the medium.</p>
   <p>Wagner reformed all this, and elevated music again to the language of the soul by his careful selection of poetic material. Out of all this, music was <pb facs="5418474_6_1649.jpg" n="2"/>supplanted by shallow composers.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, he discovered that all scenic effects must be existing in, and conditional upon the opera, and that the formal rounding of fractions of music should only be achieved by dramatic connections.</p>
   <p>In this way, and by stressing the importance of the orchestra, he provided a dignified position for opera.</p>
   <p>Wagner's stage creations display a highly artistic seriousness. His compositions possess musical character. The melodies in Lohengrin, Tannhauser, Rienzi, etc., have all the qualities to please and charm the people, although objections are being raised by anti-Wagnerians, that his music, for the greater part, can only be understood by musicians.</p>
   <p>Even Wagner himself is not entirely free from one-sided and eccentric ideas. But his fame as a composer might scarcely become clouded by that.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1650.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is the task of theatre and concert managements to make Wagner's music attainable to the widest circles, and in this way refine and cultivate the taste of the public.</p>
   <p>It is regrettable that the directors of the Chicago Opera House have forgotten this consideration completely. The price of admission is so expensive that it is impossible for any worker to obtain a true enjoyment of art without great sacrifices. </p>
   <p>Seats in the last row of the back gallery cost fifty cents; better ones cost from $1.00 to $1.50.</p>
   <p>These prices are, of course, too high for working people, because the fathers of many families only earn about $8.00 a week.</p>
   <p>Socialism has learned to appreciate the wholesome and beneficial influence of true art, and it demands the same chance for all people to enjoy art and science.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1651.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Whether this is always the case with capitalists is a question we will have to leave unanswered.</p>
   <p>In some cases music has become a fashionable disease and many persons have become affected by the genial Richard Wagner.</p>
   <p>Our admiration of the great and ideal of Wagner's music has nothing in common with this Wagner disease.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
