<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-07-31">July 31, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Lamentable Postponement</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0067</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0067.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-07-31">July 31, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LAMENTABLE POSTPONEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Judicious citizens, no doubt, regret the unfavorable attitude displayed by members of the City Council, whereby the installation of water meters was postponed. It appears quite natural that the cost of water supply should be plausibly borne by the consumer, according to his use. It is the only just distribution of the expense arising from that source. Persons in-favorably disposed toward the installation of the water meter must have a very good reason. However, it is not fair that a citizen whose water supply need is considerably smaller than his fellow-citizen's must permanently assume the partial burden for the consumer of large quantities of water.</p>
   <p>Many housekeepers, not extravagant in their use of water, will probably benefit by the water meter, since their water bills will be decidedly lower. Whosoever is opposed to the installation of water meters arouses suspicion as to his squandering of water.....Chicagoans consume a great deal more water--according to statistics--than any other city.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0068.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Chicagoans may be much cleaner than other people if judged by the consumption of water, but even then the consumption by our communities is still considered abnormally large. Our excessive use of water points to the probability that more water is being wasted by leaking pipes and faucets of our water supply system rather than by the excessive use. Despite the fact that garden sprinkling reaches its height in summer, and that some people have no scruples when operating sprinklers all day long, a system which was also adopted by the Park administration. If every transgressor had to pay for water thus squandered, many such sinners would give up their extravagancy in the interest of their own pocketbooks. Those who do not waste water have nothing to worry about in regard to water meters, on the contrary, they ought to insist upon installation of the same. It would be their only assurance against excessive water bills, and furthermore, the water bill of extravagant consumers would equal their use.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
