<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-08-28">Aug. 28, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Johann H. Muehlke</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1273</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1273.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-08-28">Aug. 28, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">JOHANN H. MUEHLKE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the demise of Johann Heinrich Muehlke, Chicago loses one of its oldest and most active Germans. He was born in Sachsenhagen, in Kurhessen, November 23, 1826. He emigrated to America in 1842, when he was only sixteen years old and, after working as clerk in various stores, first at Hamlin, Day and Company, a concern which sold just about everything needed by people living in small towns at that time, and later at H. W. Bigelow and Company's dry goods store, 151 Lake Street, he eventually became a partner of the latter firm, which thereafter was known as Bigelow, Muehlke and Company. He was highly successful and continued in that capacity until about 1865, when he dissolved the partnership and dealt in real estate exclusively, a move inspired by his own large land holdings, and also at the behest of Mr. Uhlich, who wanted Mr. Muehlke to manage his [Uhlich's] extensive properties. Muehlke's efforts proved so satisfactory that Uhlich bequeathed a considerable portion of his estate to Muehlke. Shortly before the Fire, Muehlke was considered one of the wealthiest Chicagoans. The Great Fire <pb facs="5418474_6_1274.jpg" n="2"/>and the panic of 1873 resulted in a general drop in real-estate values, and played havoc with Muehlke's land holdings, but he managed to pull through. During the last two years he was confined to his bed, but he left a fairsized fortune to his family nevertheless.</p>
   <p>The deceased was a member of Hartmann's parish, and was its secretary for twenty-five years. He took an active interest in Uhlich's Orphanage and was president of that institution; he was also connected with the Wittwen Und Waisen-Verein [a Society organized for the protection of widows and orphans] of St. Paul's parish, as well as with its Sunday school, over which he presided for twenty-three years.</p>
   <p>Mr. Muehlke is survived by his wife, Venna Katherine, nee Knust; eight children, Mrs. Louise M. Tiedemann, Mrs. Anna Henrici, Henry C. Muehlke, who holds an important position at J. V. Farwell and Company; G. F. Muehlke, who was in charge of the real-estate business during the protracted illness of his father; Joseph H. Muehlke, now a student at the university, and three <pb facs="5418474_6_1275.jpg" n="3"/>younger children.</p>
   <p>The funeral will be held this afternoon at the home of the deceased, 307 North State Street, from where the procession will proceed to Hartmann's church, and then to Graceland Cemetery.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
