<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-17">June 17, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Eight Hours</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0258</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0258.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-17">June 17, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">EIGHT HOURS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In its last session, the State legislature passed the following laws in the interest of labor: a [law establishing a] bureau of labor statistics; a law requiring subtraction from the funds of bankrupt firms to cover all wage claims prior to the payment of other bills; a law protecting wages up to fifty dollars against garnishee proceedings; a mine law protecting miners against accidents so far as possible; and several other bills affecting the welfare of workers. Several more bills would have been passed, if they had been practical. The lawmakers certainly showed no trace of bourgeois inclinations so far as labor laws were concerned. Only so much is required by our representatives: the proposals must show a measure of fairness and give evidence of being feasible. If these qualities are lacking, the legislature proceeds with the other agenda.</p>
   <p>A bill has been presented to limit a day's work in all industries to eight hours. Now what can the State assembly or the national Congress do with such <pb facs="5418474_6_0259.jpg" n="2"/>a request? It can pass a law (the national Congress passed such a measure years ago) that whenever work is being performed for the Government, a day's labor shall not exceed eight hours; but when this example is not emulated by other employers, what can the Government do about it? Shall compulsion be used to prevent any laborers from working more than eight hours when the men are willing to work longer? Shall employers be punished if they permit their employees to work longer than eight hours because the workers desire to do so? Shall a law specify that henceforth, after a given day, the wages now paid for ten hours' labor shall be paid to laborers who work only eight hours?</p>
   <p>In order to pass such a statute, the Government must also have the authority to regulate prices, but it has no such powers. Even a person of very limited intelligence knows that the sales price of a finished article depends upon the amount paid for labor, because labor has produced part of the value of the product; in fact, in many cases the cost of labor is the chief item.</p>
   <p>Suppose that it requires seventy-five cents' worth of labor to convert two pounds <pb facs="5418474_6_0260.jpg" n="3"/>of cotton, worth twenty cents, into a certain amount of cloth which the manufacturer sells for a dollar, thus giving a profit of five cents. Under these circumstances it is obvious that the manufacturer cannot pay eighty-five or ninety cents for the labor without also raising the price of the product. He could not exist if he were to sell his goods at the same price as formerly. He would prefer to close his place to continuing under such conditions.</p>
   <p>Of course, if all manufacturers throughout the land were compelled to pay as much for eight hours' work as they had formerly paid for ten hours' work, then there would at least be a corresponding increase in the price of all goods manufactured. The question arises then whether such a condition would not enable foreign manufacturers to compete successfully with us, in which case our workingmen would be left unemployed. So the latter would not benefit much, since they would have an eight-hour day but no jobs.</p>
   <p>But let us be momentarily concerned only with ourselves and assume that foreign competition need not be feared. What then is to be done if the industries in a <pb facs="5418474_6_0261.jpg" n="4"/>city or a State cannot profitably sell their merchandise because labor costs are a fourth or a fifth higher than they are in other cities? Fair words and bulldozing do not help. If a manufacturer outside Chicago sells his products for a dollar and makes a profit of five cents, while a manufacturer in the city loses five or ten cents on the same merchandise, then the latter must quit, for he cannot insist that the buyers throughout the country shall pay $1.15 instead of a dollar.</p>
   <p>Let it be remembered, however, that we do not object to the assertion that a factory worker should earn just as much in eight hours as in ten hours, regardless of whether he, as the world-reformers assure us, uses the extra two hours for recreation or for mental or moral improvement. The decrease in labor hours is a gain in itself as long as one regards labor as a task instead of a diversion, and after all, no one works longer than he has to.</p>
   <p>However, the desire to work eight hours instead of ten is quite a different proposition from being able to earn as much in eight hours as in ten hours.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0262.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>If that can be attained without complete destruction of the public welfare, well and good! And if it cannot be realized without harm, then one must be satisfied with the thought that the goal will be reached in the same way in which the European ten-hour law displaced the eleven, twelve, and fourteen-hour working periods of a generation ago; the transition was gradual. And so the eight-hour working day will be introduced here; it will come naturally, slowly--through an increased demand for goods which, in turn, will justify higher wages. This is the gist of the whole matter:labor in itself has no standard value, regardless of the question whether the products of labor are usable or not; in the final analysis the price for labor depends on the price for which goods can be sold, in other words, on the amount which customers are willing to pay.</p>
   <p>This principle holds true whether workers are their own employers, working cooperatively, or whether they are employed by a boss, a despicable capitalist who pays day wages.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
