<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-04-26">Apr. 26, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">A. Kraushaar's Clasp Improvement</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1867-04-26">Apr. 26, 1867</date>.
<title level="a">A. KRAUSHAAR'S CLASP IMPROVEMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Everyone who is familiar with the history of piano manufacturing knows that more than fifty years the European manufacturers introduced the clasp as an improvement upon the generally used bridge. The clasp supports the string just opposite the stroke of the hammer, while the bridge pin supports the string from the side only. Thus the use of the bridge pin made it impossible to obtain the required rigidity and stability for clearness and fullness of musical tone. Only a few local manufacturers have introduced the clasp. One of them claims he applied the device in 1836; another says he attached it to the iron-framed piano, while another claims he used it in connection with the strings of a violin. It cannot be denied that the introduction of the iron frame has greatly improved the modern piano; but the system, now in vogue, of placing the entire weight upon the iron frame by attaching the clasps to the iron frame with screws is advantageous only to a certain extent. It will be readily understood that the iron frame, though it makes for stability, hampers the production of clear musical tones. Only wood can develop and support the <pb facs="5418474_6_1461.jpg" n="2"/>vibrations of the strings, as experience teaches, and why should we not benefit by what sound reason has taught us for many years? The solution of the problem was to attach the clasps in such a way that contact with iron was avoided. This problem has not been solved.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kraushaar, of Kraushaar and Company, 19 North Huston Street, has done everything that can be done in this respect. He has devised a new system of attaching the clasps, and his system avoids the above mentioned faults. By his system the vibration of the strings is supported and reinforced. All tones are full, clear, and pleasing to the sensitive musical ear, and we do not doubt that the benefits of the excellent instrument which Kraushaar and Company have made during the time they have been in business in Chicago will gain for them a host of new admirers and satisfied customers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
