<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-01-24">Jan. 24, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Lobbies</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0405</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0405.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-01-24">Jan. 24, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">LOBBIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Roosevelt has started a crusade against lobbyists. He is so incensed by their activity that he threatens to recommend that Congress pass a law providing jail terms for lobbyists. Lobbies have always been considered to be an evil; several Presidents have fought them, and President Wilson once threatened to have all lobbyists arrested. However, all efforts to do away with lobbies have been in vain. Therefore, there appears to be some justification for the suspicion that there are good reasons for the existence of this institution.</p>
   <p>There are two kinds of lobbies, and they differ according to their nature. The one tries to influence legislation, the other serves as a sort of mediator between authorities. Both kinds deserve the reputation of being unscrupulous in choosing their means and of frequently corrupting politics. Despite this fact, <pb facs="5418474_6_0406.jpg" n="2"/>one cannot deny that they have a right to exist. In Congress and in state legislatures, one can find representatives of large business groups who have the duty of observing the plans of the respective legislative bodies.</p>
   <p>Since it is customary in our country to manufacture laws in wholesale numbers, one or the other of these business or professional groups is always threatened with harm by some law. The whole nation is constantly in a condition of self defense, as soon as Congress convenes; the same is true of state legislatures. And the lobbies do not always do their work from behind the scenes. They often openly take a stand on bills, and frequently express their opinions in public hearings which are held by various committees.</p>
   <p>Although this kind of lobby does not always tread the paths of virtue and justices one cannot deny that it has a right to exist. It is a necessary evil, created by American methods of legislation.</p>
   <p>The other lobbies consist of people who play the role of mediators between <pb facs="5418474_6_0407.jpg" n="3"/>various authorities. They have connections, and they demand large fees for their services. It is not difficult to explain why people who have business with federal authorities prefer not to deal with them directly.</p>
   <p>No doubt, the impression prevails in our whole country that one cannot achieve anything in Washington, unless one has connections. If one has not, then one is condemned to dance attendance on subalterns, is sent from Pontius to Pilate (sic), and achieves nothing. Decades ago, Mark Twain wrote a bitter satire on the bureaucracy prevailing in Washington--the story of the "Great Beef Contract". Meanwhile, conditions have grown much worse, for since Twain's time the number of bureaucrats at the capitol has greatly increased.</p>
   <p>Thus it appears that the lobbies can best be fought by making them superfluous. If the authorities would willingly meet citizens, give them the opportunity to state their business clearly and briefly, nobody would think of trying to reach and influence them through professional mediators, who, of course, will not act unless they are well paid. In the final analysis, the methods and practices <pb facs="5418474_6_0408.jpg" n="4"/>of our national officials are responsible for the existence of lobbies. Even jail terms will not be effective against them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
