<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-01-28">Jan. 28, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Atlantic Hotel Celebrates its 25Th Anniversary.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1102</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1102.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-01-28">Jan. 28, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">ATLANTIC HOTEL CELEBRATES ITS 25TH ANNIVERSARY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Memories of old times will rise again, when today, in the midst of old friends and guests, Messrs. Carl Roessler and Max Teich will celebrate the 25th anniversary of the Hotel Atlantic's foundation. Twenty-five years is a long time in a city that is less than a hundred years old.</p>
   <p>The hotel is the life work of two ambitious Germans, who, from small beginnings, built up their hotel in the course of a quarter of a century. With the rapid growth of the city, the hotel grew too, from the first first fireproof building, erected at the time of the World's Fair, to a 20 story skyscraper, which even today dominates South Clark Street.</p>
   <p>Known as "Kaiserhof" since its foundation, 25 years ago, up to the time when war broke out between the United States and Germany, the hotel, now known as the Atlantic, has always been a retreat for the city's Germans; a hospitable place which victoriously survived the storms of the war and postwar times, as well as the days of prohibition.</p>
   <p>Many undertakings in behalf of the German-Americans originated in the Atlantic <pb facs="5418474_6_1103.jpg" n="2"/>hotel, and large is the number of those, who found there a second home and pleasant friends. Without doubt, there is scarcely anybody in Chicago who would not wish the enterprise and its proprietors, on the occasion of the silver jubilee, a long and successful continuance.</p>
   <p>Max Teich began his activity as a bookkeeper in the old Hotel Bismarck, in the year 1893, at the time of the great World's Fair. One year later Carl Roessler came to Chicago to accept the position of head waiter in the same hotel. After years of tireless attention to duty, the two men started independently in business, in 1903.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
