<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-04-19">Apr. 19, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Germania-Insurance William Vocke</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1306</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1306.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-04-19">Apr. 19, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMANIA-INSURANCE William Vocke</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The publicity given a few months ago to the affairs of the dead Germania Fire-Insurance Company has had the effect of stirring up some of the creditors, and as a result the following notice was served yesterday on Mr. Vocke, the former Assigner:</p>
   <p>William Vocke, Esq., Assignee in Bankruptcy of the Germania Insurance Company.</p>
   <p>Take notice that we shall, on tomorrow morning, April 19, A. D. 1879, at 10 A.M. or as soon thereafter as counsel can be heard before his Honor Judge Henry W. Bledgett, Judge of the United States District Court for the Northern District of Illinois, move the Court to set aside the order heretofore entered by the Judge, ordering your discharge as Assignee in Bankruptcy of the said Germania Insurance Company, and for a rule on you for a further accounting as Assignee of the amount of money and assets which came to your hands as Assignee, and to show cause why you should not pay into the Court, for the use and benefit of the creditors of the said Insurance Company, the amount of money which may be found due the creditors, the said creditors claiming that you have not accounted for all the moneys that came into your hands as such <pb facs="5418474_6_1307.jpg" n="2"/>Assignee, at which time and place you may appear to see fit.</p>
   <p>Attorney for petitioning creditors,</p>
   <p>John Van Arman</p>
   <p>Elliot Anthony</p>
   <p>Mr. Vocke accepts service, and the matter will doubtless come up this morning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
