<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-16">Dec. 16, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Great Concert in the Auditorium</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1500</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1500.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-16">Dec. 16, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">GREAT CONCERT IN THE AUDITORIUM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The old Auditorium, which has played a prominent role in Chicago's musical history, was awakened last Wednesday from its slumbers. To relieve the sufferings of unemployed musicians, the Chicago Bohemians [a society], aided by some prominent representatives of the musical world and of Chicago society, made arrangements for a concert in the newly decorated Auditorium. The Chicago Symphony Orchestra, the Chicago Women's Orchestra, members of the orchestra of the erstwhile Civic Opera, and members of the Chicago businessmen's Orchestra under their director, Frederick Stock, all offered their services for the good cause. The concert was opened with the beautiful prelude to "Die Meistersinger". The orchestra, considerably strengthened as it was, produced a powerful effect. The solemn mood thus introduced lasted during the entire concert. Mr. Stock remarked afterwards that the program was so complete that it would have been more than sufficient for two concerts. Three prominent soloists, the highly dramatic Miss Else Alsen, the baritone, Mr. Charles Thomas, and the celebrated pianist, Joseph Hofmann, offered their services in a most heartening manner. With <pb facs="5418474_6_1501.jpg" n="2"/>their highly artistic performances, they came a long way to give us their rich gifts.</p>
   <p>Miss Alsen sang "Dich Teure Halle Gruess' Ich Wieder" from "Tannhaeuser," and the "Liebestod" from "Tristan und Isolde," putting into it her artistic expression and feeling. She also sang the "Ho-jo-to-ho" call from "Die Walkuere," in which she particularly excelled. Mr. Thomas put on a fascinating act with his beautiful and noble baritone voice. He sang "Bison Fugitive" from Massenet's opera, "Herodiade," and the overture to "Pagliacci". For an encore he selected an aria from Massenet's opera, "Le Roi de Lahore," and an Italian number which, we regret to say, did not fit into the artistic frame of the concert. In accordance with the schedule, we were supposed to be given German, French, Italian, Russian, and Hungarian compositions, and so an English song would have been quite welcome in place of the Italian street-organ song.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hofmann, the master pianist, played Rubinstein's "Concerto No. 4 in D-Minor". As a student of Rubinstein, Mr. Hofmann never fails to play this number at <pb facs="5418474_6_1502.jpg" n="3"/>special musical festivals, because it is so brimful of technical difficulties. It is a known fact that in accomplishments of technique and rendition no one can be put on a level with him. In spite of thunderous applause, the public could not force him to render an encore, and so the immense impression of his accomplishment remained unmarred. As if by command, the musicians and the public rose from their seats, thus honoring the titan of the piano.</p>
   <p>Beside the prelude to "Die Meistersinger," the following orchestrations were added: Scherzo and Romanza by Dohnanyi "Liebestraum" by Liszt-Stock, "Adagio Pathetique" by Godard, the "Walkuerenritt" by Wagner, and the "1812 Overture" by Tchaikovsky. All of these numbers were duly applauded. Imposing and overwhelming was the effect produced by the "Walkuerenritt".</p>
   <p>Mr. Rudolph Ganz, president of the Bohemians, gave a terse speech in which he thanked all participants for their readiness to serve the good cause, and also those who helped to assure the concert's financial success. The next speaker was Mr. Hammill, who pleaded in the name of the newly founded society, Chicago's <pb facs="5418474_6_1503.jpg" n="4"/>Friends of Music, for financial backing for a music building in the coming exposition. Mr. Stock went one step further than the speaker preceding him by voicing the intention to make the music pavilion a permanent institution for music festivals, popular concerts, etc., during the summer months. But he would like to have the sum of a dollar annually for five years from every one of the one hundred thousand Chicagoans. Let us hope that Mr. Stock will meet with more success than Mr. Stalin and his Five-Year Plan.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
