<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1905-07-03">July 3, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the German Teachers. Dr. Fick, President.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0977</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0977.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1905-07-03">July 3, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting of the German Teachers. Dr. Fick, President.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The last meeting of the German teachers convention took place, this morning, in the Fine Arts Building, S.Michigan Ave., where the Chicago University rented the 7th floor and gave the use of a large room, with several smaller ones. It was opened by the Federal President, B. Abrams. The first speech was: "The Position of the German Language in the General Elementary Schools" and was given by Seminary Director Max Griebsch of Milwaukee. After a short historical development of the German educational institutions, the speaker compared the course of development in the American Elementary School, with the ones of Germany. He came to the conclusion that the American school system was superior, because it was a general educational institution for all pupils, while the children in Germany, of the better classes, received their preparatory instruction in special classes. The second speaker was Mr.E.O.Schoenrich, Baltimore. His theme was: "A very much neglected Factor of the Principles of American Teaching and Education". The goal of school education should not only be to provide the children with a certain amount of knowledge, the right way to think, and to enable them to further develop themselves educationally, after leaving school, but the highest goal should be to awaken and develop their sense of duty, and conscience, and <pb facs="5418474_6_0978.jpg" n="2"/>with them, all qualifications for the formation of a solid and form character. And to educate the children to become Americans, worthy of their great fatherland. This sense of duty, indicating a higher will, guarantees the public respect or law in state and country while disobedience in school, and home, leads to disorder and crimes, to the general disadvantage of good citizenship. Mr. H. Wildmann Cleveland, read the yearly report of the Committee for the Culture of German. What common goal should the German lessons have amongst the different school systems? The Committee of Resolutions made the following report: Referring to the teachers seminary and its union publication "Pedagogical Monthly Magazine":</p>
   <p>1. The Teachers Union holds that the Seminary is an excellent institution to educate suitable persons for the teaching of the German language in the American schools, and, considers it as one of their principal duties, to support this institution with all their means, which includes:</p>
   <p>a.) Procuring money to finance and increase the foundation capital.</p>
   <p>b.) Procuring all necessary school materials.</p>
   <p>c.) Encouragement for those wishing to take examinations.</p>
   <p>d.) Propaganda of the seminary to promote the work with good German teachers.</p>
   <p>To form agitation committees, in each town, for the Teachers Union, the Teachers Seminary and the teachers publications.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0979.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Membership fee is $2.00 per year, which includes a year's subscription to the publications. Single fees are $1.50 for membership, and $1.00 for publications.</p>
   <p>Public thanks of the union are given to the American central organization of Pennsylvania for the support of an annual contribution of $25.00, and, it is hoped, that this good example will stimulate others.</p>
   <p>The Teachers Union resolved to dedicate the amount of $200.00 to cover a deficit of last year in the publications.</p>
   <p>The union expresses its full confidnece, to the management of the seminary, and has proposed the following resolutions regarding the publications:</p>
   <p>To express its deep regret on the death of members during the past 2 years.</p>
   <p>The President and Secretary of the Union shall be natives of the city where the next convention is to take place.</p>
   <p>The Vice-President, and other officers, should all be nominated at the same time.</p>
   <p>The union shall provide for its officers, an amount required to cover convention expenses.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0980.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The convention shall be held annually, between the July 28th and June 2nd.</p>
   <p>The treasurer shall prepare a list of the membership fees received for the Secretary to publish in the next issue of the publications. The executive committee is instructed a.) to examine the Constitution and By-Laws for a revision. b.) To publish the revised Constitution two months before the next convention, in the publications. c.) To put a discussion on the revised Constitution on the program of the next convention and to place, according to their importance, Prof. Dr. Otto Heller, Prof. Oscar Burkhardt, C.E. Baumann, C.O. Schoenzick, Frau Emil Dappisch, Frau Lena Reinhardt Howie, Frau Wilhelmine Mayer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
