<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-03-02">Mar. 2, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Curt Drews the Artist</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1773</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1773.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-03-02">Mar. 2, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">CURT DREWS THE ARTIST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The group of German artists of Chicago would not be complete, without Curt Drews, who through his character and his creations reminds you of the patricians of the old kanseatic city of Hamburg.</p>
   <p>Drews was born in Hamburg, Germany, and began his studies there, continuing them in Munich and Duesseldorf.</p>
   <p>Several exhibitions, which he arranged in his native town and in the Rhineland, were very successful and he was recognized as a creative artist by the German public.</p>
   <p>He came to America for the first time in 1927, and went to Madison, Wisconsin. There, besides portraits, he painted a church as well as the Union Memorial Building, which painting now belongs to the State University. His creations received the highest recognition.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1774.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>About a year ago he once more came to America intending to remain in this country permanently. For the last six months he has lived in Chicago and does not intend to leave the city, at least not at present. A sample of his skill in fresco-painting is the "Coffee Dan in the Loop." He had to execute it within ten days, a period actually too short for the work to be done. But Drews by accomplishing it acquired many admirers.</p>
   <p>Drews specializes in portrait-painting. His portraits have dignity and a patrician character. The Ladies portrait, which is his contribution to the present exhibition at the Art Institute, breathes charm and dignity. Orders for portraits from prominent German-Americans of Chicago, will keep the artist busy here for a long time.</p>
   <p>Drews besides being a painter is also a sculptor. Several of his smaller moldings show that he is also outstanding in this field, It is interesting to know, that he has worked out a plan for a Martin Luther Monument; a monument, which Chicago surprisingly does not possess as yet.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1775.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Drews is a representative of German art, whose further works may be looked forward to, with the greatest interest.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
