<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-04-27">April 27, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">Criminals Among the Pilgrim Fathers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0474</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0474.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-04-27">April 27, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">CRIMINALS AMONG THE PILGRIM FATHERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Long ago it has been proven, even if many Anglo-Americans prefer not to be reminded of it, that our largest supply from the criminal ranks, has been brought to our shores by England during the colonial period and even later. Therefore many a "real" American will find it advantageous, if he does not resort to extensive retrospection in regard to his ancestry, when he is confronted by informed witnesses. Even today the belief prevails, that at least the Pilgrim fathers of Plymouth Rock fame, and in fact, the original Puritans, were settlers of incontestable examples of virtue, not only pious in sentiment, but exceptionally obedient in regard to mundane laws and everything which that term might embrace.</p>
   <p>But even this conception is erroneous! When God conceived a Nation, in order to propagate the excellent seed of New England (according to a popular phrase) many a weed polluted the mixture and caused endless sorrow, which later, was naturally greatly increased, when hordes of criminals and undesirables of England were shipped to the American colonies. Let us revert to the Pilgrim fathers of 1620!</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0475.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We may add, casually, that these appended recollections are by no means complete, that many extra details are available.</p>
   <p>The passenger list of the famous "May flower" shows the names of several, who proved themselves to be very obnoxious and dangerous members of the new community. The career of one terminated on the gallows. Into this classification belongs John Billington and the members of his family. Before the Pilgrim fathers landed, a little episode occurred, a sort of ominous premonition of Billington's future. One of Billington's youngsters found great delight in discharging a blunderbuss (old fashioned muzzle loaded rifle) while in close proximity to an open power keg; the ship might have been blown into atoms. The old man saw to it, that the incident should indelibly impress itself in their memory! He was the first obstreperous and pernicious tough of the settlement and soon after the landing, it became expedient to hobble his feet...and neck with irons. At the outset, he refused obedience to Captain Standish, but he soon developed into a "regular" enemy of society; he fought everyone, and in the year 1630 he was hung, in retaliation for the murder of a Mr. John Newcome,---after <pb facs="5418474_6_0476.jpg" n="3"/>having been punished numerous times for lesser crimes! The latter may also be said of several other members of his family, which Governor Bradford declared "it is one of the most Godless in the community".</p>
   <p>Of course, to a great extent, environment is often responsible for the decadence and retrogression of a settler's family. These conditions, unfortunately, are invariably apparent at an early period and develop locally.</p>
   <p>Half of the "Mayflower's" passengers died during the winter in the Plymouth wilderness and the most dismal part of this catastrophe was the demise of so many parents. It is evident, that this was more tragic, considering the location, than if such mortality had happened in an older, better organized settlement. Many a young "Pilgrim father" grew into manhood, devoid of any education, so it not surprising that they developed into crooks and criminals in due time. In this enumeration we must include Samuel Eaton, whose exemplary mother died during that dismal winter and his step-mother, likewise did not survive very long. A few years later, the court records <pb facs="5418474_6_0477.jpg" n="4"/>show: "was tried and convicted;... put into irons for stealing and fighting." He and others, generally followed the precipitous path they had selected.</p>
   <p>The first white child, born in New England, Peregrine White, also developed into a thief and fighting tough; it improved in later years however, and eventually landed in... no, an office, Chairman of the community of Maryland.</p>
   <p>With many others the trend was in a constant downward direction and we soon find a band of hoodlums under the leadership of Thomas Weston who attempted to start a settlement of their own, 25 miles north of Plymouth. This bunch created animosity among the Indians. The previously mentioned Captain Standish had to subdue them in a battle. After a short interim, we find another vagabond center, with the euphonious appellative "Merry Mount" which excelled in ruthless drinking bouts.</p>
   <p>These results we find within 25 years after the Pilgrim Fathers disembarked; they did not improve subsequently. The unavoidable consequence was, that it produced a large number of austere laws, to control crime and vice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
