<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-01-26">Jan. 26, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Time-Honored Stone</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-01-26">Jan. 26, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">TIME-HONORED STONE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the 75th birthday celebration of Mr. Carl Stein, president of Carl Stein and Sons Co., 1017 W. Division St., which celebration was held yesterday at the Lincoln Turner Hall, a "Stein" (Stone), a genuine one, which had only the name in common with Mr. Stein, played a prominent role. Carl Stein received from the old country, from his own estate, a stone, as a birthday present. That stone is 200 years old and bears the inscription: J. P. St. 1734.</p>
   <p>Mr. Stein is a Swabian, born in Illigen. He came to America in 1887 and is now the president of Carl Stein &amp; Co., a well known stonecutter firm. Naturally, the Swabians celebrated their countryman's birthday. The celebration took place at the Lincoln Turner Hall.</p>
   <p>With the stone from Maulbroun hangs a tale: Hermann Stein, son of Carl Stein, was in the old home of his father not long ago. From there he <pb facs="5418474_6_1060.jpg" n="2"/>brought this venerable stone, which originates from the Maulbroun Cloister, where it was used as a cornerstone about 200 years ago. He brought also another stone which came from the stonecutter plant of his ancestors, the latter stone being thus, a real piece of the old house. The progenitors of Stein were already for 400 years in the stone cutting business, as can be seen by the initials engraved on the stone, J. P. St. (Johann Philipp Stein). These initials are the monogram of those of Stein. Mr. Carl Stein's joy, caused by this occasion, can easily be understood.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
