<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-03-27">Mar. 27, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">Against Woman's Suffrage</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0799</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0799.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-03-27">Mar. 27, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">AGAINST WOMAN'S SUFFRAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For several years advocates of woman's suffrage have claimed that the Fourteenth Amendment to the Constitution of the United States is to be interpreted to mean that a woman who is a citizen of the United States and of a state has the right to vote in the state in which she lives, even if the constitution and the laws of that state specifically grant the right to vote only to men. While it is true that ordinary common sense can find nothing in the Constitution to justify such a conclusion, this illogical conclusion has been a sacred doctrine to the advocates of woman's suffrage ever since Victoria Woodhull and several other loquacious ladies told the Judicial Committee of the House of Representatives that woman's suffrage is "an integral part of our Constitutional rights".</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0800.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At that time, Ben Buttler, one of the members of the Judicial Committee, claimed that this interpretation was correct. Of course, he too is a suffragist, but he proved time and again that he was merely making fun of his feminine political associates, by carefully avoiding the defense of that "Constitutional doctrine" before a court. However, Susan Anthony believed in it so firmly that she exposed herself to fine and imprisonment by attempting to gain her "right" to vote by force.</p>
   <p>Some adherents to the "Constitutional doctrine" have presented their claim to franchise rights at nearly every major election that was held during the past few years. One case has been appealed from the Supreme Court of Missouri to the Supreme Court of the United States. The United States Supreme Court has just rendered a decision on the issue. It has decided that the Constitution of the United States confers the right to vote upon no one, that voting is a matter left to the states, and that the Constitution of the United States contains no provisions which could possibly justify the conclusion <pb facs="5418474_6_0801.jpg" n="3"/>that the state voting laws are null and void, because they restrict the right to vote to men.</p>
   <p>Thus the endeavors of the suffragettes have come to naught again. That is as it should be. We hope that they are satisfied and that they will further efforts to "elevate" woman to a sphere into which she was not placed by nature, and where she is not "at home".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
