<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1884-05-28">May 28, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">The May Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1674</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1674.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1884-05-28">May 28, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">THE MAY FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About 7000 persons, wrapped in Sealskin coats, ulsters and Furgloves attended yesterday's brilliant opening of the music-Festival. The Thomas Orchestra played Mozarts tuneful G. Moll Symphony with their well known mastership. It is the largest orchestra Thomas ever conducted, and it follows his "baton" with admirable trustiness and delicacy.</p>
   <p>The first and second part of Haydn's Creation was also on the program. The choir did its full duty. It proved to be well drilled, strong and very effective. Of the faulty combination in regard to the pitch of the voices, which an English paper criticized yesterday, we did not notice anything. Only the tenor did not seem to be strong enough. Madame Nilsson sang with her wonderfully catching voice, so clear, so full, so beautiful, which was seldom before heard in Chicago. It is impossible to express with words what we heard. Long applause rewarded the artist for the delight she bestowed on the thousands present.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1675.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Remmers sang with good effect, Mr. Toedts' voice was not sufficiently strong for the big hall. Those sitting close to the stage were pleased with his voice. Miss Juch labored also under the same impediment. She has a clear, pretty and well trained voice, which only lacks strength in the middle notes.</p>
   <p>To-night's program contains Beethovens Eroica Symphony, and a selection from Wagner's Tannhauser. The soloists are: Mrs. Amalia Friedrich-Materna, Miss Emma Juch, Mr. Toedt, Mr. Renunertz, Mr. Heinrich, Mr. Emil Scaria and Mr. Hermann Winkelmann.</p>
   <p>To-morrow afternoon: Big Wagner-Matinee. Soloists: Mrs. Nilsson, Mrs. Materna, Mr. Scaria and Mr. Winkelmann.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
