<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-09-09">Sept. 9. 1898</date><title level="a">Carl Schurz against Annexation Politics</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0484</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0484.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-09-09">Sept. 9. 1898</date><title level="a">CARL SCHURZ AGAINST ANNEXATION POLITICS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Through the easy victories in the Spanish War a certain situation has been created which causes a widespread interest among our population in regard to the question of Annexation.</p>
   <p>Carl Schurz is among those eminent Americans, who warn the people of the destructive consequences of expansion and annexation policies. In his highly intellectual and strictly logical discussions he falls back on his strong arguments, which he employed against the quickly rising annexation politics in his much discussed speech at Saratoga. He is trying to prove that the possession of the tropical colonies would be of very little advantage to us, but that the disadvantages and dangers connected with it, will appear with fatalistic certainty.</p>
   <p>The downfall of one of the greatest colonial powers, Spain, should be a warning example for us. Great profit from colonies can be gained only if the most inconsiderate exploitation policies are applied, as for instance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0485.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>England does in many of her colonies. But this is the very thing the United States with their "humane politics" try to avoid. Where are the advantages? We have no conception to what extent this expansion politics can lead to fatal results. To rule the rebellious people on these island colonies would require heavy losses of men and money, a considerable increase of the army and navy; and perhaps, new dangers would threaten our republic as a result of these policies.</p>
   <p>The sad conditions in which many of our soldiers returned from the short campaign in Cuba, is sufficient evidence that we are not ready to cope with an adventurous policy in the tropics. The latest events prove, beyond doubt, that Mr. Schurz' warnings are opportune and sound.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
