<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-19">Apr. 19, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">German-American Churches and Private Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0098</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0098.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-19">Apr. 19, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN-AMERICAN CHURCHES AND PRIVATE SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following is the persistent report from Springfield: Two liberally minded gentlemen who represent the liberal German clubs of Chicago, were supposed to defend these clubs' attitude against the German Catholic Alliance of Illinois, which is supposedly putting up a fight against free distribution of textbooks and other similar measures in public schools. This is the manner in which they proceeded:</p>
   <p>These two gentlemen overindulged in suspecting the Catholics, as well as the Lutherans, of the intention of crippling public schools in order to perpetuate the existence of their own private schools, since competition in regard to public schools is out of question. These gentlemen emphasized the fact that public schools alone can successfully teach patriotism to <pb facs="5418474_6_0099.jpg" n="2"/>foreigners and that if they would have the authority parochial schools would be suppressed altogether. The applause which these gentlemen received made it apparent that the majority of the committee shared their attitude. However, the mass protests and petitions, signed by 50,000 Catholics, did not miss their objective, since the session adjourned without any votes being cast.</p>
   <p>If these two liberally minded gentlemen did actually denounce the German-American churches and parochial schools before the English-American Legislative Committee in Springfield, in the manner related, they have indeed not transmitted the ideas of the majority of the people whom they were supposed to represent. Eleven years ago, when the attempt was made to make use of the Bennett-Edwards legislation in order to suppress the German Protestant and the German Catholic parochial schools, the fight in upholding these schools was led by Mr. Heinrich Rabb, who had the moral support of the open-minded German people. The cause defended by these two <pb facs="5418474_6_0100.jpg" n="3"/>gentlemen is indeed without any rhyme or reason. Parochial schools need not fear competition from our public schools; moreover, parochial schools are a source of infinite help to public schools, especially in Chicago. Many thousands of children of school age would be denied the privilege of school attendance as the result of a scarcity of public schools, if parochial schools would not come to their assistance and absorb a certain percentage of school-age children. The assertion made by these two gentlemen, in their nativistic jargon, that teaching patriotism to immigrants or foreigners can be successfully accomplished in public schools only, is an infamous defamation.</p>
   <p>In addition, German parochial and private schools, as well as German churches, are sources extremely valuable in the preservation and perpetuation of the German language and customs. Information has reached us, that numerous ultraliberal Germans have made an effort to investigate these schools under attack, which led them finally to pay tribute to these institutions. They have also denounced the attempt of the Nativists to suspect and belittle these worthy depositories of learning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
