<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-03">July 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A Radical Law</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0827</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0827.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-03">July 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A RADICAL LAW</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Roosevelt has signed the Frazier-Lemke bill and has thereby made it a law. This law is the more significant because it is the only law of the New Deal which can be considered radical; it means a complete departure from the American tradition. It provides for a reduction in, or suspension of, agricultural debts. It is noteworthy that both authors, Senator Lynn J. Frazier and Congressman William Lemke, hail from North Dakota, and were formerly closely connected with the Farmers' Non-Partisan League. The law is the product of a radical agrarian policy which has many followers in the Northwest, and especially in North Dakota. It provides that every farmer who has one or more mortgages on his farm may negotiate with the holders of the mortgages for the purpose of securing a reduction of the indebtedness. If the two parties reach no agreement, the farmer may appeal to the proper federal court. This court must appraise the farm; then, on the basis of <pb facs="5418474_6_0828.jpg" n="2"/>this appraisal, it decides what amount the farmer must pay his creditors. The paying off of the mortgage may be divided by the court into several years and meanwhile the farmer has to pay interest of only one per cent on the debt.</p>
   <p>If the creditors refuse to accept this arrangement, the court has the right to postpone the settlement of the matter for five years. Meanwhile the farmer remains on the farm as a sort of tenant, and must pay to the owner of the mortgage an amount set by the court as rent. The law provides, therefore, for expropriation in the true sense of the word. The mortgage holder's property is partly expropriated by a court decision. In this situation the debtor has all the advantages, the creditor all the disadvantages.</p>
   <p>The law goes much further than the Home Owners' Loan Act of 1933. This law, which was enacted in the interest of the small city home owner, provides, also, for the reduction of the mortgage of its interest. But it presupposes <pb facs="5418474_6_0829.jpg" n="3"/>that the owner of the mortgage has agreed to the arrangement. It tries to help both the home owner and the possessor of the mortgage. Under the Frazier-Lemke Act, the mortgage holder can be compelled to accept the reduction of the mortgage or the temporary reduction of the interest to one per cent.</p>
   <p>Naturally, the law should serve as a means for the reduction of the debts on agricultural property. The total amount of agricultural mortgage debts is estimated at twelve and one-half billion dollars. This is an immense sum, but it is considerably less than the total amount of city mortgages. This one-sided favoring of the farmer over city people seems questionable. But the law is based on the idea that the farmer is a poor, hunted person, driven from house and home by the mortgage holder, a well-filled capitalist beast. This idea is fantastic nonsense.</p>
   <p>It is quite possible that the owner of a farm mortgage is worse off than the debtor. Many of these farm mortgages are in the hands of large <pb facs="5418474_6_0830.jpg" n="4"/>insurance companies, and if their existence should be endangered by the new law, hundreds of thousands of policy holders would lose their money. Naturally, the law has a safety valve, which consists in the right of the court to have the actual value of the farm appraised. This stipulation works in the interest of both parties, in that of the debtor as well as that of the creditor.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, the new law means a forcible and one-sided interference in private financial transactions. Up to the present, the protection of private property has been considered one of the fundamental duties of the State. In this case, the State not only breaks with this principle, but it takes the initiative in the attack upon private property. It does not seem possible that the Supreme Court will consider the law constitutional.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
