<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-07">June 7, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Falsification of History</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0387</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0387.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-07">June 7, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">FALSIFICATION OF HISTORY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the June 8 edition of the Saturday Evening Post there is an extremely remarkable article. It is the first article of a series and it is printed in the front of the magazine. The cover page points to it expressly. There it says, "The causes of the bank panic of March 4, 1933, by William Starr Myers and Walter H. Newton". On reading this, one soon notices that something does not jibe. One is reminded that March 4, 1933 is the day on which President Roosevelt was inaugurated. One also knows that, in the preceding weeks, more and more banks were closed, as the governments of the states declared bank holidays. One is reminded that the country was threatened by a complete financial collapse at the time Roosevelt took office, and that he, through his energetic interference, prevented that collapse.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0388.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then Roosevelt, without a moment's hesitation, declared a national bank holiday. Although this was a heroic step, it was a beneficial one. At once confidence was restored; many encouraging statements were published and, when the national holiday was over, it turned out that it was without untoward consequences. These are facts that are generally known and which were, until now, denied by no one. The writers of that article in the Saturday Evening Post have taken it upon themselves to turn these facts upside down, and to prove the opposite.</p>
   <p>The Republicans have apparently become clearly aware that all their arguments against President Roosevelt and his policies would bounce back on them because of the fact that the economic collapse began in autumn of 1929, during a Republican administration, that their party was still almost three and a half years at the helm without doing anything effective to combat the depression. Compared with this undeniable fact, all arguments against the New Deal must appear nonsensical and invalid. It goes without saying <pb facs="5418474_6_0389.jpg" n="3"/>that everyone will have, against these arguments, the following plausible answer: "If you know how the depression is to be combated effectively, why did you not do it when you were still at the helm?" Nothing that will stand the test could be voiced against this objection.</p>
   <p>William Starr Myers and Walter H. Newton now try to prove that not Hoover but Roosevelt is to blame for the depression. They gave their article the veneer of a strictly scientific and unbiased presentation. They even have the audacity to maintain: "It is the purpose of these articles to investigate why the autumn of 1932 upswing, which had just started, came to a standstill. Here we do not want to discuss the question of whether the policy of the Hoover administration or that of the Roosevelt administration was solidly reliable or not. All we want to discuss are the reasons for the sudden interruption of the upswing". In spite of this hypocritical assurance, the article is a piece of pure propaganda; it is nothing but a totally mendacious agitation for purposes of propaganda.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0390.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It seems, in the first place, to be appropriate to place the constitution under the magnifying glass. Mr. Myers is a professor who designates himself in "Who's "Who" as a Republican and who, among other things, wrote a history of the Republican party; therefore, he is a dyed-in-the-wool partisan. Walter H. Newton was President Hoover's secretary. That's enough. In the article it is contended that, during the summer and autumn of 1932 the whole world showed an economic upswing, including the United States. But when the election was over, in November 1932, the upswing came to a close, and the country was cast into a grave bank crisis. It is generally known that bank insolvencies began after the great crash on the exchange in the autumn of 1929 and that, from that period on, many thousands of banks all over the country were forced to close their doors. Anyone who maintains that the bank crisis began after Roosevelt was elected says an untruth intentionally.</p>
   <p>Just as little could the contention be proved that conditions took an upswing in the autumn of 1932. Starr and Newton contend that financial and commercial business were so frightened by Roosevelt's inflationary intentions that they <pb facs="5418474_6_0391.jpg" n="5"/>lost all confidence, and so the economic situation grew worse, until at last the bank crisis was the result. For this contention, they bring numerous proof. They cite Roosevelt and other Democratic politicians, they bring alleged fragments from papers and periodicals, all of which may be summed up to mean that the Democrats had decided to take to inflationary measures, and that this was the reason why the country became disquieted and alarmed.</p>
   <p>It is needless to go into detail about these comments. Starr and Newton simply dug up all possible utterances made by journalists and politicians that fitted into their scheme, in an effort to construe a belated alibi for the Hoover administration. They could have easily dug up just as many utterances of an opposing nature. The complete inconsistency of their contention becomes clear from the fact that now, years after the alleged inflationary measures took effect, and in accordance with the unanimous judgment of bankers and financial experts, there is no inflation at all, One could <pb facs="5418474_6_0392.jpg" n="6"/>further point to the fact that bank failures stopped completely since Roosevelt took office, and that now the public has again full faith in its financial institutions.</p>
   <p>The article in the Saturday Evening Post, as concerns content, makeup and illustrations, has been prepared with astounding refinement. What is, however, even more astounding is the boundless nerve (or rather impudence) with which the writers turn generally known facts upside down--facts that have never been questioned before.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
