<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-07-23">July 23, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Public Opinion</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0375</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0375.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-07-23">July 23, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">PUBLIC OPINION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For some time many of our newspapers have been emphasizing the fact that next year we will have to vote on the question: Shall our Constitution be preserved, or shall the New Deal continue to rule?</p>
   <p>Before it was decided that this question should be voted upon, the slogan "Save the Constitution" was used in a campaign and emphasized to the same extent. It was said that the New Deal could lead only to a change of the Constitution, and that the voters would have to prevent this, even though the Supreme Court of the United States had done its duty.</p>
   <p>It is said that the press of the country reflects public opinion. That is alleged! Here and there, however, this public opinion is published by other means, at least at Washington--when the money necessary to pay for it <pb facs="5418474_6_0376.jpg" n="2"/>has been provided. Meanwhile a great number of voters may have gradually learned what this public opinion really is, and what is hidden in back of it.</p>
   <p>Not long ago many "conveyors" of public opinion felt that they were threatened by the N.R.A. The freedom of the press was in danger. They used every means they could think of to explain to their readers what the result would be if the liberty of the press were restricted, if the press were muzzled. It should be understood that the warnings always emanated from the Government; the newspapers did not stir. They considered the "attacks" upon the press to be an inevitable result of political activity.</p>
   <p>Then came the death of the N.R.A. The conveyors of public opinion had lost their sounding board; however, the fight had to go on! A careless remark of the President offered a new bone of contention--the Constitution. Everybody may voice his disappointment after years of worry and labor--but not the President.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0377.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>One thing that seems to be very peculiar is the fact that despite the efforts of the vehicles of public opinion to undermine the work of the President, they never questioned his constitutional authority to declare the moratorium by which the country was saved from financial chaos. At that time nobody stirred, nobody appealed to the Supreme Court. On the contrary, the President was praised for his prompt action and his effective measures to ward off bankruptcy. And the people who would have suffered the greatest losses, had the financial structure of the nation collapsed, were loudest and most profuse in their praise. However, when these same people were asked to assume additional financial responsibilities in order to fight the depression--well,friend, that is "a bird of an altogether different color". Now they remember that we have a constitution! Now they peruse it diligently, seeking a way to evade the provisions of the N.R.A. and to remove the man who would deprive them of their "most sacred possessions".</p>
   <p>That is the whole thing in a nutshell. Everything else is merely willful misrepresentation. There is no adequate expression for what has been <pb facs="5418474_6_0378.jpg" n="4"/>printed about "endangering" the Constitution. At least not yet, but some day we shall have one, and it will not reflect creditably upon the conveyors of public opinion. One could fight them with their own weapons, but it would not be honorable.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
