<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-18">Aug. 18, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The Murderer</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0555</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0555.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-18">Aug. 18, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">THE MURDERER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>That infamous scoundrel, Guiteau, seems to be well aware of the fact that Garfield's death also means departure by way of the gallows for the assassin. In spite of his volubility he has the instinct of self-preservation; in other words, he fears death. But how can he save his despicable life? Simple enough: he feigns insanity. He knows that hundreds, if not thousands, of murderers, men as well as women, have cheated the gallows by the simple expedient of pleading insanity.</p>
   <p>If Garfield were a common person whose life or death did not affect the world particularly, and if Guiteau had money enough, then it would be a simple matter to obtain the shrewdest lawyers to prove him irrational. In cases in which it has been impossible to prove actual insanity these unscrupulous legal luminaries, distorters of the law, have succeeded in showing temporary insanity which affected their client at the moment and then subsided. Guiteau is not an animal; <pb facs="5418474_6_0556.jpg" n="2"/>he is a pious man. He has attended revival meetings and has revealed himself as an ardent, vociferous Christian; he is a member of Christian organizations. He would be the kind of fellow who could arouse the morbid sympathies of all the half demented, half hypocritical Protestant brethren and sisters and thus be fully exonerated. But as we said before, only if his victim had been an ordinary mortal. Since this is not the case, Guiteau's prospects take on a serious aspect, and he is sensible enough to realize that if Garfield dies, then nothing can prevent his being executed. His only hope, therefore, was to feign insanity, even if it involved another murder, and so he attempted to kill the turnkey.</p>
   <p>But this will not help much. Guiteau gave ample proof that he was not insane at the time when he shot the President, and therefore it is impossible to hoodwink the people now. But if insistence is to be placed on insanity, well and good; then he was crazy, in the same manner as a dog is which is afflicted with hydrophobia. Dogs are killed under such circumstances so that they may not endanger people. By his last attempt at murder Guiteau merely showed that <pb facs="5418474_6_0557.jpg" n="3"/>his type of insanity cannot be guarded against by imprisoning the man. If his execution, therefore, would have no value as an example of proper retribution and would not serve as a deterrent then it would still be necessary to render harmless a beast of such murderous tendencies. In case the President dies, and the murderer does not pay the penalty, that will be tantamount to making the entire nation guilty. Such a disgrace must be prevented at all costs. If the regular course of the law (and often, unfortunately, its procedure is the most irregular that can be imagined) does not suffice, then lynching may even be resorted to. Against the sound reasoning of the masses and their ruthless force the miserable technicalities of disreputable lawyers are powerless.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
