<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-10-21">Oct. 21, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Delightful Concerts of Three German Song Clubs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1527</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1527.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-10-21">Oct. 21, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">DELIGHTFUL CONCERTS OF THREE GERMAN SONG CLUBS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Liberty Song Club gave a concert Saturday afternoon at De Paul Auditorium, in conformance to a yearly custom. Director Karl Reckzeh provided an excellent program. As usual, the orchestra consisted of twenty members of the Chicago Symphony orchestra. The soloists were Minnie Starr and Micha Liushutz.</p>
   <p>Prolonged applause assured the leader, Carl Resszeh (sic) that the public was grateful for the treat.</p>
   <p>Excelsior Male Chorus</p>
   <p>The Excelsior Male Chorus celebrated its thirtieth anniversary at the Lincoln Turnhalle. (Gymnastic hall) The attendance was exceptionally large. The public was in a very receptive, animated mood, due to highly pleasing accomplishments of the performers, under the leadership of Ernest Tamm.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1528.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Excelsior Male Chorus comprising about seventy singers, is well supplied with first tenors; excellent voices. It must be added that about one half of the active members are young men.</p>
   <p>The program also provided two numbers for mixed chorus. A laudable arrangement of the Excelsior Club provides variety and also enriches its program by adding mixed choral selections, with the collaboration of the Polyhymnia Ladies Chorus. The last part of the program, "Singer's Joy," a splendid march by Kern, was given in unison with the Excelsior Club, the Song section D. U. B., the Swiss Male Chorus, North Chicago Male Chorus, the Concordia Song Club, and orchestra.</p>
   <p>Beyond question, the apex of the presentation was the first Chicago offering, an "Ode to the German Melody," with orchestral accompaniment. Miss Mathilde Reiners and Ludwig Schappey, members of the Excelsior Club, taking the solo parts. Both singers are endowed with ingratiating voices, seasoned by experience. The ode, in its overpowering, all pervading splendor, aroused the thought of listening to an oratorio.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1529.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Louis Goetz, president of the Club and host, greeted the assembly with a short address wherein he stressed the value of German songs, pointing also to the satisfaction which the Germans abroad derive from the efforts of the German Singing societies in preparing an American home for German melodies and the German language. He also expressed his pleasure in being able to give a testimonial, a diploma, concrete documentary evidence to Albert Schulz, in commemoration of having been an active member and singer for twenty-five years. In connection therewith he also mentioned several gentlemen, members of long standing: Gustav Zindler, thirty years; Rudolph Balzer, twenty-eight years; and L. Ratzki, twenty-six years.</p>
   <p>Mr. Goetz then presented Doctor Kobalter, Allied president of the Associated Clubs, and of the German Day Celebration Committee, who offered congratulations in the name of the societies he represents, as well as Christ Paschen. The latter is Chicago's building commissioner. He was invited as an honorary guest, but could not appear.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1530.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A ball and orchestral music brought the excellently attended festival to an end.</p>
   <p>Schiller Song Club</p>
   <p>The concert of the Schiller Song Club must indeed give complete satisfaction to its members. No vacant seats were available at Wicker Park Hall.</p>
   <p>The choral selections, both a capella, and with orchestral accompaniment, showed that the members have good vocal qualifications and were given proper schooling by their leader, Reinhold Walter. Naturally, the public did not stint with well deserved applause....Miss Duhr, with a selection of solo numbers, earned great acclaim, and a beautiful bouquet was presented to her.....</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the concert, a dance was arranged, the same orchestra providing the music.....Aside from the efforts of Director Walter, the <pb facs="5418474_6_1531.jpg" n="5"/>concert's success is attributable to the labors of the various committee members and these officials are: Ex-officio president Henry Kaeding, president Paul Wagner....[Altogether sixteen names are listed. Translator]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
