<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-19">Jan. 19, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Under the Microscope</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0052</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0052.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-01-19">Jan. 19, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">UNDER THE MICROSCOPE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The disclosure of widespread dishonesty, incompetence, and extravagance in the realm of war charities by a Federal district attorney of New York has attracted much attention. The lessons which these unpleasant revelations teach are applicable in no smaller degree to many branches of private benevolence. In this field, too, vanity, credulous kindheartedness, and poor management are often a hindrance to the attainment of satisfactory results, and sometimes make success impossible. Owing to the general lack of desirable public institutions in the United States, many branches of public welfare have been left to private charities. Homes for delinquent boys or girls, sanitariums for the cure of mental diseases and alcoholism, homes for the aged, and like institutions are permitted by public authorities and courts to operate as semiofficial agencies, and <pb facs="5418474_6_0053.jpg" n="2"/>are favored by them with special privileges. But these institutions are not controlled by these authorities and courts, nor are they required to give an accounting of their finances and their management.</p>
   <p>Even the care of orphans, a charitable activity which, above all others, should be in the hands of conscientious people who are willing to make any and every sacrifice, suffers from the same indifferent attitude. It is just in this field that organized private charity, acting as a deputy of the public authorities, has been found wanting. The local American press has published lengthy reports on the case of a six-year-old girl who was placed in the family of a farmer. Up to her tenth year she was afforded opportunity to go to school--now and then. But during the following eleven years she was forced to do messenger service without pay. The local Law Enforcement League took the matter to court, and a jury awarded the girl $1,500 for her services.</p>
   <p>The chairman of the League stated that twenty similar cases would soon be <pb facs="5418474_6_0054.jpg" n="3"/>prosecuted. Concerning the case mentioned above he said:</p>
   <p>"We found that this girl and five other children of her family had been taken away from their parents by the authorities and turned over to the Illinois Aid Society upon advice of the examiner. The Society then placed the children with six different foster parents in several states. The father of these children was a drunkard, and that was considered sufficient cause for disrupting the family. The mother, bereft of her children, died a year later--in the asylum for the insane at Dunning.</p>
   <p>"It required months of intensive searching to find the children. The father gave up drinking and found a home with one of his sons.</p>
   <p>"Innumerable families have been torn apart through the co-operation of several such 'aid societies,' and nearly always on the advice of so-called investigators of the juvenile court. We intend to learn the <pb facs="5418474_6_0055.jpg" n="4"/>extent of this court's authority. We shall ascertain whether it has the power to plunge so many thousands of human beings into abject misery, especially upon the advice of incompetent and negligent investigators."</p>
   <p>During this present period of widespread social unrest it seems imperative that the State devote its authority and resources to the protection and defense of the physically or mentally weak, of helpless youth and the indigent aged. The prolonged slavery of orphans was brought about under the guise of humanitarianism and is merely a system of the hypocrisy and self-deception which is so prevalent in human society. We hope that none will wait until violence brings about an awakening!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
