<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-01-28">Jan. 28, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">City Finances</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0294</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0294.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-01-28">Jan. 28, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">CITY FINANCES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As gratifying as our city finances appear, when considering the comptroller's report given to the city council yesterday evening, we see, nevertheless, serious problems involved when we scrutinize the facts more thoroughly. In giving intrinsical cogitation to some matters, one is confronted with ominous doubts about the advisability of accumulating public money at the office of the city treasurer. There is for instance, $82,276 in the city treasury belonging to the school fund--more than sufficient to build three schools. Yet, thousands of school children are trying in vain to gain admittance in public schools; thousands others must spend hours in unsanitary, inadequate, rented buildings which serve as auxiliary institutions of learning.</p>
   <p>The Department of Public Works has a cash balance of $107,315.40 available; yet, the approaches to most bridges are in dire need of repair, and the unpaved streets <pb facs="5418474_6_0295.jpg" n="2"/>are just about unpassable, quite aside from the despicable fact that the city laborers are paid in script, whereby they lose at least eight per cent. The city treasurer probably drew interest on the money with which the officials bought up the script--money which in all fairness should have been used to pay the workers.</p>
   <p>Of the appropriations for drainage canals, $63,476.92 is still unused, although we have streets where drainage ditches are a necessity. Promises were made three years ago to alleviate conditions; yet, property owners still wait hopelessly to see this work performed, and look with apprehension toward the time when children will die with scarlet fever and diphtheria.</p>
   <p>The taxpayers do not donate money to see an imposing balance in the treasury at the end of the year, but they expect public improvements to be made in conformance with appropriations, and that public servants be properly reimbursed for their labor. Hoarded wealth in the city treasury does not benefit the municipality; on the contrary, if the proceeds derived from taxation are not <pb facs="5418474_6_0296.jpg" n="3"/>kept in constant circulation, the total tax burden may become even greater. With this circulation it will not be so unbearable as when the accumulated funds at the city treasury retard the normal flow of money.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
