<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-03-30">Mar. 30, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Diligently at Work</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1310</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1310.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-03-30">Mar. 30, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">DILIGENTLY AT WORK</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The factory of Fraser and Chalmers, of Chicago, which produces chiefly heavy machinery for mines, is now manufacturing the equipment for the Chicago Mining and Milling Company. The work is about half completed. The boiler is still under construction. The machinery is now being assembled; sixty horse-power are required to drive the ore crusher, etc. An inspection of the plans which were made according to the specification, and under the supervision of Karl Weberling, the mining company's engineer, indicate that the installation has been especially designed to save labor.</p>
   <p>The ore, as it is being hauled from the mines, is dumped into a Blake stone crusher. Here [in the crusher] the ore is reduced, whereupon it is dried to evaporate whatever water is present. After the drying operation, the now partly crushed ore drops into large drums made of wrought iron, where the particles are pulverized with the aid of large balls. By automatic means the <pb facs="5418474_6_1311.jpg" n="2"/>ore now reaches a conveyor and is dropped into a perforated drum; the material thus sifted enters a funnel and drops into cars, and the material then reaches the roasting cylinders. The coarser material remaining in the perforated drum is returned, because it is not ground fine enough for roasting.</p>
   <p>In the roasting cylinders the ore is mixed with salt, heated, and [the metal] liberated. The material so treated drops again into cars and is dumped on an inclined plane, and stored to await the amalgamation process. The following procedure is now resorted to: The ore is placed in pans and mixed with mercury and subsequently pressed. The remaining amalgam is put into a retort where the mercury is evaporated [sic] and the remaining silver is melted in a furnace and cast into bars.</p>
   <p>The machinery will be completed in a short time, ready for shipment to Arizona. Mr. Weberling will leave for that State prior to the delivery of the machinery, to superintend the erection of buildings.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1312.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Anyone interested may see the plans, which were drawn by Mr. Unzicker, a German draftsman, who will be pleased to give the necessary explanations at the factory, 139-145 Fulton Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
