<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-12">Apr. 12, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">Away with Illusions and Self-Deception!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0174.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-12">Apr. 12, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">AWAY WITH ILLUSIONS AND SELF-DECEPTION!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung always considered it a special task of the Socialistic Press, to protect fighting workers from disappointments arising from false propaganda, and to strongly warn them of all illusions in this respect.</p>
   <p>As the strongly suppressing reaction, under which the workers' movement, on all lines, presently suffers, was made possible chiefly by those self-deceptions and illusions, which are still lurking in the lines of our comrades, we take the opportunity to insert in this chapter some serious outspoken remarks.</p>
   <p>What we have mentioned in former articles, in regards to this matter, was aimed against the practice of achieving advantages for the workers by means of bluffing and intimidating the adversary.</p>
   <p>We point to the harmful reaction of the "bluff game" by which these gamblers <pb facs="5418474_6_0175.jpg" n="2"/>try to bluff and deceive, first of all, themselves.</p>
   <p>It happens too frequently that we try to persuade ourselves we have accomplished much; while, in reality, very little fruitful and useful work was done, and almost no lasting effect was reached.</p>
   <p>That this defect actually is being found in all lines of our social battlefront, can be shown by numerous facts. For German workers, this standpoint can be considered as passed; but among our English speaking comrades the majority still does not realize that all these ventures, at the best, can only result in some advantages for a few individuals; and in general only lead to exposure of workers' plans by a failure in business or, if prospering, to a development of "exploiter-concerns."</p>
   <p>In this field and not less in that of one-sided political movements, as well as <pb facs="5418474_6_0176.jpg" n="3"/>the so-called radical procedure, we see staunch fighters who are playing the "bluff game" not so much against the common enemy, as against themselves.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
