<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-25">Nov. 25, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">German Theater</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Commanded by the Empress," Operetta of the Good Old Times, a Great Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1520</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1520.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-25">Nov. 25, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN THEATER</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Commanded by the Empress," Operetta of the Good Old Times, a Great Success</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The operetta, "Commanded by the Empress," libretto by Leopold Jacobsohn, music by Bruno Granichstaedten, is a play that reverts to the old days when despite the fact that empresses enjoyed unrestricted autocratical powers and no inhibitions prevented them from exercising them over their subjects, they usually remembered that others, too, were endowed with a yearning for love and happiness.</p>
   <p>In this play a young empress is exceedingly jealous of her handsome, vivacious husband, and suspects him of being the clandestine lover <pb facs="5418474_6_1521.jpg" n="2"/>of an embroideress. The latter, however, has a sweetheart, an officer of the royal guard, and towards the end of the third act everything is unravelled satisfactorily and everybody is overwhelmed with joy.</p>
   <p>The music,in a large measure, is very imposing, almost too intrinsic for an operetta, but florid melodies with a tendency to impress have also bean provided in copious quantities. The orchestra under Christoph's leadership met all demands unfailingly.</p>
   <p>Lya Beyer, in the title role, sang and played to perfection; she could not have been better. Towering above others, first rank and honor in German light opera are definitely assured for the new singer. She is blessed with a fascinating voice and exceptional gifts befitting an actress.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1522.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Rudi Hille, spick and span, lovelorn guard officer sang excellently as usual and was highly successful in his part.</p>
   <p>Helne Holstein, who played the role of the embroideress, gave us a typical affectionate girl of Vienna. Hans Muenz was a genuine Don Juan on the imperial throne. This character appeared exceptionally advantageous to him.</p>
   <p>Ernst Robert, in the role of the fabulous sausage manufacturer, the man who was not only a "somebody" but had the "wherewithal" to back this claim, came out successfully.</p>
   <p>Angelo Lippich, as the slightly silly son of the sausage magnate, who was obsessed by an all-consuming ardor for anything on the stage and behind the scenes, gave an excellent comical rendition. Kurt Kupfer, <pb facs="5418474_6_1523.jpg" n="4"/>as a guardian of morals, displayed this ludicrous dignitary in a splendid manner. Hela Lindelof was an entrancing princess whose tendencies one is inclined to forgive; after all, she is a beautiful woman. Then we had Helene Lofink, the charming needleworker. Neither shall we forget the two children Boby Follmann and Jeannette Devries.</p>
   <p>Both performances were well attended. Acclaim was generous and deserved.</p>
   <p>K. H. K.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
