<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1923-09-23">Sept. 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Arthur Von Eweyk, the Well Known Singer, Now a Chicago Citizen.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1559</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1559.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1923-09-23">Sept. 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">ARTHUR VON EWEYK, THE WELL KNOWN SINGER, NOW A CHICAGO CITIZEN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The music loving public of Chicago, will receive the news with pleasure, that a very prominent singer, who achieved great fame in Europe as well as in America, has chosen for his permanent home, our city Chicago. It is Mr. Arthur Van Eweyk, who because, of his extraordinary soft and hormonious bass baritone voice, so often has created enthusiasm among his audience.</p>
   <p>Von Eweyk was born in Milwaukee, Wisconsin, and studied music here, but later went to Berlin, where he continued his studies, and soon belonged to the most prominent representatives of his profession. He sang in almost every country in Europe and came repeatedly for a visit to America, where he always was celebrated in a worthy manner.</p>
   <p>Later he was active as teacher in various prominent music schools of Germany, as the Stern's conservatory in Berlin, it was there that he achieved his greatest success. But as the conditions in Germany grew worse, he decided to return to the country of his birth. Since then he has been heard repeatedly. For instance, <pb facs="5418474_6_1560.jpg" n="2"/>when he sang as soloist in the reproduction of Judas Maccabeus, an outstanding feature of the Chicago Singverein, his beautiful voice as well as his excellent performance attracted general attention.</p>
   <p>Mr. Von Eweyk is a member of the teachers faculty of the Sherwood Music school, but he reserved the rights, to spend a day each week in his home town Milwaukee, where he instructs at the Wisconsin Conservatory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
