<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-12-08">Dec. 8, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Sanitary Conditions in Chicago a Grave Problem</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0915</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.M"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0915.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-12-08">Dec. 8, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">SANITARY CONDITIONS IN CHICAGO A GRAVE PROBLEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anyone who has perused the statistics of the health department must have noticed that mortality rates rose considerably in Chicago this year. The records show that we had 7422 deaths in the year 1878. In 1879, up to December 1, a period of 11 months, deaths reached 8,467; adding thereto [for December] the average number of deaths during the past eleven months, we find that the year's total will be about 9,236, or 1,814 more than in the previous year.</p>
   <p>A list showing the constant increase during the various months is appended:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Deaths during</cell>
     <cell>1878</cell>
     <cell>1879</cell>
     <cell>Increase</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>January,</cell>
     <cell>572</cell>
     <cell>737</cell>
     <cell>165</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>February,</cell>
     <cell>481</cell>
     <cell>584</cell>
     <cell>103</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0916.jpg" n="2"/>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Deaths during</cell>
     <cell>1878</cell>
     <cell>1879</cell>
     <cell>Increase</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>March,</cell>
     <cell>578</cell>
     <cell>730</cell>
     <cell>152</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>April,</cell>
     <cell>508</cell>
     <cell>604</cell>
     <cell>96</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>May,</cell>
     <cell>486</cell>
     <cell>625</cell>
     <cell>139</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>June,</cell>
     <cell>453</cell>
     <cell>703</cell>
     <cell>250</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>July,</cell>
     <cell>1067</cell>
     <cell>1152</cell>
     <cell>85</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>August,</cell>
     <cell>814</cell>
     <cell>1084</cell>
     <cell>270</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>September,</cell>
     <cell>663</cell>
     <cell>687</cell>
     <cell>24</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>October,</cell>
     <cell>587</cell>
     <cell>770</cell>
     <cell>180(sic)</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>November,</cell>
     <cell>591</cell>
     <cell>791</cell>
     <cell>200</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>December,</cell>
     <cell>622</cell>
     <cell>---</cell>
     <cell>---</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>7422</cell>
     <cell>8467(eleven months)</cell>
     <cell>1045(eleven months)(sic)</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <p>This terrifying increase in our morality cannot be ascribed to an increase in our population. Even if the population were six or seven per cent larger (and <pb facs="5418474_6_0917.jpg" n="3"/>that would probably be a high estimate) the increase in mortality amounts to fifteen or sixteen per cent (sic).</p>
   <p>There is one undeniable fact--instead of becoming cleaner, our city takes on the aspect of a mud pile. The streets are swept but not cleaned; in other words, dirt and manure are swept into the gutter, where they remain and rot. As the city grows, the pollution of the river increases, and now we have an open, stagnant sewer. To this must be added the stench of some six million hogs and cattle which are being slaughtered at the yards, a most odoriferous problem with which we are confronted, even in the northernmost parts of the city, whenever south winds prevail.</p>
   <p>Undoubtedly, the unhealthy conditions now confronting us are attributable to these causes, since a large number of people are dying from diphtheria. The present mortality resulting from this sickness is tremendous.</p>
   <p>Responsibility rests with our city administration. That our streets are not properly cleaned is the administration's fault. The manner in which contractors <pb facs="5418474_6_0918.jpg" n="4"/>are allowed to perform the work is not compatible with intelligence. That the river developed into a cesspool was also the administration's fault. It was negligence--pure and simple--which brought about the present deplorable conditions. At least the north branch of the river could have been cleaned. That the stockyards and lard renderers can overwhelm us with stench may not be entirely the fault of the city officials. Undoubtedly, Dr. De Wolf has the best of intentions in making our slaughterhouses conform to health rules, but he lacks sufficient authority. In connection therewith, it becomes necessary for the public to recognize the danger confronting us, and for strong public opinion to assert proper pressure in order to support the health commissioner in his fight.</p>
   <p>The question is a matter of life and death for Chicago. At the present rate of mortality, we face a declining population.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
