<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-01-28">Jan. 28, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Raid on the Treasury</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-01-28">Jan. 28, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE RAID ON THE TREASURY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In so far as the responsibility for the payment of retroactive pensions is concerned both political parties are at fault, for while the Senate boasts of a Republican majority, the House of Representatives has a greater number of Democratic votes. However the Republicans are chiefly to blame because the President whom they counted into office willingly signed the bill which enabled his party to perpetrate the treacherous act.</p>
   <p>Of course the defenders of the measure assert that it would have been useless for the President--the pitiable wretch--to invoke the power of his veto, because it would have been overruled in both Houses. But this is not necessarily true! Had Hayes possessed the fearlessness of Grant and exposed the planned raid in unequivocal and energetic terms, his veto would not have been ignored.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0298.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the meantime popular opinion had begun to change and to show opposition to the "grab". Consequently the majority of the members of Congress would have been glad to use the President's veto as a lever to extricate themselves from the ensuing responsibility for the swindle--which is on the same level as the infamous "grab law" over which the virtuous supporters of Hayes's twaddle made such a fearful clamor during the last Senatorial election.</p>
   <p>Recently the Westliche Post (Western Post) has been busy heaving brickbats at the "grabbers". Henceforth the Westliche Post may have its babbling Hayes as leader of the "grabbers". After all, the raid which he made possible by signing the pension law will exceed by fifty or one hundred million dollars the amount looted from the treasury in 1873.</p>
   <p>Why, one might ask, are these former "Rebel Democrats" so willing to make such liberal grants and to vote for such munificent appropriations to be used as "tips" for erstwhile "Defenders of the Nation"? The reason is so obvious that <pb facs="5418474_6_0299.jpg" n="3"/>a blind man could see it: "One hand washes the other".</p>
   <p>In other words, if the Democrats help their former enemies of the North to extract generous funds from the Mint now, the ex-rebels will expect similar complaisance when Southern representatives demand millions of dollars for their constituents--in the name of war indemnity.</p>
   <p>The barrel is on tap and now everyone may draw to his heart's content.</p>
   <p>In their endeavor to make themselves as popular as possible Republicans and Democrats will resort to liberality at the expense of the Treasury, which, ultimately, means the taxpayers.</p>
   <p>"Upon sin follows the evil that you fear, Just as peeling onions makes you shed a tear."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0300.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Thus "spake" the Capucinian monk in "Wallenstein's Lager". Thus after the retroactive pension payments are begun, the recognition of Southern "war claims" will follow in quick order. "In quick order" means at the next Congressional session, when it is likely that Hayes will take as little recourse to his veto as he did during the present Congress.</p>
   <p>Thus our national finances face the pleasant prospect of being relegated into abysmal insecurity. That national financial security is available is indicated by the new "grab law, the enforcement of which points to the existence of a much larger sum than the surplus of our regular income provides. But it appears that there will be no trace of such a favorable difference when, in accordance with existing laws, one per cent of the National debt is allocated to the sinking fund.</p>
   <p>To obtain the money required, only two courses can be pursued. A greater income must be provided either by the addition of new taxes or by a loan. Congress <pb facs="5418474_6_0301.jpg" n="5"/>will hardly favor the former; the only alternative is the loan.</p>
   <p>Borrowing can be made an honest procedure by either of two means: the unpopular interest-bearing bonds, or the compulsory non-interest-accumulating loan--in other words, "More paper money!"</p>
   <p>Naturally, the very Democrats who voted for the "grab" can also vote for the latter method and thus the future Congressional decisions will be in favor of more (paper) money, and our Government's financial condition will have again been piloted into a swamp.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
