<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-07-30">July 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">State Rights Versus National Rights</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0370</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0370.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-07-30">July 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">STATE RIGHTS VERSUS NATIONAL RIGHTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Assumption of jurisdiction not only over interstate commerce but also over intrastate business by the Federal Government, was one of the chief reasons why the Supreme Court of the United States declared the NRA to be unconstitutional. That is an age-old object of contention. Again and again the Federal Government has attempted to encroach upon the rights of individual states, and at times has succeeded in doing so with impunity, for where there is no accuser, there can be no judge. In some cases individual states derived certain benefits from these infringements and, of course, entered no protest against the respective laws or measures of the Federal Government. Thus it was inevitable that the sharply defined boundary between the rights of individual states and the rights of the Federal Government gradually vanished.</p>
   <p>The Federal Constitution expressly provides that all rights not accorded the <pb facs="5418474_6_0371.jpg" n="2"/>Federal Government in the Constitution itself are reserved for the states. Formerly the Democratic party was the champion of state rights. It seems the Democrats had acquired a lease on the protection of state prerogatives and they waged bitter war on the Republicans, who were less zealous in defending state rights, whenever the G.O.P. threatened to usurp state authority. Now the Democrats are in power in nearly every state of the Union, but one seldom hears that they protest against usurpation of state rights by the Federal Government.</p>
   <p>Of course, their present attitude emanates from the fact that the Federal Government is so liberal in its appropriation of money for unemployment and direct relief. Every state is trying to gain and keep the good will of the Federal Government in order to obtain as much relief money as possible. They carefully avoid kicking over the traces or opposing Washington's measures, but swallow everything that comes from there, even though the "all-powerful" clerks of the Government treat the representatives of the sovereign states with contempt. And so it must have created no little astonishment in <pb facs="5418474_6_0372.jpg" n="3"/>Washington when the Supreme Court decided that the Federal Government has no right to interfere with the internal affairs of the states; for our national authorities were accustomed to treat state rights as a "negligible quantity". However, the Constitution still guarantees these rights to states, and although the latter may have grown too weak to defend their privileges against the President, the Supreme Court can, and does, offer the necessary protection.</p>
   <p>Meanwhile, there are always two sides to a story. The rights of states are guaranteed by the Constitution. There can be no doubt about that. However, the question may be in order: Does the jealous preservation of state rights serve the best interests of the country, or would it be advantageous to restrict these rights? Naturally, any restriction of state rights would involve a complete change in our present political system. In place of a federation of states the United States would constitute a uniform, centrally organized state, and the present states would be merely provinces within that state. Since there is a general world-wide movement to centralize the governmental powers of large areas, we may benefit if we join the movement. Great <pb facs="5418474_6_0373.jpg" n="4"/>distances separated the various state capitals in our country when most of the individual states were formed. Many days travel was required to get from New York to Chicago, and many weeks to get from Washington to California. Modern transportation has brought the various parts of America much closer to one another. It takes only four days to travel from New York to San Francisco by railroad, and less than a day by airplane. Similar improvement has been made in our postal system. There is overnight service from any point to any point. While we had but a few miles of good highway during the first decades of our country, and traveling was generally done at a great risk of life and limb, there is now a great network of excellent roads from the Atlantic to the Pacific. In the meantime the telephone, telegraph, wireless telegraph, and the radio were invented; in reality distances between states have disappeared and the boundaries dividing the various states do not actually exist for modern means of transportation and communication.</p>
   <p>Under these circumstances it may be well to consider whether the territorial division of our country into states, the resulting selfish attitude of each <pb facs="5418474_6_0374.jpg" n="5"/>state, and the formation of individual interests, do not hamper the free development of commerce, industry, and transportation, and hinder existing business enterprises which serve the general welfare of our people. Sooner or later our nation will have to consider this matter seriously and decide which course it wishes to follow. As we pointed out, however, this decision lies with the people, and not with the Government at Washington. The people are the pillars and guardians of the Constitution, not the Federal Government. Moreover, the Federal Government is the servant of the people, and it should not forget this.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
