<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-30">Aug. 30, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Friendly Admonitions to German Workers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-30">Aug. 30, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">FRIENDLY ADMONITIONS TO GERMAN WORKERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4.. We seriously advise all the German workers of Chicago to abstain from any participation in "Parades of the Unemployed" and to shun meetings on streets and in public places. The experience of the last few days had shown how such "demonstrations" may lead to riots. And in connection therewith, the English speaking press tries with might and main to blame the foreign element.</p>
   <p>Labor papers which have the interest of the workers at heart, also warn against any legal transgressions and emphasize the fact, that any "proletarian policy" which advocates force, is insanity, because it is opposed by a tremendous majority. The alleviation and abolition of the present evils can only be attained through a friendly co-operation between the various classes and through a return of general confidence without which business cannot be adequately revived.</p>
   <p>Disruption of transportation, and violence, only serve to shatter our confidence which retards business and production,and thereby increases unemployment. Neither the administration nor individuals refuse to help the bona fide, starving workers, and measures to cope with the situation are now being <pb facs="5418474_6_0137.jpg" n="2"/>considered.</p>
   <p>The great majority of our German workers do not need this warning from us. But the inexperienced and the excitable ones need this counsel. They must not forget, that by joining such demonstrations they only injure the cause of labor and endanger themselves. We remind the hot-heads and agitators - and this is to their own advantage - to remember the Illinois law whereby any agitator is held responsible for any act of violence attributable to his doctrines; that according to the criminal law he is just as guilty as the actual perpetrator, even if he personally did not commit any overt act.</p>
   <p>If, for example, a murder should be perpetrated as a result of his speeches, he would be held as much responsible as the actual murderer. This law should be taken into consideration and its tragic application in the past should be kept in mind. Agitators beware!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
