<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-09-26">Sept. 26, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Garfield's Grave</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0509</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0509.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-09-26">Sept. 26, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">GARFIELD'S GRAVE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today occurs the interment of a man who has suffered long and uncomplainingly. He will be lowered into the grave which he had selected while in the prime of life. Time and time again he had gone from Mentor to Cleveland to visit Lake-view Cemetery and had declared:</p>
   <p>"Here I want to be buried!"</p>
   <p>Garfield's grave near Lake Erie will be held in the same esteem by future generations as the grave on the Potomac which holds the remains of Washington, or the vault in the Sangamon Valley where Lincoln's body rests. The grave of Garfield is much nearer to his birthplace than the tomb of Washington is to his [native place], which is on the Potomac quite a distance away from Mount <pb facs="5418474_6_0510.jpg" n="2"/>Vernon. [Translator's note: Washington was born at Bridges Creek, near Fredericksburg, in Westmoreland County, Virginia; the distance from his birthplace to his grave is nearly seventy miles along the river.] The hovel where Garfield was born was only a few miles away from the present site of Cleveland. His mother, a woman of intelligence, was a farmer and very poor. Amid such surroundings he spent his childhood; yet his funeral exceeded the homage given to emperors and kings in death. His demise has brought sorrow to a great nation of fifty million people whose leader he became principally through his own efforts and because he deserved it, and today all civilized countries on earth honor the man and express their reverence. Standing before Washington's grave, we are inspired with awe as we remember the character of the great soldier and patriotic citizen, [especially] his sense of duty; in the presence of the mortal remains of Garfield or Lincoln one is swayed by the same emotions as if one were viewing the crypt of a long-departed father or brother. Both these men became thus endeared to us not only through their efforts in the cause of <pb facs="5418474_6_0511.jpg" n="3"/>liberty, their deeds in behalf of the country, and their martyrdom, which in Garfield's case was a long-lingering decline with excruciating pain for eighty days, but because the character of these heroic Americans also appeal to us. The one showed homely humor which often asserted itself on the most tragic occasions. The other led an ideal, exemplary family life; his speeches, his expressions of sentiment when important matters of state were at stake, proved classic gems of rhetoric, and such qualifications have brought their reward.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
