<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-08">Nov. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Health Examinations in the Schools</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0876</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0876.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-08">Nov. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">HEALTH EXAMINATIONS IN THE SCHOOLS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are many parents of school children, not only in Chicago but all over the country, who disapprove of the health examinations given their children in the schools, though this practice is coming more and more into vogue.</p>
   <p>They would not object to examinations for diphtheria, measles, and other contagious diseases, if these examinations were thorough and were made by competent physicians, and if they were not bothered unnecessarily by incorrect diagnoses, while, on the other hand, really contagious cases are often ignored until they have progressed so far that damage has already been done.</p>
   <p>These complaints are and will always be justified as long as politics plays a dominant part in this extremely important function; as long as the objective seems to be to provide applicants with well-paid positions in the <pb facs="5418474_6_0877.jpg" n="2"/>Board of Health for which most of them lack the necessary qualifications, while others, who are qualified, do their work in the superficial way which is typical of political job holders, who consider their position, obtained through favors and influence, as a profitable side line. If the condition of the children's health is to be tested, it should be done thoroughly, not only for contagious diseases but also for a predisposition to any other disease. A child of the healthiest parents may have defects of which the parents are unaware, and which, if recognized in time, can be corrected by medical science. But where there is evidence of a hereditary disease of which the parents themselves did not know, this information will serve to call their attention to their predisposition to an ailment, and they themselves will undergo a physical examination and, if necessary, resort to treatment under the direction of a physician.</p>
   <p>In the state of New York, Dr. G. M. Retan examined 1450 school children by order of the School Board of Solvay and found among them fourteen with infected lungs and a tendency to tuberculosis, a fact which the parents of <pb facs="5418474_6_0878.jpg" n="3"/>these children did not know. In his opinion, such defects in children are almost without exception curable if discovered early enough.</p>
   <p>The amount saved to each community, and thereby to the whole country by the early recognition and cure of such diseases, and the prevention of their spread, cannot be estimated.</p>
   <p>Dr. Retan's only regret is that these examinations are conducted in a too superficial manner in most schools of the country. He says that a stripping of the upper body was required in only fifteen out of fifty-eight schools. In sixty-three schools the examination was a farce, consisting merely of the filling out of a questionnaire. And in case a physician should go to the trouble of putting his stethoscope on any spot covered by clothes, the latter might be the cause of all kinds of misleading sounds.</p>
   <p>Efforts will have to be made to remove all politics from the boards of health, which are so important, and to secure competent practitioners. If this cannot be done, expenditures should be limited to a minimum and the burden on the <pb facs="5418474_6_0879.jpg" n="4"/>taxpayer should be eased by economy in this field. As the situation is now, health examinations in the schools accomplish only a small fraction of what is expected of them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
