<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-08-25">Aug. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Child Labor</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0064</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0064.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-08-25">Aug. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CHILD LABOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the present time, there is pending in Congress a bill drawn up and prepared by Representative Edward Keating and Professor Thomas I. Parkinson of Columbia University, the enactment of which would be highly desirable in the interest of child welfare. It provides, as a war measure, that children under fourteen years of age shall not be allowed to work in industry, that the work period for children between the ages of fourteen and sixteen must not exceed eight hours a day in the factories, and it also prohibits the employment of children under sixteen years of age in mines and stone quarries.</p>
   <p>These provisions are identical with those contained in a Federal child welfare law which the Supreme Court recently has declared unconstitutional. In order that the present bill shall not encounter a similar <pb facs="5418474_6_0065.jpg" n="2"/>fate, it is being proposed as a war measure, since Congress undoubtedly has the power to enact such measures. Friends of child welfare hope that the Federal government will support the enactment of such a bill, inasmuch as many young children have returned to work since the Supreme Court rendered the above-mentioned decision. They were either attracted by high wages or had to go to work in order to meet the increased cost of living. In many States, where no age limit prevails, school attendance has dropped considerably.</p>
   <p>In justification of the proposed bill it is said that it is not only designed to protect children from working at too early an age and for excessively long hours, but also to preserve national health and vitality. Children who are deprived of the opportunity to acquire a school education and to develop normally will some day make inferior citizens, mentally and physically.</p>
   <p>The passage of the Keating bill will, for the time being, stop the exploitation <pb facs="5418474_6_0066.jpg" n="3"/>of children. In the meantime, the National Child Labor Committee, in conjunction with the American Federation of Labor, will attempt to draw up a Federal law which will meet all the objections raised by the Supreme Court. After the previous law was invalidated, opponents of such legislation claimed that child protection was a matter for the separate States and should be left for them to handle. A few weeks later, an opportunity presented itself to test the validity of this claim. In the Georgia legislature, a bill was submitted the provisions of which conformed substantially with those of the rejected Federal law. The bill was severely condemned on all sides, and the committee which was considering the measure shelved it by a vote of nine to one. This result, as well as the fate of previous attempts, proves that effective child protection can hardly be accomplished by the various States, that the enactment of Federal laws is necessary. The new bill has been brought to the attention of President Wilson and, according to reports, has met with his complete approval.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
