<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-07-21">July 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The World's Fair</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Speckhardt Clock in the German House a Most Remarkable Work of Art at the Fair</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1483</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1483.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-07-21">July 21, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORLD'S FAIR</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Speckhardt Clock in the German House A Most Remarkable Work of Art at the Fair</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Daily from 11 A.M. until 4 P.M. hundreds of people assemble at the Southern side Chapel of the German House, to view one of the greatest art productions that the World's Fair contains. This is the clock build by Mr. Gustav Speckhardt, the court clock-maker of Prince Alfons of Bavaria, that is here since the opening of the fair, but suffered so much during transportation, that only until a week ago it was possible to make it work. Two things are to be admired on this clock: the case and the mechanism. The first is a wonderful structure, a masterpiece of the wood carving art. It is hard for the onlooker to believe that this is a creation of a newer date; one is more inclined to suppose that this wonderful structure, kept in the old Gothic style, comes from the fourteenth century.</p>
   <p>The substructure stands on a low pedestal and is carried by snails and turtles, <pb facs="5418474_6_1484.jpg" n="2"/>the heads of the latter actually move. Around the pedestal is a gallery decorated in the center by an eagle, fixed in Hupp's way. The eagle with Patrona Maria on its chest symbolizes the State of Bavaria and its patron-saint. Further, we see at the gallery the escutcheons of Bavaria and of the United States of North America, also at the right and left coats of arms with the colors of Nuremberg and Mount Kofel, near Oberammergau. Into this pedestal are also inlaid two beautifully etched tablets, containing the wonderful song of E. Von Destouches, "The Salute of the Cross," which refers to the escutcheon with Mount Kofel and is lettered in excellent old Gothic characters. In the interior of the pedestal are the works of an organ. On the middle structure we see the old testament represented by Moses and the Jewish prophets. A gallery-like embrace is drawn over these figures, whose Gothic designs carry various forms.</p>
   <p>But the chief points of interest for the visitor develop themselves above this gallery. In a stage-like niche is shown to us the entire history of Christ's passion, in the form of the Oberammergau passion play, so divided <pb facs="5418474_6_1485.jpg" n="3"/>into groups that after every hour a new group appears in the niche, starting at the "entry of Christ into Jerusalem" to the "Resurrection." The figures of all these groups move and the organ plays a hymn relating to the scene. All of the figures of the passion play were made by so-called "Herrgott Schnitzers" (Lord God Carvers) and therefore represent an originality on the clock.</p>
   <p>To the left and right we see the exhibition of two oriental street views in splendid sculpture of Heinrich Blab which were glazed by the painter Wilhelm Ritter. The perspective effect is masterly. Below the street pictures we read in the Latin language: "If thou hast only perceived on this thine day, what serves thee to thy peace!" On pillars stand the apostles Peter, Paul, James and John as representatives of the new testament. Tower-like rises the clock house over the center niche. Here is the dial face with the sun in the center; on the hands are the moon and the stars. Below the dial we see on a fluttering ribbon the year numbers 1492 and 1892. In the left corner we notice a part of the globe, on which is etched the word "Amerika"; at the right, Columbus, standing in a little boat. A handsome, striking clock is contained in a separate <pb facs="5418474_6_1486.jpg" n="4"/>little tower. It carries the words, on the side of the death which strikes the quarter hours, "As the thief in the night." (Added: So comes the hour of death:) On the side of the angel which strikes the full hours, we read: "Estote Parati" (Be ready). At the top of the little tower is the cock, announcing the morning and evening by loud crowing. As a crowning feature of the work, there rises 15 feet high, the "Last Judgment" represented by three angels playing trumpets. Instead of the hand indicating the seconds is used the "Egg of Columbus" which grows out of a flower. It is represented by a regular chicken's egg and makes one full turn every minute. The case contains fourteen clock works, from the big tower clock-work to the small watch-work, and the creation as a whole is designed and executed in all its details by the above-mentioned Mr. Speckhardt. The architecture for it was created by Mr. Clemens Kessler, and the sculptural works were modeled and carved by the sculptor, Mr. Blab. The work of the carpenter is excellent, and so is the painting. The entire work is an outstanding work of art and is continuously beseiged by visitors. In order to give everybody a chance to see the wonderful <pb facs="5418474_6_1487.jpg" n="5"/>mechanism function, the work is wound up at intervals of one hour.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
