<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-07-22">July 22, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Northwest Teachers Conference.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1012</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1012.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-07-22">July 22, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">NORTHWEST TEACHERS CONFERENCE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Teachers Conference started yesterday in the assembly hall of the German Lutheran Church "Holy Cross", located on Ullmann Street. The President of the conference, Fr. Rush, addressed, as usually, his numerous assembled colleagues. After explaining the purpose of the meeting, he exhorted them to "prove everything", and to "hold fast to that which is good".</p>
   <p>"We are meeting here at our annual conference to become more efficient, capable in our vocation, and also more alert, enthusiastic and refreshed for the discharge of our duties, by mutual consultation, discussion, and advice...."</p>
   <p>After the speaker concluded, the teachers immediately elected their officers. The result was as follows: Fr. Rush, President; H. Ruhland, Vice President; S. Ritzman, Secretary; and L. H. Gilster, Assistant Secretary.</p>
   <p>The first review for general discussion was teacher Lampe's question: "What should be the teachers aims in teaching biblical history?....</p>
   <p>During the afternoon the report of Mr. Decker, a teacher, was discussed. <pb facs="5418474_6_1013.jpg" n="2"/>The topic was: "Hew do you keep your lowest class in arithmetic constantly employed?" A lively debate followed which was carried on in English.</p>
   <p>Today and tomorrow two tests of teaching will be demonstrated before the conference, and several educational tasks will be discussed. P. Miller of Schaumburg will lecture to-night at the Holy Cross Church to the teachers of the conference.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
