<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-26">Apr. 26, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">German-American Educators' Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1025</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1025.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-04-26">Apr. 26, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN-AMERICAN EDUCATORS' DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The local committee of the 19th German-American Educators' Day, proposed for July 9, held a meeting yesterday afternoon at the Deutsche Gesellschaft.</p>
   <p>During this meeting an appeal was adopted, which will be made known to all Germans in the city by means of circulars and the press. The appeal reads thus:</p>
   <p>"To the German people of Chicago! The 19th annual convention of the National German-American Educators' Day, will be held in Chicago from July 9 to July 12.</p>
   <p>Questions will be dealt with which are of utmost importance to all Germans.</p>
   <p>The entire nation is showing such a hostility towards German achievements <pb facs="5418474_6_1026.jpg" n="2"/>that we have perfectly justified grounds for apprehension.</p>
   <p>German education has been abolished in the public schools of two important cities; in other places similar attacks were frustrated, but it can be expected that new attempts in this direction will follow.</p>
   <p>Therefore, it seems our duty to stand unanimously for the preservation of our present achievement, and not to relax our defense of what is acknowledged as right and good.</p>
   <p>The convention of the German-American Educators' Bund should be formed into an impressive manifestation of public opinion from this city, which boasts of having more students of the German language in the public schools than any other city in America.</p>
   <p>As this matter is of interest to all, the local committee is asking that <pb facs="5418474_6_1027.jpg" n="3"/>all those who seriously want to support German education in the school and home to do so with advice, assistance, visits to the meetings for necessary preparations, and doing their utmost to make this convention a complete success."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
