<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-17">Feb. 17, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Arizona</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Chicago Mining and Milling Company, an Explanation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1342</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1342.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-17">Feb. 17, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">ARIZONA</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Chicago Mining and Milling Company, An Explanation</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many inquiries of late convince me that the public in general is not informed about the agreements I made with the owners of mines in the Globe District, and which I designated as property of the Chicago Mining and Milling Company; and therefore I consider it expedient to make the following explanation.</p>
   <p>My agreement with Messrs. Buck and Hayse, discoverers and owners of the twenty-one silver mines described in the "Prospectus of the Chicago Mining and Milling Company," is officially recorded in Florence, Pinal County, Arizona. The contract specifies that title to the aforesaid mines, including all improvements, buildings, ores, tools, etc., as of November 14, last year, shall be transferred by warranty deed to the Chicago Mining and Milling Company, as soon as a ten-unit ore crusher and reduction plant has been erected in or near Globe City by the Chicago <pb facs="5418474_6_1343.jpg" n="2"/>Mining and Milling Company, whereupon the entire mining and milling property will become the property of the Company.</p>
   <p>Messrs. Buck and Hayse own one half of the Company's bonds. The mines are already regarded by Messrs. Buck and Hayse as Company property, and all ore mined belongs to the Company, which intends to exploit this natural wealth for the benefit of the bondholders as soon as the reduction plant is established.</p>
   <p>I hope this explanation will dispel all doubts about the true ownership of the mines enumerated in the "Prospectus of the Chicago Mining and Milling Company," and that hereby it is definitely proved that the Chicago Mining and Milling Company is the true owner.</p>
   <p>A. C. Hesing</p>
   <p>Chicago, Feb. 15, 1879.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
