<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-09-04">Sept. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Technologists Arrange Family Evening at Germania Club.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0953</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0953.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-09-04">Sept. 4, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">TECHNOLOGISTS ARRANGE FAMILY EVENING AT GERMANIA CLUB.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A pleasant family evening with music and dancing opened the 43rd annual meeting of the German-American Union of Technologists, last night in the club rooms of the Technical Society of Chicago, at the Germania Club. A great number of delegates from abroad were present. The evening was spent in animated conversation with humor and merriment prevailing, so that, in spite of the bad weather, the opening of the four-day convention turned out all right.</p>
   <p>A meeting of delegates was held this morning at 10 o'clock at the club rooms of the society, with a dinner following. Tonight, at 8 o'clock in the Germania Club, a late summer-night dance will be given.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0954.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The program for Sunday and Monday is as follows: Sunday, 12 o'clock noon, lunch at the Edgewater Beach Hotel; 2 p. m., picnic in Glen Oak Acres; supper in the Lincoln Turner Hall. Monday (Labor Day): 11 a. m., Technologist Day, lecture by Professor Adolf Carl Noe of the University of Chicago, on the subject: "The origin of our technical source of energy." Ladies are cordially invited; 2 p. m., round trip through the park system of Chicago; 7 p. m., farewell dinner-dance at the Rainbow Gardens, will close the four-day convention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
