<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Fackel</title>,
<date when="1884-04-13">Apr. 13, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">(The Drama)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1677</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1677.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Fackel</title>,
<date when="1884-04-13">Apr. 13, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">(THE DRAMA)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About the last guest appearance of Magda Irschick, in the dramatic piece, which will be given to-night in Mc Vickers, the following has been written: From the emotional life of Gustav Wasa, B. Scholz, the author, has only written a small but deeply felt episode, and with the hand of a real poet, transformed it into the dramatic play: "Mask for Mask".</p>
   <p>He chooses a time, when Gustav Wasa, liberated almost the whole of Sweden from the Danes. Only Stockholm withstood the seige. Besides the nobility of Westgothland, which greatly sympathized with the Danes, the work of liberation has been greatly retarded. Therefore Gustav Wasa decided, un known by them, to appear personally among these stubborn nobles with the intention of not only feeling their tooth, but also to draw them himself. He selects for this purpose, the Castle Grip. Its master Nils Gyllensterna and his pretty sisters, Anna and Friederike, are secretly sympathetic with the Swedes, but afraid to show it to the powerful and treacherous nobles, therefore they wear the Danish Mask. Into this family comes Gustave Wasa, <pb facs="5418474_6_1678.jpg" n="2"/>in the "mask of a Danish Officer and now begins between them a peculiar act of mutual sounding and personal temptation. The more open Wasa dares to be, the more cautiously is he answered, with Danish sentiments, and soon it comes to an open rupture with the Lord of the Manor, to whom this Danish spy has long become a burden. Anna with whom Wasa has fallen in love, dares to pretend, under the mask of a fable, to relate the life story and bravery of Gustav Wasa. This scene is the pearl of the play, and saturated with such deep poesic and grace, that modern dramatic literature can show very few similar acts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
