<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-12-13">Dec. 13, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">The War of Culture</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0590</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0590.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-12-13">Dec. 13, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">THE WAR OF CULTURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If--and there appears to be no doubt--it was President Grant's intention to make the so-called fight for culture a burning question of American party politics, then one may declare with positive conviction that his attempt was a dismal failure.</p>
   <p>What he said in a very choppy, almost schoolboyish manner about the segregation of church and state--the restriction of religion as well as irreligion in public affairs--left the nation indifferent. It incited neither intense opposition nor enthusiastic approval.</p>
   <p>The proposal to add an amendment to the Constitution to insure against a hierarchic control of schools meets with approval in all newspapers regardless of party affiliation, but none deal with the matter as if it were urgent or the peril imminent.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0591.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Blaine's amendment will probably not arouse opposition, and, if it does, the objections are not likely to develop into a religious controversy; the proposal will be restricted instead to matters of form involving constitutional law.</p>
   <p>As far as this question is concerned, an open split between the two political parties will not materialize.</p>
   <p>The two other proposals of the President--taxation of church property and the restriction of the voting privilege to those persons who are literate--prompt one to believe that Mr. Grant knows little more about the dictates of the Constitution than those German newspaper writers who asked him recently to settle a dispute over the election of an Episcopal bishop in New York by taking recourse to the official presidential powers, obviously in the manner of Ludwig of Bavaria.</p>
   <p>We heartily approve of the taxing of church property (even if it is worth <pb facs="5418474_6_0592.jpg" n="3"/>only three hundred million rather than one billion dollars), but any child should know that this is a matter with which the National Government has nothing to do. Taxation of real estate is under the jurisdiction of the states alone. The Government and the President have as little to do with it as with the management of the waterworks or the construction of a city hall for Chicago. According to the Constitution of the United States there is no connecting link which would permit the extension of national authority to tax affairs such as this. What Mr. Grant says can, at most, be regarded as advice to the political factions to include the taxation of churches in their state programs. But such suggestions are out of place in the Government's annual report.</p>
   <p>The same applies to restrictions in the election laws. No question involving the American Constitution has been settled more definitely within the last decade than this: The granting or revocation of voting rights is exercised by the separate states; it is not a government function.</p>
   <p>The Nation made no attempt to influence this voting right in any manner, except <pb facs="5418474_6_0593.jpg" n="4"/>by its stipulation that, if any state abolishes the voting privilege of its inhabitants on the grounds of race, color, or former position (slavery), that state's representation in Congress will be reduced in direct proportion to the number of disfranchised voters. This is the only power vested in the Government with respect to the ballot.</p>
   <p>The right of the individual states to deny citizens access to the voting booths--if they are illiterate--is already in existence, and the Government lacks authority to interfere.</p>
   <p>Thus Mr. Grant's proposals, presumably, will be just as ineffective as the crazy financial schemes of his predecessor, Johnson.</p>
   <p>If movements which correspond to the afore-mentioned suggestions should develop in the various states, they will not be founded on this year's message of President Grant; his annual message will have been forgotten by that time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
