<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-17">Feb. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">In the Interest of Public Health</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0859</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0859.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-17">Feb. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE INTEREST OF PUBLIC HEALTH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anyone who has eyes to see and ears to hear will not be disturbed by the report issued by the Federal Bureau of Markets, stating that about six billion cans of preserved foods are annually consumed by American families, even though the average is about fifty cans per person. These figures do not include milk, fish, and the various kinds of meats that may be bought in cans and need only to be heated before serving. The official statistics include only fruits and vegetables, and the average of fifty cans per person by no means indicates the great amount of canned food that annually finds its way into the stomachs of Uncle Sam's children.</p>
   <p>At the same time this report gives us "food for thought" when it reveals that the use of this kind of food has increased from ten to fifty cans per person <pb facs="5418474_6_0860.jpg" n="2"/>during the past twenty-five years. Will the American people finally consume only canned goods and permit the noble art of cooking to vanish from their homes?</p>
   <p>The respective authorities at Washington evidently foresee such a possibility, for they insist that more laws be enacted for the protection of food and for more severe punishment of those who manufacture or sell impure foods.</p>
   <p>It is not news that large quantities of food must be seized and destroyed because it is spoiled, but that unscrupulous and greedy merchants, nevertheless, try to sell it to gullible customers, although state or government inspectors watch them very closely.</p>
   <p>Apparently the maximum punishment provided for by the present laws is not severe enough to protect the American public from these attacks upon its health, and the proposals to enact stricter legislation, deserve ample <pb facs="5418474_6_0861.jpg" n="3"/>consideration. This is especially desirable since the firms which make it their object to dispense only wholesome canned food are the most ardent advocates of strict control over their business.</p>
   <p>Since the industry has succeeded in accustoming the public to its canned food, the demand that this food be of the best kind is only just. Of course, that does not mean that they are to offer more competition to the adherents of "home cooking", which is still in vogue among the majority of our German families.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
