<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-09-18">Sep. 18, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Bach Society.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1544</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1544.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-09-18">Sep. 18, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO BACH SOCIETY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago now has a Bach society. Music director Wilhelm Boeppler will conduct the choir.</p>
   <p>From 160 to 170 singers registered, after 18 months of hard preparatory work. The Chicago Bach Society was founded on Sep. 15. The executive committee consists of the following prominent personalities:</p>
   <p>President: Wilh. Schlake, president of the Illinois Brick Co.</p>
   <p>Vice President: Theo. Fashauer, President of "The Theo. Fashauer Lumber Co.</p>
   <p>Cashier: Wilh. Schulze, President of the Calumet Trust &amp; Savings Bank.</p>
   <p>Paul Schulze, Pres. of the Paul Schulze Biscuit Co.</p>
   <p>Dr. Fr. Ofotenhauer, Pres. of the Lutheran Missouri Synod.</p>
   <p>Prof. John Hattstaedt, Pres. of the American conservatory of Music.</p>
   <p>Gustave Fleischer, Editor of the Concordia monthly periodical.</p>
   <p>The following Bach enthusiasts belong to the committee: Dr. Theo. Poderlein, Professors M. Lochuer and Paul Boster of the River Forest Normal college; <pb facs="5418474_6_1545.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. R. List, Pastor Paul, Mrs. Arthur Bauermeister, Mrs. Albert Seidel, Miss E. Hanning, Pastor P. Sauer.</p>
   <p>The task of the Bach society is to present to the Chicago public all the unknown Cantatas of Bach. Of Bach's 295 Cantatas, only 215 can be found. Until the present time, no choir has ever performed even half of these unsurpassable works of art, with the exception of the Thoman Society of Leipzig, Germany. In all countries of Europe Bach Societies, can now be found, but up to the present time, only one in America, the Bethlehem Bach Chor, with Mr. Schwab as president. The newly organized Chicago Bach Society is the second in America, but the only one which will sing the Bach Cantatas in the German language.</p>
   <p>Director Boeppler has selected a few excellent Cantatas to be presented at Orchestra Hall next spring.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
