<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-09-22">Sept. 22, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Mourns, Garfield Dead</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0530</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0530.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-09-22">Sept. 22, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO MOURNS, GARFIELD DEAD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note: On the day of President Garfield's death and on the day following every column of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung was heavily bordered in black. A few editorials expressing the same opinions which previously had been uttered have not been translated. Only German items are given.]</p>
   <p>Resolutions</p>
   <p>The Chicago Turngemeinde [Gymnastic Association] passed the following resolutions at yesterday's session:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, the tragic announcement has been made that President James A. Garfield has finally succumbed; and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, James A. Garfield was the man who at the helm of the Republic did during the short period in which he held office best conform by his administration <pb facs="5418474_6_0531.jpg" n="2"/>to our conception of a democratic form of government; be it therefore</p>
   <p>"Resolved, that we regard the death of the President as a misfortune for the nation, and that we feel profound sympathy for his bereaved family; and be it further</p>
   <p>"Resolved, that we hope that the new President, Chester A. Arthur, will continue the policies pursued by his exemplary predecessor, who, unfortunately has been called to the world beyond before his time, and that the nation will be blessed by enduring peace and prosperity."</p>
   <p>The Hermannssoehne [Sons of Hermann], who are holding their fifteenth national convention at this time, honored the deceased President by adopting the following resolution.</p>
   <p>"What every one expected, though all hoped that it might be avoided, has happened after all. President Garfield is not among us any more. Removed from <pb facs="5418474_6_0532.jpg" n="3"/>his sphere of activity by an assassin's hand, his is mourned by the people of the United States, who remember the President's great qualifications and render their last respects to the leader who so fully deserves them. Through his own efforts, energy, and perseverance he rose from modest circumstances to the highest office in the Republic, and it would not be an exaggeration to declare, that through his death the nation has lost not only a good citizen and a genuine patriot but also a most capable and faithful official, in short, one of its most intellectual and most eminent statesmen. We feel deeply the loss incurred by the nation in his decease and as citizens of the Republic, as men of German descent, and as members of the order of Hermannssoehne now holding their fifteenth convention in Chicago, we hereby express our profound grief and sympathy to the bereaved family of the President.</p>
   <p>"We also hereby decree that the lodges and great lodges of our Order shall drape their charters for thirty days with black cloth as a symbol of our sorrow.</p>
   <p>"Furthermore, be it resolved that these resolutions are adopted by the convention <pb facs="5418474_6_0533.jpg" n="4"/>now in session, and that they shall be published in English and German newspapers. In making these declarations we are motivated by our profound sympathy for the President's grief-stricken family and by our regard for the liberal institutions of our adopted country."</p>
   <p>Notice</p>
   <p>[Various non-German items omitted.] The Hermannssoehne have decided not to give the dance at the close of their convention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
