<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1862-03-15">Mar. 15, 1862</date>.
<title level="a">Concerning the Rifles of the Home Guard</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0636</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0636.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1862-03-15">Mar. 15, 1862</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERNING THE RIFLES OF THE HOME GUARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Editor of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung: After an article appeared in your newspaper stating that the rifles which the Home Guard received from Springfield are poorly constructed and dangerous, and since I take an active interest in the safety of the public as well as in the safety of the Home Guard, I requested the Mayor of this City to investigate the weapons.</p>
   <p>From his report on this matter I conclude that the guns are of good quality and are in good condition. They are similar to the rifles which are used in the regular infantry of the German Army, and if all the soldiers of the United States Army are equipped with arms as good as the ones which were recently received from Springfield, they are well armed indeed.</p>
   <p>Fellow Citizens! We appeal to you and ask that you organize military companies not just to play soldier, but to be prepared in case of necessity. Our volunteer army is on the battlefield, and although news of victory comes from <pb facs="5418474_6_0637.jpg" n="2"/>every part of the country, we are no better prepared to meet an emergency in Chicago now than we were in March, 1861. Let everyone who would contribute his might to the great cause of liberty sign a list of volunteers.</p>
   <p>Lists may be found at the following places: Mr. Huhn, corner Wells and Illinois Streets; Mr. Moeckel, German House; Krieger and Brinckmeyer, German House; Schartz's Saloon, North Clark Street; Brandt's Saloon, North Clark Street; F. Schlund, 146 Indiana Street; Pfeiffer's Saloon, Madison Street;</p>
   <p>As soon as the necessary number of men have volunteered, a meeting will be held to make further arrangements for organization.</p>
   <p>By order of the Committee,</p>
   <p>F. Schlund,</p>
   <p>Secretary pro tempore</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
