<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-11-09">Nov. 9, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">German Citizens, Attend the Mass Meeting!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0683</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0683.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-11-09">Nov. 9, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN CITIZENS, ATTEND THE MASS MEETING!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is hardly necessary to remind our readers that it is very desirable that today's German demonstration for Fremont be as imposing as possible. Without the help of the Germans Mr. Lincoln would not be sitting in the White House now; had it not been for the votes of the Germans Mr. Lincoln would never have entered the White House as President; and had it not been for the German soldiers he would have fled his palatial abode long ago. Thus the Germans have every right to express themselves freely concerning Mr. Lincoln's political or martial edicts.</p>
   <p>As good citizens of this country we cannot, and shall not, rebel against the President's decree which relieved Fremont of his command; but it is our right and duty to publicly express our sincere regret at the Administration's treatment of Mr. Fremont, a champion of the Union and of liberty, and an upright and unprejudiced friend of the Germans. It is also our right and our duty to <pb facs="5418474_6_0684.jpg" n="2"/>protest publicly against the half measures of the Administration and the indecision which characterizes the steps the Government has taken against the Rebels. We need not permit ourselves to be diverted from exercising our rights by the croaking of a servile and corruptible Government press which condemns us as disloyal citizens because we protest the ruinous policy of the Administration. We criticize the Administration because it offers too little resistance against the Rebels, not because it opposes them too forcefully. But who is truly loyal: he who seeks to instill in the President the courage and energy necessary to subdue the Rebels, or he who servilely supports the President's policy, which is very detrimental to the cause of the Union, merely to obtain political patronage? Any honest German, be he Republican or Democrat, can easily answer this question. Therefore, all ye Germans, attend the Fremont meeting!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
