<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-03-02">March 2nd, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">German Paintings Speech of Prof. Krager and Exposition in the Art Institute.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1782</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1782.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1907-03-02">March 2nd, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN PAINTINGS SPEECH OF PROF. KRAGER AND EXPOSITION IN THE ART INSTITUTE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The French art is so well represented in the United States of America that one almost can make better studies here than in France, Professor Krager said last night at the beginning of his speech, he made in the Germania Clubhouse about the present German art of paintings. It is regrettable that we cannot say the same of the German art and even the exposition opened yesterday in the institution of art of the works of living German artists can not claim perfection and completion. It must be considered that the promoter notwithstanding his German name Knotz is a real American, who cannot speak German and can only deal with the German artists by the use of an interpeter, which makes matters very difficult, so that several of the artists had to leave him. However the exposition must be considered as a deserving experiment, a good beginning, as a first drink from the fountain, which may lead to further encouragement. Prof. Krager told his listeners that he will meet them next Friday evening at 8 o'clock in the art institute and conduct them through the exhibition. Anybody who wishes to see the exhibition under his guidance is welcome. Prof. Krager <pb facs="5418474_6_1783.jpg" n="2"/>represented some lantern slides of the best German artists and their works; among them pictures of members of the Worpsweder Artists Association, mostly sceneries of Mackensen, Moderson, Fogler, Overbeck, etc. Following were some animal sketches of the best living animal painter in Germany, Zuegel. The modern painting in the nude was represented by the works of Ludwig von Hoffmann and a number of paintings by Uhde, the modern, religious painter. The exhibition in the Art Institute consists of 93 paintings and is shown till the 24th of March.</p>
   <p>All works are for sale and 71 have been already sold.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
