<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-27">Aug. 27, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The President and the Nation</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0534</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0534.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-27">Aug. 27, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">THE PRESIDENT AND THE NATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is no hope for President Garfield; death is inevitable according to the physicians and may occur before the readers see these lines. It is a tragic occurence which will arouse the imagination even of future generations, just as we at present stand aghast before the calamity which has stricken the nation. The sentiments which prevailed fifty-six days ago, when the assassin fired the fatal shot, will hardly manifest themselves with the same intensity at this time because during this long period the President's condition has fluctuated constantly, and so the conviction has grown that death would ensue. The difference in the people's reaction on July 2 and today is comparable to the difference between losing a loved one suddenly through a heart attack and losing him after a lingering illness, such as consumption. In the latter case one experiences profound grief instead of sudden shock. Only eight weeks ago sympathy for the injured man <pb facs="5418474_6_0535.jpg" n="2"/>was still mingled with fury against the assassin. Since that time the latter has been almost completely forgotten, and attention has centered on the President's condition, as he has gradually grown weaker, and on the stupidity of his doctors. And so the inconsolable grief finally manifests itself which grips parents at the death of a beloved child, a strain which is relieved only when they finally exclaim:</p>
   <p>"Thy will be done!"</p>
   <p>But regardless of how deeply the people will be moved by Garfield's death, and how well justified their grief will be, it would be fallacious to assume that his departure will affect the economic condition of the country. Such apprehensions show little knowledge of the basic principles which control our nation. If a President of the United States dies, even if he were the best one the nation had ever had, then it would not have the same effect as when a European ruler passes away. Should the successor--and even that does not happen abroad--make far-reaching changes in the personnel and the policy <pb facs="5418474_6_0536.jpg" n="3"/>[of the Government], then only the dismissed officials suffer, whereas the country as a whole is not aware of any particular change. Everything proceeds in a quiet and orderly manner as before. Even if Arthur becomes the victim of an assassin, and the Senate selects a Democrat to fill the vacancy [in the Vice-president's office], the relations of the national administration with industry and with our national economy will not be noticeably changed. Even a Democratic President, not to mention Arthur, would not touch our financial administration as bequeathed to us by Sherman and Garfield. Anyway, Windom, who was overcautious, called for the immediate redemption of the five-per-cent bonds which do not mature until October 1, to preclude the possibility of his successor's being tempted to try a financial policy which might prove disastrous.</p>
   <p>The successful move to [obtain legal authority] to convert the 5 and 6-per-cent Government bonds into a 31/2-per-cent issue at the Government's discretion will be recognized as the outstanding achievement of President Garfield's six months [in office], his trivial errors, such as giving jobs to new officials, will <pb facs="5418474_6_0537.jpg" n="4"/>be completely obliterated. Future political developments depend on Congress, regardless of whether Arthur or Garfield is President, and the membership of that body will not be changed by Garfield's death.</p>
   <p>Economic conditions, either good or bad, will develop irrespective of who occupies the White House. Whether the gamblers on the New York Stock Exchange or the speculators in meat and grain in Chicago will bring about another depression, or even a crash--these questions will remain quite independent of the President's life or death. Industry, the real productive activity in the United States, is in a healthy condition, in spite of the failure of the wheat crop. The nation is in better condition than it has been for years, and the foundation for our present status is not a direct result of politics; a change in our leaders has even less influence. But since the death of the President cannot impair the welfare of the nation, the sympathy and sorrow expressed by the people is not based on selfish motives. The grief over his tragic end is genuine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
