<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1929-01-27">Jan. 27, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">German Artist Exhibits His Pictures at Kroch's</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1776</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1776.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1929-01-27">Jan. 27, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN ARTIST EXHIBITS HIS PICTURES AT KROCH'S</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The young German artist, Otto Reimer Nichuhr, who exhibits a collection of pencil sketches, pastels, and oils at Kroch's Book Store is greatly admired by friends of fine arts.</p>
   <p>Nicbuhr was born in Hamburg and acquired his artistical education in his home town and Munich. He has been in America for the last two years. He has become well known after his extensive travels in America and Mexico. His main productions is landscape paintings. He is not very original, but very true to life in the details of his subjects. The pastel drawing of the chapel of the Graceland Cemetary, an extraordinarily impressive picture, has already found a buyer. The drawing of the Navy Pier is also one of his best pictures and both are exhibited at Kroch's. Here he did as well with the colors as the reproduction of the whole picture, an extremely fortunate grasp, it appears to be so realistic that one can imagine of actually standing on the pier while looking at this extraordinary picture. More pictures are those of the Tribune Tower, Sunrise in Chicago, Sunset on Crooked Lake, and many more.</p>
   <p>All pictures and sketches reveal a strong talent, which arouses the greatest expectations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
