<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-25">Aug. 25, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Arthur and Davis</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_0545</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-25">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_0545.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-25">Aug. 25, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">ARTHUR AND DAVIS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Garfield is near death. Any hour now may bring the news of his demise. An entire nation awaits with bated breath the last moment--the end of his long and heroic fight for life. The number of those still expressing hope is very much reduced. Secretary of State Blaine is not among them.</p>
   <p>We must therefore come to the realization of the fact that Arthur will be President of the United States within a few days, a possibility which probably did not occur to any one at the Republican convention which nominated him for Vice-president to appease Conklin, the vanquished enemy.</p>
   <p>But if Arthur ascends to the presidency, who will be Vice-president? According to the Constitution the President pro tem of the Senate is next in succession, and then the Speaker of the House of Representatives. But at <pb facs="5418474_6_0546.jpg" n="2"/>present we have neither one nor the other. The Senate, because of the peculiar proportionment of the two political parties, has not yet settled the question, and so the President of the Senate has not been elected; and the House of Representatives has not been in session and therefore could not have elected a Speaker.</p>
   <p>If Arthur immediately called a special session, then the Democrats in the Senate would have a majority before the successors of Conklin and Platt were admitted. Perhaps the Democrats would not use this opportunity but would await the arrival of Messrs. Lapham and Miller. But if Mahone of Virginia sides with the Republicans as before, and Davies of Illinois still sticks to the Democrats, then there will be a tie, and no one will be elected by the Senate.</p>
   <p>[The election of a President of the Senate could be accomplished] only if Mahone should side with the Democrats, or if Davies should re-enter the Republican fold. The former is hardly to be expected, considering the bitter <pb facs="5418474_6_0547.jpg" n="3"/>election campaign which was waged in Virginia; the latter is more feasible and in fact is highly probable, for our rotund Davis never was a true, dyed-in-the-wool Democrat. Only a few months ago he emphasized his independence and bragged about it. He represents a Republican State--at least the preponderant majority of this State is Republican--and he will be honest enough to consider that the majority of the people of the nation voted last fall for the continuation of a Republican administration.</p>
   <p>But suppose that he should be led into temptation and should be offered the honor of presiding over the Senate--could he resist? Of course he could be elected to that post [by the Democrats] only if some Republican, or Mahone, voted for him, and besides, Davies would also cast a vote for himself; but it may be made clear to him that it can be done!</p>
   <p>The question whether a Democrat or a Republican is elected as the successor of Arthur is of tremendous importance, and is literally a question of life and death for Arthur himself. One must consider that a Democrat may be <pb facs="5418474_6_0548.jpg" n="4"/>elected President of the Senate, and that then only one life would intervene between a groveling political party which has been unsuccessful for twenty years and the bountiful trough of the national administration. Would not such a life hang by a hair? Are there no people of Guiteau's caliber in the Democratic party? After the nation's leadership has twice been changed by assassinations, why could it not happen a third time? Never before could a political party gain so much by resorting to murder as now. When Lincoln was killed, no one surmised that Johnson would become a traitor to the party which had elected him, and in this instance a Republican of somewhat different stripe would take the place of Garfield. But a Democrat next in line to succeed a Republican President--that would appear to be almost a death-warrant for the latter. As we said before, fellows like Guiteau can undoubtedly be found in the Democratic party as well as among the Republicans.</p>
   <p>It indicates a sad state of affairs and is gruesome indeed that one should be led to such observations, but it is understandable. After two Presidents <pb facs="5418474_6_0549.jpg" n="5"/>have become the victims of assassins, it would be ridiculous to ignore the possibility of another murder. And if no one else should consider this phase of the situation, it certainly must be obvious to Mr. Arthur.</p>
   <p>He certainly is not to be envied in his new official position, not even by the poorest man in the country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
