<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1909-12-15">December 15, 1909</date><title level="a">The New Orchestra Hall. its Dedication Resulted in a Triumph for Theodore Thomas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_6_1586</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1586.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>I V</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1909-12-15">December 15, 1909</date><title level="a">THE NEW ORCHESTRA HALL. ITS DEDICATION RESULTED IN A TRIUMPH FOR THEODORE THOMAS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The opening concert at the new home of the Chicago Orchestra Hall was given yesterday before 2,200 people, who will long remember the profound impression which the simple but appropriate dedication created. At 8:30 Theodore Thomas appeared on the stage and he was greeted with tumultuous acclaim. As usual, he bowed twice, and immediately gave the signal for the commencement. "Again I greet thee, beloved hall" was sung by the mixed chorus, composed of members from the Appollo and Mendelssohn Clubs. Its sentimental rendition made a great impression. Mr. George E. Adams, former president of the orchestra association gave a short address, wherein he gave special emphasis to the fact, that the building costs which amounted to $750,000 have been obtained by voluntary contributions, from 8,000 persons. Thus the middle class as well as the wealthier contingent have provided for it. The speaker then thanked the courageous leader and his musicians for the great service they rendered in elevating musical understanding and appreciation in Chicago and throughout the entire nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_6_1587.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All seats were sold and, since even the three organs were installed, the acoustic qualities of the hall could be adequately judged. Although a trial in regard to this was held several days ago and considered satisfactory, several disturbing factors manifested themselves yesterday, but these may be eliminated by a different distribution of the various instrumental groups or perhaps by the use of sound deflectors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
