<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-07-18">July 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Chicago Hungarian Home</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0946</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0946.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-07-18">July 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHICAGO HUNGARIAN HOME</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have heard quite a lot about the plans for building a home for the aged Hungarian people of Chicago. We have also heard that certain movements have really been started to make this project a reality. It is a well-known fact that the Chicago Hungarians are faithful workers when they start anything of this nature. When they start something like this they do not stop until it is finished, provided it is handled by responsible persons and capable leaders.</p>
   <p>Many things have been started in the past, but nothing has been finished, by the Chicago Hungarians. Observers watching some of these Hungarian <pb facs="5422061_2_0947.jpg" n="2"/>movements might liken them to large dark clouds moving overhead but holding very little rain. Loud talk, inspiring speeches, and spirited newspaper articles, seem to constitute the entire movement. When the time comes for tireless workers to enlist, everybody becomes silent and backs away, and so the movement is doomed.</p>
   <p>This is the way we stand at present with the building of a Hungarian Home. We all know that we need such an institution in Chicago, where our social and political affairs might be discussed; an institution the Chicago Hungarians would be proud to call their own. But up to now, we have had to be satisfied with idle talk about it. We have told each other how necessary a Hungarian Home is for the Hungarians of Chicago, but we have not acted accordingly.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0948.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The situation is not to the credit of the Chicago Hungarians. The small Hungarian colony in Aurora, consists of only 120 families yet they have built a Hungarian Home. We cannot praise these people for that, however, because they have done nothing else which would indicate that the Hungarian brotherhood really exists in that community.</p>
   <p>We can not build a Hungarian Home in Chicago by talking. Only through action can we have such a home.</p>
   <p>It seems as though some new ideas have come before the Hungarian people on the question of building this home.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0949.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The ideas are not presented by individuals, but by an organization, the oldest and largest Hungarian sick benefit society.</p>
   <p>The Chicago and Vicinity First Hungarian Social and Sick Benefit Society, has taken the situation in hand. This society is the first to take interest in the issue and give it serious thought. We can not deny the fact that nobody else would act, so all glory belongs to the ones now acting as sponsors.</p>
   <p>We can look to the future with great hope. It will not be long before we Chicago Hungarians will have an institution, of which we will have reason to <pb facs="5422061_2_0950.jpg" n="5"/>be proud.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian Home building committee consists of such well-known Hungarians, as: Joseph Rakos, Joseph Fekete, Colman Molnars and others.</p>
   <p>Members of the committee are well-known and supported by the Chicago Hungarians. For this reason we trust that these men will work hard to make the project a success.</p>
   <p>There is one thing we all must remember, namely; that a captain cannot win a battle without the cooperation of his men.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0951.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>It is useless to have a good committee if we, the soldiers, do not cooperate. Its success depends on us.</p>
   <p>If it happens that this great idea is not carried out successfully, which we believe it will be, it will not be the fault of the committee, it will be the fault of our Chicago Hungarians, and it will be to our disgrace.</p>
   <p>We must cease to be indifferent, make our brotherly love a reality and aid the committee in its good work, so that we can make this dream of Chicago Hungarians come true.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
