<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-10-30">Oct. 30, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">About Gangsters</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1091</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1091.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-10-30">Oct. 30, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT GANGSTERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>You must go, you must leave!</p>
   <p>You must gather up your belongings and must leave Chicago and the vicinity.</p>
   <p>This was the order which was given by the chief of detectives to all gangsters and gunmen.</p>
   <p>When the chief of detectives issues such orders, they had better be obeyed or else there will be real trouble.</p>
   <p>But this was not the only order issued by the chief of detectives; he also said that the characters of the underworld must leave within three days, but this time limit expired last Thursday. He told the police not to play around much with these gangsters, but should let them taste the sting of bullets if they ran across any of them before the gangsters beat them <pb facs="5422061_2_1092.jpg" n="2"/>to the act.</p>
   <p>In this last part of the order there is logic, because it is better for society to be rid of a bandit who is unnecessary, than [to be rid of]the police who are necessary to society.</p>
   <p>The first part of the order, that the gangsters shall leave the city within three days, does not seem to mean anything.</p>
   <p>It is unnecessary to state that every resident of the city of Chicago would be overwhelmingly happy if a pleasant day came along and all the gangsters would leave.</p>
   <p>But will this ever happen?</p>
   <p>We wonder whether those warriors of the underworld will pay any attention to the orders of the chief of detectives?</p>
   <p>Perhaps there are a few people who believe that this order issued by the <pb facs="5422061_2_1093.jpg" n="3"/>chief will rid the city of all the gunmen and gangsters.</p>
   <p>As far as the gunmen of the city are concerned, this order does not mean so much as a serious thought.</p>
   <p>We can't imagine the leaders of the underworld being scared by this order, after they have had the people of the city half scared out of their wits for such a long time.</p>
   <p>These gangsters are so used to such orders by now, that they don't pay any attention to them any more. These orders are just orders and they do not mean much to them. They do what they want regardless of orders, and they do not pay attention to the police.</p>
   <p>We are fully satisfied that there wasn't a single gangster or bandit who packed and left the city in accordance with the orders issued.</p>
   <p>As a matter of fact, the chief of detectives knows this also. He knows <pb facs="5422061_2_1094.jpg" n="4"/>that none of the gangsters will leave the city.</p>
   <p>If he thought that the gangsters were going to leave the city, he would never have issued the order--shoot to kill--to the policemen.</p>
   <p>The city can't rid itself of gangsters through orders such as these.</p>
   <p>We must not forget that the present-day gangster is not of the same type as was the one of bygone days--the old-time gangster came from distant cities and worked at night.</p>
   <p>The present-day gangsters are well organized and they have many influential connections.</p>
   <p>The present-day bandit can't be compared with those of long ago whose only protection was the wilderness, and that wasn't very good protection.</p>
   <p>The present-day gangsters are organized on a business-[like]basis, and these <pb facs="5422061_2_1095.jpg" n="5"/>well-organized gangsters can find protection under the fold of big politicians, and this is also on a business basis.</p>
   <p>That this is so, can be easily seen by looking at the cases of Druggan and Lake, the beer barons, who are outstanding examples of well-organized criminals.</p>
   <p>If we want to rid the city of criminals, the first thing we must do is to clean up our politics. The criminal will only work hard when he knows that he is fully protected, regardless of what his crime may be.</p>
   <p>If the protection of the criminal is stopped, then crime will cease to exist.</p>
   <p>When the criminal finds that he can't escape the hand of the law, then he will give up his criminal practices voluntarily.</p>
   <p>If the criminal does not [receive]protection, then he will find out that crime does not pay. His criminal attempts may be successful once or twice, <pb facs="5422061_2_1096.jpg" n="6"/>but sooner or later he will be caught, and the penalty he will pay will be greater than his profits.</p>
   <p>This is what will stop crime in Chicago, and not ordinary orders as issued by the chief of detectives.</p>
   <p>Stop crime in politics--that is what we want.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
