<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-05-06">May 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Career of a Young Hungarian Doctor</title><title level="a" type="sub">Hungarian Child Specialist on the North Side</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0041</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0041.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-05-06">May 6, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">CAREER OF A YOUNG HUNGARIAN DOCTOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">Hungarian Child Specialist on the North Side</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are always happy to publish accounts of the successes of our countrymen. At this time Dr. Martin Zeisler, child specialist, arouses our interest. He was mentioned in this publication several months ago in connection with a notable surgical achievement. Since that time Dr. Zeisler has received a permanent appointment to a staff position at the Children's Memorial Hospital. This hospital is known to be the best in Chicago in the field of children's diseases.</p>
   <p>The Children's Memorial Hospital, 712 Fullerton Avenue, with 250 beds, helps about 20,000 children each year to get well. The staff members are all well-known specialists. To be on this staff is an honor and a career in itself, and the Hungarians can be proud to see one of our compatriots in such a post.</p>
   <p>Dr. Zeisler is to be commended for never having been ashamed of the fact that he is Hungarian, on the contrary, we know that whenever he had the opportunity, he has given special attention to Hungarian children.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0042.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are glad to hear that this young doctor with such a fine career, has opened another office, in addition to his Lawrence Avenue location, at 1166 Diversey Parkway.....</p>
   <p>Considering that the Chicago Hungarians do not have another child specialist, we welcome this new doctor because it is time for the Hungarians to recognize the American spirit which sees its future national wealth and happiness in the children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
