<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-03-23">Mar. 23, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Unveiling of the Kossuth Statue</title><title level="a" type="sub">Airplanes in Action; People Disperse During the Speeches; Picketing against Horthy in Washington [Picture of picketers with placards, 3 cols., 4 inches high, accompanies this article.]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1755</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1755.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-03-23">Mar. 23, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">UNVEILING OF THE KOSSUTH STATUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Airplanes in Action; People Disperse During the Speeches; Picketing against Horthy in Washington [Picture of picketers with placards, 3 cols., 4 inches high, accompanies this article.]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The unveiling of the statue of Kossuth in New York took place on Thursday, March 15. More than five hundred pilgrims came from Hungary for this occasion. Most of the people who made the pilgrimage are henchmen of the Horthy regime.</p>
   <p>The liberal-minded American-Hungarians, who would like to see a republican form of government in Hungary, rallied around the flag of the League Against Horthyism and made the pilgrims feel on their arrival that they were not welcome.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1756.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The unveiling was begun with great pomp, but the League Against Horthyism disturbed the celebration when an airplane, rented for this occasion by the League, began to bombard the crowd with anti-Horthy leaflets, frightening the participants, so that they began to disperse in the middle of a speech.</p>
   <p>The people began to read the leaflets and one person gave one to Count Laszlo Szechenyi, Hungarian Ambassador to Washington, D. C., to read what the liberal-minded working class thinks of his government.</p>
   <p>Otherwise the unveiling was a success. About five thousand Hungarians marched to the statue, of whom the pilgrims attracted great attention with their Hungarian costumes and church vestments. There were twenty-five hundred policemen at the statue and an estimated crowd of twenty-five thousand.....</p>
   <p>The ceremony was closed with a volley of thirteen cannons--a tribute to the <pb facs="5422061_2_1757.jpg" n="3"/>immortal Hungarian liberator by the American Artillery.</p>
   <p>Three hundred of the pilgrims visited Washington, D. C., where Count Szechenyi, Hungarian Ambassador, wished to introduce them to President Coolidge. Inasmuch as President Coolidge could not receive all three hundred of them, the Hungarian Ambassador selected twenty of the group....and the President received them.</p>
   <p>As soon as the pilgrims reached the White House, they encountered the members of the League Against Horthyism, who picketed in front of the White House with placards. On some of the placards, the following messages were inscribed: "They profane the memory of Kossuth"; "Hejjas, a mass murderer"; "Perenyi is a Habsburg lackey"; "Tomcsanyi reinstated the whipping post".</p>
   <p>We received information that a committee came to Mayor Thompson of Chicago with the request that this city should not receive the pilgrims, henchmen of Horthy. They told the Mayor that many of the pilgrims took active part in and are responsible for the bloody terror in Hungary, which is a blot on civilization.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1758.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mayor Thompson declared that he will not receive them in Chicago officially.</p>
   <p>We must mention here that while the pilgrims came to celebrate March 15 (Hungary's Independence Day) in America, the government in Hungary ordered police to disperse the crowd that was attending a March 15 celebration arranged by the Socialist-Democrats, thereby proving that they do not honor the memory of Kossuth in Hungary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
