<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-08-07">Aug. 7, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Ground under Our Feet Is on Fire</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1557</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1557.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-08-07">Aug. 7, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE GROUND UNDER OUR FEET IS ON FIRE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The ground is burning under the feet of the foreigners--the naturalized as well as the non-naturalized. In spite of it, the fire that rages below and the danger that lurks above have not been noticed by the individuals and organizations whose duty it is to look out for the interests of foreigners.</p>
   <p>For years the writer has warned the readers of this paper that there is a systematic persecution aimed at the foreign-born citizens of this country--that the seeds of hatred have sprouted from the rotten mire of the Ku Klux Klan. We are witnessing the fruit of this hatred now in Michigan.</p>
   <p>If up to the present time we did not heed the warning or did not realize the seriousness of the situation, the time has come when we must wake up to the fact, an example of which is the new registration law of Michigan.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1558.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is a registration law in Michigan whose example will be followed by the other states. A way will be found to take our bread away from us.</p>
   <p>In Pennsylvania, at one of the Legion meetings, the motion was made that all workers register and that no foreigner should be given work as long as any American citizen is idle. In Utica, immigrants were discharged from public works first and this "good" example was followed afterwards by private industry.</p>
   <p>President Hoover and Secretary of Labor Doak look upon the fact that more foreigners are being deported than allowed to enter as a great achievement of the government, and the country is applauding.</p>
   <p>What will happen to us if the economic depression continues for another year or two, as it will, and where will the persecution of immigrants end?</p>
   <p>No one should be gullible enough to think that his citizenship certificate will <pb facs="5422061_2_1559.jpg" n="3"/>save him from all persecution and molestation. Officially, distinction is made between citizen and noncitizen, but social boycott does not take into consideration whether the immigrant has or has not his naturalization certificate. The foreigner, the immigrant, is persecuted regardless of naturalization.</p>
   <p>Anyone who thinks of the immigrant as a "hunky" or a "wop," does not take into consideration whether the "hunky" or "wop" is naturalized or not--on the contrary, he is indignant when the immigrant dares to claim that he is a citizen. This tendency becomes apparent in the naturalization procedure, which has been made a regular stumbling block.....</p>
   <p>It must be stated that the new registration law does not affect citizens officially. However, in practice the immigrant is subject to thousands of indignities. Any police official can question anyone suspected of being an alien, and our only protection against being taken to a police station is to <pb facs="5422061_2_1560.jpg" n="4"/>carry our naturalization papers or other identification with us constantly.</p>
   <p>The only difference between the citizen and noncitizen immigrant will be that the noncitizen will have to register, while the naturalized citizen--for his own protection--will have to have a permanent identification.....</p>
   <p>Those immigrants who will not be able to prove that they are in this country legally will be constantly annoyed and in many cases deported. By these immigrants we mean not those who came to this country illegally--these unfortunates know that they may be caught at any time--but those who have no way of proving how, when, and where they gained entry.</p>
   <p>Tens of thousands of immigrants cannot become citizens because they are unable to prove their entry. Therefore, thousands of aliens can be molested, blackmailed, and deported without a comeback. Nothing can be done in Michigan to change this law. It takes years in this country to pass a law, but it takes even longer to repeal it. We cannot expect the repeal of a law which is <pb facs="5422061_2_1561.jpg" n="5"/>designed to persecute immigrants and which is therefore quite popular in this country.....</p>
   <p>We must take steps to organize an effective resistance, so that other states will not enact similar legislation. The lawmakers can be influenced by two factors: the voters' expressed wishes and [their own] self-interest.....We must, therefore, mobilize the votes so that the politicians will take notice.</p>
   <p>At the next election, the naturalized citizen must ask each candidate whether he intends to support such [anti-alien] legislation. If a bill of this nature is introduced before the legislature, each foreign-language organization, newspaper, and individual voter must act and bring pressure upon the lawmakers--with telegrams, letters, committees--warning them that if they vote for the measure they will lose our votes.....</p>
   <p>In most localities the need for a joint committee of the Hungarian organizations <pb facs="5422061_2_1562.jpg" n="6"/>was recognized and now we must strive to co-operate with the committees of other national groups as well, because we all will be affected by the persecution of foreigners. We must do this now and not at the last minute, when it may be too late.</p>
   <p>Our daily bread and our personal liberty are at stake, and if in defense of our interests we cannot co-operate with one another and with other national groups, we deserve to be persecuted.....</p>
   <p>It is useless to write more about this subject. If there is anyone who still does not feel the ground burning under his feet after contemplating what has happened in Michigan, he will never realize the danger until it stares him in the face.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
