<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-09-12">Sept. 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Good News for Chicago Hungarians.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1081</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1081.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-09-12">Sept. 12, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD NEWS FOR CHICAGO HUNGARIANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We wish to announce, through the columns of this newspaper, that it is possible to communicate with Hungary through the mails.</p>
   <p>What this means to the Hungarian people is needless to discuss. We have talked and thought enough about it already.</p>
   <p>This is a piece of news that has been awaited very patiently; the oceans have opened in front of us. Now we can open communications and we have won the first item of our fight. Now we can see that something is happening for the benefit of the Hungarian people, and our patient waiting will have come to an end. Now idle talk is not necessary and the guessing game that people have conducted can be stopped. It does not make much difference when people can be assured of going to Hungary in safety.</p>
   <p>The main thing is that the Hungarian people can receive and send mail to and from Hungary, and within a short time all Hungarians will know just exactly what is happening in their homeland.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1082.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This newspaper has always said that the mail channels have to be opened before any other type of transportation or communication can be hoped for by the Hungarian people.</p>
   <p>We have always maintained that until the mail is opened to all parts of Hungary, all other activities in relation to the homeland are futile.</p>
   <p>Now we can speak with more confidence of the future. How people may have popes that in a few months, those who want to return to Hungary may be able to do so. Those people who want to return to Hungary will know just as soon as they receive their first letter, whether it is worth taking a chance. The people who are planning to emigrate can start buying presents for their relatives, because we feel that in a few months all the channels of travel will be open.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1083.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Besides the sending and receiving of letters, it is permissible to send money and packages to Hungary. Whether it is advisable to send money to Hungary is open to question. Prices in Hungary are terribly high and out of all proportion, for instance, a pair of chickens in American money would cost the buyer $24; a goose, $36 and the price of clothing is beyond belief.</p>
   <p>The sending of money would not mean very much, but to send packages containing clothing would be of much greater help. The time has come when these questions must be given serious thought by the Hungarian people.</p>
   <p>The motto of all good Hungarians must be this; "We will send more letters and packages to our loved ones."</p>
   <p>The Chicago Hungarians can do much for the Hungarian nation. This downtrodden and broken-hearted, but still spirited people, need food and decent clothing. Now that winter is closing in fast, we would advise those who plan on sending clothing to their people in Hungary, to send winter clothing, at once.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
