<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1935-06-28">June 28, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Hundred-Per-Cent Americans and the Foreigners</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1129</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1129.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>III F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1935-06-28">June 28, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">HUNDRED-PER-CENT AMERICANS AND THE FOREIGNERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The hundred-per-cent Americans, who, recently, are desirious of taking away the means of earning the daily bread from the foreign-born American population, feel justified in doing so by referring to other countries using discrimination against alien workers.</p>
   <p>This reference is based on doubtful facts and does not take into consideration the peculiar situation in the United States. These patriotic demagogues shut their eyes to historical facts. This country was not made great by those who came over on the Mayflower and their descendents only.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1130.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the birth of the independence of America, not only those of English origin gave their lives for this country, but Pulaski, the Polish general, Kovats, the Hungarian Colonel, Von Steuben, the German general, Lafayette, the French general, and Rochambeau, also a French general, to mention the leaders. At the time of the Civil War, thousands of foreign-born fought for the Union. Therefore, the bloody work of establishing a new country was shared by those of foreign blood with the "ancient" Americans.</p>
   <p>The foreign contribution to the progress of civilization and in technical fields is incalculable. America cannot boast of one great industrial or cultural creation which is not assisted or influenced by foreign ingenuity or the sweat of his brow.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1131.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In vain do the foreigner-haters blare that the aliens take the bread away from the American workers, and it cannot be disclaimed that foreigners are only employed when and where the American cannot or will not do the work.</p>
   <p>The One Hundred Percenters cannot be convinced with arguments or facts. They complain because they have been instructed to do so by certain factions whose interests require the public's attention to be focused on other things rather than the real troubles of this country.</p>
   <p>To us, the only defense against these false attacks, and perhaps this would be only a temporary respite, is to become naturalized citizens of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
