<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-10-02">Oct. 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Frontier Fortresses Are Crumbling</title><title level="a" type="sub">Attention, Hungarian-American Newspapers! (Editorial by Sandor Gondos)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0507</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0507.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-10-02">Oct. 2, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE FRONTIER FORTRESSES ARE CRUMBLING</title><title level="a" type="sub">Attention, Hungarian-American Newspapers! (Editorial by Sandor Gondos)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ten years ago, at the height of prosperity, when Hungarian-Americans willingly paid for two- and three-year subscriptions to Hungarian newspapers, and when we did not have to knock on the doors of the merchants for advertisements--because they brought them in themselves--we thought that the Hungarian-American frontier fortresses (the Hungarian-American press) were indestructible. Not the Hungarian-American churches and societies, because they were only institutions which used the Hungarian flag, but the Hungarian-American newspapers were the frontier fortresses of Magyar-America. The church, be it Hungarian, Slavic, Russian, or American, is primarily a sectarian institution and only secondarily of national character. If anyone says that any church in America is Hungarian, he is either laboring under a delusion or knowingly stating an untruth. His Excellency the Bishop (usually of Irish <pb facs="5422061_2_0508.jpg" n="2"/>descent) says sternly. "The church is mine. The school is mine. The cemetery is mine. And if you Hungarians don't do as I want you to, if you are not satisfied with the Hungarian-speaking priest I gave you, I will send you an American priest, who will discipline you. You can thank me for the goodness of my heart that I tolerate the Magyar language in my church."</p>
   <p>The Magyar race in America cannot build frontier fortresses on this foreign soil. Nor can they build Hungarian insurance institutions. Our large fraternal organizations are hesitating to consolidate with one another to form one big insurance company. However, inasmuch as their capital runs into millions, it is only a question of time until clever American politicians will covet this money and, under the pretext that the leaders are incompetent to handle the interests of their members, will turn the companies over to American "experts". With this step, which is on our threshold, the Hungarian character of our Hungarian societies will end.</p>
   <p>The only Hungarian frontier fortress whose every stone was purely Hungarian-- <pb facs="5422061_2_0509.jpg" n="3"/>it could not be anything else--has been the Hungarian press. The much-maligned, disdained Hungarian press is the only exclusively Hungarian institution in America which has always defended the Magyar language, Magyar virtues, customs, and traditions. It could not very well do otherwise and maintain its own existence.....</p>
   <p>These frontier fortresses are begining to crumble now. Martin Himler, who has kept up his chain of Hungarian newspapers through great personal sacrifice, has warned us that the complete destruction of the Hungarian-American press is fast approaching.....He says, "Beware, because the flood that will engulf all of us is on the way, and it will be good night for the Hungarian-Americans."</p>
   <p>The false pride of the individual Hungarian newspaper publishers has kept this most urgent Hungarian public affair out of print up to this time. The modest Hungarian newspaper owners would not face their readers with the statement: "We cannot carry on. We have sacrificed our mentality, <pb facs="5422061_2_0510.jpg" n="4"/>spiritual strength, money, and business honor in trying to keep up the Hungarian press. We have reached the end of our rope, and now it is up to the Hungarian-Americans to save their frontier fortresses".....</p>
   <p>Possibly we could try to publish a consolidated newspaper. Instead of the many local weeklies, we could have one or two newspapers centrally located. It would cost much less and still serve the purpose.</p>
   <p>....The drowning man grasps the proverbial straw.....Why should we, the ever-struggling Hungarian publishers, give up without a fight?....</p>
   <p>With love for our vocation the writers turn to the publishers of Hungarian newspapers and beg them to co-operate in an attempt to save all of us.....If fate has decreed that we continue to exist, let us struggle for the vital requisites of life. If we are condemned to death, let us die like men.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
