<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Geza Kenda, <title>Magyars in America</title> (Cleveland: Szabadsag, <date when="1927">1927</date>), Vol. II, Chap. 3.
<title level="a">The Early Life of Chicago Hungarians</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1587</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1587.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Geza Kenda, <title>Magyars In America</title> (Cleveland: Szabadsag, <date when="1927">1927</date>), Vol. II, Chap. 3.
<title level="a">THE EARLY LIFE OF CHICAGO HUNGARIANS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the city of Chicago, Hungarian life began only in the early nineties, when the Hungarians began to organize.</p>
   <p>Until now, the resturant of Michael Sipady, on South Halsted Street, was used by the first Magyar immigrants of Chicago. They were Joseph Molnar, Joseph Fulop, Emery Orosz, Charles Zadetzky, Andrew Kozma, John Varga and a few others who stopped in for a glass of wine, and for a friendly chat.</p>
   <p>Hungarians were diligent, hard workers. Although the wages were rather low, the cost of living was cheap, but they could put away or send some money to the old country.</p>
   <p>From the saved money, the Hungarian business originated, and every dollar sent abroad aroused the desire for emigration.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1588.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The emigrants were no longer afraid of the long journey, and of the sea, neither did they consider America a strange country, because they knew that there lived many Magyars, who would help them through the difficulties of the beginning. In Chicago, Joseph Byfield, the owner of the Hotel Sherman, was the benefactor of many immigrants.</p>
   <p>This was in the early eighties, in the "childhood of the American-Magyar life."</p>
   <p>Later, as they stayed in this country longer, the Hungarians realized that they had to adjust themselves to the American environment and to settle down, if only temporarily, but it would take a few years to reach their goal; to buy land, to earn enough money to build a house, or to send for the lonely wife in the Old Country.</p>
   <p>Then, the American-Magyars began to think about church and social organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1589.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Hungarians of Chicago as did other cities and localities, watched New York, where the greatest number of Hungarians lived, to see what this city was doing.</p>
   <p>From there, the Magyars had expected an example, a motto, and a guidance.</p>
   <p>And they did not have to wait long. On February 1, 1884 the first issue of the Amerikai Nemzetor (American National Guard) appeared with an American-Hungarian program, and with an American-Hungarian purpose and in American-Hungarian style, the only newspaper published in the Magyar language in the United States.</p>
   <p>This means the beginning of a new period, not only of the American-Hungarian history of Chicago, but for the Hungarians of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
