<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-03-24">March 24, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Successful Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0397</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0397.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-03-24">March 24, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">SUCCESSFUL FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday the Federation of Hungarian Associations of Greater Chicago held a brilliant festival to commemorate the events on the Ides of March [1848]. The Dr. Herzl Hall, in which the festival was held, was crowded to repletion. The crowd listened with attention and remarkable self-discipline to the program.</p>
   <p>The presentation of the banners belonging to the different associations made a great impression on the Hungarians, and served to create a more festive feeling in the hearts of those present. The speech of the Hungarian Consul, Ladislas Medgyessy, was highly appreciated, and this was the first time we saw an official representative of our native country at a March festival. The singing of the choir of the Hungarian Reformed Church, seventy singers strong, was so good that it was almost constantly on the stage to respond to the demand of the public. Credit for this success is in great part due Reverend Eugene Boros. The lecture delivered by Reverend Sidney Snow about <pb facs="5422061_2_0398.jpg" n="2"/>his two visits in Hungary and about his experiences while there, was rewarded with enthusiastic applause.</p>
   <p>Mrs. John Balazs, a radio singer, sang some songs in her beautiful ringing voice, thereby greatly adding to the brilliancy of this evening. Erica Buzy also reaped an acclamation, as did the festival speech delivered by Alexander Szentivanyi. The exact performance of the Kormagyar [circle dance] by the girl dancers revealed that painstaking efforts had been made to assure a faultless performance. They were instructed by Dalbert Chute and Gustave Vojtas. The trio of the new generation, the "Kopogos" [tramping dance] of the danseuse, and the dance performed by the youth division of Branch 96 of the Verhovay Aid Association brought immense applause in their wake.....Several donations were made for the treasury of the Federation, for which the latter is herewith expressing its gratitude.</p>
   <p>The palm for the brilliancy of this festival belongs to the Arrangements <pb facs="5422061_2_0399.jpg" n="3"/>Committee, which worked tirelessly to secure this outstanding success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
