<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-09-11">Sept. 11, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Hungarian Peoples Theatre to Re-Open</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-09-11">Sept. 11, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO HUNGARIAN PEOPLES THEATRE TO RE-OPEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Eugene Endrey and his wife, Margaret Padly temporarily bade farewell to the Chicago-Hungarian public last April, when they left for Budapest, from whence they were to bring back their two children to establish a permanent residence here in Chicago. The boat on which they sailed for America has already arrived in New York.</p>
   <p>Engene Endrey is the organizer of the Chicago Hungarian Peoples Theatre, and as soon as he arrives in Chicago, his work will begin: to prepare a program for the season's opening of the Chicago Hungarian Peoples Theatre, about which we will give more detailed information later.</p>
   <p>In connection with the arrival of Eugene Endrey, we print the following item which appeared in a Budapest daily paper, the Evening Courier, which deals with Eugene Endrey and the Chicago Hungarians in connection with the theatrical movement here in Chicago.</p>
   <p>This is the article which appears in the Courier:</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0198.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Eugene Endrey went to the United States two years ago, and there he organized the Chicago Hungarian Peoples Theatre. This theatre has an extraordinarily important position in the cultural lives of the Hungarian Americans, inasmuch as this is the only permanent organization of its kind in the United States. Eugene Endrey has given many performances in Chicago which have inspired not only the Hungarian people, but also the English-speaking people of Chicago. His prima donna, Margaret Padly, has gained great recognition here in Budapest also.</p>
   <p>"Endrey returned home not long ago and here he purchased many plays for the benefit of his 'Chicago Theatre'. A few days before he left here to take up again his great cultural work in the United States, one of our reporters interviewed him, and Endrey made the following statement:</p>
   <p>'My Chicago theatrical season was very successful and I am sure that the coming season will also be very good to us. I am taking back the following operettas, "The Song Has Ended," "The Singing Captain," "The Countess Maritza," "The Sun Is Shining," and many other interesting plays which have been <pb facs="5422061_2_0199.jpg" n="3"/>successfully produced in Hungary, and I feel that these plays and operettas will find their way into the hearts of the Hungarian Americans. In Chicago we have taken upon ourselves great cultural responsibilities, among which are the development of the Hungarian press, the popularization of Hungarian literature and the making of Hungarian music more accessible to the Hungarian public.</p>
   <p>'I can only speak in the most respectful manner about the Chicago Hungarians, especially with regard to their societies; the outstanding one among them all is the Rakoczy Society that will do everything in its power to assure the existence of the Hungarian theatre. It is not a small job for us poor Hungarians to struggle there among strangers, but everyone over there is striving to keep the Hungarian language alive, even though the distance from the fatherland is so great.'"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
