<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-09-18">Sept. 18, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Stephen Barat</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0043</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0043.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-09-18">Sept. 18, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">DR. STEPHEN BARAT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A very serious incident has taken place in the lives of the Chicago Hungarians. One of their most active members was taken by death last Tuesday morning.</p>
   <p>Dr. Stephen Barat received his education in Budapest and Prague. After finishing his internship, he left Hungary for the southern part of Europe. At first he settled in Sofia and later he moved to Constantinople. The Turkish noblemen recognized the ability of this young Hungarian doctor, and in a short time he was one of the best-known doctors in the Turkish capital.</p>
   <p>He came to Chicago twenty-five years ago, and established himself on the South Side, in the Bryn Mawr community where the population was very small. His familiarity with many languages made him a very popular doctor on the South Side where there were immigrants from all over the world.</p>
   <p>He was a very active man not only in his professional field, but he also took part <pb facs="5422061_2_0044.jpg" n="2"/>in all social functions. He became a member of the different business and political associations where he was recognized for his superior European education. He became the official doctor for the Illinois Steel Company, where he introduced many improvements in the medical treatment of the men of that company. The political world recognized his ability and good common sense, and his ideas and suggestions were followed in many instances.</p>
   <p>Dr. Barat was a leader in all Hungarian activities. He was a typical, outspoken, brave Hungarian man. He belonged to the old school, to which truth and respectability were sacred rights. In 1918 he took a very active part in the Hungarian-American movement for a Hungarian republic. He had very strong democratic ideas about the liberation of Hungary.</p>
   <p>His main interest was the Hungarian University Club, of which he had been president several times. His enthusiasm was a great inspiration to his co-workers.</p>
   <p>During the World War he sacrificed a great deal of service, and the American <pb facs="5422061_2_0045.jpg" n="3"/>officials honored him with recognition in many instances. Dr. Barat had a personality which was well liked by everyone. He was considered a great humorist and he was accorded honor for this at all social gatherings which he attended. His death is a loss which can't be replaced, because his leadership and his enthusiastic activities among the South Side Hungarians will not be replaced for a long time.</p>
   <p>The Hungarians of Chicago and the vicinity will remember him always with great respect. His activities and his good deeds will never be forgotten by those who were close to him. Dr. Barat was truly a good Hungarian-American warrior. May he rest in peace.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
