<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1923-06-24">June 24, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Twentieth Anniversary Jubilee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0864</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0864.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1923-06-24">June 24, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">TWENTIETH ANNIVERSARY JUBILEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The West Pullman United First Hungarian Sick Benefit Society, which was established June 7, 1903, held its twentieth anniversary celebration on June 10 at the Schlitz Hall.</p>
   <p>Guests began coming in the early afternoon to take part in the jubilee ceremonies of one of the oldest Hungarian societies on the South Side.</p>
   <p>The strains of Hungarian music filled the Schlitz Hall, played by the Rakoczi Hungarian Brass Band.</p>
   <p>The program of the afternoon began with the singing of the American and Hungarian national anthems Julius Prokop, president made the opening address. The initiation of forty-two new members followed this address.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0865.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The following organizations were represented by delegates: Chicago-Hungarian Literary and Social Club; Chicago-Hungarian Reformed Men and Women's Sick Benefit Society; Chicago and Vicinity United Virgin Mary; and St. Emerich Catholic Sick Benefit Society; Verhovay No. 96; Chicago and Vicinity Hungarian Benefit Society; West Pullman Workers' Sick Benefit Society; Protected Home Circle No. 229; and Chicago and Vicinity United Hungarian Federation of Societies.</p>
   <p>In the past twenty years, four hundred sixteen persons have joined the society. The present membership is one hundred eighty-eight. Twenty members have died during the last twenty years. The present capital of the society is $4,440.30. The society presented the seventeen charter members and present officers with gifts, token of their appreciation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
