<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-04-10">Apr. 10, 1925</date>,
<title level="a">A Bit of Joy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0124</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0124.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-04-10">Apr. 10, 1925</date>,
<title level="a">A BIT OF JOY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In this bitter world when we hear nothing but sorrow from our unfortunate homeland, and the Hungarian-Americans are fighting each other, it is encouraging to receive good news.</p>
   <p>Recently Hungarian writers have brought honor to our Hungarian population. Then there are individual stage artists who now and then happen along to glorify the Hungarian name in America. We Hungarians seldom find out that one or another of the prominent actors or actresses of the stage is Hungarian. The American tongue finds it hard to pronounce Hungarian names, therefore these prominent artists assume Americanized names, but they never deny the fact that they are Hungarians.</p>
   <p>During the past week the San Carlo Opera Company made its appearance at the Auditorium Theatre. There were very few people who knew that the prima donna of the company was Ann Roselle, or the Hungarian Ann Gyenge. The <pb facs="5422061_2_0125.jpg" n="2"/>majority of the members of this company is Italian. Much to the surprise of these Italian artists, one of America's foremost and most exacting music critics, Maurice Rosenfeld, recognized and extended the palm of glory to the Hungarian lady Ann Gyenge.</p>
   <p>Miss Gyenge made her appearance in the opera, "Aida". Mr. Rosenfeld, in an article in the Chicago Daily News, [said of her performance] that there is a possibility that the part might have been sung as well but not any better, but that her acting was far superior to any he had ever seen. The Evening American critic, Glenn Dillard Gunn, wrote: "At last we have an American girl whose stage artistry is far superior to any European artist I have ever seen." It was only natural that the Italian artists should correct him, and inform him that Ann Roselle was a Hungarian. To our joy, he apologized and corrected himself in his next article.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0126.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The success of Ann Gyenge proves to us that if one has talent and ambition [recognition will come]. Many of us remember back seven years ago when under the direction of Frank Palasthi, the New York Hungarian theatrical Society playeu at the old Globe Theatre. The name of the play was "The Count Of Luxemburg". It was at this time that Ann Gyenge made her first appearance. We knew then that in a short time she would become one of the foremost artists of the stage. She has been with the Metropolitan Opera Company which is one of the best-known companies in the world.</p>
   <p>Last Thursday she played "Nedda" in the opera "I1 Pagliacci". It was gratifying to witness her success.</p>
   <p>It is possible that this notable opera star will sign with the Chicago Opera Company.</p>
   <p>To us Hungarians it is a great pleasure to know that one of our own people has reached such heights of fame.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
