<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-10-10">Oct. 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Twentieth Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0439</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0439.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-10-10">Oct. 10, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE TWENTIETH ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Hungarian Independent Singing Society, observed its Twentieth Anniversary Sunday, October 5.</p>
   <p>When we think of the struggles and reverses an organization of this kind encounters in the course of twenty years, we cannot help admire the people who are responsible for its success.</p>
   <p>The twenty year period is now history. Our hearts were filled with joy and pride to witness the celebration. The direction of the affair was superb; <pb facs="5422061_2_0440.jpg" n="2"/>every member of the organization did his bit to make it a success. Especially do we want to pay our compliments to the instructors of the three act play, and particularly Joseph Kennessey, the director. The only ones who do not deserve credit are the Chicago Hungarians, who did not do their part.</p>
   <p>To be a reporter is not a pleasant occupation when you are unable to criticize the artists and are forced to criticize the audience. Usually the fate of a reporter is dubious, and he is forced to tolerate many unpleasant things, and it was particularly true at this notable celebration.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0441.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The play was to have started at 3 o'clock, but at that time there was hardly any one in the hall. It is with regret we report, that kind of cooperation from the Hungarian people. The development of Hungarian culture will be very slow in Chicago, we fear. We must pay serious attention to this matter because the entire world has turned against the Hungarian nation, her art and cultural activities. It is the duty of the Hungarian-Americans to cherish the Hungarian language, the works of art and literature. Will we do this? It is a sad thing to say, but we are afraid not!</p>
   <p>When this society invited the Chicago Hungarians to help them celebrate their <pb facs="5422061_2_0442.jpg" n="4"/>twentieth anniversary, and so small a number appeared, it's not much to the credit of the Hungarian colony.</p>
   <p>Now we must write about the actors and actresses who appeared in the play. Mrs. Csany had an important role and her acting was superb. Mrs. Joseph Kennessy and Mr. Schwimmer had important roles, and performed like experienced artists of the stage.</p>
   <p>During the first act a little girl gave a beautiful recitation. Her name <pb facs="5422061_2_0443.jpg" n="5"/>was Margaret Felner. We must give her great credit because she has just started to school. Her parents can be proud of such an intelligent child.</p>
   <p>The celebration was financially successful.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
