<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1924-09-26">Sept. 26, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">To Be or Not to Be</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0860</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0860.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1924-09-26">Sept. 26, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">TO BE OR NOT TO BE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This article is not being written about Hamlet as the title might suggest. No! After all, this remarkable piece of literature has been discussed by many people, and it seems scarcely possible that there might be a single cultured person who is not familiar with the quotation that is being used as the title of this article.</p>
   <p>At the present time there is a very important question confronting the Hungarians of America, and especially those who live in and around Chicago. The problem that confronts the Hungarian people is: Can there be co-operation among the different organizations, or will the lack of co-operation be demonstrated in this new movement being started to bring the different organizations closer together?</p>
   <p>In the footsteps of this idea one important question arose, which was: Would it be possible to take the two most powerful Hungarian organizations and incorporate them into one?</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0861.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Up to the present time, the signs seem to indicate that the answer will be yes!</p>
   <p>Until now there has been no indication that these organizations are afraid of this idea. It is believed that this incorporation will take place easily and smoothly, without any shocking effects.</p>
   <p>Both of these organizations have the same common interests, and depend on one another, therefore, we can recognize them as an entity only if they incorporate.</p>
   <p>About four months ago a very good and highly respected organization was formed, The Indiana Hungarian Sick Benefit and Burial Society, and now they are asking the Hungarian Sick Benefit Societies Federation in America, to incorporate.</p>
   <p>The Federation, after due deliberation, decided to agree to talk the idea over. On September 20, the delegates of both organizations got together and voiced their opinions on the necessity of the incorporation of the two organizations.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0862.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As we said before, this matter means either life or death, as far as either organization is concerned.</p>
   <p>For instance, the Federation is a first-class organization and has fulfilled its duties to its members at all times, but it has fallen along the wayside, and for the past few months its activities have been at a standstill.</p>
   <p>The Indiana Sick Benefit and Burial Society is very new. Since it is a new organization, it is still far from being one with a deep-rooted standing. In spite of this it is enlarging and is definitely on the road to success.</p>
   <p>As we can all see, both of these organizations have their faults. These faults can be corrected, but only through the consolidation of the two organizations and the use of the good points of their respective constitutions. Then as one organization, their success should be unquestionable, and within a short time this should become a large and powerful institution working deligently among the Chicago Hungarians. The consolidation will mean that the fine work <pb facs="5422061_2_0863.jpg" n="4"/>conducted by each of these organizations will come under one roof and will be practiced on a much larger scale than it was heretofore; consequently, these advantages will be enjoyed by a greater number of unfortunate people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
