<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-01-20">Jan. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Cultural Lecture</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0659</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0659.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-01-20">Jan. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">CULTURAL LECTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The I.W.W. does not limit its activities to preparing for a better future on the economic field; it also urges the mental preparation of the masters of tomorrow. Its conviction is that the workers can obtain for themselves economic favors and success only through ample preparedness in the field of science. That is the reason why the Hungarian Branch of the I.W.W. is sponsoring a series of lectures for its members and their guests. The Hungarian branch of the I.W.W. has arranged for the winter months several lectures at its own building, the Wage Earners Home, 2419 Lincoln Avenue. The lectures deal with social sciences, technical subjects, medicine, etc.</p>
   <p>On December 4 Paul Pika held a lecture on social science. On December 11, Bela Riedl, an architect, delivered a very interesting lecture on architecture. Last Sunday the talented Hungarian physician Dr. Hugo R. Ronay gave a lecture entitled: "The Struggle of Medicine against Sickness in the Past Twenty Years." Dr. Ronay spoke about recent important discoveries and achievements <pb facs="5422061_2_0660.jpg" n="2"/>in the medical field, discoveries which enable us to protect our health, prolong the span of life, and cure sicknesses hitherto thought incurable. He further discussed the origin, care and cure of certain diseases, putting emphasis on the proverb "It is easier to prevent than to cure." He explained the importance of selecting the proper nourishment and brought to our attention the results of biological researches, which now prescribe the exact quantity of proteins and vitamins needed for the development of the body.</p>
   <p>Michael Ruhig, a friend of ours of long standing was kind enough to lend his projecting machine for this lecture, thanks to which the public was able to see how x-rays are produced and used. At the end of the lecture several questions were put to Dr. Ronay, who answered them promptly to the great satisfaction of the audience.</p>
   <p>The audience must be given credit for its excellent behavior during the lecture, and for the eager attention with which it followed the words of Dr. Ronay. At the end of the lecture, the public expressed its thankfulness with thunderous <pb facs="5422061_2_0661.jpg" n="3"/>applause.</p>
   <p>The I.W.W. will continue its policy of giving lectures every week. The dates of these lectures will appear on this newspaper from time to time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
