<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-08-27">Aug. 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">About Emigrants</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1618</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1618.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-08-27">Aug. 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT EMIGRANTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We know at the present time that regardless of conditions there are certain individuals in this country who will emigrate back to Hungary, their homeland.</p>
   <p>During the time of war, working conditions in this country were ideal, and wages were high, enabling most of these people to save large sums of money. Today in Hungary one can get 20 crowns for a dollar instead of five as in the past. Possessing large sums of American money these emigrants become wealthy people in Hungary. This is one of the principal reasons causing the Hungarian people to go back home.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1619.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Already many of these people have left us. They have not been afraid of hardships nor of expense; these fears could not hold the Hungarian emigrant back.</p>
   <p>We have paid close attention to conditions existing in Hungary and we have warned the emigrating Hungarians that if they were leaving this country to seek an easy and prosperous life, with their families and relatives, they were badly mistaken. Hungary is a country that was very badly defeated, and unfortunately received the shortest end of the spoils of the war. This advice was given to our readers with sincere intentions and with nothing else in mind.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1620.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Since postal communications have properly opened up, and the people who have gone back to Hungary from the United States, have had time to realize what conditions exist there, letters have reached this country telling us what to expect when we get there. These letters explain more truthfully than those other letters which are sent to people in this country urging them to return to Hungary, The latter are written in the hope that the returning Hungarians will bring large quantities of money back with them.</p>
   <p>Contacting some of our readers we have run across some very interesting facts concerning conditions in Hungary. We will explain a few so that you may profit from others' experiences.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1621.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Take the case of a friend of ours from Chicago, who has been a resident of Chicago for the past ten years. He is around fifty years of age. This man had acquired for himself a small fortune in this country, and decided that he and his family would go back to Hungary. His entire family, with the exception of his oldest daughter who had become devoted to modes and customs of America, returned to Hungary.</p>
   <p>The father hardly had time to get warm at his home fires when he was drafted for army service. It is now six months that he has been in the army, wishing he had never left Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1622.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>These people can not write much about conditions, but we understand from what they did write that they were sorry to have left true liberty and America.</p>
   <p>There is another case similar to the one above. A friend of ours came to this country fifteen years ago, without first serving his required term in the Hungarian army. He had saved $5,000 and had taken this money back to Hungary in order to aid his aging parents. This man had hardly exchanged greetings with his folks when they drafted him. They took his money away, and under no circumstances will they release him.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1623.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The futures of people leaving this country can be better explained by the men who censor the letters that come from Hungary to the United States.</p>
   <p>As time goes on, in all probability, definite changes will take place in the economic and political setup of Hungary. The crown will in all probability go back to its proper value, but people will just have to wait patiently, and a long time for this readjustment.</p>
   <p>We must remember that for the past six years Hungary has seen nothing but destruction going on within its boundaries. It would be fortunate for <pb facs="5422061_2_1624.jpg" n="7"/>Hungary if within the next six years, this economic and political destruction which has hit the entire nation could be remedied.</p>
   <p>Today we cannot see the slightest indication of any steps being taken to correct this condition. Today destructive powers still hold the upper hand in Hungary. Our patience must not give out.</p>
   <p>Today we are still sticking to old advice; the time for mass emigration has not come for the Hungarian-Americans.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1625.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>In fact those people who can afford to bring their families to this country should do so immediately, or extend a generous hand to relatives who are in great need of help over there.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
