<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-24">Mar. 24, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The Deak Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1087</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1087.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-24">Mar. 24, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THE DEAK CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Deak Club held its meeting, as announced, at the Sherman House, at three o'clock in the afternoon, with Mr. Kiss presiding.</p>
   <p>At the beginning of the session a brief account of the Club's activity with respect to aid for the flood sufferers in Szegedin, Hungary, was given; also the proposed concert, on April 5, at Farwell Hall, was considered. According to the Club's plan, five thousand tickets are to be printed; general admission will be fifty cents, reserved seats a dollar each. The rent for the hall amounts to thirty-five dollars. The suggestion resulted in an extensive debate which ended in a resolution to await the reply of Mr. Remenyi [violinist], before deciding on the concert.</p>
   <p>The reports of the various collection committees show that $1333 has been received.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1088.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Logan was requested to approach the wholesale dealers and seek contributions. Messrs. Kornhausen and Peabody offered to see the liquor dealers. Every committee was then given authority to add members to its staff.</p>
   <p>As heretofore, the newspapers are to be notified every evening about the day's collections. Mr. Pick made a motion to ask a newspaper and a bank to issue an appeal for aid, and to accept contributions. He suggested the Illinois Staats-Zeitung and Tribune. Mr. Peabody wanted the First National Bank to be chosen for the purpose. The chairman was opposed. The motion was made, [it was explained] because many people are willing to help, but do not know whom to see about it.</p>
   <p>Mr. Peabody then made a motion that the collected money should be sent to the mayor of Budapest. The president then declared that, should such a procedure be adopted recognition for all this work would be given to Chicago, and not to the Club, precisely as happened several years ago, when money was <pb facs="5422061_2_1089.jpg" n="3"/>sent to Pest. The meeting was then adjourned until next Sunday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
