<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-06-02">June 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Performance of "The Exchanged Bride"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0272</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0272.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-06-02">June 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">PERFORMANCE OF "THE EXCHANGED BRIDE"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A crowded house enjoyed last Sunday the performance of "The Exchanged Bride", an excellently written three-act comedy, the product of our esteemed compatriot and author, Paul Berak, who has earned great laurels by writing this fine play. Those present at this performance will carry for a long time the remembrance of it in their hearts.</p>
   <p>The performers, the best amateur players in Chicago, raised the play to a high level with their ability and zeal. As there is much comedy in the play, the public laughed repeatedly. The plot of the play revolves around some boarders and their relations with their landladies.</p>
   <p>The role of "John Soos", an American-Hungarian worker, was played by Charles Csajaghy with his usual skill. Soos' wife, "Mariska" was personified by Mrs. Francis Werbovsky, who took hold of the interest of the public with <pb facs="5422061_2_0273.jpg" n="2"/>her extremely delightful acting. In the role of Mariska's sister "Helene", Mrs. Werbovsky's daughter, Marion, reaped great success, as she can act almost as well as her mother. Louis Klajnik was very good in the role of "Steve Keseru", another Hungarian-American worker. "Alex", the head waiter, was excellently rendered by Charles Hatvary, our own favorite opera singer, who, at the request of the public, on several occasions had to repeat his beautiful songs, for which all expressed their gratitude with hurricanes of applause.</p>
   <p>The role of "Sarfy", the tavernkeeper, was played exceedingly well by Bertalan Saly. Joseph Gonczy gave a perfect rendition of "Susak", an American-Hungarian worker, and Mrs. Joseph Horvath was very good in the role of Susak's wife.</p>
   <p>Joseph Ratkay played well as "Kovacs", a Hungarian-American worker. "Mrs. Kovacs" was well interpreted by Mrs. Alexander Ruzsinsky. The serious role of "Kolay", a newspaper editor, was successfully played by Joseph Kocsis.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0274.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Mici", a Hungarian-American actress, was played by Helen Gyorke, who earned much applause. The role of Mici's partner, "Juci", an actress was played by Elisabeth Csajaghy, the amiable and sympathetic wife of our good friend Charles Csajaghy. She made a great impression with the audience. Paul Oswath was excellent as the gypsy band leader "Laci", as was Mrs. Stephen Fazekas in the role of "Mrs. Hartnett". In the smaller roles, John Kary and Steve Demeter were very good.</p>
   <p>After the successful performance, there followed a dance, the music for which was furnished by the celebrated orchestra of Joseph Kovacs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
