<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1937-06-11">June 11, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Graduation Festival at Roman Catholic School in Burnside</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0328</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0328.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1937-06-11">June 11, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">GRADUATION FESTIVAL AT ROMAN CATHOLIC SCHOOL IN BURNSIDE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This year the Roman Catholic School in Burnside held its graduation festival Sunday afternoon at the Hungarian House. There was a large crowd present, such as is only seen on the occasion of the great national festivals. Those who came could see for themselves how well this School had taught the new generation to become good Catholics and useful and loyal American citizens. It was apparent to all present that these youths will not forget the land of their ancestors and will never be ashamed of their origin.</p>
   <p>The program of the festival was really very good. After the class of ten girls and eleven boys had sung its farewell song, Margaret Grand, speaking for her classmates, thanked the teachers and parents for their interest and efforts. In his commencement address Reverend Ernest Horvath advised the graduates to apply themselves with renewed zeal to the course of their future, <pb facs="5422061_2_0329.jpg" n="2"/>and then he presented the class with their diplomas. Reverend Horvath also commended the parents of the graduates for their sacrifices in making possible the education of their children.</p>
   <p>Especially nice was the Minuet of the little tots; they tiptoed hither and yon with sweet childish uncertainty, clad in droll crinoline and white wigged. The uniformed boys' troops very cleverly staged a mimic baseball play, then the sixth and seventh grade boys marched in and captured the attention of the audience with their Hungarian songs, during which three groups of the girls, clad in red, white, and green formed very attractively the Hungarian National Flag. But probably the best part of the program was the "Dream of the Hungarian Child," in which the enemies of great Hungary tore apart the territory of Hungary, each stealing a part of it, but in the end the Almighty God made them give back to Hungary all the territories they had stolen from her.</p>
   <p>The last number on the program was a dramatic presentation which was most <pb facs="5422061_2_0330.jpg" n="3"/>remarkable because all of the girls who played in it spoke the Hungarian language with astonishing clearness.</p>
   <p>The credit for the success of the School, which was reflected in this festival, belongs to Reverend Ernest Horvath, and to the teachers of the School, the Holy Sisters, in whose bosoms beat real Hungarian hearts, and who must have worked more than their share to attain such success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
