<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-07-28">July 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Icus Kiszely Departed for Budapest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-07-28">July 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">ICUS KISZELY DEPARTED FOR BUDAPEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When these lines reach our readers, Icus Kiszely, beloved singing lark of the Hungarians of Chicago,is nearing Budapest, where she will continue her singing studies at the Music Academy.</p>
   <p>Icus Kiszely left by train for New York last Thursday. There she booked passage on the fast steamer "Europa", which took her overseas. The actress is greatly missed by her parents, sisters, and a multitude of her friends and admirers. Her departure has created some sort of emptiness in the never too crowded artist life of the Hungarians in Chicago.</p>
   <p>But Icus Kiszely's destiny is to reach the highest regions of art, so that her talent may turn into a sparkling star enveloping the horizon of the Hungarian singing art in a brilliant light. To attain this, her European studies are necessary.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0091.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Therefore, all of us have to accept this inevitable temporary loss, in the knowledge that Icus Kiszely will return in a few years, enriched with great fame and laurels, to our circles and will again delight the Chicago Hungarians with her perfected art, educated voice, and charming personality.</p>
   <p>Icus Kiszely says through our paper goodbye to all her acquaintances, whom she could not see before leaving, and asks the Hungarians of Chicago to remember her just as she will always remember them from far away.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
