<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-10-30">Oct. 30, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Karolyi Again</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1781</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1781.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-10-30">Oct. 30, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">KAROLYI AGAIN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>And now the State Department is bent on showing how stubborn it can be. It continues to refuse to admit Countess Karolyi into this country. Last year, they [the officials of the Department]admitted the countess and permitted her to speak; they even admitted Count Karolyi, although he was refused permission to speak. Now they will admit neither the count nor the countess.</p>
   <p>The alleged reason for not admitting them into this country is that they they are Communists. This charge is untrue and absurd. Count Karolyi was the first president of the Hungarian republic, an enemy of the Hapsburgs, an enemy of feudalism, a democrat and a patriot, who upheld the ideals we professed to be fighting for in the World War. The position he took at great personal risk helped to shorten the war and thus saved many American lives. It is not necessary to proclaim him the <pb facs="5422061_2_1782.jpg" n="2"/>great statesman that he is; it is enough to say that he has stood for the things America has always honored, that as an exile from the tyranny which now dominates Hungary he is of the same line of men as Kossuth and Schurz, whom America delighted to honor. Only that miserable, sham Americanism which poses as good Americanism would question his right under American tradition to come here when he likes and to say what he pleases.</p>
   <p>From Mr. Kellogg and his high-hat bureaucrats no understanding of the American tradition in these matters is to be expected. The appeal must be addressed to President Coolidge, who recently has most eloquently professed his faith in traditional American liberty. If the spirit of his Omaha speech to the American Legion is the President's own spirit, then he will either not hesitate to reverse this ridiculous and disgraceful ruling, or he will produce reasons to have the order reversed.</p>
   <p>But in any event, the time has come for Congress to repeal the laws under which the State Department exercises such arbitrary powers. The opportunity is open to Congress to strip a stupid bureaucracy of <pb facs="5422061_2_1783.jpg" n="3"/>a power that it is unfit to exercise and a power it should not have. There is no conceivable reason why, in times of peace, a few officials should have the power to exclude or to gag foreigners by secret proceedings.</p>
   <p>In repealing this statutory power, Congress will be protecting the good name of America. It is not fair to the American people that they should be regarded as arrogant and ridiculous in the eyes of the world because of the underhanded and arbitrary acts of a few bureaucrats.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
