<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-03-18">Mar. 18, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Results of the "Beggar Prince" Performance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0209</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0209.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-03-18">Mar. 18, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">RESULTS OF THE "BEGGAR PRINCE" PERFORMANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A rare treat was had by those Hungarians of Chicago who attended the performance of the "Beggar Prince" on the afternoon of March 13 at the Central Theatre, 64 East Van Buren Street. The story was written by Leo Ascher. The production was held under the auspices of the Hungarian-American Theatrical Productions Company.</p>
   <p>Not long ago, the leaders of this production company were so disheartened with the attitude of the Chicago-Hungarians toward their performances that they announced that in the future they would not come to Chicago because, when given in Chicago, they were not successful, financially.</p>
   <p>The leaders of the production company, as well as the artists, were skeptical in the promise that the support of the performance would be sufficient. At this performance, the entire company was deceived, for the Hungarian culture loving people responded in great numbers. Over four hundred disappointed patrons were turned away. Among these four <pb facs="5422061_2_0210.jpg" n="2"/>hundred, were those employed by the Magyar Tribune. It was impossible to secure either seats or standing room. So it was impossible for us to see the performance, or know, first hand, what happened.</p>
   <p>We can only report about the performance from what we hear from those actually present during the performance. This is not much, which adds to our disappointment. Although we were deprived of the privilege of viewing the performance, we still are able to imagine how our fine arts friends were able to perform to the best of their ability, to understand the story, and impart realistic performances.</p>
   <p>We know the fine art players very well, and for this reason we know that such performers as Steffi Hegyesi, Boske Dobo, Julia Varadi, Mary Kondor, Louis Hededus, Aladar Zsadanyi, Louis Horvath, Sandor Palasthy, Karl Darvas, and Istvan Toth, are performers of the first class in fine arts productions. The leaders of the Hungarian-American Theatrical Productions Company have announced that they will return to Chicago on April 17.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0211.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They promised to make arrangements to accommodate more Hungarian fine arts and culture lovers on their return. They have rented the Aryon Grotto Theatre for this performance, at 8th Street and Wabash Avenue.</p>
   <p>It would be very advisable for all of us to purchase our tickets as early as possible for we believe that even though this theatre is much larger, there will be a few hundred more disappointed patrons turned away at this next performance without seats or standing room.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
