<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-02-14">Feb. 14, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Count Michael Karolyi's Lectures in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1711</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1711.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-02-14">Feb. 14, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">COUNT MICHAEL KAROLYI'S LECTURES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Count Michael Karolyi lectured in Chicago at the Masonic Hall last Sunday. The Hall, which can accommodate two thousand persons, was crowded with Hungarians. The meeting was opened by Stephen Fay, Karolyi's Chicago representative, who arranged the gathering.</p>
   <p>Count Michael Karolyi's lecture was very interesting and supplied much historical data about the October revolution, his exile, and Hungary's present situation.</p>
   <p>He revealed, backing his assertions with evidence, who are the real traitors in Hungary. He pointed out the probable outcome of the present dictatorship in Hungary and drew a general picture of where Fascism, the greatest scourge of humanity, will lead the people of Europe.</p>
   <p>According to Karolyi, only a socialist form of government can save Europe <pb facs="5422061_2_1712.jpg" n="2"/>from its present chaos and would bring about a United States of Europe.</p>
   <p>Monday evening Karolyi lectured at the Burnside Magyar Home to a huge crowd. The audience listened enthralled to the great Hungarian exile....</p>
   <p>Sunday evening there was a supper for Karolyi's more intimate friends at the Sherman Hotel's penthouse, where Karolyi is staying during his Chicago visit. Several prominent Americans were present at this dinner, among them City Attorney William Saltiel, Mr. Lovett, editor of the New Republic; Richard Folso, noted lawyer; Mr. Herb, who represented the Chicago Chamber of Commerce; and Mr. Swift, vice-president of the Workers' Bank.....</p>
   <p>One of the most noteworthy of Karolyi's public lectures was given at the City Club of Chicago. The auditorium of the City Club was filled to overflowing by Americans who were interested in hearing the great exiled Hungarian president......</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1713.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We can say that Karolyi's visit to Chicago met with success among the Hungarian workers, among the Hungarian middle class, and among exclusive American circles. The press wrote sympathetically about him, giving in detail his colorful career.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
