<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-02-13">Feb. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Hungarian Benefit Societies Federation Annual Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0905</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0905.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-02-13">Feb. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE HUNGARIAN BENEFIT SOCIETIES FEDERATION ANNUAL MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A very interesting and important meeting was held by the Hungarian Benefit Societies Federation on January 31. This meeting was the annual meeting of this organization, and many important matters regarding the functions and activities of this organization were discussed.</p>
   <p>The proceedings of the meeting were as follows:</p>
   <p>George Mihok opened the meeting with an address. Following this, the president pro-tem, Andrew Simko, conducted the meeting most efficiently and with great interest.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0906.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Alex Kirner, secretary of the organization, made a complete report in a very pleasing manner. The secretarial record was then accepted. The report reads as follows:</p>
   <p>If we look back over the happenings of the past year, we find that the Hungarians are afflicted with a great fault, namely; the true Hungarian charitable spirit is lacking and, instead, great jealousies have sprung up among various organizations. This condition has hurt our organization. The reason is that many of our Hungarian families are afraid to admit their own nationality.</p>
   <p>This organization was founded as a charitable organization and depends upon its members to contribute and to keep this cause alive. Consequently, <pb facs="5422061_2_0907.jpg" n="3"/>the smaller the membership the less we can contribute to aid widows and orphans. This small organization has for its main idea the principle of friendship, and this idea can be maintained with a few dollars. This organization is not looking for great financial standing. Therefore, no one should try to give up friendship and love for wealth.</p>
   <p>This does not mean that the officials of this organization are voicing their disgust, but on the contrary, they feel that even if they cannot contribute much, they do so with a true heart.</p>
   <p>This organization began in 1919 with a membership of 494. During this year, nine members died; each of whom had a family. The families of these men received the full benefits of this organization. One man was crippled.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0908.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>His family received one-half benefits from us.</p>
   <p>During the course of the year, 52 members were dropped from the roll for various reasons, having a membership of 432 to date.</p>
   <p>The above is a synopsis of the report as made by Alex Kirner, secretary. He presented the facts in a comprehensive manner and they were received cordially by the audience.</p>
   <p>In the above statement made by Mr. Kirner, it is readily seen that the Hungarian people are drifting away from their own organizations and joining the insurance companies in America. Many Hungarian people are led <pb facs="5422061_2_0909.jpg" n="5"/>astray by fake insurance companies. Consequently they loose the policies of their own Hungarian Benevolent Associations. This is the reason why the membership in Hungarian Societies is decreasing.</p>
   <p>The treasurer made a financial report, which was also found satisfactory.</p>
   <p>After making many important resolutions, the officers of the Federation were elected.</p>
   <p>Following is the list: President, George Mihok; vice-president, Samuel Beluscsak; secretary, Alex Kirner; treasurer, Lucas Kondrath. The trustees were: Andrew Pasztor and John Pachmeyer.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0910.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>After this meeting, the newly elected officers and the members dined together. Everyone present expressed his satisfaction and hoped for a more prosperous future.</p>
   <p>This organization originated in Chicago, and has branches throughout the State of Illinois with headquarters in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
