<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1937-08-26">Aug. 26, 1937</date><title level="a">Dedication of New Parish Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1416</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1416.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1937-08-26">Aug. 26, 1937</date><title level="a">DEDICATION OF NEW PARISH HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A highly successful festival in the life of Hungarian society was that in which the Hungarian Roman Catholic Church in Burnside had on the occasion of the dedication of the new parish home. The Catholics of the vicinity of Chicago also were represented in great numbers on this festival occasion of their brother Catholics.</p>
   <p>Early in the forenoon, the delegations of the local and out-of-town churches, associations, and priests gathered, to participate in the grand parade. The celebration of the Holy Mass followed and then the dedication ceremony.</p>
   <p>With flying colors, and to the strains of the band, they marched after the church services to the Hungarian House, where the banquet waited. The arrangement committee prepared for about four hundred guests, but there was service for four hundred fifty. To their great surprise, there were more than eight hundred persons present for dinner.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1417.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>During, and after, the banquet, there were many speakers. For the entertainment of the public, The Chicago Juniors and Amateur Club presented some very artistically trained dancers, who performed several group numbers and were clad in Hungarian national costumes. Alice Halmos, the young dancer, delighted the public with her beautiful dances; Elisabeth Biro, whom the world renowned Hungarian songwriter accompanied on the piano, sang some beautiful songs, which the public received with a tremendous enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>The young people danced with great joy in the ball-room of the Hungarian House until early morning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
