<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1928-11-11">Nov. 11, 1928</date><title level="a">Andrew Fejes Appeals Ruling.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0813</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0813.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1928-11-11">Nov. 11, 1928</date><title level="a">ANDREW FEJES APPEALS RULING.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.6.....Andrew Fejes, President of the Verhovay Aid Society, was suspended from office for his participation in the purchase of securities from the Westminister Bond and Mortgage Co. According to the judgment, Andrew Fejes transacted this business alone, and also gave an order for $50,000 worth of securities to the company; if the other officers wouldn't have consented to pay for it, they could have been compelled to do so by a court order.</p>
   <p>According to the by-laws of the association, suspended officers may appeal within thirty days, and Andrew Fejes did hand in his appeal. In the appeal he contradicts every statement of the prosecution and concludes that he is not morally responsible for the unlucky purchase of securities. He denies giving the firm an order in November,1925 on the contrary, he wired the society's legal counsel and later personally advised him against the deal. To prove that he had nothing to gain by this transaction, he points to the fact that the commission on this sale was paid to the Verhovay Aid.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0814.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Against Fejes is the fact that he signed the order Jan. 1. He defends himself by stating that he didn't know that certain officers of the society were working against him underhandedly. He goes on to say that Emil Pressburg, owner of Westminister Co., only received the order Feb. l.and that it wouldn't become Final until positive proof was shown as to the soundness of the securities.</p>
   <p>Fejes instructed legal counsel to ascertain whether the underwriters, United Lloyd were financially responsible. Legal counsel, according to Fejes, said the he found everything in order and that he saw no reason for not buying.</p>
   <p>Fejes suspects an officer and one of the directors to have had a hand in stock purchases. They made commissions and didn't account to the society. He wants a special meeting to be called where it will be decided who are the real culprits.</p>
   <p>Fejes wants satisfaction from the Verhovay. If he doesn't get it he will sue for $200,000 - even though he loves the society he has helped build.</p>
   <p>The society will investigage and if Andrew Fejes proves to be innocent, he will <pb facs="5422061_2_0815.jpg" n="3"/>undoubtedly receive satisfaction. It is up to the society to find out whether the charges made by Fejes against two leaders are true. It is for the good of the society to clear up this matter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
