<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-11-20">Nov. 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Reverend Norman B. Barr Honored by Hungary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1674</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1674.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-11-20">Nov. 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">REVEREND NORMAN B. BARR HONORED BY HUNGARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Those who know the noble personality of Reverend Norman B. Barr, superintendent of the Olivet Institute, will greatly rejoice at the good news that this gray-haired, noble-spirited gentleman has been honored by the Alliance of Social Associations of Hungary with its beautiful Great Cross and Honorary Diploma.</p>
   <p>In the person of Reverend Barr the Hungarians possess a great friend, of whom they can rightly be proud. For thirty-four years he has been the head and, so to say, the founder, the leader, and the soul of the forty-year-old Olivet Institute, and as such he is one of the outstanding personalities in Chicago society. His life has always been very clean, almost holy, and this, coupled with his unselfishness and devotion to his work, has earned him such an esteem as only few people, like Jane Addams and Graham Taylor, can boast. The Olivet Institute, which is now world renowned as the social service center <pb facs="5422061_2_1675.jpg" n="2"/>of the lower northern part of Chicago, is the mirror and true embodiment of his personality.</p>
   <p>Many years ago he noticed the neglected religious morale of the Hungarians in Chicago's North Side and turned his attention to finding a remedy. He tried to improve conditions by employing some Hungarian priests, like Zoltan Irsay, Rudolph Pompl, and even went so far as to rent a church for this purpose at 1824 Burling Street. When Nettie Fowler McCormick made a donation of three hundred thousand dollars, Reverend Barr built the present Olivet Institute (Now worth $500,000) and invited Reverend Steve Csaktornyay in 1928 to serve as priest for the Hungarians.</p>
   <p>Reverend Barr does not restrict his aid only to the spiritual needs of the Hungarians; he joins them in their demand for justice for Hungary. When the Middle West Section of the Hungarian Revision League appealed to him, asking that he deliver a speech over the radio, he gladly responded to it and spoke in the interest of the revision of the Treaty of Trianon over <pb facs="5422061_2_1676.jpg" n="3"/>the Daily News' radio station, which speech made a great sensation everywhere.</p>
   <p>Later, at the request of the Revision League, he too affixed his signature to the petition of ten thousand Hungarians [Translator's Note: Reverend Barr is not a Hungarian; he just saw the sufferings of the Hungarians during his extensive travels in Central Europe after the World War.], asking the revision of the Treaty of Trianon, and he sent it to the League of Nations, from where the answer also was addressed to him. Lately he has been following with interest the endeavors of Senator Borah, and is always read to work for the Hungarian cause.</p>
   <p>The Hungarians of the Olivet Institute, the Hungarian League for Revision, and the Magyar Club of Chicago have worked together to procure for Reverend Barr the recognition of the Hungarians of Hungary for his unselfish work in behalf of the Hungarian cause. Dr. Elmer Horvath, president of the Magyar Club of Chicago, on his return from Europe, brought <pb facs="5422061_2_1677.jpg" n="4"/>over with him the beautiful Great Cross and the Honorary Diploma of the Alliance of Social Associations of Hungary, which was bestowed on Reverend Barr. In the dipoloma, Reverend Barr was "enrolled among the best of Hungary."</p>
   <p>In honor of Reverend Norman B. Barr, a great banquet is contemplated for December 5 in the Allerton Hotel, where the ceremony of decoration will take place before many American guests, to whom the Hungarians of Chicago wish to demonstrate the great and never-ending gratitude they feel toward their unselfish friend, Reverend Norman B. Barr.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
