<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-05-07">May 7, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">New Relief Activities in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1060</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1060.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-05-07">May 7, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">NEW RELIEF ACTIVITIES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hungarian Relief activities, which have been going on for the past three months, in order to aid starving Hungarian children, have conducted a very deserving work, gathering donations totaling more than $50,000. As this activity grew older, certain conditions developed which made it very difficult to get donations for this noble cause.</p>
   <p>It was found that the Hungarians were too weak financially to make sufficent donations to meet the requirements of the fund necessary to take care of these starving children of Hungary. Other donations from people who might well affort it, were small, due to the fact that there were other nationalities conducting similar campaigns. This particular situation was not <pb facs="5422061_2_1061.jpg" n="2"/>only faced by the Hungarians, but all the other nationalities as well.</p>
   <p>A suggestion, made by the American Society of Friends, was very eagerly accepted by the different national groups.</p>
   <p>We find it necessary to explain to our readers who the American Society of Friends are. In America, there is a religious sect which is one of the oldest religious groups in this country, and are known as Quakers. They do not believe in War, and will not become involved in any enterprise where human life is at stake. This being one of their methods of teaching the faith of Christ. It is a well known fact that the United States exempted the Quakers from enlisting as soldiers. In order to <pb facs="5422061_2_1062.jpg" n="3"/>show their patriotism, and true religions beliefs, they formed the "American Society of Friends" at the outbreak of the War. Work was begun immediately when circumstances permitted. France was the first country where they started their noble work. Out of the ruined towns in this country, they re-constructed fifteen towns. They plowed vast fields, and planted various grain in order that they would produce life-giving materials. After the War, they immediately moved into the countries that were more centrally located. Germany, Austria, Russia, and even Hungary, enjoyed some of the blessed work of this good-hearted organization. What they did in Hungary can be readily seen. When railroad transportation was practically at a stand still, and hospitals were <pb facs="5422061_2_1063.jpg" n="4"/>in dire need of supplies, this organization used its own trucks to transport supplies, and in many cases, used their own supplies to aid these hospitals.</p>
   <p>This organization has submitted the following suggestion to the different foreign relief groups: To incorporate all the various foreign relief groups into one organization. Through this incorporation, the group would only have to solicit contributions only once from the American public, thereby they would receive larger contributions from individuals. The American press would cooperate in this movement, and it would supply publicity for this unified organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1064.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This proposition was taken up at a luncheon here in Chicago. Representatives from Germany, Hungary, Austria, Russia, Czecho-Slovakia, and Jugo-Slovakia, were present. The representative Hungarians who were present at this meeting were: Joseph Byfield. Dr. Stephen Barath, Mrs. Reiss, and Leo H. Laszlo. These representative Hungarians were very well satisfied with this proposition. Mr. Joseph Byfield was selected as the chairman of all Hungarian committies that will take part in this work.</p>
   <p>This luncheon also served as a medium through which the different nationaliites could bring about a more friendly feeling and a better understanding towards each other.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1065.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>This newspaper will supply accurate information in regard to this work and its progress. We feel sure our readers are deeply interested in this new development.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
