<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1924-11-14">Nov. 14, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Hungarian Home Idea</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0975</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0975.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1924-11-14">Nov. 14, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE HUNGARIAN HOME IDEA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The idea of a Hungarian Home has been considered for a long time in Chicago. The Hungarian Societies' Central Committee has put this idea forth as their main goal.</p>
   <p>Last fall it looked as though the idea was really going to become a reality, but it went up in smoke during the last minute.</p>
   <p>Now it looks as though the idea is going to take form again. It has gone so far that the committee has selected a building which they plan on rehabilitating, and they have practically decided to buy it, but this is not possible, because they do not have the necessary funds.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0976.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Before they actually buy such a place, we hope that the following advice is taken by the committee.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian Home will not be a business or speculative proposition, but it will be a foundation for a Hungarian institution where the different Hungarian organizations can hold their meetings and their various types of entertainments.</p>
   <p>Therefore the first question arises; is the building which was selected suitable for these purposes?</p>
   <p>There is a big difference between the construction of an ordinary home and a building which is to be occupied for purposes such as this building is to be used for; the health conditions and fire hazards must also be taken into consideration.</p>
   <p>There are many of us who have bought and sold homes, some people for themselves, <pb facs="5422061_2_0977.jpg" n="3"/>and others for business reasons, but all this does not qualify us to be experts when it comes to purchasing a piece of property which is to be used for the interest of all Hungarians in the city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Therefore, before the committee finally decides to buy this property, we believe it is their duty to call in a few experts to make inspection, and through their advice, decide whether or not it suits the purposes for which it is to be used.</p>
   <p>An architect, a contractor, and a capable lawyer should be selected. These people understand the laws, and they would be in a position to accurately state how much it would cost to reconstruct a building so that it could be used by the different Hungarian organizations. Then the committee can decide whether they can afford to buy and reconstruct such a building.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0978.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>When the committee is ready to submit a report stating the total cost of such a building, they can expect donations from individuals as well as the Hungarian Societies, thereby bringing to fruition the idea that the Hungarian Home may become a reality.</p>
   <p>If the committee foolishly buys an old building according to the figures and sales talk of agents who tell them what a good buy it is, and how much profit there will be, the Hungarian Home idea will be a complete flop.</p>
   <p>The smart businessman figures out his expenses and the prospects of the future.</p>
   <p>We are not experts in building and construction principles, but some other people called our attention to the fact that this building would have to be completely reconstructed internally, and we feel that these facts should be presented to the Hungarians of Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0979.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We hope that this Hungarian Home idea which is actually taking form among Chicago Hungarians will end without misunderstanding.</p>
   <p>We should forget the things that happened in the past, and we do not want anyone to commit such wrongs. We do not want the committee to present the Hungarian Home as a reality until they are sure of themselves, because if they do, it will only create a feeling of distrust and may become a laughing stock.</p>
   <p>If such piece of property does not fit the purpose, we would rather see them drop the deal than have the whole idea fall through, and all the donations of individuals and societies be lost.</p>
   <p>Serious thought must be given even when a private individual makes an investment of twenty-five thousand dollars. Much more consideration must be given when we <pb facs="5422061_2_0980.jpg" n="6"/>must think of the welfare and investment of the entire Hungarian population of Chicago.</p>
   <p>If the Hungarian Societies' Central Committee can not show a definite and sincere effort toward success in creating a Hungarian Home, then the interest of the Hungarian people will be led astray from all such ideas which aim to lead to the betterment of the Hungarian people.</p>
   <p>We expect this organization to supply the Hungarian people with adequate information in regards to the development of the idea, because the interest of the people is very apparent.</p>
   <p>As far as we are concerned we present our ideas with the greatest sincerity, and we stand ready at all times with the pages of our newspaper to aid the committee and the entire Hungarian population.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
