<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-05-12">May 12, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">"Women Hater" a Sensational Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0275</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0275.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-05-12">May 12, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">"WOMEN HATER" A SENSATIONAL SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sweet, charming Hungarian song and music filled the North Side Turner Hall last Sunday, where a group of players from the Chicago Hungarian Amateur and Singing Circle brought on the stage the beautiful operetta "The Women Hater", under the masterly direction of Joseph B. Mayer.</p>
   <p>The play was very well chosen, it being one of the best Hungarian romantic plays, and its heart-enlivening and soul-refreshing music simply creeps through the ears into the very hearts of the listeners.</p>
   <p>It is due to the unsurpassed artistic sense of Joseph B. Mayer that he succeeded in bringing this piece to the stage in such precise arrangement, such excellent rendering, such careful distribution of roles, and in such beautiful stage setting. Certainly in this latter task he was assisted by the Singing Circle, which did <pb facs="5422061_2_0276.jpg" n="2"/>not spare any sacrifice to offer the public the best possible performance. Next to Mayer's share in bringing this play to such success, is that of the performers, who did their best in making the play a success by their artistic accomplishment and so have the right to share the laurels too.</p>
   <p>In the role of Cilike, Tinike Kovacs, whose God-given talent would merit her enrollment in any company of professional artists, had a brilliant success. Her songs were so charming and her acting so full of grace that the audience had to applaud her almost continually.</p>
   <p>We were greatly pleased to note the return to the stage of Mrs. Francis Werbovszky, this veteran soul of the art, the Irene Klacsman [Translator's note: This was her stage name before she married], whom the Hungarian theater missed for so long. She played the role of "Lina," the divorcee, with a temperament that only an Irene Klacsman can possess. Her acting was so realistic that for a moment the audience feared that this temperamental woman would in fact use the double-barreled shotgun she held in her hands. It is only <pb facs="5422061_2_0277.jpg" n="3"/>natural that she would reap great success once again, just as she always did in the past whenever she appeared on the stage.</p>
   <p>Charles Csajaghy surpassed all his previous stage successes in his skillful rendering of an obstinate Hungarian landowner, whose will could not be disputed but who at last succumbed to the demands of the heart and became a lamb in the hands of his second wife. The public rewarded him with well-merited applause.</p>
   <p>In the role of "Tony Cziha," George Pasztor was excellent. He spoke in correct Hungarian and received great applause for his mastery of stage technique, his agreeable voice, his excellent acting, and his quiet humor.</p>
   <p>Grandiose was the acting of Frank Szabo, who played the role of the priest of Ipafa. He brought out the whole character of his role so wonderfully that he secured the success of the play as well as his own.</p>
   <p>Martha Schwartz was also good in the role of "Manci Mandula," and so was <pb facs="5422061_2_0278.jpg" n="4"/>Zsofika Palagyi, who won great success in the role of "Irma."</p>
   <p>Also good in their smaller roles were: [Translator's Note: Here follow twenty-five names], who contributed to the great success of the performance. The lion's share, of course, belongs to Joseph B. Mayer for his masterly work in arranging the play and training the performers. A great deal of credit is due Gladys Bauer, who accompanied with artistic precision the musical part of the play, the veteran prompter of the Singing Circle, Gizella Weiner, and the stage director Albert Komjathy.</p>
   <p>That this performance attained such excellent financial and artistic success is unquestionably the result of the efforts of the Committee of Entertainments, for which its members deserve to be praised, as they did the most thankless part of the performance.</p>
   <p>The performance was followed by a dance, which lasted well into the late hours of the night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
