<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-11-28">Nov. 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Thanksgiving Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1329</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.B.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1329.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-11-28">Nov. 28, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THANKSGIVING DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is hard for a person to recognize Thanksgiving when he or she is hungry, or if a brother or sister is hungry. We doubt that there is a single Hungarian family in the United States whose members did not fully satisfy their hunger last Thursday, Thanksgiving Day, but this is not the only day we want to talk about.</p>
   <p>Last year on Thanksgiving Day we were all very happy, due to the fact that the War had been ended and arms were laid aside on the blood soaked battlefields of Europe. Today, one year after, a thousand and one troubles have appeared before us.</p>
   <p>Peace is not restored. So-called peace has caused almost as much trouble, <pb facs="5422061_2_1330.jpg" n="2"/>misunderstanding, and suffering as the War itself.</p>
   <p>We cannot be thankful for conditions prevailing in Hungary today, unless we can be thankful for the fact that a strip of land and a handful of people have been spared, so that our century old nation and culture may survive.</p>
   <p>In the United States, peace was restored in the financial and political world. Last year a bitter war was fought in recognition of class distinction, and also in the fields of political reform. Even when considering these facts, we should be satisfied. Certainly conditions were unfavorable; the cost of living was high; but if we compare these with conditions in Hungary today, we really have something to be thankful for.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1331.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Hungarians living in the United States have been seriously affected by the fact that their brethren across the ocean were suffering so badly. But as good citizens of this country, Hungarian-Americans must admit that they did not suffer correspondingly in any way, shape or manner.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian people in the United States, earn their living by hard work, and many of them are underpaid, but there are no beggars among them, and very few suffering from hunger.</p>
   <p>Even if we do not get our share of the wealth of the United States, we have enough to help our suffering brothers across the sea, and have sufficient left for our own use. So let us remember that when we celebrate Thanksgiving Day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
