<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Geza Kende, <title>Magyars in America</title>, (Cleveland: Szabadsaz, <date when="1927">1927</date>), Vol. II. p. 208-227, Chap. XX1.
<title level="a">The First Kossuth Statue in America</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0744</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0744.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Geza Kende, <title>Magyars in America</title>, (Cleveland: Szabadsaz, <date when="1927">1927</date>), Vol. II. p. 208-227, Chap. XX1.
<title level="a">THE FIRST KOSSUTH STATUE IN AMERICA</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Where ever human rights are respected, where the people can grow enthusiastic over liberty, and can live and work for democracy, there they can also become enthusiastic about Kossuth, the Hungarian prophet of the world liberty, of immortal memory.</p>
   <p>The City Hall and the other public buildings were decorated with flags, the Public Square and in the crossing streets, the buildings, and store windows were adorned with American and Hungarian colors; at the entrance of department stores, on each side of the walls, gigantic tablets were suspended with the inscription: "Kossuth devoted his life to the cause of liberty. Ailyen a Magyar!"</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0745.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On the beautifully decorated balcony of the American House from which Louis Kossuth made his fiery speech on February 2, 1852 to the inhabitants of Cleveland, an inscription was also placed.</p>
   <p>Euclid Avenue was draped with flags and the people, in festal state of mind, are crowding the streets. But among the crowd one can easily recognize a Magyar. His gait is more erect, he carries himself with more pride. Happiness is radiating from his bright eyes, because the Kossuth statue is finished and placed to the satisfaction of the American-Magyars, and to the glory of the Magyar race. All obstacles have been removed.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0746.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On Saturday, September 21, 1902, at 2 p. M., a session was held in the Grand Hall of the Chamber of Commerce building.</p>
   <p>A multitude jammed the hall. The Magyars and Americans were united by Kossuth's spirit. The orchestra played the Rakoczy March. The Reformed Protestant Choir and audience sang the Hungarian National Anthem.</p>
   <p>After prayer, which was offered by Reverend Eleck Chrotorosh, Louis Percel, the president of the Committee, made a short welcoming speech and introduced General James Barnett, the honorary Chairman of the celebration. The gray-haired general who, as a young man, heard Louis Kossuth's silvery voice, made a speech abundant in poetic expressions. The next speaker was Col. Louis Black who introduced the other speakers in the order of their appearance on the program.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0747.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Charles P. Salen greeted the Magyars in the name of the city, relating Kossuth's action of world historic significance.</p>
   <p>Charles F. Thwing, president of the Western Reserve University, in his speech described the effect of Kossuth's ideas on the liberty movements of people, and concluding his speech, he said:</p>
   <p>"I do not understand a word of Hungarian, but shortly before you sang your National Anthem, my heart became filled with a deep sentiment and emotion. I could hear from its sounds the triumphal march of the liberated slaves. I could hear the prayer of a prisoner, languishing in a dark cell, who is not only praying for himself, but is imploring for the whole nation."</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0748.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Joseph Lseni, director of the National Alliance, who brought the National flag from Hungary, was the next speaker. He was acclaimed with an enthusiastic applause. Then Louis Bartok declaimed an ode written by him for the occasion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
