<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1931-05-17">May 17, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Every Hungarian Should Protest against Trianon on May 17</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1682</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1682.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1931-05-17">May 17, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">EVERY HUNGARIAN SHOULD PROTEST AGAINST TRIANON ON MAY 17</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>May 17 will be the day when Hungarians of the world will have an opportunity to voice their accusations against the injustice to Hungary of the Treaty of Trianon. The League of Nations will convene at Geneva to discuss the affairs of the minorities and to lighten their shackles until the time when they can be liberated.</p>
   <p>If the League is really an international institution, and if its duty is to judge the rights of the nations of this world, May 17th will be a historical day.</p>
   <p>We are of the opinion that the conscience of the world is still napping, that its judgment is biased by past horrors, and that it can only be awakened by loud voices. Therefore, all Hungarians in the four corners of the world should raise their voices in loud protest on May 17.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1683.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We aren't asking for favors, but demand justice for Hungary, and with one heart and soul we shall keep up our remonstrance until this hitherto unheard of injustice is remedied.</p>
   <p>Let us make May 17 a day to be remembered. Let all churches and other Hungarian organizations hold protest mass meetings on this day, and express their demands in cables. We are showing two sample texts for the convenience of our readers who wish to cable.</p>
   <p>Sample No. 1.</p>
   <p>The Chief Secretary</p>
   <p>of the League of Nations,</p>
   <p>Geneva, Switzerland.</p>
   <p>Deferred Cable</p>
   <p>Hungary for hundreds of years protected civilization. The League of Nations must render justice to this nation so unjustly and cruelly mutilated by the Treaty of Trianon.</p>
   <p>(Signature.)</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1684.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Sample No. 2</p>
   <p>If the League of Nations is to fulfill its high office, it has now the opportunity to render justice to the thousand-year-old Hungary, which was at all times a forerunner of Western civilization in the East of Europe.</p>
   <p>(Signature.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
