<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-03-04">Mar. 4, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Meeting for Election of Officers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0871</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0871.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-03-04">Mar. 4, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">MEETING FOR ELECTION OF OFFICERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual meeting of officers and delegates of the Hungarian-American Benevolent Society was held on February 12 for the purpose of electing officers. A committee of three, who were to choose a president to conduct the meeting and take care of its affairs, was also chosen. Those elected to the committee were: Joseph Fekete, Julius Prekop, and Istvan Belustyak. The president is Andras Simko. Belustyak announced that, after examination of all the matters before the committee, everything was found to be in order.</p>
   <p>After this Mr. Simko, the president, took over the proceedings. He encouraged the delegates to perform their assigned tasks with greater strength. He asked the delegates to help make progress towards increasing the membership and income of the society.</p>
   <p>The secretary was asked to read the minutes of the last monthly meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0872.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The secretary read the minutes as follows: "We are all here to-night, not for the purpose of making new friends, for all of us here know one another very well, and at any rate we are all Hungarians, away from our homeland, with but one aim. That one aim. which we all have, is to help our brother Hungarians in Chicago; in other words, we are to relieve them in case of death in their families. when we are aiding our brothers, they are better prepared to face their grief.</p>
   <p>"We are meeting here to-night to discuss our entire financial condition. If we look back on the 1920 records, we find that our membership has slightly increased, but to have a stronger foundation we must build up our membership. We know that many of the Hungarians in Chicago have sent their money to help their relatives in our homeland, and many others have returned to our homeland. Our task is not easy. We started the year of 1920 with 432 members, 42 members have dropped out, 6 members have died. We had 384 members left, who brought in 16 new members, making a total of 400 members. I am disheartened, for I have to announce that our fellow <pb facs="5422061_2_0873.jpg" n="3"/>member, Jancs Majlath, has just passed away after a very long sickness. Let her soul rest in peace. The term of assessment was set for February 25.</p>
   <p>"As at the annual meeting last year, the majority raised the point that the delegates did not receive payment for their services and expenses in the interest of the society. Although we are not as yet in an entirely secure financial condition, I believe we can afford to arrange, by vote, for a daily wage payment to the delegates for their services and expenses."</p>
   <p>After the annual accounting of income and expenses, the secretary announced the financial condition.</p>
   <p>Then Joseph Fekete was appointed to the office of auditor. Mr. Joseph Kocsis, Mr. Bert Bagameri, and Mr. Gabor Szaszi verified the final auditing of all the books, and reported that the accounts were accurate.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0874.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Then a supper was given, which was composed of delicious Hungarian delicacies. During the supper, speeches on conditions in the homeland were given by Mr. Simko, Mr. Fekete, and Mrs. Kozora, and as a result a fund of $11.15 was raised to be sent to the homeland. Then Mr. Kocsis, in his usual flowery language, expressed the gratitude of everyone for the wonderful and tasty supper prepared and served by Mrs. John Juszko, Mrs. John Pachmeyer, and Mrs. Samuel Belustyak.</p>
   <p>After the supper, Mr. Simko reopened the meeting, and asked the secretary to read the rules and regulations of the society. Then he requested the delegates to propose new movements of importance. Many desirable proposals were made. Mr. Fekete proposed that we name a committee for publications and advertisements. A vote was taken, and Mr. Kirner was elected, as were Mr. Fekete, Mr. Mihok, Mr. Kocsis, and Mr. Boszak. They were authorized to contract for one thousand inches of publicity.</p>
   <p>Then the matter of payment of wages to delegates was brought up. Those <pb facs="5422061_2_0875.jpg" n="5"/>delegates whose societies were unwilling to pay a daily wage voluntarily resigned, so as not to burden the society. It was decided that because such payments had never before been made, and in order to insure success of the plan, the society must arrange a form of entertainment, including a dramatic performance and a dance. Every member is to purchase a fiftycent ticket. A committee was elected to take care of all arrangements for providing an income for the payments of daily wages to delegates. The members are: Mr. Mihok, president; Mr. Belustyak, vice-president; Mr. Boszak, notary; Mr. Kirner, secretary; Mr. Kondrath, treasurer; the trustees are Mr. Pachmeyer, Mr. Andrew Pasztor, Mr. Labas, and Mr. Mike Skiba.</p>
   <p>A committee was named to take care of the individual societies' affairs; it was comprised of the following members: Mr. Packmeyer was named for the first-class societies, Mr. Kondrath for second class, Mrs. Bozak for third class, Mr. Serban for fifth class, Mr. John Csatlos for sixth class, Mr. Kirner for seventh class, Mr. Louis Szijjus for eighth class, <pb facs="5422061_2_0876.jpg" n="6"/>Mr. Simko for ninth class, Mr. Paul Bone for tenth class, Mr. A. Fukovits for eleventh class, and Mr. Joseph Pirko for twelfth class. Mr. Mihok went into detailed explanations of the work to be done by this committee.</p>
   <p>At six o'clock in the morning the meeting was adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
