<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1929-02-08">Feb. 8, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Business of the Verhovay Aid Society</title><title level="a" type="sub">by [Dr. Erno] Lowinger</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0806</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0806.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1929-02-08">Feb. 8, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE BUSINESS OF THE VERHOVAY AID SOCIETY</title><title level="a" type="sub">by [Dr. Erno] Lowinger</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Verhovayak Lapja (the Verhovay Journal), in its February issue, gives a report of the assets of the [Verhovay] Society. The report gives a clear picture of the Society's state of affairs, and reassures those who gave credence to disquieting rumors.</p>
   <p>So that our readers may have a conception of the present financial status of the Verhovay Aid Society, we present the official statement issued by the directors, and which we accept as true.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Securities, purchase price</cell>
     <cell>$1,535,769.48</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Interest-bearing bank deposits</cell>
     <cell>688,697.35</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Checking account</cell>
     <cell>43,347.44</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Total</cell>
     <cell>2,267,814.27</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0807.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Included in this total is the nominal value of bonds for $87,300, purchased from the Chicago Westminster Bond and Mortgage Company. The present value of these bonds is very uncertain.</p>
   <p>This bond company is in bankruptcy, but the bonds are not quite worthless, although no interest was paid to holders for some time. The underwriting company that guaranteed the bonds is also bankrupt. Nevertheless, some money can be realized from this investment.</p>
   <p>The considerable expense for incidentals, as well as the loss of nearly six thousand dollars interest annually, affects the treasury of the Verhovay pretty seriously, but there is no real danger threatening the Society itself, and the members have no cause to worry, as evidenced by the financial statement.</p>
   <p>Including the 5,842 members of the Young People's Group, the total membership of the Verhovay Aid Society, as of December 31, 1928, is 21,380.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0808.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We have been asked to discuss the affairs of the Verhovay Aid Society in our columns because a great many of our readers are its members.</p>
   <p>We do not wish to pour oil over the flames. Neither do we care to take part in personal controversies, for, lacking a thorough understanding of the situation, we would run the risk of being accused of partiality.</p>
   <p>Therefore, in the subsiding turmoil, we offer our criticism--objective, sincere, and constructive; not intended to serve as an accusation or an excuse. It is written in the interests of the ordinary members of the Verhovay Aid Society, members who have for years paid their dues conscientiously, so that when they die their families can be taken care of.</p>
   <p>To be an honest and prompt official and director of the Verhovay is commendable. These qualities are necessary, but not enough.</p>
   <p>When the Society in question has two and a quarter million dollars in cash and securities, the above-mentioned good qualities of its directors are not <pb facs="5422061_2_0809.jpg" n="4"/>sufficient. Other qualities and abilities are necessary.</p>
   <p>The investment and handling of this huge amount should be entrusted to professionals--financial experts.</p>
   <p>Had there been such professionals among the directors of the Verhovay, the bonds of the Westminster Bond and Mortgage Company would have never been purchased. Moreover, the greatest part of the capital would have never been invested in real-estate bonds--$1,500,000. These bonds are mostly from large buildings and hotels. It would have been wiser to distribute the securities as loans to businessmen, and as mortgages on smaller homes.</p>
   <p>The distribution of securities shows lack of experience.</p>
   <p>The investment of the cash was unprofessional also, and other motives than the secure placement of the death benefit fund should have guided the directors.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0810.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We acknowledge the fact that some small banks are just as trustworthy as the big ones, and that all banks are under federal supervision, all being more or less responsible.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, it is singular that two hundred thousand dollars--a third of the death benefit fund--is deposited in eight banks in Youngstown and two in Warren, Ohio.</p>
   <p>In our opinion, the first consideration is safety. We should get rid of the Hungarian custom of favoring friends and relatives when depositing the cash of the Verhovay. If this cannot be done totally, at least it could be reduced to a minimum.</p>
   <p>None of the cash of the Verhovay is invested in Chicago and New York, although there are big banks and Hungarian state banks in these cities, where many of the members of the Verhovay live.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0811.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>All the mistakes mentioned in this article could have been avoided had the Verhovay employed a financial expert to advise the directors about safe investments. This is the logical thing to do, just as they employ a doctor to decide on health problems, and an attorney on legal questions.....</p>
   <p>The future of the Verhovay depends on the right handling of its financial affairs more than on any other circumstance.</p>
   <p>This will be extremely important at the time when a larger number of old members will be taken away by death.</p>
   <p>We have given our suggestion.</p>
   <p>If the Verhovay directors haven't learned their lesson from the sad experience of others, let them learn from their own disappointments, such as the unfortunate investment in the Westminster bonds.</p>
   <p>We are glad to note from this financial statement that the errors of the past <pb facs="5422061_2_0812.jpg" n="7"/>did not stop the Verhovay's expansion and bright outlook for the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
