<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-10-01">Oct. 1, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">People of Hungary Still in Need of Help</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Captain Pedlow</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1046</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1046.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-10-01">Oct. 1, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">PEOPLE OF HUNGARY STILL IN NEED OF HELP</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Captain Pedlow</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We very often hear the question asked whether the people of Hungary are still in need of help from Hungarians residing in this country. I am sorry to say [this], but the people of Hungary are in dire need.</p>
   <p>From all indications last spring, the harvest this year was going to be very abundant. The people of Hungary expected a record harvest, but the weather conditions of the summer months made this impossible. Due to the failure of crops, the Hungarian farmers have practically lost everything, including their homes and farms.</p>
   <p>The number of unemployed is much larger this year than it was a year ago. Laborers, office workers and other specialized workers feel the strain of unemployment more this year than ever before.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1047.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The fate of these unfortunate people depends on you Hungarian-Americans. They have turned towards you, expecting aid from you. If these people do not receive aid from you who are more fortunate, there will be only one way out for them and that is death by way of suicide.</p>
   <p>During my last two visits to Hungary, it broke my heart to see the number of suicide cases multiply, and all this was due to the fact that it was impossible to earn a living.</p>
   <p>I am asking all you good Hungarians to do everything in your power to help your friends and relatives. I feel quite sure that the turning point is near, when it will be unnecessary for us in this country to aid those in our homeland.</p>
   <p>The present Hungarian government is proving itself successful and day by day it is gaining more recognition from the governments of other <pb facs="5422061_2_1048.jpg" n="3"/>nations, and this undoubtedly will aid its economic situation a great deal. I hope that it won't be long before I can come to you and say that aid to Hungary is unnecessary. But this time has not arrived, and until then these people have to live, and they are depending on their Hungarian-American friends for existence. Those people who expect to help by sending packages of clothing and other supplies must realize that the Hungarian government is extending many privileges for the handling and distributing of these packages.</p>
   <p>I urge all Hungarians to co-operate, and aid these poor suffering people of Hungary. The aid will be appreciated by the Hungarian government as well as the people. It is your duty to help.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
