<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune (Hungarian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1933-04-28">April 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Successful Performance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0284</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0284.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune (Hungarian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1933-04-28">April 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">SUCCESSFUL PERFORMANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A grateful and contented audience was present last Sunday at the theatrical performance given by the members of the Chicago First Hungarian Amateur and Youth Circle. The members of this Circle again gave proof of their being first-class amateur players able to perform a play so well as to be enjoyed by the public. Our friend, Joseph Kaszas, did again a masterly arranging. [Translator's Note: Title of the play and place where given not mentioned in the article]</p>
   <p>Mariska Horvath played the role of "Zsuzsika" so well that the audience shed tears, which can be easily understood, as in her play she was talking for the last time to her sweetheart, Steve Berzsenyi, a wounded soldier about to die in a field hospital, who told her his last wishes. No wonder there were no eyes left dry.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Charles Schmidt and Irene Thury, as nurses, rendered wonderful plays, as did Frank Balogh and Alexander Kreitz in their roles of wounded soliders, Anton Kovacs and Alexander Boman, as doctors, all of which contributed materially to the success of the play.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0285.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After this play there was a monologue, "Night Quarrel". In her role as a wife, Mrs. Matthew Hubert was, as she always is in whatever role she plays, excellent. Her partner, in the role of a drunken husband, was Joseph Kaszas, who gave an extraordinary good performance. The fact that all the amateurs played their roles so well can be credited to Mr. Kaszas' work as stage director. The prompter was Joseph Szenasy.</p>
   <p>The performance was folled by a dance with the orchestra of Miska Pal.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
