<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-03-28">Mar. 28, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Interesting Decision against the Registration of Foreigners</title><title level="a" type="sub">News of the Foreign Language Information Service</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1572</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1572.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-03-28">Mar. 28, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">INTERESTING DECISION AGAINST THE REGISTRATION OF FOREIGNERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">News of the Foreign Language Information Service</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Trustee Committee of the Foreign Language Information Service at its last meeting brought a decision which sharply opposes the different bills up for consideration in the United States Congress in the case of registration of foreigners.</p>
   <p>We publish the text of the decision below:</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Numerous bills were brought before Congress in the case of registration: or listing of foreigners, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The opinion of the Foreign Language Information Service is that such registration would only dismember and separate that part of the population which this nation desires to assimilate, and instead of increasing the loyalty and love of these foreigners for America these new laws will alienate them and <pb facs="5422061_2_1573.jpg" n="2"/>seriously retard their assimilation and naturalization, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, The opinion is expressed that, through registration, foreigners who are here illegally will not be exposed, although that is the purpose of the new law. On the other hand, numerous innocent foreigners and naturalized citizens would be persecuted by a spy system and shameful suspicion and there would be no end to spying, graft, and inhuman persecution, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, Such registration, even though voluntary, would become compulsory through various administrative orders and the demanding attitude of employers, and</p>
   <p>"Whereas, In the opinion of the F. L. I. S. the principle of the registration is wrong and unhealthy. It conflicts with the American conception of freedom for individuals, which is traditional. It would afford opportunity for violations and would raise more serious problems than the "evil" which it intends to stop. Summarizing all this <pb facs="5422061_2_1574.jpg" n="3"/>"It has been decided, That the Trustee-Committee of the Foreign Language Information Service will take a stand against all motions for the registration of foreigners, whether it is voluntary or compulsory, and emphatically urges Congress to discard all bills that advocate the registration or listing of foreigners."</p>
   <p>As in the past, the Foreign Language Information Service is now, too, watching out for the rights and interests of foreigners in America. However, if we want to avert the danger of registration, all language groups, their newspapers, and societies must co-operate. We, therefore, call the attention of the Hungarian newspapers, societies, and individuals and ask them to and write to their senators and congressmen that they, too, are opposed to the registration of foreigners.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
