<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-08-10">Aug. 10, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Announcement to Chicago Hungarians</title><title level="a" type="sub">Chicago, the Grandchild of Methuselah-Aged Metropolises, Celebrates its Hundredth Birthday in 1933.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0423</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0423.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-08-10">Aug. 10, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">ANNOUNCEMENT TO CHICAGO HUNGARIANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Chicago, the Grandchild of Methuselah-Aged Metropolises, Celebrates its Hundredth Birthday in 1933.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One hundred years. Nearly the age limit of man. In the life of a city a short time.</p>
   <p>The unprecedented quick development of this city gives significance to this jubilee, which will demonstrate the wonders of the twentieth century with a World's Fair. The Fair will show how the most beautiful city in the world was built in a hundred years on marshland overgrown with reeds.</p>
   <p>If there is truth to the saying that the head of the Union is New York, then its heart is Chicago.....</p>
   <p>During the winter months in certain cities, thirty per cent of the population was unemployed. In New York City it was seventeen per cent. In Chicago only <pb facs="5422061_2_0424.jpg" n="2"/>seven per cent were idle. This percentage will be even smaller as we near the completion of the plans for the World's Fair. It is natural that money comes to those who use it. It is certain that during the next five years the Chicago World's Fair will be the most outstanding commercial, technical, and cultural undertaking.</p>
   <p>What will we gain in these five years? Steady employment. The probability of higher wages. An opportunity to accumulate money. Learning and experience. Better and nicer life.</p>
   <p>And what is required of us in return? Confidence, loyalty, and consideration.</p>
   <p>The World's Fair will cost a fantastic sum. The preliminary work alone will be ten million dollars. Half of this amount should be guaranteed by the capitalists and the other half by the citizens and workers. This is not a gift, loan, or a tax that is required from the people of Chicago. It is an opportunity for a good investment when each Chicago resident, who can do so, buys ten admission tickets to the World's Fair at fifty cents each.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0425.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Each national group is allotted a quota according to their number. It is evident that Fair officals know exactly how many Hungarians live in Chicago. This city has never humiliated the Hungarians. We have enjoyed all the privileges extended to the Anglo-Saxon people. Therefore, we can't do less than other national groups. Whether we deserved to be treated well will become evident now.....For decades we would be disgraced if inferior races--yellow and black, or the Czechoslovaks, Roumanians, or Jugoslavs--should surpass us in doing their utmost to further this great cause.</p>
   <p>Any Hungarian who buys his ten tickets from an American or another national group will cause a loss to the Hungarian prestige. Each Hungarian organization will select individuals to sell tickets.....</p>
   <p>We expect every Hungarian of Chicago who is not an ungrateful citizen of this city, not only to purchase his tickets, but to aid in placing them elsewhere.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0426.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Hungarian Group of the Chicago World's Fair Committee</p>
   <p>Julius Hanko, secretary;</p>
   <p>Dr. Arpad Barothy, president;</p>
   <p>Kalman Balogh, Louis Nagy, Leo H. Laszlo, vice-presidents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
