<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1935-10-24">Oct. 24, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Wall Paintings of Nicholas Gaspar</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0151</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0151.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1935-10-24">Oct. 24, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">WALL PAINTINGS OF NICHOLAS GASPAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.5.....October 10, was the unveiling of the twenty-eight wall pictures, painted by the well-known Hungarian artist, Nicholas Gaspar in the Boy's Club, located on the 8th floor of the Union League Club.</p>
   <p>The Union League Foundation for Boy's Club was incorporated on December 26, 1919, so the poorer boys should also have some opportunity to indulge in the healthier amusements. The first club was opened on May 29, 1920 on the corner of 19th and Leavitt Streets. The second club was opened on April 3, 1927 at the corner of Lincoln and Emmerson Streets. In these clubs the boys found everything, that is close to their hearts: sports, work-exercises, reading, amusements.</p>
   <p>The wall pictures show in chronological order the phases of their development from the moment, when they first join the club to the time, when they leave it as determined young men. The pictures shows in serial order the work-shop, the gymnasium, swimming-pool, studio, club-room, reading-room etc. that is, the special world of the boys.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0152.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The artist, Gasper, solved his task with a remarkable success. With a striking directness he pictured the separate episodes, and through all a forceful life is pulsating.</p>
   <p>The guests and more so the members of the Foundation, who saw in the group of pictures the fulfillment of their sixteen years old desire, gave an enthusiastic ovation to the painter, who with this creation has given a lasting monument to Chicago, and honored the name of Hungarians. Every Hungarian has reason to be proud of these pictures and of their painter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
