<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-05-13">May 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Hungarians Prepare for Demonstration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1196</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1196.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-05-13">May 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO HUNGARIANS PREPARE FOR DEMONSTRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Without any trouble and with all truthfulness we can say that the Chicago Hungarians have co-operated with one heart in the plans of the gigantic demonstration of patriotism to take place on May fifth in Chicago. There has never been an occasion yet where the Chicago Hungarians co-operated with one another so whole-heartedly. Every lodge and society in Chicago has agreed that any personal or selfish interests should be eliminated in order that the Hungarian population of Chicago might be able to demonstrate its patriotic attitude towards the United States.</p>
   <p>In all the meetings that were held the spirit of co-operation prevailed. The affair has been publicized and announced at every social event that was being sponsored by Hungarians or Hungarian organizations. We are glad to say that the people of Chicago have taken this affair to heart. According to all signs, the undertaking will be very successful.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1197.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There were many people who took part in working out plans for the occasion. They worked tirelessly in order that the affair might be a success. The following men were a few of the tireless workers: Louis Nagy, Leo H. Loszlo, Bela Laky, Dr. Loringer, Nandon Robotkay, Beni Fodor, Bernat Schenk, H. Ormo, Stephen Soltesz, Henrik Borna, Emil Felizi, Martin Benedek, Eugene Grunfield, Emil Presszburg, John Koleszar, Charles Kassay, and many others.</p>
   <p>The success of the efforts of those who worked tirelessly will be demonstrated by the fact that for once the entire Hungarian population of Chicago will be together in one camp, leading itself.</p>
   <p>The meetings that have been held in the past few weeks have had great effect. At last the Hungarian people of Chicago have become acquainted with the real causes of this great war. At every meeting something was said about the part that the United States is playing in the war. The Chicago Hungarians will not only be loyal to the <pb facs="5422061_2_1198.jpg" n="3"/>United States which is the duty of every resident of this country, but will be better acquainted with the aims of the United States and this in turn will tie the Hungarian population of Chicago closer to the government of this country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
