<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1917-10-05">Oct. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Hungarian Activities in the United States</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1283</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1283.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1917-10-05">Oct. 5, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">HUNGARIAN ACTIVITIES IN THE UNITED STATES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hungarian American people of the United States have only one type of organization that has been of common interest to all of them and that is the lodge. The lodges are not all alike, but there is no essential difference in principles. They play a very important part in the life of the Hungarians and should be the focal point of all their various activities.</p>
   <p>Regardless of the difference in principles, it should be their duty to further the development of organizations so important to the social and moral life of the Hungarians. I know the activities that have taken place among our people in the United States, outside of those that have been sponsored by the lodges, there has never been anything of a permanent nature, undertaken and finished.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1284.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I don't want to blame any individual for their shortcomings; it would be very easy to name the persons who have done quite a bit to retard this great work. Placing the blame on individuals would not help the cause, but probably harm it, and what is more, if the Hungarian-Americans want to do something, create something, it should not be left solely to individuals.</p>
   <p>There must be enough power, leadership and cooperation among the Hungarian-Americans to develop permanent institutions, even though it be necessary to disregard individual ideas. Maybe the belief is extant that a good number of Hungarians will leave the country after the war and therefore would not be interested. But I do not think they will leave in such large numbers that permanent activities among our nationals will have to be discontinued. On the contrary such activities will probably become more important in the future since a great number of Hungarians undoubtedly will return to this country.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1285.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>I don't want to write about what activities should be started by the Hungarian-Americans because I do not want to force anything on the people that they might not want, or sincerely believe in. The people themselves should feel what they want. The Hungarian-Americans should not do what I or some one else thinks is a good idea, but they should decide what is most necessary and desirable for our group.</p>
   <p>I can not tell what the Hungarian-American feels is the most important activity in his life; But I do know that every other nationality has done something in their own interest. Their interests vary. Some are interested in hospitals, orphanages, aid societies, and sport activities; the Hungarian-American can not boast of any of these things.</p>
   <p>I don't believe that any nationality should be any more interested in such institutions than the Hungarians. A body of men such as the lodges should take the initiative, otherwise I can't see how the Hungarian-Americans can accomplish anything worth while in this field.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1286.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>I have presented this idea, hoping that the lodges and its members will go into action so that we Hungarians can keep up with the other nationalities. I do not claim to be the first one to suggest that we Hungarians do something for ourselves. Up to date our work has been planless and scattered, not touching the soul of the Hungarian-American. A radical change will have to take place, and it is up to ourselves to create the social activities and in situations which will aid us in achieving a brighter future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
