<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-03-23">Mar. 23, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Coalition of Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0820</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0820.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-03-23">Mar. 23, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">COALITION OF SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Three Hungarian sick benefit societies have united. The Chicago and Vicinity Hungarian Sick Benefit Society, the Workers' Sick Benefit Society, and the West Pullman Hungarian Society had their meeting on March 18 at Prokop Hall. Julius Prokop, chairman of the meeting, stressed in his opening speech the fact that this meeting had come together to agree on the best policy for the interests of the three hundred members.</p>
   <p>During the meeting, Joseph Kocsis kept a strict record of the minutes. After the regular business of the societies was concluded, the following points were accepted:</p>
   <p>For the monthly dues of one dollar, the member is entitled to receive sick benefit aid of fourteen dollars a week for a maximum period of twelve weeks; and in case of prolonged illness, seven dollars for another twelve weeks. This ruling is effective beginning May 1, 1928.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0821.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was agreed that the amount of death benefits was to be four hundred and fifty dollars.</p>
   <p>Due to the new Illinois law, however, these points are not definitely established. A committee was appointed to make inquiries and gather information about this new law so that the activities of the united societies would conform to its regulations. The members of this committee were instructed that inasmuch as the united society might not be granted a new charter, steps should be taken to unite with the Chicago First Hungarian Tarsalgo and Sick Benefit Society. The latter organization has already complied with the requirements of the Insurance Department and has over five hundred members.</p>
   <p>The name of the new society is "The Chicago United Workers' Sick Benefit Society."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
