<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-02-24">Feb. 24, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">About Hungarian Culture and Civilization</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Lowinger (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1763</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1763.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-02-24">Feb. 24, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT HUNGARIAN CULTURE AND CIVILIZATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Lowinger (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The vanquished nations, the losers of the World War, Germany and Hungary, knew from the first moment that peace treaties are binding only for a limited period of time. Although they couldn't do anything against it by force of arms, they felt that their higher cultural standing would save them from degradation and servitude.</p>
   <p>Germany, from whom territories with German population were taken by the Versailles treaty, bases its hopes on the Deutsche Kulturnation. Through this German cultural unity, the Germans, wherever they may be living, feel that they are united with the mother country.</p>
   <p>This spiritual union of the German people cannot be stopped by peace treaties.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1764.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The German people hope to get back their lost territories in time through this medium.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian people, who are guided by German ideology because of their common sad fate, have also tried to find a slogan, a ray of hope, a convincing argument. They have found it.</p>
   <p>The most oft-repeated argument of the Hungarians, aside from our mother country's perfect geographical entity, is the cultural superiority of the Magyars over the neighboring Balkan people.</p>
   <p>We American-Hungarians, regardless of the many disappointments, have an undying devotion for our mother country, and we find solace and hope in the obvious cultural strength of our race.</p>
   <p>We are grateful to the Almighty that in the field of art there are no medieval <pb facs="5422061_2_1765.jpg" n="3"/>restrictions, no distinction between defeated and victorious nations, no numerus clausus.</p>
   <p>Ability and talent are still appreciated, and our little mother country, amidst adverse political and economic turmoil, still produces talented people.</p>
   <p>Hungary's best export item today is the Magyar genius. Without a doubt our most sought-after geniuses are successful in the field of music. They glorify the Hungarian music, reputation, and justify Hungary's claim to cultural superiority.</p>
   <p>Franz Lehar, Imre Kalman, Victor Jacobi, Albert Szirmay, and Sigmund Romberg have brought fame to light Hungarian music abroad.....</p>
   <p>Hungarian literature has produced such world-famous writers as Franz Molnar, <pb facs="5422061_2_1766.jpg" n="4"/>Melchior Lengyel, Mor Jokai, Lajos Biro, Franz Herczeg, etc.....</p>
   <p>We have our notables in the cinema, too. Often we see Vilma Banky, Lya de Putti, Bela Lugosi, Victor Varconi, Maria Korda, etc., on the screen in Hungarian settings.</p>
   <p>The thought that neither internal nor external enemies can destroy our hereditary racial characteristics and talents, which insure Hungarian cultural superiority, is gratifying to all of us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
