<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-03-28">Mar. 28, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Important News</title><title level="a" type="sub">Important Information for Those Who Wish to Be Naturalized</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1575</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1575.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-03-28">Mar. 28, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">IMPORTANT NEWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Important Information for Those Who Wish to Be Naturalized</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Countless Hungarian immigrants find it impossible to remember the name of the steamer that brought them to, or the exact date of their arrival in, the United States. Only those who handle immigration and naturalization cases know how many people have difficulties in these matters.</p>
   <p>Why this is so can be explained from a psychological viewpoint. The difficult start after arrival, as well as the thousand and one worries and troubles connected with the struggle for a livelihood, tends to obliterate from our memory the simplest details. Many persons came to this country as small children, so that it is no wonder if they have forgotten the date of their arrival here or the name of the steamer in which they came. Sometimes an immigrant will get a steamer's name so impressed on his mind that he believes <pb facs="5422061_2_1576.jpg" n="2"/>that he came over on it even when such was not the case.</p>
   <p>Those who wish to become citizens of this country must determine precisely the name of the steamer in which they came as well as the exact date of their arrival in the United States. The same applies to those applying for a reentry permit. If the immigration authorities are unable to find any information relative to the applicant's arrival, they cannot issue a certificate of entry, and, without it, it is impossible to file a Declaration of Intention or first papers. Under such circumstances, the immigrant is unable to apply for a nonquota permit for his family.</p>
   <p>Anyone uncertain as to the exact details of his or her arrival here may get the information from the immigration authorities, who will look up the records, provided the name of the steamer and the approximate date of arrival are given. Otherwise the data has to be supplied by the applicant himself.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1577.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>According to a new plan, if an immigrant can prove that he arrived in this country before June 3, 1921, he can legalize his arrival and obtain a certificate of entry, but first he must conform to certain rules and regulations. We can avoid this lengthy and complicated procedure if we attend to this matter personally. If anyone has a case that he cannot solve all by himself, he should write to the Immigrants' Information Bureau, 215 Fourth Avenue, New York City, where experienced attention will be given to his case. Letters addressed to this office may be written in Hungarian.....</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: This is not an advertisement.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
