<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-01-29">Jan. 29, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The Central Committee Ceases to Exist</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0842</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0842.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-01-29">Jan. 29, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE CENTRAL COMMITTEE CEASES TO EXIST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Central Committee of the Chicago Hungarian Societies held what we might as well call its last meeting. The delegates who were present were: Frank Blasko, Paul Timko, and Joseph Fekete, representing the Chicago Hungarian Social and Sick Benefit Society; Frank Papp and Benjamin Fodor, representing the Rakoczy Society; Louis Barna, representing the Verhovay Society; Henry Frantz, representing the Thalia Society; and Ede Rusznak, representing the Hungarian Sport Club.</p>
   <p>Benjamin Fodor, president pro tem, opened the meeting and thanked the representatives for coming. He then spoke of the many long years of unsuccessful activities on the part of the Central Committee. He also said that as long as the Chicago Hungarian Social and Sick Benefit Society, the Independent Society, and the Rakoczy Society refused to pay their quota of membership dues, he could not see how the organization <pb facs="5422061_2_0843.jpg" n="2"/>could continue in existence. He then asked those present to express their opinions on the matter.</p>
   <p>The representatives considered the question very carefully, and they were fully satisfied that the organization could not exist very much longer. It was then decided that inasmuch as the officers' terms had expired, all operations should be suspended, since no organization can survive without officers.</p>
   <p>Then the question of the Hungarian Home came up, and it was revealed that there was a fund of $577 in the bank. This fund had resulted from donations from various lodges and individuals. It was decided that this sum should be returned to the contributors--lodges and individuals.</p>
   <p>It looks as though the Hungarian Home project is a thing of the past, unless it is revived by a more aggressive organization than the Central Committee of the Chicago Hungarian Societies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
