<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Geza Kende, <title>Magyars in America</title>, (Cleveland: Szabadsag, 1927), Vol. II, Chap. 28.
<title level="a">Hungary and the American-Magyars</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0537</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0537.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Geza Kende, <title>Magyars in America</title>, (Cleveland: Szabadsag, 1927), Vol. II, Chap. 28.
<title level="a">HUNGARY AND THE AMERICAN-MAGYARS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two American-Magyar newspapers were very active in stirring up the patriotic enthusiasm: The Magyar Napilap(Hungarian Daily) and the Szabadsag(Liberty) newspapers; the American Magyar Nepszava newspaper followed reserved measures.</p>
   <p>The first two mentioned newspapers were hostile to each other, and only the staunch belief in the outbreak of the revolution in Hungary <pb facs="5422061_2_0538.jpg" n="2"/>induced them to cease the hostilities, at least, in appearance. The editors of the two newspapers, Tihamer Kohanyi, editor of Szabadsag, and Emery Fetso, editor of the Magyar Napilap, believed that the American-Magyars will play an important role in the new Hungarian war of independence and, therefore, cooperation and unity were needed to organize the Magyars of America.</p>
   <p>T. Kohanyi, in his newspaper, Szabadsag pointing out the imminent danger of the Mother country,called a mass meeting, summoning all the Magyars living in the United States. This "summons" was also published <pb facs="5422061_2_0539.jpg" n="3"/>in the other paper, the Magyar Napilap so that all American-Magyars would learn about the occurrence.</p>
   <p>The date of the big mass meeting was set for February 22, 1906. This date is a red letter holiday in the history of the American-Magyars.</p>
   <p>The Ameridan-Magyars never before gave more imposing testimony of their ardent love for their native country and their readiness to sacrifiee for an independent Hungary.</p>
   <p>At the mass meeting held in Cleveland, Magyars of two hundred different cities, towns, and villages were represented. The chairman was Rev. <pb facs="5422061_2_0540.jpg" n="4"/>Michael Biro, a priest from South Bend, Indiana. Enthusiastic and spirited speeches were made by: Tihamer Kohanyi, Rev. Eleck Chootorosh, Calvinist clergyman, Rev. Coloman Kovats, priest, and many other prominent men.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
