<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-07-06">July 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Nine Hundred and Ninety-Two New Laws</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1117</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1117.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-07-06">July 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">NINE HUNDRED AND NINETY-TWO NEW LAWS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The record of the last session of Congress shows that the lawmakers of the United States have passed nine hundred and ninety-two new laws. Inasmuch as five laws were passed governing pensions and these include three thousand and ninety-three pension laws, these were grouped. If taken individually, the total of new laws would be four thousand and eighty.</p>
   <p>This was the Seventieth Congress. We will understand the lawmaking craze of this Congress if we compare it with previous Congresses.</p>
   <p>The Sixty-fifth Congress passed one hundred and nine laws; the Sixty-sixth, one hundred and twenty-one; the Sixty-seventh, one hundred and fifty-two; and the Sixty-eighth, three hundred and ninety-three.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1118.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Probably the lawmakers do not even know why we have so many laws. The fact is that there is no need for at least three-fourths of them. But, aside from this, the annual increase of laws brings disastrous results.</p>
   <p>Wholehearted respect for laws ceases. How can anyone be expected to respect and abide by laws when there are so many of them that no one can be sure he is not violating one daily? It is impossible for any human being to know all the laws.</p>
   <p>Is it any wonder then if we abide only by such laws as are the most convenient to us?</p>
   <p>If the purpose of these laws is to curb crime, the method is wrong. First, crime cannot be stopped by laws. The improvement of economic conditions, assuring the workers their daily bread and an opportunity to work, is the means to stop criminal activity.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1119.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The best example to prove this is that ninety per cent of crimes are committed in cities where most of the population work in factories and where their well-being depends on working conditions. The crime wave is always on the increase in winter and during unemployment.</p>
   <p>We need practical laws, not more laws. The ever-changing conditions in America, the country's progress, do not necessarily require the enactment of thousands of new laws annually. Old and impractical laws should be modified or invalidated, and only necessary new laws should be enacted by Congress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
