<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-01-09">Jan. 9, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Will There Be a New Hungary?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1816</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1816.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-01-09">Jan. 9, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">WILL THERE BE A NEW HUNGARY?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The opening of a new year provokes many questions regarding the future of that orphaned and crippled homeland of ours.</p>
   <p>We find that these questions are natural. We do not believe that there is a single person amongst us who does not feel that he should take an interest in the affairs of the government of his native land.</p>
   <p>At the same time, regardless of how much we would like to picture the Hungarian situation as a rosy one, the facts do not fool anyone who thinks seriously.</p>
   <p>We must remember that in 1914, at the beginning of the World War, we knew that we would create many enemies by saying that the War would be disastrous <pb facs="5422061_2_1817.jpg" n="2"/>to Hungary because regardless of who won, Hungary would lose. We admit that many times we in America wished that our prophesies might be wrong, because we still possess the Hungarian spirit. It is sad but our prophesy came true.</p>
   <p>Now we must speak and answer the question, will there be a new Hungary? The answer is distressing; there will not be a new Hungary. The only possible way that a new Hungary could be born would be for her to completely wipe out the present form of government and replace it with one that is totally democratic and guarantees the liberty of all citizens.</p>
   <p>The most unfortunate fact is that in those territories which have been taken from Hungary, the school teachers and other public officials fled and deserted the Hungarian people who live there. If these people had remained and maintained their integrity as well as that of the rest of the people, the time would have come when the people could have freed themselves.</p>
   <p>We read that the Turks set on the necks of the Hungarian people for one <pb facs="5422061_2_1818.jpg" n="3"/>hundred and fifty years. This is historical truth. But the Turks did not try to make a Mohamedan territory out of Hungary. The Turks were not interestedF in the people--they wanted the taxes. The Turks realized that this situation would end someday, and when that day came, they would have to get out of Hungary. The day came, and they left--fully satisfied that Allah wanted it that way.</p>
   <p>Today most of the nations <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> have taken <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> of un<gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>Hungary do not accept Turkish fatalism. The Slavish-speaking people especially are very impressive. They know that the strength of the people lies in education, therefore they are not stressing the building of churches. They say that the only time they need a priest is when they die.</p>
   <p>Can you or anyone else believe that those Hungarians in the ceded territories <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/></p>
   <p>If the Hungarian government wants to retain the respect of the Hungarians <pb facs="5422061_2_1819.jpg" n="4"/>scattered throughout the world she must render services that are far superior to those of these foreign governments. If the Hungarian-Americans expect aid from the American people, it will be up to us to see that those who are in Hungary receive bread, land and civil rights. This must be done with due legality using the Bethlen-Horthy procedure.</p>
   <p>Further the Hungarian-American press must cease its espionage tactics. When these things are done we can discuss problems of integrity.</p>
   <p>But to ask Hungarian-Americans to shoulder the burden of the abuses of the Bethlen-Horthy government is out of the question.</p>
   <p>Therefore we Hungarian-Americans are still wondering whether there will be a new Hungary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
