<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-10-05">Oct. 5 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Immigration Problem</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annotations to the Editorial of the Szabadsag (Editorial by[Dr. Erno]Lowinger)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1582</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1582.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-10-05">Oct. 5 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE IMMIGRATION PROBLEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">Annotations to the Editorial of the Szabadsag (Editorial by[Dr. Erno]Lowinger)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If the platform of Governor Smith would contain no other paragraph except the one in which he so obviously differs from Hoover's viewpoint on immigration, it would be more than enough to induce all self-conscious, upright, and thinking American-Hungarian citizens to vote for Al Smith.</p>
   <p>However, we are aware that there are other good and liberal points in Smith's program which interest the immigrant citizenry.</p>
   <p>For instance, there is Smith's promise to change the Prohibition law.</p>
   <p>The Republican's attitude on the immigration question is inflexible, and if we think it over seriously, their stand in this regard is ungrateful and <pb facs="5422061_2_1583.jpg" n="2"/>humiliating.</p>
   <p>From our Central European Kind, as well as from South and Eastern Europe, a minimum number of immigrants is desired. Some people think that even this minimum is too many.</p>
   <p>Hoover wants only five hundred fifty-eight Hungarian immigrants. Smith likes the Hungarian immigrants more than ten times as much as Hoover, because he would put the quota at nine thousand.....</p>
   <p>The sympathy, understanding, and appreciation that is reflected from this attitude of Smith concerning the limitation of the quota, means more to the naturalized citizen of Hungarian extraction than the coming of eight thousand more Hungarians.....</p>
   <p>Our largest Hungarian daily newspaper, the Szabadsag, has been staunchly Republican for almost forty years. This week the following sensible and <pb facs="5422061_2_1584.jpg" n="3"/>praiseworthy editorial appeared in the Szabadsag.</p>
   <p>"The Vice-Presidential candidate made a grave mistake when he mentioned the problem of immigration in one of his campaign speeches. He did wrong when he attacked the Democratic party's Presidential candidate because he advocates a change in the present immigration quota system. Senator Curtis did wrong when he started to dissect a problem he knows nothing about. The biggest trouble in solving the immigration problem, is that those who are in charge of the task are not familiar with the question, much less with the immigrants. Senator Curtis is of Indian origin, so he is disqualified to judge by reason of his birth. Albert Johnson, representative of the State of Washington, an old enemy of immigration, is from a state where the immigrant is unknown. The immigration question was never a problem in Washington, because very few 'undesirable' immigrants settled there. It is certain that the people of Hoquiam, Johnson's native town, never saw a live 'Polack' or 'Dago'.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1585.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"This is the greatest difficulty in the immigration question. The Federal legislature--the House as well as the Senate--should appoint men who are familiar with the question, practically not theoretically; men who not only see immigrants occasionally in the movies, but who are in daily contact with them. If Congressmen from New York, Pennsylvania, Ohio, New Jersey, Wisconsin, West Virginia, and Illinois would be on the committee, they would positively have a different opinion of the immigrant.</p>
   <p>"Senator Curtis can find many other topics that would interest the public. He can find other weak spots in the Democratic party's armor to attack without dwelling on the immigration question, because he only shows his ignorance or one-sidedness.</p>
   <p>"Undoubtedly Al Smith is right when he says that the determination of the quota, based on the census of the year 1890, is wrong. The quota should be determined on a later census.....</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1586.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Senator Curtis may be assured that we Hungarians are just as good and valuable American citizens as the English or other 'northern races' who are so unaccountably favored by the present laws."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
