<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-11-05">Nov. 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Let's Join the Red Cross</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1055</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1055.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-11-05">Nov. 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">LET'S JOIN THE RED CROSS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the past, foreign-born Americans were glad to answer any call that was issued to help those who were suffering. They were satisfied in knowing that by their liberal donations they were making life easier for the rest of the unfortunate world.</p>
   <p>This is true in Europe as well as America that these foreign-born Americans show great interest in the work being conducted by the Red Cross. Consequently, the Red Cross, with the cooperation of the Foreign Language Information Service, worked out a new plan, by which the annual Roll Call would be so arranged that each nationality would have a roll of its own. Of course, the success of this plan depends entirely on the way it is received by the people, and to what extent everyone cooperates and does his best to insure this success.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1056.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Foreign Language Information Service has informed every foreign organization and church of the new idea. They have also authorized them to become branch offices of the Red Cross. The different organizations have been furnished with the necessary equipment, and the Red Cross urges those who have not yet received this data to communicate with them immediately. The work will not be conducted directly by the Red Cross. It realizes that among the foreign population of this country, there are different organizations that can conduct a campaign, such as this, much more efficiently, there-fore, the Red Cross has welcomed these organizations into its fold.</p>
   <p>This Roll Call campaign will start on November 11 and continue until November 25.</p>
   <p>After the expiration of this time, the donations will be turned over <pb facs="5422061_2_1057.jpg" n="3"/>to the local Red Cross agencies, where it will be booked under the different nationality groups, thereby giving credit where credit is due. This is the only way they can determine which nationality contributes the largest amount to this great organization.</p>
   <p>The different nationalistic organizations have membership fees of one dollar per person in the Red Cross. By contributing this dollar, they not only aided their local committee, but they also contributed toward aiding those sufferers in foreign lands. As a reward, the Red Cross want to show the world that the different nationalities are doing their part in this country to aid those unfortunates across the sea.</p>
   <p>It is sincerely hoped that the Hungarian people will do their utmost in order that those people whom they left behind may be aided by the Red Cross. Let us all get together and contribute to the organization that means so much to humanity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
