<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-01-20">Jan. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Charity Drive on the South Side</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1008</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1008.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-01-20">Jan. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">CHARITY DRIVE ON THE SOUTH SIDE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Scarcely a few days have passed since there appeared in the Hungarian newspapers an appeal from our priests and ministers to our compatriots of the South Side, asking them to start a charity drive on their side of the city in behalf of the jobless Hungarians, and we already can report that this appeal has met with a wholehearted response from our brothers of the South Side.</p>
   <p>Reverend Father Ernest Horvath, Father Steve Poratunsky, and Reverend Eugene Boros called a meeting of the representatives of Hungarian associations for Friday, January 13, at the Hungarian Home. Almost all our associations on the South Side promptly responded and sent their representatives to this meeting. They all are to be praised for this. The leaders of the Hungarian associations in Burnside, South Chicago, and West Pullman not only attended this meeting but also did everything in their power to facilitate the work of this drive.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1009.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Reverend Ernest Horvath opened the meeting. In beautiful words he described the situation and emphasized the urgency of the drive. As the meeting had unanimously resolved to start the drive immediately, it proceeded to elect the officers of the committee. [Translator's Note: The names of the members of the committee are given in the article, together with the names of the associations represented at the meeting.]</p>
   <p>The committee decided to arrange a grand concert and dance on February 12 at the Hungarian Home, the income of which shall go to help the jobless. Entrance fee will be twenty-five cents. The committee asks all Hungarians to come to its aid, as there is need for every cent and for the work of everybody. The committee will meet every Friday evening at the Hungarian Home, where everybody interested in its work is welcome. Louis Nemeth, president of the Home Committee of the Bridgeport Aid Association, Branch 221, offered the free use of the Hungarian Home for this charitable purpose. His offer was accepted with thanks by the committee. The Kovacs Orchestra volunteered its services at the concert. Dr. Aladar Bolla, well-known <pb facs="5422061_2_1010.jpg" n="3"/>Hungarian physician, with the modesty which characterizes him, announced that he would gladly attend free of charge the jobless who are sick. Frank J. Kovach, director of the WIND Hungarian Radio Hour, offered to advertise the concert over the radio free of charge. The meeting received all these offers with great applause and expressed its gratitude to the donors.</p>
   <p>The committee is working on the program for this concert, which promises to be a great success, even from the artistic viewpoint. We hope the Hungarian businessmen will come to the next meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
