<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-02-17">Feb. 17, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Lecture on Technocracy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0657</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0657.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-02-17">Feb. 17, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">LECTURE ON TECHNOCRACY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday Engineer Ladislaus Bauer gave a lecture before members of the Hungarian branch of the I.W.W., at Wage Earners Home. The subject of the lecture was "Technocracy," which is now, at a time of industrial stagnation, very timely. In his lecture, Mr. Bauer demonstrated, with the help of unquestionable data, the efficiency of the instruments of production in the past and in the present. The growing efficiency of new tools has caused millions of workers to lose their jobs. The data published by the technocrats are supported by statistics compiled by a commission named by Hoover to investigate the industrial situation.</p>
   <p>Much acknowledgement is due Engineer Bauer for his work in collecting the material for his lecture. Almost unbelievable is the amount of work and trouble that was needed to arrange all these data, as furnished by the report of the Hoover Commission, into a lecture. The Hoover Commission's report alone contains 1,700 pages, not to mention the good sized works of the technologists.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0658.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the course of this lecture we learned of the factors that have played roles in the creation of the present industrial stagnation. Unfortunately, neither the Hoover Commission nor the technocrats has shown us a way out of this depression. Sunday, February 19, again at the Wage Earners Home, there will be another lecture on the means whereby we could get rid of unemployment. The title of the lecture will be "Technocracy, or the I.W.W." Lecturer is Paul Pika. It is of the utmost importance that the Hungarians attend these lectures in great numbers, as it is quite often that questions are debated which are closely connected with our daily life.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
