<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-02-14">Feb. 14, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">How Does the Case of the Chicago Peoples Theater Stand?</title><title level="a" type="sub">Statement of Jeno Endrey and Mrs. Endrey</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0171</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0171.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-02-14">Feb. 14, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">HOW DOES THE CASE OF THE CHICAGO PEOPLES THEATER STAND?</title><title level="a" type="sub">Statement of Jeno Endrey and Mrs. Endrey</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In one of our recent issues, we mentioned that the Chicago Peoples Theater had been disbanded, which did not mean that the corporation failed.</p>
   <p>Jeno Endrey refutes our report on the matter, a report which we published upon what we believed was reliable information. We wish to be consistent with justice when we give Endrey's article space in our paper, for we believe that he is the most competent person to enlighten our readers about the failure or nonfailure of the Chicago Peoples Theater, Inc.</p>
   <p>We had to omit parts of Endrey's article because the language he uses is so strong as to be unfit for printing. In the letter of Margit Padly, his wife, we had to make alterations too.</p>
   <p>In spite of soft-pedaling Endrey's assertions, this newspaper assumes no <pb facs="5422061_2_0172.jpg" n="2"/>responsibility in publishing them, placing the entire responsibility on him.</p>
   <p>"Inasmuch as I have read in so many newspapers that the Chicago Peoples Theater, Inc. has failed, I was not in the least surprised at the report in the Magyar Tribune, according to which the Chicago Peoples Theater had been disbanded.</p>
   <p>"Most of these reports were placed in the newspapers with the intention of arousing the thought in the mind of the public that the Chicago Peoples Theater will give no more performances, thereby aiding our enemies in achieving their aim of diminishing the number of theatergoers.</p>
   <p>"I am sure that the article in the Magyar Tribune was published upon well-meant information, since the actors who couldn't stand the unbelievable struggle--which I will continue until the end for the Chicago Peoples Theater--left the company and came back to Chicago to try to make a better living.</p>
   <p>"After all, if the members of the company were unable to get their salaries for weeks, they can't be blamed for trying to better their situation. There <pb facs="5422061_2_0173.jpg" n="3"/>always were, are, and will be scared rats that try to escape from a sinking ship, and the ship of the Chicago Peoples Theater today is fighting such a storm that the rays of the sun cannot reach her. Victor Drozdy bewailed in the last issue for his newspaper the calamity that has befallen the actors. Nevertheless, he is one of the guilty ones who are directly responsible for the plight of the Chicago Peoples Theater. He predicted the demise of the Chicago Peoples Theater when it was in its heyday, just because we did not advertise in his paper.</p>
   <p>"That the Chicago Theater is losing money and that it is in dire straits, I admit. I also admit that I am at fault.</p>
   <p>"My greatest fault was my generosity. I wanted more than was possible, more than the circumstances of the Hungarians would permit. I generously wanted to provide a living for seventy people.....</p>
   <p>"I am compelled to review Drozdy's article, to explain it so that none of the well-meaning Chicago Hungarians should be fooled. It is the duty of the Magyar Tribune to publish this and to help in the revelation of the underhanded <pb facs="5422061_2_0174.jpg" n="4"/>methods used in an attempt to ruin the Chicago Peoples Theater.</p>
   <p>"Drozdy writes that a delegation appeared in his editorial office under the leadership of Louis Horvath. If Horvath says that just because he and two others left the company the Chicago Peoples Theater has been disbanded, he tells an untruth.</p>
   <p>"When Drozdy uses the power of the printed word to write in his newspaper that I won't die in a horizontal position, my fists clench, because I will account for every cent of the stockholders' investment and I will pay all just claims against the Chicago Peoples Theater. I hope that my last profitable act will be to see that Drozdy will be removed from the editorship of the newspaper where I placed him and where he failed to fulfill any of his promises."</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The letter of Margit Padly is almost a repetition of that of her husband.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
