<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-10-30">Oct. 30, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Wave of Protest in Behalf of Countess Karolyi</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1226</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1226.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-10-30">Oct. 30, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">WAVE OF PROTEST IN BEHALF OF COUNTESS KAROLYI</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In last week's issue we wrote and told you that Secretary of State Kellogg had advised Mr. Skinner, American consul in Paris, to deny Countess Karolyi a passport to the United States. Hardly had this disgraceful action become known when a movement was started by the Hungarian press and by Hungarian organizations to protest the action taken by the State Department against Countess Karolyi.</p>
   <p>Senator Borah, who heads the Foreign Affairs Committee, openly condemned this act of the State Department. He also stated that next December he would sponsor a bill in Congress which would take away from the State Department the right to prohibit the entrance of individuals into the United States. There were also many other Democratic and Republican senators who said that they would voice favorable opinions in behalf of Countess Karolyi.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1227.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The directors of the Chicago Hungarian University Club, through the efforts of one of their outstanding members, Emil Preszburg, president of the Westminster Bond and Mortgage Company, contacted Senator Deneen, and were granted an interview with him in regard to this matter.</p>
   <p>The Senator listened to the plea of the directors of the University Club and approved the telegram that they proposed to send to the President in regard to the Countess Karolyi affair. The contents of this telegram were as follows:</p>
   <p>To His Excellency, Calvin Coolidge,</p>
   <p>President of the United States,</p>
   <p>The White Mouse,</p>
   <p>Washington, D.C.</p>
   <p>We are compelled to protest against the action of the Department of State in preventing Countess Karolyi from coming here, <pb facs="5422061_2_1228.jpg" n="3"/>because she has already demonstrated, when she was in this land, that she is an exponent of Christian progress and humanity. We are sincere admirers of your administration, and we beg for your intervention and modification of the order.</p>
   <p>Yours respectfully,</p>
   <p>The Hungarian University Club</p>
   <p>Dr. A. Rodosy, president</p>
   <p>I. Izsak, secretary</p>
   <p>M. Gawansky and Z. Weiszburg, directors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
