<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1928-10-14">Oct. 14, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Hungarians to Participate in Chicago World's Fair</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0421</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0421.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1928-10-14">Oct. 14, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">HUNGARIANS TO PARTICIPATE IN CHICAGO WORLD'S FAIR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>How are the Hungarians preparing to take part in the World's Fair and Chicago's Centennial celebration? We must say that we Hungarians are very slow when there is a call for action. We celebrate birthdays of our friends, so how do we feel about this gigantic centennial celebration which the City of Chicago is planning. How can we Hungarians contribute towards this great celebration? Up to the present time the Hungarian people have hardly given it a thought. There has been one organization which has elected a committee of three people to sell five dollar certificates for the fair, but no other organization has started any movement whatsoever.</p>
   <p>We are all waiting for some one else to start the movement of the Hungarian people in Chicago in order that they might participate in this great event. There is no reason for the Hungarian people to feel that way about this event; we all should pitch in and go to work with but one thought in mind and that is that the Hungarians will take part as one great organization striving for the same purpose.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0422.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Let us all get together, ministers, priests, society leaders and all men belonging to any social or other Hungarian organizations, and plan something for this event.</p>
   <p>There will be a meeting at the Hungarian Home on Sunday afternoon to get all these people together so that the Hungarians can take part and be well represented at this Pageant of Progress. Hungarian brothers,we want all of you to be present at this meeting.</p>
   <p>World's Fair Organizing Committee of the community of Burnside.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
