<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-11-07">Nov. 7, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Good Samaritan Work of Hungarians</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1032</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1032.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-11-07">Nov. 7, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD SAMARITAN WORK OF HUNGARIANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For over two weeks the Olivet Institute has given shelter to an army of unemployed. Twice daily they are fed, and at night they sleep on the floor of the gymnasium. These unfortunates are an orderly, quiet lot, most of whom were turned into the streets through no fault of their own. Provision is made for them by various churches where the food is cooked and served on certain days.</p>
   <p>Last Saturday evening and Sunday morning the Hungarian congregation of the Olivet Institute acted as hosts with the aid of other Chicago Hungarians. To those who partook in this noble work, November 1 will be an unforgettable day. In order to prove how warm the Hungarian heart is when called upon to help more unfortunate fellow men, the Hungarians outdid themselves.</p>
   <p>The chronicler would have difficulty in gathering the various manifestations of good will, kindness, and unselfishness into one bouquet. Not with <pb facs="5422061_2_1033.jpg" n="2"/>effrontery, but with Christian humility did the Hungarians practice benevolence--"let not thy left hand know what thy right hand doeth"--and endeavored to spare the feelings of these unfortunates.....</p>
   <p>There were 245 guests who gratefully partook of Hungarian hospitality. So much food was donated that two hundred pounds of potatoes, fifty cans of cream, eighteen pounds of butter, coffee, and sugar were left over. The total cash gifts amounted to $67.50.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
