<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-04-04">Apr. 4, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">[Hungarians Warned Not to Be Afraid of Census Takers]</title><title level="a" type="sub">We Present the Real Facts and the Questions That Are Asked</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1570</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1570.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-04-04">Apr. 4, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">[HUNGARIANS WARNED NOT TO BE AFRAID OF CENSUS TAKERS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">We Present the Real Facts and the Questions That Are Asked</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From the numerous letters received from our readers, it is evident that the taking of the census is giving rise to many fears among some of our people. Some people, especially those who came here illegally, are afraid that the census takers will ask them about their arrival and report the findings to the Immigration Authorities. Others fear that their muddled personal affairs will be exposed.</p>
   <p>The Foreign Language Information Service assures those who entertain these fears that no one will suffer any harm on account of the census. The census takers are not after information on an immigrant's entry into this country. They will not ask whether one entered this country legally or illegally. If a census taker asks questions relative to an immigrant's entry into this country, the immigrant may refuse to answer them. Therefore, let it be understood that we may answer all questions put to us <pb facs="5422061_2_1571.jpg" n="2"/>without any fear. The data collected by the census takers can be used for statistics only. The census enumerators take an oath that they will not divulge information obtained in interviews. The census data serves scientific purposes through which we will be able to gain a comprehensive picture of the country's cultural and agricultural status, etc.</p>
   <p>According to the Census Bureau, foreigners are classified under five headings, namely, country of birth, mother tongue, date of arrival in the United States, citizenship status, and knowledge of English. If the census taker, through his contacts, obtains certain information and makes it public, the law punishes him very severely.</p>
   <p>In order that the immigrant may be prepared in advance, we are publishing here the questions he will be required to answer. [A list of twenty-four questions follows.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
