<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1929-04-12">Apr. 12, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Attention, American-Hungarians</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Arpad Tarnoczy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1578</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1578.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1929-04-12">Apr. 12, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">ATTENTION, AMERICAN-HUNGARIANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Arpad Tarnoczy</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The wide gate through which we came to this new world has closed behind us. Those of our race who would follow us knock on this gate in vain. There is no power that would open it for them. We, too, find it difficult to go out through it, because unless we have our naturalization papers or a re-entry permit, we cannot hope to come back through the side door of the privileged.</p>
   <p>The difficulties of emigration and immigration, the stringent requirements of the naturalization procedure, are our own troubles. Hungary has nothing to do with it. It causes no one any headaches except us American-Hungarians.</p>
   <p>Two old people....hanged themselves in the last sixty days. They had no property, they couldn't work because they were too old, and when they tried to register at the State's home for the aged to beg for a place--oven a dog is <pb facs="5422061_2_1579.jpg" n="2"/>entitled to refuge--and a piece of bread, the law sternly inquired: "Are you American citizens?" And since the State's poorhouse can only receive America's poor, the two helpless Hungarians were left out in the cold. They trudged along until they reached two convenient apple trees...and hanged themselves.</p>
   <p>If the old country heard about this sad event, shoulders were shrugged: "That is the worry of the Hungarians of America. We have enough trouble with our own poor and can't be expected to shoulder the worries of the American-Hungarians."</p>
   <p>For forty years we've been building sick benefit and burial societies in the United States. A great many of these societies are extinct, and much of the hard-earned money of our Hungarians was lost. Where the money was entrusted to honest hands, the society is still flourishing. There are about two hundred of them in the United States. If all of these societies would unite <pb facs="5422061_2_1580.jpg" n="3"/>into one great organization, we wouldn't have any more worries about our widows and orphans.</p>
   <p>Our blessed old country can only say: "You cooked it, now eat it. I am not your cook."</p>
   <p>Blood of my blood, American-Hungarians! We have much to worry over that Hungary with her own troubles cannot share. We were severed from her and migrated to a strange land--most of us forever. We have no right to demand that she be interested in our fate.</p>
   <p>But, when the mutilated mother country sends a distressed plea to us, when she shows us her wounds caused by the dismemberment of her territories, and if she asks our financial assistance, then she expects us to do our share.</p>
   <p>The Hungarians have a beautiful hymn, which pleads to the heavens:</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1581.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Extend your helpful arm</p>
   <p>When she (Hungary) struggles with the enemy."</p>
   <p>He strikes this helpful arm with treacherous heart who refuses aid to the suffering mother country.</p>
   <p>American-Hungarians! It can be seen from these illustrations that we have many grave troubles. The Buffalo National Conference is destined to discuss these and find a solution to them on May 29, 30, and 31.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
