<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-02-13">Feb. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A Notice to Hungarian-Americans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1067</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1067.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-02-13">Feb. 13, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">A NOTICE TO HUNGARIAN-AMERICANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This article is written with reference to the activities of the American Relief Committee for Hungarian sufferers.</p>
   <p>This committee has reached a point where they think it is necessary to start activities among the entire Hungarian population of the United States in order that sufficient aid may be obtained for the children of Hungary, and to prevent their destruction. In the first <pb facs="5422061_2_1068.jpg" n="2"/>place this affair strictly concerns all Hungarians. Those starving children in Hungary are Hungarians. To whom can these unfortunate children turn, or whom can they ask, if not the Hungarians-Americans who are able to help lighten the burden of suffering in our homeland?</p>
   <p>The Hungarians in the United States know that many months passed before the Hoover Committee listened to their pleas. Finally, this committee not only granted the pleas of the Hungarians, but also helped them obtain permission to communicate with and to aid their loved ones.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1069.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The time came, and no sooner did activities begin, than the first large contribution from this country reached Hungary. Today, there are 180 kitchens in Hungary advertising the activities of the Relief Committee. The children in 103 schools and 17 hospitals wish to express their gratitude for the contributions made by the generous Hungarians of America.</p>
   <p>In order that the Hungarian-Americans might be organized properly to conduct this charitable work, we have appointed Rev. Endre Szilagyi to take charge of it. He has just returned from Europe and fully <pb facs="5422061_2_1070.jpg" n="4"/>understands the serious conditions that exist in Hungary. He will not only answer inquiries concerning these charitable activities, but will give advice in the matter of conducting them, so that to this end, the greatest good may be done and thus bring honor to the Hungarians.</p>
   <p>Reverend Szilagyi is ready to aid all Hungarian societies or church organizations in the promotion of this work. He is also willing to attend meetings and speak in both Hungarian and English in order to further this cause.</p>
   <p>As we mentioned previously, there are 180 kitchens, 103 schools, and <pb facs="5422061_2_1071.jpg" n="5"/>17 hospitals receiving benefits, from this charitable movement. It gives aid to 61,000 children in Hungary. The committee has gone one step further. It is now supplying food and plans to supply clothing soon. In a few weeks we will hear the good news that the good American Samaritan has clothed 10,000 Hungarian children. To date, contributions have reached the $300,000 mark. Of this amount, the Hoover Committee has turned over $259,000 to Budapest authorities, and at the present time they have $29,500 on hand.</p>
   <p>In order that this movement be a complete success, it is hoped that the contributions will reach the million dollar mark.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1072.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>At the present time, the Hungarian-Americans have taken very little part in this movement, which should be their own. The Hungarians have always been known as a proud people. They would never accept help from a stranger. Today, when we have to save the future generation, we are letting strangers take care of this very important matter. Perhaps our Hungarian pride is dying.</p>
   <p>Let us organize and contribute. Those suffering children will remember that these contributions saved their lives. We must help them, and our names will be blessed. The entire Hungarian population must stand together, and become a mother, who lovingly embraces her starving children, thereby saving their lives and the future of our homeland.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
