<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1936-05-28">May 28, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">At the Verhovay Jubilee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0762</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0762.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1936-05-28">May 28, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">AT THE VERHOVAY JUBILEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the Verhovay Jubilee which was celebrated by its 27th District, Gustave Brand, treasurer of the city of Chicago, who represented Mayor Edward J. Kelly, made the following speech:</p>
   <p>Mr. Chairman, honored Guests, Ladies and Gentlemen - May I first be permitted to read a telegram, which came from his Honor, the Mayor of the city of Chicago, Edward J. Kelly.</p>
   <p>"Deeply regret,absence from city will deny me the privilege of attending celebration today but I am happy to send the Honorable Gustave Brand, City Treasurer of the city of Chicago to represent me and extend my cordial greetings and congratulations on the occasion of your Association's commemorating its fiftieth anniversary. Best wishes for continued success as well, as for an enjoyable and memorable occasion today. Edward J. Kelly, Mayor."</p>
   <p>The last time I saw the Mayor, on Friday at a conference, he begged me to convey <pb facs="5422061_2_0763.jpg" n="2"/>to you all, his deepest regret at not being able to attend your celebration, and bring his good wishes to you in person. The duties and responsibilities of the Mayor of our city are thousand-fold and an important meeting pertaining to vital interests of the city, which was arranged a month ahead had to be given his attention, and therefore I was delegated to convey, as well as I could, his heartiest wishes. And so, through these circumstances the Mayor's loss is my gain, in having the honor of being your guest on this great occasion of your golden jubilee.</p>
   <p>Therefore let me add my own personal congratulations to those of your Mayor. May God bless all your undertakings and keep you in his protection!</p>
   <p>Ladies and Gentlemen, when I gaze over this vast audience over the hundreds of happy and smiling faces, my questioning mind brings back always the same unerring answer, and that is - contentment and happiness, the fundamentals of your race.</p>
   <p>Here we are practically on the most southerly boundary line of the city of Chicago; forty miles North we reach the city limits, East from the foot of the lake and <pb facs="5422061_2_0764.jpg" n="3"/>fifteen miles West we come to another dividing line - In this area, this vast expanse of land, four million people have their home, seventy racial groups live and work harmoniously together, all having the same interest, - that of making Chicago a finer and grander city to live in - to observe its laws, to promote prosperity, to help the neighbor to be a worthy member of that great family "the American citizen;" - to uphold the constitution - and follow in the footsteps of their forefathers, - Their forefathers, who left their old firesides in Hungary, knowing that hardship and privations would be theirs and their families' for some time to come, in a new and undeveloped land, - but they had confidence and they had faith in the new world of freedom and equality. They became worthy members of that great melting pot of all nationalities. They were the backbone of this new nation.</p>
   <p>And so Ladies and Gentlemen, you members of this society, sons and daughters of the early pioneers, - you are of the same stock and caliber, your principles and your ideals are the same as those of the early settlers. - For born in you is the love for freedom and patriotism. It is said that when a child is born of Hungarian parents, great immortal gifts are put into its cradle, that is - love of freedom, love of justice, love of nature and love of art and music. And these gifts stay with it until its last day.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0765.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>And I know that you are hard working and law abiding people. The crime records bear me out on this, I say that there are very few of the Hungarians who are involved in crimes and that is a wonderful tribute to your sterling qualities.</p>
   <p>We are soon going to celebrate the Centennial of the founding of the Calumet Region. One hundred years ago there was nothing but desert, waste and marshes. Today is a vast industrial empire. The people of Hungarian descent have played a great part in the building and development of the Calumet Region. All honor to them for this great contribution in this immense task.</p>
   <p>Some fifty-two years ago I made the acquaintance of one of the finest cities on the Continent - Budapest. We may talk of beautiful Vienna, sunny Rome, gay Paris, imperial Petersburg, modern Berlin and foggy London, - but if a person misses Budapest in his travels he has missed Europe entirely.</p>
   <p>Hungary has given to the world great men and women, artists, musicians and composers, - men of great learning and high ability.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0766.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>And now, Ladies and Gentlemen, may I again, in the name of the Mayor, congratulate you on this festive occasion. - May health and prosperity be yours for all time to come.</p>
   <p>I thank you!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
