<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-03-21">Mar. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">"Prince Bob"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0137</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0137.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-03-21">Mar. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">"PRINCE BOB"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On March 8, the Chicago-Hungarians were given a second chance to enjoy the grand operetta, "Prince Bob." The performance was given for the benefit of that grand Hungarian-American, Paul Borak, who, for the past fifteen years, has worked hard for the preservation of one of the most cultural societies in Chicago, the Chicago Independent Song Society.</p>
   <p>Of this performance, we are glad to state that it was performed better this time than it was before by this group of players. The outstanding actors who took part in this operetta were as follows: Michael Redey, a former member of the Budapest opera company, and Miss Irma Petrovics, former Hungarian actress. The performance of Mr. Redey was superb. But we think it necessary to say that his performance put real life into the performance of this operetta. He acted so well that when he appeared on the scene we forgot that it was merely an act, and not a true life happening. This is not taking anything away from the performance <pb facs="5422061_2_0138.jpg" n="2"/>of the other actors, who all performed in the finest way possible.</p>
   <p>The staging of the operetta was, both financially and culturally speaking, a huge success.</p>
   <p>At this time, the Hungarian University Club presented Paul Berak with a beautiful silver sword, and the Chicago Independent Song Society honored him by presenting him with a beautiful silver wreath for the work he has done for the preservation of this organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
