<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radio</title>,
<date when="1937-05-26">May 26, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Rev. Stephen E. Balogh and His Family</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0577</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0577.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radio</title>,
<date when="1937-05-26">May 26, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">REV. STEPHEN E. BALOGH AND HIS FAMILY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Above on this picture we present a priest in the circle of his family, - one, who keeps step with the progress of our age, and whom on account of his many good characters the Hungarians of Chicago and vicinity know advantageously, love and esteem. He is the first Hungarian priest, who gave a real meaning to the proverb: "If the mountain does not come to Mohammed, Mohammed goes to the mountain," when he began to spread the Holy Gospel through the radio. There are many of those, who for one reason or other can not attend the church service, however much he or she may feel the need of it. To satisfy this need, Rev. Stephen E. Balogh made a truly record breaking step, when he created the so-called "Invisible Church" service with the use of the radio. He highly recognized the tremendous advantage derived from the fact that he can reach through the radio to everyone, from the richest palaces to the poorest shacks, who are thirsting after the words of the Gospel, and to announce the greatness of Our Lord.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0578.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Rev. Stephen E. Balogh finished his gymnasium (Latin high-school) and theological studies in the Hungarian Capitol, Budapest. His first American parish was that in Leechburg, Pa., in 1929-31. From April 26, 1931 to April 15, 1934, he was at the head of the congregation in McKeesport, Pa. From the beginning of the year 1935 he is leading the Hungarian Reformed Church of Chicago - South Side.</p>
   <p>We can hear his invisible church service on the station WWAE from 5:00 to 5:30 P.M. every Sunday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
