<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-03-05">Mar. 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Society Celebrates 20th Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0900</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0900.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1920-03-05">Mar. 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIETY CELEBRATES 20th ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the South Side's oldest and largest Hungarian sick benefit societies, The Burnside Hungarian Workers Sick Benefit Society, invited all Hungarians in the Chicago district to come to the Pythian Temple Hall, located in Burnside and help them celebrate their twentieth anniversary.</p>
   <p>The charter members at this society were nothing but common, ordinary working men, who upon their arrival in this country became leaders and organizers. They felt that the Hungarians in this particular area should be taken care of, and so twenty years ago a handful of Hungarian men got together and unfurled the flag of the Burnside Hungarian Worker's Sick Benefit Society. These men went ahead risking money, sacrificing time and labor, and now without obligations to anyone, this organization has advanced steadily.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0901.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The start was difficult, but success was reached. The Chicago Hungarians recognized the call of this society, and from time to time, it gained more members, and today stands as one of the largest societies of its kind in Chicago.</p>
   <p>What this organization has done in the past twenty years, is very ably recorded by the present secretary, Mike Hornak. We find that this organization has continually contributed to charitable causes and also aided all churches in their work, both financially and morally.</p>
   <p>The following is a general audit of the books of this organization: Total income, $22,319.44; Expenses, $16,319.00;Members deceased, 13; Present membership, 234; Present assets, $6,000.</p>
   <p>The organization has two beautiful flags, one Hungarian and one American. These flags were the symbols of benevolence, cooperation and charity through out the long years of the existence of this organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0902.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The celebration was opened by singing the Hungarian national anthem. The opening address was by Mr. Charles Tarjanyi, the president of the organization at the present time. He thanked the vast audience and the ladies and men's societies that were represented. Reverend Aladar Jezerniczki, of the Burnside Hungarian Reformed Church, gave a very beautiful speech; after this Mr. E. E. Hennessy and Mr. R. O. Wyland presented a moving picture history of the organization. The picture included shots of the men who first organized this society; the pictures of the flags and its godfathers and godmother and then the present officers. The final scenes were of the funeral of a member who recently died.</p>
   <p>This was followed by speeches from officials and representatives of other Hungarian organizations; Colman Bologh, president of the First Hungarian Reformed Society, who spoke and urged the audience to cooperate in aiding the starving children of Hungary, and Joseph Rakos, president of the St. Stupen Society, who spoke on the same subject.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0903.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Father Stephen Soltesz congratulated the organization for its great work in the field of friendship.</p>
   <p>Two of the charter members were present and were called to the stage and presented with gold medals. This presentation was made by Mr. John Kovacs, who spoke briefly of the careers of these men. He also decorated Mr. Tarjanyi with a gold medal, stating that this organization could not pick a more desirable man to receive the medal of honor of this great society. Mr. Tarjanyi then thanked the society for the great honor bestowed on him, and assured the members that he would work tirelessly for the growth and betterment of this organization.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kovacs gave a rather lengthy speech explaining the necessity for each Hungarian workingman to join an organization of this kind, and with appropriate words, he closed this gigantic celebration.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0904.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The United States national anthem was then played by Joseph Kovacs string orchestra and the audience stood and sang.</p>
   <p>After this most beautiful program practically every one took part in the banquet and supper which had been prepared by the organization.</p>
   <p>The total profits from this grand celebration amounted to $500.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
