<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-08-25">Aug. 25, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Selection of Miss Hungary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0371</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0371.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-08-25">Aug. 25, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">SELECTION OF MISS HUNGARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About seven hundred persons gathered Monday evening at Herzl Hall to witness the selection of the Queen for the Hungarian Day at the Century of Progress. The coveted title of "Miss Hungary" was awarded to pretty Miss Helen Peter, who lives with her parents.....She is young, not quite 18 yet, and exceedingly beautiful. It would be hard to find another girl better suited for this title, although the other six contestants are very beautiful too, and were selected as the Queen's ladies in waiting. The Queen's court, one of the most attractive features of Hungarian Day, is composed of Margaret Gorombey, Aranka Tunkl, Gizella Szabo, all of Chicago, Julia Girasin of Indiana Harbor, and Ethel Haryada of Whiting.</p>
   <p>The selection was done by nine members of the Exposition Committee through secret voting, and in this selection the opinion, taste, and liking of the public was not taken into consideration at all. We cannot understand why all that large crowd was called together since it wasn't given a chance to <pb facs="5422061_2_0372.jpg" n="2"/>express its opinion as to the selection. Also, where were our Hungarian artists who would have been able to do the selecting through professional eyes, thereby avoiding the inevitable murmuring and dissatisfaction evident afterward?</p>
   <p>We repeat that in spite of this faulty arrangement, the selection is most lucky and the Queen, as well as her ladies in waiting, will rival in beauty, as well as in appearance, any of the other Queens and courts selected by other national groups.</p>
   <p>We have to remark that both presidents of the Hungarian Group of the World's Fair, Dr. Arpad Barothy and Ernest Holvay, who left their wives home for this occasion, were enthusiastically applauding all twenty contestants. Had their votes counted, we would have twenty Queens instead of one.</p>
   <p>K. E. [Ernest Kunstadt.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
