<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1937-10-21">Oct. 21, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Ifjusagi Kor Dancers Perform at Szureti Bal</title><title level="a" type="sub">(English Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0314</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0314.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1937-10-21">Oct. 21, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">IFJUSAGI KOR DANCERS PERFORM AT SZURETI BAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(English Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Despite the inclement weather condition of the seventeenth, several hundred people gather in the church hall to celebrate the Grape-Vintage Festival Dance. Among the crowd the Ifjusagi Kor dancers could be observed most easily because of their Magyar costumes of many brilliant colors. Long since they had danced at this church hall, the Ifjusagi Kor occupied the prominent place in the program of the evening. Although several members of both groups were not present, those who were there carried forth the colors of the club.</p>
   <p>The Kor Junior Dancing Group were the first to dance. They performed the Toborzo and then the Csardas. The crowd who had assembled thundered a mighty applause after the youngsters had performed each dance. This little group, ably led by young Szenassy and Rosemarie Szenassy, included the following: Elizabeth Balogi, Catherine Pesik, Rosemarie Pesik, Eugene Petrovitz, Lillian Radi, Catherine Schnagel, Olga Szabo and Betty Timko.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0315.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Senior Group, too, danced "Palotas" and the gay and lively "Koszoru Csardas" and it was with enthusiasm that they performed it. The people certainly enjoyed the program of dances as was most apparent from the uproar and the immense applause given to the groups. While several members did not show up at this affair, others came who had not been present at the German-Hungarian festival last week. The Senior Group, last Sunday, consisted of: Olga Chudek, Frank Chulay, Catherine Fury, Charlotte Gonczlik, Rosemarie Huzianyi, Steve Huzianyi, Margaret Kalman, Frank Kantor, Marvin Kunstadt, Ella Meszaros, Betty Mihalyka, Margaret Miller, Ethel Petrovitz, "Jim" Radi, and Alexander Szabo.</p>
   <p>We hope that these public performances will serve as an inducement to the other members of the dancing groups to show a better spirit towards our club and to cooperate more heartily. It is essential that we prove worthy of the good reputation which we are enjoying and which has echoed in Budapest. We must keep up the good work that is being accomplished. Are you co-operating fellow-member? Then do not forget our annual Dance-Festival next Sunday at the Harmony Hall, 1639 N.Artesian Avenue, which will climax with the crowning of "Miss Hungary" who will be selected <pb facs="5422061_2_0316.jpg" n="3"/>by directors and officials of the Chicago Automobile Show under the energetic supervision of Mr. A. C. Faeh, Show manager of the 38th Annual Chicago Automobile Show which will be held from November 6 to the 23rd at the International Amphitheatre, at 43rd Street.</p>
   <p>Stephen Hulzianyi.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
