<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-06-09">June 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Statement</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1367</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1367.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-06-09">June 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">STATEMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In connection with the convention of all Hungarian associations, scheduled to take place on June 23, 24, and 25 the Preparations Committee, as well as the associations and members that intend to participate, were subjected to heavy and entirely unreasonable attacks by Szabadsag and Nepszava. [Translator's Note: Abridged name of the Hungarian daily Amerikai Magyar Nepszava.]</p>
   <p>Almost all Hungarian associations of America find themselves in a grave crisis, caused by bank failures, devaluation of bonds, loss of members stricken off their membership rolls as a result of unemployment, to say nothing of the fact that many of the members are reaching old age. We can find a way out of this crisis if we lay aside our petty differences and get together, regardless of religious or political beliefs, to discuss our common problems.</p>
   <p>All Hungarian associations ought to get together, in order to ask the <pb facs="5422061_2_1368.jpg" n="2"/>government--like other national groups are doing--for reimbursement of their bank deposits and bonds. Through unification and debate we have to find a way to retain our unemployed and aged members in our ranks and to prevent their being stricken off our membership rolls. We have to take a stand on the question of old age, pensions for the invalid, and unemployment insurance by the State.</p>
   <p>The time has come when all associations, whatever their trends, have to bring into being a strong united front in order to safeguard the interests of their members. The time is here when we ought to put aside all religious or political differences that may in any way hamper the struggle for these noble aims.</p>
   <p>The convention of June 23, 24, and 25 will serve this purpose because it will deal with the interests of all sick benefit associations. Such questions as are not strictly the problems of the Hungarian sick benefit and other associations will not be considered at the Chicago convention, the <pb facs="5422061_2_1369.jpg" n="3"/>purpose of which is limited to finding a remedy for the economic ills of our associations and their members. The convention will not deal with political problems, in the discussion of which the unity of the Hungarian-Americans always splits. The situation of the Hungarian associations and their members is so oppressive that it is just about time that something be done to ease it. All Hungarian associations should do everything possible to be represented at the Chicago convention.</p>
   <p>Working against the interests of the associations and their members are those who do not want to perceive the seriousness of the problem, who try to frustrate the success of the convention by means of subterfuge and slander, and who endeavor to dissuade the associations from electing and sending delegates to the convention. The situation is extremely grave. The time is ripe for unified action and those who for any reason--the Red menace or any other equally unfounded phantasmagoria--attack the Chicago convention or try to frustrate its work, are only demonstrating their willingness to sacrifice the interests of the associations and that of <pb facs="5422061_2_1370.jpg" n="4"/>all the members for their own selfish purposes.</p>
   <p>[Translator's Note: Signed by seventeen members of the Preparations Committee.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
