<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-03-28">Mar. 28, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">The Call of the Chicago Hungarian Cemetery Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0736</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0736.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1930-03-28">Mar. 28, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">THE CALL OF THE CHICAGO HUNGARIAN CEMETERY ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Hungarian Brethren! A small but enthusiastic group of Hungarians have just realized a beautiful ideal, the realization of which--we admit regretfully--has long been our desire but was never carried through, making us inferior to other national groups.</p>
   <p>The idea of a Hungarian Cemetery occurred to some of us in March, just at the time of the 82nd anniversary of March 15, 1848.</p>
   <p>In 1848, a few fiery-souled young men, inspired by the freedom of the West, began a struggle for the liberation of the Hungarian people.....After the war for liberty came the sad fate of Kossuth and other notable heroes, some of whom were exiled and at last found peace in death.</p>
   <p>However, the veneration of the Hungarians for their national heroes did not allow their earthly remains to become dust in foreign countries; instead, and so that their descendants may kneel at their graves, they brought their bodies <pb facs="5422061_2_0737.jpg" n="2"/>back and laid them in Magyar soil, so that their dreams would be sweeter and their graves may become a place of pilgrimage for Hungarians.</p>
   <p>Here, in our adopted country, in this great and glorious land, the American heroes of the Revolutionary War are resting in Arlington, Tennessee (sic). Arlington is a sacred spot of the Yankees and a place of pilgrimage for American citizens. Not so long ago, when Taft, one of the greatest men of this great country, died, his last wish was that he be buried in Arlington..... The children of this country understood Taft's last wish, a wish which expressed his love for his country in such a beautiful way.....</p>
   <p>The greatest people of ancient time were builders--the Egyptians built the pyramids and the Romans burrowed catacombs in the cliffs to leave a mark for future generations. However, the nomads, who traveled here and there, vanished from the face of the earth because they were not cultured enough to be able to create and erect anything permanent.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0738.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Hungarian Brethren! We are not nomads. We are not inferior to other nationalities in any way. Therefore, let us not give others the opportunity to say that the descendants in Chicago of our glorious Hungary have not done their share in the building of one of the wonders of the world--the great and beautiful Chicago.</p>
   <p>It can't be permitted that we should disappear without a trace from this earth, like the nomads. Let us, therefore, inscribe our names in the history of Chicago. Let us aid the work that was begun. Let us establish permanent monuments for our descendants. Let us forget for once our religious and political differences, as well as our personal antagonisms. Let us listen to our hearts' command and not to false prophets.</p>
   <p>The foundation is laid. The place of veneration of the Chicago Hungarians is not a dream any more. The Association is not asking our Hungarian brethren for charity, but to provide themselves with a place in the Hungarian National Cemetery, <pb facs="5422061_2_0739.jpg" n="4"/>in the beautiful Elmwood Memorial Park. Sooner or later one must buy a grave, but at present one can be purchased at a smaller cost and under more propitious terms. Besides, by buying our grave lots now, our loved ones will have a duty less to perform in the sad hour of their bereavement.</p>
   <p>A beautiful monument, planned by a Hungarian artist, will forever proclaim that Hungarians have lived here.</p>
   <p>That this may become a reality, we must reserve one thousand lots. Please help us!</p>
   <p>For further information, the business manager, who is working for this noble cause without fee, will be glad to be of service.</p>
   <p>Reverend John S. Muranyi.</p>
   <p>Bert Fodor, president.</p>
   <p>Frank K. Kalman, secretary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
