<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-06-22">June 22, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Hungarian Summer School in Burnside and West Pullman</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Eugene Boros, Pastor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0627</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0627.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-06-22">June 22, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">HUNGARIAN SUMMER SCHOOL IN BURNSIDE AND WEST PULLMAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Eugene Boros, Pastor</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hungarian Reformed Church of Burnside will open a summer school, as it has done every year since the building of the church.</p>
   <p>If ever there was a need for instilling love and loyalty into the hearts of the children of our thousand-year-old mother country, whose soil is saturated with the blood of our heroes, now is the time. Every child of Hungarian parentage should be taught the glorious history--the brave past and the sorrowful oppressed present--of Hungary. This is the only way to show them a true picture of the ruined Hungary, so that some day they will want to do something for the rebuilding of our old country.</p>
   <p>He who doesn't give his children the opportunity thus offered, commits an unpardonable sin toward his children, himself, and the country of his birth. Love for our mother country can be taught to our children born in America if we <pb facs="5422061_2_0628.jpg" n="2"/>send them to a Hungarian school.</p>
   <p>The summer school session in Burnside and West Pullman will begin on June 25. Children of church members don't pay tuition fees; others pay two dollars for the semester. However, fifty cents is required of each pupil for books and school supplies, whether they are members' children or not.</p>
   <p>The semester is only five weeks. Registration closes on June 27. Closing exercises will be held at the Magyar Home on July 29.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
