<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1929-01-04">Jan. 4, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Seething Revisionist Movement</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by Dr. Erno Lowinger)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1745</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1745.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2 (Italian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1929-01-04">Jan. 4, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">SEETHING REVISIONIST MOVEMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by Dr. Erno Lowinger)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although we have repeatedly expressed our views on the movement for the revision of the Trianon treaty, we must clear up one or two points to dispel any doubts.</p>
   <p>We, too, believe that the peace treaty of Trianon is unjust. We are willing to do anything in our power to bring about its revision, as long as we don't come into conflict with American laws by doing so.</p>
   <p>We believe also that the Trianon treaty has affected the Hungarian people and has caused much suffering and privations to the Hungarian working class. The Trianon treaty is too stringent and cruel. In our opinion its revision is necessary, especially for the interests of millions of Hungarian workers.</p>
   <p>It is a well-known fact that the kettle of the revision movement is boiling <pb facs="5422061_2_1746.jpg" n="2"/>again in Magyar-America, where different ambitions and efforts are striving for recognition.</p>
   <p>Some persons are trying to push themselves to the fore to satisfy their egoistic aims. Others think that by taking part in this movement, they can stimulate their business.</p>
   <p>Still others want to be rewarded for their "unselfish" patriotic activities by the Hungarian government.</p>
   <p>All of these noble and ignoble motives or aims are negligible in our opinion.</p>
   <p>We can truthfully state that none of the aforementioned motives or aims can be applied to us. Nevertheless, we do voice two conditions which should be borne in mind whenever there is a gathering of Hungarian-Americans discussing the revision of the Trianon treaty.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1747.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Always and everywhere we must declare that the movement for the revision of the Trianon treaty is not in the interests of Hungary's feudal lords and priesthood, but in behalf of the oppressed, impoverished Hungarian people. Furthermore, the movement stands for the establishment of a democratic form of government and the restoration to Hungary of Hungarian territories.</p>
   <p>We must also explain clearly that we do not condone the present tendency of the Hungarian government to restore the king to the throne. The American-Hungarians are true to the ideals of the American Constitution and sympathize with a republican form of government. We would not make a move to help to the throne a degenerate member of the Hapsburg dynasty, or any other aspiring feudal lord.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1748.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Our other stipulation is that we should not follow or foster such Hungarian politics here as would be objectionable and in direct conflict with American political interests.</p>
   <p>In Italian circles, a few fanatical leaders wanted to start a Fascist organization on the pattern of Mussolini's organization. The result was that the American press made public this un-American activity, which proved very embarrasing to Italian-Americans, and which was discussed even in Congress.....</p>
   <p>Before the Trianon treaty revision movement becomes more serious, it would be advisable to ask the proper United States authorities whether or not it is legal for American citizens to organize an active political party for the revision of the Trianon treaty here in America.</p>
   <p>If we do not ask this information now, then when the movement has gained momentum and will mean something to the Americans, others who oppose the revision will do it. It is not necessary to say that the enemies of the <pb facs="5422061_2_1749.jpg" n="5"/>revision of the Trianon treaty are numerous and that they also have influential friends in the proper places.</p>
   <p>Let us remember, too, that it is an easy matter to persuade liberal America to form an unsympathetic attitude toward the dictator-ridden....Hungary.</p>
   <p>We believe that not even for the sake of this revision movement we would want to acquire the reputation of not being faithful and responsible citizens of our adopted country.....</p>
   <p>During the past twenty-five years we have seen, more than once, instances of feverish enthusiasm toward a cause in Magyar-America, yet the results were always--we are sorry to say--nil.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1750.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We are all horrified by the injustice of the Trianon treaty, because it is terrible.</p>
   <p>But our justified resentment should be told and explained to our influential American friends, to gain their sympathy toward this cause. This would be the proper method in our endeavor to gain our goal--revision of the peace treaty of Trianon.</p>
   <p>Let us not overexert ourselves in this cause.....Let us use brains, not brawn.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
