<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-06-11">June 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">There Will Be a Hungarian Home on the South Side</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1265</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1265.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-06-11">June 11, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THERE WILL BE A HUNGARIAN HOME ON THE SOUTH SIDE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Virgin Mary Society held its regular monthly meeting last Sunday afternoon, and the enthusiasm with which this meeting was conducted will have its effect upon the Hungarian population of Chicago, as well as other Hungarian localities in the United States.</p>
   <p>Four years ago a few members of this organization thought that it was about time the Hungarians of the South Side should build themselves a Home, and the idea was put before the officers and members of this Society. The idea was thought worthwhile, so other Hungarian organizations were consulted in regard to this question. Many meetings were held, but very little was accomplished.</p>
   <p>The Virgin Mary Society wanted to build, but they were afraid that some <pb facs="5422061_2_1266.jpg" n="2"/>other Hungarian organization also was considering this project. It seemed as though no other Hungarian organization was even thinking of putting up a building of this kind, so the Virgin Mary Society at their March meeting appointed a committee of twelve to draw up plans and make the necessary arrangements to get started on the building.</p>
   <p>This committee worked hard and faithfully, and they submitted a completely detailed plan for the construction of the Home.</p>
   <p>These plans were accepted, and it was decided at this meeting to float $90,000 worth of bonds through a reliable bank, and the Society would pay six and one-half per cent [interest] on these bonds.</p>
   <p>This projected "Hungarian Home" is a new idea in the lives of the Hungarians of America. This is the first time that a Society has gone into a project which will act as an influence for more Hungarian activity. Now the <pb facs="5422061_2_1267.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago Hungarians will have a place they can call their own and they can feel mighty proud of themselves.</p>
   <p>We do not want to look at this project as one that belongs to the Virgin Mary Society alone; we want to look at it as one that is for the interest of all Hungarians of Chicago.</p>
   <p>We think that every Hungarian person who is financially able to buy these bonds should buy some, because he will be helping a very worthy idea, and the dream that most Hungarians of Chicago have had, will come true.</p>
   <p>The editorial staff of this newspaper wishes to congratulate the brave leaders and members of the Virgin Mary Society, and the Society can rest assured that this newspaper will co-operate in every way to see that this Home is built, because we of this newspaper know more than anyone else what it will mean to the Chicago Hungarians, and especially to those living on the South Side.	</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
