<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-01-31">Jan. 31, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A Common Language Is Essential</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1184</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1184.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-01-31">Jan. 31, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A COMMON LANGUAGE IS ESSENTIAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What should be said of a world leading democracy where ten per cent of the adult population can not read the laws which they are supposed to know?What should be said of a democracy which sends an army of 2,000,000 drafted men to preach democracy among whom ten per cent can not read the letters sent them from home?</p>
   <p>What should be said of a democracy which calls upon its citizens to consider the wisdom of forming a League of Nations, to pass judgment upon a code which will insure the freedom of the seas, to sacrifice the daily stint of wheat and meat for the benefit of the Roumanians and the Jugo-Slavs, when eighteen per cent of the coming citizens of that democracy do not go to school?</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1185.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What should be said of a democracy which permits one of its sovereign states to spend six dollars a year for a child in the maintenance of a public school system?</p>
   <p>What should be said of a democracy which is challenged by the world to prove the superiority of its system of government over those now discarded, and yet is compelled to reach many millions of its people through letters printed in foreign languages?</p>
   <p>What should be said of a democracy which spends twice as much in one year for chewing gum as for school books, and more for automobiles than for all primary and secondary education in which the average salary of a teacher is less than that of the average laborer?</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1186.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>What should be said of a democracy which permits thousands of its native born children to be taught American History in a foreign language, the Declaration of Independence and Lincoln's Gettysburg address in German and in other tongues?</p>
   <p>What should be said of a democracy which permits men and women to work in places where they seldom or never hear a word of English spoken?</p>
   <p>Yet these facts were true in the United States during 1919.</p>
   <p>These figures and facts look discouraging and may present a picture that might spell doom for this Republic. But, in reality, they present an outlook that is far from disturbing and this is very gratifying that such a government as ours is ever watchful for every pitfall to overthrow it. Our will to do the right with all our might is never wanting when we are able to see our difficulties and know the way out. Already, methods have been devised by which the above mentioned conditions are being remedied with much success for the good of the country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
