<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1924-12-07">Dec.7, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Is There a Necessity for a Hungarian Catholic Church on the North Side?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1510</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1510.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III C (Slovak)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1924-12-07">Dec.7, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">IS THERE A NECESSITY FOR A HUNGARIAN CATHOLIC CHURCH ON THE NORTH SIDE?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4.... According to the census of 1920, the population of Chicago that year was 2,701,705. This census shows that of the 805,482 foreign born population, 26,106 are from Hungary.</p>
   <p>Twenty-six thousand souls would make a fair sized city in Hungary. We must also take into consideration that the Hungarians in Chicago are mostly adults, because their children were born here. For the past ten years immigration has been low, but in addition to this 26,000 there are many of our countrymen, who are from pre-war Hungary, which would swell this total considerably. Most of our Hungarians take active part in social activities.</p>
   <p>The leaders of social life among the Hungarians are their Societies and newspapers. We all know of these. Of just as great importance are the <pb facs="5422061_2_1511.jpg" n="2"/>Hungarian churches. We find three Reformed churches and one Roman Catholic church. We know the important role churches have in the life of Americans as well as other nationalities. The church is the most important institution of foreigners. Americans take note of a nation through their churches. Around the churches, schools and societies are formed. The Hungarian church is the haven of Hungarian culture and speech in a foreign land.</p>
   <p>Those who belong to the church are better people. They learn to appreciate their families, educate their children. It is the patriotic duty of the Hungarians to have as many churches as possible.</p>
   <p>Has Chicago enough Hungarian Catholic churches? The church on the Burnside can only take care of those few Hungarians, who live south of 40th Street. No one can expect people to travel two hours to church and two hours back. For this reason, the Burnside church has a membership of only 300 families of which 100 families are Polish. The 200 families total more than 1,000 souls. How about the other ten or more thousands of Hungarian Catholics? Where do they go to church?</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1512.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is a fact that 60% of post-war Hungary is Catholic, so that there are 15,600 Hungarian Catholics in Chicago today. Some of these are German Hungarians, who belong to St. Michael and St.Joseph German Catholic churches. Discounting this number, there are still 12,000 immigrant Hungarian Catholics, who need a Hungarian church.</p>
   <p>The Slovaks have seven Catholic churches. Why shall the Hungarians have only one? There are two Hungarian Catholic churches in South Bend, in Cleveland there are three. Every Hungarian regardless of his religion, feels the injustice of the position of the Chicago Hungarian Catholics. How shall we organize the Hungarian Catholic Church on the North Side?</p>
   <p>1. Let us realize that we spend a certain amount of money on churches. This amount could be given toward the support of a Hungarian Catholic church.</p>
   <p>2. Many of us would gladly give more money to a Hungarian Catholic Church, to be able to pray and sing in Hungarian, to have the last sacrament administered in our own language.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1513.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>3. The North Side societies should discuss among themselves, organize groups, gather the names of the people, and hold meetings.</p>
   <p>4. Appoint a committee to go to the Archbishop with a list of the names of Hungarian Catholics, and pledge support to such a church.</p>
   <p>Where two people ask God in the name of Jesus Christ, He is with them.</p>
   <p>Rev. L. D. Mosonyi - D.D.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
