<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1924-08-22">Aug. 22, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Immigrant Hungarian-American Doctor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1612</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1612.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1924-08-22">Aug. 22, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE IMMIGRANT HUNGARIAN-AMERICAN DOCTOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few months ago during an interview in Budapest, Berthold Singor, American consul, predicted that, those professional men who are being driven out of Hungary would be taken care of by the United States, and that he would make it his business to see that this would be done.</p>
   <p>The honorable consul's prediction has come true, because in the past two years sixteen learned young doctors have come to Chicago from Hungary. Most of these have opened their own offices, probably not earning a great deal at the present time, but they have high hopes for the future. We feel that we should single out one in particular, and that is Dr. Tivadar Koppanyi, who came to this country through an invitation extended to him by the University of Chicago to accept a position as professor of biology. Doctor Koppanyi is only twenty-three years old but has already gained recognition in his particular field. The daily American press has already expressed their recognition of the achievements of this young doctor.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1613.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Another immigrant, Doctor Szekely, is a consulting doctor at the nearby Napierville Tuberculosis Sanitarium. Doctor Klinger is a surgeon at the Western Electric Company's hospital. Doctor Zeisler, one of the youngest doctors from Hungary, has been placed in the dispensary of the Michael Reese Hospital, devoting himself to the study of internal ailments.</p>
   <p>Doctor Zeisler has been in this country for only the short period of six months. Last month he passed his State examination and has opened offices at 3100 So. Halsted Street.</p>
   <p>We want to call the attention of all Hungarians on the South Side to the fact that this young doctor is well worth considering, because he is so well versed in medics, and his medical skill is unquestionable.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
