<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-06-02">June 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Successful Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0238</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-ukrainian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0238.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2) (Ukrainian)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a (German)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-06-02">June 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">SUCCESSFUL CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was on an exceedingly beautiful spring day, in which even the sun contributed its share to the success of the occasion, that the grand spring concert of the Workers Singing Choir and the Workers Orchestra took place at the People's Auditorium, whose hall was crowded with those Hungarians who gladly aid and support the activities of these organizations. We note with great rejoicing that on this occasion there were present many people who up to them had not shown much interest in the artistic activities of the workers.</p>
   <p>It was an imposing sight, indeed, when the heavy bordeaux-colored velvet curtains were raised and there on the stage before us we saw, in well-ordered rows, the workers' mixed choir and orchestra, all their members clad in white. This is not intended to be a courteously flattering report, yet we still have to say that the director of the orchestra, Henry Helm, and the leader of the singing choir, Joseph B. Mayer, did a job which deserves praise.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0239.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The selections played by the orchestra, as well as the singing of the choir, were well received by the audience. The last number on the program, "Lady Bird," was so well liked that, on general acclamation and after a hurricane of applause, it had to be repeated. The other numbers of the program were also first-class. As to the guest artists, we must mention Laura Jean Ruhig, who played a beautiful violin solo, and Helene Varga, who earned tremendous applause with her piano solo. Great success crowned the performance of the Ukrainian Dance Ensemble; also successful was the German singing choir Freiheit, composed of fifty members. The Workers Singing Choir and the Workers Orchestra [Translator's Note: The article does not say whether or not these organizations are Hungarian] were rewarded with applause and encouraging words from the public.</p>
   <p>And now, singers of the workers, you are assured of an audience, not of five hundred but of a thousand persons at your next concert in the fall. Sing and work, you certainly deserve all support and aid.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
