<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-10-14">Oct. 14, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Educate Our Brethren</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Erno Lowinger (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1161</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1161.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-10-14">Oct. 14, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">LET US EDUCATE OUR BRETHREN</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. Erno Lowinger (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Aldous Huxley, one of England's most exceptional young authors, recently made a trip around the world. He wrote several articles for Harper's Magazine, and among them is his essay on the future of American culture. We are quoting one or two thoughts from this essay, which will explain our analysis.</p>
   <p>"America's future is the future of the world. Economic circumstances force all the nations to imitate America. It seems that the world is becoming Americanized, for good or evil. America is not unique. America simply leads on the path that other nations and continents wish to follow. When we study the good and bad sides of American life, we really study the more definite and highly developed form of today's and tomorrow's civilization."</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1162.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We Hungarians, by the will of the Almighty, or because of the persecution by the Hungarian government, militaristic or judicial, have landed in America, the seething, expanding and reigning center of civilization. It isn't a trifling matter to leave one's birthplace, be it in a small lowland village or in beautiful Transylvania, and be transplanted to America. One can't but wonder that some people are dazed by the sudden and great change.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian churches, societies, publications, social centers, and the theater, make it easier for the immigrant to get accustomed to the change.</p>
   <p>In this strange civilization, in the tiresome and unceasing toil which we find in America, the ordinary Hungarian individual would collapse if it weren't for these oases where they could be refreshed, consoled, and encouraged.</p>
   <p>The second generation of Hungarians feel at home here as much as those whose ancestors came on the Mayflower in 1620.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1163.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But we who breathed the good Hungarian air and who were taught by Hungarian school masters, have to forget first and then learn about and understand the civilization of this country.....</p>
   <p>Until we know and learn this, we may be American citizens, old settlers, and social leaders, but we won't be real Americans. Our American life will be empty. We will be only spectators, not vital factors.</p>
   <p>Many Hungarian adults are at odds with the English language. The domestic English used in our everyday work is not good enough to enable us to comprehend thoroughly the dominating civilization of America.</p>
   <p>In all probability there are only one or two in a thousand, who, through special circumstances, attain the mental level of the natives and understand the problems of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1164.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We believe that it is up to these privileged few to impart some of this knowledge to their less fortunate countrymen.</p>
   <p>We do not doubt that there is a class of people here who are not satisfied with dancing, auto riding, and movie going, but wants to learn about real American life.....</p>
   <p>We like to believe that there are unselfish and conscientious Hungarians who want to enlighten their brethren about the new world civilization and make them a part of this great country.</p>
   <p>We just want to sow the seeds of our unselfish ideas, but hope that our leaders will carry the plan through.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1165.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The question now is: Are there any high-minded, intelligent, thinking individuals in our Hungarian circle, who understand these ideals, and is there enough ambition and brotherly love in them to be willing to carry these plans through?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
