<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-02-18">Feb. 18, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">There Is No Time to Be Shy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1859</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1859.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-02-18">Feb. 18, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THERE IS NO TIME TO BE SHY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A declaration was made by Baron Sterenyi, Ex-Minister of Commerce, which is of much interest to American-Magyars. Furthermore, this declaration proves that the Magyar Tribune was right when it warned the American-Magyars to be careful when they read the "sweet" messages and promises of the great lords sent over from Hungary. We advise you not to act as "scapegoats," believing there is any sincerity in anything the great lords promise. Baron Sterenyi's declaration reads as follows: "I would loan my money to the State of Hungary. Our American brothers could save the Fatherland if they would put their savings at the disposal of the State of Hungary. The emigrated Magyars, who were persecuted while residing in Hungary, and in whom no one showed a desire to aid, could restore the country. The dollar now has such a high market value that a few million dollars would assist us greatly, also a few years of good crops would aid this country to revive itself. But it has to be made possible for us to carry on through these few years. I venture to say that our fate rests <pb facs="5422061_2_1860.jpg" n="2"/>in the hands of the American-Magyars. If I were the head of the Government, I would ask Count Apponyi to go to America to accomplish this aim. I imagine that much money has accumulated in America during the war when no money could have been sent to Hungary. If our kin would give only a part of that money, the work and the grain production could begin at home. The American-Magyars on the other hand could engage in a good business and they would make a good investment with their money, they would risk nothing. It is their duty to aid their native country and their kin left at home, even if it would call for some risk. But if this work can be done without any hazard, I think they should consider it their sacred duty."</p>
   <p>It is real Solomonic advice, is it not? We know that we could save our native country with our savings, and we always have been willing to do so, but if we are forced to donate this money to the great lords for the restoration of the old system, it would be discouraging. We will not do it. We regret that Mr. Sterenyi, a man of such high intelligence, would even suggest this plan.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1861.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, we appreciate the fact that you admit the attitude of the great lords towards American-Magyars, that the American-Magyars were always despised by the great lords of Hungary, and still you wish to send Count Apponyi to this country to aid you in this work. We know that the great lords would like to get our money, it would enable them to continue to persecute us in the future. American-Magyars, however, will not give them strength for that.</p>
   <p>At this time we give a brief answer to Mr. Von Lorthy's last week's newspaper article.</p>
   <p>Mr. Von Lorthy should be able to see that it is dangerous to wait any longer and thereby permit great lords to use every means to deprive the American-Magyars of their hard earned savings. There will be no need of any misunderstanding between us if your policy is the same as it was in the past. If you start the work on this same plan with our support, nobody will be strong enough to hinder us in this work, because if we <pb facs="5422061_2_1862.jpg" n="4"/>begin to give our protests to such treatment, that will bring some real results. Then, there will be no use for the lamp post. We want to earn the esteem of our suffering mother country and the love of her tormented people. Therefore, let us act, Mr. Von Lorthy. This is no time for shyness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
