<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-10-17">Oct. 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Duties of Hungarian American Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1078</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1078.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-10-17">Oct. 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">DUTIES OF HUNGARIAN AMERICAN SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To prevent the starvation of countless Hungarian children of Europe the first thing we must do is to start organizing a relief movement. To start a movement of this kind is not an easy task. It is true that these movements to be successful must be started by established organizations. Usually when such movements are started by society circles and various organizations it gradually envelopes all the Hungarians.</p>
   <p>Regardless of how charitable the Hungarian people are, the results will not be staisfactory if the inspiration and all the hard work is left to the newspapers to conduct, while the leaders of Hungarian societies disregard the fate of the poor people suffering in Hungary. The Hungarian churches should also lend a hand in helping the starving Hungarian children.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1079.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Religious organizations should hold this as one of their principal charities and should not be afraid of the hard work that is involved.</p>
   <p>In many cities individual societies have already started this work, and according to information received they have had splendid results.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian Reformed Federation has donated $5,000 for this cause. We must look at the organization with deepest gratitude for this worthy donation. We must admit that this organization has done its duty in aiding the unfortunate people of Hungary.</p>
   <p>If other societies follow the lead of the Hungarian Reformed Federation, even if their donation is not quite as large, they will be setting an example for all Hungarians. Then we can rest assured that Hungarians across the ocean, who are in great need, will get relief which they <pb facs="5422061_2_1080.jpg" n="3"/>will greatly appreciate.</p>
   <p>The leaders of societies should not forget this newest duty. Each and every society should consider this subject and plan to send aid to the starving Hungarian children. This should be done at once.</p>
   <p>We can not imagine a single Hungarian society that will not do its bit for such a worthy cause.</p>
   <p>We know what faithful hearts the Hungarian-American possess. We feel sure that the starving Hungarian children will soon learn about and profit from this generous spirit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
