<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-11-04">Nov. 4, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of Flags in Burnside</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0828</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0828.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1927-11-04">Nov. 4, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF FLAGS IN BURNSIDE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The First Hungarian Women's Social and Sick Benefit Society of Chicago and Vicinity held the dedication of its flags on October 23.</p>
   <p>The celebration was scheduled to begin at three o'clock, but it was six before the auditorium of the Magyar Home was filled with the attentive, serious celebrants.</p>
   <p>The delegates of the following societies were present: First Hungarian Women and Men Workers' Sick Benefit Society, West Pullman First Hungarian Sick Benefit Society, First Roman and Greek Catholic Sick Benefit and Ladies' Society, South Chicago King St. Stephen I Women's and Men's Sick Benefit Society, Verhovay Branch 37, Chicago and Vicinity Hungarian Sick Benefit Society, Burnside Reformed Men's and Women's Sick Benefit Society, Chicago and Vicinity United Virgin Mary Society, West Pullman Protected Home Circle, Branch 229, <pb facs="5422061_2_0829.jpg" n="2"/>and the Hungarian Republican Club of Burnside.</p>
   <p>Sponsors of the Hungarian flag were Mr. and Mrs. Stephen Szilvagyi and Mr. and Mrs. John Rakaczky. For the American flag the sponsors were Mr. and Mrs. John Orosz and Mr. and Mrs. John Juszko. They drove small golden nails into the flag poles. The black mourning crepe for the Hungarian flag was donated by Mr. and Mrs. George Racz and Mr. and Mrs. John Demeter. [Translator's note: Black crepe signifies that the Hungarian nation is in mourning for its lost territories of the World War.]</p>
   <p>The Reverend Stephen Soltesz, Roman Catholic priest, dedicated the flags and then blessed them.</p>
   <p>The Reverend Eugene Boros, pastor of the Burnside Hungarian Reformed Church, was the principal speaker. He explained the symbolic meaning of the comparatively young American flag and then talked of the centuries old, glorious <pb facs="5422061_2_0830.jpg" n="3"/>past and sad present of the Hungarian tricolor. He closed with a prayer and asked blessings for the Society.</p>
   <p>Other noteworthy speakers were: Reverend Joseph Kovalcsik, Greek Catholic pastor, and Dr. Geza Takats, professor of Medicine at Northwestern University.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
