<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-02-04">Feb. 4, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">An Open Letter to Von Lorthy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1873</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1873.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-02-04">Feb. 4, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">AN OPEN LETTER TO VON LORTHY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Your attitude has placed us in a pensive state of mind because we firmly believe that when we issued our first call you would support us now as you did before by serving the interests of our native country and that of the Magyars living in America. We feel, to be truthful, that since you became the general manager of the Delight Film Corporation, you are unwilling to give a little of your spare time to do something for the welfare of the working people.</p>
   <p>Furthermore, we think that you are not well informed as to the present <pb facs="5422061_2_1874.jpg" n="2"/>situation in Hungary, because you are either too busy or do not care. Our impression, after reading your newspaper article is that you do not care. Instead of inspiring the American Magyars with greater energy for action, you Mr. Von Lorthy say that "Everything will be all right and blissful. Let us wait and see."</p>
   <p>What shall we wait for?</p>
   <p>Have you read the December 21st issue of the Pesti Hirlap? Of course you, Mr. general manager, did not read it. If you had you would think differently. Did you read that Lorant Hegedus, the new Finance minister, is continuing the policy of his predecessors by cutting a new piece from the living body of the country because there is still a little left to cut? There are new tax stamps, property redemption and other redemptions. Now comes another redemption. How long will this go on? What do those "lords" want? They are pretending to be <pb facs="5422061_2_1875.jpg" n="3"/>loyal to the country. They say that they did not desert the country as we did and, therefore, are not traitors.</p>
   <p>We left the country because we did not care to suffer any longer with the great lords as our oppressors. Please, Mr. Von Lorthy, get the above mentioned newspaper and you will be amazed.</p>
   <p>There you can read about the new order of the Finance Minister: Every bank deposit was attached and twenty crowns were appropriated from every 100 crowns by the government.</p>
   <p>It seems, Mr. Von Lorthy, you have no time to find out that letters are coming by the thousands, from the suffering Old Country, asking contributions, and that every American Magyar is constantly sending financial aid. You <pb facs="5422061_2_1876.jpg" n="4"/>don't seem to know that the American Magyar banks are daily publishing large advertisements exhorting the Magyars of this country to aid the people in the Old Country.</p>
   <p>We American Magyars sent enough money to our relatives in the Old Country to make their Christmas more pleasant. However, instead of helping our people we unwillingly helped the great lords, and we made a nice Christmas for them. They put their hands on the money when nobody expected it. The contributions which we sent for charitable purposes were taxed 20 Hellers on every Crown. What do you say to that, Mr. Von Lorthy?</p>
   <p>Shall we still wait with the belief that, "everything will be all right?"</p>
   <p>Did you read the message sent by Lorant Hegedus, Finance Minister, to us "deserters and traitors." Apparently you did not. He tells us that he <pb facs="5422061_2_1877.jpg" n="5"/>will let us, American Magyars, make our beloved people,of the Fatherland, happy; he will let us do that "small part," because our money is needed there. (But Hegedus would make only his own clique, the great lords,happy; our common people could perish). They know in the Old Country that they need our help now and they try to win us by flattery.</p>
   <p>Minister Huszar tried flattery too. We have to be satisfied, however, with the result or rather with the lack of results which Mr. Huszar obtained while touring in America. If we will always be careful and refuse to be fooled by the nice promises of the ministers, we will avoid the cut just as we did when Huszar was here.</p>
   <p>We are taking the liberty to tell you, sincerely, that although we still <pb facs="5422061_2_1878.jpg" n="6"/>admire your past policy, we would like to see you show your true colors; tell us if you want to lead us with your experience and knowledge or are you siding with the revivers of the old system. In the latter case you would earn the contempt of the "deserters and traitors," and you would also deserve the lamp-post. Your proper place would be not among us, the "traitors and deserters," but among those "great patriots," the great lords.</p>
   <p>Dear Mr. Lorthy, your newspaper article is an unpleasant surprise. We believed that you, as a real working man,-who without any aid or influence obtained your position-would be our leader in this big extraordinary problem, the restoration of Hungary. We cannot stand idle and see our dear native country dying away without our aid, for which idleness we would deserve a rightful reproach. On the other hand, we might get an unreliable leader, who might deceitfully spend our contributions towards reviving the old system. Then our great sacrifices would be in vain, without any benefit to our native <pb facs="5422061_2_1879.jpg" n="7"/>country.</p>
   <p>We hope that the great lords will see and resign themselves to the fact that we do not pay any attention to their talk or to their newspaper articles. We know that the great lords want to be present during our saving and restoration activities so they could boast in the future that they have restored order and thus get an opportunity to bleed the people again.</p>
   <p>In the December 21, 1920 issue of Pesti Hirlap, under the heading: "The Magyars of Foreign Countries for Hungary," the great lords affirm our statement that only we, the American Magyars can put Hungary on her feet. The great lords call everybody who is unwilling to contribute to the cause "traitors and deserters." That means they expect us "deserters" to give our money for strengthening the old system.</p>
   <p>Now we can ask: who are the real traitors? Are not the real traitors of the <pb facs="5422061_2_1880.jpg" n="8"/>country those who, knowing that the people lost confidence in them, still would not go away from the "larder?" Since the great lords admit that only we can restore the country, and that we do not trust them to handle our money, then why don't they clear away and let us "deserters" help our beloved native country to flourish and our kin folk, the working people, happy?</p>
   <p>You, Mr. Von Lorthy, not only want to keep away from the great work yourself out you are bold enough to warn everybody else: "let us wait." For what and for whom shall we wait? What can we expect if we simply look quietly at the games of the great lords? It is a mortal sin to wait any longer and do nothing.</p>
   <p>We believe that it should not be necessary to implore you, Mr. Von Lorthy. Get into action as soon as possible. It is your duty to offer your services to the country. We can demand it because the existence of the whole country <pb facs="5422061_2_1881.jpg" n="9"/>is at stake and not the existence of an individual.</p>
   <p>Mr. Lorthy, come out of the cave of idleness, and let us get busy before it is too late. Then we can say to you: "Everything will be all right and blissful." We do not have to wait and see because we know what will happen. So, Mr. Von Lorthy, let us become active and at the same time you can prove that your political platform is unchanged.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
