<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-05-29">May 29, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Virgin Mary Society Joins the Bridgeport Federation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0788</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0788.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1931-05-29">May 29, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE VIRGIN MARY SOCIETY JOINS THE BRIDGEPORT FEDERATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After long deliberation, the Burnside Virgin Mary Society has decided to join the Bridgeport Federation, which is one of the three largest national Hungarian fraternal organizations.</p>
   <p>The decision to join was adopted irrevocably last Sunday at a special meeting of the Virgin Mary Society, the members of which will be accepted by the Bridgeport Federation under a special arrangement whereby no one will lose his membership in the Society as a result of this change.</p>
   <p>Already last fall, the Virgin Mary Society had decided to join one of the larger national societies in order to save itself from the difficult situation caused by the purchase of the Magyar Home. After conferring with the Verhovay, the Rakoczy, and the Bridgeport Federation, the offer of the latter was found to be the best, and the majority of the members of the <pb facs="5422061_2_0789.jpg" n="2"/>Virgin Mary Society voted to join it.</p>
   <p>With this union not only has the Virgin Mary Society saved itself but the future of the Magyar Home has become brighter, inasmuch as the Bridgeport Federation will pay off the debts on the Magyar Home. The amount paid for the debts will be considered as a loan, at four and one half per cent, to the Virgin Mary Society, now a branch of the Bridgeport Federation. The Magyar Home will remain the property of this branch if the loan is repaid.</p>
   <p>This agreement establishes the Magyar Home on a sound basis, and we won't have to be afraid now that it will become the property of strangers.</p>
   <p>The union of the Virgin Mary Society with the Bridgeport Federation will be celebrated by a banquet at an early date.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
