<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1929-09-13">Sept. 13, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Bedouins of Hungarian Public Life</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by [Dr. Erno] Lowinger)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1727</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1727.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1929-09-13">Sept. 13, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE BEDOUINS OF HUNGARIAN PUBLIC LIFE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial by [Dr. Erno] Lowinger)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Someone courteously sent us a Budapest leaflet. The title of the leaflet is The Goal. It is a monthly, devoted to the defense of the race and was issued in mid-July. Our attention was called to a marked article entitled "The Toll Gatherers of the Revision."</p>
   <p>We looked over this leaflet in our spare time and came to the following conclusions: that the editor and his staff think that the best way to insure the survival of the Magyar race is to eliminate all German-born and Jewish persons from public offices and in their place put only those in whose veins the pure blood of our forefather Arpad flows.....</p>
   <p>The article about the toll gatherers of the revision is directly written for our benefit.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1728.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The press of the Hungarian-Americans, the revisionist movement and its Jewish and other national participants, are attacked in this little leaflet devoted to the defense of the race.....</p>
   <p>Please believe us that it is easier to argue with a child or an inmate of an insane asylum than with these hired poisonous Bedouins.....</p>
   <p>Here, as in Hungary, there can be found unconscionable schemers who look at all public movements with a view to making money.</p>
   <p>We acknowledge the fact that these schemers can be found not only in the ranks of the race defenders, but among the unpatriotic rogues, too.....</p>
   <p>The race-defending scoundrels have ascertained the fact that the revision of the peace treaty of Trianon is the most urgent political problem, the most sacred wound of the Hungarian people. They are ready to throw themselves into the revisionist movement and make small change out of the <pb facs="5422061_2_1729.jpg" n="3"/>tragedy, the life-and-death struggle of the Hungarian people.</p>
   <p>We have heard that, in Hungary, these swindlers contrived to squeeze money out of the pockets of the already harassed people with their revisionist schemes.....</p>
   <p>In Magyar-America, where the dollars are more plentiful than the pengos in Hungary, and where the cause of revision is just as near and dear to our hearts, these heartless schemers would like to usurp the occasion for their own mercenary ends.</p>
   <p>Their method is the same as in the past.</p>
   <p>Their aim is to alienate the well-meaning Christians and Jews from this cause by maligning the Hungarian Jews, so that, in the end, they could have a clear field in this revisionist movement for their personal gains.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1730.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The sad result is that these Bedouins of public life, these outlaws of the Hungarian pen, succeeded in alienating many reputable Hungarian individuals and in this way they made their own unscrupulous goal easier to attain. But the situation is slowly changing. Time and the severity of our common fate are driving the Hungarian press and public into newer channels.....</p>
   <p>Our common fate compels us to act in unison against these Bedouins.....</p>
   <p>When these jealous, hungry, swindling, pushing individuals shout about Fascism, Jewry, and intrude similar phraseology into our honest, conscientious, unselfish public activities, they should be disregarded and not even debated. Let us not waste our time or strength on these bellowings.....</p>
   <p>These public nuisances will disperse--like the bats in a summer's twilight that disappear at the first ray of the sun--as soon as the Hungarian-Americans will be organized.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
