<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-03-19">Mar. 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">The League of Nations and the World Court</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1224</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1224.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-03-19">Mar. 19, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">THE LEAGUE OF NATIONS AND THE WORLD COURT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The editorial staff of this newspaper has continually warned the Hungarian-American people to avoid those government officials who advocate and favor the idea of the United States joining the League of Nations and the World Court. These two international organizations are focal points of European unrest which may soon come to a head. This was proved by the last meeting of the League. After Germany was forced to accept the Locarno Treaty, she was promised permanent membership in the League, but now, for some unknown reason, the League has decided to wait until next September before it will accept Germany as a permanent member. This situation does not satisfy Germany in the least.</p>
   <p>We are now involved in the World Court question. The World Court is only a back door leading to the League. The United States has committed the grave mistake of committing America to membership in the World Court.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1225.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>George Washington, the father of this country, told the people of his day to avoid all foreign entanglements and alliances. This farsighted patriot was right in every respect. Any person in American public life who does not follow his advice is not a good citizen of the United States.</p>
   <p>The two men who are candidates for United States senator are McKinley and Frank L. Smith. McKinley has made the mistake of favoring the World Court, while Smith is opposed.</p>
   <p>We believe that the Hungarian people will show how they feel toward the World Court at the election on April 13. They know the World Court favors the international bankers and not the people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
