<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-08-25">August 25, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Can We Insure Our Associations Materially?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0919</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0919.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-08-25">August 25, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">CAN WE INSURE OUR ASSOCIATIONS MATERIALLY?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John Csizmadia, member of the National Board of Directors of the National Protective Federation of Hungarian-American Associations has received from the Reconstruction Finance Corporation a very important reply, which plainly shows that if the association act jointly like the Federation wants them to do, it is possible to obtain material aid for them from the Government.</p>
   <p>Here we give a copy, as well as its Hungarian translation, of the original letter:</p>
   <p>"John P. Csizmadia Esq.,</p>
   <p>8815 Buckeye Road,</p>
   <p>Cleveland, Ohio.</p>
   <p>"My dear Mr. Csizmadia:</p>
   <p>Your letter of June 10th in regard to the Hungarian-American Sick and Death <pb facs="5422061_2_0920.jpg" n="2"/>Benefit Societies has been referred by the office of the Secretary of the Treasury to the R. F. C. [Reconstruction Finance Corporation] for reply. In the second paragraph of your letter we note your question, "Are organizations of this character, namely, Fraternal Insurance Societies, eligible to obtain financial aid under the present law?" Public Act No. 35 of the 73rd Congress, commonly known as the Fletcher Bill to authorize the R. F. C. to subscribe for preferred stock and purchase the capital notes of insurance companies and for other purposes, states in Section I thereof that any insurance company of any state of the United States may apply. Section II of the same act provides as used in this act the term insurance company shall include any corporation engaged in the business of insurance or in the writing of annuity contracts, irrespective of the nature thereof, and operating under the supervision of a State Superintendent or Department of Insurance in any of the states of the United States. If your organization is duly authorized to operate under the supervision of your State Superintendent of Insurance or Department of Insurance, <pb facs="5422061_2_0921.jpg" n="3"/>you may without doubt apply for assistance under the law, provided, of course, that your organization meets the other requirements of the Statute.</p>
   <p>Very truly yours</p>
   <p>J. P. Cooksey, Secretary."</p>
   <p>In connection with this letter, we are asking all the associations to join this noble movement and send their delegates to this Federation, whose office is located at 1425 North La Salle Street, Chicago, Illinois. All correspondence is to be forwarded to the above address.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
