<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-10-16">Oct. 16, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">The Magyar Tribune Is a Truthful Publication</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) by Ignatz Izsak</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0541</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0541.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-10-16">Oct. 16, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">THE MAGYAR TRIBUNE IS A TRUTHFUL PUBLICATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial) by Ignatz Izsak</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is not an everyday occurrence to stand by and listen to a lengthy speech of praise, or hear people express their gratitude to us. We would not be telling you the truth if we said that we didn't like it. The poor, tired editor is like the wandering actor who is more gratified by praise and glory than by the gift of a large sum of money. The fact that his tireless work is appreciated by the people is sufficient [compensation].</p>
   <p>At a banquet given in honor of Oscar Beregi, I became acquainted with a very interesting and learned person, Mrs. Stephen Czimbalmos. During the past few years this lady has had the opportunity to read the principal Hungarian papers of the United States, and during our conversation, among other things she said, <pb facs="5422061_2_0542.jpg" n="2"/>"Of all the Hungarian newspapers, the Magyar Tribune is the only newspaper that prints the truth. Whether it deals with a foreign item or an American, it gives factual news."</p>
   <p>That Mrs. Czimbalmos is not the only one who thinks thus was discovered after we talked to a Mr. Kelemen. In the course of our conversation, we asked him how he liked the banquet and he told us that he was very pleased with it, because Oscar Beregi tells the truth on the stage, as the Magyar Tribune does [in the press].</p>
   <p>We have cited two instances, but there are many other people, who perhaps are better educated and are prominent in the business world, who think this way and who follow our articles very closely. A good friend of ours was there also, Steve Riman; he told us of a very interesting incident which took place in his home. He had a visitor one day who was a radical, and this man asked him if he might read the Magyar Tribune. Riman told him that he thought that it would be rather uninteresting for him because his <pb facs="5422061_2_0543.jpg" n="3"/>ideas were rather radical in comparison with the ideas expressed by the Magyar Tribune. This man then told Riman that he had read articles which probably had been written by more intelligent men, but that there was something about the Magyar Tribune that he liked and that he could not help liking.</p>
   <p>The explanation for this favorable criticism lies in the fact that the editors of this newspaper were born and raised with the common everyday people of Hungary, and the largest part of their younger days was spent in the society of common everyday people. So naturally they learned what the people thought, what they wanted, and how they wanted others to act towards them.</p>
   <p>The editors of this paper write what the people want them to write. When people read this paper, they realize that there is nothing but truth in it, and that it is written just the way the reader would write it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
