<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-04-21">April 21, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Jubilee Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0240</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0240.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune (Hungarian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1933-04-21">April 21, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">JUBILEE CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday the Chicago [Hungarian] Workers Universal Singing Club celebrated at the Wage Harners Home its first anniversary with a brilliant and varied program, followed by a dance. The hall was crowded to the limit with Hungarians who love Hungarian songs and music. We can say that the public enjoyed this very delightful evening.</p>
   <p>The program opened with a short speech by Andor Wiener. Then Edward Rusznak stepped in front of the curtain as master of ceremonies. The first number on the program was the gypsy band of Pista Kardos, which played "The Internationale." This was followed by the Singing Choir, which showed the discipline and excellent training in the art of singing it had attained during the first year of its existence. The laurels for this achievement are due to Joseph B. Mayer, its director.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0241.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Ladislas Kerekes, a pleasant and modest-mannered young artist, sang some songs with a pleasing voice, earning well-deserved applause.</p>
   <p>Miss Pope and Mr. Opera reaped a fair success at the violin and piano. The same must be said of our young friend, Louis Hegedus, who plays masterfully on the violin, and for whom we predict a brilliant future.</p>
   <p>[Miss] Icus [pronounce: Itsush] Kiszely, as always, this time again conquered the audience with her God-given talent, beautiful voice, excellent mastery of singing, and her lovable personality. She was rewarded with thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>Edward Rusznak sang some songs that caught the heart of the audience, enriching anew his already vast series of successes on the stage.</p>
   <p>The solos were accompanied with artful precision by the pianist Aladar Harmathi.</p>
   <p>The program ended with the appearance on the stage of the Singing Choir, which <pb facs="5422061_2_0242.jpg" n="3"/>earned new applause.</p>
   <p>The program was followed by a gay dance....</p>
   <p>The jubilee festival was a great success both artistically and financially, and this success was naturally due to the good work of the Arranging Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
