<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1935-05-24">May 24, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Gates of America Are Still Open</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1548</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1548.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1935-05-24">May 24, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE GATES OF AMERICA ARE STILL OPEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The general public is under the delusion that the gates of America are forever closed to immigration. The majority of the people in this country believe that the flood of European immigration has ceased entirely and that they can never come to try their luck here with the hope for a better future. This belief is held not only in America, but in Europe. This belief is decidedly contrary to fact. The gates of America are still open to those who are found desirable. During the past two years immigration has increased.</p>
   <p>It has been often pointed out by the respective authorities that according to the quota law, anyone may obtain an entry permit who can prove to the American Consuls abroad that they will not become public <pb facs="5422061_2_1549.jpg" n="2"/>charges or objectionable in any other way. The American consuls have been instructed to use more tolerance toward the prospective immigrants and to take into consideration the individual circumstances and human traits favorable to admission.</p>
   <p>According to the latest statistical reports at the close of the year June 30, 1935, 869 Hungarian citizens were permitted to enter and only 142 asked and gained entries. The year preceding this, 152 Hungarian citizens were granted entry.</p>
   <p>Persons of good faith, who come to visit, are welcomed, and no obstacles are put in the way of their landing. It is very easy to get a visitor's visa.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1550.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Anyone wishing further information on this matter may consult the large steamship agencies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
