<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-03-04">Mar. 4, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Question of Kingdoms</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Berak Pal</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1852</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1852.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-03-04">Mar. 4, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE QUESTION OF KINGDOMS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Berak Pal</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hungarians of America will continue to hammer at this question until finally every one will clearly understand the situation. Accusations have been hurled at Von Horthy to incite him to argue over the matter. I personally do not know Von Horthy, except by his pictures in the newspapers. Looking at his picture with that scornful grin, one could sign his death warrant without flinching.</p>
   <p>In Von Horthy's writings his soul is revealed, and if we examine his soul, we must admit that he is right, though slow to act. So let us wait awhile before making any drastic move.</p>
   <p>I ask the editor of the Magyar Tribune why he would like to have Von Horthy and men like him lined up in the front rank on the battlefield. Perhaps not <pb facs="5422061_2_1853.jpg" n="2"/>because of the protest meetings organized against the monarchy, where the Hungarians wave their flag again. Or perhaps he would have them arrange a demonstration against the restoration of the monarchy and deliver speeches. Or maybe they are leading the Hungarians forth on a Crusade against the new president. Von Horthy is justified in saying that those compatriots of ours who have with difficulty struggled across the stream, are most probably earning their livelihood in Hungary and should not gamble with their security and give up their means of subsistence until the time for action does arrive.</p>
   <p>I do not want any one to think that I am stating that we should forget our native land, which is rent to pieces, and let the good Lord take care of it, satisfied with whatever the good Lord may decree.</p>
   <p>These articles express diverse views, and everybody should express his opinion openly here where we have freedom of speech. We should not begin to help our native land in such a way as to harm ourselves as well as Hungary. We must first digest the best and the most advanced ideas and then begin our work.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1854.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Let us first seek and find the causes why Hungary is laboring in the struggle to restore the monarchy. We see that the newspapers here also publish powerful propaganda in the Hungarian struggle for the restoration of the old adorable apostolic system.</p>
   <p>Hungary has been ruled from time immemorial by the aristocracy and the hierarchy, whose leader was the king. As a result of the disruption of the country after the World War the people were deprived of their means of making a livelihood, and this caused the ruin of the aristocrats. The hierarchy is aware that if in the mutilated country's territory a democratic form of government should spring into existence, then the power which they have heretofore enjoyed would vanish.</p>
   <p>The hierarchy called upon the aristocratic rulers, who were able to command the confidence of the people, to strive to restore the monarchy as soon as possible. This would also have restored their ancient environment of luxury for the aristocrats. The Hungarians of America have for many years helped our <pb facs="5422061_2_1855.jpg" n="4"/>native land with the dollars that we have saved, and if we continue this help and in addition send a supply of vigorous and powerful workers there, then the material disturbances will cease. The people, tormented to death after the war, do not much care whether they have a democratic form of government or the monarchy restored. All they want is that peace and prosperity shall reign, so that they may have the means of gaining a livelihood, for starvation, misery, and poverty have no time for patriotism, [which will be revived] when the people are well fed and materially satisfied. As the Hungarian says, "the rest we will take care of later".</p>
   <p>In reading newspapers and letters from Hungary we find that they assert that King Charles is still the ruler over the country, and that he did not abdicate his throne, but merely retired until law and order should be restored.</p>
   <p>In one of his letters Count Apponyi states that in the course of his travels through Switzerland he felt it his personal duty to locate and do homage to the nation's anointed king. All these letters are written to the Hungarians <pb facs="5422061_2_1856.jpg" n="5"/>in America for the purpose of misleading us.</p>
   <p>If the king could be quickly and successfully restored to his throne, then the ruined upper class, the so-called aristocrats by birth, would recover their positions in the governmental offices, under the shadow of the king's throne. However, unless the king is restored, these aristocrats and the upper class in general will be forced to earn their livelihood by doing honest work, a thing which they utterly despise. The hierarchy will lose its tremendous entailed estates and its other possessions. Their destiny would be similar to that of France after the collapse of the royal government. The bloodthirsty struggle which is now taking place in Hungary is due to the attempt to restore the king to the throne. They should follow the example of Germany, which also suffered the disruption of its territory after the World War. The entire world gazes with admiration at Germany, which is slowly regaining its self-respect because its leaders have strictly confined themselves to the development of commerce and industry.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1857.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Should our homeland's national government hold a parliamentary meeting and decide, by vote of the people's chosen representatives, that the first step in settling the affairs of Hungary is to restore the king to the throne, then the protests that we Hungarians in America make would be in vain. The result would be identical with that experienced when we protested in Washington against the continuance of the World War, just before the armistice was declared, in order to save our unfortunate country. Our people and our country were treated like Jesus, who although innocent was nailed upon the cross.</p>
   <p>I wish to bring the attention of the Hungarians in Chicago to the terrible situation as outlined in my article, and I want every thinking Hungarian in Chicago to express his opinion, so that we may know what to do.</p>
   <p>According to my notion the Hungarians in America should not listen to their high-toned compatriots but [instead] should save up their money so that they <pb facs="5422061_2_1858.jpg" n="7"/>will have the necessary means with which to help when the time comes to do so.</p>
   <p>In the meantime I advise those Hungarians who are returning to Hungary and those who are corresponding with that country to urge our kinsmen not to choose representatives to the parliament who are of the aristocratic class.</p>
   <p>We want them to choose those upright compatriots who wholeheartedly seek the welfare of the people and do not wear their hearts on their chins. Then perhaps those poor tortured people will not have to sweat their millions to maintain the king's gardens, the tremendous list of unnecessary offices for the aristocrats, and the king's bodyguard. Instead, they will be able to restore their mutilated country and to develop themselves agriculturally, industrially, and commercially. In recognition of this the entire world will accord to our country the respect which is due to it and will give substantial aid to it instead of leaving it as now, to struggle alone.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
