<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1929-03-31">Mar. 31, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">To Our Brethren, the Hungarian Roman and Greek Catholics in Chicago and Vicinity.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0804</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0804.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1929-03-31">Mar. 31, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">TO OUR BRETHREN, THE HUNGARIAN ROMAN AND GREEK CATHOLICS IN CHICAGO AND VICINITY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.2...Our organization, the First South Chicago St.Stephen's Hungarian Roman Catholic Sick Benefit Society in its drive for membership, offers the following inducements: Between the ages of 16 and 45, the applicants may become members without paying the usual initiation fee; those over 45, are required to pay half the fee only. Doctor's certificate of physical examination is necessary.</p>
   <p>Our society's aim is not money hoarding, but to benefit our members, therefore, for a membership fee of fifty cents a month,members receive seven dollars a week sick benefit.</p>
   <p>The full seven dollars weekly benefit is paid for three months,and half <pb facs="5422061_2_0805.jpg" n="2"/>the amount for another three months. For funeral expenses, the society allows $100 from its treasury, and one dollar from each member. To members getting married, girl or boy, we give $10. To maternity cases, two weeks sick benefit, seven dollars, is paid.</p>
   <p>We ask our Hungarian Catholic brethren to take advantage of this favorable opportunity to join our society. Our organization is the best of its kind, has the most members, and has the largest capital of any like society in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Inquire further from Istoan Polyan, South Chicago, or Frank Czetenyi, Burnside, Secretaries.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
