<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1927-03-20">Mar. 20, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Remember Our Ancestors (Address of the Rev. J.M. Hanko, Mar. 15 at the Chicago Magyar Club).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1311</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1311.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1927-03-20">Mar. 20, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">REMEMBER OUR ANCESTORS (ADDRESS OF THE REV. J.M. HANKO, MAR. 15 AT THE CHICAGO MAGYAR CLUB).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.4....As on the stage, where we see the actors portray roles of bygone heroes, let us raise the curtain of our forgetfulness, and remember the events of March 15, 1848. Let us remember the history of our thousand year old country.</p>
   <p>Arpaid, the father of our country, said "I gave you a beautiful country and protected her from enemies, keep this beautiful country and defend her with your lives." "It is to the advantage of the Magyar people to become Christians, therefore, I decree that all pagans become Christians," said Stephen, our first Christian king. "Our country has become a cemetery," said King Bela IV," but with God's help, I will rebuild it." King Louis, the Great, "We are bounded by three seas, there is peace and prosperity." John Hunyadi, "The Turks want to enslave us, beware do not let yourselves lose faith. Follow me, your leader, I will lead you to victory." "The power of kings lie in the happiness of the <pb facs="5422061_2_1312.jpg" n="2"/>people "said King Charles II"not the Turk, but dispute among ourselves, was our downfall at the battle of Mohacs." According to our records, "Our country is split three ways, An Austrian is on our throne, Turks overrun our plains; only in Transylvania is there Magyar spirit, but there too the Austrians and Turks are working. Beware that the Austrian assistance doesn't become a boomerang."</p>
   <p>The selfishness of Charles III, Maria Therese's insincerity, the tyrannical rule of Joseph II, have not killed our love of country," said Berzsenyi.</p>
   <p>"The United States of America has gained recognition, France has won liberty, everywhere around us the sun is shining on the nations, shall the Magyars be the only ones to remain in bondage? "asks Stephen Szechenyi! "Rise, ye Magyars," says Petofi (greatest poet) on Mar. 15, 1848. The chronicler goes on to say: "The youths, whose leader was Petofi, freed the Press, outlined in fourteen points the demands of the Magyars and had them accepted by parliament. The new laws went into effect April 11. Victory was ours without bloodshed. But as night follows day, the Austrians resented Hungary's freedom, and hired the Croations, Slavs, Serbs and Roumanians to war on the Magyars in the hopes that fear will drive them for protection to the Austrians. Kossuth, the real father of our country, said, "We would rather die than give up our <pb facs="5422061_2_1313.jpg" n="3"/>independence." Our army of volunteers was victorious over all when the cornered Austrians received reinforcments from Russia. This put an end to the uprising Most of our leaders were killed in action, others were captured and executed. Kossuth escaped to England and later went to the United States." The Austrians later made a pact with Hungary and the two countries were on more or less friendly terms from 1867 until 1914 when the world war broke out. We were automatically swept into this war and lost everything. We are free now, but beggars, because two thirds of Hungary's territory, more than half of the population fell under foreign rule. We are completely desolated.</p>
   <p>The last act is over, the curtain goes down, and the history of our country up to today is ended. We, who saw in our imagination, the great heroes of the past, on't despair. Our country is not dead. We hope that we have learned a lesson and that our country will again be powerful some day.</p>
   <p>We who have two countries, have responsibilites too. Even though we are far from the land of our birth, we shouldn't forget her and we should try to help in every way. It is a beautiful gesture to die for one's country, but still more beautiful to live for it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
