<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1937-05-28">May 28, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Mount the Horses, You Hungarians!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0331</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0331.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1937-05-28">May 28, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">MOUNT THE HORSES, YOU HUNGARIANS!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During a conversation in regard to the arrangement of the Chicago Hungarian Day, Mayor Edward Kelly expressed his desire, that the Hungarians, being a nation of good horsemen, should appear mounted on horses during the festival. He is willing to put a certain number of police-horses at the disposition of the arranging committee. The arranging committee asks all those, who know how to ride a horse, - in the first line those who as soldiers served with the hussars, or who were Csiko's (cowboys) in the old country, - to make application in such number, that a detachment of at least fifteen riders could be formed. As there is an opportunity, to show ourselves in one of our better capacities, we must bring out only first class things, therefore,only such ones should apply for participation in this mounted band, who really know how to ride, and under whom the horse will feel, that it has a Hungarian horsemen on its back. We know on another occasion in the past, a group of horsemen were carried by their mounts <pb facs="5422061_2_0332.jpg" n="2"/>just like so many sacks of flours, showing that their horsemanship instructions had been gotten in dreams. Such things ought not to happen again.</p>
   <p>There certainly are among us many, who could perform some kind of attractive show, for example voltige, the use of the whip (karikas-ostor) , zarriat, etc. which all would attribute to great success of the festival. We need also, someone who has been a bugler with the cavalry. Let us apply, therefore, in great number, and try to enlist such Hungarians, as are sure of being able to perform as well as a Hungarian horseman should perform.</p>
   <p>Apply to the president of the arranging committee of the Hungarian Day, Joseph Berceli, either personally or by letter in the Hungarian House in Burnside, or by phone (Stewart 2474.)</p>
   <p>So: Mount the horses, Hungarians!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
