<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-11-08">Nov. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Hungarian Culture on Foreign Soil.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0475</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0475.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-11-08">Nov. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">HUNGARIAN CULTURE ON FOREIGN SOIL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new star has appeared on the horizon of the Chicago Hungarian societies, which is spreading its bright rays upon the Chicago Hungarians, and this new star is the star of culture.</p>
   <p>Without any exaggeration the Chicago Hungarians can be mighty proud of the fact that out of all the Hungarian Colonies in the United States the Hungarian colony in the city of Chicago has more societies than any other city. Every one of these societies is working for a worthy cause. Each one of these societies have different principles and different ideas, out they are all worthy and necessary. But there isn't a single one of these organizations that is engaged in cultural development, this is due to the fact that all the different organizations are either benevolent associations or are engaged in charitable work, and these things are necessary also.</p>
   <p>There has been cultural societies in this city also, but these organizations were either very lax or falsely named as such, because they did very little <pb facs="5422061_2_0476.jpg" n="2"/>or nothing towards cultural growth.</p>
   <p>But just recently when Andon Garvay and his theatrical group were in Chicago we got a glimpse of the star of culture.</p>
   <p>The Thalia Literary and Song Society is the Hungarian society which grasped the idea and took it upon itself to associate the word Thalis with culture. This society is introducing itself to the Hungarians of Chicago as an organization to develop culture.</p>
   <p>The Thalia Literary and Song Society did not honor Andon Garvay for the sake of publicity, but because they wanted the people to know that for the sake of promoting culture they are always to fight those who are working against culture.</p>
   <p>We should not praise them because this is one of the primary duties of this organization. But we must be proud that we Hungarians of Chicago can have such a wonderful organization, which, not only, is a cultural society, but is also a cultural development association.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0477.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This association, or society, is making great plans for the future intending to go into this cultural work on a large scale. It will be a hard job, but for a worthy cause. It is hoped that they will not give up because at times their job will be hard. They must be brave, because "victory belongs to the brave."</p>
   <p>So far as this newspaper is concerned, this society will receive our fullest cooperation and we believe that the Hungarian population will realize the value of the work being done by this organization and will aid it in carrying out its high ideals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
