<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-03-04">March 4, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Operetta, "Koldus Grof," (Beggar Prince) Coming to Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0212</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0212.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-03-04">March 4, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE OPERETTA, "KOLDUS GROF," (BEGGAR PRINCE) COMING TO CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It has been a long time since the Hungarians of Chicago have had the pleasure of being entertained by the beautiful performances of the Hungarian-American Theatrical Producers. The last time that they were in Chicago it was announced that they would exclude Chicago from their tours. Their announcement was made at that time for the reason that they believed the extent of support and cooperation given them by us was insufficient. We did not blame them for the announcement, for it was clear that the producers were justified. Just as a good teacher deals with bad pupils, the producers are dealing with us. They decided to give us another chance.</p>
   <p>As we have learned, the Hungarian-American Theatrical Producers' Company has been reorganized. In reading over the list of members of this company, we find that they are justified in being proud of their cast of fine arts dramatists. The performances will start at 2:30 P.M., promptly, Sunday, March 13, at the Chicago Central Theatre, 64 East Van Buren Street. The setting and the costumes are exquisitely ornamental. With our distinguished prima donna, Steffi Hegyesi, we have for the first time such exceptional performers as Boske Dobo, Sandor Palasthy, Julia Varadi, Marie Kondor, <pb facs="5422061_2_0213.jpg" n="2"/>Louis Hegedus, Aladar Zsadanyi, Karl Darvas, Istvan Toth, etc. The author of the three-act operetta, "Koldus Grof," is Leo Asher. This operetta is one of the best of fine arts productions. It has enjoyed a remarkable success at every performance. We are depending more on the success of the operetta than on the performers, because of the fact that the operetta is in the capable hands of such exceptional artists. The artists are not only excellent performers, but are capable of understanding the real points that the author has desired, and bring these fine points out in their performance. They become adapted to the author's imagination.</p>
   <p>All indications point to a very successful performance of fine arts, and we believe everyone will enjoy it immensely. Now then the main problem for the success of the performance is for us, as Hungarians of Chicago, to do our duty and attend this performance. The more, the better. Let us show them that we are entitled to have them return more often to Chicago. Let us all be there. Admittance prices are $2.20, $1.65, $1.40, $1.10, and 85 cents.</p>
   <p>Reserved seats and tickets can be purchased at Hercoq Bros, 534 West North Avenue, telephone: Diversey 5428; Julius Rudolph, jeweler, 1460 East 57th <pb facs="5422061_2_0214.jpg" n="3"/>Street, Midway 90<gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>7; Pal Berak, 902 West 119th Street, Pullman 1811; Louis Nagy, 223 West Grand Avenue, Superior 346, Eugene Petrovics, 1502 Clybourn Avenue, Diversey 4089; Samuel Ratkay, tailor, 908 West 119th Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
