<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1933-07-02">July 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Fourth of July</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1933-07-02">July 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">FOURTH OF JULY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Exactly one hundred fifty-seven years ago, the North American Republic was born. In the one hundred fifty-seven years, its life has been like man's: It has enjoyed the advantages of peace, but it has often weathered the storms of war. It has had days of prosperity, but it also has had adverse conditions. The young country was sorely tried.</p>
   <p>The last few so-called depression years were a time of suffering, and, although the American people suffered greatly, somehow their fate was better than that of the nations which lost the War.</p>
   <p>The shadows of depression are fading. There is no need for prophets, who for years prophesied that prosperity was around the corner, because we sank deeper into the "bottomless sea of depression." The prophets are silent now. Any same person can see that, at last, we are on the road to more <pb facs="5422061_2_1298.jpg" n="2"/>normal times.</p>
   <p>The spirit of the American people bravely faces adversity, and they are to be praised for patiently waiting without complaining for a better future.</p>
   <p>The belief that better times are in the offing, has helped the American people overcome their troubles in the past.</p>
   <p>They were bolstered by memories of the past, which were sometimes sad, but more often glorious.</p>
   <p>Since Lincoln's Gettysburg address and the Civil War, the growth of America has been boundless and unparalleled in the history of the World.</p>
   <p>This terrible depression also has its victims, but, undoubtedly, this young country will recuperate rapidly.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1299.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We, the adopted children of America, celebrate its one hundred fifty-seventh birthday with faith in the brighter future of our adopted country. We will try to forget that we feel doubly the effects of these adverse times.</p>
   <p>Let us have faith in the future, and that this great country will some day embrace all its people equally, no matter where they first saw the light of day, and regardless from whence they came to find happiness.</p>
   <p>This will be the real "New Deal" that will unite the souls of all of the children of Great America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
