<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-04-10">Apr. 10, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Sick Benefit Societies Must Unite!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0857</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0857.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-04-10">Apr. 10, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">SICK BENEFIT SOCIETIES MUST UNITE!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This is an answer to the question; Shall the Hungarian sick benefit societies unite? The question was asked by the Chicago Hungarian Social and Sick Benefit Society. We have been expecting this question. When the immigration laws were passed, the Hungarian quota was cut to an absolute minimum. We realized what effect this would have on the membership of the Hungarian sick benefit societies. We knew that these immigration laws would hinder the development of the Hungarian societies of America.</p>
   <p>We knew that as immigration slackened, so would the increase in the membership of Hungarian societies. We realized that the Hungarian societies would have to find new methods if they wanted to continue their activities and remain alive.</p>
   <p>Yes, they must find new paths in order to protect the interest of their members and the financial condition of their sick benefit fund. The ways <pb facs="5422061_2_0858.jpg" n="2"/>and means to do this must be found immediately. The immigration laws will affect all our societies throughout the United States.</p>
   <p>In order to save the smaller societies and the Hungarian activities which are a product of these organizations, there seems to be only one way out; the small ones must either combine or unite with the larger ones.</p>
   <p>The unification of these Hungarian organizations would mean perhaps that many individuals will lose their official positions, but the membership of these organizations surely realizes that their life depends on unification. At the same time they must realize that as one organization, the saving in administrative costs is great.</p>
   <p>We know that this is an important question in the life of our societies. Our opinion is that certain societies must combine with others in order to ensure their continued existence.</p>
   <p>We think that each and every sick benefit society should send representatives <pb facs="5422061_2_0859.jpg" n="3"/>to a meeting to be held on the fourth Sunday in May, at which time this question will be thoroughly discussed.</p>
   <p>We believe that this open statement will not be ignored and that all organizations will be represented.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
