<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-04-28">Apr. 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Successful Performance of the Hungarian Theater</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0279</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0279.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune (Hungarian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1933-04-28">Apr. 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">SUCCESSFUL PERFORMANCE OF THE HUNGARIAN THEATER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday the Dr. Herzl Hall was filled to capacity by theatergoing Hungarians, who gathered there to see the performance of a group of ambitious actors from the Hungarian Theater. The performance, which was a success and made the audience laugh to tears, proved that our public supports the theater and will continue to do so as long as it sees good will on the part of the theatrical company, that is, as long as the latter endeavors to satisfy the demands of the audience, giving real value in return for the entrance fee it receives.</p>
   <p>Well aware of what the public expects, Louis Horvath Jr., leader of the theatrical company, is doing his best to overcome all obstacles and tries hard to give the public good performances. This is the reason why at this occasion the group played to such a crowded house.</p>
   <p>The first play, a one-act burlesque, "Master Ciprian Cures Everything," kept <pb facs="5422061_2_0280.jpg" n="2"/>the public laughing through the whole play. Naturally, the credit is due the performers, who, without exception, did their parts to the best of their ability.</p>
   <p>The role of "Master Ciprian" was played by Horvath himself, who acted so well that everybody believed a real fakir from India was on the stage. No wonder the public applauded him so loudly.</p>
   <p>Etus Humay was so good in her role as the mute, yet very quick-tongued and child wishing woman from Budapest, that even a professional actor would have envied her.</p>
   <p>In the role of "Safarny," Ladislas Szilagyi made the public feel the great danger he feared should the fakir be able to give back to his wife the power of speech.</p>
   <p>Another good performance was that of Joseph Diosi (Dokman) in the role of a peasant who lived in constant anxiety for his cow. He interpreted his small <pb facs="5422061_2_0281.jpg" n="3"/>role excellently, proving that in good hands even small roles become big ones.</p>
   <p>Mr. Meszaros and Miss Gabnay were very good in two smaller roles, and we believe that in the future they will be able to play bigger ones just as successfully.</p>
   <p>The other play of the evening was the two-act comedy, "I will die tomorrow, anyhow." In this play Henry Somlai, the much-loved comedian played the role of a man who wanted to commit suicide, showing how a timid man can be transformed into an energetic one. He was rewarded with thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>Henry Szigeti reaped a great success in his role as clerk of the Suicide Protective Bureau. He held the public spellbound with his exceedingly perfect diction and the naturalness of his acting. Berta Wiener played very well the role of a manhunting energetic girl. Other successful players were Joseph Dokman and Tibor Tomory.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0282.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A very pleasing feature of the program was the magnificent dance by Rozsika Kardos, who danced at the accompaniment of the girl choir. Another successful number was a song in English by the girl choir of Harminckettes Baka [Private of the Thirty-second Budapest Infantry Regiment].</p>
   <p>Just before the last act, there appeared on the stage Joseph Dokman and Emery Berger, accompanied by their wives. They were the donors of the expensive violin which Martin Benedek presented to Joseph Horvath, Jr., director of the Theatrical Ensemble. Horvath was so touched by this courteous recognition of his talent, that he promptly played two beautiful Hungarian songs on the violin that had just been given to him.</p>
   <p>Many thanks are due those who co-operated financially in the success of the performance, first of all Mrs. Joseph Dokman, who not only assisted with her work but also advanced the necessary money to cover the preliminary expenses.</p>
   <p>Others who did much to make this success possible were....[Translator's Note: <pb facs="5422061_2_0283.jpg" n="5"/>Here follow twelve names in the article.]</p>
   <p>The performance was followed by a dance which lasted well into the morning hours. It was still a big crowd that left the Herzl Hall at this late hour with a lasting good impression.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
