<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1936-03-19">Mar. 19, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">The Hungarians of Chicago Celebrated the Ides of March with Deeds</title><title level="a" type="sub">by John Soltesz Secretary of the Federation of Churches and Associations of Chicago South Side</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1236</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1236.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interest</title>,
<date when="1936-03-19">Mar. 19, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">THE HUNGARIANS OF CHICAGO CELEBRATED THE IDES OF MARCH WITH DEEDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by John Soltesz Secretary of the Federation of Churches and Associations of Chicago South Side</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The spirit of the first ides of March, which wrote its souvenir of Hungarian creative genius with flaming letters in history by bringing about the free press, the national army and constitutional parliament, repeats itself again and again in the life of Hungarians of the South Side.</p>
   <p>Here was born the idea of the National Hungarian Day in connection with the World's Fair, and since this date, on March 17, the idea of collecting signatures on behalf of the peaceable demand for revision of her boundaries started. Before an audience of approximately 1,500, Hungarians are sending through this paper their resolution on the March celebration to Hungarians of America.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1237.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Federation of Churches and Associations of Chicago's South Side arranged the imposing meeting in the Liberty Hall last Sunday. Those present voted by a big majority in favor of the following resolution:</p>
   <p>The Hungarian public of Chicago and vicinity celebrating March 15, commissioned the Federation of Churches and Associations of Chicago's South Side, that this federation shall ask every Hungarian to act as co-sponsor of a nationwide movement for the repayment of the war debt Hungary still owes America.</p>
   <p>The celebrating Hungarians of Chicago and vicinity deeply understand the position forced on our native country by the Treaty of Trianon which made it impossible for her to make full restitution of war debts to America because she lost so much territory and natural resources. We also feel we could show our gratitude towards our old country if we would take on our shoulders her obligations towards America, which amounts to about $200,000, we, the Hungarians of America, who found a new home here in the United States. Regardless of its other features, this plan is easily feasible. We are positive in our surmise <pb facs="5422061_2_1238.jpg" n="3"/>that it would greatly help to gain the acknowledgement and understanding of the rightful demand for a revision if Hungary would pay its debt to America as soon as possible. If this proclamation of ours is favorably received by the ranks of the Hungarians of America, the celebrating Hungarians ask the Federation of Churches and Associations of Chicago's South Side to get in touch with the leaders of the nationwide great four Hungarian associations, requesting them to be the collectors and responsible leaders of this great common cause of the Hungarians, and to form a national committee for this purpose.</p>
   <p>This resolution was read by the Rev. Stephen E. Balogh. It was put to a vote and almost unanimously approved by 1,500 persons present.</p>
   <p>As soon as the resolution had been announced the originator of the resolution, Emery Fegyverneki, announced that to start the collection he would contribute from his own pocket the sum of $25. Shortly afterwards, John Soltesz, secretary, and Helen Hada, of the Ladies Revision League, who were named by <pb facs="5422061_2_1239.jpg" n="4"/>the Federation to take up the collection, reported donations of many of those present. As long as the National Committee is not yet functioning, the money thus collected will remain in the custody of the South Side Federation.</p>
   <p>As we are publishing this resolution in the columns of the Interest, we are asking other Hungarian newspapers, Hungarian associations and all the Hungarians to consider our proposal although it is not yet worked out in all details; to criticize and suggest what they think best to further the plan so that it will become a reality in the very near future. The address of our Federation is 817 East 92nd Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>The occasion on which this resolution was adopted was one of the most memorable ides of March in our American life.</p>
   <p>After the usual singing of the Hungarian and American anthems, the Associations exchanged greetings. Then Mayor Edward J. Kelly spoke in a <pb facs="5422061_2_1240.jpg" n="5"/>very appealing manner. Rev. Ernest Horvath followed with an address regarding the American public. He was very eloquent in his speech, telling them about the importance of the Hungarians. Preceding the speech of Rev. Horvath, the Royal Hungarian Consul, Ladislaus Medgyessy, greeted the audience in the name of our native country, and urged the hearty co-operation of all Hungarians in our adopted country. The program was diversified so as not to make it too monotonous. Of other speakers we mention: James J. Sullivan, committeeman; Aldermen Ryan from the 10th ward; Duffy, 19th ward; Lindel, 9th ward; and Mulcahy, 8th ward. Festival speeches were delivered by Rev. Stephen E. Balogh of the Reformed Church, and Rev. Theodor Fedas of the Greek Catholic Hungarian Church.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
