<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-01-04">Jan. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Why the Hungarian Worker Is Well Liked by America.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1200</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1200.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1918-01-04">Jan. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WHY THE HUNGARIAN WORKER IS WELL LIKED BY AMERICA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There has never been a better opportunity to prove that the American people recognize the Hungarian workers. This is probably due to the conditions which exist between this country and Hungary. A question has been asked in the United States, what shall we do with the Hungarians? Shall they be dealt with the same as the Germans, or shall they be deported, as they are from most countries, who are citizens of a foreign country? This powerfully organized country has recognized the love, loyalty and liberal mindedness of the Hungarians who have become voluntary citizens of this country.</p>
   <p>The United States government has recognized these facts. President Wilson, instead of recognizing the Hungarians as hostile foreigners, as usual, in time of war, has put his arms around them and assured them that within the United States they may walk as free men. They shall have the same opportunities for employment that they have had. They shall have the same rights <pb facs="5422061_2_1201.jpg" n="2"/>within the law that they have had.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian people have never denied their love for Hungary. This country never asked them to deny their love for the country of their birth. All the United States government wanted of them was that they be law abiding and faithful workers towards the fulfilment of tasks of this country. The Hungarian Americans have lived up to these expectations. These facts, of course, have put the Hungarian workers in favorable light in industry.</p>
   <p>Although the fact remains that the Hungarian worker did not establish himself during the war but away before the war they were recognized as favorable people to build the nation both morally and physically.</p>
   <p>The question will be asked, how did he establish himself? The answer is simple, the Hungarian is a good worker, and a good man as a citizen.</p>
   <p>It is natural that the Hungarian worker commands a lot of respect in industrial <pb facs="5422061_2_1202.jpg" n="3"/>centers due to the fact that he can do hard physical work as well as good mental work. The Hungarian worker has a few very definite characteristics, he is exacting, sober minded, faithful and loyal in his work.</p>
   <p>The worker is not only liked by the employer, but is also liked by the city government and the community in which he lives. In order to analyze a man's character the American asks, does he belong to a church? Is he a God fearing man, and is he religions? And the Hungarian has everything in his favor with regards to the religious questions.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian mechanics are recognized as some of the best, and the American employer never hesitates to hire a Hungarian professional man.</p>
   <p>Industry likes the Hungarians, but does the Hungarian make a good soldier and does he like industry? The answer to this is unquestionably, yes.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1203.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is only natural that Hungarians are entirely welcome to become citizens of the United States. They have been found to be good citizens both in this country and in their own.</p>
   <p>Therefore, taking everything into consideration, the Hungarian man becomes a contributing factor in the building of this country, and industry appreciates them and recognizes them for all they are worth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
