<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-06-22">June 22, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Hungarian Societies and the Chicago World's Fair</title><title level="a" type="sub">Less Personal Antagonism and More Democracy Needed (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0427</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0427.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-06-22">June 22, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE HUNGARIAN SOCIETIES AND THE CHICAGO WORLD'S FAIR</title><title level="a" type="sub">Less Personal Antagonism and More Democracy Needed (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago Hungarians want to take part in the World's Fair and to share in its success. To do so is not only their right, but also their duty.</p>
   <p>The question still is: How--in what way--can the fifty thousand Hungarians living in Chicago be enlisted in this movement? The answer is simple: Thorough organization.</p>
   <p>How can this Hungarian population be approached, organized, and enlisted in the preliminary work of the World's Fair? By enlisting our organizations--churches, societies, and clubs. These organizations are composed of the self-conscious, working, patriotic class of our Magyars.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0428.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is not enough that meetings, speeches, concerts, banquets, and other simple activities be arranged by a few individuals or one organization. To enlist the aid and co-operation of all the Hungarians, we must persuade the leaders of all churches, societies, and other organizations.</p>
   <p>If we neglect to follow this procedure, success will be doubtful and the fruits of our efforts bitter, because the method of organization would be at fault.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian committee of the World's Fair has been temporarily chosen. Action had to be started and it has in a way.</p>
   <p>At first some individuals came together who took it upon themselves to do the pioneering work. We must understand that the World's Fair is still in a preliminary stage, as it won't start until 1933.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0429.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The greater the competition now the better, and the more the enlisted aid to find ways and means, the surer we will be of ultimate success.</p>
   <p>At the last meeting of the committee, much enthusiasm was manifested. This is a good sign, even though some individuals used a tone that others disliked.....</p>
   <p>There isn't one person in Chicago, or in the world for that matter, who has the confidence of everyone. Therefore, it would be futile to voice our doubts as to the ability of any member of the Hungarian committee to do the task entrusted to him before giving him a chance to prove his worth.</p>
   <p>Let us not forget that we can have only one chairman and one treasurer. These posts are not alone honorary, but tiresome.</p>
   <p>Are our organizations willing to stand by the present committee, brushing <pb facs="5422061_2_0430.jpg" n="4"/>aside their individual objections against some members and following the old American democratic system of government by the people? Do they want to have a committee named under this system?</p>
   <p>The leaders of the organizations should come to a unanimous agreement as to who should represent the Hungarians of Chicago in the Fair.</p>
   <p>This is not a personal question or the prerogative of one organization or individual, but the prerogative of our Hungarian organizations as a whole.</p>
   <p>The work of the World's Fair has been started so early that there should be ample time for all to take part in the planning and to get ready for participation.</p>
   <p>Success is assured only if we all work together.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
