<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Geza Kende, <title>Magyars in America</title>, (Cleveland: Szabadsag, 1927), Vol. II Chap. 1.
<title level="a">Roving through Magyar-America in 1872</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1539</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1539.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Geza Kende, <title>Magyars in America</title>, (Cleveland: Szabadsag, 1927), Vol. II Chap. 1.
<title level="a">ROVING THROUGH MAGYAR-AMERICA IN 1872</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are grateful to Paul Lipthay, who in 1872, made a tour of the United States, in a search for Hungarians, a task which was not so easily done as it is now.</p>
   <p>The traveler today, in a strange city can find a Hungarian name without any difficulty in the telephone directory.</p>
   <p>In the early seventies when only a few Hungarians lived in America, nobody had a record of them and there was no Hungarian newspaper, which would have helped in the search.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1540.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From Lipthay's news reports, which have been written in a style of short stories, published in Budapest magazines, and newspapers, which voyage descriptions were very popular with its feminine readers, just as much as the novels of Marlitt of Gustaw Lauka, we can learn also about Hungarians living in different cities of the United States concerning their struggles, sorrows, and happiness. Concerning Chicago, Lipthay writes: "Chicago, Illinois." I met very few compatriots in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The first Magyar found here, after seeing his sign board, was our compatriot, Utassy, who, contrary to democratic America writes his name, "D'Utassy."</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1541.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Formerly, he had his business in New York, but after his warehouse in Chicago was destroyed by fire, he came here to settle his business. He speaks ten languages.</p>
   <p>At his home I met Francis Laskay, who came to the United States in 1870, to seek a new fatherland. Although he has been here only one and one-half years, he is the agent of six different insurance companies.</p>
   <p>When paying my respects to the Chicago postmaster to get acquainted with interior organizations of the Chicago Post Office, I was very much surprised to find two Magyars among the officials: Alexander Yekelfalushy and Francis Langenfeld. They came to America after the Hungarian War of Independence and served in the American Civil War, too. Both had established homes and were heads of families.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1542.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Yekelfalushy is a real master in the preparation of gulash, or papricash.</p>
   <p>Langenfeld, however frequently writes articles in the local newspapers.</p>
   <p>Among the Magyars living in this city, we should mention Joseph Molnar, who is business manager of one of the branch stores of Utassy; N. Wehle, owner of a porcelain store; and Samuel Magyar, tin and hardware merchant.</p>
   <p>I should not forget to mention the Hungarian Coffee House, which, in spite of its name, is an Inn. I shall conclude my visit with Chicago and Magyar enterprises.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
