<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-02-17">Feb. 17, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Hungarian Radio Hour in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0601</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0601.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-02-17">Feb. 17, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">HUNGARIAN RADIO HOUR IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Were a chronicler to write the history of the Hungarians in Chicago and vicinity, he could not help writing a separate chapter on the far-reaching cultural work which a small group of Hungarians is doing over the radio in order to acquaint the public in this country with Hungarian music and song, thus bringing, all at the same time, fame to the Hungarian name and joy and happiness into every Hungarian home.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian Radio Hour, as if by magic brings back to the Hungarians sweet memories of the beloved old country, the mirage-ridden plains, the sound of bells as the herds take their noontide naps, the call to prayer of the little church's bell, the gay giggling and chatterings of the buxom maidens in the village spinning gathering; it brings back memories of windows full of geraniums, of gypsy music, of the sweet song of the lark, and of everything else interwoven with our souls; it brings back memories of our youth and exalts that indescribable, hidden sentiment which only the Hungarians can feel and which accompanies them to the grave.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0602.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the last few years there were some unsuccessful attempts to establish a permanent Hungarian Hour, but what for lack of artistic qualities and what for other reasons, these attempts never got very far.</p>
   <p>It is now almost a year since, at the initiative of Steven Komarik, and under the artistic leadership of Irma Komarik-Ferenczy, we began to receive over the air, from radio station WIND in Gary, a good Hungarian program, one which, not only in its musical aspect but also in its artistic arrangement, has stood its place victoriously among the best radio hours of other foreign-language groups. The program has been praised by many American lovers of music.</p>
   <p>The Hungarian Radio Hour, broadcast over the radio station in Hammond, is by now a public institution in the Calumet region, and it alone offers more entertainment than quite a number of other artistic or cultural movements.</p>
   <p>The warm attachment of the Hungarians of the South Side and the Calumet region toward the Hungarian Radio Hour, prompted its directors to arrange for a similar <pb facs="5422061_2_0603.jpg" n="3"/>Hungarian Hour here in Chicago. We hope there won't be any Hungarian home where our song and music will not be heard at least once a week.</p>
   <p>This Hour runs into quite some work and expense, but the directors had received so much encouragement and petitions from Hungarians in Chicago and vicinity that they decided to broadcast a program from a station able to cover all of Chicago. The Century of Progress Station, WSBC, 1210 Kilocycles, has been chosen. The program will start at 5:30 every Saturday evening.</p>
   <p>Steve Komarik, secretary of the Danubia Broadcasting Service, who in this capacity has made possible the broadcasting of Hungarian music and songs on the German radio program,will be the announcer.</p>
   <p>From an artistic viewpoint, the success of the Hour would be assured if its management is entrusted into the skillful hands of the celebrated Hungarian singer, Irma Komarik-Ferenczy.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0604.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We take pleasure in announcing this new enterprise and are quite certain that the Hungarians of Chicago will share in our joy.</p>
   <p>The directors of the Hungarian Radio Hour ask the public to send postcards to the station, saying whether it is satisfied with the program. This interest on the part of the public will serve as a foundation for the difficult task that lies ahead-- a task undertaken out of pure love toward Hungarian culture. We think this is the least sacrifice the promoters are entitled to expect from the part of the public. The address is Hungarian Group Station WSBC, 1300 South Michigan Boulevard, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
