<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-01-07">Jan. 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Dutzy Kerekyarto</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-01-07">Jan. 7, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">DUTZY KEREKYARTO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Music lovers of Chicago, had a very pleasant surprise Tuesday Jan. 4. Dutzy Kerekyarto, noted Hungarian violin virtuoso, who was born at Ruttka, Hungary, and acclaimed in New York, presented himself for the first time before a Chicago audience, in Orchestra Hall.</p>
   <p>His program consisted of selected works of the celebrated composers, Corelli, Tartini, Schubert, Sarasate and Pazanim.</p>
   <p>At 8 o'clock the audience had thronged into the hall and occupied their seats. When at 8:15 the hall became dark, all eyes turned to the stage, and with bated breath, those present awaited the appearance of the great artist. In the background of the stage, the door suddenly opened and <pb facs="5422061_2_0134.jpg" n="2"/>there appeared the portly young Hungarian Artist. The audience burst into a storm of applause, lasting four minutes.</p>
   <p>Kerekyarto, our dear artist, placed the violin to his chin and began playing "La Folia," by Corelli. The instant he began to play, the audience was carried away by the strains of the violin. We saw only one violin, but it seemed a whole orchestra was playing. Kerekyarto is a young man, but as an artist surpasses the popular older violin virtuoso's of the present time.</p>
   <p>While Kerekyarto was playing, the mind of the audience was roaming far away in a fairy land, among vari-colored beautiful flowers, where there is no worry, no misery, and where everybody is happy.</p>
   <p>The proverb says that the "criticism of the people decides." Regarding <pb facs="5422061_2_0135.jpg" n="3"/>the art of Kerekyarto, the people decided his greatness, because after every number the audience applauded wildly, and the great Hungarian artist was called three or four times to appear before the curtains. Everybody was applauding; everybody was paying homage to the technique of the great artist.</p>
   <p>His talent manifested itself especially in the "Nightingale"; the audience imagined itself in a fairy forest listening to the sweet songs of birds. Only when they glanced at the artist, did they realize they were in a theatre, and that the pleasant tunes were coming from Kerekyarto's violin.</p>
   <p>At the concert, the Magyars were present in imposing numbers. We saw quite a few prominent Magyars who enjoyed the playing of our eminent artist and shared the triumphal success of Hungarian art. We never expected that Hungarian art would be the great success in America <pb facs="5422061_2_0136.jpg" n="4"/>Kerekyarto made it.</p>
   <p>Toward the end of the program, the Magyars of the audience, as if united by the same thought, all cried at once, "Magyart!" (A Hungarian!"). Kerekyarto, with double ardor and "Magyar heart," played a number by Hubay, which was tremendously applauded, not only by Hungarians, but by the rest of the audience.</p>
   <p>After the concert many of the Magyars congratulated the young artist, who received them with warm friendship.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
