<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1934-02-18">Feb. 18, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Activities of Chicago Magyar Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1251</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1251.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1934-02-18">Feb. 18, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">ACTIVITIES OF CHICAGO MAGYAR CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Magyar Club held its big yearly meeting Sunday afternoon, and Dr. Elmer Horvath, president, opened the session. Dezso Glosz, recording secretary, read the yearly report, which shows that the club has been very active during the depression year. This activity has its reward, because they have not only succeeded in keeping their financial status on the level of past years, but have also increased their income. There were fifteen interesting lectures. Among the lecturers, we find such notables as Dr. William E. Evans, Chicago Tribune's health columnist, and Dr. Geza Takats, Dr. B. J. Hoag, Dr. Wm. McGovern, Dr. Oscar Schnetzer, Dr. Carry Croners, and Dr. Imre Grimm, all university professors.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1252.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Other activities were: memorial gathering for an honorary member, Count Albert Apponyi; celebration in honor of Hungarian Independence Day (March 15, 1848); observation of Oct. 6, 1849, death of thirteen martyrs at Arad; celebration of the eminent writer Franz Herzeg's 70th birthday.</p>
   <p>A notable event was the club's committee delegated to greet Marshal Italo Balbo; also, the visit of Burton Holmes, and the reception in honor of Joseph Szigeti, world famous violinist. The club always sent delegates to the other organizations' affairs.</p>
   <p>After the closing speech of Dr. Horvath, wherein he thanked all officers for their cooperation in the past year, the new officers were elected. The new president is Frank Schmidt, Victor Wasserman is vice-president, John L. Fix, secretary, and Alajos Mueller, treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
