<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-02-11">Feb. 11, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Up on the Lamp Post with Mr. Von Lorthy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1868</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1868.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1921-02-11">Feb. 11, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">UP ON THE LAMP POST WITH MR. VON LORTHY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If you, Mr. Editor, want to enjoy a good hanging, you have to come in front of the studio where I am working and bring the mob with you; you can get a long rope here and find a 25-foot lamp post in front of our studio. What do you say to that? Will it be all right? I have to say the same thing the Tribune said. I was surprised by the sudden change in your friendly opinion regarding the Tribune or its editor in chief, who knows me well since I came to this country. He thinks that I deserve to be hoisted up on a lamp post for the simple reason that I advise my "deserting" fellow-patriots not to hurry things up but wait until developments show them what is best for our native country and for the common welfare of Hungary. Furthermore, the Tribune considers it a crime that I did not read a December issue of the Pesti Hirlap and that I missed the great lords' messages sent over to dupe us, as you expressed it yourself. No, I didn't read that the new Finance Minister is planning to cut out an enormous lump of flesh from the body of the country. Nor did I read that you complain that the new Minister appropriated the contribution that we sent to our relatives and friends.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1869.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I admit that I never read anything about all these terrible things in the Pesti Hirlap. Had I read all these things, would I have asked the Tribune what was to be gained by the people of Hungary or the Hungarian people in this country? Could I have prevented all this, if I had learned all about it way ahead before it happened?</p>
   <p>I wonder at the twisted conclusion of the Tribune in condemning me for something I haven't done. I have never changed my political views or will change them in the future. However, I must declare openly, although I am sorry to do so, that I will not be lured by the Tribune to participate in any political adventure injurious to our native country, which went through so many changes lately. It is better to take it easy. It hardly need be said that we do not trust the political leaders of pre-war times; some of them gave us reason enough for distrust. On the other hand, there are others among the old-time political leaders who, through their knowledge and experience, could be very useful in the task of re-building Hungary. If they have some old-time political sins, let these sins be forgiven.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1870.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Besides, among the political leaders of Hungary there are some who cannot be rated as servants of the old system. Take for example Julius Rubinek, a clear-minded man of great knowledge and a loyal patriot. Therefore, we should not criticize and condemn them all.</p>
   <p>I don't see any reason for attacking Finance Minister Hegedus before he is given a chance to do something good or bad. As a banker, Hegedus has no time to serve the old political system; just because he began his political career with a "little bleeding" of the country, we don't have to club him instantly. If he ordered that twenty cents are to be deducted from every crown of our charity money, there is still some money left for the poor.</p>
   <p>Let's give him time and see how he will progress. Perhaps he will be the first to understand that it is impossible to make anything fast with worn out screws. Probably he will give up the idea of cutting out flesh when he realizes that there are only bones left. Those newspaper articles of the "great lords" don't have to be taken with such an anger either.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1871.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is a punishment by itself when the "great lords" have to humble themselves and call the deserters and traitors their brothers and their kin in order to get their help. By doing so they admit their own helplessness. There is Count Apponyi, the great statesman, who never in his life wanted to harm his country. He can be of great use to our native country with his knowledge. We don't have to hurt his feelings. Therefore, we don't have to send everybody to the lamp post before his time.</p>
   <p>Mr. Benedek, you are a bad boy. I would never have thought before that such a tiny-winy man as you could be so spiteful.</p>
   <p>I advise, let's wait for my hanging until I deserve it; perhaps the opportune time will soon come when we can start with united strength the work of upbuilding and restoration.</p>
   <p>I would like to call the attention of the Tribune to a very simple thing, not to newspaper articles, but to facts. I wonder whether the Tribune ever examines the letters that come from Hungary. If it does it must have noticed that the stamps on the envelopes read in large letters, "Help <pb facs="5422061_2_1872.jpg" n="5"/>Hungary." This shows what has become of the once noble and proud nation. When we read these words, our eyes fill with tears. Although now we can do nothing, the time will come when we will prove to the world that our kin don't have to resort to begging, not even on their postal stamps. The Tribune still wants to send everybody to the lamp post; even those who are able or eager to help their native country.</p>
   <p>I would propose that it would be wiser to postpone all hangings on the lamp posts at least until we put Hungary on her feet, that is, until she occupies the place of which she is worthy.</p>
   <p>So, I have to say again: Let's wait a while, everything will be all right.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
