<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune (Hungarian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1933-05-12">May 12, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">News about the Exposition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0389</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0389.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune (Hungarian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1933-05-12">May 12, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS ABOUT THE EXPOSITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Hungarian Committee of the World's Fair, under the chairmanship of Dr. Arpad Barothy, held a meeting on May 8, at the Chicago Magyar Club. The meeting elected the sixteen persons who will officially represent the Hungarians at the ceremonial opening of the Exposition on May 27.</p>
   <p>The officers of the committee have succeeded in finding the whereabouts of the Hungarian flag sent some years ago to the unveiling of the Kossuth Monument, and took the necessary steps to insure its return to Chicago from Homestead, Pennsylvania, before the opening day of the Exposition.</p>
   <p>The committee has sent out the following call to Hungarian associations and individuals:</p>
   <p>"The Federation of Hungarian Associations of Greater Chicago, in co-operation with the Committee of the Hungarian Group of A Century of Progress World's <pb facs="5422061_2_0390.jpg" n="2"/>Fair, later reorganized on November 1, 1930, held a meeting to name a new committee on May 1, 1933, at the Chicago Magyar Club.</p>
   <p>"Presidents and other officers of the Associations belonging to the Federation were named to this committee, with Ernest Holvay, president of the Federation, as copresident of the Hungarian Committee of the World's Fair. From among the officers of the old Committee, the meeting elected Dr. Arpad Barothy president, Joseph Kaszab vice-president, and Joseph Csanady secretary,</p>
   <p>"This committee will handle all Hungarian World's Fair problems. It will also name the sixteen Hungarian delegates who will represent, true to the geographical traditions in national costumes, the Hungarians in the festive march of thirty-two national groups scheduled to take part in the opening of the Fair.</p>
   <p>"We are cordially inviting all those willing and able to create something to join us in this work--all those who guard with sorrowful self-consciousness <pb facs="5422061_2_0391.jpg" n="3"/>in their hearts the deep grief of the people of one-thousand-year-old Hungary, now cruelly dismembered and lamed--all those who hear the people of that land cry for justice and human rights--all those who, led by their unselfish idealism to co-operate with us, are willing to work, so that, by dignified representation, the Hungarian nation, which is culturally the equal of any of the cultured nations, may make a deep impression on the delegates of other nations gathered here from all parts of the World.</p>
   <p>"We are asking all associations willing to work with us, to apply to Joseph Csanady, Secretary of the Committee, 201 East Ontario Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
