<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-06-27">June 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Severe Restrictions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1639</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1639.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1919-06-27">June 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">SEVERE RESTRICTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The present congressional session will place some very severe restrictions, and enact laws with reference to immigration. This is being done in order to keep undesirables out of this country. They will also enact laws which will give sufficient power to the government to deport those undesirables who have succeeded in coming into this country.</p>
   <p>This resolution was brought before the House by Albert Johnson, who is the chairman of the committee on immigration.</p>
   <p>With reference to the more recent radical disturbances and bombings, this resolution will be passed by the House in record time. The committee on immigration will have this bill up for consideration next Wednesday.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1640.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The fundamental points of this bill are as follows:</p>
   <p>1. To suspend immigration for the next two years.</p>
   <p>2. A thorough investigation of the immigrants who are now living in the United States.</p>
   <p>3. The deportation of those people who neglected getting their first papers in order that they might be free from enlisting for duty in the American Army.</p>
   <p>4. The deportation of all aliens who have records as blackmailers, all those who teach or are practicing the ideas of communism, or are members of an organization practicing or teaching anti- <pb facs="5422061_2_1641.jpg" n="3"/>Americanism.</p>
   <p>5. To allow immigrants only a temporary stay in this country, and grant a permanent stay only after a thorough investigation.</p>
   <p>6. To enact severe restrictions with reference to the registration of all sailors, or boat hands, and a severe penalty on those steamship lines who fail to live up to this restriction.</p>
   <p>These restrictions will enable the United States to get acquainted with all information concerning the immigrant.</p>
   <p>This bill would require everyone to register upon entering the United States, present a photograph and be fingerprinted. The registration and photography would be compulsory each year after entering the United <pb facs="5422061_2_1642.jpg" n="4"/>States.</p>
   <p>The two-year restriction on immigration will be modified so that those people who have relatives in foreign countries can make arrangements to have them brought to this country.</p>
   <p>It is to be remembered that immigrants, who after investigation prove undesirable, must be deported immediately.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
