<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-01-06">Jan. 6, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">[Twentieth Year]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0497</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0497.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1933-01-06">Jan. 6, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">[TWENTIETH YEAR]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today, on the front page of our newspaper and below the title, there appears the caption, "Twentieth year," which means that during the last nineteen years we have served with unselfish perseverance the Hungarians of Chicago and vicinity. Like a faithful soldier, the Magyar Tribune has stood watch through nineteen years over the Hungarian interests, so that nobody and nothing could hurt them. For nineteen years we have been preaching with unyielding consistency liberal and, in some measure, even radical ideas, in which we see the only way to a happier future.</p>
   <p>All this we have done only through our own work, with great sacrifices on our part, especially during the recent years of depression. We fought against all obstacles, because the Magyar Tribune is not solely a business enterprise but also a Hungarian institution, which, in fulfilling its calling, does not shrink back from making any sacrifices in order to promote the interests of the <pb facs="5422061_2_0498.jpg" n="2"/>Hungarians.</p>
   <p>In this struggle of ours, our only support has been the mighty legion of our readers, which is warmly faithful to us, and is together with us in our struggle. Our enthusiastic readers give us the strength to continue our fight. They know and feel that ours is not a battle for individual gain but a battle for human rights and to build up a better future.</p>
   <p>Now at the beginning of the New Year, we ask our readers to keep us in their affection and to strengthen us by renewing their subscriptions, so that we may further serve the interests of the Hungarian-Americans.</p>
   <p>In return we pledge ourselves to be in the future what we were in the past: the determined fighters for the interests of the Hungarians and the torch-bearers of progressive ideas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
