<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1934-07-22">July 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Hungarians in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Text of Radio Discourse by Chicago Hungarian Consul)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1551</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.L"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1551.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I L</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Otthon</title>,
<date when="1934-07-22">July 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">HUNGARIANS IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Text of Radio Discourse by Chicago Hungarian Consul)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the beginning of the last century, there were only a few Hungarians in this country, but toward the end, this number had been increased many times. In time, hundreds of thousands of Hungarians emigrated to this country, seeking a better future.</p>
   <p>The American-Hungarians are deeply interested in the affairs of their Mother country. Outside of private correspondence, the Hungarian newspapers published in the United States always have columns under caption of "What is New in my Home Town." In this way, the ties between the new and old country can be preserved for an indefinite period.</p>
   <p>Among the Hungarian immigrants were industrial workers, but mostly farmers. These farmers could not pursue farming in this country, because the methods used are so different from those used over there, most of them found employment in steel mills and mines. Their purpose was to work here a few years and <pb facs="5422061_2_1552.jpg" n="2"/>return with their savings. Later, their children, who went to American schools, wanted to stay in this country, so their original plans did not materialize.</p>
   <p>There are 75,000 Hungarians in Chicago and vicinity. Most of them live on the South Side of Chicago, close to the shops and factories. About 6,000 families are centered in Burnside, South Chicago, and West Pullman. The rest of them live on the West and Northwest Side. The sections populated by Hungarians can be recognized because they have built their homes around their churches.</p>
   <p>There are two Protestant, one Baptist, one Roman, and one Greek Catholic Church; also there are twenty societies on the South Side. On the North Side there is one Protestant, one Roman Catholic, and one Israelite church.</p>
   <p>The 1929 financial disaster has affected individuals as well as organizations. The income of the churches has dropped considerably and the debts have mounted. The societies were affected similarly.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1553.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Hungarians are a proud people and will seek charity only when there is no other way out. They are hoping for better times.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
