<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-07-03">July 3, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">The Consolidation of [Hungarian Benefit] Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0855</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0855.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-07-03">July 3, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">THE CONSOLIDATION OF [HUNGARIAN BENEFIT] SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The second meeting held by the representatives of the various Hungarian sick benefit societies to settle the question of consolidation cannot exactly be called a success. This is not surprising to those who are acquainted with the histories of our sick benefit societies, but we thought that those societies which ought to be vitally concerned about this idea would show greater interest and would have a larger representation at this meeting. We noticed that there were representatives from only three or four societies, and it seemed that these representatives were there for the sole purpose of securing information about this [consolidation] movement. This indicates that most of the societies are waiting for the others to decide.</p>
   <p>Because of the situation that exists [today] among the sick benefit societies, there is absolutely no reason for waiting. The Hungarian Workers' Sick Benefit Society has submitted its plan whereby this strong Hungarian organization will <pb facs="5422061_2_0856.jpg" n="2"/>take into its fold all societies that want to consolidate with it. Every society adopting this plan may do so without any loss to its members. The way we see the situation, this plan is in accordance with the agreement made at the first meeting of the societies interested in consolidation.</p>
   <p>It was again stressed that the members of the societies should be notified about this plan for consolidation, so that their ideas and questions could be carefully considered and discussed.</p>
   <p>Even though this second meeting seemed so unsuccessful, we believe that consolidation will result because it is an absolute necessity, in view of the economic and social changes that are taking place. We would like to see this consolidation plan carried out in the most progressive and democratic way, so that we could say that the Chicago Hungarians are keeping pace with the trend of the times.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
