<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune (Hungarian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1933-06-23">June 23, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Convention of the Hungarian-American Associations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1364</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1364.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune (Hungarian Tribune)</title>,
<date when="1933-06-23">June 23, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">CONVENTION OF THE HUNGARIAN-AMERICAN ASSOCIATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is interesting to look back at the feverish bustle that has been going on during the past few weeks. The iniciators of the Hungarian associations' convention--and theirs is the merit and also the responsibility--have put a heavy burden on the shoulders of the champions of Hungarian public life. However, there are many who have quietly stepped aside, preferring to have nothing to do with the convention, not to mention those who are insultingly kicking about it, hinting their suspicions, throwing accusations and making fun of the action and its initiators, and who are tireless in their efforts to ridicule the idea, regardless of the fact that this action for a convention of all Hungarian-American associations is not aimed at satisfying anybody's vanity or greediness but has been started by the have-nots, the exploited, the forgotten, who recognize the calling voices of this age and want to do something at this late hour, something which should always be remembered in the history of the Hungarian-Americans.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1365.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This convention will discuss questions that are equally important to the Bridgeport Aid Federation, the Verhovay Aid Association, the Rakoczi Aid Association, the different Catholic or Reformed associations; the Workers Sick Benefit Federation, the International Workers Order, the Independent Hungarian-American Sick Benefit Association, the Protected Home Circle, and every other association whatever its name. No association is excepted as sooner or later every one of them will hear its death knell. If, in our united efforts, we would always keep the interests of all before our eyes, we could find an expedient which would result not only in saving our members but in gaining new ones as well. This way we could successfully accomplish the beneficial work started by our different associations and would not have to drop with bleeding hearts and eyes full of tears our unemployed members, now grayhaired after many years in our associations, just because they cannot pay their dues.</p>
   <p>We have to consider the men, not the money, because, after all, man is the <pb facs="5422061_2_1366.jpg" n="3"/>creator of money. If there is the will, there will be enough money, as there always was, only that up to now we trusted the bacon to the dog and never cared for the interest of all.</p>
   <p>The strength of unity is demonstrated by the 157-year-old Constitution of the United States. We only have to use this time-proved system as pattern, and then we can be sure we will save the present and assure the future of our associations.</p>
   <p>Forward, therefore, with united forces and peaceful understanding, to find such good remedy for the ills of our associations that even our enemies shall become our friends and shoulder to shoulder, hand in hand, united with us, help us build a bastion of defense for the Hungarians.</p>
   <p>Preparations Committee.</p>
   <p>Luis Nagy</p>
   <p>Chairman.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
