<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Geza Kende, <title>Magyars in America</title>, (Cleveland: Szabadsag, 1927), Vol. I.
<title level="a">Lincoln Riflemen</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">The Early Hungarian Settlers</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1536</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1536.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Geza Kende, <title>Magyars in America</title>, (Cleveland: Szabadsag, 1927), Vol. I.
<title level="a">LINCOLN RIFLEMEN</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">The Early Hungarian Settlers</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the 24th Infantry Regiment of Illinois, two more Magyar ex-army officers, refugees of Hungarian War of Independence, of 1848-49, served captain Gustav Kovats, who on June 12, 1862, near Jasper, Tennessee was wounded so gravely that it made him unfit for military service.</p>
   <p>He was promoted to the position of major for his bravery, and returned to Hungary in 1871, where he became a teacher at a Reformed Protestant parochial school, in town of Gyula (Diula). He died in 1874.</p>
   <p>Among the Chicago-Magyars, there was still Francis Langenfeld, who was first lieutenant, Joseph Folop, Joseph Molnar, and Michael Pipady who, as noncommissioned officers, served in the Civil War.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1537.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Julian Kune, the grand old man of Chicago-Magyars, wrote an autobiography rich of colorful events with the title, "Reminiscences of an octogenarian Hungarian Exile," published in book form in 1911. After the Civil War, he entered the Chicago Board of Trade. In 1869, he made a journey to Europe and even visited his native country, Hungary, where many years ago he was exiled. He was still in Europe at the outbreak of the Franco-Prussian War, in 1870. He witnessed this war as a war-correspondent of the Chicago Tribune.</p>
   <p>His war reports attracted general notice for their descriptions of dramatic vividness proving him to be an expert of the warfare.</p>
   <p>Julian Kune again returned to Chicago, where the elderly gentleman was held in great esteem. He always was interested in Hungarian activities and was in close connection with the other Hungarian leaders.</p>
   <p>When he died, his coffin was covered with wreaths of red, white, green, <pb facs="5422061_2_1538.jpg" n="3"/>Hungarian colors, and American colored ribbons. About ten thousand Magyars and Americans, with tearful eyes, stood by his coffin and escorted him to his last march.</p>
   <p>Julian Kune was the last surviving warrior of 1848-49, among the exiles who remained in the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
