<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-01-06">Jan. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Are There More Criminals Among Immigrants Than Among Native Americans?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1111</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1111.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1928-01-06">Jan. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">ARE THERE MORE CRIMINALS AMONG IMMIGRANTS THAN AMONG NATIVE AMERICANS?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Recently a professor of the University of Minnesota made a study of criminality in the United States and at the same time made a comparison between the native Americans and the immigrants. Up to the present time the general belief was that the percentage of criminals among immigrants is much greater than among the natives. The basis for this belief was upset, because during the course of research it was found that the immigrants do not play a leading part in criminal activities.</p>
   <p>Three methods are used to determine the ratio of criminals. According to Judge Kavanagh of Chicago, "Aside from the Negro criminals, two-thirds of all crimes are committed by immigrants or their direct descendants." This statement is essentially correct, but the relative proportion is exaggerated. It would be more precise to say that fifty-five per cent <pb facs="5422061_2_1112.jpg" n="2"/>is the ratio of which thirty per cent are immigrants and twenty-five per cent immigrants' children.....</p>
   <p>The second method figures the ratio by the number of convictions and imprisonments. Apparently four hundred eighty-nine out of one hundred thousand immigrants go to jails or to reformatories annually, while at the same time only two hundred thirty-nine natives are convicted.....This estimate does not take into consideration that the immigrant criminal group differs from the native in sex, age, and composition. This is important because the majority of offenders are young adults and there are many of this element among the immigrants living in cities.</p>
   <p>The third method is the correct one. It compares and differentiates between white natives and immigrants according to age, sex, and geographical division. According to this method, the foreigners are not on top of the criminal wave.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1113.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Many argue that the immigrants lead in major crimes. If we use the comparative system in calculating the ratio, we find that the natives lead in both major and minor criminal activity.....</p>
   <p>If we summarize all forms of criminality according to each national group of immigrants, we find that the Finns come first, followed by Mexicans, Irish, Austrians, Greeks, Norwegians, Swedes, Poles, Russians, and lastly the Hungarians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
