<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-04-24">Apr. 24, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">Forgotten Information</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_1268</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-19">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1268.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1925-04-24">Apr. 24, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">FORGOTTEN INFORMATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Those of our readers who are seeking information concerning the play, "The Music Lies," Which was given by the Chicago Independent Song Society last Sunday, can save themselves a lot of work, because we have not written anything about it.</p>
   <p>We are not giving any information about this particular performance. The reason for our attitude is that we did not receive the usual courtesy accorded the press on such occasions --we did not receive the two usual complimentary admission tickets. Those who neglect us, we neglect.</p>
   <p>We do not know whether it was because they did not know any better, or whether it was plain negligence, or whether it was because they did not want us there. We do not care.</p>
   <p>Those who forget about the rights of the press, must be dealt with accordingly.</p>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_1269.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This does not only apply to the Chicago Hungarian Independent Song Society, but it applies to all organizations sponsoring banquets, dances, etc. We ask each and every organization to understand this.</p>
   <p>Some time ago we neglected to write an article about the Easter Celebration of the Rakoczi Society. We did this for the simple reason that they forgot to inform us, and they did not invite us to this affair. Yet we like the officers and members of this organization; we are interested in their activities and we wholeheartedly support them.</p>
   <p>But we can stand only so much.</p>
   <p>Our dealings with the Chicago Hungarian Independent Song Society have always been of great interest. During their jubillee celebration, we printed a detailed article concerning this particular activity. We do not hold anything against the present officers, and we are not picking <pb facs="5422061_2_1270.jpg" n="3"/>out any individuals. We are guided by certain principles, and we aim to stick to these principles.</p>
   <p>We will admit that one of our reporters was present at the play--he was there at his own expense, and he submitted to us a very interesting report of the affair. We put this report aside regretfully. Orders are orders, as they say in the army--so we of the press also declare.</p>
   <p>Many of our subscribers have asked us for information about the above-mentioned affair, but we are going to stick to our decision.</p>
   <p>Those who forget about us -- we in turn shall forget about them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
