<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-01-08">Jan. 8, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">A Beautiful Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5422061_2_0844</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-04">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5422061_2_0844.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>HUNGARIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Magyar Tribune</title>,
<date when="1926-01-08">Jan. 8, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">A BEAUTIFUL CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Sunday, the Chicago Hungarian Independent and Charitable Ladies' Society celebrated their tenth anniversary in the Rose Room of the Morrison Hotel. There were more than two hundred people present. There was no parade, no brass band, and no delegates from other Hungarian societies. It is just possible that the ladies did not invite any of the other Hungarian societies. They probably wanted to do their celebrating in just the same way that they have carried on charitable work--that is, all by themselves.</p>
   <p>When all had taken their seats at the banquet tables, Mrs. Glantz, the president of the organization, opened the celebration with a fine speech. Mrs. Chanyi was then appointed toastmistress, and she proved to be a very capable one. She introduced the charter members of the organization and praised them for the wonderful work that they had done. She then presented Mrs. Daniel Wolf, founder of the organization, who refused to take any <pb facs="5422061_2_0845.jpg" n="2"/>credit for the work of the organization. She said that all the credit belongs to the active members.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Chanyi then praised Mrs. Glantz for her great work, pointing out that when Mrs. Glantz became president three years ago, there was a membership of only about eighty, whereas today the membership is over two hundred. In addition to the fact that Mrs. Glantz did so much toward building up the organization, she continually worked for the welfare of her fellowman, almost going to the extreme of begging from house to house in order that some suffering individual might be aided.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Weigl, who is the newly elected president, then spoke in praise of the work being done by the organization. She thanked the members for electing her president of such a great organization.</p>
   <p>The program then continued with the appearance of Charles Kovacs, who <pb facs="5422061_2_0846.jpg" n="3"/>is one of the foremost Hungarian composers in America. Mr. Kovacs is also a well-known music teacher in Chicago. He played the piano, while Mrs. Kovacs sang. The songs which were presented by this couple were all Mr. Kovac's own compositions.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ignatz Izsak and Mr. Paul Berak were then asked to speak. They told of their high regard for the work being done by this great organization. They said that they were proud of the fact that the Chicago Hungarians had an organization such as this.</p>
   <p>It is really gratifying to learn that the Society extends a helping hand to everyone, regardless of creed. This welfare work is done almost secretly, whenever it is found that aid is needed. The Society has spent five thousand dollars for welfare work during the past ten years. Last year alone, eleven hundred dollars was expended for welfare work. The Society's motto is: "To aid all those in need, without expectation <pb facs="5422061_2_0847.jpg" n="4"/>of thanks or gratitude from the public."</p>
   <p>Chicago Hungarian-Americans! We must take our hats off to these big-hearted ladies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
