<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Amerikanski Slovenec</title>, Vol. XXXIV, No. 88, <date when="1925-06-05">June 5, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">We Must Support Our Newspaper</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>chicagoforeignl0chic_0143</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-12-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0143.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>SLOVENE</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>
Amerikanski Slovenec</title>, Vol. XXXIV, No. 88, <date when="1925-06-05">June 5, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">
WE MUST SUPPORT OUR NEWSPAPER</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>We notice that our friends and supporters accepted with great satisfaction
the enlarged size of our newspaper. We are receiving daily thousands of
letters from all parts of this country, congratulating us on our efforts
to improve the reading, matter and enlarge the size of our daily. This makes
us happy and gives us energy to continue such policy.</p>
      <p>But in order to fulfill the already made promises to give our readers a
newspaper of high standard and quality, as well as to meet the growing
expenses incurred with newspaper expansion, we must have additional capital.
We are in great need of a new and modern printing machinery to speed up
work on a higher rate circulation. New appearance of the newspaper enlarged
size, increase in reading matter, all these require more capital which, we
are sorry to say, we are unable to secure from any other sources except
from the reading public. Our plan to secure additional capital is plain,
<pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0144.jpg" n="2"/>
we figure that the increased expenses can be covered by securing from
700 to 800 new subscribers, and we are strongly appealing to our readers
and friends for this support.</p>
      <p>We do not need go further with an explanation why our Slovenes need their
own and the only Catholic newspaper, nor what benefits they are getting
by reading its very interesting and highly educational pages. We hope that
such reasons already have been printed on many pages of this paper, but
the only opinion we do express is that it would not be nice of Slovenes
if, in this critical hour for our newspaper's existence, they will withdraw 
their helping hand. We do not have other means to provide additional
capital, and we must assure you that without sufficient capital this paper
cannot be published in an enlarged form or have better reading material.</p>
      <p>Now that we have laid down our problem, it is up to you, friends and
readers, to help us with solicitation of a few hundred new subscribers,
and if you succeed in this work we will keep our promises of going to
the limit.</p>
      <pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0145.jpg" n="3"/>
      <p>All Catholic organizations are requested to organize their work on solicitation, 
and as soon as we have the required number of new subscribers
filled, our work on developing the newspaper will be fast.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
