<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Amerikanski Slovenec</title>, Vol. XXXIII, No. 131, <date when="1929-07-06">July 6, 1929</date>.
<title level="a"/></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>chicagoforeignl0chic_0218</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-III.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.B.3"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-III.B.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-I.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-12-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0218.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>SLOVENE</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>III E</item>
          <item>II B 3</item>
          <item>III B 2</item>
          <item>I C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Amerikanski Slovenec</title>, Vol. XXXIII, No. 131, <date when="1929-07-06">July 6, 1929</date>.
<title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="3"/></title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The Slovenian Eagles form our largest colony in America, Cleveland, Ohio,
arrived here today under the leadership of their spiritual leader, Rev.
Father H. Jager, assistant pastor in the Slovenian church there.</p>
      <p>This evening in Czech-American Hall, 1440 W. 18th St., they will meet 
and exhibit their drills and other calisthenics, which will interest all.
It is needless to say that we expect all Slovenes, young and old, to be
present and our cordial invitation is extended.</p>
      <p>An especially hearty welcome to our Cleveland visitors who are honoring 
us with their contribution.</p>
      <p>The Slovenian Orel (Eagles) have had no better chance to show their
accomplishments than they have today in Chicago, and tomorrow at the
<pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0219.jpg" n="2"/>
all-Slavic congress at Lemont, Ill. never before had the American Slovenes an 
opportunity to witness such a glorious performance in their adopted country.</p>
      <p>The Slovenian Orel is a purely Slovenian institution. The Orel organization
is a Slovenian national school out of which the people and church may get something mighty and
of great significance.</p>
      <p>We need a pure, simple character here as well as in the old country. The 
old country needs it to surpress a continuous wall of foreign propaganda
which is denationalizing and irreligious, and which aims to swallow us
when we are nationally and politically weak.</p>
      <p>More than ever, here in America, we need a national Catholic Slovenian 
character. Anybody that wants to, can see how anti-Slovenian evangelists
are misleading (us). Here is where we need a revival of our characteristics!
How?</p>
      <pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0220.jpg" n="3"/>
      <p>The American-Slovenian generation, born and raised in America, is getting
more numerous from year to year. This young generation is here and 
ready to take over our organizations, lodges, clubs, parishes in fact
all that is ours. In ten years this new generation will reach maturity
and our American-Slovenian institutions will naturally fall on their shoulders.</p>
      <p>Now the question is How much is this young generation Slovenian in
national and religious spirit? How are the families and individuals? Responsibility lies with leadership.</p>
      <p>Against Americanization there is no remedy; that we are in the melting 
pot there is no question, but there is no sufficient reason why we go
so fast.</p>
      <p>A great help to preserve our national and religious spirit is derived 
from Slovenian organizations. Among the first ones is the Orel (Eagles)
<pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0221.jpg" n="4"/>
organization. The purpose of the organization is obvious. It wants to 
raise strong national and religious characters. With athletics and physical
education, Catholic in spirit, raising them in a Christian faith, 
leading them regularly to receive sacraments, where Orels with faith 
in God are prepared for the fullest life, and are the most competent for leadership.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
