<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Memorial Book of the First All-Slavic Singing Festival.</title><date when="1934">1934</date>.

        </bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>chicagoforeignl0chic_0123</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.B.1.a"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.B.2.e"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-V.A.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-III.C"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-12-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0123.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>SLOVENE</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>II B 1 a</item>
          <item>II B 2 e</item>
          <item>V A 1</item>
          <item>III C</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Memorial Book of the First All-Slavic Singing Festival.</title><date when="1934">1934</date>.
</bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>The name Adrija means Adriatic. The sky-blue Adriatic Sea has always been
an object of tender affection and almost devout reverence for Slovenes, and
their love for it is reflected in their songs. They share this feeling with
their southern neighbors and kinsmen, the Croats. A number of Slovene and
Croatian singing societies call themselves Adrija or Jadran.</p>
      <p>The Adrija Slovene Singing Society of Chicago is a mixed choir. Since its
organization fourteen years ago the number of its members has fluctuated.
There have never been less than twenty-five nor more than forty-five active
singers.</p>
      <p>The Adrija choir is affiliated with the Slovene Roman Catholic Church of
St. Stephen, at Twenty-second Place and Lincoln Street in Chicago. Besides
its liturgical singing in the aforesaid church the society gives one or two
concerts every year in the school hall adjacent to St. Stephen's Church,
<pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0124.jpg" n="2"/>
and it often renders programs for the lodges, clubs, and fraternities of the
local community. It has also appeared on the concert programs of other Slovene 
singing societies in Chicago, namely, the Lira, the Zarja, the Sava,
and the Preseren, and at present it is cooperating; with the oldest and largest 
of them all, the Slovan. Adrija was the first Slovene choir in Chicago
to attempt the radio field; it has appeared in four Slovene radio programs
over Station WHFC and in one program over Station WCFL. A number of Slovene
phonograph records are also included in its list of accomplishments. These
latter are characteristic sketches with dialogue and song, such as the Slovene 
Wedding Festival, the Announcement of Spring (Advent of St. George),
and others.</p>
      <p>The Adrija choir by its untiring efforts and commendable sacrifices was instrumental 
in securing a new electro-pheumatic two-manual organ for St.
Stephen's Church, installed February 19, 1928.</p>
      <p>The proceeds of the choir's various activities are turned over to the parochial 
treasury, and its needs are provided for, and its expenses paid by the
parish.</p>
      <pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0125.jpg" n="3"/>
      <p>New members for the Adrija choir are constantly being recruited from the
ranks of the local parochial grammar-school graduates.</p>
      <p>The director of the Adrija Singing Society is Mr. Ivan Racic, organist of
St. Stephen's Church. His connection with the choir goes back practically
to its inception. Mr. Racic received some of his musical training in Europe
and is now working for a degree in music at De Paul University in Chicago.
He was the unanimous choice for leader of the Slovene aggregation of singers 
at the First All-Slavic Singing Festival in Chicago.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
