<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Proletarec</title>, Vol. XXII, No. 1024, <date when="1927-05-01">May Day 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Youth in the Slovene Fraternal Societies</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>chicagoforeignl0chic_0170</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.D.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-III.A"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-III.E"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.B.3"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-12-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0170.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>SLOVENE</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>II D 1</item>
          <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
          <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
          <item>III A</item>
          <item>III E</item>
          <item>II B 3</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Proletarec</title>, Vol. XXII, No. 1024, <date when="1927-05-01">May Day 1927</date>.
<title level="a">YOUTH IN THE SLOVENE FRATERNAL SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>New thoughts and ideas develop every day. These new thoughts and
ideas must find new outlets in the same manner as any mechanical
implement or device. New implements, new thoughts and ideas are rarely
accepted unanimously, and until they are accepted, they must struggle
for their existence.</p>
      <p>The young generation in the Slovene National Benefit Society has
developed new conceptions. To put these into operation under the
old system would be impossible, so nothing more desirable could have
happened than to have them branch into separate lodges in accordance
with their new ideas.</p>
      <p>These new thoughts could not possibly be of any value to the parent
lodges; yet when they were properly assembled in their new forms
and put into operation, they met with surprising success. Unheard
<pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0171.jpg" n="2"/>
of events, houses filled to capacity, things done just a little
different from the others. From the way these events were received,
we must feel that they were welcome wholeheartedly. It is our
desire and our purpose to keep building the fraternal spirit and
to keep pace with the most up-to-date styles of entertainment.</p>
      <p>But even today, after proving unusually successful (functioning for
over a year and a half) some people still question the right of
young English-speaking Slovenes to organize into subordinate lodges.
Nevertheless, we must say that a big majority of the membership,
as well as the main body of officials, have given the movement
considerable support. In the main, however, it is not our purpose
nor is it proper for any participant or sympathizer to denounce
those not actually in favor of the movement, but rather to produce
evidence and proof to convince them that the policies pursued are
safe, sound, and justifiable. All claims that the young generation
could not exist and function should be banished immediately, for
<pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0172.jpg" n="3"/>
the performances of the past year well verify our statement that
more life and energy in the subordinate lodges has never been
brought to light. Of course, reference is made to the seventeen
English-speaking lodges of the SNPJ. Baseball and other sports

did not materialize as many predicted. Instead, membership campaigns, 
dances, picnics, and other means of obtaining funds to 

bolster the locals were instituted. One could venture to say that

these newly organized people are considerably more interested in

the affairs of their respective lodges than can be said of the

majority of the elders.</p>
      <p>We don't doubt a bit that it was likewise with our parent lodges.

Good will, plenty of life and enthusiasm, and mainly excellent

results were obtainable when they were founded. But goodness how

this has diminished! Solely for the reason that the discussions

and thoughts concurred in were of the plain repeated style. What

we propose to do, however, is to use variety, by giving the young

generation the most modern disposition and meaning of fraternalism;

<pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0173.jpg" n="4"/>
the most up-to-date kind of amusement and entertainment; and the most

sincere cooperation and friendship.</p>
      <p>Experience is the best instructor. And while a few profess to have

an exceptionally rare collection of knowledge, the membership is

learning from day to day; correcting the inaccuracies of previous

mornings. As time passes, a better system will be instituted as

the result of a better understanding of the fraternal situation.

As a general rule most of the young element is fairly well situated

in other English fraternal organizations, so that our task of

interesting them is somewhat difficult. Other fraternal organizations

have more to offer in the way of recreation than the SNPJ. Consequently 
the above is true. Organizers must use precaution and good

judgment, because the disposition of those of the age limit is very

indefinite and quite obscure. We must not only talk fraternalism

to them; no, that will never do. It is essential that we mention

social functions as well, until they have sufficiently mastered
<pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0174.jpg" n="5"/>

the scope of our field. You elders - your tasks were hard. Ours are

none the easier. Lend us your support; especially in the localities

where the population is widely scattered. The future of any Slovene

fraternal organization lies in the hands of the offspring. Similar

expressions are heard and read frequently. But it is not sufficient

to merely speak and write these words. It is necessary that these

remarks be backed with moral and financial support. And what about

the Slovene language? What effect will these new organizations

have upon it? Heated discussions on the subject are witnessed

regularly. From the most timid tales to the most capable defensive

arguments one is able to pick statements that would astonish even

the most unconcerned bystander. Some fear that the Slovene fraternal

organizations have reached their limit; that the English subsidiary

is their only salvation. Others quite differently proclaim no fear 

for the language, even for the distant future. And so we conceive

the opinion that no immediate change is to take place in our

generation because within the rank and file there exist a large
<pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0175.jpg" n="6"/>
percentage of those favorable to the organization of these English
lodges yet willing to sacrifice time and money for the development
of the Slovene language.</p>
      <p>It is true that the official business of these lodges is transacted

in the English language, but it is also true that a greater percentage

of these youngsters attempt in either speak, read, write, or sing

in the Slovene language now more than heretofore. Prosveta is read

with delight, for it is convenient to glance from its pages to the

other sections for various announcements and suggestions. What is

more, magazines such as Mladinski List and Proletarec, while not

in the limelight, bear great watching. Perfected to a higher degree

of satisfaction, such magazines will be of great assistance in

partially keeping up the nationality. However, if the Slovene language 
is destined to extinction in this country, the English-speaking 
lodges will not be the cause nor will such lodges bear the responsibility. 
Besides being a well-balanced fraternal organization, the

Slovene National Benefit Society is known to be a powerful weapon

<pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0176.jpg" n="7"/>

when used in defense of the workers.</p>
      <p>Without question it must be said that conditions, both working and

living, have been improved. Organizations such as our fraternal

order have been responsible, at least in part, in bringing about

such improvement. You might consider such action as entering

politics, but politics or otherwise, if the steps taken will

bring about better living and working conditions, I deem it essential

and necessary to say that our fraternal societies continue pursuing

such tactics as long as the prevailing system of plundering the

masses last. The Jugoslav Socialist Federation and its educational

department is another institution which is also active in all such

struggles, as is the League for Industrial Democracy. Knowing this,

how can we fail to support them? Remembering that the years will

tell the story of your present behavior, let us make history as

it has never been made before.</p>
      <p>In conclusion it is necessary to appeal to the Jugoslavs of this
<pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0177.jpg" n="8"/>

country to help build up their race by organizing new English-speaking

lodges, to keep and uphold the race by bringing up their offspring

so they can speak the Jugoslav language and to support such institutions 

from whom most benefit is derived. If you do this, we can

assure you that our language will not die; that the movement will

grow and prosper and will not astonish or amaze anyone.</p>
      <p>Donald J. Lotrich.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
