<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <bibl><title>Majski Glas (May Herald)</title>, <date when="1937-05">May 1937</date>.
<title level="a">The Future of Building and Loan Associations</title></bibl>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno>chicagoforeignl0chic_0114</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
        <bibl>
          <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
          <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
          <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
        <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
      </xi:include>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene"/>
        <catRef target="#grp-slovene #code-II.A.2"/>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2012-12-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
      <change when="2012-12-28">Initial TEI transcription</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0114.jpg" n="1"/>
      <div type="group">
        <list>
          <item>SLOVENE</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="codes">
        <list>
          <item>II A 2</item>
        </list>
      </div>
      <div type="citation">
        <bibl><title>Majski Glas (May Herald)</title>, <date when="1937-05">May 1937</date>.
<title level="a">THE FUTURE OF BUILDING AND LOAN ASSOCIATIONS</title></bibl>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <p>By Donald J. Lotrich</p>
      <p>For a good many years Building and Loan Associations have enjoyed the
confidence and good will of our people and have therefore played quite
prominently in their lives. Particularly has that been true in localities 
where our people have settled more compactly and in larger numbers.
Say what we will, these institutions have been used and are still being
used by the progressive and thrifty elements as savings institutions.
Many, many have used to advantage the credit and services of these
institutions to acquire their homes. Some who were not so prudent or
who overestimated their earning ability and plunged too deeply into
debt, however, could not be rescued even by such institutions. Wherever
the management was wise and alert to the trends and conditions it can
be generally said that there the association was a great asset to the
people and to the community. The direct opposite is true wherever the
management ignored the principal factors of good business management
and economic tendencies.</p>
      <p>The mere fact that we were able to survive the depression gives us
<pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0115.jpg" n="2"/>
assurance and courage to continue. But I know that mere words are
insufficient to assure anyone anything in the present capitalistic
set-up. It's got to be more than that. Action must accompany words.</p>
      <p>Permit me to say, then, that the 1937 Board of Directors of the Jugoslav 
Building and Loan Association have adopted, among other things,
a goal of 160 new subscribers for 1937.</p>
      <p>Ten have already begun to pay their weekly allotments. Twenty two more
have pledged to do the same in a short time. We are intent on disposing
of the real estate on hand and pay off the old obligations just as soon
as conditions warrant.</p>
      <p>Incidentally, I might say that there is a brisk demand for homes and
that one property has already been sold and that a number of bids on
other properties have been received.</p>
      <p>There can be no doubt but that the experiment of the Federal Government
<pb facs="chicagoforeignl0chic_0116.jpg" n="3"/>
in providing mortgage credit through Associations like ours has proved
successful. Hence, there can be no doubt but that greater support and
a more definite desire to participate in the work of these Associations
will be the continued policy of the Federal institution.</p>
      <p>A nation's basic wealth is its land and homes and mineral deposits.</p>
      <p>With a well organized mortgage reserve system behind it, there is no
sounder investment than the home mortgage cooperative units or mutual
associations give to the investor the maximum in returns. With management, 
foresight and vision there is every reason to believe that our
associations can still grow and prosper and give that service, both
to investor and borrower, that was given in the past.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
