<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-09-21">Sept. 21, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Commemoration of "September 18th"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0238</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0238.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III B</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-09-21">Sept. 21, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">COMMEMORATION OF "SEPTEMBER 18TH"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A mass meeting was held last Sunday at the Chinese Emergency Relief Society's Auditorium in commemoration of "September 18th," which marked the Mukden incident of 1931.</p>
   <p>At 7 P.M. the auditorium was fully occupied, and all the late-comers had to stand at the door which is symbolic of the Chinese public enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order at 7:30 P.M. by Mr. C. S. Mah, the assistant chairman of the exhortation and publicity committee.</p>
   <p>Mr. Y. C. Moy, president of the Chinese Emergency Relief Society began the program with an explanation of the origin of this commemoration. He, then, introduced the first speaker, Miss Tsuo Shuioli, a student at the University of Chicago, who spoke on "The Commemoration of 'September 18th' and Fighting the Japanese till the End." She emphasized the three important methods of attacking Japan - militaristic, economic and cultural. We, who live abroad, should lead our country towards economic attack by supporting our government financially <pb facs="5418479_0239.jpg" n="2"/>and boycotting Japanese goods, which eventually will result in a Japanese financial collapse.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hwang Kai-Lok, a student at the University of Wisconsin, then, spoke on "Why Americans should be concerned with Sino-Japanese problems?" Mr. Hwang stressed the fact that we should utilize every opportunity to exhortate individually, explain, and give detailed information, if necessary, on Japanese invasion of our Chinese territory. Our duty is to enable the Americans to realize that the Sino-Japanese war is not merely a Far-Eastern problem, but a problem of world peace. The domination of Asia will not appease the wild desire of imperialistic Japan but will seek the domination of Western atmosphere as well. Therefore, if America wants to avoid unnecessary sacrifices due to a possible future war with Japan, she should resent Japanese militaristic movements and sympathize with China by assisting both materially and spiritually.</p>
   <p>The evening program was concluded with the showing of films depicting Chinese civilization and the Sino-Japanese war <pb facs="5418479_0240.jpg" n="3"/>All in all it was a grand program for a grand commemoration. Fellow countrymen who attended the meeting were not only benefited by it, but they left the auditorium with more zeal, enthusiasm, and determination than ever before.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
