<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-10-11">Oct. 11, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">The Commemoration of Independence by the Chinese Emergency Relief Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0233</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0233.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-10-11">Oct. 11, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">THE COMMEMORATION OF INDEPENDENCE BY THE CHINESE EMERGENCY RELIEF SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the first time in the long history of China, our people are now fighting for their existence. It is true that China has been conquered by Mongols and Manchus before, but the motive behind these conquests was the overthrow of the throne of China, the life of the Chinese was not endangered. The present Japanese invasion, has as aim to crush China, dominate China, and slave China. It affects the age-long freedom of the Chinese people. A liberty loving people, nurtured in pacifism and acquainted with the arts of war, China is now fighting for its independence.</p>
   <p>Heretofore, China's desire for peace has been capitalized by Japan. Territories were taken away from us. Our people have been ruthlessly murdered. Japanese goods were smuggled into our country openly. Our hatred of war and our love for peace only encouraged Japan to launch fiercer attacks against us.</p>
   <p>We want peace, we pray for peace, but what we get is a permanent war against our people and government until every Chinese has become a Japanese slave and every province a part of the Japanese Empire.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0234.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To-day is our National Independence Day. It marks the Chinese will for independence and unification. It marks the Chinese struggle for demorcracy. It represents the countless lives that have been dedicated to this cause. It represents the countless lives that are daily taken away on the battle - fields and in defenseless cities,by the Japanese militarists. The ideals which this day symbolizes are ours to cherish and keep. No one can take them away from us. Our fight will go on as long as Japan refuses to renounce her dreams of conquest.</p>
   <p>The behavior of the Japanese militarists has once again proved to the world that they stop at nothing. Law, order, and moral standards from which the peace of the world depends mean nothing to the Japanese.</p>
   <p>Japanese militarists are the common foe of peace and humanity. We hate war. We hate barbarism. Therefore, let us unite and by our concreted efforts defeat Japan.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
