<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chinese Daily Times</title>,
<date when="1936-09-26">Sep. 26, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">The Chinese Herchant Mr. C. P. Wu Murdered</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0202</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0202.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chinese Daily Times</title>,
<date when="1936-09-26">Sep. 26, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">THE CHINESE HERCHANT MR. C. P. WU MURDERED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. C. T. Wu was born in Shin-Hwei, Kwantung, more than sixty years ago. He has been in Chicago over thirty years. He was a meek and quiet business man with pleasing manners. He has been operating a number of restaurants in the city with his brothers and cousin as partners. His business has been prosperous. His loop restaurant Hoe-Sai-Sai is the most famous of all Chinese restaurants in Chicago. He was naturally wealthy and was considered one of the leading Chinese merchants here.</p>
   <p>Yesterday morning at 1:30 A. M. while Mr. Moy was on duty at his westside restaurant a chinaman entered. At that time Mr. Wu was at the register behind the counter. The intruder addressed Mr. Wu as "uncle" and there were only a few words exchanged before the intruder drew a gun on Mr. Wu and fired three shots. Mr. Wu fell immediately while the murderer escaped. There were over twenty customers witnesses of the shooting.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0203.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Immediately after the shooting employees of the restaurant telephoned the police station while the victim was sent to the hospital. But Mr. Wu died from the bullet wounds before reaching the hospital. After the arrival of the police at the restaurant they immediately questioned all customers and left with a number of restaurant employees for further questioning at the station. They were, however, released later.</p>
   <p>At present there are two Chinese suspects arrested for questioning at the detective bureau. An hour after the shooting the Hoe-Sai-Cai restaurant was visited by a Chinese stranger who appeared much like a murderer and he asked for Mr. Wu Chien (a cousin of Mr. Wu the victim) the manager. But Mr. Wu Chien had left for the West Side restaurant after receiving the telephone report of the shooting. The stranger then left.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0204.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The following is a description of the shooting:</p>
   <p>Address------ Chui-Lok-Yven Restaurant, 4007 West Madison Street.</p>
   <p>Time---------- 1:30 A. M. September 25, 1936.</p>
   <p>Victim---------Mr. C. T. Wu.</p>
   <p>Murderer----- Chinese, age about 30, height - 5 feet 4, wearing brown overcoat with grey cap.</p>
   <p>Wounds------- Left shoulder, right arm and abdomen.</p>
   <p>Murderer-suspect - Wu An and Wu How, proprietors of the neighboring Shin-Chui-Lok-Yven Restaurant.</p>
   <p>Motive-------- Unknown - perhaps due to business competition and jealousy.</p>
   <p>Weapon------- A 34 automatic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
