<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chinese Daily Times</title>,
<date when="1935-09-04">Sept. 4, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Chinese Natural Science Club American Branch Bulletin</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0152</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0152.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chinese Daily Times</title>,
<date when="1935-09-04">Sept. 4, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">CHINESE NATURAL SCIENCE CLUB AMERICAN BRANCH BULLETIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chinese Natural Science Club is recognized as the power of pure science.</p>
   <p>The club was organized eight years ago at Nanking Centralist University. Its aim was to spread the common scientific knowledge to the public.</p>
   <p>The work of the club, at first, was the publication of a magazine named Scientific World. Then followed a monthly lecture on the air from the Centralist Wireless station. Club memberships increased up to many hundreds within a few years and the club functions likewise expanded. The club propsed a natural science course in the Middle School (High School) and the establishing of a research laboratory and a scientific library, etc. Because of the expansion in club functions and the increased memberships, it was necessary to establish branches, not only all over the country, but all over the world. (We realize that there are thousands of Chinese studying abroad.) The American branch was one of the many branch clubs established last year.</p>
   <p>This club was first organized in our country and then branched abroad. Therefore, on a comparative basis, as far as memberships are concerned, we naturally have <pb facs="5418479_0153.jpg" n="2"/>more members in our country than abroad. There are over a thousand Chinese students in America and almost half of them are pursuing a natural science course.</p>
   <p>Due to the fact that our branch clubs here in America were newly established, it was naturally known to very few. We are, therefore, sending the president of the American branch club, Dr. D. H. Jung and Mr. C. Tsai and other to represent the Chinese Natural Science Club at the All America Chinese student delegate conference in Chicago. This will provide opportunity for those who are interested in our club to make the proper arrangements for membership.</p>
   <p>We believe all of you are enthusiastic as a matter of fact too willing to serve your country. We conclude, therefore, that all of you will show your interest in upholding our club whose work and objective is for the "happiness and good fortune of the people."</p>
   <p>As for the qualifications of a membership and its arrangement, will you all kindly get in touch with Dr. Jung whose address, during the student delegate conference, will be room, #473, International House.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
