<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-08-10">August 10, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Chinese Colony Indignant at the Plan for Detecting Chinamen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0215</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0215.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1892-08-10">August 10, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">CHINESE COLONY INDIGNANT AT THE PLAN FOR DETECTING CHINAMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chinese quarter on South Clark Street was visited last night by a reporter for the Tribune to ascertain the feeling of those residents as to the photographing and measurements now being taken of Chinese in the large port cities of this country by government officials in furtherance of the recently enacted Exclusion Law. The entire colony sat on the sidewalks and doorsteps. They smoked long stemmed thimble sized bowled pipes or held cigarettes in their mouths. Of the larger tea merchants Sam Moy was not in. As Hip Long's place was reached a sidewalk fight started between two Chinese. Hip Long shouldered his way through the perspiring jabbering crowd of his country-men and in a fatherly way counseled peace. The belligerants were separated and the pipe and cigarette resumed sway.</p>
   <p>The reporter introduced himself to the Tea Prince who angrily waved him away with a Chinese newspaper, as one would brush aside an impetuous fly. The reporter insisted on asking as to the Exclusion Act. Hip Long demanded: "Where you come from"? "The Tribune, will your people consent to sit and be photographed?" "Go way! I not talk".</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0216.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Chow Tar was called on. The reporter was met by a servant who shrilly called out "What you want?" The business was explained. He disappeared, quickly re-appeared, and said "He lie down, He not see you". "We get dlink". After he had taken a long robust forget-me-not drink of common Peoria whiskey he said in clear English: "If that law means that all my countrymen, residents in America are to be measured as criminals and labeled as so many packages of tea it will never be enforced. The ridiculousness of its provisions will kill it. Are we not residents here? Do we not pay taxes as all other property holders? It would be more nearly justice for them to drive us out. So long as we are accepted as residents we are entitled to some rights. We are not law breakers. There certainly would be a great deal of trouble should an attempt be made, such as you have indicated to place all Chinese residents on a par with professional criminals. For the record of such measurements and pictures would be classed as a "rogues" gallery. Would this Chinese "rogues" gallery be put on exhibition in the Worlds Fair to show the advancement in civilization that this nation has attained? No, no, I think that a telegram stating that such measurements and photographs are now being taken of Chinese in the cities which are ports must be a hoax. "We take another dlink".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
