<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chinese Centralist Daily News</title>,
<date when="1937-09-12">Sept. 12, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0155</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0155.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chinese Centralist Daily News</title>,
<date when="1937-09-12">Sept. 12, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Editorial</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As we know, our country of today is a country of war-fare. Newspapers are indispensible to society and humanity. We realized our responsibility, hence the publication of The Chinese Centralist Daily News, of the middle-west.</p>
   <p>The main object of the revolution was freedom and equality for our country, China; in order to achieve this goal we must wake up the public with an extensive proclamation; and the newspaper is the only means with which to achieve this end.</p>
   <p>Newspapers will reach all, far and near and it is a hundred-fold better than mere verbal proclamation.</p>
   <p>During this invasion by our enemy, and while we, people of China as a whole, are putting forth our united efforts to resist our invader, a rapid news service would be indispensable.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0156.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This would gather and express the opinion and spirit of the people. To this, we, as publishers of the news, acknowledge our responsibility.</p>
   <p>Since the beginning of this world, our country has been noted for its large population and territory and for its civilization and historic background. But during the last decade, we have suffered insults and mistreatment from all stronger powers, especially the imperial nations. Do we know just what the reason for it is? Yes! Briefly it is due to the lack of patriotism and spirit of co-operation and unity on the part of the people as a whole. But we who are here in a foreign land, realize our position as foreigners and strangers. We appreciate the circumstances surrounding us. We were influenced by it and thus, stirred up our spirit of patriotism. We offered our co-operation and help to our leader of Revolution. The republic of China was then established and since then, our leader has praised us and refers to us in foreign lands as "The Mother of Revolution."</p>
   <p>In view of the beginning of a long lasting warfare in our country, the <pb facs="5418479_0157.jpg" n="3"/>responsibility of publication and proclamation is very heavy. We must forget ourselves and concentrate our efforts on serving our country and fellow countrymen. Our duty the, as publishers, is to strive to publish all important and accurate news and facts in this.</p>
   <p>We solicit your hearty co-operation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
