<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title><bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>, <date when="1937-10-11">Oct. 11, 1937</date></bibl></title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0207</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>                
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.1"/>
    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0207.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div> 
  <div type="citation"><bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>, <date when="1937-10-11">Oct. 11, 1937</date></bibl></div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The secret design of the Japanese militarists is to conquer the world. First North China, then all China, the Philippines, Guam, Wake Islands, Hawaii and then the Western World. A distinguished American has publicly warned his country that the scrap iron shipped to Japan in large quanities today might return to America some day in the form of bullets.</p>
   <p>By subduing China the Japanese think that they will gain access to the vast resources and the huge man power of China so as to be able to continue their conquests. In the present undeclared war, which might prove later to be only the initial stage of Japanese world-wide imperialism, China is really the first line of resistance against the fantastic Japanese greed for power and supremacy.</p>
   <p>These international outlaws from Japan, who have no respect for the sanctity of treaties and who scoff at such ideas as national morality and international justice, must be disciplined. Their aggressive warfare in China must be immediately halted before they have done too much damage to the foundation of peace, which it took the democratic countries many years of untiring effort to build up.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0208.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The most effective peaceful means to bring Japan to her senses is the economic boycott especially with the active participation of the two great democracies of the world - Great Britain and the United States.</p>
   <p>Japan cannot, in fact, afford this expensive war, which she is waging on China. It costs Japan at least $7,000,000, - a day to support her army and navy in China. Her anxiety to bring Nanking to capitulation in the shortest possible time is indicative of her lack of sufficient resources to finance a prolonged war. With the realization of this fact, the Chinese government adopts the strategy of retreating to the interior in North China, where China can carry on a protracted defensive warfare.</p>
   <p>America can help China to put a longer and stiffer resistance by sending, directly or indirectly, munitions and war equipment to her. While in the meantime, placing an embargo on war equipment shipments to Japan. America can hasten the collapse of the Japanese war machine and of her imperialistic plans.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0209.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Fifty per cent of Japan's foreign trade is with America and England, and a greater part of the remaining fifty per cent with China. Now, the Chinese market is completely lost to Japan, and Anglo-American boycott of Japanese goods would greatly reduce, if not completely annihilate, Japan's financial ability to purchase war materials abroad. A dollar's purchase of Japanese goods here means a massacre of a score of innocent Chinese by relentless Japanese soldiers.</p>
   <p>With nearly all her standing army in China, with half of her navy in Shanghai and the other half patrolling the Chinese coast, Japan is not physically able to attack any Western nation taking part in an economic boycott. A concerted action by world powers in applying sanctions (penalties) against Japan, particularly Anglo-American cooperation, is a positive step toward the preservation of world peace. Such a step involves no danger of becoming entangled in the war.</p>
   <p>It is an encouraging fact that an economic boycott against Japanese goods is gaining momentum in England. Inevitably, it will make the Japanese realize what their greed for supremacy and their disregard for international obligations will bring to their country. Japan must be taught the lesson that might is not right.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
