<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chinese Centralist Daily News</title>,
<date when="1937-10-11">Oct. 11, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">What We Should Know in Regards to Commemoration of Independence Day (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0228</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0228.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chinese Centralist Daily News</title>,
<date when="1937-10-11">Oct. 11, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT WE SHOULD KNOW IN REGARDS TO COMMEMORATION OF INDEPENDENCE DAY (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Amidst this disastrous autumn we commemorate our Nations Independence. While dancing with joy and happiness in commemoration there came a sudden impulse.-patriotism.</p>
   <p>The Independence of to-day should, therefore, include at least the following factors which we all who have the same objectives, must know.</p>
   <p>1. In commemorating Independence, we should all remember our obedience to the orders of the highest leader of our Central Government. We must recall that the commemoration of to-day, is due to our Republican leader's triumph in the Revolution; obedience on the part of the revolutionary members, and sacrifices made by the martyrs made it possible. He never gave up in spite of defeats.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0229.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This was what led to the"Wu-Chong" incident - overthrowing an imperialistic government and instead, establishing the Chinese Republic. And that was the birth of our Independence.</p>
   <p>During these critical moments of national crisis we must continue cooperating with our leader from the Central Government, and that is, only, the first step in defending and saving our country.</p>
   <p>Back in our history, Mock-Tze proposed an absolute dictorial government. His policy was to have a government that was under an absolate leadership of a dictator in order to maintain peace in society and to strengthen the national power. An absolute leader will utilize his rights and power to execute governmental affairs for protective purposes of his country and people. And if such measures are achieved, the national government will undoubtedly become a world's power, therefore, to follow and obey our leader is today the predominant factor in saving our country.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0230.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>2. In commemorating Independence we should commence with some new revolutionary activities. An ancient saying reads- " To right one's heart before cultivating one's self; to cultivate one's self before dominating a home; to dominate a home before executing national politics". Therefore, if we want to save our country we must begin with self-cultivation, and if we want to save our country we must begin with self-cultivation, and if we want to cultivate ourselves we must begin with some revolutionary movements or activities.</p>
   <p>Every since the new national activities headed by General Chiang Kai-Shiek, the whole nation has united in its efforts to organize and, subsequently, to defend it successfully.</p>
   <p>Yes, this is, indeed, the result of a new revolutionary movement and activity. We hope all overseas country-men will realize and agree that our aim is to protect and to save our country. And the new revolutionary activities and movements are the foundations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
