<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-10-02">Oct. 2, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">A Requiem Mass for General Director Frank Moy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0192</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0192.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-10-02">Oct. 2, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">A REQUIEM MASS FOR GENERAL DIRECTOR FRANK MOY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A requiem mass was said yesterday (September 30, 1937) in memory of the deceased Mr. Frank Moy, general director of the Chinese Emergency Relief Society. The mass was held in the Chinese Christian Church on Wentworth Avenue.</p>
   <p>The requiem mass committee had the church decorated very appropriately. Directly above the entrance of the church hung a large placard, with the inscription "The requiem mass of General Director Frank Moy." Inside the church chamber a picture of Mr. Frank Moy was placed on the sacrificial altar, which was gorgeously garnished with fresh flowers and wreaths. Elegiac scrolls filled the church chamber from end to end. It was indeed, an impressive decoration.</p>
   <p>Mr. C. S. Chin was the presiding chairman, and following were the numbers of the program:</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0193.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>1. Music and hymn in charge of Reverend T. Y. Lee.</p>
   <p>2. Three-minute meditation in memory of Mr. Frank Moy.</p>
   <p>3. Mr. C. S. Wong, acting consul took his seat on the rostrum.</p>
   <p>Mr. Y. T. Moy, President of the Chinese Benevolent Association,</p>
   <p>Mr. Y. C. Moy, President of the Chinese Emergency Relief Society,</p>
   <p>C. H. Yu, W. R. Lee, C. Tang, C. P. Lee, and N. Moy followed in the above order.</p>
   <p>4. The congregation saluted the picture of Mr. F. Moy.</p>
   <p>5. Acting Consul Wong, offered fresh flowers at the altar.</p>
   <p>6. Mr. Y. F. Chew said the requiem mass.</p>
   <p>7. Telegrams of condolence were read by Mr. C. S. Mah.</p>
   <p>(The senders included Ambassador C. T. Wong, of Washington, D. C., and Consul General Hwang of San Francisco, etc.)</p>
   <p>8. Mr. H. Chien, then gave a brief biography of Mr. Frank Moy, emphasizing his whole hearted patriotic activities. After which Reverend T. Y. Lee repeated it in English for the benefit of the English speaking people present.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0194.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>9. Acting consul, then, spoke briefly but patriotically, encouraging our fellow country-men to continue their patriotic activities untiringly. Consul Wong also repeated his speach in English.</p>
   <p>10. Mr. Y. N. Moy representing the survivors of the deceased answered a few words of thanks.</p>
   <p>11. The requiem mass ended with an anthem sung by the Chinese Church choir.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
