<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-09-23">Sept. 23, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">The Return of Mr. O'young Chee to Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0348</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0348.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-09-23">Sept. 23, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">THE RETURN OF MR. O'YOUNG CHEE TO CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. O'Young Chee, president of the Yung-Ming Life Insurance Company, has returned to Chicago yesterday from a nine months trip to China.</p>
   <p>During his trip Mr. O'Young visited all the leading cities in China, making a general study of the present condition of our country.</p>
   <p>Mr. O'Young stated emphatically that since the beginning of the Japanese invasion both our government and its people are preparing definitely for a prolonged war. The whole country is determined and ready to make unlimited sacrifices. Furthermore, prominent citizens and leaders all over the country are co-operating splendidly in finance, transportation, and defense matters as well as in spirit.</p>
   <p>The rapid unification of our country for defensive purposes is indeed a surprise to the Japanese, who consider it as a really perplexing problem. Because of the existing situation, the Japanese have used their concentrated efforts in their invasion of our country. But in spite of their lawlessness and brutal tactics used in their attack, our country as a whole is united as strongly as ever. The long looked-for sacrifices were not a surprise to us. We are all prepared for it, and <pb facs="5418479_0349.jpg" n="2"/>the longer the war lasts the stronger our country will be. While our enemy is not in the position to maintain a prolonged war, and if she should be forced to prolong her attack, then, a Japanese internal shake-up is inevitable. Then,and only then, will we reap the final victory.</p>
   <p>Our government, therefore, is looking forward to a continuous financial support of a prolonged war from the overseas Chinese, and a genuine sacrifice from all those who are in action.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
