<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-08-27">Aug. 27, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Chinese Consulate an Open Letter from the Chinese Embassy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0371</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0371.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-08-27">Aug. 27, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO CHINESE CONSULATE AN OPEN LETTER FROM THE CHINESE EMBASSY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are concerned about the growing Sino-Japanese warfare because it means the future of our national government is at stake. But we are, indeed, glad to mention that our oversea fellow Chinese are putting forth all their efforts in backing the national government financially.</p>
   <p>Time and again we have received letters regarding the proper place where the contributions should be sent. Now, in order to solve this problem, the Ambassador is making this public announcement to all fellow countrymen, that the New York Branch of the Bank of China has been decided upon as the contribution receiving center. He also mentioned the two divisions in contributions. That is, all contributions solicited for emergency relief for the dead and the dying will come under the Chinese Red Cross Association, and those of war fund will come under the Chinese Embassy.</p>
   <p>This unique arrangement of the Embassy has been presented to the national government, and we are positive that this will avoid all possible confusion.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0372.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For the sake of convenience to all Chinese in North America the following banks have promised co-operation with the Bank of China in New York.</p>
   <p>First National Bank of Boston, Boston, Mass. Bank of Canton, San Francisco, Cal. Seattle First National Bank, Seattle, Wash. The Imperial Bank of Canada, Toronto, Can. The Imperial Bank of Canada, Montreal, Can. The Imperial Bank of Canada, Winnipeg, Can. The Imperial Bank of Canada, Victoria, Can. The Imperial Bank of Canada, Vancouver, Can.</p>
   <p>We are also negotiating with banks of Chicago and other large American cities for co-operation. We hope all of our countrymen will send their contributions to the above mentioned banks or direct to the Bank of China, 40 Wall Street, New York City.</p>
   <p>But, please remember the safest way to send your contributions is by draft and not cash.</p>
   <p>Regarding the receipt of your contributions, the Bank of China in New York is preparing a special form which will contain the sum contributed and its purpose, etc. This special form of receipt will be available next week. In the meantime all contributions <pb facs="5418479_0373.jpg" n="3"/>will be given ordinary receipts.</p>
   <p>Chicago Chinese Consulate</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
