<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-04-12">Apr. 12, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Increasing Laundry Prices by the American Laundry Union and its Influence Upon the Chinese Laundries in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-04-12">Apr. 12, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">INCREASING LAUNDRY PRICES BY THE AMERICAN LAUNDRY UNION AND ITS INFLUENCE UPON THE CHINESE LAUNDRIES IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In order to meet the problem of the ever increasing standard of living the Chicago Westside Laundry Union had a meeting on April 9th. Over a hundred representatives were present. They discussed the following increase in prices. The prices are :- Shirt-15c - Collar-05c - Handkerchief-03c - BVD-15c - Socks-06c - Summer Pants-30c - Womens' Uniforms- 35c - etc. The new price list will be effective April 9th.</p>
   <p>And on the same day the Chicago Northside Laundry Union had a similar meeting and decided upon a 15c charge for a shirt and a 1c increase on other articles.</p>
   <p>Now as far as the Chinese are concerned we were represented at both meetings. Mr. C. C. Lee, representing this paper was welcomed heartily as the Roosevelt Road Union meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0134.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He was called upon to speak and he emphasized the fact that he was not representing any particular Chinese organization but, rather, as a newspaper reporter, came to secure facts for free discussion and investigation by the Chinese. After the meeting Mr. Lee, accompanied by Mr. Newman, Vice-president of the Union, visited the Sherman Hotel where another Laundry Union meeting was still in progress. Mr. Y. T. Moy, President of the Chinese Consolidated Benevolent Association was present at this meeting.</p>
   <p>Both Unions were willing to cooperate with the Chinese Laundry Union, in rendering mutual help for a uniform laundry union policy.</p>
   <p>We understand that the Westside Laundry Union meeting will have another meeting next Sunday. And we hope that all Chinese Laundries in that location will realize that this important matter concerns the future of the laundry business. We hope, that as many Chinese Laundries as possible will be represented at that meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0135.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>And finally we suggest that, if the Chinese Laundry Union is in favor of such representation at an American Laundry Union, they should get together and elect a certain number of representatives that must be represented by the President and Secretary, of the Chinese Consolidated Benevolent Association. Because such representation will display the spirit of unity in our Chinese organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
