<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-10-11">Oct. 11, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Japan's Undeclared War in China</title>
- By Ambassador C. T. Wong.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0321</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0321.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-10-11">Oct. 11, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">JAPAN'S UNDECLARED WAR IN CHINA</title>
- By Ambassador C. T. Wong.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>While the far-seeing statesmen of the world proclaim again and again the principles of international self-restrain and advise abstinence in the use of force in the pursuit of national policies, the military oligarchy of Japan is ravaging China with all the deadly weapons of war. Those who are not quite familiar with this phase of baneful influence from which the world is suffering today, will do well to examine the illegal actions of Japan in China. In recent years, the world has come to openly question the good faith of Japanese pretentions regarding China. Time and again, responsible Japanese officials told the world that Japan has no territorial designs in China, but their actions in China belie their words.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0322.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Steadfastly and incessantly Japan has encroached upon the administrative and territorial sovereignty of China. In less than six years, she has occupied four large provinces of China in addition to certain parts of the provinces of Suiyuan and Chahar, generally known as Eastern Mongolia. It is characteristic of Japanese aggressions in China, that "incidents" are purposely created, and under such pretenses armed force is invariably resorted to. When the smoke clears after each conflict, we find Japan occupying more Chinese territories, and more firmly entrenched in positions, which enables her to infringe further upon China's rights.</p>
   <p>In regard to the military occupation by Japan of the north-eastern provinces of China since 1931 and the fighting in Shanghai in 1932, the legal aspects are very clear. The impartial commissions appointed by the League of Nations, clearly stated that Japan acted in Manchuria and at Shanghai without any justification and in violation of the covenant of the League, of the Kellogg Peace Pact and of the Nine-Power Treaty of Washington.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0323.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Recently, Japanese aggressions have been directed against the five northern provinces of China, particularly Hopei, Chahar and Suiyuan. Her object is to set up therein another regime upon the pattern of the puppet state "Man-chukuo". There is no limit to the ambitions of Japan. According to her fixed policy, generally known as the Continental Policy, Japan will extend her domination not only over China, but also over the whole of Asia.</p>
   <p>To realize their domination over North China, the Japanese militarists purposely created on July 7th, the "incident" at Lukuochiao, or Marco Polo Bridge, where Japan has no right to station troops and hold maneuvers. Since then the Japanese forces have been in control of the whole Peiping - Tientsin area, from which emanate terrific attacks on Chinese positions.</p>
   <p>The fighting that is raging in Shanghai is not a mere local event. It is a tactical measure purposely employed by Japan to consummate another conquest. The fact that Shanghai is the chief economic and financial center of China and an international city where foreign commerce and investments abound, is too well known to require elaboration.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0324.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>And that is the reason why Japan has chosen such a place as an object of her vandalism. While China is compelled to make supreme sacrifices for the preservation of her national existence, it is tragic indeed that innocent lives and properties have to suffer in atonement for the sins of Japanese militarism.</p>
   <p>The cause of the present hostilities in China is very apparent. It is actuated by two diametrically opposite motives - on the part of Japan it is an undeclared war for national aggrandizement and territorial expansion. While for China it is armed resistence for the preservation of her national existence and independence. The whole issue, however multifarious and complicated, can be correctly called "Jingoism versus national self-determination."</p>
   <p>Resistance is the only course opened to us. China has exhausted every effort for a peaceful settlement with Japan. Indeed, our government has made it known to Japan as well as to the world that it is prepared to settle any or all of the differences with Japan by any of the pacific procedures known to international law and practice.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0325.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>But such suggestions have received no response from the Japanese government. In spite of our conciliatory attitude and utmost patience, Japan repeatedly has resorted to force to seize Chinese territories. Our government wishes it to be known that the provocations and aggressions of Japan have forced China to offer armed resistance to the best of her ability since all attempts on her part at conciliation have proved unsuccessful.</p>
   <p>It should be understood that China, while resisting the Japanese aggressions primarily on her own account, is also upholding at the same time, the sanctity of the international treaties, such as the Covenent of the League of Nations, the Kellogg Peace Pact and the Nine - Power Treaty of Washington. While China does not expect the friendly nations to start a crusade in her behalf she expects that all signatory powers to these pacts should feel conscious of their obligations under them.</p>
   <p>Lastly, we must, however, express our deep appreciation for the moral support and the keen sense of justice of the American people, although we must all understand that some concrete actions are indispensable to crystallize this moral force so that it may hasten the advent of peace in the Far East.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
