<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-08-31">Aug. 31, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Open Air Mass Meeting on Sino-Japanese War - Sponsored Jointly by the North American Student Association and the Chinese Emergency Relief Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0366</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0366.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-08-31">Aug. 31, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">OPEN AIR MASS MEETING ON SINO-JAPANESE WAR - SPONSORED JOINTLY BY THE NORTH AMERICAN STUDENT ASSOCIATION AND THE CHINESE EMERGENCY RELIEF SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since the beginning of the Sino-Japanese war the entire Chinese body of Chicago, under the leadership and guidance of the Chinese Emergency Relief Society, has contributed over $200,000 in Chinese currency within a few days.</p>
   <p>Mr. J. Chin, president of the North American Chinese Student Association and Miss S. L. Tsuo, ex-president of the Chicago Patriotic Society, have returned from an exhortation trip of Canada. They were honor guests at a banquet where all the student delegates were entertained yesterday afternoon by the On-Leong Chinese Merchant Association. At six-thirty o'clock, following the banquet, the open air mass meeting commenced. A crowd of about 700 were present.</p>
   <p>Mr. Y. C. Moy, president of the Chinese Emergency Relief Society, was the presiding chairman of the meeting. Speakers were introduced by Mr. T. S. Mar, vice-chairman of the publicity department. The main topic of the meeting was, "The Problem of Final Victory of the Sino-Japanese War."</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0367.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Miss S. L. Tsuo was the first speaker who stressed the fact that the only possible means to defeat Japan is to fight until the end. Miss Tsuo then spoke of Chinese history - its place in the world and its relationship with the other nations. She concluded that the final victory belongs to China. The audience responded with thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>Mr. T. V. Tung, president of the Chinese Student Association at Harvard University, followed with a report on Chinese students' patriotic work in Boston and Southern States of America.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was Miss C. T. Chen, a Chinese student delegate from the South, who related the war of 1832 in Shanghai.</p>
   <p>Dr. J. Y. Yee, executive officer of the North American Chinese Student Association, then spoke of his future service to our country. He related that he has devoted all his time to chemical research work and that he is returning to China to render his services to the munitions factories and fulfill his duty towards the government.</p>
   <p>Finally, Mr. J. Chin presented his belief of ultimate Chinese victory by stating <pb facs="5418479_0368.jpg" n="3"/>five important reasons. He also emphasized the fact that the only factor that will stop the present war is the return of our Northern Chinese lost territories.</p>
   <p>The speeches lasted about three hours and the audience was not in the least bored, which proves the enthusiasm and patriotic spirit of all fellow Chinese.</p>
   <p>The presiding chairman, Mr. Moy, concluded the program by stating that our brothers and fellow countrymen are sacrificing their lives and all for our country, and should we, as oversea Chinese, keep on loving and worshipping money? The entire audience was stimulated by his timely and precious words. Then they all arose and cheered - "Fight Japan with united effort till the end; down with Japanese imperialism, and long live the Chinese Republic!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
