<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-09-30">Sept. 30, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Our Consul's Report of the Chicago Chinese Community's Patriotic Activities to the Ambassador</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0346</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0346.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-09-30">Sept. 30, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">OUR CONSUL'S REPORT OF THE CHICAGO CHINESE COMMUNITY'S PATRIOTIC ACTIVITIES TO THE AMBASSADOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On request of Ambassador C. T. Wong, Mr. K. S. Wong, the acting Chinese consul in Chicago, went to Washington, D. C. yesterday. During his brief visit at the Embassy Consul Wong will give an accurate but brief report of his opinion on the present Sino-Japanese, as well as of the Chinese patriotic spirit in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Consul Wong's report contained four vital points:</p>
   <p>1. The determination of our government and its people to fight till the end in the present Sino-Japanese war is prompted by the desire to protect and maintain the independence of the Chinese Republic. We are proving to the world that what China wants is peace, and peace only, in the Far East, and that the only means to achieve this end is for the Japanese to return our land to us. Otherwise, China will and must fight till the end for her liberty and independence.</p>
   <p>2. Since the beginning of the Sino-Japanese war, the entire world is aware of the cruel and merciless tactics used in the invasion of our land. The inhuman practices of the Japanese are, as a matter of fact, endangering the civilization <pb facs="5418479_0347.jpg" n="2"/>of the modern world. With such a vivid knowledge of the situation which will, eventually, concern the rest of the world, how can they afford to take an indifferent attitude?</p>
   <p>3. The united efforts of all our fellow country-men in defending our country is, indeed, symbolic of the spirit of unity, co-operation, and sacrifice. It is upon this spirit, as a foundation, that we will establish a new united China.</p>
   <p>4. Consul Wong, then, gave a detailed report about the Chinese patriotic activities in Chicago, such as the generous contributions in behalf of the defending armies and for relief. He also described how the Americans are extending their sympathies to us spiritually and materially.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
