<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-08-30">Aug. 30, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">The Experience of Chee Hwan-Shiang</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0369</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0369.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-08-30">Aug. 30, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">THE EXPERIENCE OF CHEE HWAN-SHIANG</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The newly organized Chicago Chinese Emergency Relief Association, was the result of Chinese public opinion. Its rules were, for all Chinese under the jurisdiction of the Chinese Consolidated Benevolent Association, to contribute accordingly; those who refuse to contribute will be dealt with severely as violators of the rules. Furthermore, no violators will be protected by any individual or organization, - in other words, they must take the consequences unsparingly.</p>
   <p>We learned that on the 27, while the soliciting squads were making their rounds on the North Side, a certain H. S. Chee, owner of a laundry at 6239 Broadway, refused to contribute, and to make matters worse, he even indulged in uncalled-for verbal arguments with the solicitors, which exasperated all who heard of the incident.</p>
   <p>However, H. S. Chee came to realize, shortly afterward, that it was rather a serious matter to exasperate the public. So he asked Mr. C. C. Chao, a Chinatown merchant, to convey his apology to the Chinese Emergency Relief Society - saying, that he was untactful and careless in his conversation with the solicitors, for which he apologizes wholeheartedly. He pleaded for forgiveness from the officers of the Society and promised a contribution of $100. Mr. H. Moy, general director of the <pb facs="5418479_0370.jpg" n="2"/>Society, realizing that is was purely ignorance on the part of Chee, and with Mr. C. C. Chao's sincereness in entreatment on behalf of Chee, he accepted the apology. It was then, and then only, that the public feeling calmed.</p>
   <p>In spite of this unfortunate incident we must say for Chee that he was brave in his repentance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
