<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chinese Daily Times</title>,
<date when="1935-08-14">Aug. 14, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">All America Chinese Student Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0277</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0277.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chinese Daily Times</title>,
<date when="1935-08-14">Aug. 14, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">ALL AMERICA CHINESE STUDENT ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Arrangements for the coming mass meeting of all Chinese students in the United States is progressing rapidly. Every Chinese student association of the various schools all over the country will each send a delegate to the Chicago meeting which will take place August 30 to September 5, 1935.</p>
   <p>We understand that the Chicago Chinese Student Association due to the coming meeting has been working very hard in renting the meeting hall and selecting the proper temperary resident quarters for the delegates. Such negotiations were properly made.</p>
   <p>They have also decided upon the problems to be discussed during the meeting, and the daily meeting programs were tentatively planned. All student problems will be discussed and investigated by separate delegate groups and for a final discussion and decision during the general meeting. A tentative program was sent to each of the delegates by mail yesterday.</p>
   <p>We learned that the Chicago Chinese fellow country-men are very enthusiastic and sympathetic toward the principle, work, and organization of the All America Chinese <pb facs="5418479_0278.jpg" n="2"/>Student Association. They have been very co-operative with the Association financially.</p>
   <p>Mr. K. L. Lee, president of the Chinese Consolidated Association and Mr. T. Tang, general manager of the Chinese Trade Company have taken upon themselves the obligation of expenses incurred by the student delegates' sight-seeing trips and their noon dinner, to fulfill a rightful duty as hosts and the spirit of sympathy and helpfulness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
