<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chinese Centralist Daily News</title>,
<date when="1937-11-08">Nov. 8, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">The Excellent Record of Chinese Monthly Contributions Toward the War Fund the Average Individual Monthly Contribution Is Above Nine Dollars - Quota the Success and Smoothness in Solicitation Procedure Is in Itself a Record</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0316</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0316.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chinese Centralist Daily News</title>,
<date when="1937-11-08">Nov. 8, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">THE EXCELLENT RECORD OF CHINESE MONTHLY CONTRIBUTIONS TOWARD THE WAR FUND THE AVERAGE INDIVIDUAL MONTHLY CONTRIBUTION IS ABOVE NINE DOLLARS - QUOTA THE SUCCESS AND SMOOTHNESS IN SOLICITATION PROCEDURE IS IN ITSELF A RECORD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ever since the organization of the Chinese Emergency Relief Society, Chinese in Chicago and the adjoining towns have contributed very generously. As a result the total first period contribution has reached a history making record of $370,000.</p>
   <p>Beginning the second period of contributions we have decided upon an unlimited period of monthly solicitations. According to this arrangement we have planned to have various groups of three to four solicitors in each, and they will make a monthly round of all pledgers for contributions.</p>
   <p>The first two groups of solicitors were sent out on November 4, and they returned with cash contributions over $900 - and ten-day pledges of some $800. The next <pb facs="5418479_0317.jpg" n="2"/>day (5) there was only one group out. The group consisted of U. T. Moy, Y. S. Wu, S. L. Wu, S. H. Chien and with Y. F. Moy as the driver. The group started toward the Chicago North-West side. Wherever they stopped they were met with enthusiastic reception and voluntary contributions. As a result of the work of that particular group on that day they realized a total cash contribution of over $700, pledges close to $300, and this is, indeed, and excellent record.</p>
   <p>Since we have decided upon making the second period solicitation on a monthly basis for an unlimited period, we are requesting that all contributors who have contributed $10, for the first period, will set that amount as their monthly contributions.</p>
   <p>The average individual monthly contribution for the first two days' record is over nine dollars.</p>
   <p>If such is the expression of our feelings toward our country then there should not be any difficulty in meeting our national problems.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
