<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-08-25">Aug. 25, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">A Telegram from the North American Chinese Student Association to Washington, D.C.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0210</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0210.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-08-25">Aug. 25, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">A TELEGRAM FROM THE NORTH AMERICAN CHINESE STUDENT ASSOCIATION TO WASHINGTON, D.C.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following is a telegram sent by the North American Chinese Student Association to President Roosevelt and Secretary Hull on August 16.</p>
   <p>The critical condition of our country - China - and its gallant effort in maintaining the territorial rights have acquired the sympathy of the entire world. Your country - The United States of America - was the leader in the Nine-Power Peace Pact. The treaty was to respect Chinese integrity and territorial rights. We know that your country has always maintained a peaceful and friendly relationship with our country. This Association, therefore, requests earnestly of your government to maintain and execute your rightful duty, to warn Japan forcibly, if necessary, of her violation of the Peace Treaty.</p>
   <p>Your country's contemplated Neutrality Act, if passed and executed, will harm Chine immeasurably. Not only will it mean a National catastrophe to our people but it will also increase and encourage the Japanese unmerciful and inhuman desires, which eventually will become a menace to the world peace and harmful to countries other than China.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0211.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For the sake of world peace and the purpose of the League of Nations' existence we ask your government to refrain from taking a neutral stand which subsequently, approves the Japanese unreasonable aggression, but rather to execute your rightful duty in maintaining world peace.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
