<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chinese Centralist Daily News</title>,
<date when="1937-09-24">Sept. 24, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Mr. Frak Moy's Funeral</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0186</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0186.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chinese Centralist Daily News</title>,
<date when="1937-09-24">Sept. 24, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">MR. FRAK MOY'S FUNERAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our general director of the Middle-Western Chinese Civilian Relief Association of Chicago, was taken by death on Sept. 17th, at 6 A.M.</p>
   <p>The On-Liong Association has been in charge of his funeral and the service was held at 2 P.M. yesterday at the Chinese Presbyterian Church on 23rd and Wentworth Avenue.</p>
   <p>The church was filled with funeral flowers. Every space was taken by the hundreds of relatives and friends, that was available, ( including his American friends.)</p>
   <p>The services opened with a prayer by Rev. T. Y. Li, followed by a three minute meditation. Then a song was sung by the chorus and the reading of a brief biography of Mr. Frank Moy by the president of the On-Liong Association, Mr. Moy U-Cho, followed. Again a song of grievance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0187.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then vice-president Mr. Li -Shen-Wei representing the On-Liong Association and the family of the deceased took lead in acknowledging their relatives and friends sympathies.</p>
   <p>The service concluded with Rev. T. Y. Li leading the congregation past the coffin to pay their last respects to the deceased, Mr. Frank Moy.</p>
   <p>Then the immediate relatives of Mr. Moy and the officers of the Qn-Leong Association escorted the coffin to the hearse. The funeral procession was formed with a special police patrol leading the hearse. Following immediately were his American wife, daughter, relatives and intimate friends. Then a long procession of both American and Chinese friends representing all Chinese Associations and clubs etc.</p>
   <p>The prominent men present included Vice-consul Mr. Wang and Mr. H. Moy, representing the On-Liong Association of Washington, D.C.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0188.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After reaching the Chinese cemetery, Rev. Li offered prayer and again relatives and friends paid their final respect by saluting the deceased, before burial.</p>
   <p>The funeral procession numbered thousands and certainly the greatest ever seen.</p>
   <p>We conclude, therefore, that the patriotism of the deceased and services rendered to his fellow-men have obviously commanded the respectful devotion of us all.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
