<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-12-06">Dec. 6, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Financial Factor in Building Aerial Defense - the Enthusiash of Chicago Chinese with Their Contributions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0310</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0310.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-12-06">Dec. 6, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">FINANCIAL FACTOR IN BUILDING AERIAL DEFENSE - THE ENTHUSIASH OF CHICAGO CHINESE WITH THEIR CONTRIBUTIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since the removal of Central Government from Nanking to Chungtu, Canton has practically become the military and financial center of China.</p>
   <p>The recent aerial attacks by our enemy on our Cantonese railways and forts were just the beginning of the Jap's efforts to break our transportation, communication and unity between the North and South. We can readily see, at the same time, that our enemies are determined to invade the southern interior if given the opportunity, due to the lack of improper defense.</p>
   <p>In view of the critical possibilities, the Canton Province has decided upon building up a more powerful aerial defense. It will not only defend the Canton Province but eventually it will be a national defense.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0311.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>So then, the Aerial Defense Fund Association was organized. Oversea Chinese were notified by telegrams asking their support. The aim of the organization is to solicit funds for the purchasing of war-faring planes, subsequently for our aerial defense.</p>
   <p>The Chicago</p>
   <p>Chinese Consolidated Benevolent Association had a special meeting of the Board of Directors on the 3rd., of this month. All directors, realizing the organization's aim in protecting our homes and our country, decided upon a whole-hearted support,</p>
   <p>The plan was to turn over the November contributions to the Chinese Emergency Relief Society, for the aerial defense program only. However, it is optional to the contributor. (That is the contribution will be from their regular monthly pledges which entitles them to the National Bond of the like amount.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0312.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But those who desire to turn their regular November contributions to the aerial defense program will not be given National Bonds in return, as this contribution will be of a voluntary nature rather than an obligatory pledge.)</p>
   <p>As a result, more than $30,000 in Chinese money was realized and forwarded to the Aerial Defense Fund Association in Canton, China. This is the extent of enthusiasm and determination of the Chinese overseas.</p>
   <p>The South China Military Organization and its aerial defense have, long, been one of the important factors in our Central Government's united effort to defend our country from the enemy, - Japan. Just a month ago Mr. S. S. Li was sent from the Central Government Aeronautic School to inspect the Cantonese aerial defense units.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0313.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>While the Canton Province is under the supervision of the Central Government we feel the necessity of cooperating with the Central Government to strengthen our aerial defense, due to the ever increasing crisis. To strengthen our aerial defense power we realize the purchase of more planes is indispensable and then, of course, the anti-air craft guns, machine-guns, bombs, etc., which compose a wholesome aerial defense unit. And finance is the only means to achieve such an end.</p>
   <p>Yes, in order to strengthen our aerial defense we must have your financial aidfinancial aid of all overseas Chinese. Your enthusiasm and whole-hearted generosity will be the only means to express your spirit of patriotism. We hope, then, that all of you fellow country-men will contribute liberally. This will make it possible for us to defend the South successfully. And subsequently it will mean a successful national defense.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
