<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-09-10">Sept. 10, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Chinese Women's Participation in Patriotic Movements</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0116</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0116.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-09-10">Sept. 10, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO CHINESE WOMEN'S PARTICIPATION IN PATRIOTIC MOVEMENTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During these critical moments of national warfare, we fully realize that our duty, to protect our government and its people, rests on the shoulders of every Chinese citizen. Each must do his or her utmost for our country and our people. This is the time sex will not dominate the course of patriotic activities. Women have equal rights of citizenship as men and therefore they share the same rights and responsibilities.</p>
   <p>Miss M. L. Soong, wife of Gen Chiang Kai-Sheik, and Miss T. C. Li, wife of Gen. Feng, and other leading women organized the Women's Consolation Society of the wounded in the Capital. The Society made known the duties of women in times of war. In her public speeches Mrs. Chicang Kai-Sheik once said, "To-day Spanish women are fighting in the front line like the men. During the world war women of all countries helped their countries in gaining an ultimate victory. I say, therefore, my fellow Chinese women, that this is our opportunity to show to the world our patriotic spirit." She also said, "We as women should encourage the men, to let them know that we women have our own methods of giving them our co-operation and support. Bravery of a fighting hero in the front line depends totally on the support behind him."</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0117.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We recall even in history how Miss M. L. Hwa joined the army in place of her father, and how Mrs. C. Li helped her husband in protecting and guarding a city. These are cases known to even women and children. With these famous historic cases well in mind many women have sought to duplicate their fete since the beginning of the Sino-Japanese war. Yes, the number of heroines and female martyrs are increasing as the war goes on. Indeed, they are ready to sacrifice all.</p>
   <p>Now, the oversea Chinese women - although they have not returned to China to participate in action - they certainly have encouraged the men by helping in solicitation of war fund, etc., and at the same time showing the world their patriotic spirit.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Chinese Emergency Relief Society has a squad of female solicitors. We understand they have had splendid success. Through their influence even children have turned in their candy money for contribution towards the war fund. Such is the spirit existing in the minds of our women and children. It's not now much we give but it's how we give that counts.</p>
   <p>Our Chinese women's participation in patriotic activities will not only help the government materially, but they will educate our children and instill in their <pb facs="5418479_0118.jpg" n="3"/>minds a practically natural patriotic instinct because of their close relationships with the children. We can readily realize, now, that our future government rests on the shoulders of our women who are up-bringers of our future leaders and soldiers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
