<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chinese Centralist Daily News</title>,
<date when="1937-09-24">Sept. 24, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Is the American Government Actually Enlightened?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0108</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0108.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chinese Centralist Daily News</title>,
<date when="1937-09-24">Sept. 24, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">IS THE AMERICAN GOVERNMENT ACTUALLY ENLIGHTENED?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The latest American government's attitude toward the Sino-Japanese has two distinctive errors. First, forbidding the transportation of armaments to either China or Japan. Second, the withdrawal of its Ambassador from the so called strongest nation in the world, America- is certainly an embarrasment.</p>
   <p>The editor doesn't care to give such matters further discussion. But since yesterday, the attitude of the American government was suddenly changed. First, the government even dared to warn Japan for bombing Nanking.</p>
   <p>As a violation of peace treaty and human rules. Such a warning was recognized as a "direct hit" at the Japanese government. Second, the acceptance of the American government, the membership to the Geneva conference of Far Eastern problems. The American government has decided to send the Ambassador at Switzerland, as its delegate. We see now, the American government has expressed its co-operation with the League of Nations in <pb facs="5418479_0109.jpg" n="2"/>handling the Far- Eastern problems.</p>
   <p>The reason why Japan has taken advantage so boldly in invading China, was because Japan realized the impossibility of co-operation from the more powerful nations.</p>
   <p>During the Moukden incident, six years ago, the American government warned Japan through its delegate. But England and France did not wish to co-operate with the United States. Instead, they expressed sympathy for the Japanese. The American government naturally did not want to take an active part alone. Subsequently there were no definite steps taken against Japan. But today, the British and French policies have changed. They all realize the cunning scheme and desire of Japan in disturbing the world peace.</p>
   <p>These nations have been anxious in helping us to fight Japan, but more or less feared non-co-operation of the American government.</p>
   <p>Now that the American government has turned from "soft" to "hard" which is <pb facs="5418479_0110.jpg" n="3"/>a good expression of enlightenment, I hope sincerely that the American government will never again indulge in "empty-talk" and vachousness. We hope that the League of Nations will soon engineer definite steps against Japan. When that day comes then the end of Japan is near.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
