<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chinese Daily Times</title>,
<date when="1935-08-13">Aug. 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Marriage Ceremony of Mr. Pang and Miss Wong.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chinese Daily Times</title>,
<date when="1935-08-13">Aug. 13, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">MARRIAGE CEREMONY OF MR. PANG AND MISS WONG.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. F. L. Pang, a Mississippi Chinese merchant, and Mr. C. W. Wong's daughter Miss P. W. Wong were married yesterday at 2 P. M. The wedding ceremony took place at a local hotel on 23rd. Street. It was a grand ceremony with Chinese music. There were over two hundred Chinese and American friends present at the ceremony. Indeed it set a record for Chicago Chinese marriages. Refreshments were served after the ceremony, and it was certainly a joyful occasion.</p>
   <p>All gifts from the bride's relatives and friends were exhibited in the bride's chamber. Most of them were expensive and precious. A banquet of twenty some tables at the Hwayin Restaurant was ready at 5:30 p. m. for all relatives and friends present.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0063.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the conclusion of the banquet Mr. C. H. Pang related a brief biography of the bridegroom and his engagement experience. He was followed with speeches by Mr. K. L. Lee, president of the Chinese Consolidated Association; Mr. C. S. Chen, president of the On Leong Chinese Merchants Accociation; Mr. L. F. Chen, editor in chief of the Chinese Daily Times; and Mr. Y. F. Cho, editor in chief of the San Min Morning Paper. They all spoke of good fortune and offered tremendous applause. The banquet lasted until after 8:00 P. M. It was certainly a flourishing occasion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
