<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-10-11">Oct. 11, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">China Marches Forward</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418479_0326</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-chinese #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418479_0326.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>CHINESE</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>San Min Morning Paper</title>,
<date when="1937-10-11">Oct. 11, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">CHINA MARCHES FORWARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is gratifying to know that since the outbreak of the Sino-Japanese War, world opinion invariably has condemned the Japanese aggression. The Japanese lust for conquest cannot be exterminated by any plea whatsoever.</p>
   <p>Japan asserts that China is not unified. She assumes the self-styled savior role to "free" the Chinese people. However, China has been and is unified. The progress made during the last year is little short of phenomenal. Foreign observers often are amazed at the rapid pace of development.</p>
   <p>According to an American professor, who left China in 1919, "there were less than a thousand miles of motor roads in the whole country. When he returned in 1932, there were over forty-five, thousand miles. Today it is claimed over eighty, thousand miles of highways have been completed."</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0327.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our financial reorganization has been a success. Ever since the Silver Act was passed by the United States, our stock of silver has been depleted by exportation to foreign countries. We faced the danger of national bankruptcy. So on November 3, 1935, we adopted the policy of nationalizing our silver, there by stabilizing our foreign exchange and establishing the Central Reserve System. The tax system has been revised. The stability of the foreign exchange during the recent trying times attest the sound foundation of our financial setup.</p>
   <p>For the last several years, the Ministry of Public Health, has done much to safeguard the health of the citizens. Clinics are opened in different parts of the country, giving medical and sanitary aid. Training classes are conducted to turn out more health officers and public health nurses. They provide, also, mobile units which travel all over the country.</p>
   <p>Realizing that transportation is vital in promoting better living, the Ministry of Railways has completed many important lines. British, French and other credit extensions enable us to start a program of railway construction. Aviation also has made great strides in the last decade. Airlines extend far into the interior.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0328.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The national educational budget has increased five times in the last five years. Certainly, education has helped to bring national consciousness to the masses of the people.</p>
   <p>The government undertakes to supervise and encourage private enterprises and expands government - owned industries. It takes special effort to increase the export of tea, tung oil, silk, and other articles. Improvement in quality is stressed in all cases.</p>
   <p>All in all, the last few years witnessed the unification of China and the authority of the central government extends over all the provinces.</p>
   <p>The Chinese people strive to build a new China. China is on the road to permanent political and economic stability.</p>
   <p>While China is busily engaged in national reconstruction, Japan cast an envious look at our recent accomplishments. Japan hates to see a unified and strong China. In order to carry out her plan of territorial expansion, Japan attacks China while it is weak.</p>
   <pb facs="5418479_0329.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>There would be no war if China were not unified, no war if China were not organized, no war if China were not progressive. We are forced into war. We are fighting a defensive war, a war for freedom, a war for peace.	</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
