<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-09-20">Sept. 20, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">A Teacher's Jubilee</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0094</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0094.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-09-20">Sept. 20, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">A TEACHER'S JUBILEE</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nicolaus Dreher is the enviable man who can look back upon twenty-five years of activity in a field of noble work, the work of a teacher and educator. Mr. Dreher has been the beloved teacher at St. Joseph's parish school since 1862, during which time he has worked untiringly and successfully to educate and prepare young people to become good and useful members of society. In this task he has not failed. To celebrate this jubilee, publicly, the students of Mr. Dreher's class and others, who in years past used to be his students, headed by the Youth's Society of St. Joseph's community, have decided to make a universal celebration. A concert was given, the proceeds of which, with other large contributions of money, was presented to this excellent and highly deserving school master. The concert was at the north side Turn Hall, last night, and the immense attendance showed us the high esteem Mr. Dreher enjoys. Here is a short sketch of Mr. Dreher's career. He first became associated with the just then newly erected school, built by the Benedict Fathers on the corner of Chicago Avenue and Carpenter Streets, and remained there until 1864, when he was chosen as Superintendent for the boys school at St. Joseph's parish school. After Chicago's Great Fire he left for Pekin, Illinois, and established there a German-Catholic parish school. He didn't remain there very long, but returned <pb facs="5418474_12_0095.jpg" n="2"/>to Chicago and became associated with St. Peter's school, corner Clark and Polk Streets, executing his duties there, as teacher, until 1873 when he to take over the management of the new St. Joseph school, then located on Hill and Market Streets. It is there where we find him, today, an untiring worker, assisted by the Sisters of the Order of Benedict. Mr. Dreher was always concerned, not only with the religious life of the students, and the preparation for a successful battle with life, but also in cultivating the German language. There was an improvised open book on the stage of the Turn Hall, composed of roses and other flowers, bearing this inscription in flowers: 1863 - Our Teacher-1887. Arrangements are under way for a reunion of Mr. Dreher's pupils for next Monday night at St. Joseph's school auditorium at Hill and Franklin Streets.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
