<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-09">May 9, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Theodore B. Weber</title><title level="a" type="sub">His Reputation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0132</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0132.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-05-09">May 9, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">THEODORE B. WEBER</title><title level="a" type="sub">His Reputation</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jacob Mueller, former vice-governor of Ohio, pays the following tribute to Mr. Weber. We reprint the account as it appeared in the Waechter Am Erie (Erie Sentinel), as it will be of interest to Chicagoans:</p>
   <p>"The parents of Theodore B. Weber were our neighbors. I went to school with him, up to his confirmation. Weber [Translator's note - he was a Chicagoan according to a previous article, fairly prosperous, etc., bequeathed money for a non-sectarian German high school and later changed his last will], even during early youth showed great ability and proved outstanding in every class. Prior to 1850 he immigrated to America--when he was but sixteen years old. Through diligence, good character, and talent, he was able to make rapid progress, and thus acquired a high business as well as social position. He was regarded as highly intelligent as well as cultured, and above all as a man of philanthropic tendencies; in fact, whenever human need became an issue he gave <pb facs="5418474_12_0133.jpg" n="2"/>wholeheartedly and proved himself to be an ardent friend. He helped his relatives whenever necessary. As a businessman he showed sagacity and scrupulous honesty. His character was above reproach.</p>
   <p>"Among the many people I know there is no one for whom I have a higher regard for integrity and genuine German reliability. He started on the lowest rungs of the ladder, climbing upward until he was remarkably successful. Selfishness and greed never dominated him.</p>
   <p>"It is one of the bewildering facts of life that such a man was slain!"</p>
   <p>J. M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
