<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-07-02">July 2, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Paul Grottkau</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0126</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0126.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1879-07-02">July 2, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">PAUL GROTTKAU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The acknowledged leader of the Socialist Party in the city of Chicago, is Paul Grottkau, a fugitive from Berlin, Germany. He is extreme in his views, narrow, ignorant, and in a measure, shrewd and eloquent. He is a man of much personal magnetism, though cowardly in his instincts and methods.</p>
   <p>Although for many years a resident of Chicago, he does not speak the English language and apparently does not care to learn. He knows little of American institutions, and is an agitator and a revolutionist by instinct and education. He is more to be feared perhaps than any man of his class in Chicago; not because he has the courage to carry out his schemes, but because he has the power to set a movement on foot, which he may not be able to control or stop.</p>
   <p>From Mr. Richard Michaelis, editor of the Neue Freie Presse, a reporter for the Tribune yesterday obtained some interesting facts concerning the insurrectionary plebeian. By trade he is a bricklayer and is now somewhere in the neighborhood of thirty years of age. Some years back, he was picked up by Von Schweiter, one of the greatest socialistic leaders of Berlin, who discovered his ability to speak to the rabble. He trained Grottkau and gave him ideas and topics for the display of his oratory. He became noted and was employed after a while <pb facs="5418474_12_0127.jpg" n="2"/>by the trade unions as an agitator. Von Schweitzer died and Grottkau became more prominent than before. He, in a measure, took the place of his illustrious leader, having some of his ability, but little of his courage. A paper was started in Berlin, called the Freie Presse, and Grottkau was placed in the position of sitz-redacteur, a position not known to American journalism. The person who assumed this place, is the advertised editor of the paper and responsible for its utterances. Men of culture and learning do not like the German jails, and in order that they may escape incarceration, they usually hoist the name some man whom they employ for this purpose, who has no other duty to perform than to go to jail when required. Such were the editorial duties of Herr Paul Grottkau. One day he was wanted by the government for something which had been written and published by the real editor. He became frightened and abandoned his paper, and with the money he had received for the duties he was paid to discharge but failed to, he ran away and came to America. He had no sooner arrived here, than he began to denounce the institutions of which be knew nothing, and to stir up his countrymen to sedition and violence.</p>
   <p>"Has Grottkau a large following in Chicago?", asked the reporter. "Larger than that of all the others combined. Yet he is so ignorant of our institutions that he was recently talking about the election of a postmaster and a collector for the port of Chicago." </p>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0128.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"I see that he does considerable talking. What sort of sentiments does he give utterance to here?" "They are apt to be quite viclent. For instance, at a meeting held last week, he told the crowd he was addressing, that it was their duty to go to the newspaper offices in the evening, and if they found that they were printing any attacks on the red flag, to demand that these articles be suppressed; and if that were not done, to pie the forms and whip the editors. He suggested that they should have a committee to attend to this special business of threshing editors and pieing forms; and that was cheered and applauded. He pointed out a reporter who was present and said, 'Here is one of these hounds who comes to report our meetings, and caricatures our speeches. Perhaps the best thing to do is to wring his neck. He certainly ought to be well whipped.'"</p>
   <p>"You can judge from this instance, the character of this man's addressed. Intelligent Germans know better. Why do they follow him? They have no one to take his place. He has no political wisdom. During the last election, some of the socialistic leaders were purchased for money by the democratic party, and Grottkau did not even know it. What is the reason the Germans leave the republican party and vote the socialist ticket? I will tell you. The Germans acknowledge that the republican party has freed the country from slavery; that it has done more for free labor than the democratic party; that it has done more for the <pb facs="5418474_12_0129.jpg" n="4"/>Germans in America than any other party. Yet they claim that the republican party has tolerated corruption within its own ranks by allowing notorious swindlers to go free. Not only are they allowed to go free, but they are allowed to go into their conventions and to take a prominent part in politics. They allow men like Myers, of the Bee Hive Bank, to walk about the streets unpunished."</p>
   <p>"When the socialist asks why these men are not punished, they are told that there is no law for it. They want to know who is responsible for there not being any law; and they are answered, it is the republican party. Thus they see there is plenty of law to punish a man for stealing a loaf of bread, but no law to punish a man who robs a poor man of the earnings of a lifetime. They think the very fact that the republican party has made no effort to cure these ills, either shows that they are in sympathy with criminals and bank swindlers, or, at least that they don't care to punish them, and that the party has no sympathy with the people."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
