<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-10-07">Oct. 7, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">Farewell!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0246</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0246.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-10-07">Oct. 7, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">FAREWELL!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. R. B. Hoeffgen, founder and part owner of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung, will retire from this newspaper today. He is in need of rest and relaxation, for he has worked diligently for many years.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hoeffgen, a pioneer among Chicago's Germans, may also be called a pioneer of German culture in this great western metropolis; for it was he who presented the city with its first German newspaper. Anyone who has any idea of the difficulties connected with the establishment and management of a German newspaper which has gained ground but very slowly can readily estimate the full amount of labor and energy which must be expended and the many obstacles which must be overcome in order to conduct successfully a German publication in the far West, in a place far out on the prairie, in a city so small and insignificant fourteen years ago that it certainly did not deserve the title "city". However, our departing friend was equal <pb facs="5418474_12_0247.jpg" n="2"/>to the great task, and his perserverance was crowned with success. The modest little paper, which he called into being in a wilderness amid the most trying and discouraging conditions, grew with the city and the German population. It developed into one of the largest German dailies in America, and has attained that influence which every organ of public opinion may acquire if it faithfully endeavors to present the opinion of the majority, and advocates and supports justice and impartiality in all political and social matters.</p>
   <p>We hardly need mention that the number of Mr. Hoeffgen's personal friends, among whom we are happy to be included, is much larger than that of many of the old settlers of the Garden City. His honesty, his sense of justice and goodness, his indefatigable efforts to promote humaneness and freedom, have won for him the respect and good will of all citizens who appreciate these qualities of character. All his friends will regret that he is retiring from public life; but they will also rejoice because his was a successful life and he can now reap the fruits of his labors.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0248.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>So we bid farewell to our old and esteemed friend; we wish and hope that he will have the satisfaction of seeing his handiwork continue to grow and serve its purpose: to promote culture, justice, and liberty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
