<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1881-01-17">Jan. 17, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Hans Haerting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1881-01-17">Jan. 17, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">HANS HAERTING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are many in Chicago who will deeply regret to learn of the death of the genial, good-hearted Hans Haerting, a talented German journalist who was prominently identified with local politics as a Democrat, and who latterly occupied the position of secretary of the Fire Department. His death occurred last evening at a quarter of seven o'clock, in his room on the south-east corner of North Clark and Illinois streets, his brother Carl and a few friends being at his bedside during his last hours.</p>
   <p>During the canvass preceding the last election, Mr. Haerting contracted a severe cold, which he did not pay much heed to, and on the 6th inst., he was compelled to take to his bed with an attack of erysipelas. Dr. Henrotin was called and prescribed for him, and he showed signs of a speedy recovery until yesterday afternoon, when he became unconscious. Dr. Carlson was called in, and with Dr. Henrotin, everything was done that medical skill could devise: but the patient sank rapidly, the erysipelas having extended to the brain and caused inflamation, that resulted in death at the time above stated.</p>
   <p>In 1866, his parents emigrated to America and took up their home in Milwaukee, where Hans, then a bright and ambitious young man, obtained a position on the Herald as a reporter. After brief experience, he became city editor of the <pb facs="5418474_12_0114.jpg" n="2"/>Milwaukee Banner and Volksfreund, a place that he filled satisfactorily and ably.</p>
   <p>In 1872, he came to Chicago to assume the editorial chair on the Union, a German daily newspaper, serving in that position for a short time until the Union ceased to exist. He was next installed as a correspondent for the leading German daily of Chicago, the Illinois Staats-Zeitung. In 1876, he was chosen for the chief editorship of the National Democrat, a German daily newspaper that started out under favorable auspices, but was short-lived. Later, he was editor of the Neue Freie Presse, and also of the Volksfreund.</p>
   <p>Having always taken an active part in politics, acting uniformly and consistently with the democracy, Mr. Haerting was rewarded for his political services; and because of his fitness for the position, by the appointment as secretary of the Fire Department, serving with fidelity and ability up to the time of his last illness.</p>
   <p>Thus has ended a brief life, eventful and full of promise for the future. All who knew Hans Haerting - and there were many - liked him for his geniality, his liberality, and for his many excellencies.</p>
   <p>The dead journalist leaves a father at Cleveland, a brother in New York, and one <pb facs="5418474_12_0115.jpg" n="3"/>here.</p>
   <p>Due notice of the funeral will be given later.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
