<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-04-01">Apr. 1, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Ernst Schnidt and His Chief Supporters</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-04-01">Apr. 1, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">DR. ERNST SCHNIDT AND HIS CHIEF SUPPORTERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With all due respect to Ernst Schmidt as a doctor and as an individual, we are wondering whether the businessmen and other respectable citizens who favor him, have considered his supporters.</p>
   <p>Obviously, the gentlemen who are in favor of voting for Schmidt have not read the German paper Arbeiter (Worker), the party organ which espouses his cause. In this election campaign, the newspaper is resorting to the vilest attacks upon anyone who is in opposition, to unbridled agitation against the owning class, and to outrageous threats against those who intend to vote for a candidate other than Schmidt. At the same time, Arbeiter is extolling the virtues of communism. That this most dangerous element of society will regard the triumph as its own, instead of Dr. Schmidt's, seems to have been lost sight of by the voters; otherwise they could not be so deluded as to vote for Dr. Schmidt, merely to express a personal liking.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0141.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Anyone who has the real interests of Dr. Schmidt at heart, will vote against him, in order to liberate him from the association of people whose despicable conduct he must secretly abhor.</p>
   <p>Several German Citizens.</p>
   <p>We ask that our names be withheld. As nonpoliticians we cannot be expected to expose ourselves and our families to the vilification of a scurrilous press.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
