<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-03-20">Mar. 20, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">Sigmund Selig</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0083</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0083.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1) (Jewish)</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-03-20">Mar. 20, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">SIGMUND SELIG</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sigmund Selig, justly the favorite actor and director, will celebrate his thirtieth anniversary next Sunday.</p>
   <p>It is impossible to express in a few work what it means to be an untiring and Getermined actor for the German dramatic art for thirty years, under conditions which create new difficulties continually. But in spite of all the unfavorable circumstances, Mr. Selig has kept at it, these many years, and we do not exaggerate, if we recognize his as one of the chief supports of the German theater. During the last few years he has enjoyed the satisfaction of seeing the German theater in Chicago prosper under his leadership, and dramatic art find response, again, in the hearts of the Germans.</p>
   <p>Mr. Selig is closely associated with German dramatic art in Chicago. As a young man of eighteen years he made his first attempt to act on the stage in a small theater on the West Side, which was then under the management of Deutsch and Studle. This was in 1858.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0084.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The directors of the theater immediately recognizied the dormant talents for acting in the young artist, so that he was permitted to take part in the plays presented every Sunday. Through persistent effort he soon became an accomplished actor and in 1839 he was engaged as juvenile comedian by the director.of the regular German theater, which was then in the German House, located at the corner of Indiana Avenue and Wells Street. Here he remained two years, and was always a welcome and favorite player. After an absence of five years while playing in New York and Philadelphia, he returned to Chicago and was received with remarkable enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>Again he visited Chicago in 1872, where he played with the Globe Theater under G. Ostermann. In 1876 Director Collyer engaged him as first comedian for the city theater in Milwaukee, where he remained for six years, and where he celebrated his twentieth anniversary as an actor.</p>
   <p>In 1886 he returned to Chicago where he has been engaged eversince, partly as actor but, principally, as theater manager.</p>
   <p>Mr. Selig's talents for art comes to full expression in the brilliant roles. He has been nearly unexcelled in the presentation of Jewish types, and whenever he <pb facs="5418474_12_0085.jpg" n="3"/>announced "One of our People", as a benefit performance, he could expect with certainty that the house would be crowded. He also attained considerable success as a musical comedian.</p>
   <p>We do not entertain the least doubts that his performance will be a powerful attraction, and, that he still retains the ability to electrify an audience, although he has been strenuously active for thirty years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
