<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-09-26">Sept. 26, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">John P. Altgeld</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0100</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0100.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1886-09-26">Sept. 26, 1886</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN P. ALTGELD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Local News, a newspaper particularly read in law circles, published September 18th, the following lines about John P. Altgeld.</p>
   <p>John P. Altgeld, Democratic candidate for Superior Judge, is known as a man of honor and is a member of the Chicago Bar Association. He was born 1847 in Germany, but came as a child with his parents to the United States, where they settled in Ohio. His father saved enough through hard work to buy himself a small farm. The young Altgeld had no opportunity to go to a public school, but was instructed in the evening by his father and added considerably to his knowledge by his own study.</p>
   <p>In the year 1864 when only 17 years old, John P. Altgeld, joined the Union Army and served during six months in the garrison at Washington. For several weeks he also participated in the campaign on the St. James River. In the year 1867 he became a teacher and two years later went to Savannah, Mo., <pb facs="5418474_12_0101.jpg" n="2"/>where in 1871 he was admitted to the bar as a lawyer and became States Attorney the same year.</p>
   <p>Rejecting a reelection in the same town the following year he was elected States Attorney of Andrew County, Mo., in 1874.</p>
   <p>John P. Altgeld came to Chicago in 1875, where he became a successful as a lawyer. He is a good orator and a popular man. If Mr. Altgeld is elected, he will be the first German judge of a Superior Court in this county. Mr. Altgeld never had held public office before and made his first political appearance two years ago as a Democratic candidate against representative for Congress Adams. The general opinion is that John P. Altgeld is the right man for the important position of Superior Court Judge.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
