<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-19">July 19, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Resignation of Paul Grottkau</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0130</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0130.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-07-19">July 19, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">RESIGNATION OF PAUL GROTTKAU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The undersigned is resigning from editing of the "Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung" the "Fackel" and the "Vorbote."</p>
   <p>Reasons: In the presence of the Managing Officials of the "Socialistic Publishing Society" one of this Society's men reproached me: That my activity is the ruin of the aforementioned papers of which I have been the editor. 2. It was insisted that I was not competent and displace better elements. 3. It was further insisted, that my work was not efficient and has not been in proportion to my salary, and 4. I have been called a vagabond.</p>
   <p>For all this I ask of the Management an explanation, whether they have entrusted a vagabond with the editing of those newspapers and if not, this insult should be repelled as a defamation and explained, that I have in every repect fulfilled my duty, defended Socialistic Principles, and through my activity, these newspapers, whose Editor, I have been, not only promoted but, <pb facs="5418474_12_0131.jpg" n="2"/>to a certain extent made their existence possible.</p>
   <p>The management did not protect me against the defamation mentioned, although only one of the proposed explanations would have sufficied. With phrases, that the management can not interfere with private disagreements, they would like to close this affair, After listening to such defamations, it was to be expected, that an explanation would follow. But this did not take place. In the interest of the Party and in my own defense as to my spotless past, I am resigning as Editor of these newspapers.</p>
   <p>To the "Solialistic Publishing Society", I have sold my work and activities, but not my honor. Dishonesty is asked of me, but I do not qualify for it. I am satisfied to say, that the "Socialistic Labor Party " and the proletarian emancipation studies I have served well. This declaration I owed to my honor, to the"Socialistic- Labor Party" and to the readers of the "Arbeiter Zeitung", "Die Fackel" and "Vorbote."</p>
   <p>Paul Grottkau</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
