<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-08-17">August 17, 1877</date><title level="a">Wilhelm Vocke's Answer to the "Times"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0122</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0122.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-08-17">August 17, 1877</date><title level="a">WILHELM VOCKE'S ANSWER TO THE "TIMES"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Publisher of the "Times".</p>
   <p>In last Wednesday's issue of the Times appeared an item discussing my appointment as a member of the Board of Education. In this article my character is somewhat attacked, and to correct this error, I feel the necessity of writing to you. You stated that I, as the trustee of the bankrupt Germania Insurance Company, did not do the right thing as far as the creditors were concerned when I (supposedly) disposed of Mr. Hesing's exchange at a price far below their value, and those of Mr. Schintz for twenty-five cents on the dollar. At the creditors' meeting of the Company in April 1873, the Hesing case has been thoroughly discussed and all those prsent at the meeting approved the court's action as well as mine....What an empty phrase to say that I sold Mr. Schintz's exchange bills for twenty-five cents on the dollar, while I could have sold them for the full price....Due to my efforts Mr. Schintz received seventy-five percent on the dollar. The statement that the Court disapproved this action is also wrong. You named five aldermen who were opposed to my appointment to the School Board, because I was supposedly not honest in my dealings with the creditors of the bankrupt company and no aldermen of a German ward would dare to vote <pb facs="5418474_12_0123.jpg" n="2"/>for me; this is not so either, because it is simply a case of personal enmity....My appointment to the School Board is not based on any political speculations.... I did not seek this nomination, it was offered to me four years ago by Mayor Medill, but I did not accept the offer for various reasons....I was urged by my friends this year again to accept the nomination if offered to me....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
