<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-07-25">July 25, 1891</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0053</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0053.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-07-25">July 25, 1891</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At one o'clock this morning the telegraphic report reached us from Cadowa, Silesia, Germany, that our great colleague and friend, Hermann Raster died. His loving and faithful family was at his bed side. His long illness caused much suffering.</p>
   <p>H. Raster was born in Raguh, Germany, May 6, 1827..... He acquired thorough knowledge of the English language as a young boy and mastered it as well as the German..... At the universities of Berlin and Leipzig he studied philosophy, history, and philology. It was here that his tendencies toward politics and journalism was aroused and he arranged his studies accordingly.</p>
   <p>The young man of twenty-one was deeply affected by the revolution of 1848. He was a pioneer in a progressive Liberal Party, and, in his writings and pamphlets he demonstrated proficiency with the pen.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0054.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Later, the revolutionists were persecuted, and Raster was compelled to emigrate. He chose the United States, and came here with the determination to become a good citizen of the republic, and to establish a home of his own....</p>
   <p>A short time after, he became editor of the (German) Evening Newspaper in New York. Through his brilliant articles, and attractive arrangements of the reading matter, he soon gained a good reputation. At that time he became a reformer of the German-American Press, by fighting for a better style and against the use of foreign words.</p>
   <p>When the Republican Party was organized he took part with ardent zeal and enthusiasm, and although he had shortly before received his citizenship papers, he was made an elector at the presidential election in 1856. This proves his great popularity even at that time.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0055.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>During the Civil war he was the New York correspondent for two of the most outstanding German newspapers. In his reports and letters he stood definitely and with convincing power on the side of the Union, thereby creating a friendly attitude toward the union in Germany, which favored the acceptance of her bonds.....</p>
   <p>In 1867 Raster was called by A. C. Hesing to become the chief editor of the Illinois Staats Zeitung, which opened for him a tremendous field of activity. The Staats Zeitung was then one of the largest German newspapers. He quickly became familiar with the public life of the West, and not only achieved greatness in journalism in western journalism, but he also became quite eminent in national politics.....</p>
   <p>As a member of the Republican National convention at Philadelphia in 1872, he was the author of that famous paragraph 16 of the Republican platform, which led the party at that time towards liberal tendencies in regard to the matter of alcoholic drinks.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0056.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As a member of the first Board of Directors of the Public Library in Chicago, Raster attained also great merits! He contributed much to a practical and sound policy and it therefore rapidly became a hugh success. Not only the English reading public benefitted, but he saw to it that all Chicago's citizens could read the chief treasures of their literature in their mother tongue.....</p>
   <p>During the last years he was also a member of the directors of the School Board in Cook County. In this capacity he fought for a sensible method of instruction.</p>
   <p>His greatness, however, was most apparent in his German American journalistic activity. Not only his varied and broad knowledge, but also his impressive, overwhelming, and often humorous style of writing made him famous. He also contributed considerably to the English American literature, and was a co-laborer of the first edition of Appleton's Encyclopedia.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0057.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>About one year ago he went to Germany to seek relief for his illness. With forebodings of death he visited the grave of his parents at Zerbst to secure there a place of rest for himself.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
