<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-10-23">October 23, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">The Municipal Election</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0231</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0231.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-10-23">October 23, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">THE MUNICIPAL ELECTION</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For Mayor: Henry Greenebaum - so writes the Chicago Tribune, and thereby utters a thought of further bearing than it, itself, perhaps realizes. The election in this moment of a German banker as Mayor may be worth millions to the city. It is the surest, most infallible way to inspire German capital with confidence in Chicago and to attract large loans. That the city, in the time of its greatest need calls a German business man to its helm - a man whose energy is as firm as steel, whose probity is as true as gold - will be taken as a pledge the world over, that our horrible calamity has had a purifying influence also on our local politics.</p>
   <p>Henry Greenebaum is in the best sense of the word a self-made man - since his boyhood, with all his planning and doing, rooted in Chicago. He is a Chicagoan with enthusiams. He is one of the best representatives of the indefatigable spirit of enterprise, the persevering energy and the noble unselfishness that have made Chicago great... To be Mayor during the next two years, means to have a better chance to perpetuate one's name in national history, than a Senator or State Governor usually has. And Henry Greenebaum would be the man to take advantage of this chance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0232.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The proposal of the Tribune, to which all Republican papers (we have reason to believe, will assent) shows at the same time in what way the city can be preserved from being plunged from its present calamity directly into the hodge podge of party politics. Both parties should come to an agreement about an electoral ticket comprising the most capable and most honorable members of both - a ticket that could be elected without quarrel, nor opposition. The Republican Greenebaum as Mayor, the Democrat Gahl as Treasurer...in such a way a list of candidates can be constructed with which every citizen can be satisfied, so that an opposing list does not need to appear at all.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
