<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-10-17">October 17th, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">"The Cunning Banker before the Congressional Committee."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0120</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0120.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-10-17">October 17th, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">"The Cunning Banker Before The Congressional Committee."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Committee appointed by Congress, to investigate the affairs of the "German National Bank" of which Henry Greenebaum, the former President has been accused of swindling, has begun its activities to-day. The investigation is conducted by Messrs. Buckner, Price and Lounsbury. According to instructions, the committee's duty is to investigate what has really taken place, since the liquidation of the bank, and the principal point for this, has been furnished by the "Arbeiter Zeitung" in its completely published report of the Bank Inspector Washburn. At the Organization Committee's advice, Chairman Buckner expressed himself to the effect, that the investigation is limited to clearing up Washburn's report, and possibly find clues for further proceedings.</p>
   <p>At the opening of the afternoon session were, Lawyer Jussen, Counsel for the bank, Lawyer Flower and Henry Greenebaum present. The first witness called by Mr. Jussen, was George B. Weber, who took the stand for his absent brother and, who has been fimiliar with the bank's business, before it failed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0121.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>According to his report, he had questioned Mr. Greenbaum in November, 1877, then President of the Bank, on various matters, and received a written reply stating that the bank is not in a position to discount notes, but that depositors have nothing to fear and that the value of a share is still 90 per cent. The witness was also present at a director's meeting at which it was suggested, to liquidate the bank, and thus, the share-holders could at least realize 80 cents on a dollar. A committee has been appointed for the prodeedings of the liquidation, with Henry Greenebaum at the head of it. The witness could not say with certainty, whether the liquidation committee has doctored the bank's securities, but has heard that a private request by Greenebaum to Franz Arnold, for information about the activitied of the bank has been advised, although Arnold has been denying, owing anything to the bank. Lawyer Jussen explained to the committee, the well-known transaction with the $20,000 note, drawn by Mr. Clay of New York, which was indorsed by Tom Hoyne and John Herting, and which has been protested later on. Lawyer Jussen touvhed on the bank's connection with different branches of Greenebaum's private businesses and stated, that those have received $25,000 from the bank between December 1st and December 3rd, 1877 and on December 4th the bank was declared insolvent. The committee will meet to-morrow again.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
