<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1885-12-15">December 15, 1885</date>.
<title level="a">William Floto</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0103</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0103.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1885-12-15">December 15, 1885</date>.
<title level="a">WILLIAM FLOTO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>William Floto known and esteemed by his fellow citizens of German extraction died yesterday, victim of a heart attack. William Floto was a book merchant and also a member of the School Board. He was born in Kassel in the year 1828, where he learned the watch making trade. He came to America when 18 years old and settled in New York, but could not resist his wanderlust for very long and went to California and from there to South America. Not finding Eldorado there, he disappointedly returned to the United States and went to Cincinnati where he married. Even then he could not settle down, and chose shortly before the outbreak of the Civil War, New Orleans as a future field for his activities, There he established a commission business under the name of Floto &amp; Marmet. When war broke out between the North and South he, although a faithful Unionist was forced into the rebel ranks and attached as commander of the citizens' guard. But as soon as New Orleans was victorious against the Federal troops be gathered his few belongings which had not been confiscated, and returned at Cincinnati, being for a short time, in command of a regiment, just when General Bragg of the South was threatening Cincinnati. Mr. Floto came to Chicago in 1863 opening a grocery store at Clark and Madison Streets. In 1867 he became President of the "Chicago Lithographical Company" under the firm name of Floto, Kurz, &amp; Co. functioning in <pb facs="5418474_12_0104.jpg" n="2"/>this capacity until the great fire of Chicago when, discouraged by the loss of his possessions, he returned to Cincinnati. He was back in Chicago in 1873 and at that time became business manager for the Scipp Brewery. Two years later he founded the book store of Floto and Meininger, which business he gave up about three years ago when he became an associate of Mr. Congdon of the shoe and boot whole-sale house. But he again became interested in another undertaking and founded, in company with Mr. Heinrichs, a similar store on Adams and Market Streets. Years ago Mr. Floto played an important part as a Republican in the politics of the 18th ward, in spite of which he was appointed as member of the School Board by Democratic Mayor Harrison in 1881. Mr. Floto was a member of the "Germania Male Chorus" of which he was President several times, the "Concordia Lodge" of the Masons, the "Chicago Sharp Shooting Society" and the "Templar Knights".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
