<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-08-17">Aug. 17, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">A Solemn Festival in Commemoration of H. Raster Arranged by the German Press Club of Chicago</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0037</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0037.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-08-17">Aug. 17, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">A SOLEMN FESTIVAL IN COMMEMORATION OF H. RASTER ARRANGED BY THE GERMAN PRESS CLUB OF CHICAGO</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As soon as the news of Raster's death reached us, a desire was manifested not only by his intimate friends and colleagues, but also by the people in general, to honor the memory of this great man by a public demonstration, and to express our deep sorrow for the overwhelming loss caused in our midst by his departure from this life....Raster was well known, not only in Chicago, but throughout the whole country....</p>
   <p>The commemoration of yesterday, arranged by the German Press Club of Chicago, was uplifting and beautiful.... A day before the actual affair the seats in McVicker's theater were sold out.... The president of the German Press Club, Mr. Th. Janssen, stepped upon the stage where the singers and speakers were seated in a half circle and addressed the audience as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0038.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"...The German Press Club has chosen one of Raster's close friends, Mr. J. Rosenthal, to preside over this meeting, and I have the honor to introduce him."</p>
   <p>Mr. Rosenthal delivered the following address: "Ladies and Gentlemen! Due to the reverent action of the German Press Club.... an opportunity is presented to us, which we have greatly desired, namely, to express publicly our admiration and respect for the deceased. Among the thousands of brave and noble people, who are passing daily into the other world, there are few who die serving their fellow men and whose departure is deeply felt for a long time by a great many people. Our deceased is one of those few. Through his incorruptible character in all walks and circumstances of life he compelled the respect of even his opponents. A deep sense of justice and morality penetrated his being, and combined with it he possessed a remarkable clear understanding, and an ability to express his view points originally and precisely. He was a fearless opponent of all evils, of destructive and ugly things, of all pretensions, frauds, and affectations in state and society, by <pb facs="5418474_12_0039.jpg" n="3"/>high and low; among Germans, as well as among others; among religionists as well as among agnostics. But few have been his equal in mastering the complete and vigorous treasure of the German language, and in the skilled and adept use of it.....No other man in this country was as able as he to show us the beauty, the fullness and vigor of our mother tongue, and to stimulate us daily with new love and admiration for the same.</p>
   <p>His political, economic, and social writings were all from the same cast, taken from life, and meant for the living, founded upon keen and penetrating observation for many years in the old, as well as in the new world. He was well versed in the ancient and the modern literature, well acquainted with the manifold systems of science, philosophy and pedagogy, and no dogmatical metaphysical, and speculative thinking could confuse his head. His mental discipline and training in thought processes from his youth on kept his mind perfectly clear and calm. His writing and his speeches were fresh, original, clear, energetic, and intelligent; when necessary, accompanied with cutting remarks or well pointed humor. He was not only a man of distinction and importance, but <pb facs="5418474_12_0040.jpg" n="4"/>also a singularly affectionate man....These merits alone are sufficient to secure for him an abiding place in the hearts of our people. As much as it was in his power he enlightened us during a time when confusion prevailed about the cardinal problems of the day, when men were striving almost exclusively after material gains; he taught us to think independently of party currents or deep rooted prejudices about the tendencies and weaknesses of our social and political systems. He instructed and trained us to accurate thinking and just actions in public affairs.</p>
   <p>H. Raster was a real, genuine German American citizen. His whole sturdy nature was saturated with German traits, morals, and discipline. He clearly recognized the importance of German cultural methods and elements for the ethical elevation of the American people, for its effects upon training and culture of the mind. He lifted the standard for those cultural elements with the courage of his own conviction; and what a powerful opponent against our enemies, narrow mindedness and stupidity, he was! Having a thorough knowledge <pb facs="5418474_12_0041.jpg" n="5"/>of American life and American institutions, he was able to defend his stand point without being unfair and intolerant toward his antagonists. Where ever he appeared, he was fully recognized and respected....The speaker then introduced the editor in chief of the Westlichen Post of St. Louis, Mr. Emil Prectorius.... Upon the conclusion of Prectorius" speech, members of various men's choirs under the direction of H. Balatka rendered the song of Uhland, "Unter allen Wipfeln ist Ruh" (Restful quietness under tree tops). Then followed Mr. Thomas B. Bryan, Vice President of the World's Fair, who spoke in commemoration of the dead.... Joseph Bruncker was the next German speaker at this occasion....</p>
   <p>After the orchestra played Beethoven's Funeral March, Mr. L. Laflin Mills stepped before the audience to speak words of farewell in honor of the deceased....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0042.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Again the choirs rendered a German song, and following this several resolutions in memoriam of Raster were read by E. Hoechster. These resolutions were sent in by the German Press Clubs of Chicago, St. Louis, Cincinnati, and by a German newspaper in Baltimore....The whole affair was in every detail uplifting and dignified... The songs, so excellently rendered by the men's choirs, made a marvelous impression upon the audience.... It was a genuine and ideally German commemoration festival, celebrated by human beings who had come together to pay their tribute of thanks and admiration to their departed friend and great champion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
