<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-08-16">August 16, 1877</date><title level="a">Hesing and the Workers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0153</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0153.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1877-08-16">August 16, 1877</date><title level="a">HESING AND THE WORKERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Schneider's organ, the Abendblatt, attacks Mr. Hesing for a remark published in yesterday's Staats Zeitung in connection with Mr. Hesing's activities in favor of working people. It would be well for Mr. Schneider, who knows the history of Chicago as well as Mr. Hesing does, to search his memory. He will thus find that Mr. Hesing has every right to pride himself for his activities in behalf of working people. About twenty years ago a proposition worked out by Mr. Hesing, was accepted, to contact the legislature for a new law by which the wage worker would be protected against attachments up to the sum of $25.00, but that their tools should be altogether free from attachment. This proposal was accepted by the Republican Convention, whereupon Mr. Hesing spent all of the following winter in Springfield, and succeeded in his efforts in behalf of the working people. Mr. Schneider will also remember that at the time when the eight hour work day was a matter of discussion by labor, Mr. Hesing again went to Springfield and induced the delegation from Cook County to endorse <pb facs="5418474_12_0154.jpg" n="2"/>this law unanimously, which with the support it had, was accepted. It was also Mr. Hesing who in the year 1864 by request of a labor committee, aroused late at night N. B. Judd, then candidate for Congress, brought him to the office of the Workingmen's Advocate and induced him to pledge his support to the eight hour working day, a promise which as everybody knows, Mr. Judd has faithfully kept. He submitted the proposal to Congress and devoted all his activities to this worthy cause until it was pronounced a law. The eight hour system went into effect in all Government workshops.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
