<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-09-18">Sept. 18, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Lorenz Brentano Died</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_12_0046</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0046.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-09-18">Sept. 18, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">LORENZ BRENTANO DIED</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lorenz Brentano, at one time one of the most famous Germans, and German-Americans, died here last night at the age of 78 years.</p>
   <p>He was born in Mannheim, Germany, and studied jurisprudence at the universities of Heidelberg and Freiburg. As an excellent jurist he soon gained the respect and esteem of people, and became one of the most outstanding members of the House of Commons of the Grand Duchy of Baden, where he belonged to the Opposition Party, fighting for a free and united Germany....</p>
   <p>In 1850 he started a new life in the United States. At first he was the publisher of a country paper, "The Lighthouse at Pottsville, Pennsylvania, but his articles against slavery enraged the old German Democrats there. He left therefore, and went to Michigan, where he purchased a farm near Kalamazoo, and remained there the following years.</p>
   <p>At the time the Douglas Bill created the movement for liberty, Brentano again appeared in public life. In 1859 he became one of the editors of the Illinois Staats Zeitung, and in the spring of 1862 he became one of its owners and editor <pb facs="5418474_12_0047.jpg" n="2"/>in chief. In this position he rendered the cause of the union during the Civil War very valuable services. He also was a member of the Illinois State Legislature at this time.</p>
   <p>At the close of the Civil War he was elected a member of the Chicago School Board, and later became its chairman. In this capacity he, with his colleague, H. Felsenthal, contributed his greatest efforts towards the introduction of instruction in German in our public schools.</p>
   <p>He sold his share of the Illinois Staats Zeitung in 1867 to A. C. Hesing and in 1869 he went to Europe, where he represented the just cause of the U. S. during the court proceedings at Gent about the Alabama question.</p>
   <p>President Grant appointed Brentano in 1872 as consul of the United States at Dresden, Germany. After his return to the United States he was elected to Congress....</p>
   <p>At a later period he left the Republican Party and became an independent Democrat....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_12_0048.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Among his survivors are his widow, his son, Theodore Brentano, the present Judge of the Superior Court, his daughter, and a step daughter....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
