<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-03-12">Mar. 12, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Student Group Visits Mexican Colony</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0133</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0133.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-03-12">Mar. 12, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">STUDENT GROUP VISITS MEXICAN COLONY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A group of students from Northwestern University, interested in the study of the customs and culture of the Mexicans, has planned an observation tour of the commercial and social centers of our colony in Chicago, This tour has been planned for March 12.</p>
   <p>Without doubt some of our readers will remember that in years past this same group has visited us, having been much impressed by our educational, social and artistic progress.</p>
   <p>Dr. Frank Beck, in cooperation with Reverend William O'Neill has prepared a magnificient cultural program which has excellent features. Some of the numbers are:</p>
   <p>A discussion concerning the Mexicans in Chicago, by Mr. Robert Jones and Mr. A. Wilson. A moving picture of the Archaeology and the Architecture of Mexico, explained in detail by Mr. Joseph O. Valesco.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0134.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Well known artists of our Colony will take part in the affair. Outstanding among them are Salvador Mendoza, Leopoldo Escobarete, and the famous Tipica Morales.</p>
   <p>Reverend William O'Neill will function as master of ceremonies. He will also deliver a constructive lecture. The dinner which will be served has been prepared by the women of the Good Pastor Society, and will take place in the Mexican Social Center located on the corner of Maxwell and Newberry Streets, at 6 p.m.</p>
   <p>The Honorable Consul of Mexico, Mr. Rafael Aveleyra, will give a lecture in which he will discuss affairs of great interest.</p>
   <p>There can be no doubt that Dr. Beck's idea of organizing events of this character is commendable. In this way foreigners will come to know and understand us better and be able to appreciate the importance of a people still so little known. The admittance fee is seventy five cents.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
