<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Ideal Mexicano</title>, Vol IV. No 4.
<date when="1936-11-01">Nov. 1, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Msgr. Fulton Sheen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0197</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0197.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Ideal Mexicano</title>, Vol IV. No 4.
<date when="1936-11-01">Nov. 1, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">MSGR. FULTON SHEEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Msgr. Fulton Sheen, a notable professor in sociology of the Catholic University in Washington, said: "We must go to the poor, the unemployed and form a Christian Proletariat as they (the Communists) have formed the Communist Proletariat. "Contraria Contrarlis Curantur," a Latin adage says, that the contrary things can be cured with those which are contrary also. Christianism and Communism are in itself antagonistic to each other, thus where one exists, the other cannot exist. The Christian Proletarian should be a group whose members have acknowledged through rational analyses that it is impossible to have an economic and material equality. Since all the people cannot produce the same, they can not possess the same. Even though the impossible should occur at a given moment, not all the people would be able to keep it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0198.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Some because of larger families, others due to a free expenditure on vice, or ill adminstration. However, there are many inevitable differences in production, Therefore, the Communist equality is not only an awkard chimera, but also an unjustified system. The Communist Proletariat is, in the contrary, the conglomeration of workers who have been seduced and deceived through false promises, which is an unjust impossibility as we have demonstrated above.</p>
   <p>To reach that stage, they do not stop before any kind of crimes, robberies, assasinations etc. Under such circumstances peace and tranquillity become impossible, and thereby also the study to progress and happiness. Communism, far from being the welfare of the people, breeds misfortune instead of progress; standstill or retrospection; and instead of morality, corruption and crime.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
