<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Liberal</title>, Vol I. No 11.
<date when="1933-09-16">September 16, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The Queen Contest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0452</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0452.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Liberal</title>, Vol I. No 11.
<date when="1933-09-16">September 16, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE QUEEN CONTEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What happened to the Queen? This is the question that most people ask? It seemed that this year that a Century of Progress is taken place, we the Mexicans in Chicago would be ready to show the progress of one decade, a real progress of unit and brotherhood by celebrating our "Independence Day" as members of one family and as sons of one Mother. But all looks just the opposite, because it ratifies the old adage: That which has a bad start, invariable has a bad end. This is what we believe happened however, we do not know whether there were any bases in the contest,or there were some bases but no contest. It is evident that the Patriotic Committee from its very beginning was badly organized and in the process our nationality had mixed themselves in something which was purely a matter for us to decide.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0453.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The object of the contest in 1933 was to elect the most popular girl in the colony to be the Queen of the Fiesta. The girl who could get the most votes would become Queen. The votes were on sale at one cent each and part of the money from the votes was to be spent for the Queen's and princesses costumes. All the contestants who were not elected to Queen, would automatically become Princesses. However, this contest caused considerable disturbance among the various groups who sponsored and had candidates in the competition. In virtue of this fact the Patriotic Committee decided to cancel the Queen proposition.</p>
   <p>The festival took place in the Ashland Auditorium with an attendance of more than five thousands Mexicans and about five hundred Americans. Among the speakers was the American philospher Mr. Carlston, who discusses the news with his friend Nick over W. A. A. F. Radio Station. Many other prominent Americans were present at this festival. The Mexican Consul and other officials attended and remained during the civic and artistic part of the program.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
