<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-04-29">Apr. 29, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A New Brigade of La Cruz Azul Mexicana Will Be Built in South Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0729</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0729.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-04-29">Apr. 29, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW BRIGADE OF LA CRUZ AZUL MEXICANA WILL BE BUILT IN SOUTH CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On April 24th, at 8:30 p. m. the first meeting of the commission which is to organize a new auxilliary of the Cruz Azul Mexicana (Mexican Blue Cross) took place in that locality. The meeting was presided over by the initiator of that idea, Dr. Oscar G. Carrera, because the Mexican Consul was not able to attend. The object of the meeting was to elect an organizing committee to begin the preliminary work of establishing a new auxiliary. The following persons were elected: Dr. Oscar G. Carrera, president; Jana R. de Pena, secretary; C. Roberts, treasurer; Mrs. Carlota Gonzalez, Eva A. de Carrera and Mr. J. Pena were elected as assistant officers.</p>
   <p>According to the facts which we have been able to obtain, another meeting has been scheduled for next week when the Board of Directors which is to govern the destinies of this institution will be elected.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0730.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Oscar G. Carrera, the initiator of the idea, emphasized the fact, that the unanimous cooperation of the Mexican colony of South Chicago is needed for the happy realization of this undertaking.</p>
   <p>An auxiliary of the Cruz Azul Mexicana, (Mexican Blue Cross) is a powerful necessity to which all must contribute at the same time. The big Mexican colony in that locality needs an institution of this kind for the protection of its members. No institution is called upon to more accurately fulfill the need in social aid and protection than is imparted by the Cruz Azul Mexicana (Mexican Blue Cross) because this is an institution for all and by all. Our fellow country-men of South Chicago must second Dr. Torre's idea without tottering and vacillations.</p>
   <p>It is high time for the colony of South Chicago to have an auxiliary and other colonies as well. On Wednesday, April 30th, a literary social will be held at the Community Hall, in the Union State Bank Building on Houston Avenue and 92nd at 8:00 p. m. when the official body of the auxiliary will be elected. All the colony is cordially invited to the affair.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
