<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-03-01">Mar. 1, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Anti-Tuberculous Conference</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0238</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0238.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-03-01">Mar. 1, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">ANTI-TUBERCULOUS CONFERENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting has been called for Sunday, March 2, 7 P. M., to which the whole colony has been invited.</p>
   <p>The purpose of this gathering is to instruct the citizens on ways of guarding themselves against tuberculosis, a disease which has caused havoc in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Rafael Aveleyra, Chicago Mexican Consul, will talk on the urgent need of the public for greater health protection and valuation.</p>
   <p>Dr. Benjamin Goldberg, director of the Chicago Anti-Tuberculous Sanatorium, has instituted an intensive educational campaign against this dangerous malady. The Chicago Mexican Consul, whose interest for the betterment of the colony has been put forth in relief roles repeatedly, has willingly offered to cooperate to the fullest in order that this campaign may be a <pb facs="5423405_1_0239.jpg" n="2"/>complete success and that it may produce the desired results.</p>
   <p>All presidents and leaders of various groups, whether social or religious, have been cordially requested to aid in this campaign. Among these we are able to refer to Rev. O'Neill, a gentleman highly esteemed for his cultural activities; Rev. Lacy Simms, a religious leader who has gained much prestige among the members of the colony; Rev. J. Fernandez, a person very much loved by our colony for his cooperative efforts, and many others. Mr. Sam Fraga, president of Mexico, and Mr. Betancourt, editor of La Raza have also willingly offered to cooperate with Dr. Goldberg.</p>
   <p>Admission to this meeting is absolutely free.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
