<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-05-06">May 6, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Mexicans Who Ran Over John Patlon Acquitted</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0854</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0854.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-05-06">May 6, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">MEXICANS WHO RAN OVER JOHN PATLON ACQUITTED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Friday the case against nine Mexicans, who ran over an old man was heard in the court of Judge Zeller, magistrate of Chicago Heights. The occupants of the automible were on their way to Mexico when the misfortune occured. Thanks to the active efforts on the part of Mrs. Mary Belle Spencer, a lawyer very well known in our colony, who was able to show in court that the misfortune was accidental and not the fault of the fellow citizen who was at the wheel.</p>
   <p>The Mexicans referred to are Louis Martinez, Carlos Martinez, Dolores Martinez, and her baby, Sebastian Zapota, Magdaleno Villanneva, Cavo Rodriguez and Francisco Abundes, all of Gary, Indiana. They had started on a journey to Guadalajara, Jalisco in an automobile, having taken Lincon Highway. Near Chicago Heights the car collided with a buggy driven by John Pelton, of the mentioned city, who was on the highway in front of the car, both going in the same direction. The old man was thrown to the pavement and badly hurt. He was taken to Saint James Hospital where it was found that his condition was very grave.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0855.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All occupants of the car were arrested at once by police of Cook County Highway. Mr. Carlos Martinez who had worked in Gary for the last eight years put up a bond of $1000.00 for the release of his brother who was driving the machine.</p>
   <p>The family of the injured engaged the services of attorney William Kennedy of Chicago Heights, and the Mexicans were aided by Mary Belle Spencer, one of the most eminent lawyers of the city.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kennedy instituted charges against the Mexicans, based on the laws of Illinois, which if proven carried a sentence of one year in prison and a fine of $500.00; that is if could be proven that carelessness in driving the machine was the cause of the accident. He demanded, however, that the Judge should order the custody of the occupants of the car in order to hold them for murder or homicide in case the injured might die within a year and a day after the accident, as is provided by the law.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0856.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Attorney Spencer defended the case for three days, obtaining acquittal of all criminal and cival charges. She secured the signature of Mr. John Pelton,as well as from all legal authorities on the necessary documents to prevent further legal action in case the injured should die. Mr. Carlos Martinez paid the hospital expenses of $100.00.</p>
   <p>After attorney Spencer had prepared the document and succeeded in having Mr. Pelton sign it Judge Zeller returned to Mr. Martinez the $1000.00 which he had deposited as a bond. The fellow citizens, with this matter settled resumed their journey to Guadalajara.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
