<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Defensa</title>, Vol. 2, No. 37,
<date when="1936-09-12">September 12, 1936</date><title level="a">Editorial:</title><title level="a" type="sub">"This is the Way to Do."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0441</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0441.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Defensa</title>, Vol. 2, No. 37,
<date when="1936-09-12">September 12, 1936</date><title level="a">Editorial:</title><title level="a" type="sub">"This is the Way to Do."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Director of the Chicago Park Commission with the object to facilitate the people of the city of Chicago a few hours of recreation out in the open, and without any cost, a festival has been organized with major or minor interest, to be sponsored by the parks Urban System. Among the future plans, they have announced an annual festival, in which the principal organizations of these different nationalities residing in Chicago, have been invited. The first of said festivals took place at the Stadium, better known as "Soldier's Field", last Monday on a "Labor Day" celebration. The program consisted of twelve numbers of typical dances. Beginning with the old American dances and closing with those originated in Palestine.</p>
   <p>When the organization of the program was initiated, the Directors of the South Park District requred to the various Consulates in order to obtain the names of the societies of the colonies they represent, in order to solicitate their cooperation for the presentation of an interesting foreign program. The Consulate of Mexico gave the names of the Societies 'Miguel Hidalgo' and Josef Ortiz de Dominguez'.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0442.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The plan was presented to them and also their cooperation was solicited. These Mexican Organizations immediately began to work, and from their efforts resulted the presentation of the numbers which was best liked among the twelve which constituted the program. The three Mexican numbers were of great significance. When the name, 'Mexico' was transmitted, the audience burst out aloud and the prolonged applauses from the twenty five thousand spectators. It was a manifestation which indicated that our country is well thougt of and that our typical folklore, costumes and art is well appreciated by the sons of this country. The presentation of the Mexican numbers in the Soldier's Field, meant a great sacrifice on the part of those who organized it, because all of them are working people who have very little leisure and what little they have, would like to dedicate to rest. The artists who took part were amatuers and with scarce resources. None of them received economic renumeration. All their obstacles faded before the effort and tenacity in the preparation. It was very interesting, even though the skeptic thinks that we can not <gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>nite our efforts.</p>
   <p>The act required several weeks of daily practice. Many of them did not have the <pb facs="5423405_1_0443.jpg" n="3"/>necessary costumes but, they ordered them for this occasion, also many costumes were facilitated by the House of "Blas Ensiso &amp; Hijo". The Director of the group was the sympathetic Chiquita Rangel, who sacrified a great part of per time and energy in order to train the artists exclusively to present something worthwhile in the name of Mexico Colony. The attitude of both societies "Miguel Hidalgo of Costilla" and Josefa Ortiz de Dominguez in accepting the responsibility was commendable and patriotic. It demonstrated that much can be done of which many of us think is possible, so as to reach the place that we as a colony deserve among the other foreign groups.</p>
   <p>The applause with which the name Mexico alone was received, signified that we are liked, and there is great desire to know us. It is our duty <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>respond to that affection and satisfy the inquistiveness. Good for the "Miguel Hidalgo" and "Josefa Ortiz!" Good for Chiquita Ranguel and her sixty amatuers!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
