<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-05-06">May 6, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Mexican Blue Cross Forms Auxiliary in South Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0722</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0722.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-05-06">May 6, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">MEXICAN BLUE CROSS FORMS AUXILIARY IN SOUTH CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The literary-musical function which was recently announced by our paper, was held in Community Hall, 92nd and Houston Streets. There were more than 400 persons present, among whom was the Chicago Mexican Consul, Mr. Rafael Aveleyra.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the affair was to select a board of directors to take charge of the newly formed South Chicago Auziliary of the Cruz Azul Mexicana (Mexican Blue Cross). The following were chosen: Mrs. Maria Luisa Sanchez, president; Miss Merced Rios, vice-president; Mrs. Juana Pena, secretary; Mrs. Guadalupe Urrola, treasurer; Mr. Carlos Roberts, director of propaganda; Mrs. Eva A. Carreras, director of nurses; Mrs. Carlota Gonzales, director of ambulances; Miss Ana Maria Gonzales, director of festivities; Dr. Oscar G. Carrera, counsellor, and Miss Eloisa de la Paz, flag bearer.</p>
   <p>During the function the sum of $31.19 was collected. This, added to $14.00 previously collected, was turned over to the treasurer of the New Auxiliary by Mr. Roberts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0723.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The program was an artistic feat and did much credit to its promoters.</p>
   <p>The affair started with the singing of our National Hymn, with which the audience greeted the Honorable Consul of Mexico, Mr. Rafael Aveleyra, as he came into the hall. The minutes were then read by Mrs. Juana Pena, secretary of the Order; after which Mr. Fernandez and Mr. Salas, master musicians, rendered piano and violin selections.</p>
   <p>The principal speaker was Mr. Rafael. His talk covered the object of the gathering, history and purpose of the Mexican Blue Cross, and the benefits to be derived from the formation and activities of the new unit.</p>
   <p>After Mr. Aveleyra's talk, Miss Ana Maria Gonzales entertained with popular songs. Then the Blue Cross orchestra played one number. These two musical treats were well applauded.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0724.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Jose Nieto, whose declamations are well known, recited, to the delight of the audience. When the applause which followed this number abated, the election of the directors began.</p>
   <p>The Mexican Colony of South Chicago will, without doubt, support this new organization, which gives all kinds of aid, and contributes in one way or another to its growth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
