<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Defensa</title>, Vol 2, No. 34,
<date when="1936-08-22">August 22, 1936</date><title level="a">Editorial: "Race"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0120</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0120.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Defensa</title>, Vol 2, No. 34,
<date when="1936-08-22">August 22, 1936</date><title level="a">Editorial: "Race"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since we initiated the "Voice of the People" and "What do you wish to know?" we have been receiving contributions and consultations, to which we have given the attention they deserve, by publishing them and making an effort to answer the questions with clarity and exactness as nearly as possible. We believe we have discharged our duty as servants of the people. We shall make an effort to continue and thereby improve in every way.</p>
   <p>Last week we received a note that contained eight questions, which the author, as we believe, expected the answer in the "What do you wish to know?" column, within a reasonable time. The character of the questions, nevertheless prevented us from satisfying the desire of the questioner due to the small space allotted to the section already mentioned. These are questions that cannot be answered with a monosyllable or a phrase. The character of one of the questions is so important and of such interest to all the people, that we have decided to dedicate our entire editorial section, not to satisfy the curiosity of the author but in order to study a series of serious problems which pertain to all of us. The first question asked by the author of this note under the pseudonym, T. A. Tornillo, is the following: "Why are the great majority of the corpses of our <pb facs="5423405_1_0121.jpg" n="2"/>people in the Hull House district buried by negro undertakers?" This is a question which has occupied our own minds. It is a delicate social question, deserving a profound study. From the material point of view the only reason we can give to explain the case is that the only undertaking establishment conducted by people of the negro race is situated in the center of our people and has an employee that speaks Spanish. We are not antagonistic, nor have we any prejudice against the negro. The white resident, native or foreign, has a very low opinion of the negro. He despises his standards and his mercantile and social activities. Concomitantly are despised those who associate with the negro in any way and then are considered morally inferior to a human being of ebony anatomy and they are despised more than the negro. The negro himself experiences a feeling of superiority toward his white employees and clients, the number of which, let us repeat is rather small. The economy of the price paid to a negro undertaker for a modest funeral, is not sufficient to pay for the bad name we acquire and the demerit suffered by our social standards from the point of view of those who consider that the negro race should be forced to live entirely isolated. The fact that there is a person who speaks our language and <pb facs="5423405_1_0122.jpg" n="3"/>is used as an interpreter in the arrangements of funerals is not, nor will ever be, a reason of sufficient weight to explain satisfactorily that a negro agency be engaged for the majority of the funerals of our people, in a neighborhood where our group is so numerous.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
