<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Defensa</title><date when="1936-09-16">Sept. 16, 1936</date> Vol. 2 No. 38
<title level="a">"Important Institution being organized in Chicago".</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0183</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0183.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Defensa</title><date when="1936-09-16">Sept. 16, 1936</date> Vol. 2 No. 38
<title level="a">"Important Institution being organized in Chicago".</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the purpose to better the economic conditions of Mexican residents of Chicago, and vicinity, an important cooperative has just been organized, and incorporated under the laws of the State of Illinois, it is known as: "Cooperativas Aliadas Mexicanas Inc." ("Allied Cooperatives Inc.") The directive body of this institution considers it a high honor to offer this organization to the Mexican Colony of Chicago, and nearby regions. It is proposed to publish a series of articles in order to have a complete knowledge of aims, and plans of concrete functioning, since we have accepted the benevolent cooperation from the Editors of La Defensa. We judge opportune to declare in advance, that these cooperative societies have been formed not to benefit the organizers or any other group. The directors are persons who have been dedicated to social work for a good number of years, and in their pursuit to better the cultural, and economic standard of the Mexican people in the United States. The idea "Cooperative" has been founded as a medium, which if utilized and properly directed, is called to produce the unification of the Mexicans, upon mighty solid bases of mutual assistance and economic <pb facs="5423405_1_0184.jpg" n="2"/>protection. Hoping to publish more information in the future so as to enlighten the colony upon the plans of this institution we now invite all persons who may be really interested in the betterment of the conditions of the Mexican in the United States. Information may be solicited from the president either by mail in person or by an appointment. On 47th and Ashland Ave., Mr. Jose Rosales has been commissioned as organizer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
