<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-03-13">Mar. 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">We Are the Victims of Our Own Ignorance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0054</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0054.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-03-13">Mar. 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">WE ARE THE VICTIMS OF OUR OWN IGNORANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Actually, the Mexican colony of this city, as a whole, is made up of those who are frequently victims of their own ignorance. Now, it might be that our honorableness is taken advantage of, or it might be in the form of insults; then again, it might be that we are incapable of living among a people said to be civilized, - - - - and finally a thousand of defects with which we find ourselves confronted. In all of these faults, of which the majority of the Mexicans are accused, there are some which are, in a way, true; however, we do not fail to recognize all that is just. How are we to respond, when we are treated as assassins? If we look into the past, we will actually see that we have, in times gone by, committed murders (made characteristic of us because our uncalled-for faults are not individualized, Mexicans being spoken of in general).</p>
   <p>And what should we do in order to wipe out such hideous generalization? It is a thing apparently impossible, as we see it, but a simple thing, if we place ourselves under the point of scientific investigation. There are two ways open to us:</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0055.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>First, man come into this world bringing with him a sacred duty to fulfill. This consists in guiding his children through the narrow path of right, and seeing that they obtain a good education; in seeing that they do not fall victims of falsehoods and fantasies. In a word, to see that the scheme of education develops a true spirit of friendship and a true spirit of sociability among these sons or daughters who are to correct the evils of our elders.</p>
   <p>This offspring, if we make it possible for them to receive a good education, and give them the advantage of our experience, may then be well fitted to fill their place in society. They will not be criminals, because their early life has been set up along the line of honesty and integrity. And, naturally, they will be disinclined to fantasies and the spirit of vice and crimnality. This is the first calling of the head of a family; even if there are some who maintain that all men found with the obligation of family, are not in a position to give an education to their children, because of the lack of funds. This objection may be answered in this manner:</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0056.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The man who desires a good education for his children, and who has no resources with which to give it to them, will find some way to do this job. He will start by sacrificing everything considered of little importance. With this effort, it will be found that the task is not so great as was anticipated, and the results which accrue to the children for exceed the sacrifice.</p>
   <p>The second approach, which is considered more convincing is this: If we do not wish to be victims of ourselves, and wish to stop the attack which we encounter at every step from those men of distinct nationalities, and not be victims of brute force, that they, as well as we, have used up to the present time in order to stain one or the other with blood, we should organize to form a union which will stand for the principle of confraternity, a sacred duty which we have to fulfill, one for the other. Likewise, we should put a premium on the up-building of all groups: to seek all means suitable to giving our children the best education possible. We should join every force which seeks to combat crime among our group.</p>
   <p>Mexicans! if we wish to have the good name of our dear mother-country respected, let us give effect to our beliefs and form a society which will <pb facs="5423405_1_0057.jpg" n="4"/>have for its purpose the intellectual and moral advancement of all groups and other race brothers. Let us put all our efforts into action in order to form this great bond of confraternity and love which may unite all, from the smallest atom to the most gigantic sun.</p>
   <p>Only thru unity, will we be able to conquer vice and crime.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
