<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Ideal Mexicano</title>,
<date when="1936-10-04">Oct. 4, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Schedule of Classes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0070</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0070.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Ideal Mexicano</title>,
<date when="1936-10-04">Oct. 4, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">SCHEDULE OF CLASSES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>By sepcial request from various families, we transcribe the schedule of the classes taught by the Cordi-Marian Sisters. The parents who may wish a real education for their children, and the preservation of the faith in their little hearts, must send them to a wholly Catholic school, and no other. Location: 1100 So. May Street, Chicago.</p>
   <p>Kindergarten from 9:00 to 11:30 A.M. Evening from 3:00 to 5:00. Monday: Spanish by Sister Filomena. Tuesday: Music by Sister Ana Maria. Wednesday: Drawing and Religion by Sister Filomena. Thursday: Manual and Carpenter work by R.M. Lara. M.O.M. For older children - Friday: Spanish by Sister Filomena. Monday: Spanish by Sisters Severa and Angeles. Tuesday: Instruction by Sister Angeles. Wednesday: Instruction by Sisters Severa and Angeles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0071.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Thursday, Crocheting and Gymnastics. Friday, Instruction and Recreation for girls. Monday,Flower making by Sister Lara. Tuesday: Religion and Cooking by, Sister Lara. Wednesday: Embroidering and Sewing by Sister Lara. Thursday: Music and Declamation by Sister Ana Maria. Classes for Miss and Mrs. Monday from 9:30 to 11:00 A.M. Embroidering by Sister Lara Tuesday: Flower making by Sister Lara. Wednesday: Grammar by Sister Filomena; Thursday and Friday: Embroidering and Flower making by Sister Lara. During the evenings: the following is taught. Dress-making, English, Needlework, and Cooking. The young men and adults will be taught the Spanish and English languages.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
