<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-03-12">Mar. 12, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Atlas Basket Ball Team in Action</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0669</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0669.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-03-12">Mar. 12, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">ATLAS BASKET BALL TEAM IN ACTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Atlas Sport Club, recently formed in South Chicago, has a good reason to be proud.</p>
   <p>The basket ball team, since its incorporation January 4th up to the 9th of March has played 17 games of which number it has won 15, having lost one and tied the other.</p>
   <p>The teams over which they were victorious are: Pirates, of Indiana Harbor; Silver Streakes; Cuauhtemoc; Confederated Boys of Chicago, Oak Park, Bethlehem, Park Manor, Villa Park, Maywood, Esses and Chiefs.</p>
   <p>The game which they lost was played against the Pirates and the tied one against Oak Park.</p>
   <p>The directors of the Theological Seminary of Chicago University, have offered them an opportunity to show their mettle again by admitting them to a recently organized league which will compete for a silver trophy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0670.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They have already begun the games, playing the first one last Monday when they defeated the Feds by a score of 18 to 9. Taking into consideration the powerful team of the Feds Quintet, this victory of the Atlas Club may be considered as a forerunner of other more decisive triumphs.</p>
   <p>The Mexican Colony of South Chicago, is gratified and quite satisfied with the accomplishments of this famous Sport Club which has given prestige to the name of Mexico.</p>
   <p>The Atlas Sport Club is always making an effort to improve the team and broaden its activities. It now informs us of having planned a dance, the Glory of Saturday, a ball which, without doubt will be attended by all of our young people. The place selected is the Community Hall of South Chicago, a place where the unit already referred to has given several social functions.</p>
   <p>The members of the Atlas will never cease their efforts to build up a team which will be the glory of Mexico and capable of facing any team from any other country. We congratulate these young men who have earnestly devoted themselves to the development of sports.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
