<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-06-02">June 2, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">"This Is the Way to Do It"! -By our Mexican Band.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0504</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0504.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-06-02">June 2, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">"THIS IS THE WAY TO DO IT"! -By our Mexican Band.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The example has been set, dear friends and illustrious compatriots. This example will be perpetuated forever.</p>
   <p>It proves that there is not an obstacle that can paralize the will power, energies, and virility of men who wish to see crystalized that which at one time was only a dream. You may pardon me for saying, "our band," which made its appearance last Saturday at the Ashland Auditorium, because all that is Mexican belongs to us.</p>
   <p>It is ours simply because it is Mexican and everything that is Mexican is ours. It happened one day when we least expected it. Francisco Calderon,with a group of Mexican musicians presented to us what they had acquired through study, efforts and privations in order to show to the world of what we are capable.</p>
   <p>I have never seen festivals being organized by us in this city in a better way.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0505.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Great was the crowd assembled in the Ashland Auditorium. As soon as we walked into the building, there were two gay chaps perfectly dressed in a blue uniform to direct us. Inside of the hall, we could see and admire the four thousand, three hundred persons properly seated, anxiously awaiting the moment when the curtain would arise and permit them to see the splendid Mexican artists.</p>
   <p>When the performance started maestro Calderon appeared in an impeccable military uniform, with baton in hand. It was a gorgeous sight.</p>
   <p>They played masterfully in spite of being amateurs. Much applause was heard, the auditorium was filled to capacity with good looking women, cultured ladies, handsome gentlemen and in general a very select audience.</p>
   <p>When the baritone Jose Lopez Oseguera appeared on the stage, the audience broke out into a thundering applause, for he is well known in all the artistic centers and has taken part in many of the Mexican festivals in the colony.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0506.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>On that night he offered us all he possessed; his art, voice and dynamic personality, all these were concentrated in his performance. His distinguished personality left an immense impression on the people.</p>
   <p>After the concert a splendid dance followed, where we saw the most select of our society. The young and elderly ladies displayed their wardrobes that night.</p>
   <p>It was a "gala night," a Mexican night, and a glorious night for our colony in Chicago including the Mexican Band and its director Francisco Calderon. The Mexican Band of Chicago has set an example and has shown that this is the way to do things. This is the way to show the world what we are able to do. We must set examples with facts, and not with empty words. It is up to us now to follow this example, let us be united, abolish old policies, also organizations of dances which lead to nothing, like the so called "Mutualist Societies," if you please, which in other words are private institutions organizing dances and other entertainment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
