<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-08-13">Aug. 13, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Aviation Captain Charged with Embezzlement Freed on Thousand Dollar Bond</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0830</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0830.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-08-13">Aug. 13, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">AVIATION CAPTAIN CHARGED WITH EMBEZZLEMENT FREED ON THOUSAND DOLLAR BOND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Captain and instructor, B. J. Venegas, appeared before, Judge Borrelli, last Monday in the court located at 48 South Wabash.</p>
   <p>As we have already informed our readers, the captain had been accused of embezzlement. He was found guilty, arrested and fined $1,000.</p>
   <p>He was also held on other charges which will be heard by the Judge on the 23rd of this month, at nine o'clock in the morning.</p>
   <p>The defendant, was apprehended last Saturday and was immediately freed on bond. The bond was put up by his mother. Mrs. Venegas, guaranteed by a house which she owns.</p>
   <p>The lawyer for the defendant, Lic. Julio I. Puento, asked for a continuance in order to give Captain Venegas time to raise the money with which to repay Mr. Deza.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0831.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One version of this lamentable affair is it seems that Captain Venegas was the victim of a pickpocket who robbed him of a large quantity of money. For that reason he was not able to meet the payments toward the purchase of the plane.</p>
   <p>This version of the affair was given to our reporter and as such, we give it to the public. In the meantime we will be on the look out for new facts in this interesting case.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
