<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-05-13">May 13, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Mexican Murdered in Gary, Indiana</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0810</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0810.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-05-13">May 13, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">MEXICAN MURDERED IN GARY, INDIANA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday morning Domingo Gonzales, a Mexican citizen passed away in the hospital, as a result of gun-shot wounds which he received during the previous evening. He was a victim of an unidentified aggressor who shot him from an automobile while it was going at top speed. The victim was 35 years of age and lived at 1604 Jefferson Street, Gary, Indiana. He was caught in the cross-fire when he found himself in front of a pool-room located at 1609 Madison Street. Angelo Traficamp, 35 years of age,also received a wound in the chest when he left the pool-room and went to the aid of Gonzales. His condition is considered critical.</p>
   <p>Another victim of this shooting incident is Hans Hansen, 40 years of age who was nearby. He received two gun-shot wounds in one leg, but his condition is not considered serious.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0811.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the under-world of Gary, Gonzales gained the reputation of being a stool-pigeon for the police, telling them what he knew,of the many secret hiding places of the "bootleggers" of the neighboring city.</p>
   <p>The theory prevails that the assailant was Joseph Montano, chief of a gang of "bootleggers" who marauds thru the northern part of Illinois. Traficamp told the police that he seemed to have recognized Montano as being the man who walked thru a small passage-way a few moments before the tragedy.</p>
   <p>On the theory that Montano is the murderer, the police have begun to search for him, hoping for his apprehension.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
