<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-10-27">Oct. 27, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">[Mexicans Swindled by Fake Employment Agency]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0890</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0890.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-10-27">Oct. 27, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">[MEXICANS SWINDLED BY FAKE EMPLOYMENT AGENCY]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jose Duran, an employment agent, is being sought by the police. Another confidence game assuming vast proportions has taken place in the colony. It occurred just a few days ago when Jose A. Duran, of 40 S. Halsted street, swindled over two hundred Mexicans on the pretense of sending them to work. He has mysteriously disappeared from his temporary employment office at 40 S. Halsted street.</p>
   <p>His confidence game consisted in collecting money from Mexicans seeking for work at the agency. In order to make the victims gobble the pill so artfully prepared, he distributed some attractive literature among the Mexicans. Among other things the place where these workers were supposed to report for work was at the Navy Yard of Cleveland, Ohio, where all kinds of work could be had. Of course those who didn't want to do labor could be used as electricians or mechanics. Five dollars a day was the minimum wage. Considering the lack of work that prevails at this time in this city, Duran's appeal must have had a good response. The literature in question offered a good job with free transportation, furnished rooms, stoves, coal, light, clean bedding, and dishes, all guaranteed for six months. The days for registering were from Oct. 15th to 22nd, and the day of departure for Cleveland, Oct. 25th. On October 20th Duran disappeared. The departure for Cleveland was quite a joke that has been felt by more than two <pb facs="5423405_1_0891.jpg" n="2"/>hundred Mexicans. When they came to the depot they were told that the Mr. Deming who signed the literature was absolutely unknown. When the workers had convinced themselves of the truth they went to the Desplaines Police Station to lodge a complaint. The police promised to do everything possible to find Joe Duran, alias A. B. Deming.</p>
   <p>Jose Duran is married to a girl from Argentine and it is said he was in financial straits. It is believed that in order to avoid suspicion for his disappearance, he suspended the enlistment of workers the day he left, telling those who asked to go to Cleveland that all the vacancies had been filled. It is estimated that Duran collected about $3,000. Many people paid him $15, $10, and $5. Some not only paid their fee, but also paid for those who were penniless. No one suspected the insolvency of Duran and everyone had faith in him. The swindle was cunningly planned. The date to carry it out was precisely at the time when hundreds of Mexicans converge into the city in preparation for the winter season. Duran knew that this was the time when most of the workers had received their half month salary and was the only time in which his project could bring results.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
