<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Defensa</title>, Vol. 2. No. 44.
<date when="1936-11-07">Nov. 7, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Two Women Assassinated.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0818</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0818.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>LA DEFENSA</title>, Vol. 2. No. 44.
<date when="1936-11-07">Nov. 7, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">TWO WOMEN ASSASSINATED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A young Mexican killed his wife and mother-in-law. The home of Mrs. Angela Rodriguez situated in the first floor of the Oberman Building 14th, and Newberry Ave. was a theatre of a tragedy last Thursday, when Federico Chavez 21 years of age, Mexican by nationality, killed his wife, Mrs. Aurora R. de Chavez, and Mrs. Angela Rodriguez his mother-in-law.</p>
   <p>Antecedents.</p>
   <p>Federico Chavez, is an individual who has been known never to have had a permanent occupation. He is well known among the young elements in the neighborhood and in social centers of which there are three or four within the block where the crime occured. Six months ago after a brief betrotal Federico persuaded Aurora to abandon her maternal home, and they went to get married in the nearby city of Crown Point. Mrs. Rodriguez who always <pb facs="5423405_1_0819.jpg" n="2"/>objected to the relations of her daughter with Chavez when she saw the marriage certificate, surrendered to the irremediable, and forgave Aurora for getting married without consent. The newly married couple established their home in a modest four room apartment at 817 So. Morgan St. where they had the honeymoon, which did not last quite six months due to the apathy of the husband in seeking an honest job, whereby he could support his young and attractive wife.</p>
   <p>Frequent Aversions.</p>
   <p>For some weeks until this date the disagreements between the new couple became frequent and serious. The wife, accustomed to an unencumbered life carried on at the side of the mother, could not habituate herself to the series of privations obligated to go through due to the indifference of the husband to fulfill his obligations. According to some people who knew intimately the young man, there were not a few days in which there was nothing to eat in their poor home. Very frequently Aurora, and even her husband came to the maternal <pb facs="5423405_1_0820.jpg" n="3"/>home asking for food.</p>
   <p>The Tragedy.</p>
   <p>Thursday morning just before noon, Aurora made one of those frequent visits to her mother. Shortly before four o'clock Federico arrived too, and said he was just from his house looking for his wife. A strong discussion started between husband and wife because she gave the marriage certificate to a woman friend to keep, so she said. Strong words continued for few minutes, at the end of which, Federico asked his wife to a bed room where they could speak with more liberty. Aurora agreed to the suggestion. Mrs. Rodriguez and the other occupants of the house suddenly heard Aurora screaming desperately and hurried to the room, but just before they got to the room they heard three detonations. When they opened the door Aurora was found on the floor mortally wounded.</p>
   <p>Two Women Assassinated.</p>
   <p>When his mother-in-law appeared in the door, Federico turned his revolver <pb facs="5423405_1_0821.jpg" n="4"/>and shot her in the abdomen.</p>
   <p>The Assassin Arrested.</p>
   <p>The police were called by one of the persons who were in the house, as soon as he heard the first shot, and within a few minutes the police arrived at the place of the tragedy. The proximity of the Maxwell station within two blocks where the crime was committed, caused the police to reach the place before the assassin completely realized his guilt and intended to escape, he was surprised by the policemen while sitting on the edge of the bed with the revolver yet in his hand, and in a state of apparent stupor. While being arrested he showed no resistance. When he was interrogated at the Police Station Chavez said that he suspected infidelity of his wife and that his suspicion increased greatly by the act of his wife when she took the marriage certificate away from home.</p>
   <p>(to be continued.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
