<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-05-20">May 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">More Mexicans Attacked</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0807</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0807.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 1</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-05-20">May 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">MORE MEXICANS ATTACKED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many thieves who commit robberies near Halsted and Taylor Streets, are a continuous threat to the neighborhood and especially to the Mexican citizen.</p>
   <p>These robbers are well organized in several gangs and well known to the police. It is imperative that the authorities clean up this city ward, for the benefit of its inhabitants and merchants.</p>
   <p>We see daily, around Halsted and Taylor Streets, groups of Italians who are planning robberies. It is very dangerous to reach this part of the city, because the bandits attack even during the day. There is an assumption that some Italian politicians protect them, when one of them is caught by the police he is freed very soon without punishment. With this procedure the neighborhood is terrorized.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0808.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Last week two young Mexicans were brutally beaten at the corner of Halsted and Taylor Streets, by a group of six or seven persons. The Mexicans escaped from their assailants due to their swiftness in running.</p>
   <p>The bandits have always numerical superiority over their victims and know perfectly well they have political protection.</p>
   <p>Now we must relate that last Sunday about 4 P.M. two Mexican workers, at that tragic corner: Halsted and Taylor, were assaulted by more or less 10 Italians. Our compatriots work in a railroad section outside the city and come weekly to purchase provisions. The bandits intended to rob them by day. The two workers fought as two wildcats, but at the end, were vanquished, but one of them escaped and found shelter in Mr. Ignacio M. Valle's store, owned by this esteemed Mexican trader. The robbers waited outside the store for their Mexican victim, who remained there until he thought that his assailants had gone; however, when he intended to go outside toward Mr. Enciso's tailor shop he was attacked again. The Mexican wished to get his trousers mended, which were torn during the previous struggle.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0809.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In this occasion the Italians were very angry and assaulted him furiously. The Mexican used a knife and stabbed according to some witnesses, some of his rivals, who threw stones at him. Being unable to go to Mr. Enciso's tailor shop he retreated back to Mr. Valle's store. The bandits became very angry at their victims flight, and threw stones against the plate glass windows of "El Arte Mexicano".</p>
   <p>The attackers fled in three automobiles. The damage done to the store is estimated at $500.00, excluding the window panes which were insured.</p>
   <p>Mr. Valle called the police and reported the attack. An American eye-witness took the number of one of the automobiles; but the police found it was a stolen plate.</p>
   <p>The Mexican people will ask the Mexican Consul to look into this matter and demand from the authorities the punishment of these people. If the authorities are not willing to protect us there is the intention to make a formal appeal to Washington by the conduct of the Mexican Embassy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
