<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>, Vol. VIII. No. 742,
<date when="1934-01-20">Jan. 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Fault Finding</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Leon Lira (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0128</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0128.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>, Vol. VIII. No. 742,
<date when="1934-01-20">Jan. 20, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">FAULT FINDING</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Leon Lira (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our social leaders in action. And I say in action, because they are going to defile on this column now. I promised to write of them, (or about them) and I shall do it with all impartiality that it is possible. Not even I shall be excused from it, for I have acted as a leader on some occasions. No fooling! Of the many types that I am going to speak of, there is one in whom I can be identified. I cannot say which one, because that would be too much self exposure for whoever unveils his soul is in danger of being scoffed at, lapidated and even exploited. I am not ready to suffer the consequences, (why should I?) as one of my cousins would say. (A Mexican usually calls the American, a cousin).</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0129.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In a psychological study as the one we are treating at this moment, no exceptions should be made, if truth is the torch to illuminate our guiding path. In the course of this study we may speak of ironical things if necessary, but, it shall be truth as I understand it. By the way, let me say that my intention has been and shall be to speak plain, so I can be understood. It wouldn't be my fault if what I say is mal-intrepreted, for we know that a lack of comprehension is one of the greatest ailments afflicting us most severely. May I say, that my attitude has been toward constructive things and if it has not produced the effects desired, it is due to the arid soil I have tried to cultivate. As social leaders, we may consider them, (even though they are not) all those who take an active part in the guidance of a social group, thus it is necessary to have some term to designate them.</p>
   <p>There is a variation of types, even though in appearance they may look the same. They have come to the scenery of our social life, and precisely to this variety is due the lamentable failure in the accomplishment of a social work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0130.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The different characters of our leaders have been manifested in the methods they have employed upon the same undertaking. We have had dreamers, idealists, ill-intentioned,selfish, true patriots and mouth piece patriots, but the ignorant elements have predominated, having been characterized by one or more of the afore said qualities, have figured prominently, but unjustly. And specially to these people is due the disorganization of the colony. It is because them that has always existed the enmity amongst our social groups particularly when something is being done for the unification of the colony. It is because them, also, that those who have intended the confederation of Mexican societies, have failed completely in bringing mutual understanding, proper orientation and a more coordinated work. And if we add to these, newspaper editors who have a lack of civil courage, who from time to time have come to enlighten us, we complete then the group really responsible for the disorganization we are now lamenting. The newspaper men that I speak of are responsible, because they have tried to evade their responsibility, they have not been concrete when they should, that is to say when we tried to cure the ailment which caused the decay in our social organism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0131.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The masses cannot be blamed because of their unconsciousness, we must take into consideration that mental development is a slow process. Very frequently we have heard that the colony does not respond to the call when something beneficial is intended, but that is a false affirmation. During my stay in Chicago, I have noticed the large contributions made by our colony for different purposes. The colony has been defrauded of such contributions by unscrupulous individuals,in other words, pickpockets and thieves who appropiate to themselves that which is entrusted into their care. Many cases of these nature have occurred, that is why the colony within its unconsciousness refuses to support our leaders. The story shall be different the day when a sound and well directed group may be formed, and above all with well-intentioned aims. The unification of the colony, in order to be effective, must be conscious, intelligent, and honestly directed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
