<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-02-20">Feb. 20, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A Campaign against Tuberculosis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0628</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0628.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-02-20">Feb. 20, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">A CAMPAIGN AGAINST TUBERCULOSIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The directing committee now campaigning against Tuberculosis held their first meeting last Thursday, at 2048 West Washington St. The meeting was attended by Dr. Gracia Trevino, Mexican Consulate attache; Rev. Lacy Simms, Presbyterian Minister and director of the Neighborhood House; Mr. Sam Fraga, Editor of Mexico, Rev. C. Gurrola, Baptist Minister, and Rev. William O'Neill, Methodist Minister.</p>
   <p>Father S. Savoldi, Mr. Jose O. Velasco, Antonio Acosta, Jose Fernandez, and many other persons representing social and religious organizations, are very courteously invited to the next conference to be held by this committee in the near future. The main purpose of this campaign is to combat this serious disease, which, according to statistics, has caused considerable suffering among our nationals. In order to prevent its propagation, we must give the public sound and valuable advice on how to be protected against it. Dr. Benjamin Goldberg, director of the Municipal Tuberculosis Sanitarium of <pb facs="5423405_1_0629.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago, with the cooperation of Mr. Rafael Aveleira, consul of Mexico in Chicago, intends to begin a real campaign against the spread of the disease which is gaining ground in an alarming proportion, according to the statistics of the Sanitarium. This educational campaign,--as was said in our edition of last Saturday,--shall consist of lectures, illustrated with films, by the Chicago Health Department. The increase of tubercular cases, so sharp in 1928, was counteracted in 1929 thanks to the campaign so effectively undertaken by the Health Department. Tuberculosis is easier to avoid than to cure, and its prevention depends largely on the public's ability to notice the first symptoms so as to go to a clinic for an examination before the infection sets its roots in the organism, that is, if the infection really exists. This is the aim pursued by Dr. Goldberg. The cooperation of the people is necessary, if we are to reduce the disease to a minimum. The Health Department maintains a board of medical experts and excellent clinics provided with the best advancements of science, where examination is free to any person who may have the symptoms or any indication of tuberculosis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
