<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Indicador</title>, Vol. I. No. 1.
<date when="1933-04">April, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Educational Paper</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Why, El Indicator is Published" (Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0537</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0537.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Indicador</title>, Vol. I. No. 1.
<date when="1933-04">April, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">EDUCATIONAL PAPER</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Why, El Indicator is Published" (Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If we are going to speak of ourselves in the future, it is better to begin right now, and let it be known who we are, what we think, and what we wish. In other words, according to the Editor's custom the public must be informed of the signification of a new publication. In presenting this paper, we must put forward the bases, upon which we are to build a mutual understanding between the interested people, that is to say, the public and the publication. We are not going to stop now on routinary details, the lack of space forces us to be concise and omit that which is superfluous, in order to speak of our objective.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0538.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>El Indicador, is a paper destined to make people think, and begins its labor now. Its effectiveness of course is to be seen, and will depend largely upon the favorable atmosphere we may find. We are not moralists, nor reformers, nevertheless during our editorial life, we are going to have much to do with morals, and social evolution. But since we are liberals, we shall not force these ideas upon any one. We shall write something that may contain some importance, on literature, or philosophy. However, the reader is at liberty to accept whatever he may like, and refuse what he does not like. The base of our work is the compliance of our duty, and that is the only thing we are preoccupied with.</p>
   <p>The lack of organization of the Mexican Colony in Chicago is lamentable and shameful, each day gets farther from the conventional route, and is degenerating so fast that the compliance of duty is something of the other world.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0539.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The heroic actions are in the sky, depravation is at our door, the pride of the race tends to disappear, and the chaos is near. One does not have to be psychologist to notice the moral decay, suffice to observe the actions of the majority in order to realize the menacing danger. We come to give the sound of alarm and try to form conscience in the people who represent a country abroad. Our work is not to criticise alone, but to indicate the destructing causes, and point out a way to subdue these causes. We do not only preach, but will also act; thus our work in the social camp will show. That is why we bring this publication to light; we are identified with the "Asociacion Panamericana", who is furnishing the money for the campaign we have initiated, and shall continue for indefinite period of time. Therefore, we sustain a pleasant illusion for the future of our work, and we hope that when we no longer continue the struggle, we would have constructed, or influenced the element that may finish what we have now started.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
