<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1933-04-29">Apr. 29. 1933</date>.
<title level="a">May First Labor Activities</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0189</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0189.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1933-04-29">Apr. 29. 1933</date>.
<title level="a">MAY FIRST LABOR ACTIVITIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The local organizations of the Chicago Workers Committee on unemployment, locals 32 and 36 have been requested to get together all the other locals of the above mentioned Committee. The purpose of this move is to have the full Committee, 72 locals in all, meet at Roosevelt Road and Jefferson Street on the first of May at 12:00 noon to make an unemployment demonstration. The parade will begin at Michigan Boulevard and Washington Street, and proceed from there to the City Hall passing thru various streets until it is disbanded.</p>
   <p>All the Mexicans are invited to take part in this May First demonstration. Scenes and pictures will be taken of the parade as well as of the persons who will make speeches during the celebration.</p>
   <p>The main object of this demonstration is to persuade the Illinois State Legislature as well as the Federal Government to begin the work projects which they have planned for the unemployed and also to bring pressure on the State of Illinois to approve the compensation law which is now being debated at Springfield.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0190.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The said law will guarantee a certain unemployment compensation in accordance with the salary or wages which each individual earns.</p>
   <p>We hope that the Colony will respond to the invitation which has been made by means of the columns of this paper. The invitation originated with Mr. Borders, president of the Committee who is always actively interested in the welfare of all those Mexicans who find themselves without work in the City of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
