<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Defensa</title><date when="1936-10-10">Oct. 10, 1936</date> Vol. 2 No. 40
<title level="a">"What are the Mexican Cooperatives?"</title>
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0185</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.D.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0185.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>La Defensa</title><date when="1936-10-10">Oct. 10, 1936</date> Vol. 2 No. 40
<title level="a">"What are the Mexican Cooperatives?"</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the last issue we promised to publish a series of articles to enlighten the colony upon the work of this institution, and we initiate with pleasure this undertaking, asking from the readers to follow the series in order to have a perfect idea, and benefit by the practical results offered by the Cooperatives. It is to lament the lack of economic organization among those who reside not only in Chicago, but in the United States. Until this date, little or nothing has been done to better these conditions, that makes us feel the enormous necessity for unification. Such a need produces the shaking, precipitation of the Mexican ideal that without a real Institution to foment the coalition of its members, or raise the economic benefits and high honesty, it is embraced by the local atmosphere which is diametrical to our nature and idealism as a race. To remedy these conditions there can not be a medium more adequated and practical than that which may produce the creation of the common interest. The organizers of the Mexican cooperatives are convinced of the limited benefits that any other institution may produce and for that reason we have turned to a medium that is in accordance with the present day needs, to improve the conditions of the Mexicans <pb facs="5423405_1_0186.jpg" n="2"/>in the United States. The persons interested enough to obtain a complete information either verbally or by mail concerning the cooperatives, kindly communicate with:</p>
   <p>Mr. Gregorio Perez P., chairman, 3140 W. Carlisle Place.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
