<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-05-14">May 14, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">A Scene of Tragedy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0106</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0106.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-05-14">May 14, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">A SCENE OF TRAGEDY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A compatriot's attention was attracted by a six weeks old infant's insistent wails. The plaintive cries issued from an old building located in the slum section of this city. When Manuel Casetillo, entered the building, he stood horrified at the sight of the baby making futile efforts to reach its mother's bosom. Her body was motionless. This woman, while alive, was named Conception Guiterrez de Arriga.</p>
   <p>Five small unclothed and hungry children were standing around the bed where their lifeless mother was stretched out. The windows of the house were boarded up, leaving the place in complete darkness.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0107.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>ABANDONED BY FATHER</p>
   <p>Through the investigation of the case of the Arriga family, it was learned from Santos, who was eleven years old, that the father had not been home for several months. Also that on various occasions they spent days without a piece of bread and that the sacrificing mother did not desire to give her children to a charitable institution for fear that they would not have the care which she could give them. She preferred to have them at her side in misery and poor surroundings, doing what she could to give them food, which their heartless father had denied them.</p>
   <p>DIED FROM LACK OF NOURISHMENT</p>
   <p>By medical examination it was discovered that the mother died from starvation. The family did not receive help from any institution, but only from friends which the devoted mother received through house to house solicitations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0108.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>She took this to her children to the old house, called home.</p>
   <p>When Mr. Casetillo entered the house, Santos cried in a high voice, saying: "Mother does not want to wake, she must be sick, very sick".</p>
   <p>On the table of that room, practically unfurnished, was a piece of hard bread, probably the last contribution the mother had obtained for her children and which had as yet not been given to them for fear of increasing their hunger.</p>
   <p>The children are: Santos 11, Irene 7, Jesus 5, Pedro 1 year and 10 months and the newly born baby.</p>
   <p>It also was learned that a sixth child, Carlos, was in one of the near by hospitals, with a broken spine, which resulted from a fall from the second floor of the building in which they live.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0109.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The local authorities gave Miss Paubla Martinez, of 1244 West Newberry, custody of the children. She is God-Mother of the little boy, Pedro.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
