<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-09-15">Sep. 15, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">S. M. Carmen I and her Court of Honor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0500</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0500.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-09-15">Sep. 15, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">S. M. CARMEN I AND HER COURT OF HONOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Seven thousand votes were casted in her favor, this is a worthy work of the Mexican colony in South Chicago. To S. M. Carmen I.- Miss Carmen Gallaga, and her Court of Honor, we are pleased to dedicate this page of our special edition. Lamenting only that we are not able to present her picture together with the nine good looking girls who form the Court of Honor of the Patriotic celebration in South Chicago. Probably it is the turn of the South Chicago colony to have the privilege of organizing the Patriotic Festivals.</p>
   <p>We are pleased to say that this noble neighborhood really is entitled to an applause for the work they have been carrying on with so much anticipation. It is well known to the colony of South Chicago the double efforts made of many of the residents of that vicinity in the organization of the program for the 16th of September.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0501.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>And it is due in the first place to the colony of South Chicago and secondly to the Caballeros de Guadalupe, (Knights of Guadalupe) whose institution was assigned by the colony to direct the work. One of the most important numbers in the program is the inauguration of the South Chicago Mexican Band whose members are workers of the Illinois Steel Company and other foundries in that region who, for the first time shall present to the colony the fruit of many years of labor. To make a complete history of the South Chicago Band is something that is not in our reach because we have not the complete information, nevertheless, we shall try at least to give you an idea of its beginning. Therefore, we now take the privilege of introducing the contents of a circular that was published at the inception of this organization which reads as follows.</p>
   <p>The organizers of the "Chicago Mexican Band" have the pleasure to invite all the young people who like music and may be interested to take part in the formation of the Band. And thanks the great sympathy of Mr. P. A. Newton, General Superintendent of the Illinois Steel Company, and Mr. T. H. McKeeney, Manager of the same, who have offered us their valuable protection that is to give the members of this Band a preference in employment.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0502.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>They have given orders to the employment office to that extent, so, any person interested in the art of music may call at the Academy of Music 8751 Buffalo Avenue, South Chicago. There you may subscribe as a member, obtain all the necessary information and then we will send you to the employment office of the Illinois Steel Company. The academy is open from 9:00 A.M. until 11: P. M. and is located at the above address. South Chicago, Illinois. July 16, 1926. Signed: Gumaro Ortiz Director, Pedro Luna and E. Aragon colaborators.</p>
   <p>This copy of the circular was loaned to us by Mr. Pedro Luna who said that, at the time of its publication it was not taken into consideration that Mr. Luna and Mr. Aragon were the real organizers of the Band. Therefore, this is only an idea of the birth, the rest of its life is lost in the course of time. It is known that the members went through all kinds of experiences in their training with various teachers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0503.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The time went on and the help offered by the company was neglected some-how, perhaps because of the little or no advancement in the group. Some of the students became demoralized and suspended their studies, and others who did not went to see the dissolution of the band continued the studies.</p>
   <p>Three years ago Professor Cirilo Rodriguez through the friendship of Melesio Espinosa was brought to Gary, Indiana, where another band was being organized and thanks to the skill of Professor Rodriguez, who took the direction of the group,in nine months time the band was inaugurated. The same professor has undertaken the instruction of the Band of South Chicago, and perhaps the small progress that they have accomplished lately is due to his efforts.</p>
   <p>Let this humble note serve to congratulate Professor Rodriguez and his South Chicago Band. Their work deserves praise for their effort, persistence,courage and good-will in trying to conquer the art of music in spite of all the vicissitudes encountered.</p>
   <p>Signed,</p>
   <p>M. E. Mefisco</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
