<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Winnetka Talk</title>,
<date when="1934-04-12">April 12, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Jose Alvarez, Spanish Dancer.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0335</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.A.3.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0335.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (2)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Winnetka Talk</title>,
<date when="1934-04-12">April 12, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">JOSE ALVAREZ, SPANISH DANCER.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jose Alvarez and Mira Soriano are presenting a program of Spanish dances at the Haven School, Evanston, Monday evening, April 23, at 8:30 o'clock.</p>
   <p>Spain's concert dancers will appear in a program of Spanish dances.</p>
   <p>As the chorographic map of the peninsula is particularly diversified, each province and each town has its own ancestral tradition of the dance, such as the picturesque gypsy dance and the joy of the Aragones Iota.</p>
   <p>The further the dancers go, the more their manner divests itself of all that is accessory and tends towards the pure dance.</p>
   <p>It is not always realized by the critic that Spanish dancing has two distinct types and that, although there are dances embodying elements of both styles, the two differ sharply not only in character but in technique as well.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0336.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Senor Alvarez with his beautiful partner, Senorita Mira Soriano, will present the characteristics of Spanish dances and the colorful costumes of his native land.</p>
   <p>He will be accompanied at the piano by Senorita Maria Soriano, who will also play classical selections from the works of Spanish composers.</p>
   <p>Senor alvarez is also a well known teacher. He creates all the dances for his partner and himself and last year taught many of the movie stars in Hollywood.</p>
   <p>He has danced in the movies as well as in the best theaters of America and Europe.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
