<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-05-26">May 26, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Political Activities of Mexicans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0201</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-italian #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0201.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I F 2 (ITALIAN)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-05-26">May 26, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL ACTIVITIES OF MEXICANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John Lord, the young politician of the South Side, who is running as a delegate to the Republican National Convention, is adding many new adherents to his cause each day judging by the good returns which have come in up to this time from his workers in the south part of the city.</p>
   <p>The Italian and Spanish element of the suburb are supporting Lord, because he has been known to take a constructive interest in the affairs of the people and has never failed to aid them in times of need. Lord is being given wonderful support and his triumph in the primaries is taken as a matter of fact, since 99 percent of the Italians and Spaniards, by whom his political ambitions are well known, have faith in him.</p>
   <p>In addition to the above mentioned support Lord can count on the aid of the republican leaders of the "Ward" who see in him a young man who can be a constructive force in the future activities of the party.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0202.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The group which is supporting Lord in his political aspirations are well organized and in a position to cooperate to the end that his triumph may be assured.</p>
   <p>In order to obtain funds with which to defray part of the expenses of this political campaign, the Pro-Lord group has just planned, in all details, an elaborate dance which will take place April 2, in the Lithuanian Hall, 3133 South Halsted Street. This dance promises to be one of the most brilliant and most agreeable affairs which has been witnessed on the South Side for years, because of the splendid publicity which has been given it and the purpose for which it was organized.</p>
   <p>Among our Spanish speaking colony Lord can count many adherents and sympathizers who will not cease in their effort to make his campaign a success. Lord has obtained the good will of these people thru his good work, being the type of man who never refused aid in time of need. For this reason he is entitled to the support of the Spanish speaking people, since it is more beneficial to support a friend than one who is not known.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
