<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-10-27">Oct. 27, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Mexican Swindler Wanted by Police</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0892</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.8"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0892.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-10-27">Oct. 27, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">MEXICAN SWINDLER WANTED BY POLICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few days ago,one of the meanest swindles was revealed in the Mexican Colony through the mysterious disappearance of Jose A. Duran. He had established a fake employment office at 40 South Halsted Street, with the purpose of securing employment for all those Mexicans who wished to leave the city.</p>
   <p>This individual has swindled a large sum of money from more that 200 of his compatriots, who paid him fees for the jobs they were to obtain.</p>
   <p>He cunningly took in a large sum of money and then disappeared. Duran, had distributed cards which explained the various types of work. The lowest wages being $5.00 daily. The locations for the work were in Cleveland, Ohio, in the Navy Yard and dock yard as well as in other cities.</p>
   <p>In view of the hard times, the people naturally grasped at this opportunity, which the swindler offered. The cards that were distributed stated that transportation would be free. The day set for the departure for Cleveland was October 25th. On October 20th, Duran disappeared.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0893.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When the enlisted men went to the Railroad Station to leave for Cleveland, they were informed that the "Deming" whose signature was on each card was an unknown person.</p>
   <p>Convinced that they had been swindled, the Mexicans went to the Desplaines police station. There they were told that everything would be done to capture, Jose A. Duran alias A. B. Deming. Our compatriots are now lamenting over the money they lost.</p>
   <p>It is known, that a short time ago, Duran married an Argentine girl. At the time of his marriage, he was probably short of money. He collected approximately $3,000 before his disappearance. The fees he charged ran from five to fifteen dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
