<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-04-26">Apr. 26, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">The Meaning of Health</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0763</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0763.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-04-26">Apr. 26, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">THE MEANING OF HEALTH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Tuberculosis Institute, of which the Centro Sanitario Mexicano, at 840 South Halsted Street, is a branch, contributes the following article.</p>
   <p>By Clara M. Hayes, M. D. member of the Medical Board and Medical Service of the American Association for Infant Welfare. "May Day makes us remember another problem."</p>
   <p>"The nation eagerly awaits May Day; stimulus to the culminating point of the annual program for Health and Children's Welfare. It is on that day when we get ready to make the children happier, through obtaining better medicines for their health. Do we by any chance remember the more than one million children, between the ages of 10 and 15 who are employed by industry? What a misfortune, that the work and youth have to be associated together! These are among the less privileged and must receive special consideration. This question may be considered from many angles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0764.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These children must have the right nourishment, appropriate clothing, sufficient hours of sleep, and physical examinations to discover those defects susceptible to correction, these things must be done every year. One must insist that the factory or the place where they are employed should not expose them to danger and should allow them the time and place to play. Even after these problems are being solved, we must be sure that the seclusion necessitated by their work and the duties other imposed upon them, do not diminish their vital strength, nor injure their health in general; this would make them physically incapable in their future life. It is the duty of the community to facilitate the work in all its' phases so that the child who works may have sufficient hours of rest and play. Children who have this responsibility must play enough and this should be done under close supervision and guidance.</p>
   <p>In some of the States of the Union, even the time required for school is shortened so as to permit the children to go to work. This deprives these children of the opportunity to read good books, newspapers and reviews and robs them of what we may properly call the most indispensible thing in their education, next to the cultural possibilities and the opportunity to develop their inborn abilities and follow the career they like best.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0765.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Are these our plans for May Day - to reach these children who are overwhelmed with a burden heavier than they are able to carry? Are we doing everything possible to give these children healthier, more robust bodies and a better mental development with which they can ably meet the problems of their youth? Are we trying to give them an opportunity in life, equal to that possessed by those with a higher social rank? Will they through our efforts derive a favorable idea of the justice of our nation for its less privileged class.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
