<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-04-01">April 1, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Mexican Stabbed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0861</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0861.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-04-01">April 1, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">MEXICAN STABBED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday night there was quite a disturbance in the South Chicago Mexican Colony, in which, as at many other times, the razor was brought to play.</p>
   <p>The victim was Mr. Francis Bravo, a man highly respected and well liked in the Mexican Colony. He was the proprietor of the"South American "billiard parlor situated at 92nd street and Brandon Avenue.</p>
   <p>The instigator of this crime has caused other disturbances in the Mexican Colony and is a well known bully from Torrence Avenue, an individual of the daring type usually carrying a knife in his belt. He already has a record in several police stations and is quite well known for his merciless and quarrelsome nature. His name is Jesus Barragan, alias " The Monkey", who, as we have been informed, has already committed a more serious misdemeanour than the one committed Saturday.</p>
   <p>"The Monkey" was playing billiards with another Mexican. Apparently Barragan had been drinking "moonshine" and found himself under its influence.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0862.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since the opponent of "The Monkey" could not have been acquainted with his style of play, a heated argument followed and Barragan drew a barbers razor from his pocket to attack his companion at play.</p>
   <p>Mr. Bravo took notice of the intentions of "The Monkey" and interceded in behalf of the rival of Barragan.</p>
   <p>Barragan would not listen to reason but assaulted Mr. Bravo, giving him several razor cuts on the left cheek.</p>
   <p>Finding himself wounded, Mr. Bravo seized a billiard cue and tried to capture Barragan in order to hold him for the police. However, some of the companions of the "bully" who were in the billardroom ran to his defense and guarded his escape.</p>
   <p>A doctor was called immediately and Mr. Bravo was taken to the South Chicago hospital.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0863.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At this moment "The Monkey" has not been captured. However, it is greatly desired that his whereabouts be discovered and brought to justice so that he may receive his rightful punishment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
