<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-01-30">Jan. 30, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Mexicans Go on Shooting Spree</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0869</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0869.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-01-30">Jan. 30, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">MEXICANS GO ON SHOOTING SPREE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Three Mexicans were arrested and held in custody of the police pending an investigation of the death of officer Louis Szewcyzk, who was shot at the corner of Buffalo Ave. and 90 St. yesterday. The shooting occurred when the policeman, dressed in plain clothes, attempted to question three Mexicans who were passing by.</p>
   <p>Those apprehended were, Max Garcia, 27 years old, 3040 E. 22nd St., accused of being the murderer; Jose Garcia, 26 years of age, of the same address, but not related to Max, and Alfonso Reyes, 29 years old, 8425 Mackinaw Ave.</p>
   <p>Max Garcia was seized by officer Daniel Collins, partner of Szewcyzk, shortly after the shooting. The others, Jose Garcia, and Alfonso, were apprehended and held as material witnesses in the case of the accused.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0870.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Collins, in making a report of the case, said that he and the victim were making a round thru Buffalo Ave. when they encountered a group of three individuals who looked suspicious. When he and Szewcyzk went up to question them, one drew a pistol and opened fire on Szewcyzk, who fell mortally wounded. The trio immediately fled, two of the men running south in Buffalo Ave. and Max Garcia fleeing north. It was then that Collins ran after Max Garcia, shooting at him as he ran, and trying to protect himself from the bullets of the fugitive, who escaped.</p>
   <p>Garcia was finally overtaken in 88 St. and arrested. He still held the pistol in his hand.</p>
   <p>Walter Krause, a chauffeur, 9370 So. Chicago Ave., and Mr. and Mrs. Andrew Anaszewickz, 8837 Buffalo Ave., witnessed the cross-fire and were the ones who took the wounded policeman to the Illinois Steel Company's Hospital, where Szewczyk died a few moments after his arrival. The murdered officer lived at 9332 Colfax Ave. with his wife, Anna, and their five-year-old daughter, <pb facs="5423405_1_0871.jpg" n="3"/>Angelina. His body was taken to the Walkowiak mortuary, 8803 Commercial Ave.</p>
   <p>At present the investigators are trying to disclose what led the accused to commit his crime, and whether it is certain that he shot the officer without the latter having given Max a cause to do so. Collins reported that there was no cause for the crime.</p>
   <p>Szewcyzk was dressed in civilian clothes when he approached Max Garcia and his two companions, and it could have well been suspected that Garcia might have felt that he was about to be a victim of a hold-up. As to the facts of this, we are not sure, because it was not possible for us to talk to the accused.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
