<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-05-13">May 13, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Next Debut of the Light Opera and Musical Comedy Company</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0396</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0396.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-05-13">May 13, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEXT DEBUT OF THE LIGHT OPERA AND MUSICAL COMEDY COMPANY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The director who managed prfessor Paco Perafin and the composer Don Silvano R. Ramos, has informed us that his light opera and comedy company of genius and burlesque will make its debut on the sixth of next month. This affair will be at the Eighth Street Theatre, at 8:30 P. M.</p>
   <p>The manager has chosen for the preliminary showing two well liked works: Gigantes and Cobezudos, a Spanish musical comedy of genius,and Chin Chun Chan, a musical comedy portraying Mexican customs. Adequate publicity has been given these plays because the manager desires to recall to us the happy days of the theatre and inform the public that both of these plays are symbolic of a significant date in the annals of Spanish American theatres.</p>
   <p>Among the principal feminine figures of the company we have Maria and Herlinda de la Vega and also Lupe Plaza.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0397.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Vega sisters because of their training and the gift of art which they possess will, no doubt, know how to carry out their parts. On the other hand the winsome Lupe Plaza, who has distinguished herself by her dances and sentimental songs, will also please the audience.</p>
   <p>We will give further information to our readers concerning this coming event which will be a complete success in the theatre annals of our colony.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
