<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-04-25">April 25, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The New Policy of Hoover</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0221</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0221.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-04-25">April 25, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW POLICY OF HOOVER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The situation created by the attitude of President Hoover regarding more protection for American citizens who venture into foreign countries in search of wealth, has provoked considerable consternation in Wall Street circles. This policy is destined to ruin many American companies engaged in the growth of bananas and other products.</p>
   <p>These interventions, in the guise of protecting foreign subjects, are only designed to disrupt international relationship which exist among civilized countries. Latin-America cannot see any good reason for sending United States marines to her countries as a means of protecting Americans, since such an act is in violation of the sovereignty of any nation.</p>
   <p>The policy observed by ex-president Coolidge during his administration was disastrous for Pan-Americanism, and gave rise to criticisms and accusations against the high-handed methods used by the United States marines, in their dealings with the small and defenseless nations of the Western Hemisphere.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0222.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There is no excuse to justify the presence of a foreign army in a free and sovereign nation. This, more than anything else, whould have been called to the attention of the United States before this time. The intervention, which the United States has exercised in Nicaragua and other Central American countries, presents many difficulties. This not only humiliates a race or nation so interfered with, but also serves as a basis for politicans to sell themselves for Yankee gold. It also causes tyrants and dictators to be set up as protection against whatever movement the marines of Uncle Sam might make.</p>
   <p>People who do not have their absolute sovereignty cannot govern themselves adequately. A good example of this is Cuba, a beautiful nation which is under the bayonets of the marines and the will of the reformer Platt, which is arbitrary and supreme.</p>
   <p>Hoover has set a good example and should continue it. The adoption of a policy of strict neutrality with respect to the business and internal character of the Spanish American nations, will benefit commercially both Saxon and Latin-America, and will strengthen their good relationship.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
