<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scrap Book of Robert C. Jones</title>, <date when="1927">1927</date>. <title>Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1931-04-23">April 23. 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Mexican Recital Spanish Songs and Dances Are Well Received</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0383</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0383.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scrap Book of Robert C. Jones</title>, <date when="1927">1927</date>. <title>Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1931-04-23">April 23. 1931</date>.
<title level="a">MEXICAN RECITAL SPANISH SONGS AND DANCES ARE WELL RECEIVED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Charming Program given at Goodman Theatre. Dances of Spain and Mexico were presented in a highly engaging manner by Clarita Martin and Milla Dominguez, at the Goodman Theatre last night. The two artists had appeared in a similar program early this season, but theirs is the kind of entertainment that is not blunted by repetition. It is a blend of persuasive material, deft presentation, and entrancing costuming, in a program both fleet and smart.</p>
   <p>A great part of the list was unfamiliar. Even the numbers best known have not come into general use. Some of the songs were first introduced by Tito Chipa, some of the dances presented by La Argentina, but these made only a small part of the total. All the numbers were brilliant, all were done in enticing fashion, and all were greeted by hearty and prolonged applause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0384.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mme Dominguez was obliged to add "The Maids of Cadez" to what was announced on her first group and "Clavelitos" to her second; Mme. Martin being a dancer was less able to add extra numbers, but she closed the first half of the program with Valverde's "La Corrida" and at the instance of the audience it was done not once but twice. A mere male cannot be expected to deal exhaustively with Spanish costumes other than to add his tribute to their loveliness. He can, however, express his admiration for the ringing brilliance of Mme. Dominguez's voice, and the sprightly, accurate grace of Mme. Martin's dancing. Together they composed a charming program.</p>
   <p>The recital was sponsored by a group of about twenty ladies of foreign Consuls resident in Chicago, the international relations committee and the heads of a dozen artistical and educational organizations. The guests of honor were Dr. J. M. Puig Casauranc, Ambassador of Mexico, and Mme. Casauranc.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
