<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Eduardo Peralta</title>, 3212 91st Street, Chicago, Ill., by Nicolas M. Hernandez,
<date when="1936-12-11">Dec. 11, 1936</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0636</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0636.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Eduardo Peralta</title>, 3212 91st Street, Chicago, Ill., by Nicolas M. Hernandez,
<date when="1936-12-11">Dec. 11, 1936</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>He said the following: "I am the chairman of the Club Deportivo Yagius, 91st and Brandon. We have 35 members and we meet the first Sunday of each month during the winter, in the summer we meet often. Our Club is an athletic organization, we play baseball, basket-ball, football, and indoor-ball. We have dances about two, or three times a year. There is no educational training, except that which is connected with our line of work. Our Club was founded in 1932.</p>
   <p>We are associated with the Club Deportivo Monterrey, and Sociedad Pro-Mexico. We have no benefit fund in our Club, but we do help our members in case of sickness, or when they get hurt while playing. We are recognized by the Chamber of Commerce of South Chicago, and we are members of the Calumet Region League. We benefit the public, because we give them entertainment without cost. We help Commerce by purchasing all the objects we require in our equipment. Last year in one store alone we spent $237.00 in one occasion. That is doing something, is it not?</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0637.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our aim is to do right in every way possible to the community, and to procure the welfare of our members at the same time. The officers are: Eduardo Peralta, President; Manuel Garcia, Manager; Miguel Hernandez, Treasurer; Lindro Areas, Vice-Chairman; Jose Diaz, Festival Commissioner; Salvador Vallos and Carlos Maravilla, Coaches; Jose Almaguer, Captain. We hold our meetings in the basement of the Mexican Church 91st and Brandon Avenue.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
