<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scrapbook of Robert C. Jones</title>, <date when="1928">1928</date>. <title>Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1928-10-25">Oct. 25, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Provides Aid for Mexican Babies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0768</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0768.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scrap Book of Robert C. Jones</title>, <date when="1928">1928</date>. <title>Chicago Daily News</title>,
<date when="1928-10-25">Oct. 25, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">PROVIDES AID FOR MEXICAN BABIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Daily News Sanitarium works wonders for defective waifs. In that babel of tongues through which moneyless mothers pour out the illness of their children, only the Mexican mother is silent. She makes no headway in the language and has nobody to tell her that Mexican babies who are brought to northern cities escape the bad sanitation of their own country only to miss their one aid to health - sunshine. She knows one thing, however, that of the many children she bears a large number die and Amelia Guerra's mother must have been thinking of it at the Daily News Sanitarium. Anyhow she placed the tiny bundle which contained her baby down on the floor of the winter nursery and pointed to it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0769.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Oh, see the cute little dark-eyed baby". thoughtlessly said some one who came along just then and Mrs. Guerra, hearing it, tried her vocabulary - four words - with gusto. "She near two year, she near two year", the mother said over and over. It was true. Amelia who is so pretty and well proportioned that everybody stops to admire her, was within a few days of two years and weighed less than fourteen pounds. She couldn't walk or feed herself, or even handle a spoon. She seemed when picked up to have almost no bony structure.</p>
   <p>Even yet strangers accept her as a very young baby. In her few weeks at the baby haven she has made no headway, except to gain two pounds. With the aids now being given, she may escape the further development of that rachitic trouble, which depletes transplanted Mexican babies if crowded into dark tenements through a northern winter, A two month old sister to Amelia weighs only four pounds, and a Mexican family in the same neighborhood has four children, none of whom, it is said, is able to walk, because of rachitic trouble.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
