<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-04-18">Apr. 18, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Presence of the Honorable Mexican Consul and a Selected Group</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0402</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0402.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-04-18">Apr. 18, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE PRESENCE OF THE HONORABLE MEXICAN CONSUL AND A SELECTED GROUP</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The festival arranged by the Excelsior Amusement Club was a great success. The affair took place at the Thorp School, and was well attended. Among those present were our distinguished Consul, Mr. Rafael Aveleyra, the Vice-consul, Mr. Adolfo G. Dominguez, Mr. Emilio Almada, Mr. Manuel Hernandez, Dr. Oscar G. Carrera and his wife, and other personalities - among them many Americans.</p>
   <p>For this occasion the Mexican comedy in three acts by Calalina D'Erzell, entitled "These Men" was presented. This play is one of the best we have had in our theatre, and the young people acted their roles exceedingly well.</p>
   <p>Those who distinguished themselves and who received much merited applause were Mrs. Maria de Jesus Farres, who played the part of Azucena; the young man Fernando Cornejo, in the role of Fernando; and Richard Ruiz, in the role of Don Panchito.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0403.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Others who also gained much applause were the lovely Misses Esther Bautista Cruz Garcia, Elvira Ramirez, Leonor Chavez and Mrs. Felicitas Cornejo Luque. The other young men, Augustine Mendoza, Serofin Garcia Joseph Diaz and the well known painter Mr. Francisoo de la Rosa also received merited applause. The guitar duet by the Hernandez brothers was also very pleasing.</p>
   <p>Our honorable Consul, Mr. Rafael Aveleyra gave an address, praising the Clubs efforts on this night and its work in general- especially with respect to its constructive activities in our colony.</p>
   <p>Our well known soprano, Mrs. Milla Dominguez, president of the Blue Cross Club of South Chicago, also took part singing many of our folk songs. The well known actor Mr. Joseph Nieto who is always, very humorous in his parts, which makes him a valued character, merited applause.</p>
   <p>The event ended with a brilliant dance which was prolonged into the late hours of the evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
