<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-03-24">March 24, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Spanish Film</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0562</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0562.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1934-03-24">March 24, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SPANISH FILM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Due to an effort made by persons who are deeply interested in Spanish objects it has been possible to attain for exhibition at the International House Theatre, at 1414 East 59th Street, one of the outstanding Spanish Films. "Spring-time in Autumn" is the title of this film and is conducted by the eximious author Gregorio Martinez Sierra, in collaboration with the 'Fox' house. It shows there, the eminent Spanish actress Catalina Barcena in a series of delightful situations that immediately captivates your feelings. Surrounding the actress is Gilberto Roland (the Spaniard Luis Alonzo) and other Spanish artists who are the favorites on the screen and delight us with their Spanish caste and Latin gentility. Even for those who do not understand the Castillian, the expression is so forcibly that its meaning is made perfectly clear, thus it depends on the voice, gesture and the whole expression being of these artists.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0563.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The grand guitar player Jose Rodriguez takes part on the screen with many excellent numbers and the 'Fox' House has not spared one effort to make out of this picture something that may represent us with art and justice. After having made so many ill-talking pictures in Hollywood, based upon a vain subject with which the Hollywood studios thought they were serving the Spanish speaking countries. This great movie cannot do less than to constitute a spiritual feast for those who are justly proud of our beautiful language and for those foreigners who love the phrases of Lopez and Cervantes. Unguestionably, the victory of some of our good artists in the movies, must influence the Spanish talking pictures considerably, so as to cause this to become a consolidated work with deserving honor for all and at the same time create a new field of development for our artists. But, for this, it is necessary that each one of us who were born in different countries but who are united through the common use of one language shall respond with our adherence every time a good picture is presented in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0564.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mean while we shall protest to the absurd exhibition that fill the stages daily and exploit our nomenclature and characteristics for commercial ends with detriment to us. The International House informed us that unless a large public may attend this Spanish movie, further presentation will be cancelled. Thinking that nothing could damage us worse than a failure of this kind, we make an appeal to you so that on that night this theatre be well packed. And, in this manner we shall thank the University of Chicago, the Salon Espanol and the International House whose efforts will mean a triumph for the Spanish Art. This will he the first decisive victory for all, that is why we ask for the collaboration from all.</p>
   <p>The picture will be exhibited on the 26th an 27th, of March at 4:30 and 8:30 each day. Jose Rodriguez the famous guitar player will be there in person to give a recital Monday at 7:30 P. M. at the International House in honor to the guests of the Salon Espanol of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
