<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview, with Mr. Julie de Diego</title>, Spanish Painter, 508 Grant Place, by Victer Chavez,
<date when="1936-12-16">Dec. 16, 1936</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0321</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0321.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview, with Mr. Julie de Diego</title>, Spanish Painter, 508 Grant Place, by Victer Chavez,
<date when="1936-12-16">Dec. 16, 1936</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Julie de Diego gives his biography in the following terms:</p>
   <p>"I never went to anything that you may call a school. I have learned painting by painting and looking at paintings.</p>
   <p>"The works are very insignificant, but I have ambition. I am always trying to be a painter. I do not know if I am one. People have been, and are, kind in their criticism.</p>
   <p>"I have been in Madrid, Spain, since May, 1900. From the time I was born until, I became 15 years old, nothing eventful happened. I never studied art in any school because my father was absolutely opposed to my painting and drawing. Finally, in 1915, after seeing the Ballet Russe (the Diagelief, Pawlova, Niejinoki, etc. Company) I ran away from home and became the apprentice of a theatrical scenery painter. From that time, on and off, I worked at this kind of painting and interior decoration sometimes without getting paid for it. In 1919 I enlisted in the Spanish army and lost three years <pb facs="5423405_1_0322.jpg" n="2"/>of my life. I was a sub-lieutenant. In 1921 I made my first trip to Paris. I worked at different trades.</p>
   <p>"In 1924 I inherited some money from my father and made my first trip to the United States. A few months later I threw the last quarter from my inheritance from the Woolworth Tower in New York, and the moment I set foot in the street I started to look for a job.</p>
   <p>"I worked in New York doing fashion designs, illustrations, cartoons and decorating churches and cabarets. In 1928 I went back to Spain and studied etching and lithography in the Escuela de Artes Graficas (School of Graphic Arts) in Madrid.</p>
   <p>"I exhibited my work in Madrid, Paris, New York, Chicago. Milwaukee, Dallas and other cities west and east of Chicago.</p>
   <p>"In 1935 I received the Martin B. Cahn prize and also honorable mention at the Art Institute of Chicago at the last American Painting and Sculpture <pb facs="5423405_1_0323.jpg" n="3"/>Show. As may be seen, my life has not been very brilliant as an artist, and I can't give brilliant names as teachers. In fact, I never had a teacher. All I know I have learned from books and by looking over the shoulders of artist friends.</p>
   <p>"In Chicago there is not yet a single art critic. All are just reviewers. No one gives you constructive criticism. They say it is good, it is bad, it is too high, too low. Madre de Dios!</p>
   <p>"When I exhibited in Grant Park the people just looked as if I were a rare specimen and very few bought paintings. You see, I have to make a living and many times I have been hungry. Artists do not fill any need. You have to be an artist to buy an artistic object. The world is interested now in fascism, communism, high wages, low wages, consumption and production. In the meantime, you know we must live and eat every day. Now I have to retouch one of my paintings that belong to the Art Institute. This one has been exhibited in <pb facs="5423405_1_0324.jpg" n="4"/>several cities in the United States, and they want it retouched because it has been mishandled very much."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
