<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-10-20">Oct. 20, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A Doctor Makes Insolent Declarations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0165</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0165.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-10-20">Oct. 20, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">A DOCTOR MAKES INSOLENT DECLARATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Articles such as the one published in the Chicago Tribune, do not foster good relations between Mexico and the United States. This article is a summary of insults by Dr. Goldberg. Such writings inspired by hate and malice and so contrary to truth, jeopardize the good relations between the Mexican and the American people. The quack selects the already ill-treated Mexican as the target of his insults. He said nothing of other nationalities. Here is the article:</p>
   <p>"The Mexican emigrants who cross the Rio Grande in numbers and who multiply very rapidly are not only undesirable but they also constitute a menace to the health of the American people."</p>
   <p>The Tribune said this is a "warning" given yesterday by Dr. Benjamin Goldberg, chief physician of the Municipal Tuberculosis Sanatorium, to the health authorities.</p>
   <p>"Considered from thesanitary point of view, the American industrialists who <pb facs="5423405_1_0166.jpg" n="2"/>import 'cheap labor' from Mexico, saddle on the people of this nation a burden that will not only impair the health but also deplete the pocket-books of the American people unless immigration is promptly restricted."</p>
   <p>Notice that this doctor does not speak of Gypsies, Italians, or Polish. It is the Mexican who comes here to infect them and to steal their money. It is a pity that this quack cannot see further than his nose. When the industrialist and agriculturist of the West and Southwest import Mexican workers he imports at the same time people who are full of susceptibilities. The profit the industrialists make by paying cheap wages is more than counter-balanced by the taxes they have to pay for charitable purposes. The Indian within the confines of the United States soon became infected with the vices of the white man. He was not adaptable to urban life. His race died out without any serious repercussion upon the white man. Dr. Goldberg believes that all the Mexicans are uncivilized Indians and that they still carry bows and arrows. This doctor should be better informed before making such a blunder.</p>
   <p>"Last year out of 7,000 Mexicans who are in Chicago, 68 died of tuberculosis. In 1907, 91 Mexicans came into this country; in 1908, 5,000; in 1911, 18,000; <pb facs="5423405_1_0167.jpg" n="3"/>in 1919, 29,000; and in 1924, 87,000. After that time the regulations of 1924 came into effect but in spite of that, 42,000 entered this country in 1926, and 66,000 in 1927. The number of Mexicans who died of tuberculosis in 1927 was 97.1 per 100,000 against 87.7 per 100,000 which is the average in Chicago."</p>
   <p>The sanitary and social agencies as well as the municipal executives should compile statistics relative to the Mexican immigrants. It is regrettable that Dr. Goldberg should have insulted the Mexican people because many of them have died of tuberculosis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
