<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-12-05">Dec. 5, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0156</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0156.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-12-05">Dec. 5, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few months ago Mr. Javier Mondragon announced in the Mexico newspaper that a Mexican Center would be established in Chicago soon. The object of said institution was to give a mutual and collective aid to the Mexican people in the field of culture and education and to offer an opportunity to the Mexican children to express themselves in sports, art and in other phases of education. This, however, gave us the impression that we would soon see the Mexican colony occupying a place of honor among the other foreign colonies in this modern 'Babylon' called Chicago. The time passed and we heard of this project no more, so, we thought that this talk was just a momentary flame, which lasted only while being discussed. During all this time we were wondering as to the reason for remaining inactive and defenseless amidst a fearful misery affecting many of our homes and outrages suffered by many of our people.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0157.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We had almost forgotten such project and its solution. But, now the Committee is announcing its first public appearance on the night of December 1st. An effort will be made to convince the Mexican of the increasing necessity which compels us to build our own shelter, since we have to suffer in private some racial discrimination. Due to our own negligence, either willingly of forcibly we are compelled to join the public charities. Therefore, we say that only through a strong organization we can,to a certain extent, overthrow the hostile propaganda voiced in some of the newspapers who accuse us of being a burden to the Relief institutions, a menace to the public health, and a hindrance to the estability and advancement of the life of the native worker. One other reason adduced by the organizing committee, is the development of our social life, of which we feel happy because they thought of so important part. After the presentation of this project by the committee, there will be a dance and a real moment of expansion for all. Dear countrymen: Let us form the Centro Mexicano.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
