<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-10-10">Oct. 10, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">The Victim</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0110</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.B.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0110.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 c</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1928-10-10">Oct. 10, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">THE VICTIM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jose Barcenas and his wife arrived here from Mexico full of dreams.</p>
   <p>Jose, at first, was very proud. His income was equal to his aspirations and he praised the day on which he had decided to come here --- But during prohibition, his wife got the idea of making beer at home which could be secretly sold to Jose's fellow workers.</p>
   <p>Barcenas agreed and in a short while his customers increased and his gains multiplied. But while Jose was making big profits, he became the victim of a bad habit. Barcenas began to drink and soon became a habitual drunkard.</p>
   <p>However, because Barcenas had for many years performed his duties well at the places where he had worked, the managers had much sympathy for him and excused his weakness.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0111.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One morning, some time after the 19th of March, Jose went to work in a half drunken stupor. In celebration of his patron Saint he had gone on one of his customary sprees.</p>
   <p>His superintendent assigned him to watch a steam-shovel where shortly after 1 A.M. he was injured. His fellow- workmen rushed to his help and found that he had broken his back. He was taken to the hospital where he had to remain for several months. The hospital, doctor's bill exhausted all his savings.</p>
   <p>When he returned home from the hospital he found three hungry small children and a distressed wife. Reverses continued to increase. Finally one day Jose, died at the break of day. This ended his dreams which he had hoped to realize in the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
