<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-05-20">May 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Handicraft Exhibition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0294</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0294.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-05-20">May 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">HANDICRAFT EXHIBITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The exhibition of handicraft which was held last Saturday, by "The Old Town Boys' Club", is a great testimony of the Mexican boys' talent.</p>
   <p>Among the 400 members who form this club, there are 125 Mexicans, and among the 22 rewarded members, 11 were Mexicans. The prizes were given as follows:</p>
   <p>Paper handicraft. First prize, Augustin Vasquez. Second, Fillmore Schiller and third, David Espinosa.</p>
   <p>Brass works. First prize, Antonio Ojeda; Second, Gilberto Jaime; and third, Pascual Servin.</p>
   <p>Modelling in soap. First prize, James Kendzior; Second, Edward Casper; and third, Isadore Rossof.</p>
   <p>Tin-plate works. First Prize, Abe Rossof; Second, Francisco Nunez; and third W. Levinowitz.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0295.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Drawing. First prize., Delfino Guerrero; Second, Concepcion Moreno and third, Rosendo Mendoza.</p>
   <p>Stamps Collectors. First prize, Jerome Schwartz; Second, John Reindhl and third. Mike Levinowitz.</p>
   <p>Modelling of aeroplanes. First and only prize, Isadore Spector.</p>
   <p>Binding of paper. First prize, Jose Ventura; Second, Mike Nikonsuk and third Jose Toledo.</p>
   <p>The prizes were medals of gold, silver and brass for the first, second and third places, respectively.</p>
   <p>These works are on exhibition at L. Klien's department store windows, 14th and Halsted Street, and at the 12th Street Store, 12th and Halsted.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0296.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Jose Ibarra, a Mexican,is the teacher of soap modelling and wood carving. The following persons were invited in order to obtain the best results:</p>
   <p>Mr. Paco Perafan, Mr. Silvano R. Ramos, Mr. Garza, Mrs. Lupe Plaza and Miss Alicia Villalvaso. All these artists acted according to their art and talent.</p>
   <p>Mr. Guillermo Ortiz presented a interesting collection of linoleum engraving. This kind of work is little known in this country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
