<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>, Vol. VIII. No. 736.
<date when="1933-12-02">December 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">An Open Letter to the Readers of El Nacional</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0530</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0530.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>, Vol. VIII. No. 736.
<date when="1933-12-02">December 2, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">AN OPEN LETTER TO THE READERS OF EL NACIONAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Editor of El Nacional,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>Dear Sir:</p>
   <p>Through your distinguished columns we wish to solicit the cooperation of your respectable readers. Undoubtedly many of them have been reading the articles of the F. L. I. S. published regularly in these columns. And, perhaps some of them may not know that the F. L. I. S. articles come from the Foreign Language Information Service, who prepares them as part of its work to interpret the foreigners to the Americans, and the Americans to the foreigners. The object of this letter is to request the readers of your paper, to kindly inform us,of their opinion about the articles.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0531.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We would like to know if they like them, and of what profit they have been to the average reader. Also, we would like to know, what subject would be best to cover in the subsequent articles. It would be fine if the readers should take this, as a personal letter, and write to us even if it is a postal card, commenting on our service. Our address is Foreign Language Information Service, 222 Fourth Avenue, New York City.</p>
   <p>Perhaps it may be of interest for our readers to know that these articles constitute only a part of the work undertaken by the F. L. I. S. Month after month our organization answers hundreds of letters to foreigners residing all over the United States, who write to us for information and advice concerning their particular problems, be it immigration, contracts, education, etc. The F.L.I.S. also makes an effort to the effect, that the people of foreign origin together with their heredity and cultures be better understood by the North-Americans in general.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0532.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We also aim to prevent the discrimination against the foreign born in regards to employment, to unite the families who are divided due to immigration laws, try to obtain reduction on naturalization fees, and to see that similar measures are taken in furthering the establishment of equity and justice between the foreign and the American born.</p>
   <p>The work of the F. L. I. S. is supported through personal contributions ranging from one dollar and up, to be paid annually. In conclusion may we say, that suggestions and comments from the readers of this paper will be of great help. Therefore we request all those who may be interested in our work to write to us at their earliest convenience.</p>
   <p>Foreign Language Information Service,</p>
   <p>222 Fourth Avenue,</p>
   <p>New York City.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
