<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-06-03">June 3, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">80 Mexicans Arrested</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0851</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0851.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-06-03">June 3, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">80 MEXICANS ARRESTED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>80 Mexicans were seized by the police, last Friday in a pool-room, at 617 West Madison Street. Among the arrested persons some were playing, others were spectators in the pool-room, and others were in a near barber-shop getting a haircut or shave.</p>
   <p>The police arrived suddenly and nobody understood why they acted in this way without motive, arresting so many compatriots. Somebody informed us that a Mexican fellow who was getting a shave, was forced to leave the barber-shop and taken to jail.</p>
   <p>Jesus Cordova was the only one among the arrested able to furnish bail. When he was freed, he went to the Mexican consulate to report this abuse. The Consul immediately began an investigation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0852.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All the arrested remained in their cells until Monday afternoon, when they were conveyed as a group before the judge. Only two men were found guilty, because they carried "Marijuana" cigarettes, in their pockets.</p>
   <p>The pool-room located at 617 West Madison Street, is very much attended by the Mexican people. In this time of crisis many went to play and others to pass the time. Somebody reported this to the police. Many were beaten because they protested against their imprisonment. Twenty were put in a cell in very bad hygienic condition.</p>
   <p>The Mexican Vice-Consul accompanied by the lawyers, Friedman, Elebogen and by the Consulate's lawyer started an investigation. They adduced that the arrested Mexicans had not committed any crime.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
