<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-04-08">Apr. 8, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Victory of the Spanish Amusement Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0690</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0690.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1931-04-08">Apr. 8, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">VICTORY OF THE SPANISH AMUSEMENT CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Amusement Club of the Spanish Benefit Union of Gary, Indiana, announced last Sunday a decisive victory over the "Selection of North Indiana League". It was a hard fought encounter in which the Spanish Club distinguished itself from the beginning to the end.</p>
   <p>Louis and Pacheco were the heroes of the contest. Mike was injured at the beginning of the game but returned during the second quarter. There were two injuries, one for the Spaniards and the other for their opponents. The score was one to nothing.</p>
   <p>This event caused great excitement among the boys of the Spanish team who fought boldly without giving an inch of ground to their opponents, who had been chosen from several clubs with the object of doing all possible to defeat the "impossible".</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0691.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In spite of the fierce resistence put up by the "Selection of the North Indiana League, their defense broke down before the avalanche of the Spaniards. They already had been maltreated in a game in which they were defeated by the German team.</p>
   <p>The game Sunday was very satisfactory from the point of view of the Spanish team, especially when the power of the team which they opposed is considered. The victory was one of the most spectacular we have seen lately.</p>
   <p>On this occasion the Spanish team demonstrated their real calibre and it is our hope that the victory Sunday will be the beginning of a continuous series of triumphs in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
