<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scrap Book of Robert C. Jones</title>, <date when="1927">1927</date>. 5337 S. Ellis.
<title level="a">Milla Dominguez</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0381</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0381.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scrap Book of Robert C. Jones</title>, <date when="1927">1927</date>. 5337 S. Ellis.
<title level="a">MILLA DOMINGUEZ</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A girl who refused the opportunity to be an opera star because "I am Mexican, and to us the home is more important than any career there could be", will sing ancient Mexican, Indian and Spanish songs Chicagoans never heard before, with Mexico's Ambassador to the United States among honor guests in her audience, in recital Friday night, April 22nd, at the Goodman Theatre. She is Milla Dominguez, wife of the vice-consul for Mexico in Chicago, and she will appear in joint recital with Clarita Martin, dancer, who also chose marriage in preference to a career that already had made her so well known as an exponent of old Spanish dances that she was "commanded"to a special performance before the former king of Spain.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0382.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Born in Mexico City, Senora Dominguez appeared for some time as a concert pianist, "because I didn't think I had a voice". Then she began to sing, and later, coming to Chicago to study under Karleton Hackett, won three successive scholarships. When she arrived in Chicago she could not speak a word of English "But in three months", she said today proudly, "I was singing the English score of 'Hansel and Gretel' (with the American Company) without understanding one word I sang". Now she speaks English fluently, having learned it during her stays at Washington, at New York, in Canada and now for three years, in Chicago. She sang for some time with the Mexico City opera, then married and retired. "You can't have a career in opera and a home and husband, too," she says,"so opera was not important to me." For her recital with Mrs. Martin the night of April 22nd, Senora Dominguez has arranged a group of Mexican songs, many of which are not even written but only handed on from one singer to another.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
