<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>La Defensa</title>
      <date when="1936-06-06">June 6, 1936</date><title level="a">Editorial - Let Us Prepare Ourselves</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0042</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0042.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>La Defensa</title><date when="1936-06-06">June 6, 1936</date><title level="a">Editorial - Let Us Prepare Ourselves</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is lamentable, really, the lack of interest shown by the largest number of our Colony for advancement and education. We are in a country where centers of culture exist, schools and colleges, in which one can obtain vast knowledge, in order to emancipate ourselves from slavery. But in spite of this, how few are those who have the courage to overcome the apathy or indifference as it may be called, to obtain certain height. Why? There is no one here to blame. We can not blame the Government, or the Catholicism for our retardment.</p>
   <p>The fault is ours only, as it has been in all times. Dance billiards, drunkenness, girls, etc. Here is the advancement and culture for the youth. It is very near the school term this year, and possibly we may see how small is the number of graduates in the colony. We must not observe this with indifference, but stimulate the youth. The obligation is that of the parents, to procure by all possible means the progress of their children; school and more school if they desire the happiness of their children and the agrandizement of the country. Today when so much is heard of wars, united fronts, and of revolutionary conquests, and many other things on the same order we must fight the enemy No. 1; Ignorance.
   </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
