<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-03-29">Mar. 29, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Mexicans Get Facts about Health Care</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0232</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.M"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0232.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I M</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-03-29">Mar. 29, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">MEXICANS GET FACTS ABOUT HEALTH CARE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. J. B. Medina lectured to the Mexicans living in and around Chicago on March 23rd, 1930 as follows:</p>
   <p>For many years there has existed a certain difference between the Medical and Dental professions with respect to infection and disorder set up in the human body because of teeth decay. However, during the last four or five years a firm alliance and"practice arrangement" has been worked between the two professions, and today they are working jointly in promoting good health.</p>
   <p>The medical profession admit that 70 percent of rheumatism, 50 percent of heart disease, 50 percent of neuralgia and disturbances of the liver and kidneys, many of these maladies proving fatal, are caused by disorder or infection of the oral cavity; that is, the mouth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0233.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the mouth, we not only find the teeth, the decay of which is the cause of suffering and systematic infection, as has been indicated, but besides Gingivitis is set up; that is to say, inflammation of and wasting away of the gums, having the same effect of distruction as pyorrhea. This wasting away of tissue continues into the mucous membrane lining of the mouth, which is susceptible to infections. Then, there is the tongue so important and so liable to cancer in the presence of decayed and broken teeth. Again, the salivary glands whose secretion is so necessary to proper digestion may be effected by disorder in the mouth. A disordered condition in the mouth may and usually does cause infection of the pharynx, called Pharyngitis, an adenoids, the infection of which may cause serious consequences.</p>
   <p>The exercise of the jawbones in the proper mastication of our food is very essential to good digestion. Another essential is that the food remain in the mouth long enough to stimulate the salivary glands and fully absorbe sufficient saliva so that good digestion may take place.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0234.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>From these facts it is clear that sound and perfect teeth are absolutely necessary. A lacking of these means that our food cannot be properly broken up in the mouth. Then when this insufficiently masticated food enters the stomach this organ is upset, in that it has to secrete more than a normal amount of gastric juice to prepare the food for further digestion. The net result is, that in time this most essential organ is damaged causing serious consequences to the body as a whole.</p>
   <p>The formation of a set of teeth begins in the prenatal age. Then in order to assure the unborn baby properly developed and formed teeth, much attention should be given to the diet of the future mother. This means that the diet should be made up of fresh and natural foods, pure water, exercise in pure air, and daily walks outdoors, exposing as much of the body as possible to the sun. The irremissible decalcification of the enamel of a woman's teeth at this important stage should receive the best of care. This can be effected by proper hygienic care of the mouth. There is no reason why so noble a Being should be brought into this world handicapped in its most tender age and suffer conditions which could have been avoided.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0235.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If one is ignorant of proper prenatal care proper advice should be sought in the early stage of pregnancy and before danger becomes serious.</p>
   <p>Children should receive special attention due to the delicate condition of their bodies and to their inability to care for themselves. Proper care to the needs of children in their most tender age will make it possible for them to avoid such maladies as typhoid and scarlet fever, small-pox, meningitis, bronchitis, measles and others generally called childrens diseases. Any one of these may prove fatal or leave the child crippled or otherwise handicapped throughout life. If the child is given proper hygienic care all of these maladies may be avoided. The adult should also see that he himself be well informed on the ways and means of conserving health and with this his happiness and well being in this life is assured.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
