<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scrap Book of Robert C. Jones</title>, <date when="1927">1927</date>. 5337 S. Ellis.
<title level="a">The Mexican in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0630</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0630.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scrap Book of Robert C. Jones</title>, <date when="1927">1927</date>. 5337 S. Ellis.
<title level="a">THE MEXICAN IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Meet Sunday, July 23rd, 2:15 P. M. North Door of Field Museum, Inside Left. Background - 2:30 P. M. Exhibits of Old Mexico - a lecture tour of the fine Mexican exhibits of the Field Museum- to form a basis of appreciation for cultural origins. Spanish and Indian beginnings. Adjustment - 3:30 P. M. Fireman House 1213 Gilpen Place. A social and religious center of Mexican life. Rev. Lacy Simms is director. Mr. Robert Jones, author of the"Mexican in Chicago", and a careful student of Mexican immigration and city life, will speak on "The Mexican in strange surroundings". Art - 4:30, Hull House -Internationally known Settlement House, the produce of the social genius of Jane Adams, a citizen of the world. A conducted tour with special emphasis on Mexican art and crafts.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0631.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Business - 5:00 P. M. South Halsted Street - the way of all nations - Mexicans, Greeks, Italians, Jews, etc. Interesting window displays, strange faces, a panorama of city life - Restaurants, Shops, Employment Agencies. A stop at Esteriro's the trading center for things Mexican. Church- 5:45 P. M. St. Francis Mission Church - an outstanding Roman Catholic institution of Chicago's great West Side. One of the few Churches in the city in which services are held in the Spanish language. Father Rafael Servano is the Pastor. Opportunity- 6:00 P. M. Mercy Center- Mr. Newton N. Smith, Superintendent. A community center of the Methodist Episcopal Church affording social and educational facilities to many Mexicans in this Ghetto area. Mexican Dinner- Real Mexican food consisting of: Frijoles, Arroz, tacos, tortillas, enchiladas and postre. Trends- 7:00 P. M. "The New Mexico, Dr. Garcia Trevino, a physcian familiar with Mexican and American life and one of the most respected members of the Mexican population.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0632.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Folk-Way- A miniature Fiesta- (Dinner and Fiesta sponsored by Club Netzahualcoyotl) Dancing Jarabe Tapatio, Singing corridos, Instrumentals, guitar, banjos, and violin. Fee-$2.00 all inclusive (taxi, good food fine programs, services of Director-none-profit). Make reservations now by writing or telephoning the Director, Russell Delong, 5706 Drexel Avenue, Dorchester 6116.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
