<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Liberal</title>, Vol. I, No. 8,
<date when="1933-08-19">August 19, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Popular Dinner</title><title level="a" type="sub">By J. Xavier Mondragon</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0619</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0619.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Liberal</title>, Vol. I, No. 8,
<date when="1933-08-19">August 19, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">POPULAR DINNER</title><title level="a" type="sub">By J. Xavier Mondragon</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With great success the popular dinner was effected. Amongst the enormous enthusiasm and comradeship we celebrated our first "Popular Dinner" on August 11, at the Puerto de Veracruz Restaurant. We began at 8:45 P. M. at which time most of the guests had arrived. During their arrival an increase in traffic was noticed. At the hour here indicated, a few moments before the plates began to be served, the writer of these lines made the presentation of the Mexican Consul Senor Carlos Palacios Roji, the Vice-Consul Senor Tomas Morlet, Prof. F. Ortiga Rodriguez, and other gentlemen who were specially invited to this popular dinner. Having no other object in mind except to bring together periodically the representative elements of our colony and to bring closer relations of friendship and nationalism which must necessarily be impulsed in the Mexican family outside of Mexico.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0620.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Mexican Consul, the Vice-Consul and Professor Rodriguez took the floor, stressing the necessity of unity and fraternity among the various elements in our  colony. All the guests, very frankly were in favor of the continuation of this <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>. The <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> however was very rich, consisting of "Mole Poblano", tacos, tostadas, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> frijoles, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> desert and Mexican cheese. For drinking, there were beer and coffee. The dishes were very well <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>for her still <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>culinary art. The following persons were present at the dinner, Senor Carlos Carlos Palacios Roji, Tomas Morlet, Consul and Vice-Consul of Mexico, Prof. Fortunato Ortega Rodriguez, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, Dr. Eluid Garcia <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, E. Beristain, Rev. Guillermo <gap unit="char" extent="2" reason="illegible"/> O'Neil, Dr. Jose <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, Jesus M. Martinez, Victor Leon, Jose F. Rivas, Leon Lopez, J. Maldonado, Angel <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>, Antonio Reyes, A. Gomez, Atty, T. Russell Baker, Enrique G. Cervantes, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/>Sanchez Octaviano V. Hernandez, Otilio Rangel Ramon Torres Delgado, Juan Gonzalez, Jose Arana, S. L. Huntley Cartoonist of the Chicago Daily News, E. C. Hernandez, J Xavier Mondragon, Prof. Justino Sanchez Raul Re Gonzales, Mrs. Gonzalez, William Steel Atty, and Mrs. Steel.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0621.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The next dinner will be held during the last week of September and is dedicated to the Mexican Societies of Chicago, each group must send at least three delegates. We are making preparations to that extent and will send the invitations on time. We beg all our friends to pardon us for not sending them invitations, but it was due to the limited capacity of the place where the dinner was to be served. From Indiana Harbor we received several letters from some of our country-men who wanted to come to our dinner, but unfortunately could not attend due to brevity of time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
