<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-05-17">May 17, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">The 13Th of May</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0575</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0575.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-05-17">May 17, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">THE 13TH OF MAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To write a chronicle that may do justice to the exquisite Radio-Program which took place on the 13th inst., it would be necessary to invoke the sonorous and sublime Castillian Language.</p>
   <p>The Spanish Hour which was inaugurated by the newspaper Mexico, and organized by Miss Esther Gonzalez, has been a brilliant success. It was one of those acts which seemed to loose upon the heart, all of those very dear memories, of the beautiful Mother-Land, where the radiant Phoebus cherished our foreheads with its prolific rays in the cheerful days of our youthful existence.</p>
   <p>It was one of those acts which seemed to release a melancholic soul from its mortal prison and transport it to that cheerful home-land, that dear soil which our feet trampled in childhood, that age when all seems to smile, and life is an everlasting idyl of love and illusions. Music!</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0576.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What an enigma! What a natural fascination music has when it recalls many reminiscences of our Father-land, of the little house we lived in, the tender smile of the little girlfriend who would run with us in the back yard, and many hiding places. The trill of the birds that populate our forests, the melancholy waltz which the winds compose upon the crystal keyboard of our gentle rivers, the caress of the incomparable love which our mother gave us in her loving arms, at her breast. The kiss of love with which our first sweetheart scorched our lips in sudden impulse of delirious passion. Everything seemed to reverberate in our mind, making our exile more painful and detestable.</p>
   <p>Miss Esther Gonzalez Lavalle had the natural gift to select such fine numbers for this excellent program. Miss Gonzalez sang "Cicatrices"(Cicatrice) with delicious taste. She knows how to transmit the sweet melodies and the sad complaints of her aching soul.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0577.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Francisco Tortolero sang "Granadina"(Native of Granada Spain). It is sufficient to say, that the distinguished tenor of the silvery voice is a professional singer and one of the outstanding figures of the Chicago Civic Opera Company. The baritone Lopez Chavez, with his sonorous and ever potent voice placed into every note the fire of his youthful and dreaming soul. Mr. Nieto, with his poetic masterpiece. The Misses Navarro - what shall we say now-if spiritism were a reality, I would invoke the spirit of Calderon, de la Barca, or of Becker so they could lend me, out of their rich prose, the fortune of the song and the honey of their poetry, for these are two Panamian stars of first magnitude in the Latin Sky of Chicago. Their jovial character, charming smiles and above all the silvered timber of their mellow voices, the sweet melody with which they sang a dueto made one proud of having being born in Latin-America.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Milla Dominguez sings beautifully and pours into her music such sentimentality that the listener feels that such melodies can only be executed by an angel of Heaven and not by a being who lives on earth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0578.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>What can I say, that could be worthy of Milla Dominguez? I must repeat, like a minstrel "Plates of diamonds are needed - thus- in the fire of the Sun, to moisten the pen."</p>
   <p>Julio Y Agosto</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
