<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Radnik</title>, Vol. IX, No. 83,
<date when="1937-06-07">June 7, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">About the Consolidation of Serbian Benevolent Societies</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0705</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-serbian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0705.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SERBIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Radnik</title>, Vol. IX, No. 83,
<date when="1937-06-07">June 7, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT THE CONSOLIDATION OF SERBIAN BENEVOLENT SOCIETIES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is no doubt that the consolidation of Croatian benevolent societies in the Croatian Fraternal Union influenced the Serbian workers to be interested in the consolidation of Serbian benevolent societies, but the main factor was the material situation and pressure of political facts.</p>
   <p>There were more resolutions in this direction. Lately a society of Ohio sent to other organizations a stronger resolution, which we will bring to our readers for consideration and eventually for action.</p>
   <p>The resolution reads: "To all Serbian benevolent societies and organizations of America. Dear Brethren and Sisters: The situation of our Serbian benevolent associations of America is, to put it mildly, unfavorable. The great, rich insurance companies put obstacles in the way of every benevolent society, also of ours, in the form of claims to have a large reserve fund and other things.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0706.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"After the war in America, through organizations or certain persons, laws are introduced to burden the foreigner regarding his movements and work. To prohibit or limit the organization of foreigners, and to limit and censor the foreign press.</p>
   <p>"Immigration laws are adopted. Many bills are introduced for registration, fingerprinting and photographing of immigrant workers. These bills are before the United States Congress and may become laws at any time.</p>
   <p>"It can easily happen that the right to organize benevolent societies will be taken away. All such actions are directed against immigrant workers, also Serbians.</p>
   <p>"The divergence of our benevolent societies, caused by inimical politics of the old country, the confidence in them lost because of malversations, demand a consolidation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0707.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The consolidation of Srbobran (Serb Defender), Union of Freedom, of the union of conscious Serbians is possible, if all these organizations take the idea in hand and act according to the following points.</p>
   <p>"1. The constitution of a committee of three members for each participating organization.</p>
   <p>"2. That the candidates for such a committee be named by June 1st.</p>
   <p>"3. That the candidates be nominated at regular meetings.</p>
   <p>"4. Elected at the above time.</p>
   <p>"5. The majority of votes decides.</p>
   <p>"6. The committee elected has to (a) examine the standing of each organization, (b) call a convention, (c) prepare everything necessary for such a convention.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0708.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"7. That the elected committee have full freedom of action.</p>
   <p>"8. That the decisions of this committee be valid for each represented organization.</p>
   <p>"Adopted unanimously at the regular meeting on April 11, 1926, by the Society of St. George, No. 80, at Canton, Ohio.</p>
   <p>The coming convention of Serbian organizations must act seriously for the consolidation of all.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
