<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. Maximilian Olay</title>, Spanish Translator and Lecturer, 431 S. Dearborn St. by Victor Chavez,
<date when="1936-12-22">Dec. 22,1936</date>.
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0274</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0274.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. Maximilian Olay</title>, Spanish Translator and Lecturer, 431 S. Dearborn St. by Victor Chavez,
<date when="1936-12-22">Dec. 22,1936</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Olay expressed himself as follows: "I was born in Oviedo, Spain in 1893. Came to the United States when I was eleven years old. My education was only elementary. I worked in New York and in Tampa, Florida as a lecturer in the tobacco factories.</p>
   <p>"I will explain this custom to you. While the workers manufactured the cigars I read to them and informed them of current events.</p>
   <p>"I am and have been always interested in what happens around me, in other words, sociology, etc. interests me.</p>
   <p>"Some years ago I wrote a book "Recovery Through Revolution" in 1933.</p>
   <p>"In 1920 I arrived in Chicago as translator for the Export Magazine of the National Manufacturers Association.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0275.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"This company went under during the depression of 1921 so I started my own "Bureau." At first I translated Spanish but now I translate any language because I have native translators working under me who are very capable and specialize in this work.</p>
   <p>"I lecture in Spanish affairs and labor problems. Since the Civil war in Spain I am chairman of the Committee for the Defense of Spanish Liberties, I believe in the democratic attitude of the government of Madrid and I have tried to help them with my personal contribution as a lecturer and with funds derived from our dues.</p>
   <p>"Because "Edward" loves "Wally" the newspapers are full of headlines; but it takes a Civil war to bring Spanish news to the newspapers; that will explain why I have always tried to inform my audience of what happens there."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
