<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-03-29">Mar. 29, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Lecture of Cuban Consul Feature Mexican Radio Program</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0584</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0584.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-03-29">Mar. 29, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">LECTURE OF CUBAN CONSUL FEATURE MEXICAN RADIO PROGRAM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following is a short speech made last Monday by the Cuban Consul over W C F L during the Mexican Radio Hour:</p>
   <p>To-night, it is with much pleasure that I take advantage of the opportunity which Mexico, triweekly of the Spanish-American life which is published in Chicago, has made for me. I take this occasion to cordially address the sons of the 20 Latin Republics who reside in this city. I also wish to take advantage of this opportunity to congratulate the promoters and managers of these weekly broadcasts for the interest they have taken not only to acquaint those in this country with the sweetness and beauty of our music, but for the plan very fitting indeed of binding more closely the relations which ought to exist among those Spanish speaking countries. Having race ties and similarity of ideals we should endeavor, in the near future to fulfill the wish of the great Bolivar; that is, to form one union Our America.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0585.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Republic of Cuba, whose government I have the honor to represent in this City, desires each day to draw more closely those bonds of friendship, bonds of true love, which have always united us with the other Latin-American Republics. Our Republic aspires to have the sons of these sister lands feel as if they were in their own countries when they might visit ours. Our brother country is deeply concerned with the affairs of its own sons and it considers with enthusiasm and fervour the plan of strengthening and stimulating cordial relations.</p>
   <p>And Cuba, enamored by its liberty and by its sovereignty, which it acquired by suffering and abnegation, feel to-day as yesterday and as it will feel tomorrow, that liberty is but one thing and that thing is the love of democracy, which ought to be understood and practiced with an inclination to a lofty and full concept of social equality. Mexicans or Chileans, Colombians or Peruvians, Argentinians or Equadorians, whatever may be our orgin, our place of birth does not matter, as far as the human concept is concerned we are all equal.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0586.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is because of this that Cuba, on receiving them, does it with wide open arms. She receives them as she might receive her own, mindful of the fact that she receives men and not races.</p>
   <p>The Cuban Republic, also enamored by the ideal of Marti, Juarez, Bolivar and such immortal brothers, only covet and struggle for absolute sovereignty and happiness for all our common brothers. I desire, once more to extend to the editors of the credited and well informed newspaper Mexico, my most heart-felt praise for the spirit of unity and harmony which has been and is being realized in the Latin Colony, and permit me to urge that you do not leave the path which you have taken, for the benefit of our race and our language.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
