<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-02-25">Feb. 25, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago in Bankrupcy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0216</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0216.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-02-25">Feb. 25, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO IN BANKRUPCY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The City of Chicago, this great modern city, pride number two of the United States, is broke, and therefore without a cent to pay its teachers. It is asking for loans and reaching with both hands for it, so as to quiet the swarm of municipal employees who have sent their clamorous cry to the sky and become submissive, what a sacrifice! to continue being tied to a small slice until they see a change in the air. Among us Latin people it is not a novelty to be broke, for, we have never bragged of being rich and potential, thus, our way of thinking is that we have to taste a little of everything, even though if such a taste at times may have the savour of honey mixed with vinegar. The lack of money to pay the teachers, especially those on pension, is so common in our countries that the teachers there have grown callous and learned how to combat hunger, with air.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0217.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To smuggle one's hand into the Municipal or State funds, that also is not new among us. We are used to that and recognize it. The sad part, the unpardonable is, what is happening to this haughty city of Yankee-land, The land of those who never failed as administrators." In our countries they stick their hands up to the wrist, but in Chicago, they have stuck theirs up to the shoulder. At last we are avenged. The title of, "thiefs" that our rulers retained, has been won in a knock-out by our good friends of the North. This time you really have won. I bet you say that, this is a lie. This fits very marvelously into some of those coat-changers of our race who are sold to the idea that every great thing that exists is in the United States. Let them take this pill and if they cannot stand it, let them spit it out.</p>
   <p>Chicago is in a greater ruin that the writer of this and its debts are larger than those that Germany placed upon herself in because of reparations. The evil is attributed to three or four long-handed persons who opened the money bag and stuck their hands into the armpit. That is natural.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0218.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Everywhere those who are on the top get fat. These thieves who wore "spats" and hats seven story high are not from Chicago, the municipalities complain, as much as saying that it is too bad it was not done by Chicago individuals. This is getting complicated and the most practical thing is to let those who entangled this matter straighten it out. If the example of good government is Chicago, let the package remain closed.</p>
   <p>Better than that we have at home, even if no one wishes to believe it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
