<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1929-08-17">Aug. 17, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Federal Agents Act to Curb Crime in South East Chicago and Adjoining Territory</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0872</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0872.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1929-08-17">Aug. 17, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">FEDERAL AGENTS ACT TO CURB CRIME IN SOUTH EAST CHICAGO AND ADJOINING TERRITORY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Scores of prisoners, among them some Mexicans, were taken in a recent raid carried out by Federal Agents in the Calumet District. Many of them are threatened with deportation as undesirable aliens.</p>
   <p>This action was taken by the solicitor of So. Bend, Indiana, for the United States Department of Justice, who has decided to rid the Calumet District of all vice dens and houses of prostitution, even if he has to declare a state of martial law.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, news is current that Gary will be the next objective of the Prohibition Agents who raided East Chicago and Indiana Harbor last Thursday night. The Federal Authorities said that many of these vice dens were operated <pb facs="5423405_1_0873.jpg" n="2"/>by aliens.</p>
   <p>The status of each prisoner will be investigated by the immigration authorities. Those without citizenship papers will be listed. This group will be deported, the basis for deportation being that they are aliens attacking public morals and order.</p>
   <p>The Solicitor from the Department of Justice, Mr. Loomis, speaking upon the subject of the recent raid, said:</p>
   <p>"The condition in East Chicago, judging by the reports of the government agents, are such that the immediate declaration of martial law is not necessary.</p>
   <p>The investigations show that sickness and prostitution are common; that the health of the whole district has been undermined; that gambling was wide open; that immorality was allowed and practiced as indiscriminately as in those days <pb facs="5423405_1_0874.jpg" n="3"/>when the citizens allowed zones of prostitution which were advertised to the public with red lights.</p>
   <p>In addition to this, there were reports on types of so called sport activities which cannot be mentioned to the public.</p>
   <p>This complete breaking down of the moral standard of the district is the result of some years of lawlessness there. However, the bad feature of it is that it has happened by the consent and license of those charged with enforcing law and order."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
