<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. Ignacio M. Valle</title>, Manager Art Store, 39 W. Van Buren Street, Chicago, Ill. by Victor Chavez,
<date when="1936-12-22">December 22, 1936</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0273</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.A.2"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0273.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. Ignacio M. Valle</title>, Manager Art Store, 39 W. Van Buren Street, Chicago, Ill. by Victor Chavez,
<date when="1936-12-22">December 22, 1936</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Valle has the most interesting array of art I have ever seen. He expresses his work as follows: "There we have exclusively Mexican art in clay, wood, leather, feathers, glass, cloth, rugs, hats, furniture, etc. For instance we have these silhouettes much of different kinds of cloth portraying Mexican types, cowboys, girls in national costume, bull fights, etc. Rugs of intricate Maya and Aztec designs. Hand blown blue glass work. Pottery made so as to resemble blue steel as you can see you can not tell it is clay; the meticulous design does not leave any details untouched so it will look like steel. We have leather works, cigarette cases with Aztec and Maya motives. The wood carvings are exceptional pieces of art because of the careful and detailed patterns. We have been commended by the press of Chicago in the beautiful feather work we have. We make birds in their original colors and with their own feathers in different sizes;as pictures, also calling cards. In pottery work we have cooking dishes, table sets, exotic Mexican motives and animal designs; they are grotesque but very amusing and artistic. The Mexican girls are dressed in native costumes.</p>
   <p>"We are trying to make the public anxious of the Mexican art because very few people know the artistic talent of the Mexicans."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
