<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-05-13">May 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Mexican Supports Move for Better Transportation in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0544</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0544.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Mexico</title>,
<date when="1930-05-13">May 13, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">MEXICAN SUPPORTS MOVE FOR BETTER TRANSPORTATION IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>John R. Pelendech, representing the Chicago foreign language press, appeared a few days ago before the city transportation committee. He explained why foreign language newspapers are requesting a new ordinance which would provide for a unified system of transportation, one which would make possible the use of a universal transfer.</p>
   <p>Mr. Pelendech pointed out that a large percentage of those who patronize the transportation companies are foreigners, readers of the foreign language press. These persons, he said own their own homes, and live in the suburbs where rent is low, and they have to wait for hours in cold weather for streetcars.</p>
   <p>Chicago needs a faster transportation service than it has at present. The people who pay taxes are entitled to it. The city has authority to demand that the companies bring their service up to date.</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0545.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Pelendech said that any plan which did not provide for subways would be unpractical. A subway would make possible a rapid and economical service, and at the same time relieve congestion in the streets.</p>
   <p>The foreign press, as a whole, endorses Mr. Pelendech's subway plan because it is believed that not only is this the way to solve Chicago's transportation problem, but it would give work to many who are unemployed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
