<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>La Defensa</title><date when="1936-11-21">Nov. 21, 1936</date> Vol. 2 No. 46
<title level="a">"What Fred Chavez, says".</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0815</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-mexican"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0815.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>LA DEFENSA</title><date when="1936-11-21">Nov. 21, 1936</date> Vol. 2 No. 46
<title level="a">"What Fred Chavez, says".</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The young assassin related his life story and motives which caused him to commit the crime. Last Tuesday after considerable efforts, a representative of "La Defensa" was permitted to see Federico Chavez, who is now waiting for trial for the murder of his 16 year old wife, and his mother-in-law. The interview took place in the County Jail, and after our reporter told him the object of his visit, Federico manifested good will in giving him the intimate details of his brief and tragic matrimony. Federico, appeared to be as a school boy who is being punished, but to whom the disiplinary measures taken to correct his ill tendencies don't matter in the least. Federico Chavez is 21 years of age, 5 ft. 6 inches tall, black eyes, short nose, without any beard and weights 126 lbs. Federico voluntarily related to our reporter what he thought had been of utmost interest in his life. He was born in San Antonio, Texas, in the year of 1914, his father and mother were Mexican immigrants, his mother died when he was 3 years old, and he was raised by his grand mother on his mother's side. His father, after becoming a widower, went further into the United States looking for work. When Fred was just a kid he used to carry a shoe shine box, and shine shoes in the streets, in <pb facs="5423405_1_0816.jpg" n="2"/>order to help his grand-mother to support him during which time he had a chance to associate with bad companions. When Federico was 15 years old, he was arrested together with a boy older than him, because the police found them in possession of a stolen suit; and a considerable amount of money. Both were unable to explain how they had obtained the suit and money and Federico was sentenced for 15 months to the school of correction. After Federico served his term, his father, who was already in Chicago, sent him some money and told him to come to Chicago, but since his father was again married, he could not get along very well with his step-mother. Federico then had to go to an uncle on his mother's side who also was in Chicago, and it was the latter who supported Federico and sent him to school, but he did not finish the grade school. Federico's efforts to find employment were unsuccessful on account of the industrial crisis. Federico's best record of employment, is a 3 months period during which he worked as a kitchen helper in a restaurant located at 63rd and Dorchester Ave. Outside of this he has worked whenever and whatever he could find to do. He was 21 when he met Aurora Rodriguez, a 15 year old girl, who was at that time attending the San Francisco Parrochial School. Aurora's mother opposed the relations of her daughter with Federico in view of this fact, Federico urged Aurora, to leave <pb facs="5423405_1_0817.jpg" n="3"/>her home, and go with him to which she acceded. Four days after they eloped the Juvenile authorities, held the girl but her mother gave her consent to the marriage which had been already performed at Crown Point, Federico's father paid the expenses connected with the marriage and offered his home to the young couple. The honey-moon was very bried, and shortly after the difficulties with authorities ended, the dissentions, between husband and wife started, and Frederico's father was forced to tell them to leave his house. The couple established their home in an apartment house on Morgan Street, in which even the most indispensable means of life were scarce. About three months after the marriage, Federico took his wife along and went to Garry, Indiana, looking for a job.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
