<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-03-26">Mar. 26, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">The Plight of Two Mexican Girls</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423405_1_0896</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-spanish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0896.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SPANISH</item>
     <item>MEXICAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>El Nacional</title>,
<date when="1932-03-26">Mar. 26, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">THE PLIGHT OF TWO MEXICAN GIRLS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The disappearance of two Mexican girls has caused consternation in the Spanish-American colony of Chicago. They were daughters of two very well-known and socially prominent families here.</p>
   <p>Yesterday morning the news came to this paper through Mr. Lacy Simms, one of the editorial staff, that the young women who disappeared were Fernanda Rodriquez and Remona Talamantes, 17 and 18 years of age respectively, who lived at 2522 South Lowe Avenue.</p>
   <p>The following account of the disappearance of the two young people was given to the editor of El Nacional: "My name is Refugio Rodriquez and I am the father of Fernanda. Because of the difficult situation in which we found ourselves, my wife and I permitted our daughter at the close of last year to accept a position which had been offered to her by a company which was then publishing a Catholic magazine. The company provided regular remuneration to agents who represented it. If I remember correctly this firm of publishers is known as the 'Crosier Missionary,' with offices on the north side of the city."</p>
   <pb facs="5423405_1_0897.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Do you feel that you can give us particulars in connection with the disappearance of your daughter?"</p>
   <p>"I have reason to attach importance to some details and incidents which occurred during the time my daughter was working for the company to which I have referred. On a certain occasion, Fernanda, who never kept secrets from me, mentioned that an individual who was one of the personnel of the firm for which she worked had offered her money, and that she had refused. This man was an American who molested her daily, she said.</p>
   <p>"My daughter is very friendly with her neighbor, Ramona Talamantes, a young woman who is worthy of the highest respect, and with whom she worked at the 'Crosier Company.' The parents of this young woman are intimate friends of my family."</p>
   <p>The public authorities have been investigating the case for three days. They have been checking the personnel at the "Crosier Company," for the man who answers the description of the one who Miss Rodriquez claims molested her. They are also looking for another individual of Mexican nationality who goes under the name of "Rodgers," who it has been found sought the friendship of <pb facs="5423405_1_0898.jpg" n="3"/>Fernanda. No further progress has been made in the investigation of the case up to today.</p>
   <p>The parents of the two young women fear for their safety, because of the bad social conditions in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
