<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-01-03">Jan. 3, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Our Program</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0644</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0644.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-01-03">Jan. 3, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">OUR PROGRAM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The time is here for newspapers to announce their program, and the Svenska Nyheter is following the tradition established by its colleagues in Journalism.</p>
   <p>The people demand it - demand that once a year the newspaper speak of itself, as throughout the year it is speaking for itself.</p>
   <p>Irrespective of consequences, the Svenska Nyheter will, in the present year as in the past, remain independent and impartial in every field and in regard to everybody. When we make our hardest fight in favor of the sons of toil, those who carry the heavy load underneath a broiling sun, the reason is that we are strongly convinced of the justice in the demand for life's comforts, made by the producing masses, and we endorse the old saying, "He who will not work should not eat."</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0645.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If we be blamed for not joining, with youthful ardor, in the battle between the political parties, our defense is that the party interests are being pulled down into the mire by vote-sellers, and the ideals are being overcast with mud by the leaders. For these reasons, we consider it degrading for a representative of the press, who still maintains the ideals of the press, to join the fight in those lairs.</p>
   <p>If, in the work for enlightening the people, we do not join hands with the religious leaders, the reason is, that, in our opinion, these leaders deviate from the road which leads to light and life.</p>
   <p>Svenska Nyheter will remain as many sided as possible. In addition to the latest news from Sweden, and reliable domestic and foreign reports compiled from interesting information from near and afar, we will present such special departments; as, "Questions of Law"; "Woman and the Home"; "Among the Sons of Toil"; "Portrait Gallery of Swedish-American Singers and Musicians"; etc. We value scientific and literary endeavors, and <pb facs="5423404_3_0646.jpg" n="3"/>gladly make space for such activities. Our literary serials are more richly supplied than in any other Swedish-American newspaper. Our editorials are kept in strictly individual style, and are written to and for the people, invariably treating the most stirring questions of the day. We believe the people capable of doing their own thinking; we desire them to think straight and along broad lines, and to act in accordance with such thinking. Ever shall we fight those who would be the mental and political guardians of the people, in other words, those who would become the oppressors of the public.</p>
   <p>Svenska Nyheter is opposed to lotteries of any type, including the various guessing contests which create, among the subscribers, hopes which from the very inception are doomed to fail. We want new subscribers; but rather than gain them by dishonorable means we would cease as a newspaper......</p>
   <p>Svenska Nyheter costs only one dollar per year. We do not make any excessive promises for the future; we do not offer any "valuable premiums." We know our worth, and we invite the Swedish-American people to take advantage of our offerings.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
