<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-02-27">Feb. 27, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The Young Woman's Friendly Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0926</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.D.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0926.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I D 2 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-02-27">Feb. 27, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE YOUNG WOMAN'S FRIENDLY CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Young Woman's Friendly Club is the name of a society which was organized among the servants girls of Oak Park last Thursday. The society's aim is to awaken interest in the community; place the members in a position to be mutually helpful; prepare an opportunity for them to take up useful broadening studies, and to work for the recognition of those worthy, who are engaged in social endeavors. Besides this, to help the needy outside the organization.</p>
   <p>The club's annual meeting will be held the first Thursday in October, and regular weekly meetings will be held the first and third Thursday of each month.</p>
   <p>At the weekly meetings, a program of literary and musical endeavors will be held, when various questions will be discussed, and subjects to broaden interest will be approached by speakers invited for that purpose.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0927.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the first meeting the club members have as their subject for study and consideration: "India, and her People."Mr. Frank Moore, librarian at the Scoville library will lecture. India is of special interest to the members since it is their purpose to aid the native-born Hindu Missionary, Premdita Ramabai, in her work among the young widows of India.</p>
   <p>About twenty servant girls joined the organization at its first meeting. Among them were the following: Ada Stackelberg, Annie Anderson, Mary Lyman, Jennie Olson, Sophie Larson, Mary Anderson, Alma Larson, Christine Rosdell, Agnes Carlson, Ida Peterson, Louise Haglund, Ida Knut, Clara Vigren, and Freda Qwiberg.</p>
   <p>A large number of girls have given notice that it is their aim to join the organization, and it is expected therefore, that the membership will soon be quite worthy of notice.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
