<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-05-16">May 16, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Tribune Sold</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0636</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0636.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-05-16">May 16, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH TRIBUNE SOLD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Early last week the Swedish Tribune, together with the paper Fosterlandet (The Fatherland), was sold to Mr. Charles F. Erickson who had resigned as advertising manager of the Svenska Nyheter a few days ago. Mr. J. E. Norling, the former owner of both papers probably considered it desirable to sell because several important industrial undertakings in which he has large interests, claim all of his time.</p>
   <p>Mr. Erickson, the new owner of the papers, is an energetic and progressive man, comparatively young, of liberal tendencies, and of unusual capacity for work. He has not been carried onward in the world on the arms of others, but has made his own forward course, and in so doing, has left many pleasing impressions of his activities in the commercial life.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0637.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Erickson was born in Halleberg in Vestergotland, Sweden, May 6, 1866. (He bought the paper on his birthday, although this was not learned until later.) In the year 1887, he came to America and for a time stayed in Marinette, Wisconsin, after which he came to Chicago and took the position of advertisement agent for the daily Scandia. During the years 1891-92 he held a position in the circulation department of the Record-Herald, then left for Omaha, Nebraska, where he vigorously entered politics. The party which he acknowledged as his, without consulting him, and against his wishes nominated him for state comptroller. He was beaten at the election, but, as it is expressed in the beautiful Swedish-American language, he "runnade ahead of ticket'en" (ran ahead of the ticket). During the exposition in Stockholm in 1897, he was recommended to the United States Secretary of State as commissioner to the exposition, by the board of directors for the exposition to be held in Omaha the following year. He received the appointment,<pb facs="5423404_3_0638.jpg" n="3"/>and at the exposition in Stockholm made observations which greatly benefited the directors of the Omaha exposition the following year. Mr. Erickson was also appointed to observe the Brussel's exposition later in the same year, but he declined the appointment with thanks.</p>
   <p>In 1899 he came once more to Chicago and was given a position on the Swedish Tribune, the paper he bought a few days ago. When shortly afterwards, the paper was sold to Mr. J. E. Norling, Mr. Erickson sought a new field for his activity and accepted the position as advertising manager for the Svenska Nyheter. This position he held till a few days before buying the two papers mentioned above.</p>
   <p>In 1895 Mr. Erickson married Miss Selma Dahlstrom, a daughter of a railroad employe in Omaha, Mr. A. G. Dahlstrom, well known throughout the Middle West.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0639.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>His married life has been happy from the start. There are two children, a boy seven, and a girl five. Mr. Erickson is a member and director of the Swedish Glee Club; member of Svithiod Singing Society; of the King Oscar Lodge of the Masonic Order, and of some American clubs.</p>
   <p>Svenska Nyheter wishes Mr. Erikson luck and good progress in his course as a newspaper publisher, a course frequently troubled and difficult.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
