<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-07-27">Jul. 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Editor Johan Person is Dead</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0560</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Split transcription from 5423404_3_0556, where pp. 2-4 were included, and added transcription for p. 1.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0560.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-07-27">July. 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">EDITOR JOHAN PERSON IS DEAD</title>
[Half-tone, one column--fifth of a page, full-face picture of editor Johan Person]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Johan Person, editor of the Svenska Kuriren, died July 19 in the Bowmanville Hospital here, at the age of fifty-three. He had been in poor health for the past few years, and only his remarkable will power enabled him to go on with his work, the major part of which he was forced to do at his home. About three weeks ago, he became so seriously ill that he had to be taken to the hospital, where he died from a brain infection.</p>
   <p>Johan Person was born in Asarum, Blekinge, Sweden, March 19, 1868. He went to school in Karlshamn, and later attended the Vaxjo Gymnasium for a couple of years. His desire to get into newspaper work caused him to break off his studies, and in the course of events he came to America in 1887. After having worked at a variety of jobs here, he finally became associated with the Swedish-</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0561.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>American press in 1895 by contributing articles, poems, and translated novels to the Svenska Tribunen. Later, he joined the editorial staff of that paper. Since then he has been either editor or on the staff of the following newspapers: Skandinavia, Worcester, 1899-1901; Svenska Folkets Tidning (The Swedish People's Journal), Minneapolis, 1901-1903; Svenska Kuriren (The Swedish Messenger), Chicago, 1904-1909; Svenska Amerikanaren (The Swedish-American), Chicago, 1909-1910; Vestkusten (The West Coast), San Francisco, 1911-1912; Svenska Amerikanska Posten (The Swedish-American Post), Minneapolis, 1912-1913; Svenska Kuriren, 1914-1921.</p>
   <p>Person contributed to many Swedish-American newspapers under the pen name Cornelius Corncob. His column, "The Evening Pipe," had to be discontinued during the war because he stepped on the toes of certain narrow-minded bureaucrats. After the war, he contributed to the Canadian Forum.</p>
   <p>He also published two books printed in Swedish: In Swedish America (1900), <pb facs="5423404_3_0562.jpg" n="3"/>and Swedish-American Studies (1912), in which Swedish-American life is depicted.</p>
   <p>With the death of Johan Person the Swedish press in America has lost one of its ablest men. He was never strong physically, but in spite of that handicap he enriched Swedish-American newspaper literature as few others have done. Had he not been so busily occupied with routine work, his talents as a writer and storyteller would undoubtedly have found a wider scope than they did. His was what is termed a "sharp" pen, but the satire which flowed from it was mixed with a never-failing humor of a somewhat pessimistic tendency. In his writings he displayed an intimate knowledge and understanding of Swedish-American life in all its phases. In addition to his excellent prose he also wrote some very fine poetry, which revealed a sensitive mind appreciative of the beauties of life. He will be remembered as a physically weak but spiritually great man.</p>
   <p>A reserved and sensitive man, he did not acquire a large circle of friends, <pb facs="5423404_3_0563.jpg" n="4"/>but the few friends he did have admired and loved him. His wife, who was Betty Swenson, and a brother, Axel Person, of Chicago, survive him.</p>
   <p>A large number of Swedish-American newspapermen attended the funeral services in the chapel at Rosehill Cemetery, and editors of six Swedish publications in Chicago were pallbearers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
