<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1916-02-03">Feb. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1308</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1308.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1916-02-03">Feb. 3, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.11.............Scandia Life Insurance Company, held its 10th annual meeting last week here in Chicago. Over fifty of the company's General Agents from Illinois, Iowa, Nebrasks, Minnesota, North and South Dakota, Michigan and Connecticut were present. The agents meeting was held Tuesday and Wednesday at La Salle Hotel, where the company last Wednesday gave a banquet for its agents and others interested. At the banquet, the company's president Mr. N. A. Nelson, expressed the company's appreciation of the splendid work performed by the agents during the past year, whereupon he gave the word to the company's vice president, legal adviser and chief of the agent personal, Mr. Edwin A. Plsen, who then assumed the duties of the evening's "master of ceremonies." After an invigorating speech, in which he told of the company's accomplishment and what great things they were looking forward to, he introduced Judge Rufus Monroe Potts, Life Insurance Inspector for the State of Illinois. Mr. Potts confined his speech to insurance and particularly praised the company's splendid financial situation. He also advised the agents to invite <pb facs="5423404_3_1309.jpg" n="2"/>prospective clients to write to the State's Insurance Department, in case any doubt arose as to this company's ability to meet its obligations. The next speaker was Mr. Henry S. Henschen, Director of The State Bank of Chicago, who spoke on the necessity of life insurance for all, rich or poor.</p>
   <p>The former corporation counsel of the state Mr. Edward J. Brundage and the former insurance inspector Mr. Fred W. Potter, delivered forceful addresses. All participants at the banquet were presented with silver cuff links with the initials of the Scandia Life Insurance Society engraved upon them.</p>
   <p>The policy-holders' meeting was held Thursday at LaSalle Hotel. Reports from the president, secretary, treasurer and auditing committee were read and received with enthusiasm. The reports showed, the company had enjoyed a most successful year. New policies were issued amounting to nearly $6,000,000.00, receipts increased with $300,000.00 and net profits with more than $50,000.00, total insurance in force was $23,000,000.00, gross receipts were $2,110,000.00 and cash on hand $554,000.00.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1310.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>At the meeting five directors were to be elected. The retiring directors were: Charles E. Walin, Minneapolis, Minnesota; A. G. Anderson, Fergus Falls, Minnesota; T. F. Northwall, Omaha, Nebraska; A. J. Lawrence, Paxton, Illinois, and Theodor Freemon, Chicago, Illinois, These gentlemen were all unanimously re-elected as directors.</p>
   <p>After this meeting the Board of Directors came together and elected the following officers: President, N. A. Nelson; Vice President and Legal Adviser, Edw. A. Olsen; Secretary-Treasurer, C. H. Boman; Chief Surgeon, Dr. Wm. A. Peterson; Actuary T. L. Grimes.</p>
   <p>Judging from all reports, the work progresses steadily and all indications are, that 1916 will be a successful year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
