<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-05-29">May 29, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Interesting Lecture</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0913</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0913.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-05-29">May 29, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">INTERESTING LECTURE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.11....................An especially interesting lecture was given by the widely traveled editor of Jamtlands-Posten (Jamtland-Post), V. Hugo Wickstrom, Ph. D. on the significant subject "Varer Svenske" (Be Swedish) last Sunday afternoon at Phoenix Hall, 324 East Division Street, before an unusually large and attentive audience. In a concise, biographical talk, Editor Jakob Bonggren introduced the already well-known lecturer to the large audience, which welcomed Dr. Wickstrom with applause on his appearance. The lecture began by expressing his longing to meet his many countrymen in America, a longing which he found so much more justified since America now has nearly half as many descendants of the sons of the North as old mother Svea herself.</p>
   <p>Then he began to expound his subject: "Varer Svenske" (Be Swedish) and said that this was an exhortation which concerns countrymen here as well as in Sweden. As a speaking proof of the possibility of remaining Swedes, even in a foreign country, and an example worthy of being followed, he now held up the little Swedish colony, <pb facs="5423404_3_0914.jpg" n="2"/>Gammal Svenskby, down on the Black Sea's shores in South Russia. In an entertaining manner the speaker depicted the colony's history, describing how the Swedes in Gammal Svenskby (Old Swedish Village) preserved the Swedish language, the Swedish outlook and not so few of the Swedish customs in spite of the fact that they have been pressed from all sides. If the Swedish people's origin has any meaning, if cultures hearth has any birth-right, then, even "the good Swedish" should be preserved,the speaker said, and held up in this connection that middle and Southern Sweden,according to newer investigations, is the original home of the Aryan people. Sweden, he pointed out, has never been conquered by foreign people, its old mythology is profounder and nobler, its conception of the right is cleaner, its laws better and its history greater-in-kind than any other people. In regard to spiritual culture, Sweden takes its place among the world's noblest nations, likewise, also, its learned men are counted among the world's greatest. The language of the Swedish people is sonorous, its literature is beautiful, its arts are recognized, and its schools are superior. For these reasons, and many othere, which were touched upon, the speaker said "the good Swedish" should be preserved. Toward the end of the lecture the speaker told how important it was for Sweden that "the good Swedish" be preserved in <pb facs="5423404_3_0915.jpg" n="3"/>this country. Threatening times were near for the old country, and then the native-land would need both spiritual and material aid from the Swedish people in America. The lecture closed with a warm greeting from the native-land to its sons in the far West. Besides the lecture, on the program, there was a beautiful baritone solo by Christ. Brusell, two well-rendered violin solos by Miss Appelon, and a pair of arresting songs by Miss Elina Malmborg. Dr. Enander thanked the lecturer on behalf of the audience, and sent greetings to the beloved native country in the high North, through the lecturer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
