<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1919-01-30">Jan. 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Scandia Life Now Named "Mutual Trust Life Insurance Company"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1919-01-30">Jan. 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDIA LIFE NOW NAMED "MUTUAL TRUST LIFE INSURANCE COMPANY"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual meeting of the policy-holders of the Scandia Life Insurance Company was held at the Hotel La Salle on January 23. It was made known that the year 1918 was the best year in the history of the company.</p>
   <p>New insurance for the year totals over twelve million dollars. Premiums now total $3,694,317.62, and the amount of insurance in force is over thirty seven million dollars. The net surplus is more than $407,639,13.</p>
   <p>The directors,whose terms have expired are: Charles E. Wallin of Minneapolis, Minnesota; A. G. Anderson of Fergus Falls, Minnesota; A. J. Lawrence of Paxton, Illinois; C. E. Johnson of Galesburg, Illinois; and Andrew Klingman of Chicago, Illinois, were all re-elected for a term of three years.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1305.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>One of the more prominent business matters concerned the change of the name of the company. In regard to this question, the president of the company had the following to say in his yearly report: "Some one may ask, perhaps, this question: 'Why must the name be changed?' The answer is simple enough. We live and operate exclusively in America. This company should, therefore, have a modern, American name, a name which needs no further explanation. Broadly speaking, it does not matter much what kind of name a company carries, but it may happen that a name is misinterpreted, which often leads to erroneous conclusions. "Scandia Life" is certainly a good name, but it has often been responsible for the idea that it is a foreign company. For this reason, the policy-holders have deemed it wise to change the name. The change will have no effect whatsoever on the insurance policies taken out before this date, and no evidence of identification is necessary either."</p>
   <p>When the resolution regarding the change of name was placed before the assembly every vote, a total of 449, was in favor of the change. Thus, <pb facs="5423404_3_1306.jpg" n="3"/>"Scandia Life" hereafter will be known under the name of "The Mutual Trust Life Insurance Company."</p>
   <p>After the meeting the directors convened, and re-elected the same officers for the next year, namely; President, Nils A. Nelson; vice-president and adviser in legal matters, Edwin A. Olson; secretary-treasurer, C. H. Boman; company physician, Dr. William A. Peterson; actuary Irvin L. Grimes.</p>
   <p>In the evening, the yearly banquet was held at the Hotel La Salle. More than one hundred agents from ten different states participated. The president of the company introduced the vice-president, Edwin A. Olson as master of ceremonies. The various speakers were; L. A. Anderson, actuary at the Wisconsin Insurance Department; Congressman Carl R. Chindblom, and Rev. M. E. Borders, Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1307.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>During the year 1918 the disbursements have been unusually large, due to the large number of deaths, as has been the case in other life insurance enterprises, also. But "Scandia Life" has already had an adequate surplus on hand so the company went through the influenza epidemic with flying colors.</p>
   <p>The company maintains the same rate of premiums which falls due next May 1. During the year 1919 the company hopes to issue new insurance for not less than fifteen million dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
