<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-04-17">Apr. 17, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Colony of Mercy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1332</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1332.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-04-17">Apr. 17, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE COLONY OF MERCY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have received the following letter in behalf of the new charitable institution, the Colony of Mercy:</p>
   <p>"The attention of Swedish organizations, as well as individuals, is being attracted increasingly to the Colony of Mercy. In the beginning, most people considered the plan too ambitious ever to be realized. But the idea was longingly cherished, and one could only admire the courage of Pastor Elof Johnson, who never lost faith.</p>
   <p>"But this impossible idea has now taken hold among the Swedish-American public here, and especially among the pastors of the various Swedish congregations. Several meetings have been arranged, and the enthusiasm is mounting. Last Monday, a well-attended meeting was held in the Morrison Hotel at the initiative of Emil Skoglund, who is one of the originators of the plan. Many new charter members have signed up, and have donated one thousand dollars each to the proposed Colony. It is hoped that after the <pb facs="5423404_3_1333.jpg" n="2"/>Easter holidays the movement will gain added momentum.</p>
   <p>"As most of the Tribunen's readers already know, the plan consists in establishing a charitable institution which will receive incurable Swedish-American patients, mental cases, and persons who are convalescing from severe illnesses. It will be located in the vicinity of Elgin, Illinois. Those who wish to contribute to this humane cause may present their donations to the pastor of their own church, who will forward them to the Finance Committee, or they may send their contributions directly to Pastor Elof Johnson, 1650 Foster Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
   <p>"Let those of us who enjoy good health, and other of life's blessings, get together and help our less fortunate countrymen! And who knows? This home may well open its doors for any of us some time."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
