<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-09-17">Sept. 17, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">What Does the Swedish National Society Accomplish?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1175</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1175.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-09-17">Sept. 17, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT DOES THE SWEDISH NATIONAL SOCIETY ACCOMPLISH?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The above question is asked daily by various persons. Instead of asking this question they should investigate for themselves, but they go through life with closed eyes. The best opportunity to find the answer is to become interested in the activities and achievements of the society, which seems to be, strangely enough, better known to the American institutions of charity than to the Swedish-American societies of Chicago.</p>
   <p>You will not believe it if I tell you that the society secured employment for about six thousand men and women within a year, because you cannot understand that in this egotistical world people can be found who have sympathy for the suffering and the needy.</p>
   <p>Neither will you understand if we say that thousands of dollars are spent freely for food, coal, etc., for the unfortunates who have lost the battle for the almighty dollar, and who are in need of bread.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1176.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Swedish National Society renders assistance and service as far as it is able to do so. Any one in need of help and desiring it, is given assistance: The aged are placed in Old People's Homes; the incurable sick are placed in charitable institutions best suited for them; those afflicted with tuberculosis are sent to better climates; and release is obtained for those who are sent to prison innocently. Now you may understand that the society can carry on this work with your friend's help. With every ticket you buy for the society's summer or winter festival, you help us feed the hungry, clothe the naked, and house the homeless. When you sit in the theater and watch the performances of the pretty actresses, somewhere on the North, South or West Side a little old lady eats her bread with tears of gratitude. These tears of gratitude belong to you, because you have helped her to this bread. As often you come to our festival, just as often you help the poor unfortunates to food and milk, as well as to fuel.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>Svenska National Forbundet</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
