<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1916-07-27">July 27, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">[Summer Festival]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0297</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0297.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1916-07-27">July 27, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">[SUMMER FESTIVAL]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 12....The Swedish National League's "summer festival" in Riverview Park last Sunday was favored with beautiful weather and a great "turn-out."</p>
   <p>The "weaker sex" was very much in majority particularly after the sun had gone down and the temperature permitted dancing.</p>
   <p>The "festival" began in the early afternoon with a short welcoming speech by the "League's" president, Mr. O. S. Ohlander, who later introduced alderman, J. E. Tyden, who, after his speech, assumed the roll of "master of Ceremonies."</p>
   <p>The speech of the day, which one would expect to be made by a Swede, as this day is called "Swedish National Day", was made by the well-known reform advocate, Professor C. E. Merriam, - a member of the city council. He made a very fine speech, which was well received. This was followed with music from Svithiod's Orchestra and folkdances by the dancing-club "Frihet" (Liberty). The "Swedish Singers' League," under the direction of Mr. Gustaf Carlson, sang a few unusually well rendered song-numbers <pb facs="5423404_3_0298.jpg" n="2"/>which were particularly well received. A little later an exhibition was given by a company from the "Svithiod Lodge" and one from the "Hildur Lodge" as well as by the parade companies of "Valkyria Lodge No. 1, "I.O.L.V." directed by Mrs. Hulda Magnuson, and "Hildur Lodge No.3,"L.I.O.S." under the direction of Mrs. Larson.</p>
   <p>The most interesting part of the program was no doubt the competition among members of the "Swedish-American Athletic Association," and a football match between a mixed team from the latter association and the Norwegian football team "Fram."</p>
   <p>Carl Pierson, Oscar Munson and Bernard Roman were the leaders in this part of the program; O. Munson as Referee and Ever Hammer and Gust. Krantz as Timekeepers, John Erison, Dr. Axel Akeson, Harold Nelson, Paul Lundberg, C. Goranson, Thure Andreen and Gust. Wahlstrom as Prize Judges. The result was as follows: 100 Yard Dash; (best time 102/5 sec.) 1. Erik Johnson; 2. Gust Rundquist; 3. H. Grevin (scratch). Shot Put: (36 ft. 7 in.) 1. Ed. Johnson; 2. G. Wahlstrom; 3. Gust. Rundquist. Discus Throw: (123 ft.) 1. A. Carlson; 2. H. Grevin; 3. E. Olson. High Jump: (5 ft.6 in.) 1. C. Anderson (scratch); 2. M. Anderson; 3. G. Rundquist. 220 Yard Dash: 1. Ernie <pb facs="5423404_3_0299.jpg" n="3"/>Olson; 2. H. Grevin (scratch); 3. Erik Johnson. Two Mile Run: 1. Hugo Carlson (scratch); 2. W. Jensen; 3. C. Pearson; 4. B. Johnson; 5. E. Palm; 6. George Karl-berg. Broad Jump: (20ft. 4 in.) 1. K. Lowencrantz; 2. O. Lawrence; 3. E. Magnuson. 440 Yard Run: (57 sec.) 1. Enok Johnson; 2. H. Munson; 3. K. Lowencrantz. Hop-Step &amp; Jump: (41 ft. 3 in.) 1. O. Ternstrom (scratch); 2. G. Rundquist (scratch); 3. O. Anderson. Javelin Throw: 1. Gust Johnson; 2. Ed. Johnson; 3. O. Ternstrom.</p>
   <p>The football game was very thrilling, and was won by the Norwegian team "Fram" with three goals to two for the Swedes. The prizes were given out by O. S. Ohlander, H. Grevin and O. Munson.</p>
   <p>A cup donated by the Swedish Ladies Gymnastic Association went to the Norwegians for winning the football match. Hugo Carlson, the winner of the two-mile race, received a cup donated by Eric Hall, the architect. The other winners in the athletic competition received medals.</p>
   <p>In the Ladies Popularity Contest, Miss Sigrid Swanson was crowned "Queen" and also received the $25.00 in gold, donated by the "Swedish National League."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
