<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1893-01-25">Jan. 25, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Sweden and the Chicago World's Fair.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0410</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0410.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1893-01-25">Jan. 25, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDEN AND THE CHICAGO WORLD'S FAIR.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swedish section at The World's Fair in Chicago is going to be very prominent. The interest in the Fair is steadily increasing and there is restless activity everywhere to get things ready for the exhibition before the time for their shipment expires. The number of exhibitors have increased to nearly 300.</p>
   <p>The Exhibition pavilion, in parts, is already on its way from Sweden to Chicago and so are most of the objects intended for The Fair. Engineer A.Leffler, commissary for the Swedish Exhibition, and G. Wickman, architect will depart for Chicago in February to supervise the erection of the pavilion and other arrangements.</p>
   <p>The great Swedish industries, especially the steel and iron, are going to be represented in a most worthy manner. The Swedish Tourist Society and the Nordic Museum are working each in the field to contribute to the exhibition by designing peasant houses, photographs of beautiful places in Sweden and winter sport scenes and other scenery.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0411.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Swedish Society, that encourages people to cut in wood, has made great efforts to be represented. Swedish gymnastics will also be represented at The Fair. A great chorus of 500 Swedish-Americans will sing at The Fair together with prominent singers from Sweden, who also will give concerts at The Fair.</p>
   <p>An exhibition of maps from the Stockholm Exhibit is going to be sent to Chicago, as well as sport exhibitions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
