<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-05-29">May 29, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Vernamo Marknad</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-05-29">May 29, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">VERNAMO MARKNAD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Vernamo Marknad (Vernamo Fair) opened last Sunday afternoon. An unusually large crowd of more than two thousand persons took part in this Swedish-American fresh-air entertainment, which indicates the popularity that this annual event has won. The fair continues this week and next week under the auspices of the Svithiod Singing Club, and judging by the large crowds attending the first evening, the Fair this year will be visited by at least thirty thousand people.</p>
   <p>The official opening took place at seven in the evening, when the Svithiod Singing Club, assisted by the Swedish Glee Club, the Nordstjernan Chorus, the Orphei Chorus, and the Norden Chorus, formed a combined chorus of over one hundred voices and sang "Vart Land" (Our Land) with power and feeling. "Hor Oss Svea" and other songs were rendered.</p>
   <p>The president of the Svithiod Singing Club, Mr. Olof F. Nelson, welcomed the large audience, and Attorney G. Bernhard Anderson gave a short, forceful talk <pb facs="5423404_3_0373.jpg" n="2"/>concerning the Vernamo Fair, and declared the Fair opened. Mayor Harrison was introduced and in words of praise, spoke of the Swedes of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The songs as well as the speeches were received with stormy applause. The Mayor thereupon went from one stand to another and appeared to find much pleasure in examining the arts and handicrafts imported from Sweden, and in conversing with the Vernamo flickorna (Vernamo girls) at the various displays.....</p>
   <p>The Svithiod Singing Club has been successful in obtaining splendid talents for its vaudeville. Special mention is earned by Werden and Sheppard's stereopticon views. For the rest, in all parts of the park there are to be found objects of interest which please and entertain. Here we have "marknads-gubben" (the fair-man) who is represented by the inimitable comedian, Ernst Ekberg; there a chamber organ player; there a dance pavilion, upon which the boys and girls in Swedish costumes dance the Swedish polka. Further away there is a fish dam with gold fish in it, and over the whole park rises the great Ferris wheel with its thousands of incandescent lights. On the first evening of the Fair five hundred <pb facs="5423404_3_0374.jpg" n="3"/>persons rode on the wheel. Tomorrow, which is Decoration Day, about five thousand people are expected at the Fair. That will be an opportunity to meet friends from all sections of our metropolis. "Vitraffas pa Vernamo."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
