<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-06-25">June 25, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish National Midsummer Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-06-25">June 25, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH NATIONAL MIDSUMMER FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This Swedish festival was celebrated Sunday evening and was a great success; to say that it was better than any before it would be putting it mildly. Elliott's Park, where it was held, appeared at its best. All of us who have Swedish blood in our veins, after a long wait for the sun and summer, were in our best humor to enjoy the beauty that nature so abundantly afforded. To speak of the beautiful weather with which we were favored would be trite. We all know by this time that Mrs. Myhrman stands in well with the weather forecaster in the Auditorium tower, and the weather needed for our recreation never fails us. In the morning the sky looked threatening for a while. We saw on Mrs. Myhrman's countenance a look of disgust as she gazed toward the office of the weather prophet, and we heard her mutter,</p>
   <p>"See here, professor, what kind of foolishness is this?"</p>
   <p>And the professor hastily turned on another kind of weather. Nothing was <pb facs="5423404_3_0318.jpg" n="2"/>lacking to make it a real national celebration. In fact, it was larger than last year's, even if other midsummer festivals were being held elsewhere. To count those present was impossible, but that is hardly the function of a lousy reporter.</p>
   <p>We guess, however, that there were 25,000 present; but we would swear that there were 20,000. Car after car brought a dozen or more each from 8 A.M. on; at noon the crowd went to the park, where several thousand had already gathered. It is wonderful to come from the drab streets to God's free nature and to roam over the green grass among a festive throng. And out there was the fluttering emblem that never fails to make the heart of Swedish man or woman beat faster--the Swedish flag. The platform used by the speakers, the gymnasts, and the dancers was beautifully decorated with American and Swedish flags. The park was crowded with people at ten o'clock, when the music began, and I tried to get through the entrance to the park. The music was the signal that the guest of honor had arrived, sent by Sweden to represent that country on this gala occassion, the Honorable H. L. F. Lagercrantz.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0319.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>He had been escorted from Chicago by the magnificent throng which welcomes him on all occasions, a crowd such as Swedish-Americans had hardly dreamed of before. He was the guest of Vice-Consul John R. Lindgren, who followed him into the park. A reception committee had attended at the [Illinois] Central Railroad Station to escort the guest of honor. He was presented to the president of the National Society, the Honorable G. E. Q. Johnson. From the station he was escorted by three musical societies to the speakers' platform. After this had taken place, the American and Swedish flags were raised while the band played.</p>
   <p>Frithiof Malmquist read a festival poem. A song was sung by the Svea Chorus and the audience. Now a recess in the official program was taken to partake of a dinner given for the guest of honor and others. After that the program was resumed with songs and other music; then the Scandia Gymnastic and Athletic Club performed wonderful gymnastics. This was followed by the national Swedish dancers, who presented a long program of old dances which we had known in Sweden.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0320.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Honorable Mr. Lagercrantz expressed his appreciation to the gymnastic club as well as to the national dancers because they have maintained their [Swedish] skill among his compatriots here.</p>
   <p>After this there were songs by the Swedish ladies' quartet, and then G. E. Q. Johnson as president of the National Society gave an address of welcome, after which he presented several of the county commissioners and Corporation Counsel Edward J. Brundage, who gave a talk on Swedish contributions to American citizenship. Mr. Brundage told of the worthy things which the Swedish-Americans have done in building the nation. Perhaps the speech was somewhat burdened with statistics, but since it was a Swedish audience, the speaker was splendid; let no one complain about him. The whole speech was an acknowledgment of the high place which the Swedes enjoy as citizens and [of their promptness in] becoming naturalized. The speaker was loudly applauded. Then the Honorable Mr. Lagercrantz was presented to the audience, which welcomed him most heartily. His personality and his whole appearance and carriage were such that nothing else might have been expected. His <pb facs="5423404_3_0321.jpg" n="5"/>countenance reveals a splendid character. He is a gentleman, not one of the snobbish sort that you find among people of his standing. To his audience he gave the impression of a democratic, urbane personality, not acting unnaturally but as one who deserves real popularity. His talk was like himself, straightforward and without unnecessary eloquence. But it was not lacking in sincerity or significance or warm sympathy; no one could help feeling that every word came direct from his heart.</p>
   <p>"I wish first to bring a greeting from the Northland, from Sweden, from father's land and mother's land, where once they lived," so he began.</p>
   <p>"When I was about ready to set forth on my journey here, and I was saying farewell to the grand old monarch, he put his arm around me and said,</p>
   <p>"'Greet them! greet all my beloved Swedes who live over there; even if they are Americans on paper, they will always be Swedes to me.'"</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0322.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>That greeting of the old and respected king was met with loud cheers of joy. The speaker told how Sweden had recently bestowed the right to vote upon all, a right which up to recent times had not been granted.</p>
   <p>In one of the papers in Stockholm recently they spoke of the Honorable Mr. Lagercrantz's journey in answer to an invitation from this country; no doubt they counted on his winning some of their sons and daughters who live here back to Sweden again. However, in the latter part of his speech he spoke of how well off the Swedish-Americans appeared to be over here and of the good working conditions. He did not complain because we had taken so well to our beloved bride, for although Mother Sweden may mourn over our leaving, yet she is glad that she is not forgotten. The speaker was happy because all the Swedish-Americans whom he had met were well thought of. He said that President Roosevelt had told him that Swedish-Americans did not lose their modesty and become self-conceited. His talk was not without humor. Among other things he said that in a meeting of old people in Sweden, when he was about to sail, an old lady asked him to greet her son Axel. It <pb facs="5423404_3_0323.jpg" n="7"/>never occurred to her that America is several times larger than Vastmanland or than Sweden and several other countries put together. A little later he learned that Axel lived in Seattle, Washington.</p>
   <p>"I understand that you love your foster country," said he. "I have been here only three weeks, and I feel half American already."</p>
   <p>The audience applauded. When the speaker had finished, the band played "America". Later a telegram was sent to King Oscar as follows:</p>
   <p>"Twenty-five thousand Swedish-Americans in Chicago under the auspices of the Swedish National Society assembled to celebrate the midsummer festival in Elliott's Park with Minister Lagercrantz as guest of honor. Beg to send a greeting from our foster country to our beloved Monarch."</p>
   <p>This was the answer received:</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0324.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>"President Johnson, Swedish National Society, Chicago: With great pleasure I received your telegram and beg you to offer to the Swedish National Society my heartiest thanks. My interest and my blessings are offered to all. Oscar."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
