<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-06-16">June 16, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Historical Society of America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0515</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0515.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-06-16">June 16, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH HISTORICAL SOCIETY OF AMERICA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swedish Historical Society has recently acquired a large addition to its library from the Engberg-Holmberg Publishing Company in Chicago. They gave samples of all publications of which the firm owned more than one volume, amounting to more than four hundred volumes. Among the donated books, we find that many belonged to other publishers which the above mentioned publishing company had purchased from such companies as the Swedish Lutheran Publication Society, Julin &amp; Hedenberg, Julin &amp; Rylander, A. Hult, Wistrand &amp; Thulin, J. T. Relling Company, Enander &amp; Boman, and Sangen Publishing <pb facs="5423404_3_0516.jpg" n="2"/>Company. The oldest printed book in this collection goes back about fifty years. A complete set of the firm's catalogues, old and new, were included in the donation. The library of the Swedish Historical Society consists of about one thousand volumes, the largest part of which is printed in America by Swedish publishers. The Augustana Book concern, and the Methodist Book concern have also donated from their collections. Even from Sweden, valuable gifts have been received from the Academy of Stockholm, and P. A. Nerstedt &amp; Sons. From the Government's Archives in Stockholm, a large shipment is on the way.</p>
   <p>The library of Uppala University has promised to send what they can of their <pb facs="5423404_3_0517.jpg" n="3"/>volumes where they have duplicates that might be of interest to us. The generous Swedish-Americans have also wonderfully supplied the library with books. Among them is a very valuable selection of Swedish-American newspapers donated by Consul G. N. Swan of Sioux City, Iowa, Prof. C. W. Foss, of Rock Island, and also from the Augustana College.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
