<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-02-27">Feb. 27, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">To Our Readers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0526</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0526.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-02-27">Feb. 27, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">TO OUR READERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter has always done its best to offer its readers a refreshing variety of reading matter, such as the most significant and interesting news, and entertaining as well as educational feature articles. That is one of the reasons why the paper enjoys such widespread popularity, which in turn has a stimulating effect on its entire staff, encouraging us to do our utmost to maintain and strengthen the paper's position as the leading Swedish-American newspaper. In this effort we have the assistance of highly regarded occasional contributors, and among these associates are some of the finest Swedish and Swedish-American writers.</p>
   <p>We wish to call attention to an article in this issue which is the first of a series especially intended for our women readers. These articles are published on the initiative of the Swedish Women's Citizens League, which <pb facs="5423404_3_0527.jpg" n="2"/>includes in its program the dissemination of knowledge and understanding of social and humanitarian problems. And they are edited by the noted scholar Jenny Velander, who is known and admired even in this country since her visit here a few years ago. The articles are written by the most prominent Swedish publicists and deal with topics of high educational value. They will appear once or twice a month, and we hope that they will arouse interest among all members of our Swedish-American homes, and especially that they will be appreciated by our esteemed women readers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
