<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-12-22">Dec. 22, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">[Report Of] Swedish National Association.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1231</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1231.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-12-22">Dec. 22, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">[REPORT OF] SWEDISH NATIONAL ASSOCIATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swedish National Association, strong and powerful by virtue of the combined support of the Swedes in Chicago, is responsible to the Swedish-speaking population in Chicago for the activities of the Association, and for this reason begs to present to its friends and supporters a few leaves [from the book] of its history and activities during the past year.</p>
   <p>Through the free employment bureau maintained by the Association, 3,367 Swedes have gained employment--2,305 men and 1,062 women. In many cases, the applicants were unfamiliar with the language of our country, and for these especially, the need for employment was imperative. The minimum cost of gaining employment through some agency rendering the service for a fee could not be less than two dollars per applicant, or $6,734 for the entire number. The value of the activity of the Association along these lines is therefore easily recognized.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1232.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Association extends a helping hand to many destitute Swedes. During the past year, aid has been rendered in 208 cases to the total amount of $910.65. Widows and abandoned wives with many children have always been given the preference when aid was to be granted. The destitute in Norrland, Sweden were aided with $354, and an elderly unemployed man was provided for at the Home of Mercy in Bowmansville.</p>
   <p>In hundreds of other ways the Association has aided needy Swedes,both men and women. Ailing people have been sent to Colorade, to California, to Oregon, and to the southern States, there to regain their health and strength. Some have been sent home to Sweden to recuperate. Swedes lacking employment have been sent, without cost to them,to Minnesota, Nebraska, and other States, where the Assoication had secured work for them.</p>
   <p>To the extent possible with the means at its command, the Association has given clothes, lodging, and food to Swedes who were in need.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1233.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Swedish National Association has always done its best to assist unfortunate compatriots. As is well known, the Association has made efforts to obtain a new trial for John Nordgren, who has been found guilty of murdering his wife. Strong doubts were felt as to the guilt of John Nordgren, but Judge Chetlain refused to grant a new trial. The Association has appealed his decision. The expenses in connection with the appeal will amount to about two thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>The activities of the Association are being supported exclusively by the funds accruing from the two great annual festivals arranged by the Association: the midsummer festival, held annually in one of the attractive parks in the neighborhood of the city and usually attended by some ten to twenty thousand people; and the midwinter festival, held annually in the Auditorum, the largest and most expensive theater in the city. Through their attendance at these festivals, our Swedish-Americans become supporters of the worthy activities carried on by the Association.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1234.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>On the tenth and eleventh of February, the famous play by Jules Verne, "Around the World in Eighty Days", will be presented by the Association as the midwinter festival play. We welcome all Swedish-Americans to this festival, and in the name of the sick and the poor among our compatriots in the city, we express in advance our gratitude to all those who will attend.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
