<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-03-10">Mar. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Freedom of the Press</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0569</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0569.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-03-10">Mar. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE FREEDOM OF THE PRESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As previously reported, Senator King of Utah has submitted a bill before the United States Senate, the avowed purpose of which is to further limit and encumber the distribution of that section of the American press which is printed in languages other than English. This result will be obtained in a roundabout way, by the purely technical provision which requires that a newspaper must be printed in English in order to be accepted as second class mail.</p>
   <p>After personal opinions and sentiments have been put aside, there still remain two questions raised by this bill which should be answered before it becomes law, namely: Is such a law constitutional? And if it is, would it be wise to incorporate it into the statutes of the United States?</p>
   <p>To be sure, the law would not, like its counterpart in Oregon, deliver a <pb facs="5423404_3_0570.jpg" n="2"/>knockout blow to the foreign-language press. Rather, its elimination would be a slow and painful process. Newspapers not printed in English would not be admitted as second class mail, or in other words, the cost of distribution would become so high that such publications would not be able to survive. The rate for third class mail is two cents a pound within the first zone, and increases for each zone, the highest rate being eight cents a pound, and in addition, each item must be provided with the proper stamp. One can readily see what this would mean to a publication with, say, seventy thousand subscribers. Furthermore, all other mail takes precedence over that of the third class, and newspapers thus rated, might often be subjected to delayed delivery, which is another important setback.</p>
   <p>The powers that be should not forget the fact that about twenty-five million people now living in the United States were born in a foreign country, and that many of these, even though they may be well able to read English, prefer to read a newspaper printed in their mother tongue. There is much valuable reading matter in those papers which cannot be found in the English-language <pb facs="5423404_3_0571.jpg" n="3"/>press, and it also should be pointed out that foreign-language newspapers are read and enjoyed not only by foreign-born persons, but by their children and others who have acquired the ability to understand some language other than English. We venture to say that the foreign-language press in this country, on the whole, has it all over its American competitors as a conscientious and dependable source of information and enlightenment.</p>
   <p>Now let us consider the constitutionality of the proposal. One of the most indispensable paragraphs in the Constitution contains the provision that the Congress shall not enact any law which encumbers the freedom of speech and the freedom of the press.</p>
   <p>This is the rock upon which the existence of the American press is based, and neither this nor any other paragraph in the Constitution gives the Congress the authority to proclaim that our newspapers shall be printed in English, Latin, or any other language exclusively. To determine by law what people shall and shall not be permitted to read is a gross violation of what has hitherto been considered the undisputed right of every citizen. The bill does <pb facs="5423404_3_0572.jpg" n="4"/>not even pretend to make a distinction between good and bad reading.</p>
   <p>It seems improbable that our Congress, faced by the inviolable rights set down in the Constitution, will attempt to make such inroads on the privileges of citizens as are implied in this bill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
