<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-10-07">Oct. 7, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish Cultural League Opens Lecture Season</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0823</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0823.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1931-10-07">Oct. 7, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH CULTURAL LEAGUE OPENS LECTURE SEASON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The annual series of lectures which the Swedish Cultural League has been presenting for several years in Cafe Idrott's lecture hall, 3204 Wilton Avenue, will begin next Friday, October 16. It is now sixteen years since the League was founded.</p>
   <p>These lectures have always attracted much attention, and made the League very popular in the district. The program for the coming season has been planned so as to represent a variety of interests and points of view. Some of the lecturers are well known from previous years, while others will appear for the first time, and it is evident that the lecture committee has done its best to secure a representative group of speakers, that will maintain the reputation which the League has earned in the past.</p>
   <p>At the first meeting, Dr. C. G. Wallenius will talk on "Some Swedish <pb facs="5423404_3_0824.jpg" n="2"/>Contributions to World History," and a program of song and music will be presented. The two following lectures will be given by Ralph Chaplin, who will talk on the two famous literary figures, Emile Zola and Don Quixote.</p>
   <p>On November 20, a new feature will be introduced, namely a debate. The very controversial issue of prohibition will be debated, and Attorneys Sheldon and Mozart will take opposite sides. On January 8, a Karlfeldt evening will be arranged. [Translator's note: Karlfeldt is a noted Swedish author and poet]. All in all twenty-two lectures will be given during the season, which will close March 25. Announcements regarding each meeting will be found in this newspaper from time to time, and detailed information may be obtained from the League's secretary, Gunnar Adolfson, 3206 Wilton Avenue. The admission to single lectures is twenty-five cents, and season tickets cost two dollars!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
