<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-07-10">July 10, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish-American Charity</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1196</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1196.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1906-07-10">July 10, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH-AMERICAN CHARITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A remarkably pleasing characteristic of the Swedish-American press is its willingness to give our people due credit for its outstanding good points: intelligence, business ability, morality and charitable activities. This characteristic of the press is credited by our countrymen as being a most encouraging attitude.</p>
   <p>The attitude of the press is based on a thorough knowledge of the fundamental principles of the Swede--his intelligence and his natural born desire to "Do unto others as ye would have them do unto you"; his almost invariable practice of making the Golden Rule a guide for his entire life.</p>
   <p>The desire of this and hundreds of other publications, at present, is to turn the public spotlight on the charity of the Swedish-American. During <pb facs="5423404_3_1197.jpg" n="2"/>the past few years especially, their building of hospitals, [has been remarkable], not only in Chicago, but in every city where the Swedish colony circles invariably cooperated in successfully establishing a substantial organization for the welfare of their countrymen.</p>
   <p>Many of the large lodges and church denominations have practiced, and still, practice cooperation in establishing substantial homes for the aged and orphanages. In this respect the Swedish colony of Chicago has proved its right to be regarded as an ideal, whose activities and spirit are examples worth following in every Swedish community in this or any other country in the world.</p>
   <p>While our Chicago Swedes believe that "Charity begins at home," they are an example of willingness to let the rays of charitable warmth shine wherever they may be needed and where they are beneficial. There is only one thing a real Swede finds impossible to do, that is, to harden his heart or let it <pb facs="5423404_3_1198.jpg" n="3"/>turn into a block of ice when his countryman especially, and the world in general, is stricken by a catastrophe that makes a fellowman helpless.</p>
   <p>The old saying that "blood is thicker than water" is proved beyond a shadow of a doubt by our Swedish colony and similar communities wherever they are located.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
