<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1915-04-15">April 15,1915</date>.
<title level="a">Progress of Swedish Engineers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0490</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0490.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren (The Swedish Courier, Weekly)</title>,
<date when="1915-04-15">April 15,1915</date>.
<title level="a">PROGRESS OF SWEDISH ENGINEERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With reference to the planned Swedish engineer congress, to be held here Sept. 9-11, the general committee for the congress has published a membership book containing a complete list of the Swedish,as well as the Swedish American participants, together with a brief history of the congress and its objectives. Since the organizing committee was formed last year, the work has been pursued with such success that at present ninety members in the eastern states have announced their decision of participating, and eighty in the western states. It may, however, be confidently expected that a far greater number will register within the near future, as soon as the program for the congress has been decided upon and has been distributed to the nine hundred engineers and industrial leaders whose names are on file with the two committees for organization, but who have not as yet announced their intention of participating in the congress.</p>
   <p>In regard to the objectives of the congress it is stated: "The objective of the <pb facs="5423404_3_0491.jpg" n="2"/>convention is, in part, to bring the visiting Swedish engineers together with their brothers in the field in this country, in part, to bring about cooperation among Swedish engineers who have settled in America. All Swedish engineers in the United States and in Canada are being invited to the congress, as well as all other prominent men in industry no matter whether they belong to the organized engineering societies in this country or not.</p>
   <p>The address of the Western Committee for organization is 619 City Hall Square Building, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
