<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-01-01">Jan. 1, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Editors to Celebrate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0647</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0647.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1905-01-01">Jan. 1, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH EDITORS TO CELEBRATE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Hamlandet is the first Swedish-American newspaper to obtain the age of half a century, having been published continuously since January 3, 1854 and next Tuesday its golden anniversary will be commemorated by the issue of an illustrated jubilee edition in colors and containing a review of the past fifty years of important events in its own and the Swedish-American people's history. Previous to 1854 the number of Swedish immigrants then in this country was limited. The Bishop Hill colony and at Andover, Moline and Galesburg, with a few colonies in Iowa and other western states, probably did not number more than 5,000 people.</p>
   <p>The Augustana Lutheran Synod was organized and the Hemlandet became the official organ of the Synod and continued as such until 1872, since which time it has been owned by private parties. Its editors during this half century of the Swedish-Americans as Rev. Dr. E. Norelius, Dr. Erland Carlson, Jonas Engberg, Dr. E. R. Cervin, P. A. Sundelius and the present editor, the venerable Dr. J. A. Enander.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0648.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>From January 3, 1854, until 1859 the Hemlandet was published in Galesburg, Ill., when it moved to Chicago. Its principle owner and president of the Hemlandet company since 1896 is the noted Swedish-American, A. E. Johnson, Knight of the Royal Swedish Order of the Wasa, who can also celebrate his golden anniversary, as it was in 1854 ,he arrived in Chicago from Sweden.</p>
   <p>The principle members of the staff of the Hemlandet today are Dr. J. A. Enander, vice-president and editor in Chief; A. Schon, secretary and assistant-editor; Aaron Edstroom, exchange editor; Carl T. Strandberg, treasurer and general manager; Gunnar Boberg, assistant business and advertising manager.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
