<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-09-26">Sept. 26, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Theatre (Review)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0125</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0125.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-09-26">Sept. 26, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH THEATRE (Review)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday, the Swedish Dramatic Society, under the direction of Ernst Behmer, gave a four-act play, "Uncle Knut from Norrkoping," at Music Hall. The play is originally French, and has been translated into Swedish by Mr. Behmer, with some alterations. The play is a farce, entertaining and interesting throughout, full of action and rich in quick verbal exchanges. On the whole, it would have been better, however, if one or more jolly exchanges had been omitted, the piece would have gained thereby. The total impression of the play was good. The role of the benevolent "Henrik Brandes," who is always anxious about the affairs of others, was presented by Ernst Behmer in a very satisfactory manner, but in the third act when he changed characters, having <pb facs="5423404_3_0126.jpg" n="2"/>put on the spectacles of "Uncle Knut," he should have needed to make the change more definite, even in the matter of make-up. The philanthropist could not quite give way to the misanthropist, and especially did the scene at the wife's desk appear somewhat insipid. Carl Liljegren presented "Uncle Knut"....one of the characters who suspects everything and everybody, and whose only aim in life is to make money. Liljegren mastered the task with little difficulty, and was rewarded with applause. Leopold Kjellman (the son of "Uncle Knut") has retrograded since last we saw him on the stage. He tried, again and again, but could not win his public. Werner Melinder,.... as the first lover, left much to be desired, but then his object of love was a veritable piece of ice, Miss Anna Anderson (the daughter of "wholesaler Ahlengren"). John Melin was not unsuitable in his role as clerk, and Carl Milton was good as "Shoemaker Sundquist." Mrs. Augusta Milton....did not appear to us to have understood her role; a disdainful smile hovered on her lips when the smile should have been sweet as honey. Mr. C. Sheldon.... Werner Melinder, and Anna Anderson, had learned their lessons by heart.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
