<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-09-21">Sept. 21, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedish National Sanitarium</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1345</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1345.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-09-21">Sept. 21, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDISH NATIONAL SANITARIUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p/>
   <p>The Tribunen-Nyheter and other Swedish-American newspapers have repeatedly reported on the activities for the benefit of the Swedish Sanitarium in Denver, Colorado, and have urged their readers to support this institution as generously as they possibly can. It represents one of the most deserving causes ever placed before the Swedish-American public. A campaign is now being conducted for the purpose of soliciting funds with which to expand the facilities of the sanitarium, so that it can care for more patients. The drive is directed by the energetic Dr. Julius Lincoln, and has progressed quite well so far.</p>
   <p>It cannot be denied, however, that our Swedish-American public has not responded to the appeal as readily as one might expect, and there has been no united effort in behalf of this humanitarian undertaking, which really <pb facs="5423404_3_1346.jpg" n="2"/>deserves a place close to the heart of every one of our countrymen. We are inclined to believe that this state of affairs is due to thoughtlessness rather than to willful negligence. When our Swedish-Americans become fully aware of the importance of this cause, we are sure they will come through as they have done so many times in the past, when appeals were made to them in behalf of unfortunate fellowmen.</p>
   <p>Dr. Lincoln has proposed that the date on which we celebrate the memory of King Gustaf Adolf be designated as a special "Sanitarium Day". We like the idea, and sincerely hope that it will be observed in every community where Swedes have made their homes. [Translator's note: Gustaf Adolf (also called Gustavus Adolphus) was a Swedish king whose memory is revered by the Swedish nation. He is best known for his participation in the Thirty Years' War.] The selection of this date should particularly appeal to our church people, for whom the memory of the hero king is of special significance.</p>
   <p>It is of interest to study statistics on the prevalence of tuberculosis <pb facs="5423404_3_1347.jpg" n="3"/>among Swedish-Americans. According to the latest tables, twelve thousand of them have the disease, and last year five thousand died from it. About twenty-five per cent of those that are sick have no money and no relatives or friends from whom they can get any help. The Swedish National Sanitarium in Denver represents the only attempt made by our nationals to aid these unfortunate countrymen. As a rule, Swedish consumptive patients do not like to be among strangers in state institutions, whereas they thrive in the Swedish sanitarium, where life is more like a family affair. Since the sanitarium was established, about three thousand persons have applied for admission, and at the present time it can care for only thirty-seven.</p>
   <p>By observing "Sanitarium Day" on the same date on which we celebrate the memory of Sweden's greatest king, this good cause should receive new impetus. Let us all do our share so that the very first observance will bring in enough money to finance the planned expansion of the sanitarium, and that the subsequent observances will take care of its maintenance.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1348.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Let us not leave to their fate those of our unfortunate countrymen who are struck by the terrible white plague. Let us help them!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
