<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1919-02-06">Feb. 6, 1919</date><title level="a">Swedish Old People's Home Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0259</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0259.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1919-02-06">Feb. 6, 1919</date><title level="a">SWEDISH OLD PEOPLE'S HOME SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The regular members of The Swedish Old People's Home Society gave their yearly banquet at the Svithiod Sangarklubb Hall last Wednesday evening. Approximately two hundred persons were present at the affair, which proved to be a very pleasant entertainment.</p>
   <p>The chairman of the festival committee, Mr. Albert Swanson, or "Father Swanson" as he is called in these circles, opened the festival with a short address, in which he made it known that Congressman Carl R. Chindblom had taken it upon himself to function as master of ceremonies for the evening.</p>
   <p>Congressman Chindblom began with an exhortation that America be sung in unison. In well chosen words, he then pointed out that the work <pb facs="5423404_3_0260.jpg" n="2"/>for the Old People's Home during the past year had been crowned with fine results, despite hard times, due to the effects of war. He, thereupon, introduced the chairman of the Women's Club, Mrs. C. M. Hedman. She accounted briefly for the work which this club does for the good of the Home. She gave a vivid, and yet a touching description, of the life led by the old folks in the Home. Finally, she expressed her sincere thanks to the departing director, Miss Anna Holm, for her work well done for the benefit of the Home, and for the well-being of the old folks.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Hedman spoke in Swedish, the language favored by the old people. She appealed to all Swedish women to become members of the club, and <pb facs="5423404_3_0261.jpg" n="3"/>ended her fine talk with the recitation of a poem in honor of the old people.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was the chairman of the Men's Club, Dr. John A. Christenson, who pointed out that the Swedish Old People's Home is the most popular of its kind in all Cook County. He prophesied that in due time it would surely become the finest Old People's Home in the whole state. He expressed his thanks to Mr. John P. Friedland, chairman of the Villa Committee of last year, through whose energy and persistence, the wealth of the society had been increased to $18,600. "The aim is now to have the Home enlarged," continued the speaker. "We wish to make an addition of a wing so that the Home will be able to accommodate more inmates than it does at present!'</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0262.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>After Dr. Christenson's speech, the president of the Old People's Home Society, Mr. Aaron Miller, spoke. He also expressed a wish that the Home might be enlarged so that there would be more room, and hoped that the Society would be able to start the work soon. It would be possible if the interest in the Home is not allowed to wane, but kept up as it has been during 1918. If all were willing to work as hard and accomplish as much as Mr. John P. Friedland, success would be certain.</p>
   <p>Miss Agnes Berg, of the Augustana Hospital, sang two Swedish songs, accompanied by Miss Lindstrom. Other speakers were: Mr. George Q. Johnson, and Dr. M. Wahlstrom. The latter pointed out the <pb facs="5423404_3_0263.jpg" n="5"/>desirability of having a Swedish home for invalids in Chicago. The last official speaker of the evening was Attorney Edwin A. Olson, whose appearance was greeted with the loudest applause of the evening. His talk was very lively, gay, and humorous. He mentioned that the permanent members should always be active members.</p>
   <p>In closing the affair, Mrs. C. M. Hedman presented Miss Anna Holm with a gold watch as a token of appreciation from the permanent members. The gift was presented to Miss Holm with a few fitting words of thanks and as a tribute of their love and respect for this good woman. Miss Holm, visibly moved, thanked the Society for the gift, and therewith the pleasant affair was brought to a close.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
