<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1913-05-15">May 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Olympics in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0991</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0991.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1913-05-15">May 15, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE OLYMPICS IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The latest newspapers from Sweden tell us that a great international athlete's feast has been scheduled to be held here in Chicago at Grant Park from June 28 to July 6 this year, and that our countryman, Mr. Charles S. Peterson, after a conference with Mr. Everett C. Brown, the director-general of the races, offered to pay the travelling expenses for a Swede participating in the feast of the Swedish athletes, who won the first prize at the Olympics last summer.</p>
   <p>The races are supposed to be grand, but in spite of all this, there seems <pb facs="5423404_3_0992.jpg" n="2"/>to be some doubt if the Swedish athletes ought to avail themselves of this opportunity.</p>
   <p>We agree with the Swedish newspapers in praising Mr. Peterson's generosity, which deserves our gratitude, whether he himself will pay for these expenses or, as we have heard, will only make the necessary arrangements. Mr. Peterson must know, of course, from whence the money will be available, otherwise, he would not have made such an announcement to the Swedish press. However, the question is: would it be sensible for the Swedish athletes to accept Mr. Peterson's offer and make the journey across the Atlantic to participate in the affair? We, who know the conditions here in Chicago, feel that the proposal is too loosely constructed. We are now in the middle of May, and the Olympics are supposed to start within <pb facs="5423404_3_0993.jpg" n="3"/>six weeks. What preparations are made? Is the foundation to the great proposed Stadium building in Chicago laid? Or are we going to be satisfied with the erection of a few temporary galleries and call it "Stadium?" The planned Olympics have already got a "black eye" when the chairman for the International Olympic had forbidden that the name "Olympic" be used. Instead, one has to be satisfied with the more humble title, "Champion." The proposal has not been received here in the United States with any enthusiasm. Our opinion is that our countrymen in Sweden ought to be familiar with all these conditions before they accept Mr. Peterson's invitation.</p>
   <p>The proposal to arrange a giant chorus for the occasion seems to be reasonable, and also Mrs. Young's promise to let 20,000 school children <pb facs="5423404_3_0994.jpg" n="4"/>participate in the affair. But all in all, the whole business seems to have such little preparation, that we doubt it would be a success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
