<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1929-08-01">Aug. 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The Independent Order of Svithiod</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1075</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1075.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1929-08-01">Aug. 1, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE INDEPENDENT ORDER OF SVITHIOD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Independent Order of Svithiod has recently held its 37th annual Grand Lodge convention, at which 138 delegates from the Order's 73 lodges were present.</p>
   <p>From the Grand Lodge secretary's report we make the following extracts: During the period July 1, 1928--June 30, 1929, 1,388 new members have joined the Order; out of this number, 914 have joined since the beginning of 1929. The total membership at the end of the fiscal year was 16,030. Six new lodges have been organized during this last 12 months.</p>
   <p>The finances of the Svithiod Order are in excellent condition and show a very satisfactory increase over the previous year. Thus the assets of the Grand Lodge total the huge sum of $1,360,232.71 and the combined individual assets of the lodges a total of $427,865.66, or a grand total of $1,788,198.37. Practically all of the assets of the Grand Lodge are invested in first mortgages bearing interest at the rate of 6%.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1076.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since the Order came into existence 37 years ago, a total sum of $2,769,970.46 has been paid out to members on life insurance policies, for sick and funeral benefits, and in donations.</p>
   <p>The Order's Old Peoples Home on Lake Minnetonka in Minnesota is now the haven for 18 aged members. During the last year the incumbrance on the property was reduced by $10,000, or from $35,000 to $25,000.</p>
   <p>Election of officers for the ensuing year was in order and resulted as follows: Andrew Rasmussen, Grand Master; Dr. Herman G. Almquist, Vice Grand Master; Otto Hanson, Grand Lodge secretary; August Lindeberg, Grand Lodge treasurer, and Dr. Carl G. Rydin, Chief Examining Physician.</p>
   <p>The retiring secretary, Mr. John A. Sandgren, of Chicago, has held this position within the Grand Lodge for the last 27 years. Other activities necessitated his withdrawal. He was made the object of great ovations and received many tokens of appreciation for his dutiful service.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
