<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-09-29">Sept. 29, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">To Our Subscribers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0664</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0664.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-09-29">Sept. 29, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">TO OUR SUBSCRIBERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Starting with our next number, Svenska Nyheter will appear as a sixteen-page paper while the subscription price will be the same as before, one dollar per year.</p>
   <p>For this increase in size, our subscribers and the buyers of individual copies of the paper deserve full credit; it is their warm and cordial support which has made it possible for us to be now publishing Chicago's largest and most inexpensive Swedish newspaper.</p>
   <p>When fourteen years ago, in the year 1890, the publisher of this paper began publication of Humoristen (The Humorist), a paper which steadily grew in size and scope, he did not expect that in this year of grace 1903 <pb facs="5423404_3_0665.jpg" n="2"/>the paper, under the name of Svenska Nyheter, would prove to be the largest Swedish paper in Chicago.</p>
   <p>It is not for us to praise the paper, whether for its typographic excellence or for the richness of its contents; this we leave to the many thousands of readers of the paper. Our daily and weekly readers have written us that the Svenska Nyheter is filling its place in the Swedish-American press in a manner which hardly leaves anything to be desired. That these expressions of satisfaction with the paper are sincerely meant is proven by the interest the subscribers have shown in getting others to subscribe. A large number of new subscriptions are received by us every day, and we feel certain that when we now enlarge and, if possible, improve the paper, the sacrifices required of us will be rewarded by a renewed activity on the part of our subscribers in speaking well of our paper to their friends and acquaintances.</p>
   <p>Our program remains the same as before: clean thoughts, clean language, <pb facs="5423404_3_0666.jpg" n="3"/>determined opposition to all types of hypocrisy and insincerity whether in the field of religion, social relations, or politics.</p>
   <p>The Editors.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
