<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-04-07">Apr. 7, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Literature</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Reviews)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0704</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0704.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-04-07">Apr. 7, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">LITERATURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Reviews)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have recently received the first two numbers of the magazine, Hemmets Van (The Friend of the Home), a monthly which is being published in Chicago, and edited by Doctor Phil. Emanuel Schmidt and Reverend John Rocen. From the view point of typographical presentation, these two volumes hold a unique place in the Swedish press and in the Swedish world of books as well. The good impression made by the appearance of the magazines leads us to read the contents carefully in order to reassure ourselves on the question of whether the latter is worthy of the expensive cover which includes it.</p>
   <p>In reading this magazine, we meet first of all the universally respected poet and etcher, Doctor J. A. Edgren; the poet and editor, Doctor Jacob Bonggren; Professor C. G. Lagergren; and the editor of the magazine, Dr. Phil. Emanuel <pb facs="5423404_3_0705.jpg" n="2"/>Schmidt, together with their individual contributions. The Reverend Erick Sandell analyzes Socialism in the light of the Scriptures; here we are being "spiritually nursed," there is a "Hymn of Peace" by J. M. Omberg, and "God's Praise" by Anna Maria Lenngren. In the pages following, we meet the other editor of the magazine, the Reverend John Rocen. We also find Frans Hedberg's beautiful poem, "The Silent Forces," and Brother Arvid's (Rev. C. A. Hagstrom) "Grain for the Little Birds." Then we go on an excursion with Doctor Schmidt through the "Lands of the Bible," and listen to the "Echoes from the Mission Fields" by Reverend J. O. Backlund, who leads us back "In the Pioneer Age" where he paints a picture of the "Culture Drawings from the Tune of Conversion of the North."</p>
   <p>"Among Swedish Authors" is to become a permanent department in Hemmets Van.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0706.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In this department, the editors will publish such articles of the most renowned Swedish authors worthy of being translated into English. In the magazine, we meet Grafstrom's, "Norrland;" Pontus Wikner's "My Mother's Testament;" and F. M. Franzen's "The Song of the Lapp," in translations from the Swedish into English.</p>
   <p>In the second volume of the magazine, we are charmed by the beautiful poem, "My Mother," by the warm hearted poet, Zakarias Topelius; the poem," Contentment," by the aged Johan David Valerius. Doctor Frank Peterson tells "Something of the Swedes in America;" Reverend Sandell instructs us in "Methods for Literary Studies;" Fridthjof Nansen's "To The South" follows; then Nicander's "Evening;" and Franzen's "Machine for Light."</p>
   <p>Both volumes are richly illustrated. They are free from advertisements, and <pb facs="5423404_3_0707.jpg" n="4"/>each consists of eighty pages. The Hemmets Van costs two dollars per year, and subscriptions may be left at 637 Unity Building, Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
