<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-01-31">Jan. 31, 1905</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1318</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1318.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-01-31">Jan. 31, 1905</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To The Members of Scandia Mutual Life Insurance Company:</p>
   <p>As we are gathered here for our annual meeting, our thoughts linger with satisfaction over the activity of our society during the past year. Letters received from every section of our country testify to the high regard in which the society and its activity is held; the general attitude is that since the time of society's reorganization, the results of our work have been highly satisfactory. The objections which at first were raised a gainst the "liens" which had been called and for which it was found necessary to assess against the letters of membership given by the original society seem to have lost their force. The members in question have no doubt realized that however troublesome the "liens" were, yet they were both necessary and equitable. From many of the hundreds of our countrymen, we have received grateful letters during the past year. These members have received grateful letters during the past year. These members have received financial aid on the occasion of the passing away of relatives, also members of our society. The knowledge that we are thus instrumental in allaying the bitterness of sorrow in many a home through the extension <pb facs="5423404_3_1319.jpg" n="2"/>of financial aid is encouraging. For many cases, except for the financial aid received from Scandia Mutual, physical suffering would have been added to the bereavement, and we have reason to be gratified at having been instrumental in thus extending aid when hours are dark...</p>
   <p>A total of 1,025 new members have been gained during the past year. They constitute eloquent testimony of the confidence reposed in the society by our people, but also of the energetic work of our agents. The popular confidence in our society needs to be guarded, and its value appreciated; for we know from experience that without this confidence, neither agents nor officers can make their efforts for development bear fruit. For this reason, we need to perform our duties here in such a manner as to maintain and even increase the confidence in our work now in evidence among our people. The total membership of the association is now 8,870. The net increase in membership during the year is 582. The average age of our members is somewhat lower now than last year, a fact of great importance for our association. The governors of the society have considered it their duty to appoint the best possible agents in districts where the field <pb facs="5423404_3_1320.jpg" n="3"/>seemed promising. This has caused greater expenses, but the expenses have not been wasted; they have brought good returns. It is of the greatest importance for our society to gain accession of young blood. We have also made effort to get able and conscientious physicians to examine those seeking membership. This has increased costs considerably, but the board is convinced that there is no more effective means of saving for the society than by being most careful in accepting new members. One single mistake in this regard may cost the society more money than that of the salary of any one of these officials. During the year, Scandia has taken care of all its financial obligations, insurance amounts, as well as current expenses. In addition, the reserve fund has been increased by $58,987.45, so that this fund now has risen to $387,619.96.</p>
   <p>We believe that the members of the Society have, by this time, in some measure studied the proposal to change the constitution, which was presented some time ago by the board of directors, so that now they are able to act intelligently on those proposals. The board did not present to the members this proposal to an important change in the constitution of our <pb facs="5423404_3_1321.jpg" n="4"/>society without having first considered the matter carefully. We have become convinced that the interests of Scandia demanded our presentation of the proposal to the members. At the same time, we have not for one moment been oblivious to the fact that the directors are but the servants of the society as at present constituted; the board of directors can, for reason of this fact, initiate no change not contributory to the welfare of the society. The board of directors, however, became convinced that a change as proposed will be of great benefit as regard the future of our society. It was, therefore, considered a duty by the board to place the matter before the members. The full and only purpose of the proposed change is to make it possible for Scandia Mutual Life Insurance Company to issue letters of membership of a type which our people, and especially our young people, desire. The proposed change in the Society's constitution is the means, under the laws, by which the purpose mentioned can be realized. After the change has been made, the society remains constituted of the same members as before, and will be, in fact, the same society. The value of the present membership letters will not be altered, and "assessments" will be issued <pb facs="5423404_3_1322.jpg" n="5"/>monthly for them as hitherto. But we are convinced that it is our duty to meet the constantly increasing requests that letters of membership be offered which, while costing more, offer advantages which those issued under the present rules cannot offer. If we do not meet these demands, other corporations will gladly meet them, and in so doing, cause a great, and perhaps disastrous loss to our society. We beg to remind our members that as time goes on it becomes ever more difficult for insurance societies using the "assessment" method to persist. Thus, for example, we are not now permitted to insure in several states where there are large colonies of our people; New York, the New England states, Wisconsin, Kansas, and several other states. If our society accepts the proposal for re-organization presented by the board of directors, we will be enabled to send our representatives into all the states in the Union, and there will be the very best prospects that our people may build up a very strong insurance company. As far as we have been able to ascertain, the proposal for change in our constitution has been met with general acceptance by our members. Many requests for information have been contained in the letters received from <pb facs="5423404_3_1323.jpg" n="6"/>various parts of the country, but no one has expressed any dislike to the proposal itself, while most of the letters have applauded it warmly. It needs to be added that the re-organized new corporation has merely the significance of making possible the indicated change in the policy of the society, and we beg to express the wish that the name of the society may remain unchanged.</p>
   <p>Respectfully submitted,</p>
   <p>L. G. Abrahamson, President.</p>
   <p>Chicago, January 26, 1905.</p>
   <p>As a result of the meeting (referred to in Pres. Abrahamson's report, Tr.) Scandia Life Insurance Company was consolidated with Scandia Mutual Life Insurance Company by nearly a unanimous vote. 4,010 votes were cast for the consolidation and 320 votes against it. The society will remain a mutual life insurance company, the directors to be elected by the members, as in the past.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1324.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>From the report of the secretary, it appears that during the past year, $136,389.17 was paid in death claims, and that all losses has been adjusted satisfactorily. The reserve fund has increased by $58,987.45. The reserve capital is now $387,619.96, and the total capital, including "liens", amounts to $1,541,705.73.</p>
   <p>During the year, 1,025 new members were accepted; 128 members died, and 227 discontinued their membership for various causes. The net increase in membership during the year is 582.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
