<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-06-25">June 25, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Swedes Celebrate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0325</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0325.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1907-06-25">June 25, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO SWEDES CELEBRATE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As we have observed, there are many Swedes in Chicago. Last Sunday, on Midsummer's evening, the Swedes turned out in great numbers. The Swedish National Society, with twenty-five thousand children gathered in Elliott's Park. The Singing Society, and the Svithiod Club, who numbered nine thousand, in their glad celebration, gathered at Columbia Park. The Good Templers, many thousand of them, had a enjoyable time on an excursion on the Lake. Besides all of these groups, many families celebrated in Swedish picnic style out on the lawns.</p>
   <p>One thing we must admit that in Sweden, we have never seen so many people gather on this occasion. Chicago is, therefore, entitled to the first prize But we observed something also more important than the large gatherings at these celebrations. We noted that the Swedes in Chicago have had time to "classify" themselves in the "upper and "Lower" classes. Such self-praise has never accomplished anything good, more often it has done much harm.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0326.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Even among the Chicago Swedes, possibly there are Swedish "classes" that wrangle over trivial matters for supremacy, and thereby loose their strength. But until these conditions are found, we think of them as only imaginary. As long as one people, or one nation has a mutual understanding there will be no bitter feelings toward one another. One finds brotherhood in this understanding, one finds strength. In the cultured European countries, it seems impossible to change this class distinction.</p>
   <p>Minister Lagercrantz said in his talk before the Swedish National Society at the midsummerfest that in Sweden during the past ten years a change has taken place, which is hard to believe possible, and with long strides, conditions have become better in every way. The conditions for the laborer have become better, and a brighter outlook for a more democratic union is seen. Such conditions in our homeland are much desired; because it means progress in all kinds of endeavor. When that day comes that the Swedes in <pb facs="5423404_3_0327.jpg" n="3"/>Stockholm and Gottenborg have progressed so far that they have no feeling of superiority, or "class distinction," when twenty-five thousand of them can assemble at one time to celebrate a national holiday as they did in Chicago, then, and only then, have the Swedes much to hope for from her sons and daughters.</p>
   <p>This progress means unity, and with unity there follows progress in all kinds of endeavor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
