<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-12-28">Dec. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">New Year Thoughts</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0589</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0589.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1915-12-28">Dec. 28, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">NEW YEAR THOUGHTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is an age-old custom at the turn of the year, to thank one's friends and associates for pleasant relations in the past year and wish them happiness in the new one. It is a fine custom, expressing humane sentiment and good will among men.</p>
   <p>The Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter is pleased to follow suit, and we are anxious to give voice to our gratitude and sincere thanks for the confidence and support which we have enjoyed during the year that is now drawing to a close.</p>
   <p>The strength of a newspaper is measured by the confidence which its readers and the general public have in it, and the moral and material support which it receives from these sources. The Tribunen-Nyheter is fortunate in this respect, and that is why, in spite of the stiff competition, it is able to <pb facs="5423404_3_0590.jpg" n="2"/>hold its lead among Swedish-American newspapers. Our success so far spurs us to new and increased efforts in the future, and when we today take the opportunity to express our hearty thanks to our thousands of friends and wellwishers, we want to add the hope that they will stick with us also in the new year.</p>
   <p>The Tribunen-Nyheter will remain faithful to its established traditions as a newspaper for the Swedish-American general public. We will try to cultivate and preserve the Swedish spirit, report happenings impartially, and continue our policy of political independence. We will further lend our support to the temperance cause and to the struggle of the workers for better living conditions.</p>
   <p>As a Swedish-American paper, with the accent on Swedish, the Tribunen-Nyheter will continue to pay special attention to activities among our nationals, both in and outside of Chicago. While we are on that subject, we wish to point to such features as our having a special correspondent at the <pb facs="5423404_3_0591.jpg" n="3"/>San Francisco Fair, who in a series of articles, accompanied by fine illustrations, gave our readers a thorough description of the Swedish art and industrial exhibit at the Fair. This was the only Chicago paper that carried a detailed report on the exhibit.</p>
   <p>The Tribunen-Nyheter will maintain its position as the foremost Swedish-American newspaper, and will continue to encourage and support cultural activities among our countrymen, as well as reform movements for the common weal. We shall do so without in the least detracting from efforts in the same direction made by other foreign groups or by the native American elements, and neither shall we forget the privileges we enjoy under the Stars and Stripes, and the duties that go with them.</p>
   <p>We are not planning any radical changes in regard to reading material and its arrangement. As before, the Tribunen-Nyheter will present the latest news from all parts of the old country, as well as from America and the rest of the world. Plenty of space will be given to happenings among Swedish- <pb facs="5423404_3_0592.jpg" n="4"/>Americans. As before, we will offer the best serials and short stories available, and all other features which our readers are accustomed to look for on our pages, will be kept on the same high level. There will be contributions from the finest pens in both Sweden and Swedish-America. In short, we will strive to make this newspaper so interesting and well liked that no Swedish-American home will want to be without it.</p>
   <p>This, briefly, constitutes our policies and plans for the coming year, and, in closing, we thank our subscribers, friends and wellwishers for pleasant associations in the past and wish you all</p>
   <p>A Happy and Prosperous New Year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
