<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-05-24">May 24, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Presented to the City Unveiling of the Linne Statue at Lincoln Park</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1049</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1049.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1891-05-24">May 24, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">PRESENTED TO THE CITY UNVEILING OF THE LINNE STATUE AT LINCOLN PARK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With the sun shing from a cloudless sky on the trees and flowers which were his life study and surrounded by thousands of admiring fellow countrymen, the statue of Carl Von Linne in Lincoln Park was unveiled yesterday and formally became the property of the people of Chicago. The Swedish-American population of the city joined with visitors of that race from the Northwest in honoring the memory of Sweden's illustrious botanist, doctor, chemist, and zoologist.</p>
   <p>All the Swedish societies of Chicago, supplemented by labor organizations, several brass bands and prominent Swedish-American citizens in carriages rendesvoused at 155 East Chicago Avenue shortly after two o'clock. Marshaled by D. R. Sven Windrow, who wore the uniform of a select Knight of America, the procession passed between crowds of spectators via Dearborn Avenue to the park in the following order: Platoon of Police, Marshalls and Adjutant, Guard of Honor, Select Knights of America, Invited guests in carriages, directors of Swedish Linnean Association of Chicago, Society Svea <pb facs="5423404_3_1050.jpg" n="2"/>Odd Fellows, First Swedish Lodge, Society of the North Star, headed by Swedish Gymnasium Society; Court Vega, Independent Order of Foresters, Independent Order of Svithiod, Scandinavian Society Kronan, Society Bolder, Society Thor, Courts Linne Stockholm and Tegner A. O. Foresters of America, Society Gustavos Adolphus, Society Dunee, Society Baltic, Harmony Knights of Pythias, Vikings, Alpha Literary Club, Society Linne, Independent Order of Good Templars, and Workingmen's Societies.</p>
   <p>A Brilliant Spectacle</p>
   <p>The procession was a brilliant spectacle. Most of the societies were uniformed and their gorgeous silk banners, mingling with the Norwegian, Swedish, Danish, and American national flags, added luster to the scene. As the procession turned into the Stockton Drive and advanced toward the statue, the thousands of citizens, women and children, who crowded around the platform and monument turned an admiring eye upon the approaching host and cheered lustily. From the platform as far as the eye could reach almost on all sides were to be seen people of all classes, equally divided as to sex, the typical Swedish features naturally predominating.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1051.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After a patriotic selection by the band on the platform, Robert Lindholm, president of the Linnean Association, removed his hat, advanced to the front of the platform and delivered the presentation speech which was frequently interrupted by applause. He said:</p>
   <p>The Presentation</p>
   <p>"In the name of the Swedish Linnean Monument Association, I have the honor and pleasure of presenting to the Commissioners of Lincoln Park and to the City of Chicago, a statue of Carl Von Linne, the naturalist, the doctor, the chemist, and the founder of scientific botany.</p>
   <p>"When we concluded to testify our regard for our adopted country and our favorite city in a proper and enduring manner, it did not take long for us to decide upon Linne as the best representative of that scientific foundation upon which rests the constitution, the government, and the wonderful development of the industrial resources of the great Republic of North America. Not that our native land is poor in great men, for no country has a greater percentage. Thrones have tottered at the beck, and empires have been disposed of by Swedish statesmen. Oppressed Europe has appealed to Swedish <pb facs="5423404_3_1052.jpg" n="4"/>arms for deliverance, and have in vain.....</p>
   <p>Linne was in science what the old American pioneers were in industry. He embarked upon unknown seas. He left old landmarks behind him and made his own roads through the labyrinths of natural science, and he staked out these roads so plainly that his followers could not lose their way. He divided the vegetable kingdom into twenty-four classes and the animal kingdom into six classes. These classes he divided into orders; the orders he subdivided into genera and these again into species, and by so doing brought order out of chaos, and made it possible for his investigators to pursue their investigations intelligently. He never claimed that his classification (based on outward semblances) was a scientific basis and he hinted at the changes that were subsequently advocated by Curie, who made anatomy the basis for clarification, but Linne knew that no one man could hope to accomplish in his life a purely scientific classification, and he made the easiest road he could, knowing that some road was necessary before any progress could be made, and science today is traveling on his roads.</p>
   <p>The idea of different sex in plants, dreamed of by Aristotle 2,000 years before was first promulgated by Linne and made use of in his classification. He published scientific works mostly in Latin, commenced with his system of <pb facs="5423404_3_1053.jpg" n="5"/>nature, embraced nearly every branch of natural science as well as medicine, and there are twenty-eight in number.</p>
   <p>As Mr. Lindholm uttered the last word his eleven year old daughter Vesta, attired in a Swedish peasant dress and garlanded with carnations and smilax, pulled the cord attached to the top of the statue. After a few seconds of suspense the flags of Norway, Sweden, and the United States, parting and falling to the base of the monument revealed to the view of the great throng the bronze feature of Carl Von Linne.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
