<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-03-20">Mar. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Scandinavians and the World's Fair in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0194</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0194.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-03-20">Mar. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">SCANDINAVIANS AND THE WORLD'S FAIR IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Scandinavian Council, which was formed for the purpose of promoting Scandinavian participation in the coming world's fair, held its regular monthly meeting last Wednesday in the Cliff Dwellers Club. The chief subject of discussion was the propaganda tour of the Scandinavian countries, which has been under preparation for some time. The party will consist of some fifty persons, most of whom are native Americans and prominent in the business and social life of Chicago. All of them are, of course, enthusiastic supporters of the fair. They are to travel in one group under the leadership of Charles S. Peterson, who is a vice-president of the organization in charge of the fair. The party will sail from New York June 19 aboard the liner "Gripsholm" which is scheduled to arrive in Gothenburg on June 28. The cities of Oslo, Bergen, Stockholm, and Helsingfors will then be visited.</p>
   <p>It was further decided that the Council is to act as host to prominent Scandinavians who visit Chicago. The first event of this kind will be arranged <pb facs="5423404_3_0195.jpg" n="2"/>by the Norwegians, who are represented in the Council by C. H. Sinding. He will preside at a luncheon which will be given for the Norwegian explorer Frithiof Nansen. The Swedish representative, Peterson, will make the necessary arrangements for the entertainment of Professor John Roosval of Sweden, who will arrive in Chicago in the near future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
