<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-09-26">Sept. 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Instruction in English for Newcomers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0795</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0795.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-09-26">Sept. 26, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">INSTRUCTION IN ENGLISH FOR NEWCOMERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have on several occasions commented on the laudable interest the young Swedes who have arrived here during the past year have shown in learning the English language as quickly as possible. In order to help these ambitious newcomers, several Swedish churches in the city have started night schools where they may receive instruction by competent teachers, in most cases entirely without charge.</p>
   <p>The following churches have taken up this avtivity:</p>
   <p>The Trinity Swedish Lutheran Church, located at Seminary and Barry Avenues. Its night school, comprising four classes, is attended by some two hundred pupils. Classes meet Monday and Wednesday nights.</p>
   <p>The Swedish Free Church, 3516 Sheffield Avenue, opened its night school a couple of months ago, and it has now about four hundred pupils and four teachers. Classes meet Monday and Friday nights.</p>
   <p>The Saron Swedish Lutheran Church, Shakespeare Avenue and Richmond Street, <pb facs="5423404_3_0796.jpg" n="2"/>offers English instruction Monday and Friday nights at eight o'clock. There is no charge.</p>
   <p>The Swedish Lutheran Messiah Church, Waller Avenue and Iowa Street, in Austin, offers instruction in English every Monday and Wednesday night. The instructor is Sylvia Johnson, who is a teacher in the public schools.</p>
   <p>The Ebenezer Swedish Lutheran Church, Paulina Street and Foster Avenue, is giving instruction to about two hundred and fifty pupils. There are four teachers.</p>
   <p>The Swedish Baptist Church, in Ravenswood, is also conducting a night school.</p>
   <p>The congregations pastor, P. Engelbrekth, is the instructor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
