<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-09-24">Sept. 24, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Another Forward Step</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0539</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0539.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-09-24">Sept. 24, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">ANOTHER FORWARD STEP</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter is enjoying a steadily widening circulation among Finnish Swedes both in the United States and Canada. We have now about two thousand subscribers among this group, which we are sure, is a much higher number than any other Swedish-American newspaper can claim.</p>
   <p>These Swedish Finlanders constitute a unit which is making itself increasingly felt, especially through one of its organizations, the Runeberg Order, whose branches are found in every part of the country.</p>
   <p>The Tribunen is fully aware of the importance of this group, and has just completed arrangements for being of special service to it. Beginning with this issue, we will present a Swedish Finlander's Department, comprising <pb facs="5423404_3_0540.jpg" n="2"/>four columns, two of which will contain news from Finland, while the remaining two will be devoted to miscellaneous items that are of special interest to the group. The editor of this new department is a Swedish-Finish journalist who knows the problems of his national group and its cultural and literary aspirations. On page seven of this issue he outlines roughly the program which he is planning to follow in order to make his department render the best possible service to the cultural and literary interests of his countrymen in the United States and Canada.</p>
   <p>The Tribunen hopes that this innovation will be well received and appreciated by those for whom it is especially intended. It does of course, mean considerable added expense, which we gladly incur, however, because we believe this new department will fill a real need, and we are confidently counting on the cooperation of the Swedish-Finish group.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: There is a large number of people of Swedish ancestry in <pb facs="5423404_3_0541.jpg" n="3"/>Finland, dating from the time when that country was under the Swedish crown. They have maintained their cultural ties with the mother country, and the Swedish language is widely used in Finland.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
