<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-01-10">Jan. 10, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Fifty-Year Jubilee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0642</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0642.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1905-01-10">Jan. 10, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">FIFTY-YEAR JUBILEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our honored contemporary Gamla och NyaHemlandet (The Old and The New Homeland) had cause to review its long and honored past the other day. On January 3, fifty years ago, the paper was founded under the name Hemlandet, Det gamla och Det nya (The Homeland, The Old and The New), at Galesburg, Illinois, and from that city the paper was transferred to Chicago in 1859. In honor of the fifty-year jubilee, the Hemlandet for January 3 appeared in jubilee edition, twenty-eight pages, very elegant, and also very rich in its contents. An exhaustive historical account of the development of the paper through stormy times and fair, going back to the very time of its foundation, is one of the very interesting features of the jubilee edition, which is accompanied by biographies with photos of all those who during the years have contributed, in the various departments, to make the Hemlandet <pb facs="5423404_3_0643.jpg" n="2"/>what it is today, one of the most prominent Swedish-American newspapers. It may be said, however, that from the time when the Hemlandet was taken over by our outstanding compatriot A. E. Johnson, the paper has made the most pronounced advancement. Svenska Nyheter begs to send its best wishes for further progress, on the occasion of the jubilee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
