<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-03-03">Mar. 3, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The World of Finance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0573</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0573.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-03-03">Mar. 3, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORLD OF FINANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under this heading the Tribunen-Nyheter presents in this issue, for the first time, a department which we know will be of great interest to many of our readers and, we hope, will be consulted and appreciated just as much as our already well-established column of legal questions and answers.</p>
   <p>Of late we have been receiving numerous inquiries in regard to money exchange rates and other financial matters which are now subjected to daily fluctuations; and it is for the purpose of giving information and, possibly, advice to such questioners that we have opened our columns to "The World of Finance."</p>
   <p>We have succeeded in interesting a prominent Swedish banker here in this undertaking, and he will conduct the column, supplying needed information and answering questions.</p>
   <p>In this manner the Tribunen-Nyheter wishes to supply expert aid and advice in <pb facs="5423404_3_0574.jpg" n="2"/>these uncertain and difficult times. It is, of course, understood that we can only try to give as reliable information as possible, without undertaking any legal responsibility. Those who submit questions must sign their full names and addresses, and if a personal answer is desired the questions must be accomplished by postage.</p>
   <p>Letters should be addressed to The World of Finance, Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter, 180 North Dearborn Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
