<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-09-24">Sept. 24, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Next Swedish Day to Be Celebrated in Swedish-Owned Park</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-09-24">Sept. 24, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">NEXT SWEDISH DAY TO BE CELEBRATED IN SWEDISH-OWNED PARK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago's Swedish Good Templars--district lodges No. 2 and No. 5, to be exact--have for a long period of years celebrated their Swedish Day midsummer festival in Ravinia Park. So also last summer, when, despite bad weather, the event was attended by some ten thousand people.</p>
   <p>During the last few years, many people have voiced the opinion that Swedish Day ought to be observed in a Swedish-owned park, and this sentiment has been gaining favor among our countrymen right along. A few weeks after last year's festival, a meeting was held and a committee appointed for the purpose of preparing plans for the purchase of a suitable location. This committee made several excursions to Fox River Valley, where a number of sites suitable for the purposes of the Good Templars were for sale. An agreement was finally reached with the owners of one of them, and last week the deal went through.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0250.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A tract of land comprising 62 1/8 acres has been bought; it is conveniently located in very nice surroundings, near the town of Geneva and next to the Aurora-Elgin electric railroad, which actually cuts through a corner of the park, where a station is to be built. The park will be named by the new owners. The purchasing price was $32,500.</p>
   <p>One result of this purchase will probably be a joint celebration of Swedish Day by all Good Templar lodges in Illinois. Two lodges in Rockford, one in De Kalb, and one in Geneva joined the two Chicago lodges in buying this park, and the scope of the popular midsummer festival will thus be extended.</p>
   <p>It is expected that many other Swedish organizations will rent the park and its facilities for summer outings.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
