<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-11-12">Nov. 12, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Engineers' Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0508</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0508.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Amerikanaren</title>,
<date when="1908-11-12">Nov. 12, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH ENGINEERS' SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swedish Engineers' society held a meeting Saturday evening at Kuny Remler Hall on Wabash Avenue, where a large number of engineers were invited to enjoy a dinner with the members of the society. This was a very congenial gathering where both the body and the soul's needs were satisfied. Henry Nyberg, president of the society acted as master of ceremonies, and opened the meeting with a short talk in which he pointed out the outstanding part taken by the Swedish engineers in America. Mr. E. W. Olson also spoke about the Engineers' society. Other speakers were: Professors Carlson, Sjoquist, and Lindquist; Engineer Okerlind; contractors Erickson and Peterson; and Engineers Nyberg and Calgren. The most interesting talks were made by Erickson and Okerlind. Mr. Erickson pointed out the part the Swedish people of Chicago have taken in <pb facs="5423404_3_0509.jpg" n="2"/>the building industry, and assured us that twenty-five per cent of all the building now being done in Chicago was in the hands of the Swedes. Okerlind explained the work done by the Swedish engineers, he being the logical man to do this, as he was the driving force that made this meeting possible.</p>
   <p>Several Swedish songs were sung, with Mr. Lindblad at the piano. The society adjourned at midnight. In one of his points, Okerlind advised the Swedish technical tradesmen to join the only genuine Swedish society of its kind in Chicago. He gave good reasons why the Swedish engineers and architects should bind themselves together.</p>
   <p>We understand from the tone of the meeting that the society will not only accept Civil engineers as members, but also Swedish men in the industrial <pb facs="5423404_3_0510.jpg" n="3"/>field with technical knowledge would be accepted as members also. Information regarding membership should be made to Engineer G. A. Okerlind, Secretary of the society, 1702 Railway Exchange Building.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
