<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1893-02-08">Feb. 8, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">News from the World's Fair.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0406</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0406.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1893-02-08">Feb. 8, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM THE WORLD'S FAIR.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new portrait of King Oscar II has been done by the artist Axel Jungstedt in Stockholm upon the order of a Swedish Society and will be sent to the World's Fair in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The picture is a full length one of the king in the uniform of an admiral; and he wears a plumed hat of that rank too.</p>
   <p>Amongst his royal medals he wears the French medal as a life savior and values it very much. The portrait likeness is well painted and is placed in a frame made of oak, which is gilded.</p>
   <p>Artist C. Rosenberg, Stockholm,has been working on a giantic painting ordered by the Swedish Tourist Society, Stockholm, since fall. The view is taken from <pb facs="5423404_3_0407.jpg" n="2"/>Hotel Ryberg. The Royal Castle appears in the middle of the painting. The sun is shining over the tree tops of the Stromparterr, over the folk-crowded Norrbro, where the military parade is passing by and over the glittering Strommen, filled with sailing boats. Skeppsholmen is also noticeable and so is Gustaf Adolfs Torg. The painting will worthily take its space at the Swedish Exhibition at the World's Fair.</p>
   <p>The Swedish Directors of the Lighthouses will exhibit a Swedish lighthouse at the Fair. It is one well known to sailors in the Swedish waters; the light burns ten days without having to be refilled or tended and with a never failing light. The lamp was constructed by C. V. Lyth. The lighthouse is to be erected in front of the Swedish Pavilion.</p>
   <p>The Great Kopparbergs Company will also be represented in the Pavilion showing the different products of the company.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
