<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-11-16">Nov. 16, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Form Scandinavian Folk Dance Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0154</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-norwegian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0154.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2) (Norwegian)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2) (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1932-11-16">Nov. 16, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">FORM SCANDINAVIAN FOLK DANCE SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Representatives of the Scandinavian folk dance societies in the city met recently and decided to form a central organization under the name, United Nordic Folk Dancers of America. Swedish, Norwegian, and Danish dance societies in other parts of the country will be invited to join, and inquiries have already been received from some of them. If the present plans materialize a convention of Scandinavian folk dancers will be held here in Chicago during the "Scandinavian Week" which is to be sponsored by the Century of Progress Exposition next year.</p>
   <p>The first public appearance of this new organization will take place Sunday, December 11, in Wicker Park Hall on the West Side. On that occasion the Scandinavian public will be given a taste of the kind of performance they may expect next summer when the dancers will appear at the World's Fair. The individual Swedish, Norwegian, and Danish dance societies have often appeared before audiences consisting of their respective nationals, but next Sunday will <pb facs="5423404_3_0155.jpg" n="2"/>mark the first time that they perform together, and it will be interesting to make comparisons.</p>
   <p>A group of Indians from Wisconsin will also be on hand, and they will demonstrate old Indian war dances as well as peace dances. Folk dancers from Rockford and Waukegan, Illinois, have been invited, and they may also appear on the stage. </p>
   <p>The show will wind up with an ordinary dance and Schmidt's orchestra will furnish the music. </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
