<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-12-29">Dec. 29, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Our Program</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0660</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0660.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1903-12-29">Dec. 29, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">OUR PROGRAM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During these last days of the year practically every newspaper contains announcements from the editors as to the policy to be pursued during the coming 366 days, both in regard to humanity in general and the subscribers to the paper in particular. We, too, have caught the program-announcing fever; we feel the urge to make a brief statement to the many thousand Swedes with whom we are in touch, week after week, through the Svenska Nyheter.</p>
   <p>Svenska Nyheter is about to enter its fifteenth year of existence. Strong and progressive, it is able to review its activity during the past years and say without exaggeration: "I have done my work to the best of my ability; I have fought a straight, clean fight for the right as I saw it." What more can the Swedish-Americans in Chicago and its environs expect of a newspaper?</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0661.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Other newspapers may rest upon the laurels they have won; Svenska Nyheter cannot and will not rest upon its past achievements. Our age, our people, and our present society demand more of the newspapers of today than was ever demanded in the past. Let those who are unable to keep step with the army of progress stay behind and rest on their past achievements; let those from whom youth has fled dream of the customs of days that are gone; let those tired ones go to sleep, their faces toward the past, or let them form the rearguard of the sorry army of reaction. Svenska Nyheter speaks to the young warmhearted people whose minds are afire with visions of the future. To them, Svenska Nyheter speaks of the accomplishments that may be achieved in the field of great ideas, through unity and co-operation.</p>
   <p>Svenska Nyheter is the organ of the labor class, of the people who produce, and it will continue to defend the interests of this class. Without fear of consequences, the paper will speak against everything which demoralizes our people or leads them astray; and without fail, a lie will be called a lie in this paper, and truth will be called truth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
