<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-22">Jan. 22, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Art Exhibit at Swedish Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0083</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0083.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-22">Jan. 22, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">ART EXHIBIT AT SWEDISH CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The ninth Swedish-American Art exhibit at the Swedish Club will be held from March 27 to April 4. This year's exposition takes place rather earlier than usual.</p>
   <p>We wish to mention that the opportunity to participate in this exhibition is open to all Swedish-American artists, and that announcement cards may be obtained from Mr. Axel Hulten, 523 Plymouth Court, Chicago, Ill.</p>
   <p>This year's exhibition committee is composed of John E. Ericsson, Peter Ericsson, Marcus Gustavson, Max Hedman, Axel Hulten, Walter Jones, B. O. Larson, John S. Meck, O. C. Nylund, Charles S. Peterson, and Eric Warner.</p>
   <p>The number of prizes and the list of the judges selected will be published at a later date in the press.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0084.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This exhibit differs from the eight previous in that most of the exhibited work will become permanent exhibition material to be sent to the East, first to New York and Brooklyn, and later to Sweden, where it will be shown in the larger cities as an evidence of what the Swedish-American painters are able to do in the realm of art. It should be pointed out that it has been decided not to take sculptural works to Sweden. The tour of the art exhibit throughout the East will be under the patronage of the American-Scandinavian Foundation, and the auspices of the Swedish-American Institute in Sweden. In order to make this exposition as representative and complete as possible, it has been arranged to take along not only the more recent art works but also such art creations as have been previously exhibited and proved to be the best the artists have put upon the canvas. Many of these art works are now privately owned, but it is believed it will be possible to prevail upon the owners to loan them for the sake of the good cause. These formerly <pb facs="5423404_3_0085.jpg" n="3"/>exhibited works will not be shown at the Swedish Club this year, but after the regular exhibition, a jury will be chosen to select those works which they consider worthy of being taken along to the East and to the old homeland. It is to win time for the tour of the exhibition to Sweden, that the exposition at the Swedish Club is given earlier this year.</p>
   <p>Art creations produced in the East need not necessarily be sent to the exhibit in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
