<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-03-16">Mar. 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Active in Swedish-American Societies</title> [Half-tone, one column, sixth of a page, full-face picture of Richard Flodberg.]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1103</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1103.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1921-03-16">Mar. 16, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">ACTIVE IN SWEDISH-AMERICAN SOCIETIES</title> [Half-tone, one column, sixth of a page, full-face picture of Richard Flodberg.]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As reported in last week's issue, Richard Flodberg, of 3317 Herndon Street, Chicago, has recently been elected head of the Vasa Order's District Lodge No. 8, of the Illinois District. The election took place during the organization's annual meeting, which was held in Moline, Illinois, March 5 and 6.</p>
   <p>Flodberg belongs to the Harmoni Lodge No. 313 of this city, and is one of its founders. Formerly he was a member of the Oscar II Lodge No. 129, and has been associated with the Vasa Order for twelve years.</p>
   <p>It is safe to say that Flodberg is one of the most popular men in the organization. He enjoys the confidence and good will of all, and his words and judgment carry weight when important decisions are to be made. In <pb facs="5423404_3_1104.jpg" n="2"/>discussions involving the policies and welfare of his lodge his keen intelligence, together with his respect for the opinions of others, are apparent. These qualities more than make up for any shortcomings he may have as an orator.</p>
   <p>Flodberg was born in Varmland, Sweden, July 21, 1880, and came to America at the age of 20. His first three years in this country were spent in Bridgeport, Connecticut, but in 1903 he moved to Chicago, where he has made his home ever since. He is a plumber by trade.</p>
   <p>Since Flodberg joined the Vasa Order, he has held many offices within that organization. He has served as secretary, president, vice-president, and master of ceremonies, and in the Harmoni Lodge, of which he is now vice-president, he has also served as financial secretary. In addition, he served on the executive committee of the District Lodge, and was a delegate to the convention of the Grand Lodge in Jamestown, in 1912. Finally, for many years he has been, and still is, a delegate to the Swedish National <pb facs="5423404_3_1105.jpg" n="3"/>Association of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Besides being a very active member of the Vasa Order, Flodberg also belongs to the Independent Order of Good Templars, the Svithiod order and to the Loyal Order of Moose. He has taken an active part in the affairs of the co-operative restaurant "Idrott" since it was opened, and is now on its board of directors.</p>
   <p>In 1914 he married Esther W. Lundberg.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
