<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-06-09">June 9, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">North Park College</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Advertisement]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0804</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0804.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1920-06-09">June 9, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">NORTH PARK COLLEGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Advertisement]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Mission Covenant's School in Chicago, established in 1891, opens its thirtieth school year on September 6, 1920 in the following departments:</p>
   <p>1. The theological seminary; for the training of pastors and missionaries. Pupils are admitted only on the recommendation of congregations and pastors.</p>
   <p>2. The junior college; a two-year course for young men and young women who have graduated from high school, and wish to prepare for the university.</p>
   <p>3. The high school; offering four parallel four-year courses for boys and girls who have completed the eight classes of grade school.</p>
   <p>4. The business school; offering practical, up-to-date training in book-keeping, stenography, typing, and other subjects needed in a thorough business course.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0805.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>5. The two-year high school course; offering a combination high school and business course. It is designed for boys and girls who want additional schooling, but are not able to take a full high school course.</p>
   <p>6. Elementary courses; for young persons, and for mature persons who need some formal instruction in English and also want to continue their general education.</p>
   <p>7. The school of music; where competent instructors give lessons on the piano and violin. Harmony, voice, and the history of music are also taught. Graduates are qualified music teachers.</p>
   <p>8. The correspondence school; for Sunday School teachers, and those seeking knowledge and understanding of the Bible and the teaching thereof. Graduates are qualified Sunday School teachers.</p>
   <p>There is a Christian atmosphere about the school, and good comradeship prevails. The staff is composed of experienced teachers.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0806.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Students participate in gymnastics and athletics.</p>
   <p>Our catalogue gives information about courses, expenses, and other details of interest to prospective students. Write to D. Nyvall, president, 3225 Foster Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
