<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-01-10">Jan. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedenborg Bust</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, photograph of the bust of Emanuel Swedenborg]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1015</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1015.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1923-01-10">Jan. 10, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDENBORG BUST</title>
[Half-tone, one column-sixth of a page, photograph of the bust of Emanuel Swedenborg]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time last summer it was reported that Mrs. L. Brackett Bishop, 4339 Drezel Boulevard, had in her possession a bust of the famous Swedish scientist, Emanuel Swedenborg, and that she wanted it to become the property of the Swedes of Chicago, to be placed in some club or, possibly, in a park. For a while, nothing more was heard of it; but last week it began to look as if Mrs. Biship's plan might become a reality. Preparations are under way to place the bust in Lincoln Park, where a statue of another world-renowned Swedish scientist, Carl Von Linne, has been standing for more than twenty-five years.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Bishop paid one thousand dollars for the bust, which was modeled by the well-known Swedish sculptor, Adolf Jonsson. It is thus an authentic work <pb facs="5423404_3_1016.jpg" n="2"/>of art.</p>
   <p>If present plans work out, and the bust finds a permanent place in Lincoln Park, the credit should go to our countryman, C. S. Peterson. He undertook the task of getting the Lincoln Park Board interested in the idea. A member of the Board, Samuel Gessler, has promised his support.</p>
   <p>The estimated cost of the base on which the bust is to rest is one thousand dollars, which sum is to be raised by subscription. It is hoped that the Swedish public of Chicago will be sufficiently interested in the project to contribute this amount.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
