<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-15">Jan. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Society of Journalists</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0575</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0575.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-15">Jan. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH SOCIETY OF JOURNALISTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first annual meeting of the Svenska Journalist Forbundet (Swedish Society of Journalists) was held on January 7, at 68 West Washington Street. All Chicago members with the exception of one, were present, and three new members were accepted. The directorate, which has served since the society was founded, was unanimously re-elected. This directorate is composed of Frithiof Malmquist, chairman; Nils R. Swenson, vice-chairman; S.H.S. Leonard, secretary; and Johan Person, treasurer. Erik G. Westman was re-elected Auditor for a period of three years.</p>
   <p>The treasurer's report announced that the financial status was by no means unsatisfactory. The annual report of the directors for the most part ran as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0576.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"When the Swedish Society of Journalists was organized last fall with the aim of furthering the social and economic interests of its members, by all honorable means, of forming a bond of union among the members, and of speaking for them on all questions regarding commissions, etc., there was no lack of grounds for sceptical views in respect to its future. The same steps had been taken in the past.</p>
   <p>"On various occasions and without exception the attempts to organize the Swedish-American Journalists had been in vain. An undertaking such as the present Swedish Society of Journalists had therefore come to be looked upon more as an impossibility than as a possibility.</p>
   <p>"At its first annual meeting, five months after its founding, the Swedish Society of Journalists can show such progress that it should more than parallel the original expectations. Its membership is greater <pb facs="5423404_3_0577.jpg" n="3"/>than had been expected at its founding. As the Swedish Society of Journalists of America, the official title taken at this meeting, enters a new stage of usefulness, its outlook for the future appears bright; from what has been accomplished, the greatness of the future task of the society may be most clearly seen. In the first place, the undivided attention and co-operation of the members, is the basis upon which the future of the society depends."</p>
   <p>In regard to the publication of a Swedish-American annual for which a proposal was prepared by V. Berger, a New York editor, it was decided among other things that the first issue would appear toward the end of 1920, and that as much as possible, it was to be of purely Swedish-American content, and that as co-workers, Swedish-American writers and authors who are not directly associated with any newspaper and, consequently, <pb facs="5423404_3_0578.jpg" n="4"/>are not members of the society, would be invited. As a committee for the preliminary work in connection with the publication of the book, Frithiof Malmquist, Nils J. Lindskoog, and S. H. S. Leonard were chosen.</p>
   <p>Dr. Jakob Bonggren, who had been invited to lecture at this meeting, had chosen for his subject, "The Skanish School of Literature." The lecture was received with much applause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
