<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1919-02-27">Feb. 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">John Ericsson Memorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1021</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1021.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1919-02-27">Feb. 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN ERICSSON MEMORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The John Ericsson Memorial Committee, at a meeting at the Hotel La Salle decided upon another meeting for the members of the committee in the West. This meeting was a continuation of the one held on February 8, in New York City for the members of the committee East of Chicago, with Mr. John Aspegren as chairman.</p>
   <p>At this meeting in Chicago, Mr. Aspegren was also present, and was elected chairman. Others present were Chas. L. Eckman of Jamestown, New York; Charles Hallberg of Ottumwa, Iowa; bank director Henry S. Henschen, Chicago; city engineer John Ericsson, Chicago; C. S. Peterson, (secretary of the meeting); director T. P. Seeburg of Chicago; Mr. John Lokrantz, who assisted at the New York assembly. At an elegant luncheon, the meeting was opened with a speech of welcome by Mr. Henschen. The chairman of the meeting thereupon unfolded in a rather long, interesting address, the aim of the assembly. He pointed out that a number of places in the capitol city had been offered <pb facs="5423404_3_1022.jpg" n="2"/>for the erection of a worthy memorial to John Ericsson.</p>
   <p>The best site for this purpose is, according to the unanimous view of competent judges, located in Potomac Park, beside the magnificent Lincoln Memorial, which is now being constructed under the supervision of architect Henry M. Bason and the guidance of the noted sculptor, French.</p>
   <p>The John Ericsson monument, however, may not have this location on any other terms than that it be erected in such a manner that it harmonizes with the Lincoln Memorial. The chairman and committee decided that these terms should be met. Thus, John Ericsson would be in the company of the greatest man of his time President Lincoln. Another point in favor of this location is that anyone viewing the Lincoln Memorial could not overlook its companion piece erected in memory of the man of Swedish descent who, during President Lincoln's darkest hours, by his inventive genius, made possible one of the most decisive victories of the loyal North. Mr. Aspegren also pointed out <pb facs="5423404_3_1023.jpg" n="3"/>that the monument to John Ericsson does not necessarily have to be a statue, for, as he said, John Ericsson never won his great renown through his appearance, but through his works. John Ericsson's life and works are to be represented in the memorial. The sculptor, French, has submitted a proposal to the committee for a monument to our countryman.</p>
   <p>The proposed memorial consists of a fountain, sixty feet in diameter and nine feet in height, constituting four different sections, in which would be a portrait of John Ericsson, and allegorical figures from the life of the great man.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
