<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-12-10">Dec. 10, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">An Anniversary</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1068</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1068.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-12-10">Dec. 10, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">AN ANNIVERSARY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Order of Svithiod, the well-known sick benefit and insurance society, is now observing the fiftieth anniversary of its founding. This marks the second important anniversary of this kind in a year. Last June the Viking Order, an organization conducted along similar lines, celebrated its fortieth year of existence with appropriate festivities.</p>
   <p>On such occasions we are reminded of the fact that the large Swedish organizations in this country are no longer to be considered as being in the trial stage, or as temporary affairs that flourish one year, only to be dissolved the next. It is true that most of these organizations have passed through periods strewn with difficulties, when the outlook was so discouraging that less optimistic members were about ready to give up. But as far as the larger groups are concerned, that is past history. Their activities <pb facs="5423404_3_1069.jpg" n="2"/>are expanding steadily even though unemployment and other circumstances may slow them up temporarily.</p>
   <p>We take it for granted that the veterans of the Svithiod Order will be feted on this occasion, and nobody should begrudge them the tribute which is their just due. They laid the foundation and were the builders of the organization, formulating its principles and living up to them during the first difficult years. The experience which they gained has helped them in guiding its later development. If anybody deserves thanks these men certainly do, for their years of faithful work without thought of compensation or other personal gains. Thanks to them, Svithiod is now up in front among Swedish-American societies. However, the Svithiod Order, with its present membership and large financial resources, does not represent the work of a few. It may be true that a few outstanding men have contributed so greatly to its progress that their names will always be associated with it. The fact remains that it is the loyalty of the great majority of members, the rank and file, which has made that progress <pb facs="5423404_3_1070.jpg" n="3"/>possible. And that goes for every Swedish-American organization which from a small beginning has branched out and become national in scope.</p>
   <p>The Order's activities during the past fifty years speak for themselves. Large sums have been paid out in sick benefits life insurance, and donations to worthy causes. During the last few years both the Vasa Order and the Viking Order have opened homes where old members who have no near relatives may spend the evening of their life in peace and tranquility.</p>
   <p>The veterans of Vasa have every reason to be proud of their achievement and we offer them and the entire membership of the Order our most hearty felicitations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
