<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-08">Jan. 8, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Over Here, by G.N. Malm</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0715</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0715.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1920-01-08">Jan. 8, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">OVER HERE, BY G.N. MALM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the review of a newly published Swedish-American novel printed in a Swedish newspaper the other day, we read the following harsh criticism.</p>
   <p>"One need not be any preacher of morals in order to ask oneself in what sort of company have those people in America found themselves who, during the past years, have contributed to the stream of literature with their delineations of Swedish-America. It is self-evident that they are knaves and ne'er-do-wells who have won a little fame, and between the lines one can see how the authors enjoy themselves over their pranks. The honorable, industrious countrymen on the other side of the Atlantic are usually presented as comic figures whose gibberish is supposed to make the reader laugh. They appear to have never been in contact with actual Americans, for they are so superficial, so inconsiderate, so lacking in every ideal interest. This is how they are usually delineated in the Swedish-American novels. These are truly not genuine portrayals."</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0716.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The truth of this judgment we cannot challenge, but we can give an explanation. These American novels are intended for the public in Sweden. Therefore, with the exception of the narrative, they have all faithfully followed in the footsteps of Henning Berger's untruthful delineations of America which were received so well in Sweden, by the public as well as the critics. Among the Swedes in America these Swedish-American depictions have hardly been noticed. Henning Berger has never had a really large public, although some of his characters have been quite amusing, and easily recognizable.</p>
   <p>Perhaps it is not difficult to guess the name of the novel which has lately received such a slashing criticism in Sweden. The reason why we alluded at all to the matter is for the simple reason that at the same time we were reading that critique we received, for our approval, a newly published work on the Swedish-Americans from the Swedish seat of learning at Lindsborg, Kansas. The author, well-known in many fields and not entirely unknown in the field of literature, is G. N. Malm.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0717.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As we have done in the heading of this article, Mr. Malm calls his book Over Here, and says that it is a true representation in four acts of the everyday life of the Swedish-Americans.</p>
   <p>Now we have read the book and can testify that the author has spoken the truth. He has kept his promise to give an accurate reproduction of everyday Swedish-American life. That he has let it take place in four acts is his own affair, and it does not lessen the interest in the reading, it rather does the opposite. When the actors are permitted to speak for themselves and are not merely characterized by the writer, one gets a livelier and more natural impression of the presentation.</p>
   <p>Intrigue is to be found in the book but whether it is sufficiently good to be presented in the theatre, we do not wish to commit ourselves. We hardly think that this was the aim of the author, but that he only followed an old pattern and "painted because he found it pleasant to paint."</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0718.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The critic in the Swedish newspaper, which we cited in the beginning, speaks of the cant which the Swedish-American authors allow some characters to speak so that the public in Sweden may laugh at them. Mr. Malm's Swedish-Americans also indulge in double-dutch. We must acknowledge that it did not exactly jar us, but at the same time it did not evoke any pleasure. We enjoyed the book even though cant was found therein. Perhaps it was necessary to have them speak thus. Since Albert Engstrom in Grisslehamn, allows his characters to speak the high-spirited jabber, why should not Malm in Lindsborg permit his characters to speak the language which they doubtless would have spoken in the same region had they been alive?</p>
   <p>We have refrained from saying anything about the contents of this book. We have zealously left that to the end so that you will read it on our recommendation, and, at the same time, so that it will have all the pleasures of a novelty.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0719.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The book costs one dollar and can be ordered directly from the author, G. N. Malm, whose address, short and sweet, is Lindsborg, Kansas.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
