<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title><date when="1915-01-07">Jan. 7, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">To the Many New Subscribers (Digest Announcing Policies)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0593</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0593.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren (The Swedish Courier Weekly)</title><date when="1915-01-07">Jan. 7, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE MANY NEW SUBSCRIBERS (DIGEST ANNOUNCING POLICIES)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The accession of old and new subscribers has been so great that not only did it meet our expectation but exceeded our hopes. For the sake of the many new subscribers it seems that we ought to give, very briefly, a statement of our policies and attitudes.</p>
   <p>Politically we support party rule in government because it makes possible genuine government by the people, creating the only effective control over those in power at the moment.</p>
   <p>The Republican party has aided greatly in the development of our country and is highly deserving. Undoubtedly it will yet for many years be accorded leadership in politics. It is well, however, that we also have the democratic <pb facs="5423404_3_0594.jpg" n="2"/>party at hand to control republican "bossism," although the role of the democratic party in general may be designated as an example of warning, showing how our country ought not be governed. The parties ought to be allowed to run their own internal affairs without interposition of law.</p>
   <p>Religion we consider the private concern of each individual.</p>
   <p>The temperance question and the question of women's equal rights with men are the two greatest social questions in our country, and on these questions we take a liberal stand. We believe in temperance but not in prohibition because we consider personal liberty as the corner stone in our union. We believe in equal rights for women and men as far as nature permits.</p>
   <p>In regard to the war we are neutral, only desiring that peace may come soon and that the end of militarism may follow speedily.</p>
   <p>Our paper is published exclusively for the Swedes in America, and only to <pb facs="5423404_3_0595.jpg" n="3"/>them are our obligations. The Swedes in Sweden must cease their foolish prattle about the obligation of the Swedish Americans toward Sweden, about the mother country, mother churches, etc. When they do, then may a real condition of brotherly attitude develop between Swedish Americans and Swedes in Sweden to the mutual advantage of both parties.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
