<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-09-04">Sept. 4, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Preparing for the Chicago World's Fair</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0190</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0190.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1929-09-04">Sept. 4, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">PREPARING FOR THE CHICAGO WORLD'S FAIR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The organization which has been formed to promote Scandinavian participation in the coming Chicago World's Fair in 1933, held its regular monthly meeting last week, under the chairmanship of Charles S. Peterson. It was decided by acclamation that a luncheon be given for the world famous Swedish sculptor Carl Milles, upon his arrival in Chicago in the near future. The luncheon may be given in the Tavern Club, and due to the prominence of the guest of honor, who is considered Sweden's greatest sculptor , next to Sergel, it is sure to become an event of great interest to Scandinavians in Chicago. The Danish-American, Ove Vett, is in charge of all arrangements concerning the luncheon.</p>
   <p>Mr. Peterson announced that preliminary work on the exposition site will start within thirty days, and that space for Scandinavian participation, consisting of five acres of land, already has been reserved. He also informed the members that the organization's honorary member, Dr. A. Albert, who is also a trustee of the Fair, is now in Europe, where he is studying the great expositions now being held in Barcelona, Prague, and in Belgium, in order to get new ideas for the Chicago <pb facs="5423404_3_0191.jpg" n="2"/>exposition.</p>
   <p>It was announced also that a Scandinavian art exhibit will be arranged late this coming fall, and all members were urged to help make it a success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
