<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-12-10">Dec. 10, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter's Radio Program</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Anita Arno]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0753</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0753.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-12-10">Dec. 10, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">SVENSKA TRIBUNEN-NYHETER'S RADIO PROGRAM</title>
[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Anita Arno]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the program presented last Sunday night by the Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter over radio station WCFL, the studio orchestra played the "American Sons and Daughters of Sweden's Parade March," composed by Axel Austin, and also a Swedish potpourri arranged by Ole Nielsen. Dr. Julius Lincoln gave an interesting account of his recent visit to Sweden, and the noted baritone singer, Werner Wennerstrand, rendered two solos, "Drivsno" (Drift Snow) and "Sveriye" (Sweden). It is no exaggeration to say that Wennerstrand ranks among the finest Swedish singers in America. His melodious, well-trained voice and his sympathetic personality have made him very popular among his countrymen here. The announcer was Editor Herman Cederblad.</p>
   <p>If we are to judge by the many telephone calls and letters which we have received, <pb facs="5423404_3_0754.jpg" n="2"/>the Swedish radio listeners liked the program. We quote from one letter: "We have just been listening to the Swedish program over WCFL, and wish to express our pleasure and our thanks to your paper. For those of us who left dear, old Sweden not so long ago, it was good to hear Dr. Lincoln's perfect Swedish, the wonderful Swedish music and song and, last but not least the well-known voice of Editor Cederblad."</p>
   <p>Next Sunday's program will be given for the benefit of the Swedish-American Relief Committee, and will include a brief address by Dr. Julius Lincoln and Swedish music by the well-known accordion virtuoso, Ronald Hanell, and by the studio orchestra. As a special attraction we will present the Swedish opera singer, Anita Arno, who has graciously consented to appear. Madame Arno has just completed a concert tour of America, and is now about to return to Sweden. She is a ranking opera singer, and has been acclaimed by American critics.</p>
   <p>Tune in WCFL next Sunday night at eight o'clock.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
