<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-10-25">Oct. 25, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">In Memoriam</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0444</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0444.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-10-25">Oct. 25, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">IN MEMORIAM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The untimely death of Ottilie Liljenkrantz in Chicago at the age of thirty-four is a great loss to American letters," says the Minneapolis Journal; and the American press in general pays tribute to the deceased authoress in similar terms.</p>
   <p>Ottilie Liljenkrantz did not have the genius of a Myra Kelley, but she was a gifted and popular writer, whose departure is deeply regretted by a large and appreciative public. Her best-known books, such as The Thrall of Leif the Lucky and The Ward of King Canute, deal at length with the close relationship which existed between Scandinavia and England and Scandinavia and America in earlier times. She suggests that instead of feeling like strangers in America, the Scandinavians should feel very much at home here, since it is a well-established fact that their forefathers discovered this new continent centuries before <pb facs="5423404_3_0445.jpg" n="2"/>Columbus left Palos and found the American tropics.</p>
   <p>The Scandinavians are closely related to the old American stock being even closer to the Anglo-Saxons than the Germans. King Canute the Great of Denmark was also King of England, and one third of England was named the Danemark; Harold, who fell at Hastings, was of Danish blood on his mother's side. There is hardly a person in England and Scotland who does not have Scandinavian blood in his veins; and as for Ireland, Scandinavians once ruled the central part of the island from Londonderry to Cork.</p>
   <p>Miss Lilijenkrantz revived this old history in her books, and she possessed unusual narrative talent. The romance of the old North fascinated her, and with the exception of Homer's tales, there is hardly anything in ancient history as interesting as the voyages of the Vikings in their remarkably seaworthy open ships from the fiords of the north to the coasts of England and France.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0446.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Miss Liljenkrantz leaves a vacancy in the artistic and literary life of Chicago which will be difficult to fill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
