<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-09-13">Sept. 13, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Nestor of Swedish-American Press Is Dead</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Long Working Day Has Come to an End</title> [Half-tone, two columns-third of a page, full face picture of Johan A. Enander.]

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0601</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0601.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-09-13">Sept. 13, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">NESTOR OF SWEDISH-AMERICAN PRESS IS DEAD</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Long Working Day Has Come to An End</title> [Half-tone, two columns-third of a page, full face picture of Johan A. Enander.]
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The grand old man of the Swedish-American press, J. A. Enander of Chicago, passed away last Friday in his home, 3256 Oak Place, Lake View, after a long illness, at the age of 68.</p>
   <p>Johan Alfred Enander was born May 22, 1842 in Skinmoen, Vastergotland, Sweden. He attended school for sometime, but, being poor, he had to go to work until 1865, at which time he continued his studies. Lack of money forced him to quit school again in 1869, when he took the advice of Pastor Vieselgren in Gothenburg and emigrated to America, hoping to obtain a scholarship at Augustana College, which was at that time located at Paxton, Illinois. He did <pb facs="5423404_3_0602.jpg" n="2"/>attend the college for a few weeks, until in December of 1869 he was offered the editorship of the Swedish-American weekly, Hemlandet, (The Homeland) in Chicago, and this was the beginning of his career as a newspaperman which only ended at his death.</p>
   <p>During the great fire of 1871 Enander lost all he had, and the following year he established, together with G. A. Bohman, the firm Enander &amp; Bohman, and purchased Hemlandet, which during the next few years reached the peak of its circulation and influence.</p>
   <p>With Enander as editor, the firm also published the monthly, Nar Och Fjarran, (From Near and Far), from July, 1874 to March, 1877. It was a fine illustrated publication, which, however, had to be discontinued for lack of popular support. From 1879 the firm undertook the publishing of Ungdomsvannen, (Friend of Youth), which went into other hands two years later.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0603.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In 1890 Enander sold his interest in Hemlandet, and accepted the chair of Swedish language and literature at Augustana College, which by that time had moved to Rockford, Illinois. He held this position until 1893, when he became chief editor of Svenska Journalen (The Swedish Journal) of Omaha, Nebraska. In 1896 he returned to Chicago, and again became editor of Hemlandet.</p>
   <p>No other Swedish-American newspaperman has had such influence among his countrymen in America as had Enander. Among the reasons for this were his excellence as a lecturer and political speaker and also his popularity as a writer. He was very active during the political campaigns of 1888, 1892 and 1896. In recognition of his services to the Republican party, President Harrison appointed him United States Minister to Denmark in 1888, but due to poor health, Enander could not accept.</p>
   <p>As an author he was particularly noted for his historical works, the most <pb facs="5423404_3_0604.jpg" n="4"/>important of which was his Forenta Staternas Historia, (History of The United States), which was translated into Danish, and parts of it also into English. Among his other historical works was his Nordmannen I Amerika Eller Amerikas Upptackt (The Norsemen in America, or The Discovery of America), which was published in 1892 in Rock Island. Many fine poems also came from his pen.</p>
   <p>Enander was an honorary member of several societies, such as the Swedish Historical Society of Chicago and the Polish Alliance. Augustana College conferred upon him the degree of Doctor of Law, and King Oscar of Sweden honored him with a medal for "meritorious contributions to literature and art".</p>
   <p>He is survived by three children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
