<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1918-11-21">Nov. 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Historical Society in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0476</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0476.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1918-11-21">Nov. 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH HISTORICAL SOCIETY IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The officers of the Swedish Historical Society convened in the Swedish Club last Tuesday, November 12. This gathering might be called the "annual meeting," as the regular annual meeting was deferred on account of the War, and the members had been requested to vote by mail in the election of new officers to replace the five retiring officers.</p>
   <p>An interesting report was read by the corresponding secretary, William F. Carlson, which showed that the interest in the work was increasing, and that in spite of the War crisis, more members had remitted their annual dues than ever before in the history of the society. Among the new members was Dr. H. G. Leach, who was accepted as a life member, for which the fee of $50 was paid, also Grosvenor Library, Buffalo, N. Y., and New York State Library in Albany, became members. The treasurer's <pb facs="5423404_3_0477.jpg" n="2"/>report showed receipts to be $461.56 and disbursements were $436.99, leaving a small amount of cash on hand.</p>
   <p>The nominating committee reported that the following persons were unanimously elected as members of the executive committee: Hans Lagerloff, N.Y.; Marcus Skarstedt, Evanston, Ill; Alfred Norton, Andrew Toft, and Pastor G. S. Oslund, Chicago. As officers, the following were elected: Edward C. Westman, president; H. A. Nelson, vice president; William F. Carlson, recording secretary; E. E. Freeman, treasurer.</p>
   <p>Several questions were discussed, the most important of which was the library question, which finally has been solved, even though not entirely satisfactorily. On account of the society's great collection of nearly six thousand volumes, many of which can not be replaced, should they be destroyed, it was absolutely necessary to secure a fireproof storage vault for these collections. An agreement has been reached with Augustana College, <pb facs="5423404_3_0478.jpg" n="3"/>Rock Island, Ill., for safe storage of these valuable collections in Swedish Historical Society's own name in the new Denkmann Library there. The book collections, which were moved there in October, will be classified, indexed, and stored away for the time being. The collection will always remain the property of the Swedish Historical Society, and will be released whenever so demanded, and particularly when the society, has obtained its own library. This thought is still alive with the society, although building plans necessarily have been deferred due to various well-known reasons.</p>
   <p>At present, the collections are well taken care of at Denkmann Library, Rock Island, and can be viewed during the hours the library is open to the public.</p>
   <p>It is possible later on that a person will be appointed to assist the librarian in handling these collections. This question, however, was not settled when the meeting adjourned at 10 P.M.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
