<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-04-23">Apr. 23, 1930</date><title level="a">Preserve the Language of Our Fathers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0425</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0425.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-04-23">Apr. 23, 1930</date><title level="a">PRESERVE THE LANGUAGE OF OUR FATHERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An organization named the Swedish Literary Society has just been formed in Moline, Illinois, on the initiative of engineer Charles A. Carlson. According to its statutes, its purpose is to promote love and respect for the language of our fathers, and to keep alive the interest in Swedish literature, song, and music. The educational phase of its activities is emphasized, and members are urged never to forget the debt that they owe to Sweden and their ancestral culture.</p>
   <p>There are not many such organizations among Swedish-Americans, and one newspaper described the situation well when it stated that it was formed by "a group of Swedish enthusiasts". As a rule, anybody who tries to form a Swedish organization of a cultural nature is not received with much enthusiasm, and unless the leaders of such ventures possess more than ordinary ability and energy their aspirations are not likely to be attained.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0426.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At Swedish-American educational institutions there are Swedish literary societies, which hold regular meetings and at intervals arrange social gatherings; and they undoubtedly aid in maintaining the specific Swedish character of these schools. The North Park College, of this city, which is conducted by the Swedish Mission League of America is particularly fortunate in this respect. For it has at its disposal a fund, which was established on the initiative of our countryman, Axel W. Anderson, for the purpose of maintaining a department of Swedish language and literature, and it is thus assured that these subjects will be taught in the school for a long time to come. Under such circumstances, a literary society of students and friends of the school is likely to flourish.</p>
   <p>As to independent societies of this kind the situation is different and vastly more difficult, and experience has shown that it requires exceptionally intelligent and energetic leadership to keep them alive. The majority expire within a shorter or longer time for lack of support.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0427.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We believe that much would be gained if such cultural organizations in different localities would keep in touch with each other and co-operate. One society might learn much from another one in regard to organization and working methods, and arrangements might be made for the exchange of speakers and literature, joint meetings, etc.</p>
   <p>Intensive co-operation is needed if Swedish cultural activities in this country are to be maintained and preserved, and we think that to bring about such a co-operation is a task which is made to order for the Swedish Cultural League of America. [Translator's note: This appears to be another name for the Society for the Preservation of Swedish Culture in America, whose mother organization is the Society for the Preservation of Swedish Culture in Foreign Countries with headquarters in Sweden]. If, for some reason or other, the League cannot undertake this task the literary societies must take the situation into their own hands. They need each other, and in unity there is strength.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
