<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-01-11">Jan. 11, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Sports and Education</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0996</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0996.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1910-01-11">Jan. 11, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">SPORTS AND EDUCATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Educators all over the country are now beginning to consider sports from the proper point of view, namely, as an important factor in any educational system and as part of the training to which every child and older student is entitled.</p>
   <p>During the last few years, sports, particularly as practiced within our institutions of higher learning, have developed in the wrong direction, and have become, so to speak, a marketable commodity which is being sold to the highest bidder. Some big schools put such emphasis on sports that they are in danger of neglecting the welfare of their general student body for the benefit of a select few, and in smaller institutions physical training has almost been abandoned.</p>
   <p>To have an opportunity to play is part of any child's birthright, and the child <pb facs="5423404_3_0997.jpg" n="2"/>should be given a chance to participate in such games which tend to promote fine manhood and womanhood and to develop a capacity for leadership. If this is not done the race will gradually degenerate.</p>
   <p>The popular conception of sports places the emphasis on the spectacular, and the match between Jeffries and the Negro, Johnson, which is to take place next July 4, provides a fine opportunity to observe this attitude. Judging by the excitement caused by this proposed fight one might think the future welfare of both races depended on the outcome of this struggle. This kind of sentiment means money to those clever men who make a good living by exploiting it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
