<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-04-10">Apr. 10,1901</date>.
<title level="a">The Orphei Singers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0063</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0063.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen</title>,
<date when="1901-04-10">Apr. 10,1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE ORPHEI SINGERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.11... The Orphei Singers, the boys out there at 1428 School St., who are recognized and praised both in Northern Chicago, and to a lesser extent in the South,realized that Easter Day ought to be celebrated in an oriental fashion.</p>
   <p>To this end a large amount of eggs, and herring-salad were secured. Brass and string music furnished accompaniments to the festival. Singers, too, were engaged for the occasion. The event was characterized further by a mixture of ox-steak, and "Declaimers"; punch and potatoes; speakers and cherry wine. However, harmony reigned throughout the whole affair.</p>
   <p>Happy boys and pretty girls danced to their hearts content to the music of the I.O.V. orchestra. The musicians seemed untiring; although each of its members danced occasionally too.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0064.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The singers sang at least a dozen songs. Their crisp tones had "summer warmth" of depth as their music rolled forth toward the egg devouring crowd. Enraptured by their beautiful tones, friend Hessel got his drink appetizer in his wind-pipe and Lindman sat enthralled and gaped, with a fish-bone in his throat. There was unforgettable expression in their eyes, too when Frithioff Malmquist read "Dobeln vid Jutas", a Swedish-Finnish poem by Runeberg. In fact, the entire crowd was strangely and deeply moved.</p>
   <p>The charming feminine listeners were quiet a long time.. They really said nothing until Henrik Anderson sang SOLDATGOSSEN (The Soldier Boy) by Runeberg.</p>
   <p>The program changed to other activities which were enjoyed far into the night and in the lesser holiday, the day after Easter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
