<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-07-02">July 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Swedenborg Bust Unveiled</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_1010</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1010.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1924-07-02">July 2, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE SWEDENBORG BUST UNVEILED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The bust of Emanuel Swedenborg, one of Sweden's greatest sons, was unveiled last Saturday. The memorial is located on a small island in the Lincoln Park lagoon, which is connected with the mainland by a bridge, and it is a worthy tribute to the memory of this world-famous Swedish scientist and philosopher.</p>
   <p>The unveiling ceremony was attended by a large number of people, among them most of the leading Swedes in Chicago and high city officials.</p>
   <p>The chairman of the monument committee, C. S. Peterson, introduced Dr. Wallenius, who outlined Swedenborg's life and work. Other speakers were Congressman Carl R. Chindblom, who conveyed a personal greeting from <pb facs="5423404_3_1011.jpg" n="2"/>President Coolidge and read a letter written for the occasion by the Chief Executive; and the Swedish Minister to Washington, Axel Wallenberg, who came here from the capitol to attend the ceremony. Mayor Dever was represented by Corporation Counsel Hornstein, who paid tribute to Chicago's Swedes in flattering terms.</p>
   <p>Minister Wallenberg presented the bust to the Chicago Park Board, which was represented by former mayor William Hale Thompson. The memorial was covered by an American and a Swedish flag, and the actual unveiling was done by Lola De Dardel, the little daughter of the Swedish consul in Chicago. Mr. Thompson accepted the bust on behalf of the Park Board with a brief speech, in which he stressed the constructive qualities of the Swedish people in the field of ideas as well as in erecting structures of steel and concrete. [Translator's note: The reference is to the prominence of Swedes in Chicago's building industry.] The ceremony ended when everyone joined in the singing of "America".</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_1012.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Our readers may remember that it was Mrs. L. Brackett Bishop, of Chicago, who originated the idea of placing this memorial in some public square or park in Chicago. She owned the bust, and donated it to Chicago's Swedes, who then gave it to the city. Mr. and Mrs. Brackett Bishop were also present at the ceremony.</p>
   <p>An especially festive touch was provided by the presence of hundreds of Swedish-American singers, who were holding their great convention here in Chicago last week.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
