<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-12-03">Dec. 3, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Swedish Radio Program</title><title level="a" type="sub">Tune in Wcfl Next Sunday and Listen to Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter's Program</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0755</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0755.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter</title>,
<date when="1930-12-03">Dec. 3, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">SWEDISH RADIO PROGRAM</title><title level="a" type="sub">Tune in WCFL Next Sunday and Listen to Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter's Program</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Half-tone, one column-fifth of a page, picture of Franklin C. E. Lundquist]</p>
   <p>It has been suggested from many quarters that there should be a regular Swedish radio program in Chicago. The Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter agrees, and has, after consultation with Franklin C. E. Lundquist, director of the Federation of Labor's station, WCFL, decided to present a series of such programs from that station.</p>
   <p>The first program will be heard next Sunday, December 7, from 8 to 8:30 P.M. It will consist of Swedish music played by the studio orchestra, songs by the noted baritone singer, Werner Wennerstrand, and a brief address by Dr. Julius Lincoln. Editor Herman Cederblad will be the announcer.</p>
   <p>It is really Mr. Franklin C. E. Lundquist who, by his friendly co-operation, <pb facs="5423404_3_0756.jpg" n="2"/>has made this program possible. Even though he was born in this country, Lundquist is more Swedish than many a "home-grown" countryman. He is proud of his Swedish ancestry and training and he speaks Swedish fluently. He is a noted musician and received his first musical instruction from his father who, as a young man in Sweden, belonged to the Kalmar Regiment band, and who, after his arrival in America, organized the band of the Order of Svithiod and directed it for many years.</p>
   <p>Franklin Lundquist has been very active in Swedish-American societies, and was at one time Grand Master of the Order of Svithiod. At the present time he is holding the job his father once had as director of the Order's orchestra. It is also interesting to note that he has been a director of the musicians' union.</p>
   <p>It was Lundquist who actually took the initiative for the presentation of this program, which will now be sponsored by the Svenska Tribunen-Nyheter. Don't forget to tune in on WCFL next Sunday night at 8 o'clock!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
