<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1927-07-21">July 21, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">From the Swedish Old People's Home Great Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423404_3_0205</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-swedish #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-28">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0205.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>SWEDISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svenska Kuriren</title>,
<date when="1927-07-21">July 21, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE SWEDISH OLD PEOPLE'S HOME GREAT DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1....The festivals of the Swedish Old People's Home in Evanson last Sunday were a great success. It was commonly estimated that the visitors numbered more than 30,000, with the weather all that could be wished for. Under such conditions it is only to be expected that the pecuniary result will be fully as good as last year. Franklin C.E.Lundquist was Master of Cermonies. The Swedish Singers' League of Chicago, under the direction of William F. Nordlin, rendered a dozen songs, which were all greeted with thunderous applause.</p>
   <p>The welcoming speech was made by Oscar W. Johnson, the president of United Swedish Societies, Old People's Home Society, whereupon the Maypr of Evanston, Hon. Chas. H. Bartlett, in behalf of the city, extended his best wishes for continued progress and prosperity to the Home, and all those, who through their work and liberal gifts, helped this grant institution.</p>
   <pb facs="5423404_3_0206.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A fine speech was made by Dr. Hoffsten, who, in a very entertaining manner told about Sweden and what was due this highly educated and progressive nation. The redest roses fell perhaps at the feet of "Smalanningarne," which can be explained by the fact that Dr. Hoffsten himself, comes under this category.</p>
   <p>Consul Carl O. de Dardell is always to be found in the first ranks, when Sweden's interests are concerned, and his speech went home; he also urged all Swedes to work in unison for the Good of the Home.</p>
   <p>The late Senator from Minnesota, Hon. Magnus Johnson, was invited, as the chief speaker of the day. It can be truthfully said, that his speech was received with attention and lively applause. The political part of the speech was neither long nor comprehensive, but he urged the Swedish-Americans to work for clean politics. The speaker thought, President Coolidge would be re-nominated, if he desired, but he feared the President would decline the honor, in which case a so-called dark horse would take his place. Mr. Johnson, with deep respect paid a high tribute to the land where his cradle stood, but he <pb facs="5423404_3_0207.jpg" n="3"/>was of the opinion that we Swedes had come to America for the main reason that we did not like the King, the Czar, the Kaiser, etc., but had a high regard for the free institutions of America. The fact, that the great masses of our emigrants came here without having given our free institutions, any serious thought, but largely to secure himself a richer sustenance, than the old land offered; this senator failed to mention. His speech was flavored with many amusing episodes from the old,as well as the newer days. The senator was loudly applauded both during the speech and after.</p>
   <p>All the songs and speeches were heard very distinctly, due to a loudspeaker installed on the speaker's rostum by Hilmer Erickson Elec. Co.</p>
   <p>An entertaining radio program was also heard over station WCFL, owned and operated by Chicago Federation of Labor.</p>
   <p>O. Sandine, 2113 Windsor Ave.; the lucky person, who, after the conclusion of the festivities rode home in the large Buick automobile; the Chevrolet automobile was taken home by Mrs. Nels Shoan, 426 Clinton Place; the <pb facs="5423404_3_0208.jpg" n="4"/>secretary,donated by Petersen Furniture Co., was won by R. Christopherson, 4205 No. Albany Ave.; the costume donated by Benson and Rixon, to C. B. Hedstrom, 3223 No. Clark St.; the coxwell chair, donated by Anderson Bros. Furniture Co.,to Max R. Selman, 602 Davis St., Evanston; $25.00 cash, donated by Lake View State Bank,to Doris Nelson, 3438 Foster Ave.; the Salon clock, donated by A.W.Johnson &amp; Co.,to Dr. C.W.Anderson, 1051 Irving Park Blvd.; clothing, donated by Hedstrom's Stores,to A. Magnuson, 1667 Edgewater Ave.; $25.00 Savings Account, donated by Builders &amp; Merchants State Bank, to Elmer Johnson, 916 Maple Ave.; and $20.00 in gold, donated by John P. Friedlund and Oscar W. Johnson, to Edwin Linder, 5627 Glenwood Ave.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt but that the festival was a grand success in every respect; what the cash proceeds will be, we cannot say until all receipts and disbursements have been tabulated.</p>
   <p>Anyway the encouraging fact remains, that our future welfare seems to be a concern close to all hearts of the Swedes in Chicago, and true to previous years traditions, gave a good lift to this important charitable institution.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
