<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-30">Jan. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[Chicago Rabbis Receive Inadequate Wages]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0666</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0666.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-30">Jan. 30, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[CHICAGO RABBIS RECEIVE INADEQUATE WAGES]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Vienna, Austria is not the only city that pays starvation wages to its rabbis. Many rabbis in Chicago are receiving starvation wages and have to seek an outside income. Five out of every thirty rabbis in Chicago receive inadequate salaries. The late Rabbi [Simon Harry] Album (may his memory be blessed) suffered all of his life. There are today in Chicago many rabbis, honest Jews and scholars, who have to provide for a family of six or eight persons on a weekly salary of from ten to twenty dollars.</p>
   <p>I never understood, and I do not understand even now, why the Chicago Jews treat a rabbi worse than they treat a plain working man. When a Chicago businessman employs a worker, he pays him enough wages to enable him to make a living. Why should a rabbi be treated worse than a worker? If a synagogue says to a man: "Give us all of your time, all of your energy and all of your <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0667.jpg" n="2"/>knowledge for the benefit of our synagogue," it ought, at least, to pay him a fair salary so that he can make a living.</p>
   <p>A rabbi is entitled to make as fine a living as a physician or an attorney because he, too, studied for many years before he became a rabbi. No synagogue should pay a rabbi less than sixty or seventy dollars a week, but there are in Chicago many synagogues that pay their rabbis six or seven dollars a week, and yet wonder why the rabbis, in search of an outside income, accept work that is unbecoming to a rabbi.</p>
   <p>If you really want to raise the standing of the rabbinate and the prestige of the rabbis, then the first thing that you should do is to pay the rabbi decent wages, so that he will be able to make a fair living; then he will be able to devote all of his time to the congregation and will not look for an outside income.</p>
   <p>I move and second that....but you understand, don't you?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
