<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-06-12">June 12, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Charities.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-06-12">June 12, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH CHARITIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 3 - The National Conference of Jewish Charities opened its session at the Sinai Temple yesterday.</p>
   <p>These important questions will be discussed during the conference: The cooperation of all charitiable societies, in the establishment of hospitals and colonies in Colorado, Texas and California, for the benefit of sufferers from tuberculosis; advisability of inducing poor families to move to smaller cities and farm districts, where opportunities for employment are much more frequent. And finally, the question ofdiscontinuance of the established custom, of providing applicants with free transportation, thus adding to the burden of the community.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0299.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Emil Hirsch, welcomed the delegates. Mr. Max Senior, the president, read the annual report, especially emphasizing the necessity for the erection of hospitals for tubercular patients. Mr. Senior denounced the custom, of providing poor families with free transportation to other cities. He declared that this was not done in the spirit of charity, but in an effort to shift responsibility. Mr. Max Hersberg, spokesman for the committee for transportation suggested that poor Jewish families should be given every possible chance and inducement to exchange city life for a life in rural districts. A lecture on "Confederacy versus Consolidation of Jewish Charitable Societies" was given by Morris Loeb of New York, during this afternoon's session. He sharply criticized the custom of giving entertainments for charitable purposes. A reception was held at the Lakeside Club in the evening, in honor of the delegates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
