<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-06-05">June 5, 1918</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1712</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1712.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1918-06-05">June 5, 1918</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The firmer the Zionists and Poale Zionists become in their convictions, the more strained become the relations between these two parties. The following sharp conflicts between the two party organs. Dr. S. M. Melamed, the editor of the official Zionist organ, attacked the Poale Zion as though they were Bolsheviks.</p>
   <p>The official organ of the Poale Zion crowned Mr. S. M. Melamed with titles such as, squealer, and so forth. But the unofficial representatives of Zionism also are not satisfied with the aims of the Poale Zion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1713.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The opinion of these Zionists, was most clearly expressed by the Zionist author, M. F. Zeidman, who is the director of the Nationalistic-Zionist press agency, the Jewish Telegraphic Agency. Mr. Zeidman claims that the Poale Zion has entered a false path. If they are sincere to their Palestine ideal, they should devote all their energy, and do all in their power to establish legions of labor pioneers and organize them for the work in Palestine. Instead of that, says Ziedman, the Poale Zion waste their time and strength to create a sympathetic lay body for Zionism. In answer to this claim, B. Zukermann, the well known leader of the Poale Zion, stated that a congress of sympathizers for Zionism will, through its resolutions, have a great influence at the coming peace congress.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1714.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There is no reason why the Poale Zion cannot be in the same position to work both in the American Socialist Party and to fulfill their duty to the labor movement in Palestine.</p>
   <p>According to present indications, they will get the assistance of all the Socialist and trade unions; even those who are convince that Zionism darkens the class struggle, will always be ready to help morally and materially in the organization of the workers to organize a Socialist Party in Palestine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
