<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>, 
        <date when="1918-04-29">April 29, 1918</date>.<title level="a">The Labor Conference for a Jewish Home in Palestine</title>
    
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1715</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G (Zionism)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>, 
        <date when="1918-04-29">April 29, 1918</date>.<title level="a">The Labor Conference for a Jewish Home in Palestine</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
  <p>Approximately four hundred delegates assembled yesterday in the West Side Auditorium to deal with the question of Jewish workers having a Congress with the object of supporting a home for the Jews in Palestine.</p>
  <p>M. Schuchter, Federative Committee of the Chicago Poale Zion, opened the conference by declaring that this conference was not a Poale Zion one, and not a partial one, but one entirely in the hands of the labor organizations that have sent delegates to the conference. They must determine the objectives of this movement.</p>
  <p>He opened the nominations for chairman and Mr. Tabbac of Local #144, Amalgamated, was unanimously elected. A. Herman, delegate of the United Hebrew Trades, was made vice-chairman.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1715.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The delegates Schuchter, Shaffer, Kominsky, Berenstat, and Feinblatt were appointed on the Credentials Committee. Delegates Botkin, Katz and Kysnis were appointed as secretaries.</p>
   <p>The chairman then introduced Friend Nathanson who addressed the conference. Friend Nathanson pointed out the importance of adopting the true revolutionary character in progressive nationalism.</p>
   <p>He showed the reactionary character of the conservative element of Zionism and he strongly emphasized the necessity of remembering, that the conference is a labor conference and must stand on revolutionary grounds, that it must demand national cultural rule, wherever Jews are located, and the right to a territory for Jews. Only Palestine is the place where the Jews should have their Jewish state.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1716.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Then the Credentials Committee reported that a number of countrymen vereins were represented. Also delegates from the Poale Zion and National Worker's Alliance and a great number of unions.</p>
   <p>The first session closed with the election of a resolutions committee which consisted of these delegates: William Nathanson, H. Dolnik, B. Shapiro, M. Schuchter, J. Herman, Kominsky, Bukenblatt, Yukelson, Shaffer, Pearlstat, and Nadler.</p>
   <p>SECOND SESSION.</p>
   <p>Delegates Sherman of the Poale Zion was elected chairman and Atkin, vice-chairman. William Nathanson read a list of resolutions which were unanimously adopted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
