<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-06-20">June 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Christian Science Advertisement in a Jewish Newspaper</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0874</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0874.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-06-20">June 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CHRISTIAN SCIENCE ADVERTISEMENT IN A JEWISH NEWSPAPER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>First Church of Christ, Scientist, Winnipeg. A free lecture on Christian Science by Clarence W. Chedwik, C.S.B., member of the Board of Lectures of the First Church of Christ, Scientist, in Boston, Mass., Wacker Theater, Sunday 3:15 P.M., June 17. The public is cordially invited. - This is the contents of an advertisement we read this week on the last page of the Winnipeg nationalist newspaper, The Jewish Word.</p>
   <p>That's sufficient. Extraordinary commentaries are unnecessary. The advertisement, which cordially invites the Jewish public of Winnipeg to attend a lecture on Christian Science and, it is understood, to join as members of the Christian Science Church, amply speaks for itself as to the low depth the business management of some of our newspapers, on whose columns the writers preach the rebirth of the <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0875.jpg" n="2"/>Jewish Word and the nation ideal, have sunk. What is this Christian Science? Why was this "science" more privileged to be advertised in a national Jewish newspaper than the ordinary missionary Bible studies?</p>
   <p>First of all, let us explain what sort of "science" this is. The Christian Scientists want that their new doctrine, handed down by Mrs. Mary Baker Eddy, be based upon the Bible, i.e., on the Pentateuch, Prophets, Hagiographa, and on the New Testatment, and that the Bible cannot be understood as it is written because it contains secrets and mysticism which constitute the importance of it. The Christian Scientists believe that the Bible can also be applied as both a health book and as a remedy itself, in order to acquire a practical conception of God, reposing on the words of Jesus of Nazareth: "Cast out the wicked and heal the sick."</p>
   <p>This has recently produced quite a recruit of practitioners. Should anyone have an ulcerated stomach, he is not advised by the Christian <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0876.jpg" n="3"/>Scientists to undergo an operation, but to recite a few Psalms of David, read devoutly the Gospel, and pray to God that He should help him. Should it happen that the ulcer heals by nature, then the Christian Scientists show, as good evidence, that their "science" helped, but if the sick one dies through the sheer negligence of not procuring medical aid, then they claim that he was not an ardent believer and did not pray devoutly, for God knows the degree of conscientiousness existing in man and He cannot be deceived.</p>
   <p>They have recently employed expedients to lure the Jewish masses into their faith, and where the Evangelists and other missionaries fail they succeed, much to our regret. The Christian Scientists are no strict interpreters of the law. They do not ask their followers to observe certain dogmas, or even become baptized. They merely ask you to believe sincerely in the holiness of the Bible, which is universal, and in the law of Jesus of Nazareth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0877.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Christian Science appeals to the obscure masses, not because of its spiritual interpretation of the Bible, or the saving of the soul, but because of its promises of healing the human body. And just here is where the great danger lies. It is very pitiful that so much ignorance and superstition still exist today; that there are people who believe in demons and evil spirits. However, the belief in demons or witchcraft is not so dangerous to illiterate masses as is the belief in Jesus, because the former is no organized religion, whereas Christianity is.</p>
   <p>That Christianity, in the new form and in the disguise of Christian Science has invaded and gained influence among the ignorant English-speaking Jewish masses, is to be observed from our English-Jewish Reformed newspapers, which are full of articles on this doctrine, pro and con. These controversies, appearing in our Jewish "Church Newspapers," are no more than the expression of the members who apparently have no other interest in life but the knowledge of "Christian Science."</p>
   <pb n="5"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0878.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Naturally, the editors of that newspaper cannot be held responsible for this advertisement, but the management is. This would be of no concern to us, were it not that it bears upon the entire Jewry.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
