<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1881-04-08">April 8, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Report of the Executive Board of the Chicago Sinai Congregation.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1118</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1118.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Jewish Advance</title>,
<date when="1881-04-08">April 8, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL REPORT OF THE EXECUTIVE BOARD OF THE CHICAGO SINAI CONGREGATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the date of our last annual meeting we were without a leader, and even without any definite plan to guide us in the effort of finding a man, in whose hands it might be safe to trust the management of a pulpit, which seems destined to unite the indifferent sons and daughters of Israel, and lead them onward to renewed zeal and earnestness in carrying out the inherited mission of our name.</p>
   <p>It is indeed a great cause for congratulation that our efforts in this direction have been crowned with an unqualified success. We have placed at the head of our congregation a gentleman, who by his learning and oratorical talent, as well as by his manly and fearless character, commands the esteem and love of all our members, and of every unbiased Israelite. His sermons and lectures, coming as they do from a devoted and enthusiastic source, are awakening a kindred spirit in the hearts of his hearers, and have become the means of attracting a steadily growing attendance on the part of the rising Jewish generation.</p>
   <p>Nor is our Rabbi's sphere of activity limited to the pulpit. Rev. Dr. Hirsch is also a teacher; instructs a class of our pupils personally and superintends <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1119.jpg" n="2"/>our Sabbath School with an energy and zeal worthy of our undivided acknowledgment.</p>
   <p>But also in another respect did the past year bring us a rich blessing, our financial status has been materially advanced. By the sale of our Van Buren street property we have become enabled to pay an encumbrance resting upon the same, and, in part at least, provide for the cancellation of the bonded indebtedness encumbering the temple property, and maturing on the 26th day of July prox.</p>
   <p>One year ago the congregation was burdened with an indebtedness of $47,000. With the means in hand now, all but $17,000 can be paid upon July 26 next, and in order to meet this deficiency we recommend that the Trustees of this congregation be authorized by you to issue scrip covering said amount, in denominations of $100, payable on or before five years after date, at the option of the congregation, with interest at the rate of six per cent, per annum, payable annually, and to secure said scrip by a trust deed on the temple property.</p>
   <p>MEMBERSHIP.</p>
   <p>It would certainly be unjust to attribute the disinclination of our Chicago <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1120.jpg" n="3"/>Israelites to join our rands to a lack of interest on their part, or to a general indifferentism. The very fact that our applications for the rental of pews at our temple have, during the last year doubled, does at once refute such an assumption. The causes are to be found elsewhere, and the truth is, that our constitutional enactment, which requires every member to purchase a pew at a fixed valuation, is chargeable with this lack of good results, and although it may be asserted that all our present members did bring similar sacrifices, we must not forget that they were actuated by the desire of aiding in the erection of our temple, the building of which was regarded as a dire necessity. The temple being built, this want does not exist any longer, and we are of the opinion that it would be in the interest of the congregation to modify our laws in reference to admission of new members, so as to enable applicants to join our ranks without compulsion to purchase a pew.</p>
   <p>The Incoming Year.</p>
   <p>We present an estimate of receipts and disbursements for the incoming year as recommended by the Committee on Finance, for your kind consideration.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1121.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Expenditure.</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Salary of the Minister</cell>
     <cell>$3,600.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Life Insurance Minister</cell>
     <cell>200.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Salary of Sexton</cell>
     <cell>500.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Salary of Reader</cell>
     <cell>700.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Salary of Janitor</cell>
     <cell>300.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Choir and Organist</cell>
     <cell>2,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Taxes</cell>
     <cell>100.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Fuel</cell>
     <cell>250.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Gas</cell>
     <cell>50.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Sunday School Teachers</cell>
     <cell>650.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>United Hebrew Relief Association</cell>
     <cell>100.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Repairs to Temple and Parsonage</cell>
     <cell>1,500.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Insurance</cell>
     <cell>300.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Interest on $17,000 July 1881, to April 1882, 6%</cell>
     <cell>765.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Interest on $3,200 January to July, 1881</cell>
     <cell>1,200.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Incidentals</cell>
     <cell>500.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>$12,715.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1122.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Income</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>Dues from 86 members, at $40.00</cell>
     <cell>$3,440.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Assessment on pews, $59,500 at 8%</cell>
     <cell>4,760.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>From rents of pews</cell>
     <cell>3,000.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Interest on bills receivable</cell>
     <cell>550.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>Surplus at end of fiscal year</cell>
     <cell>900.00</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>$12,650.00</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
