<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-04-23">April 23, 1922</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1665</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1665.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1922-04-23">April 23, 1922</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jews in the History of Chicago. Jacob Siegel.</p>
   <p>Jews settled in Chicago ten years after it became a city. Chicago was incorporated in 1837 as a city. The Jews first settled in the beginning of the 40's of the last century. The first Jewish settler was Abraham Cohen.</p>
   <p>Abraham Cohen laid the corner stone for the reform Jews in Chicago. Exactly when the first Russian, Polish, Rumanian, and Galician Jews settled in Chicago is not known.</p>
   <p>Neither the orthodox, nor the reform Jews introduced new cultural methods or ideas to Chicago. They brought with them the old fashioned Judaism - the synagogue, the cantor, and the rabbi. No more. They did not enter America in search of new Gods or more knowledge. They were contented with the old God and with what they had learned in the old country. They came to seek a livelihood and improve their material and political conditions, mainly their material condition.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1666.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first generation born in Chicago by the immigrant Jews, lacked cultural and educational upbringing. They were neither taught Judaism nor Christianity. The result was horrible. They became foreign to everything in Judaism. They did not understand the Jewish spirit, Jewish poetry, the Jewish traditions and the Jewish literature. If a few adhered to Judaism, it was due to two things: first, anti-Semitism, and secondly, superstition, the fear of God, which brought them to the temples and synagogues.</p>
   <p>The first great migration period, after the pogroms of 1905, brought new life into the Jewish quarters. They imported the Jewish desire for knowledge and education, the Jewish turbulence, and began creating cultural work. True, the result can not be seen so soon, although they planted the seeds from which the sprouts can be seen every where.</p>
   <p>An open sign is found in Chicago, concerning the life of the Jews. It is a tablet placed on the corner of the Post-Office Building, Clark and Monroe.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1667.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It was located at Wood and Blutcher. It was later reconstructed in a modern building in the Douglas Park District. The third institution that the orthodox Jews built, and derived very little pleasure from, was the Kosher Hospital (Hospital observing dietary food laws), which carried the name of Moses Maimonides. On its ground stands the Mt. Sinai Hospital, today, which conducts itself in a different manner.</p>
   <p>With the exception of the three above mentioned institutions, the orthodox Jewry built many more institutions, which are of slight value. Most of them carry a purely religious character, such as Hebrew Schools and Synagogues, and secondly, they are very small and do not play an active part in the local social life. Two orthodox institutions now in existence for a long time, possess a singular character. These institutions are the two Sheltering Homes.</p>
   <p>In 1911 an attempt was made to unite all orthodox charity institutions into one body. The purpose was twofold: to systemize the charity contribution of <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1668.jpg" n="4"/>the reform Jews and to introduce economical and practical management. Prior to that time every institution, small or large, was self sustaining. The money was gathered through collectors. Real anarchy prevailed. In order to cure these nauseating practices, the Federated Orthodox Jewish Charities of Chicago was organized. At the first call to organize all charitable institutions into one federation, the following were undersigned: Benjamin J. Schiff, B. Hurwitz, Samuel Phillipsohn, and Harry Lipskey. Chicago was the first city in America where orthodox Jewry established such a federation of charities. But in this undertaking, the orthodox Jews could not survive without the support of their reform brethren, who continuously covered their deficits.</p>
   <p>The federation contributed a great deal to the art of systemizing and uniting the charity institutions, although it did not unite all institutions under its management. Now much controversy, in combining the Orthodox Charity <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1669.jpg" n="5"/>Federation with the Associated Jewish Charities, is going on. They want to eliminate several institutions. The orthodox element has a Home for the Aged and the reform element has a similar home. They both have orphan asylums. Double institutions, double expenses and double in every respect. This duplicity is a result of the Kashruth (dietary laws) issue. Recently it appeared that the reform Jews granted the authority for Kashruth to the orthodox Jews. The uniting will, at present, be a material and financial one. In this manner, a great sum of money will be saved.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
