<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-07-21">July 21, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Jottings</title><title level="a" type="sub">by H. L.M.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1498</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1498.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-07-21">July 21, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">JOTTINGS</title><title level="a" type="sub">by H. L.M.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recent election in Chicago for delegates to the Zionist Congress showed how poorly the Zionists of Chicago are organized. It also shows how small their membership is. Out of a total vote of 2,080, the Poale Zion received 838 votes. The next in line were the Mizrachi, with 644 votes, while the Zionists, together with Hadassah, received the inspiring and tremendous number of 328 votes!</p>
   <p>Chicago Hadassah leaders showed themselves as poor sports. Instead of taking their medicine like fighters who lost a skirmish and prepare for another fight, they sit down and whine. They have resigned from the Administrative and Executive committees of the Chicago Zionist Organization - good and well. But <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1499.jpg" n="2"/>not content with that, they have drawn up a set of resolutions, which is published in this issue, forwarding a copy to all the members of the Executive Committee, saying that because the President of that organization offended them in some way, he is to be read out of the movement and decapitated at sunrise. Why these Hadassah leaders are so vindictive, no one seems to know. They evidently forgot to take into consideration the action taken by the Zionist Organization of America at its convention held recently in Chicago, that they are to be severed from participating in the councils of the Zionist Organization of America, and that they should continue to do their work independently. As good sports they should swallow whatever indignities may have been heaped upon them in the heat of controversy, and continue their labors in spite of it. By doing that they would win the hearty applause of the Zionists and the satisfaction of their own hearts that they are doing Zionist work not for glory and applause, but for a cause which is dear to them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1500.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Bickering and backbiting and stirring up dissention and turmoil within the organization are not in the true spirit of Hadassah. There is too much work to do, which Hadassah has been doing so nobly in the past, to find time to stoop to such tactics. The sooner they forget about it the better for all concerned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
