<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-06">Oct. 6, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">What Is the United Synagogue?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English) by Rabbi Phillip A. Laugh, Director, Middle West</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0773</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0773.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-06">Oct. 6, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS THE UNITED SYNAGOGUE?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English) by Rabbi Phillip A. Laugh, Director, Middle West</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"What is the United Synagogue?" is a question asked by many people.</p>
   <p>In June, 1913, [at] the first convention of the United Synagogue of America, Professor Solomon Schechter, its founder, said: "I hope to leave the United Synagogue a heritage to American Israel."</p>
   <p>Since that time over two hundred organizations, congregations, and auxiliaries, united on the basis of loyalty to traditional Judaism, have joined the movement.</p>
   <p>The vast scope of its work is indicated by the nature of its extent: From <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0774.jpg" n="2"/>Portland, Maine to Portland, Oregon, it embraces the whole country. "We have a continent for our vision," was the way the late-lamented Professor Friedlander put it. To describe the varied character of its work would be beyond the limited space of this article. We can only trace its outlines here.</p>
   <p>Over 53 communites, small and large, scattered throughout the land, have been benefited by it last year. The number is very much larger this year. Organizing incipient communities, embryo congregations that would otherwise fall easy prey to the prevalent reform; affording speakers, rabbis helping form their Hebrew schools, their Jewish social centers, conducting membership campaigns, these are only some of the many ways of extension work. In Chicago there are several congregations [that have] benefited in this manner. It is acting as a reservoir to retain those elements, Americanized and American, who of essentially Orthodox stock would otherwise fall easy prey to the radical Reform temple. Two such congregations in Chicago, recently formed, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0775.jpg" n="3"/>have been saved for conservation [Editor's note: that is, conservative Judaism] only through the United Synagogue.</p>
   <p>The Jewish student, destined to be prominent in American Jewish life, is looked after through the Jewish student houses, where all Jewish student activities center, Menorah, Zionist, or social affairs, and where kosher meals are served to them. [Of] such student houses there are four, two in New York City, and two in Philadelphia, a fifth one is about to be established by the Boston Branch of the United Synagogue, and the time is not [far] distant that will see one at the University of Chicago.</p>
   <p>It [United Synagogue] is employing a competent staff of educators and rabbis who are preparing textbooks for use in its Hebrew schools. One has already appeared and several are under preparation. It is standardizing its Hebrew schools through the adoption of a uniform curriculum, through joint public <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0776.jpg" n="4"/>graduation of its schools, through the awarding of United Synagogue diplomas to those pupils that fulfill its requirements.</p>
   <p>It is encouraging the establishment of kosher restaurants of high grade in the business sections. Several such in the East have been founded. It has compiled a directory for [the] use of Jewish travelers, containing information of all kosher hotels and restaurants throughout the country.</p>
   <p>It organizes young people's religious and educational activities in the thickly settled Jewish districts, such as Young Israel [groups], in order to help keep the American young man loyal to traditional Judaism.</p>
   <p>But while mention of a great many activities must be here omitted because of space, no account would be complete without some reference to the wonderful <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0777.jpg" n="5"/>work of its Women's League. One cannot [help] but be inspired when coming under the spell of such women as Mrs. Solomon Schechter, Miss Henrietta Szold, Mrs. Charles I. Hoffman, leaders of the National Women's League. They have published small pamphlets of Friday night stories to be told to children by their mothers. They are engaged above all in strengthening the Jewishness of the home, which is their particular sphere. Leaders of the Chicago Branch are Mrs. Benjamin Davis, Mrs. Leon Waldman, and Mrs. Joshua Ginsburg.</p>
   <p>The United Synagogue is establishing a national bond between Jewish communities, that will mold them into a national organization, through which ultimately, the K'lal Israel may express itself.</p>
   <p>Young in years, few yet in accomplishments, the United Synagogue is rich in ideals and in its portents for the future. It is accomplishing a feat that <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0778.jpg" n="6"/>has not been thought possible, namely, the establishment of the American Synagogue, teaching that though partaking of the full intellectual and social life, though permeated with the best of modern thought, it is still possible to remain intensely and thoroughly Jewish, loyal to his traditions and faithful to his ancient heritage.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
