<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-27">July 27, 1913</date><title level="a">Large Memorial Meetings for Dr. Theodore Herzl</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0911</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0911.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-27">July 27, 1913</date><title level="a">LARGE MEMORIAL MEETINGS FOR DR. THEODORE HERZL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The memorial meetings for Dr. Theodore Herzl were over-crowded by the attendance of vast numbers of Chicago Jews of all classes, who paid tribute to the great Jewish leader on his ninth memorial anniversary.</p>
   <p>The radical nationalists held their meetings Thursday and Friday evenings and at each meeting the throng was so vast that the halls were too small to accomodate all. The National Workers' Alliance held its meeting Thursday evening in the Palace Opera House where K. Marmar and Dr. A. Levinson spoke.</p>
   <p>Two meetings were held last evening in the Chicago Hebrew Institute, one was under the auspices of the Poale Zion which was addressed by D. Aberson, K. Marmar, and B. J. Shapiro; the other was under the auspices of the Hatchayoh which was addressed by Judge P. P. Bregstone and H. Steinberg.</p>
   <p>The principle meeting, however, will be held this afternoon at the Ohavah Sholom Congregation, Marks Nathan Congregation, and Tifereth Zion Congregation. These meetings will be addressed by noted leaders of the Chicago Jewry. They will endeavor to raise a fund in the name of the great Zionist leader for the purpose of buying houses for the Jews in Palestine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
