<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-07-19">July 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[The Future of Orthodox Judaism in Chicago]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0655</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0655.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-07-19">July 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[THE FUTURE OF ORTHODOX JUDAISM IN CHICAGO]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Reform Jews do not have to worry about the future because there isn't going to be any future, if one can judge by their work at the present time. The Orthodox Jews of America, however, do have a reason to think occasionally of the future. They would not feel particularly happy if they thought seriously about this question.</p>
   <p>When one attends Jewish meetings in Chicago, one sees the pioneers of Orthodox Jewry in Chicago, who have built up the great Orthodox institutions, who have built up Jewish Chicago. They are all gray-haired now, not because they are old, but because they have become gray-haired doing pioneer work. One always sees them alone, never or only rarely, in the company of their sons. Samuel Phillipson, B. Horwich, B. J. Schiff, M. Salk, and many others who have done pioneer work in Chicago have no children to follow in their footsteps. The sons of those pioneers of Chicago's Orthodox Jewry will not do the work which <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0656.jpg" n="2"/>their fathers have done. This means that the Chicago Orthodoxy, as well as the Orthodoxy of other Jewish cities in America, did not create a tradition. This also means that if America is to remain a great center of Orthodox Judaism, American Orthodoxy will continually have to produce new pioneers. Woe to a movement which depends upon pioneers alone! Such a movement can never have the influence and the position it deserves to have by virtue of vitality and numbers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
