<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-05-23">May 23, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Hias (Jewish Shelter and Immigrant Society) and the American Legion</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1606</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.7"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1606.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II D 7</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-05-23">May 23, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE HIAS (JEWISH SHELTER AND IMMIGRANT SOCIETY) AND THE AMERICAN LEGION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American press say that among organizations to participate in the reactionary conference, called by the American Legion, was our Jewish Hias, and that its representative voted for the reactionary resolutions adopted by the conference, one of which was against the open door policy.</p>
   <p>Every one familiar with the activities of Hias, knowing how energetically this organization has always defended the interests of the Jewish immigrants, can readily see that this is a misstatement, and that Hias, now as ever before, ranks first in the fight against the new immigration cruelties.</p>
   <p>The Forward, therefore, ignored the information entirely, and it looks now as if it did no mistake. Before us lies an official statement from the president of Hias, in which he denies the entire report.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1607.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The truth is that Hias was not represented at this conference and consequently it could not have approved the reactionary resolutions that were adopted there.</p>
   <p>"The Hias representative in Washington sent a protest to the Legion for saying that Hias was represented and also summoned the "Associated Press" to withdraw their false announcement.</p>
   <p>From the Same statement we learn:</p>
   <p>"A short while back Hias received an invitation to participate in a conference on immigration and citizenship, two subjects in which it is interested."</p>
   <p>Hias answered that its representation at the conference would be to protect the interests of the immigrants, but learning later that the purpose of the conference was just the opposite, it did not send a representative, and since then had no connections with them whatsoever.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
