<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-09-07">Sept. 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">It Should Not Have Been This Way</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0633</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0633.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-09-07">Sept. 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">IT SHOULD NOT HAVE BEEN THIS WAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jews are reputed to be wise businessmen but when it comes to community work, they are very impractical. When a Jew wants to put through a business deal, he sits down, works out a plan, analyzes all the details of his plan, and then, after it has been worked out, he takes steps to carry it through. However, he acts differently when it comes to a community matter. At meetings, you often see Jews who want to propose something, but they don't know what nor how. They grope in the darkness. They have no plan and no ideas regarding organization. Everybody at the meeting talks, everyone is excited, but nobody says anything worth while and nobody has anything of positive value to propose.</p>
   <p>This situation was obvious at the last big meeting of rabbis and synagogue presidents of Chicago. The meeting should have carried out some constructive <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0634.jpg" n="2"/>work. It should have accomplished something, but it did not accomplish anything, other than its adoption of a resolution about the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization]. The meeting could have accomplished much more, but it did not have a program of work nor did it have an agenda. The blame for this falls not upon the rabbis but upon the synagogue presidents. The rabbis do not have to be parliamentarians and businessmen--this is not their forte. The synagogue presidents, who are at the head of large congregations and are businessmen, should have known how a meeting like that ought to be conducted, how it ought to have been organized. They did not organize the meeting, nor did they give the meeting a program of work. A great opportunity to do practical work was missed. That should not have happened. It is very much to be regretted that the meeting took such a turn and was so unproductive.</p>
   <p>We cannot, however, change the past. What has been done, has been done. We must think of the present. We must do better and more productive work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0635.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We should not become discouraged over a failure for which--we emphasize it again--the rabbis are not to blame. It would have been much better if a committee of synagogue presidents had first consulted the rabbis and then worked out a program for the meeting. If this has not been done before, it should be done now.</p>
   <p>Many important problems face us, which must be solved: education, charity, judicial council, agents for foreign charities, unification of our forces. Jewish community work in Chicago is badly disorganized [at the present time]. One person does the work of ten, while the ten do nothing. It should not be this way. If the community work was organized and divided into various branches, then everybody would know what he had to do, everybody would do his work punctually, and the individual would not be a victim of the group. Standing committees can be organized, and each committee can be assigned to a certain kind of work. This requires planning and figuring, and occasional meetings are not sufficient.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0636.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We, therefore, believe that the synagogue presidents ought to organize a committee to work out plans for organizing Jewish community work in Chicago. When this committee, which should be made up of prominent citizens and rabbis, has finished its work and is ready to render a report, then a general meeting should be called of synagogue presidents, rabbis, and representatives of institutions and organizations to whom this report should be made. A gathering, similar to the one that just took place, will then have before it a working program and will be able to accomplish something. If such a meeting is not able to put through all the points on the program, it will, at least, work on the most important ones. When the men who attend that meeting see that something concrete is being done, they will be inspired to attend another meeting, and thus the entire program will be realized in the course of time.</p>
   <p>We now have in the city a great rabbinical authority. This religious authority can accomplish a great deal, working in co-operation with the rabbis of the city because respect for an authority has not yet died out <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0637.jpg" n="5"/>among the Jews. The leaders of the city have only to call the attention of the religious authority to what is wrong in the city and to what must be done. Plans can be formulated, after a thorough investigation and consultation, and put before the representatives of the Orthodox community of Chicago.</p>
   <p>We say frankly that we regret the circumstances of the last meeting because a golden opportunity to do great work was missed. We also say that this mistake can be rectified if the leaders of the city will be just as careful with Jewish community affairs as they are with their own private business affairs.</p>
   <p>Begin constructive work now, seriously and enthusiastically, and you will be successful.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
