<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-04-09">Apr. 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">American Rabbis</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0847</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0847.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-04-09">Apr. 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN RABBIS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is not merely a question of the Orthodox rabbis or Reform rabbis, but a question of all rabbis looking forward to American rabbinical prospects of the future. Both groups are confronted with identical problems except that the Reform rabbi needs more academical education and has to have a university degree in order to become a rabbi. The Reform rabbi, in order to be accepted as such, must graduate from a university besides graduating from a theological college.</p>
   <p>Student rabbis receive reductions in tuition fees at any university or college. It would have been otherwise impossible for some to obtain an education. In spite of all these fine privileges granted to rabbis, of very few American boys are attracted by this profession. The majority of Reform rabbis are generally immigrants who already had a wealth of Jewish knowledge when they came to the Land of the Free.</p>
   <p>Very few American-born rabbis possess enough Jewish knowledge to be recognized as real leaders of a community at least in the true sense of the word, as the title of rabbi was understood by the pious Jews in the days of yore.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0848.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Besides conducting the weekly services, the Reform rabbi serves as a sort of business administrator for the community, and as such he is employed by its president and trustees. It is his duty to conduct the services; to be active in community affairs; and to officiate at marriages and funeral processions. In other words, he is a combination of rabbi, cantor, sexton, and lamentator.</p>
   <p>In case some Reform rabbis do work themselves up as influential leaders of such communities, it is not because of their intellectuality, but simply because of the ignorance of such communities, which know very little about religion.</p>
   <p>Such communities give their rabbis the power and authority to rule over both religious and social problems.</p>
   <p>There is very little room in the Reform field of Rabbinism to become broadened or expand spirtually. A Reform rabbi may become a great social worker and be able to accomplish good deeds that are not connected with the profession proper.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0849.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Reform rabbi in America is a finished product: It does not grow any more, nor does it develop any longer. It is static. Some Reform rabbis may show extensive knowledge in research of the Jewish past, yet, this has nothing to do with the future of Jewish problems.</p>
   <p>The young man of unusual abilities will sooner enter a profession where he will be able to create and discover new ideas and things, than to enter the rabbinical field.</p>
   <p>In some ways the Reform rabbi is worse off than the Orthodox rabbi for the following reason: The old-fashioned Orthodox rabbi can create new commentaries and deviations; he can transport himself into the depths of the Talmud and debate on the passages about the dark mysteries of purgatory; or he can imbibe himself in the yet unveiled parts of the heavenly glories, absorbing himself in the Cabala, etc.</p>
   <p>A Reform rabbi, however, cannot permit himself such spiritual pleasures. The average American Reform rabbi becomes so obsorbed in the business of his congregation, that he loses the propects of his office as rabbi of the Jews. He is only a rabbi of his congregation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0850.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>When two rabbis are alike in their viewpoints about Judaism, they have studied in the same Theological Seminary.</p>
   <p>Take, for instance, a rabbi like Dr. Philipson, of Cincinnati. He not only has the audacity to consider himself a rabbi of his own congregation, but of all Israel as well. Rabbi Philipson is not even concerned with his pulpit or the errors he is making in the Hebrew language. This is the natural development of rabbinism in America.</p>
   <p>These Reform rabbis even lack the traditional love for study that the Reform rabbis in Germany had.</p>
   <p>Why Reform Judaism is still having a foothold in America, we do not know. However, we must be grateful to the West European immigrants. Their children are the members of the Reform temples. Twenty per cent of the German immigrants still adhere Judaism and attend weekly services.</p>
   <p>The children of the Russian-Jewish immigrants, who came to the temple, will not remain Reform Jews very long, for the most another generation.</p>
   <pb n="5"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0851.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>a rabbi in America, Reform or Orthodox, will not get the proper recognition as rabbi unless he takes a post-graduate course at the University of Jerusalem, where he will be able to spend a few years in an intensive Jewish atmosphere in order to imbibe the spirit of the Bible and of the Hebrew language, and to receive the proper perspective on Jewish history, life and nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
