<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-05-14">May 14, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Welcoming the New Cardinal</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0429</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0429.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Forward</title>,
<date when="1924-05-14">May 14, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">WELCOMING THE NEW CARDINAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago newspapers have, during the past few days, "plastered" their front pages with news items dealing with the first Chicago Cardinal recently created by the Pope. Whole pages dealt with every move made by the Cardinal; his departure from New York City, his trip to Chicago, the reception tendered to him at the station, and the speech that he delivered. Over one million persons participated in the parade in honor of the Cardinal. The Mayor of Chicago kneeled before him and kissed the sacred signet worn only by cardinals. What a display of the vast power possessed by the Catholic Church in America!</p>
   <p>Such demonstrations have, until recently, been foreign to the soil of America. In European countries, where the church and the state are united, such religious scene are common public sights. Thousands of people participate in them. Here <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0430.jpg" n="2"/>in America, in this free land, however, the reactionary spirit of the Church has not held sway. But in recent years conditions have changed. The war brought in its wake an obscurantism; and, in America, as elsewhere, those reactionary elements who feared the radiance of the brilliant sun have suddenly lifted up their heads, and, jumping on the backs of the illiterate masses, are riding them hard. The influence of these obscurantists is becoming greater and greater. So far has it gone that a mayor of a city of four million inhabitants publicly kneels before a cardinal. There is nothing wrong in the act of kneeling itself: the Mayor is a devout Catholic and considers the action of the Pope as an honor to Chicago Catholics. The truth of the matter is, however, that by kneeling before the Cardinal the Mayor demonstrated his subjection to the will of the Cardinal. A mayor who kneels before a cardinal is subject to his orders. The Cardinal may now become, if he has not already done so, the "boss" of Chicago. For not only did the Mayor kneel but so did County Judge Jarecki, a Polish Catholic, County Clerk Sweitzer, a German Catholic, and many other officials.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0431.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The American reactionaries are served in return very faithfully by the Catholic Church. Non-Catholic capitalists bowed before the new Cardinal as well as Catholic capitalists. The Cardinal serves Capital; and Capital pours its money into the Church to strengthen it and to enable it to enslave the workers and force them to be obedient slaves to the Golden Calf. One hand washes the other.</p>
   <p>In his speech expressing his appreciation of the great honor bestowed upon him Cardinal Mundelein assured the capitalists of his full support. He explained that the Holy Father blessed Chicago and honored the city with a cardinal. He also discussed his duties and told his listeners what his program would be. Here is a part of the program: "And now about our duties. We must keep our country united. We must keep our country clean from foreign influence. We must dispose of those who try to separate us, halt our program, and disturb us in our mission for peace and prosperity."</p>
   <p>The new Cardinal of Chicago uses the same expressions that Judge Gary, all capitalists, and all reactionary officials use. The capitalists and the Church <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0432.jpg" n="4"/>speak one language, serve one God, and oppress and harass one and the same class of people--the working class. But the reign of reaction will not last forever. The reactionary forces are being driven out of Europe; they will not reign long in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
