<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-15">Mar. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Rabbis Organize United Rabbinate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0549</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0549.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-15">Mar. 15, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO RABBIS ORGANIZE UNITED RABBINATE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the Hebrew Theological College yesterday afternoon, the foundation for a United Rabbinate in Chicago was laid. The meeting was called by prominent rabbis of this city and plans were formulated with regard to the activities of this new organization. Rabbi Judah L. Gordon was chairman and Rabbi Eliezar Mishkin was secretary. Various matters of importance concerning the Jewish community were discussed. Questions concerning education, the Sabbath, relief, kashruth, etc., were taken up.</p>
   <p>It was decided to appeal to the president of the Jewish Charities, Mr. Julius Rosenwald, demanding that the office of this Jewish organization, which is in the Administration Building, be closed on Saturday.</p>
   <p>The newly organized United Rabbinate determined to carry on activities for relief work during the week of Passover, particularly on the last day of Passover.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0550.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A committee consisting of Rabbi J. L. Gordon, Rabbi Ephraim Epstein, Rabbi Alshwang, Rabbi Rubenstein, and Rabbi Astrakahn are to meet this evening with the mazoth manufacturers for the purpose of placing relief stamps on each package of mazoth.</p>
   <p>In order to realize the long-planned Kashruth Bill, a committee composed of Rabbis Ephraim Epstein, S. Silber, and Mishkin will meet with Attorney Nathan D. Kaplan in order to draw up the Kashruth Bill.</p>
   <p>A committee of five was appointed by the chairman to elect an executive committee, and this committee will direct the policy of the organization.</p>
   <p>The United Rabbinate will hold its next meeting on Wednesday. The election of officers will take place and the executive committee will be appointed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
