<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-06">May 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Peoples Relief Installs Reforms in its Administration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0154</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0154.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-06">May 6, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">PEOPLES RELIEF INSTALLS REFORMS IN ITS ADMINISTRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The yearly conference of the Peoples Relief which was held yesterday at the West Side Auditorium was characterized by reports of much good work with respect to the installation of reforms in the collection and administration of relief moneys.</p>
   <p>The contributed reports did not please everyone, yet they were approved since it had been previously decided to appoint an accounting committee composed of three members of the Peoples Relief, and three members of the Central with the authority to appoint an expert auditor who shall examine the books for the entire period of the existence of the Joint Relief Committee.</p>
   <p>This was the only question which created stormy debates; all others were dealt with in the usual manner.</p>
   <p>Dr. Hyman Cohn, chairman of the Peoples Relief, opened the conference with <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0155.jpg" n="2"/>an address in which he outlined the aims of the conference. Mr. I. Urey, the financial secretary then presented the report of the $100,000 campaign, pointing out the fact that at the time when the campaign started, an order was issued to instigate workless holidays which prevented many workers from donating a day's pay for relief. However, after hard work and a long campaign, the drive succeeded in collecting $23, 467, and taking into consideration the hard times under which the campaign was conducted, the secretary thinks the achievement a great success. To collect this sum, an expenditure of over twelve hundred dollars was required, besides the customary expenses of the Peoples Relief.</p>
   <p>In the yearly report, Mr. Urey pointed out that the Peoples Relief under the self-taxing system, has organized one hundred and seventy-five blocks where about four hundred volunteers have been collecting relief moneys throughout the year. Through this system, $11, 634 was collected, and together with the incomes from other sources and undertakings, as the bundle day and the picnic, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0156.jpg" n="3"/>the total money collected last year was brought to more than $39,060.</p>
   <p>The conference then began to consider the matter of the Cleveland Convention. A committee of ten was appointed to formulate the instructions to the five delegates whom Chicago will send. The instructions are: that the local branch of the Peoples Relief shall have full autonomy--which means full authority in all local matters, and full power in all its relations with the Central Relief Committee with which the Peoples Relief is combined.</p>
   <p>The elected delegates are: Silvelberg, Gross, Ziskind, Urey and Glickman.</p>
   <p>At the close a new Executive Committee of nineteen was elected. This Executive Committee obtained more authority than its predecessor. It will elect a chairman, a vice-chairman and a secretary who will be responsible to it, unlike the present officials who consider themselves responsible only to the <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0157.jpg" n="4"/>yearly conference which used to elect them. It was also decided to put under bond those officials of the Peoples Relief to whom finances are entrusted.</p>
   <p>The new members of the Executive Committee are: Stern, Dr. Cohn, Dr. Adler, Dr. Golin, Metzger, Agranovsky, Strassman, Ziskel, Shapiro, Wallman, Savitsky, Urey, Leibman, Bruch, Mrs. Ratner, Ziskind, Nisansohn, Silverberg and Glickman.</p>
   <p>About two hundred delegates attended the conference. The first session was under the direction of Attorney Savitsky, and the second, at which only half of the delegates were present, under Dr. Nadler.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
