<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-18">June 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">United Synagogues No Longer a Place for Dr. Adler</title><title level="a" type="sub">Reject His Ultimatum against Zionism and Elect a New President</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0859</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0859.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-18">June 18, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">UNITED SYNAGOGUES NO LONGER A PLACE FOR DR. ADLER</title><title level="a" type="sub">Reject His Ultimatum Against Zionism and Elect a New President</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(Special to the Courier), New York, June 17: The sixth annual convention of the United Synagogues was held yesterday and today in Schechter's Theological Seminary. This organization was founded by the deceased Professor Schechter to strengthen traditional and historic Judaism, and it consists of eighty-six affiliated synagogues, including seven in Chicago, and has a membership of ten thousand people in all parts of the country.</p>
   <p>The convention adopted resolutions to thank England for its statement on Zionism, and to appoint a committee which should handle the problem of the reconstruction of Palestine. Last year the convention expressed itself in favor of Zionism, and because of that, Dr. Cyrus Adler, the successor of Professor Schechter, resigned his office as president. At the present convention, where the enthusiasm <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0860.jpg" n="2"/>for Zionism was even greater than at last year's, Dr. Adler felt entirely out of place. However, he did come to the convention and permitted himself to be nominated for president. But when he gave his ultimatum that he would accept the presidency only on the condition that last year's resolutions on Zionism be withdrawn, he immediately found out that this institution was no place for him. And at today's session he actually did not appear. Naturally his ultimatum was rejected and Rabbi Elias Solomon, a well-known New York Zionist was elected president.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
