<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1884-11-30">Nov. 30, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">[Biography of Hon. Jacob Gross]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1884-11-30">Nov. 30, 1884</date>.
<title level="a">[BIOGRAPHY OF HON. JACOB GROSS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The name of Hon. Jacob Gross stands out. Mr. Gross was born February 11, 1840 in Jarokswiler, Rheinpfalz, Germany. He received a common school education and came to Chicago in 1855, when he joined three of his uncles established in business in that city. For one year after his arrival he was a pupil in the Brown School of Chicago, after which he learned the tinsmith trade with Messrs. Greenebaum and Sons. After serving his apprenticeship he went to Richton, Cook County, where two of his brothers-in-law kept a country store, and clerked for them till the outbreak of our Civil War. He enlisted in Company B, 82nd Illinois Regiment, as Private, August 14, 1862. Among the battles in which he fought were those of Chancellorsville, Va.; Gettysburg, Pa.; Lookout Mountain, Ressaca,, and had his right leg shattered at the battle of Dallas, Ga.; May 25, 1864. This necessitated the amputation of his leg above the knee. He lay in the hospital at Chattanooga and Nashville till November. After convalescing he was transported to the Marine Hospital in Chicago, and in February, 1865, he received his <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1310.jpg" n="2"/>honorable discharge from the army. After his discharge from the army he passed a thorough course in a commercial college in Chicago, and was next appointed deputy clerk in the only police court which Chicago could then boast of. Thrice he was elected collector of the West Town of Chicago, and in 1872 he was chosen by popular suffrage for the responsible position of Circuit Court Clerk, the term being four years. Twice he was reelected. At the fall election of 1880 he received a larger vote in Cook County than the late lamented President Garfield.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
