<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-04">Apr. 4, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Tasks of the United Rabbinate</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0524</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0524.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-04">Apr. 4, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE TASKS OF THE UNITED RABBINATE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recently organized United Rabbinate of Chicago faces many difficult tasks, and the success of the United Rabbinate depends upon its approach to the solution of the difficult problems confronting it. The United Rabbinate can maintain peace in its own camp, if it takes its tasks for granted, i. e., if it remains a paper organization only; but it will face a severe struggle, if it really sets out to establish order in the city.</p>
   <p>The United Rabbinate must control the kashruth in the city, and this control must be absolute--without any compromise. The United Rabbinate must control the whole religious life of the city, and this control must be absolute--without any compromise. In this city there is a United Rabbinate--the highest rabbinical authority--and no individual must do anything to weaken or undermine <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0525.jpg" n="2"/>this authority. Otherwise, the United Rabbinate will be in no position to do anything, and will, therefore, have to remain a paper organization.</p>
   <p>Only when the rabbis who belong to the United Rabbinate decide, once and for all, that they must subordinate their personal interests to the interests of the United Rabbinate, will the newly organizaed rabbinical organization in Chicago be able to accomplish anything.</p>
   <p>If there is an individual or group of individuals within the United Rabbinate itself, that does not want to subordinate its personal interests to the interests of the United Rabbinate, then it is the duty of the United Rabbinate to come out publicly and declare: "This individual or this group is disrupting the work". We are convinced that in such a case, the Jewish public in Chicago will know what to do and will do whatever is right and proper.</p>
   <p>The pretext that the United Rabbinate should deal, for the most part, with <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0526.jpg" n="3"/>religious questions and Din Torahs [lawsuits decided informally through voluntary arbitration according to the Jewish or common law], is a very poor one. Every rabbi can render a decision of a Din Torah and answer religious questions; but not every rabbi is able to control the entire religious life of the city, and the administration of Jewish life in the city. A United Rabbinate should see to it that these things do not happen: no rabbi should unite a man in holy matrimony who has not divorced his wife according to the law of Moses; no rabbi should grant a divorce for five dollars, or label something Kosher which is not kosher, etc. A United Rabbinate can and will control these things properly, if the rabbis are willing to subordinate their personal interests, or if the majority of the rabbis of the United Rabbinate has the courage to come out openly and point out the one who disrupts their peace and harmony. We are convinced that the public will support the United Rabbinate morally and materially, and will respect its decisions.</p>
   <p>The rabbis need only have a feeling of responsibility and the courage of their <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0527.jpg" n="4"/>convictions. They must not be misled by false motives or by personal considerations. The task of the United Rabbinate is a tremendous one, and it requires courage, and more courage, to fulfill it. By debating behind closed doors and remaining silent, nothing can be accomplished. As long as there is a majority in the United Rabbinate in favor of a certain policy, it is the sacred duty of this majority to see that its will and opinion is carried out, and enforced.</p>
   <p>The immediate task of the United Rabbinate is to establish harmonious relations within its own folds. It must have the courage to do that which it should do because it can rely upon the public's support. If only the United Rabbinate and the laymen are determined, there will be order in this city [Jewish community].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
