<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
wk. of <date when="1892-01-02">Jan. 2, 1892</date>. pp. 357-358.
<title level="a">"Chicago Jews in the Late War."</title><title level="a" type="sub">Excerpts from an Article by Frederik Mayer.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1306</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1306.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
wk. of <date when="1892-01-02">Jan. 2, 1892</date>. pp. 357-358.
<title level="a">"CHICAGO JEWS IN THE LATE WAR."</title><title level="a" type="sub">Excerpts From An Article By Frederik Mayer.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the December issue of the North American Review there appeared an article by J.M. Rogers in which he stated that during 18 months service, he did not remember meeting one Jew in uniform or hearing of a Jewish soldier. Furthermore notwithstanding the fact that he traveled for 25 subsequent years among old soldiers, never did he meet anyone that remembered serving with Jews.</p>
   <p>Hon. Simon Wolf refutes, in the Washington Post of Dec. 10th, J.M. Rogers' statements. He not only points out that gallant services were rendered for the Union by Jewish citizens, but thoroughly disposes of all the groundless charges.</p>
   <p>The Jewish population of Chicago, at the outbreak of the Civil War, could scarcely have attained a higher figure than six or seven thousand souls. It was certainly far below ten thousand, and at that time there existed <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1307.jpg" n="2"/>but three congregations.</p>
   <p>Hon. Simon Wolf furnishes a long list of names derived from official and other sources. It may prove interesting to learn how some Jewish gentlemen of this city participated in the war.</p>
   <p>In Chicago, the name of Edward S. Solomon is present in all minds. The first company he raised was formed almost entirely of Jews. Brigadier General Solomon left Chicago in 1870, being appointed Governor of Washington Territory. He had entered the regiment as Lieutenant-Colonel and had commanded the 82nd Illinois.</p>
   <p>Joseph Gruenhut was captin of one of the companies raised in this city, and raised, too, in but a few days. He was promoted to the captaincy of the 82nd and is a brother-in-law of Edward S. Solomon.</p>
   <p>Another company, composed mostly of Jews, was formed by the Concordia Club. It mustered nearly 100 strong. It was Captain La Salle who commanded this <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1308.jpg" n="3"/>particular company. Wm. Loeb, the well-known resident of this city was a lieutenant under Captain La Salle. The 82nd was 1,000 strong. About 10% of these being Jews.</p>
   <p>Not a company of this regiment was devoid of Jews and they proved themselves to be excellent soldiers.</p>
   <p>Chas. Herrick of Chicago is but another example of one of those plucky Jews who, enlisting first for a period of three months, undertook to serve their country's cause for three years.</p>
   <p>Captain Frank is another well known militaire. He enlisted in Chicago and was elected first lieutenant of Company C of the 82nd Illinois, in which he served about two years. He was at Chancellorsville and at Gettysburg from first to last. Captain Frank fought under Gen. Carl Schurz on several occasions.</p>
   <p>The above mentioned names are but a few of the Chicago Jewish soldiers who did their duty during the Civil War.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
