<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-13">Mar. 13, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Good Morning</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0555</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0555.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-13">Mar. 13, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD MORNING</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Jews ask me who the legitimate rabbis and who the illegitimate rabbis are. I can best answer this question by assuming that generally the rabbis of the large synagogues are true rabbis, and the fake rabbis, over whom the rabbis of large synagogues and synagogue presidents have no control, usually get jobs in the small synagogues. When a large synagogue engages a rabbi, it, as a rule, knows whom the rabbi is and what his qualifications and his background consist of. However, a small synagogue engages a rabbi not because it is in need of one, but because it wants to appear "big," and it also wants the rabbi to attract a large crowd. A small synagogue requires of a rabbi that he be, above all, an "orator," or, as they call it, a "public speaker". Sometimes he is a good public speaker and sometimes he is only an impudent clown. Since the synagogue does not seek a real rabbi but simply an orator, questionable elements creep into the rabbinical profession. This is one of the reasons, if <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0556.jpg" n="2"/>not the reason, why America is so inundated with rabbis who are not rabbis and who disgrace rabbinism. The members of the small synagogues are to blame for this deplorable situation because they indiscriminately engage anyone as a rabbi if they believe he will attract a large crowd--as though it were the task of a rabbi to draw a large crowd. The real rabbis must fight against this distorted conception of rabbinism, otherwise rabbinism will be completely undermined.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
