<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-12-10">Dec. 10, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">An Interview with the Leboshay Rabbi</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0906</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0906.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-12-10">Dec. 10, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">AN INTERVIEW WITH THE LEBOSHAY RABBI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>I found the Rabbi in a large room, bent over a deep book. On hearing my footsteps, he straightened and extened his hand to me, saying, "Sholom Alechim!" (Hello!).</p>
   <p>A strange feeling enveloped me. It seemed as if I had seen the entire house many years ago somewhere in Russia, not here. The old Jews I encountered at the entrance, with their half-gray beards, their old-fashioned garments, truly appeared to be kindred Jews. Then that table so littered with books, with large, thick Gommorahs, and the Rabbi in his short prayer shawl, carried my imagination for back to the old home (Russia).</p>
   <p>I could not begin at once, but sat a while absorbing everything in view. Finally, with much respect, I addressed the Rabbi, requesting that since he had so recently returned from Russia, he could tell me something of Jewish life there.</p>
   <p>I observed a faint shadow flash across his face. His bright eyes, shining brilliantly but a moment ago as he read the Gommorah, dimmed perceptibly <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0907.jpg" n="2"/>and a heavy sigh escaped his breast. "Bad, very bad," he said quietly. "The Jew is driven from the villages and estates to the city, where he has no means of sustenance. Should he rent a river or a brook, it is taken away from him. This creates a bad influence in Jewish life. Despair makes the Jew sink mentally; he sees only evil until disgusted with everything; quite often it becomes impossible for him to uphold that respectability of which we Jews are so proud. Life is very oppressive at present in Russia, for the Jewish people."</p>
   <p>He was quiet. When I lifted my eyes to his face, I saw that the Rabbi had just suffered much, for he knows that the troubles of the Jewish people in Russia are far more painful than what he has stated.</p>
   <p>"What is your opinion of Jewish life in America?" I asked him.</p>
   <p>"It is even better than the opinion I had formed of it in Russia," was his reply. "You know", he said to me, "we in Russia do not have the right idea of Jewish life in America. Everyone's belief is that here one has better things to eat, one earns more, there is no pressure, no abeyance, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0908.jpg" n="3"/>but, Torah and Jewishness are completely ignored. And, it may be possible that at one time it must have been so, but, now it is different, entirely different.</p>
   <p>"First in New York and now in Chicago I have been observing how the large Jewish communities are being strengthened from day to day. They build Talmud-Torahs, support Yeshivas, and study the Torah.</p>
   <p>"What pleases me most of all is that the American Jew, no matter how worldly he becomes, is not ashamed to say he is a Jew, which is not the case with most Russian Jews."</p>
   <p>I could distinctly discern a certain anger expressed in his words. "Do you intend to remain in America?" I asked him.</p>
   <p>"Everything depends on my father, "he explained. "If I should remain in America, my father would believe that I seek huge gains. I sent him a letter and although no answer has as yet come, I know he would not be pleased if I do not return. I will explain at home that here in America <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0909.jpg" n="4"/>life blooms again. Perhaps he will consent to my being the Rabbi of my kinfolks in New York, who sent for me."</p>
   <p>Again he bent low over his book, as if it would shield him from something. It may be that perhaps these worldly discussions are distasteful to him. Who can tell? Perhaps he merely wished to expel a tragic thought, the sentiment of leaving his old father.</p>
   <p>On taking my leave, he wished me well and I left.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
