<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-16">Mar. 16, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Is Immigration against the Interests of the Workers?</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Sol Posner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1684</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1684.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-03-16">Mar. 16, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">IS IMMIGRATION AGAINST THE INTERESTS OF THE WORKERS?</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Sol Posner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The immigration problem, which has been practically dead for the past few years, as a result of the World War, has been revived, and is again one of the topics of the day in our political and industrial world. Again two factions have formed, each with its own interpretation of this problem; each is organizing to protect its interests, which, each faction claims, are vitally connected with [the problem of] immigration.</p>
   <p>That the immigration problem, at the present moment, is a very serious one, is proved by the fact that the House Immigration Committee, of which Representative Johnson is the chairman, is studying this problem at the present <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1685.jpg" n="2"/>time, and will soon begin a public hearing. Following the public hearing, the Committee will present a report to the House, recommending, at the same time, new laws for or against immigration, as it deems necessary.</p>
   <p>At this time, we do not wish to discuss the position of the chief foes of immigration, who claim that immigration is a misfortune for America because the foreigners who come here are inferior to the Americans. These enemies of immigration, in whose brain and blood this un-American thought exists, "like a worm," will certainly not change [the tone of] our newspaper articles. We merely want to mention here the words of a prominent American lecturer, Mr. Hiller, who gave a scientific lecture, two weeks ago, on the problem of immigration before the Americanization institute of the Young Men's Christian Association.</p>
   <p>The lecturer proved that not only is immigration not detrimental--it is <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1686.jpg" n="3"/>actually a blessing to America because the immigrants bring with them their spirit of idealism, which, in our industrial America, has been slowly strangled in the fight for the dollar. Mr. Hiller did not base his lecture upon empty speculation, but upon scientific, statistical facts.</p>
   <p>To prove that the immigrants who come to America are idealists, and, therefore, welcome guests here, Mr. Hiller introduced the statistical data, published by the Chicago city officials, of the number of criminals of each nationality in Chicago. These statistics show the percentage of criminals for every one thousand inhabitants from each nationality: Canadians, 5%, Germans, 5%, English, 7%, Greeks, 7%, Austrians, 8%, Hungarians, 9%, Russians, 30%, Irish, 40% and Americans, 56%.</p>
   <p>These figures need no comment, and we, therefore, will consider the argument of the "industrial opposition," which claims that immigration harms the <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1687.jpg" n="4"/>interests of the American workers.</p>
   <p>The main argument of this industrial opposition to immigration, headed by Samuel Gompers, president of the American Federation of Labor, is that the immigrants will increase the number of unemployed, and through competition, will take away the jobs of American workers.</p>
   <p>Despite the fact that this claim is untenable, nevertheless, the ignorant American workers have been influenced by it through Mr. Gompers and his clique. But now, when unemployment is entirely unknown in this country, and an actual shortage of labor exists, this argument is not only groundless, it is simply ridiculous. Gompers and his clique advance such an argument in an attempt to impress the organized workers [with the fact] that they are trying to protect the workers' interests. The latter have lost their faith in them.</p>
   <p>The American economists who are studying the causes of the rising cost of living in America, and with whom Gompers agrees, are in unanimous agreement <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1688.jpg" n="5"/>that the fault lies in the shortage of production. If this explanation is true, then immigration, at the present time, is the only way to solve the [problem of the] high cost of living in America, and is, therefore, a blessing to the American workers who suffer most from the rising prices.</p>
   <p>The fear that even the present, limited immigration will harm the American worker, and the campaign which Gompers has announced he would open soon, are even more ridiculous. Gompers' attitude springs from the profound ignorance of this senile labor leader, who, as the head of organized labor in America, has, for the past few decades, adhered to the same old standpoint as existed a half-century ago.</p>
   <p>Reports of the Immigration Bureau state that the majority of the immigrants of today are individuals who, for a certain length of time had lived in America, but returned to their native land because of the World War.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1689.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>It is hard to believe that those immigrants who have lived in America, and have orientated themselves to the American standard of living, would suddenly begin to compete with the American workers. The fact is that it is not at all necessary for those immigrants to deny their alien birth, because the foreign-born workers have already proven their loyalty, idealism, and readiness to protect the ranks of organized labor in America. They are admired and respected for this attitude by the American workers and all the prominent labor leaders, with the exception of Gompers and his clique.</p>
   <p>The last great strikes in America, the coal strike and the steel strike, raised the foreign born workers one-hundred per cent in the eyes of their American co-workers who consider them [shining] examples of organizational loyalty and fighting ability.</p>
   <p>The foreign-born steel workers, who not only endured hunger and misery, with <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1690.jpg" n="7"/>their wives and children, but also suffered horrible brutalities at the hands of thugs, murderers, robbers, and cutthroats, hired by the steel trust to terrorize them, deserve the admiration of all. They also suffered at the hands of government employees who honestly and faithfully served the interests of the steel trust. The highest tribunal of justice in America has found the steel trust to be a legal corporation, founded on just principles and administered accordingly.</p>
   <p>John Fitzpatrick, liberal president of the Chicago Federation of Labor, speaks with admiration and respect of the foreign-born workers, whose loyalty and devotion in the struggle, he has had the opportunity of observing. Fitzpatrick says that he personally saw hired thugs enter the homes of these strikers and beat them, their wives, and their children almost to the point of death. Later, these strikers were arrested and locked up in jail. The Spanish Inquisition was a mere trifle compared to the torture the strikers had to endure, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1691.jpg" n="8"/>and yet they did not yield. They stood firmly determined to fight to the end.</p>
   <p>All American labor leaders, with the exception of Gompers, speak respectfully of the foreign-born workers and do not oppose immigration. Gompers has personal reason to fear immigration. The greater the number of foreigners arriving here, the sooner will Gompers' "throne," which is already on the verge of collapse, be destroyed. We don't have to take Gompers' fight against immigration seriously because his influence upon American labor is today almost negligible, and will, therefore, have little effect.</p>
   <p>Gompers was defeated by his own local in the election of a delegate to the national convention; recently, he has not only been ignored, but has been simply ridiculed by labor federations of Indiana, Illinois, Michigan, and many other states. He is now politically dead, and his crusade against immigration will be as successful as his fight against the Labor party. Poor Gompers!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
