<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-31">Mar. 31, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Celebrate Seventieth Birthday of Rabbi J. L. Gordon</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0440</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0440.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-31">Mar. 31, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">CELEBRATE SEVENTIETH BIRTHDAY OF RABBI J. L. GORDON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Over four hundred men and women, all the rabbis of Chicago, representatives of synagogues and organizations, gathered last night to celebrate the seventieth birthday anniversary of Rabbi Gordon.</p>
   <p>The banquet, in connection with the celebration, was a grand affair. The hall in the Jewish Theological College, where the banquet took place, was crowded with the most prominent Orthodox Jews of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The public enjoyed eating the fine food and listening to words of the Torah.</p>
   <p>Mr. George Marok, president of the Tiphereth Zion Synagogue, where Rabbi Gordon is the rabbi, was the toastmaster of the evening. He was introduced by Mr. Jacob Gray, chairman of the arrangement committee of the banquet.</p>
   <p>Speeches were given by Rabbi Ezriel Epstein, Dr. S. M. Melamed, Sam Ginsburg, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0441.jpg" n="2"/>Max Shulman, Rabbi Resht, Gershon Gutman, Rabbi [A.] Margolin, Rabbi Saul Silber, Rabbi Renenberg, and B. Horwich.</p>
   <p>All speakers praised Rabbi Gordon highly for his genius and pointed out that the Jews of Chicago had gained greatly in the fields of Judaism, unity, community interests in general, by having Rabbi Gordon as their chief rabbi.</p>
   <p>Cantor Tolomash sang appropriate melodies. Rabbi Gordon responded in a masterful speech, full of wisdom and Torah.</p>
   <p>The banquet was served by Mr. Lieberman of the Zion Restaurant.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
