<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-03">Aug. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">From the Public Rostrum</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0831</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0831.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-08-03">Aug. 3, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE PUBLIC ROSTRUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by J. Leibner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The various branches of the Adas Bnai Israel [an ultra-Orthodox, anti-Zionist organization] are a strong force within Orthodox Judaism in Chicago. One of its branches, with headquarters at 1118 South Marshfield Avenue, will celebrate its anniversary next Sunday; it was founded seven years ago.</p>
   <p>The history of this branch is brief but interesting. Its first members were students of the Yeshivath Etz Chaim (Hebrew theological college), who undertook to do whatever they could for Judaism, and particularly to propagandize among the Jewish youth for the observance of the Sabbath. They have done a great deal in this respect.</p>
   <p>Many young Jews who were not absorbed in sports, or in playing pool, were attracted to this organization. Thus the membership grew larger and larger.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0832.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Thanks to these young men, we now have four branches of the Adas Bnai Israel in different parts of the city. They have clubrooms where they meet to discuss problems pertaining to Judaism. The important thing is that they all observe the Sabbath, thus proving that one can hold a job in a factory or a store, or that one can carry on one's own business in America, and still observe the Sabbath.</p>
   <p>Ask any one of the modest, truly Jewish youth of the Adas Bnai Israel at Marshfield Avenue what the purpose of the organization is, and he will answer:</p>
   <p>"We advocate the observance of the Sabbath and we obtain jobs for those who do not want to work on the holy day of the week.</p>
   <p>"We are striving to create a strong and powerful organization of all the Jewish youth who cling to the tenets of Judaism.</p>
   <p>"We seek to spread the ideals and aspirations of Judaism, and especially to <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0833.jpg" n="3"/>clarify the importance and holiness of the Sabbath."</p>
   <p>To this let us add what the youth, in his modesty, failed to say--that the above-mentioned Adas Bnai Israel seeks no honors in our community, and plays no politics. The members give their assistance to every Jewish enterprise, but Orthodox Judaism is their most important concern.</p>
   <p>They have arranged a splendid program for their anniversary next Sunday, and we wish to see a large Jewish gathering at their celebration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
