<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-22">Aug. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[Appeal to the Chicago Orthodoxy]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0646</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0646.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-22">Aug. 22, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[APPEAL TO THE CHICAGO ORTHODOXY]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If the Chicago Orthodoxy, which is organized in synagogues, does not want to drive the youth away from the synagogues and does not want the Jewish Masses to turn to Reform Judaism because they are dissatisfied with the order prevailing in many Orthodox synagogues, then the Chicago Orthodoxy will have to introduce regulations which will change the synagogue into a solemn place of worship for those who come to pray. I certainly am not a friend of the Reform temple but whenever I enter a Reform temple and note the calmness, the solemnity, and the decent behavior of the people who pray, I begin to understand why so many of our Americanized Jewish brethren are leaving the Orthodox synagogues for the Reform temples. It is quiet and orderly in a Reform temple during the services. The president of a Reform temple does not deliver any speeches from the pulpit. Quiet and solemnity reign in a Reform temple.</p>
   <p>I can very well imagine an old-fashioned Orthodox synagogue where quiet, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0647.jpg" n="2"/>solemnity, and order reigned during the services. I can very well imagine an Orthodox synagogue where no speeches by the president were delivered. I can very well imagine an Orthodox synagogue as attractive to our youth as a Reform temple. The presidents of synagogues can enforce quiet, solemnity, and orderly behavior in a synagogue. The rabbis can insist that their place, the pulpit, shall not be debased by speeches of the president.</p>
   <p>If the Chicago Orthodoxy would introduce these regulations, then the Orthodox synagogue would become attractive to our youth, our Americanized Jews, and our Jewish brethren would cease to run to Reform temples.</p>
   <p>I say this seriously to the representatives of the Chicago Orthodoxy, without any secret motives, and without any intention whatsoever of insulting anybody or of showing disrespect to anybody. I want Orthodox Judaism to be as beautiful and noble outwardly as it is beautiful and noble inwardly.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
