<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-04">Mar. 4, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A Conflict Over a .... God</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0564</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0564.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-04">Mar. 4, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">A CONFLICT OVER A .... GOD</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Protestant Church in America is up in arms at the present time. A prominent Protestant minister, Dr. Grant, has publicly declared that he does not believe in the divinity of Christ nor in Christian theology formulated by the Apostles. Futhermore, Dr. Grant says he does not believe in the doctrine of the Trinity; he holds the Christian concept of God to be an obsolete and much overworked theology, which no modern person can accept.</p>
   <p>Nothing that Dr. Grant said about the Christian faith, or the Trinity, or the obsolete Christian theology is new. This question was first debated three hundred years after the death of Christ, and has never been entirely resolved. Academic Christian theology has, for a long time, proclaimed the purely mythological character of Christian religion. Dr. Grant said nothing new to those who are somewhat familiar with the <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0565.jpg" n="2"/>modern critics of the New Testament.</p>
   <p>The Christian masses in the civilized countries have long since given up their belief in the principles of Christianity. The Christian churches have been empty for one hundred years; the Catholic Church alone is still frequented by women. In Anglo-Saxon countries, where the Christian church is still strong, it derives its power from political and social forces, rather than from religious [forces]. In England, for example, affiliation with the Church of England is a matter of patriotism because the Church developed from the struggle against Roman Catholicism. The Protestant Church in England is the symbol of national freedom, and its antithesis is not heresy but Papacy. In England, Papacy is synonymous with national dependence and reaction. Hence, in England, the Church is a national and political institution, and every patriotically inclined Englishman is a member of the Church of England. It has nothing to do with religion or the doctrines of faith. In England, men of great erudition, who are philosophical freethinkers, attend church regularly on Sunday.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0566.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In continental Europe, however, the situation is quite different. There, church attendance is practiced only by the believers, and their number is quite small. In 1900, statistics regarding church attendance in Germany proved that only three per cent of the entire population of Germany attended church, i.e., twenty years ago, ninety-seven per cent of the German population did not attend church. It is also worthy of note that in Germany, under the Kaiser's regime, religious instruction was obligatory in public schools, and every German child was compelled to study religion.</p>
   <p>In countries where religion is not part of the school curriculum, as for example in France and in the Scandinavian countries, church attendance is much smaller than in Germany, and that is why such statements as were recently made by Dr. Grant, have no significance in Europe. In Europe, anti-Christian traditions have prevailed ever since the French Revolution.</p>
   <p>From the standpoint of numbers, Christianity is today the faith of a <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0567.jpg" n="4"/>relatively small number of people, although it is still the dominant religion of the white race, in so far as it has no competition. If a candidate for a political office has no opposition, he is declared elected, notwithstanding the fact that only a handful of votes were cast for him. If a religion has no opposition, it is also considered the official one; only in this sense is Christianity still the official and dominant religion of the white race. But as an active religious force in the world, Christianity has long ceased to exist.</p>
   <p>We must take these facts into consideration, if we wish to appreciate fully the significance of the statement made by Dr. Grant. His statement made not the slightest impression upon the general public, but it infuriated all the church circles in America, i.e., the clergy, the church politicians, the small group of believers, and all those who have connections with, or derive a livelihood from the church. The American people are not upset, but the American church is, because that which Dr. Grant said, does tremendous harm to the Christian church as an organization from which hundreds of thousands <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0568.jpg" n="5"/>earn a comfortable living. Two or three hundred years ago, Dr. Grant would have been stoned for his heresy because at that time, there were still a large number of Christian believers, and, at that time, Christianity was still the driving and creative religious force in the life of the people. Today, open heresy on the part of a clergyman does not arouse any protest because Christianity as a driving religious force in the life of the masses is dead. Only the clergy and those who derive a livelihood from the Church are interested in Christian theological problems.</p>
   <p>What was the Christian reaction to Dr. Grant's statements? His superior, Bishop Manning, sought to expel the heretic from the Church. He demanded that Dr. Grant resign, but since the Bishop did not pay Dr. Grant's salary and his congregation did, and since his congregation did not oppose his heresy, the Bishop's demand was not satisfied, and Dr. Grant remained the pastor of his congregation. This alone shows how much churchgoers think about Christianity as a theological system, and how much interest they take in church questions. If the members of the <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0569.jpg" n="6"/>church are indifferent to the type of heresy that was enunciated by Dr. Grant, we can easily imagine how unimportant the whole matter is to the broad Christian masses who never go to church and who are not members of any church. To them, Dr. Grant's statement was not worth the publicity that the newspapers gave it.</p>
   <p>However, the heretical statement of Dr. Grant had a crushing effect upon those who are interested in the Church because Dr. Grant deprived them of their stock in trade, their existence, their livelihood. The conflict over [the question of] God, opened by Dr. Grant for the benefit of those who are not entirely clear, is actually a struggle against an organization from which many people earn a living. A struggle against the religious principles of the Church is of no greater importance than a struggle against the principles of [trade] unionism, or against the basic principles of any other organization. Just as the teaching of [rugged] individualism is a vital threat to <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0570.jpg" n="7"/>trade unionism, just as the teaching of anarchism, in its mildest form, is especially hateful to state officials and politicians who earn a living from the state, and just as the teaching of pacifism is despised by those who profit from war, i.e., the militarists and munitions manufacturers, so the heresy of a Christian clergyman is abhorrent to all who earn livelihood from the Church. But the general public is not even interested in this matter because it has long given up its Christian faith. Under the most favorable circumstances, the public believes that the value of the Church lies in its ability to keep the masses in check, and in nothing more. The public is not interested in the minister's beliefs.</p>
   <p>The reaction of the clergy to the heresy of Dr. Grant is very interesting because it proves how helpless they are. At a conference of clergymen in Ohio, a resolution was adopted affirming their belief that Christ is not only a part of the Trinity, but that He Himself is God. The resolution reads, "He is the very God," i.e., He Himself is God, and not, as has been accepted, that He is only a part of the Divinity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0571.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>This resolution does not express the general Christian attitude toward Christ and many Christian believers will rightly see in this resolution a deviation from the orthodox Christian belief. The fact that Dr. Grant asserts that Christ was only a mortal being prompts his opponents to go to the opposite extreme [that He is God]. Another group of clergymen in the United States, realizing the weakness of their own position, do not declare a theological battle against Dr. Grant, but satisfy themselves with denouncing him for his lack of tact and impudence. It is as if they wanted to say to him, "Why do you bite the hand that feeds you?"</p>
   <p>If the Church ceases to preach the Christian dogma, what justification for existence does it have? If the teachings of Dr. Grant should become general, what will the clergymen preach from their pulpits, and why should the Church and the whole apparatus of a Christian church organization be maintained? This is the one question that keeps the representatives of the Christian church in America busy today. Since they cannot openly present these arguments, they must either accept the resolution as formulated by the Ohio conference, which will hardly meet with general <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0572.jpg" n="9"/>approval, or they must denounce Dr. Grant as one who undermines the foundation of their existence. Therefore, the conflict over a God, which Dr. Grant evoked by his heretical statement, is actually a struggle against an organization which feels itself materially threatened by such proclamations. The epoch of religious wars is today part of history; the period of spiritual strife within Christianity has run its course. The professors of Christian theology in all Protestant universities are freethinkers as far as the principles of Christian faith are concerned, and among the Protestant clergymen themselves, there is only a small minority who still cling to a belief in the Divinity of Christ, and if the others do not follow the example of Dr. Grant, it is because they find it neither becoming nor necessary. The modern individual does not generally speak openly of his religious or metaphysical convictions because he believes that religion is a private matter, a matter between God and himself. It is for this reason that thousands of Christian clergymen keep their religious convictions to themselves and do not emulate Dr. Grant.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0573.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>The Christian church cannot repudiate Christian mythology even if all its representatives became convinced that the whole Christian dogma is a mythological antique because the Christian church, apart from the Christian dogma, has nothing to offer. Christianity has no ethic and is not as integrally bound up with an ethic as is the Jewish religion. [The Christian religion denies this world, and its whole center of gravity is placed upon the "Heavenly Kingdom". If the " "Heavenly Kingdom" is only a mythological legend,] which the modern person cannot accept, what then remains of Christianity? Nothing. That is why the Christian church organization guards its dogma more carefully than the representatives of the Jewish religion do the principles of Judaism. If we should remove from Judaism its purely dogmatic aspect, that is, that the Torah is God-given, etc., the Torah would still remain, with its noble system of ethics, of jurisprudence based upon ethics, of social and economic justice, etc. Whether one believes in the divine origin of the Torah or not, that which the prophets of righteousness and justice taught and preached, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0574.jpg" n="11"/>still remains great and noble. But if a Christian denies the Divinity of Christ, what does he have left? He has nothing. He has neither God, nor ethics, nor social justice, nor ethical doctrines of the state. He has nothing; he has simply awakened from a remarkable dream.</p>
   <p>The Christian church, however, cannot transform Christianity into a system of ethics and say: We, the former representatives of Christianity, preach ethics today because Christianity is, in its essence, thoroughly unethical, Ethics are for this world. People on earth must be good and righteous, but anyone who denies this world, as Christianity demands, cannot, and must not do anything to make this world better, more beautiful, or more satisfactory. Ethics has one objective: its belief in the future of mankind on this earth, and its relationship to life [on this earth]. Christianity denies [earthly] life and preaches a future not of this but of the next world [after death]. For this reason alone, Christianity cannot be modified by a system of ethics. If a belief in the Divinity of Christ is erased from the Christian faith, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0575.jpg" n="12"/>there remains only one thing to do: Close the Christian churches and declare publicly the absolute bankruptcy of Christianity.</p>
   <p>We cannot reproach the representatives of Christianity for their reluctance to do this [declare bankruptcy]. To them the Christian dogma is no longer a question of religious conviction, but is rather a question of being in favor of or opposed to Christianity. So far as Judaism is concerned, dogmatism is not a question of pro or con because no one has yet shaken the philosophical basis of Jewish dogma. Monotheism today is as strongly intrenched philosophically as it was one-, two-, or five-hundred years ago, and the formal dogma of Judaism is certainly not essential to its existence. Judaism will not perish even if the formal dogma is completely given up. The Jewish God will still live and the prophets of truth and righteousness will also live. The Jewish concept of God is too depply imbedded in Ethics for a formal dogma to imperil it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0576.jpg" n="13"/>
   <p>Fifteen years ago, when philosophic materialism was still very strong, a scientific society in Germany submitted questionnaires to all German scientists, asking their opinion on God. The German public was surprised to learn that ninety per cent of the scientists, including chemists, physicists, astronomers, geologists, biologists, etc., declared their belief in one God. Less than two per cent avowed a belief in the Christian Trinity. Hence, the sum total of Christian heresy is not directed against the belief in one God, but rather against the belief in the Trinity. Christianity stands and falls on the teaching of the Trinity. Apart from this belief, Christianity has nothing to say, has nothing to offer; it is in a precarious position because its concept of God is impure. It is a compromise between ancient idolatry and Judaism. If a Christian relinquishes his belief in Christianity, and rejects the Christian concept of God as an affront to the human intellect, and is still of a religious nature--a person to whom a belief in a Supreme Being is essential--he will, reluctantly or otherwise, have to accept the Jewish concept of God because even without any dogmatic coloring, it is pure <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0577.jpg" n="14"/>and serene. Instead of being the antithesis of reason, as is the Christian concept of God, it is demanded by the human intellect. Human reason agrees with the contention that everything is accidental, that our whole universe is an accident, that the planets rotate in their orbit by accident, that all natural laws are accidental. The Jewish concept of God demands human reason, while the Christian concept of God is opposed to reason. Why should a God be borne of a woman, die, and then be resurrected in order to redeem mankind? Could He not have redeemed mankind without such humiliation? The human mind can never satisfy itself with such a God. That is why the Church had to wage war against reason and against science, whereas Judaism never participated in a war against science and human reason.</p>
   <p>Who denounced Copernicus, Galileo, Lamarck, and Darwin? It was not the representatives of the Jewish religion, but the representatives of the Christian church because the Christian religion cannot compete with reason, with science, whereas the Jewish religion primarily appeals <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0578.jpg" n="15"/>to the human mind, and has made reason an essential factor of life.</p>
   <p>In Christianity, knowledge is synonymous with sin. In Judaism, knowledge is synonymous with love, and love is not sin, as in Christianity--love is pleasing to God. Anyone who says: this life, this world, must include love. But to the individual who denies this world and claims "the Heavenly Kingdom alone," love is sin. If love is identified with knowledge, then knowledge is also sin, and in fact, knowledge is sin, in Christian theology.</p>
   <p>For this reason, Christianity must wage war against reason and science, and when the awakened, critical mind frees itself of Christian theology and metaphysics, everything collapses. Nothing remains....</p>
   <p>The representatives of the Protestant Church know full well that many of the clergymen are freethinkers as far as Christian dogma is concerned, but as long as they keep quiet, no one will question their beliefs. But when one publicly defies Christian dogma, as Dr. Grant has done, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0579.jpg" n="16"/>the representatives of the Church become uneasy because without Christian dogma, Christianity is destined to perish, whereas Judaism does not depend upon dogma and can exist without it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
