<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-09">June 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Clubhouse for Jewish Boys from the Great Lakes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1241</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1241.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-09">June 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CLUBHOUSE FOR JEWISH BOYS FROM THE GREAT LAKES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Waukegan Club of the Jewish Welfare Board will hold "open house" today, Sunday, June 9. Waukegan is the nearest city to the Great Lakes Naval Station and is the favorite spot for the sailors. Among the great number of sailors are several hundred Jewish boys who have voluntarily answered Uncle Sam's call of : "War upon the Wild Beast of Berlin!"</p>
   <p>The Jewish Welfare Board found it necessary to provide for the Jewish sailors so that they might have something to occupy them in their leisure and keep up their spirits, and so that they would not be worse off than their Christian buddies, who are supported by such a great, benevolent institution as the Y. M. C. A.</p>
   <p>For this purpose the Jewish Welfare Board of Waukegan, Illinois has opened a clubhouse for Jewish sailors at 218 South Genesee Street, where they may spend their leisure time in reading, writing, or other forms of diversion. There they can obtain everything from a Bible to a modern Jewish book, belles-lettres, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1242.jpg" n="2"/>poetry, scientific books; also all kinds of Jewish newspapers are requested. As for writing paper and other writing implements, there is no question but that they all receive as much as they need.</p>
   <p>A special program for this Sunday has been arranged by the Board and the general public is cordially invited. The affair will begin at three-thirty in the afternoon. Mr. Samuel Schwartz, chairman of the Waukegan Branch, J.W.B., will preside. The Chicago Branch will be represented by its chairman, Judge Philip Stein and Milwaukee will be represented by its chairman, Rabbi C. S. Levy. Other speakers will be: Chaplain V. P. Williams, U. S. N. of the Naval Station; L. J. Levinger, field representative of the Jewish Welfare Board in the Great Lakes(area), and others.</p>
   <p>A fine musical program will be given. The famous Great Lakes Orchestra will play, and the professional actors, Mr. Grossman and Mr. Sobel will entertain in order to keep the audience in a gay and happy mood.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1243.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The rooms of the clubhouse will be open to visitors this Sunday from two in the afternoon until ten in the evening. A large crowd is expected.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
