<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1914-02">February 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Herzl Memorial Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0250</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0250.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1914-02">February 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Herzl Memorial Meeting</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A large and enthusiastic audience was present to honor the memory of Theodore Herzl on the celebration of the tenth anniversary of the death of the great founder of Zionism. The meeting was opened by the Chairman of the evening, Judge Philip P. Bregstone, who briefly explained the occasion of such a memorial meeting.</p>
   <p>Following the Chairman's remarks, Mr. Philip L. Seman delivered an address on the place which Theodore Herzl will occupy in the history of the Jewish Thought and Life of the Future. He briefly told how Dr. Herzl, at first indifferent to the needs of his people and even apparently unconscious of his being a member of the Jewish Faith, appeared on the scene of activity at the psychological moment, roused the slumbering forces of Judaism, and by giving a new interpretation to its future hopes, created a national movement, the scope of which we of today are hardly in a position to judge.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0251.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Following the eulogy of Herzl by Mr. Abrahams, the secretary of the "Hatchuach", under whose auspices the meeting was held, a memorial-prayer was rendered by Mr. Zuckerman. Mr. Hyman L. Meites of the Zionist Council made an announcement concerning the public school to be built by the Chicago Board of Education and to be named after Theodore Herzl. He informed the audience that a life-sized bust of Dr. Herzl is now being made in the Bezalel School in Jerusalem by Professor Boris Schatz and when completed will be placed in the new Herzl School. Mr. Steinberg made an impassioned plea on the necessity of supporting the national fund. Mr. Frankel of Palestine gave an interesting and enthusiastic talk on his work in Palestine. He gave a review of Dr. Herzl's plan for the financial needs of Zionism and laid special stress on the fact that inasmuch as Zionism was a Movement of the Jewish people, funds should come not so much from the wealthy as from the masses. The meeting was closed by the singing of the Jewish National song, "Hatikvah".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
