<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1928-01-20">January 20, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Young Judaea Column</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Fanny Slobod.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1337</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1337.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1928-01-20">January 20, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">YOUNG JUDAEA COLUMN</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Fanny Slobod.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>DEBATING LEAGUE.</p>
   <p>The climax to the debates will occur on Sunday, February 5, when the two winning teams will debate of the subject: "Resolved That America Is Destined To Become The Greatest Jewish Educational Center In The World." This subject was chosen as a fitting close to the previous topics which were along educational lines.</p>
   <p>On Sunday, January 22, the Hammond Juniors and the members of Ain Harod will enter the last lap of their journey to see who will debate in the finals with the girls from Beth Gan. The subject of this debate is: "Resolved That A Jewish University Should Be Established In the United States."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1338.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Hammond Hebrew Juniors have the affirmative and the boys from Ain Harod the negative. The debate will take place at the Jewish People's Institute, 1243 N. Wood Street, at 2:30. A delegation will meet the Hammond representatives at the Randolph Street Station and the members of the Beth Alpha Club will entertain them after the debate is over.</p>
   <p>Chicago is anxious to return the hospitality extended to them when they were in Hammond. Both clubs feel confident of victory and the judges are going to have a difficult time making a decision.</p>
   <p>GEVA'S IDEA.</p>
   <p>The idea for an Intermediate Debating League was suggested by members of Geva, better known as the "Hakoah Juniors" and one of their members, Rudolph Rosenberg, has handled all the arrangements. Preliminaries were held and thus selections made.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1339.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>CHECKER TOURNAMENT.</p>
   <p>Elimination contests in the various districts are being held in order that two teams may be selected to take place in the finals which will be held on Sunday, February 5. A Junior and Senior team will be chosen from each district and then the various teams will compete against each other in the finals.</p>
   <p>Galilee will hold its elimination contest on January 22, and the South Side on January 29. The Emeek will also hold its elimination contest soon. Trophies will be awarded to the winners in each division.</p>
   <p>EXECUTIVE REPRESENTATIVE</p>
   <p>Every registered club will be entitled to cast a vote for the individual it thinks should be selected to the National Executive Council on February 5.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1340.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The nominees are Ada Quiat, Jonas Meyers, Lena Brodsky, Lester Carmel and Fanny Slobod.</p>
   <p>REUNION DANCE.</p>
   <p>For the benefit of those young Judaeans and their friends who will attend Chicago Young Judaean's Dance at the Stevens Hotel on Saturday, February 18, we want to make it plain that the dance is strictly informal and not a couple affair. In fact, couples will be discouraged because this dance will be a mixer and its main purpose will be to make the attendants acquainted with one another. Chicago Young Judaean's Reunion Dance will be an affair that will be different."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1341.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It won't be one of those dances where young men and young women come up and sit around gazing coldly at one another. A special committee has been appointed to see that the young people mix. Chicago Young Judaea ranks among the leaders in its educational work and its friends will discover that it can rank as a leader in sociability as well.</p>
   <p>MID-WEST CONFERENCE.</p>
   <p>Chicago Young Judaea will be host to a large group of young Judaeans from out of town on February 13, and February 19. On those two days will take place a Mid-West Conference to which leaders from as far east as the State of Ohio and as far west as the State of Colorado will be invited.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1342.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Chicago Young Judaea is aiming to make this conference one that will not be forgotten by its visitors. Any young Judaeans who can accommodate a guest are asked to see Sam Strauss.</p>
   <p>LIBRARY</p>
   <p>Miss Ada Quiat reports that she has collected quite a bit of money for the Young Judaean Library. Two dollars is being asked from each club and with this money books will be purchased and the names of the clubs inscribed thereon. Isaac Siegel recently contributed a book to the library and the latest contribution is a set of Ginsberg's Legends of the Jews. This was made by a friend of Young Judaea. For the information of our readers we wish to say that books in Hebrew, and Yiddish are as welcome as books in English.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1343.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The Young Judaean Library is being used primarily by the leaders and not by the children as seems to be the belief among some. Contributions will be welcome and will be properly acknowledged and young Judaea's friends are asked to help make the Young Judaean Library a place for the emanation of Jewish knowledge.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
