<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
wk. of <date when="1891-09-04">Sept. 4, 1891</date>. pp. 34-36.
<title level="a">[To Resume Regular Sunday Meetings]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1071</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1071.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
wk. of <date when="1891-09-04">Sept. 4, 1891</date>. pp. 34-36.
<title level="a">[TO RESUME REGULAR SUNDAY MEETINGS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday Sinai Congregation will, after the summer months vacation, resume its regular Sunday services. They are held this year in the new temple of the sister congregation at 33rd St. and Indiana. This fact is significant. It shows that narrow bigotry and raving fanaticism have no place in the Chicago Jewish community. The Jews of Chicago have recognized that there is room for all parties. The congregation that opens its temple to Sinai is certainly not among those who would be called radical. And still it is glad to open its' doors to the Jews who will come on Sunday to listen to a discourse and to participate in the religious exercises which precede and close the sermon. This is an object lesson in tolerance.</p>
   <p>Sinai Congregation has had, as we would call it, the good fortune, or as others might style it, the evil lot, to be from its very first day, a clear cut, radical body. The very name it carries is a symbol of its radicalism. It was called after the valiant periodical published in the interest of <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1072.jpg" n="2"/>radical reform by the late Dr. Einhorn, who loved to call himself a radical. Were Sinai the only Jewish congregation in this city, then there might be something of bigotry and narrowness in its attitude of uncompromising radicalism. But, as it is not, and as all other shades of religious opinion have founded their own institutions, we should not be critized for our liberal policies of Sinai.</p>
   <p>Whoever in Chicago wishes to worship on Saturday is not deprived of the opportunity. The closing of the Saturday services on the part of Sinai robbed no one in this community of the chance to observe, as he chose, the historic Sabbath. Visibly, the discontinuance of the Saturday service in Sinai left no mark. One who goes through the business streets of our city today will find on Saturday not one single store opened that was not open before Sinai, from want ot attandance, closed the doors of its temple on Saturday. The congregations of other temples have neither been diminished nor augmented by this step on our part. Sinai has coerced no one to forego his tastes.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1073.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It left to every individual the right to choose his religious affiliations and to order his religious life in accordance with his own convictions.</p>
   <p>The Sunday services in Chicago for many years were not, numerically considered, a success. Year after year, however, interest grew. The attendance became larger until today the present temple of Sinai is too small to accommodate the ever growing membership.</p>
   <p>Sinai Congregation is not dismayed either by the fact that again it largely stands alone among the congregations of the land. For even in Philadelphia, the Sunday movement has not the character it has among us. We are strong enough to stand alone.</p>
   <p>It is not true that Sinai lacks a true religious spirit. We own that we have little sympathy for emotionalism or ritualism. Whatever is done or spoken in Sinai Temple is for the purpose of realizing a fuller life, and <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1074.jpg" n="4"/>building a completer character.</p>
   <p>Sinai Congregation is not founded on Kaddish Judaism. It will not vest with sacred character the ancient form of making a book, and cannot understand the harm of substituting for the ancient form of handwritten scroll, the printed pages of modern make. This view has not come to us in recent years. As early as 1876 the pomp and pageantry which almost makes of the scroll a fatish, had been laid aside. And for all this, Sinai Congregation is a Jewish congregation.</p>
   <p>The foregoing views were expressed by Dr. Hirsch in the editorial notes.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
