<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-20">June 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Greatest Zionist Convention</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Eyes of All Jews Are on Cleveland, Where the Zionists Will Tackle Practical Plans for a Jewish Homeland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0144</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0144.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-06-20">June 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREATEST ZIONIST CONVENTION</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Eyes of All Jews Are on Cleveland, Where the Zionists Will Tackle Practical Plans for a Jewish Homeland</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The twenty-first convention of the Zionist organization of America will open on the twenty-third of June in the Soldiers and Sailors Memorial Hall in Pittsburgh, and will continue until the following Thursday evening. It will undoubtedly be one of the most extraordinary of all history-making assemblies. The purpose of this convention is to formulate plans for the development of the Jewish national homeland in Palestine. The realization of this homeland has been made possible by the declarations of England, France, Italy, and Greece in favor of such a project. This convention will mark the success of the twenty-year-old controversial issue which has encountered many difficulties and obstacles at every step, and in which the leading opposition was made up of many Jews all over the world; it will <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0145.jpg" n="2"/>mark the success and the transition of a movement of a handful of idealists into a program of political action with which the greatest world powers are reckoning, and which has become one of the aims of the Allies in this war.</p>
   <p>The Zionists have the official declaration of the European Allies upon which to lay the foundation of the Jewish homeland that is to be built in Palestine. The most important step has already been taken--the setting up of an administrative committee in Jerusalem, appointed by the English Government. The declaration of President Wilson says that one of America's war aims is to give autonomy to every one of the small nations. This will serve the Zionists as a guarantee that the Peace Congress will recognize the legality of their aspirations.</p>
   <p>When Dr. Herzl spoke of this project in his famous pamphlet, A Jewish State, he spoke of Palestine as a "model state", a state before which the best <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0146.jpg" n="3"/>examples of existing governments would have to hang their heads in shame. Herzl gazed far into the future, although he did not overlook or lose sight of the petty differences existing all over the world--yet in his "model state" petty differences had no place. This ideal has been kept and preserved in the throbbing hearts of the Zionists through two decades of strife. And now, when the long-cherished dream is being realized, let Palestine become the "model state" of which the great Herzl dreamed so ardently.</p>
   <p>We can say that the opposition to Zionism has entirely disappeared. All classes of Jews in every country, have taken up their stand in favor of this movement--Zionism; the extreme Orthodox, the radical, the Reformed religious groups have all gathered closely together and are working together for the great cause. During the last few months, the big Jewish unions have adopted resolutions favoring a Jewish homeland in Palestine, nor were they the first to do so. Similar resolutions had been adopted earlier by the International <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0147.jpg" n="4"/>Socialists, the British Labor Party, and the American Federation of Labor. The big Jewish fraternal orders, one after another, took their stand in favor of the Zionist movement, and many have even joined the Zionist organization as a group. A large campaign has just been completed. And now, in addition to the fifty thousand regular members of the Zionist societies, and the fifty-six thousand members of the Independent Order B'nai Brith, there are one hundred thousand new dues-paying members of the Zionist Organization of America.</p>
   <p>The most interesting days of the convention will be Monday and Tuesday, June 24 and 25. Then the delegates who represent the different Zionist groups within the movement will gather at a joint meeting to discuss the problems pertaining to Palestine.</p>
   <p>The Monday evening session will be opened and addressed by Dr. Stephen S. Wise, chairman of the Provisional Zion Committee; Mr. Jacob De Haas, secretary of <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0148.jpg" n="5"/>the same committee, will deal with the Palestinian program as a whole. Professor Felix Frankfurter, administrator of the United States war and labor activities, will deal with the political and legal principles of the Jewish homeland. Dr. N. I. Stone, federal statistician from Boston, will discuss the economic foundation of the Jewish homeland.</p>
   <p>At the Tuesday night session, the discussion of the Palestinian program will be continued. Mr. S. Joseph Faelz, the single-tax leader will deal with the land question; Professor Harris Collen will speak on the nationalization of the land, natural resources, and public utilities; Mr. Bernard A. Rosenblatt, of New York, will discuss a plan regarding land taxes and Jewish labor in Palestine. Dr. Shmarya Levin will speak on the Hebrew University, and Rabbi Meyer Berlin will talk on the question of religious upbringing.</p>
   <p>Dr. Harry Friedenwald will be chairman of the opening session. At this session Judge Julian W. Mack will introduce a resolution expressing the loyalty <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0149.jpg" n="6"/>of the Zionists to America and the Allies. This resolution will be seconded by Dr. Stephen Wise. Sunday evening a mass meeting will be held at which only Hebrew will be spoken--the language of the Prophets, the language of our past and the language of our future. Rueben Brainen will preside; Dr. Shmarya Levin and Dr. Ben-Zion Mossinson will speak.</p>
   <p>Monday's program will consist of group sessions; there will be the sub-convention of the Hadassah, a conference of the Jewish Legion, which will be conducted by Major Bruson White of the English-Canadian Recruiting Mission, and also a conference concerning a new organizational plan for the movement in America.</p>
   <p>Tuesday's sessions will be devoted to the reports of the various Zionist newspapers and the leaders of the various departments, especially of the departments on organization and propaganda. The National Fund Bureau will give a report at this session. Hadassah will also hold its subconvention <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0150.jpg" n="7"/>on Tuesday, when the budget and the new constitution will be taken under consideration. Afterwards, the nomination and election of officers will take place. Wednesday night a great demonstration will be staged in the Syrian Mosque; all the important Zionist speakers will address this meeting. Thursday, after the results of the elections are given, the convention will close to enable the Provisional Zion Committee to hold its session.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
