<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1893-08-28">Aug. 28, 1893</date>, 2:7.
<title level="a">Jews Are the First</title><title level="a" type="sub">Their Ancient Church Opens the Religious Congresses</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1056</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1056.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1893-08-28">Aug. 28, 1893</date>, 2:7.
<title level="a">JEWS ARE THE FIRST</title><title level="a" type="sub">Their Ancient Church Opens The Religious Congresses</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A large audience of representative Jews gathered in Columbus Hall at the Art Palace yesterday to assist in the program of the Jewish Denominational Congress, the first of a series of religious congresses to be held here under the auspices of the World Congress Auxiliary. Mr. C. C. Bonney as President of the auxiliary occupied the chair of honor, while Dr. Emil G. Hirsch presided as chairman and introduced the speakers. The devine blessing was invoked by Rabbi J. L. Leucht of New Orleans. C. C. Bonney in making the address of welcome said:</p>
   <p>"The providence of the God of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, who created in his own image, and gave him from Sinai's glory-crowned summit the law of a righteous life, has so ordered the arrangements for the Religious Congresses to be held under the auspices of the World's Congress Auxiliary of the World's Columbian Exposition that without any plan to that end this congress of the Jewish Church is the first of the series. Thus the mother church from which all the Christian denominations trace their lineage, and which stands in the history of mankind as the especial exponent of august and triumphant theism, has been called upon to open the religious congresses of 1893."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1057.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Rabbi K. Kohler of New York then made an address on the "Synagogue and the Church," and their mutual relations with reference to their ethical teachings, which was an exhaustive paper on the relations of the Jewish church to humanity and Christianity, and many of his statements were liberally applauded.</p>
   <p>Rabbi L. Mayer of Pittsburgh opened the evening session with an invocation. Then Rabbi Isaac M. Wise of Cincinnati delivered an address upon the fundamental doctrines of Judaism, which was a profound paper.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Joseph Silverman of New York read a paper on "Popular Errors About the Jews." He said: "There is scarcely any truth save the false, or any right, but the wrong. One of the worst evils to befall a man or a people is to be misunderstood. To be robbed of our own identity, to have one's own words misquoted, was to suffer all the pangs of mortification. Those were not the greatest martyrs who died for any cause, but those who had lived and struggled against misrepresentation. The vilest vices and crimes have been credited to the Jews, while by a few they have at the same time been accredited with the highest virtues. The Shakespeare story of Shylock was untrue in every detail. The Jew in all history has never been known to exact his pound of flesh, and yet the entire world had accepted this Shakespearean <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1058.jpg" n="3"/>idea as a true portrayal and has applauded this abortion of character rather than that portrayed in 'Nathan the Wise.' All sorts of stories have been told about the Jews and the general public has accepted an erroneous idea of them. Speaking of the Jews as a particular race was an error. The Hebrew race from which they descended had been impregnated with the people of every race and every clime, until now they had no country, no flag, and nothing but their religion left. The land of their nativity or their adoption was their country. Its laws they obeyed, its government they loved, and its judicial decisions they observed, and they pledged their lives and honor to do so. If there was a remnant of exclusiveness in the Jew of to-day was he to blame? He did not create it. The isolation from without had now come to seem the law of their being. Fraternity was desired by the Jews, but they would not accept it as a matter of patronage, but only on the ground of equality. The ostracism of the Jews had not been on account of any fault, but from false logic, which imputed the sins of a few to the many and gave no credit at all to virtues like those of Montefiore or Baron Hirsch."</p>
   <p>He predicted that the Jews would be able, in spite of all this, to live down all misrepresentation, but said they would never abandon their religion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
