<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1909-01-16">January 16, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Brevities.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0972</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0972.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1909-01-16">January 16, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">BREVITIES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago has not seen in many a day such an outpouring as it did on Saturday last. Almost every orthodox synagogue on the West, North and South Sides had the opportunity to listen to an out-of-town rabbi who had been designated by the arrangement committee to bring to the different congregations the message of Zionism. The rabbis perfumed the air of Chicago with Zionistic fragrance, for each and every one aimed to impress his auditors with the message he delivered. Credit must begiven to the congregations who gave up their synagogues for the cause and came in abundant numbers to listen to the respective speakers. From the way the synagogues were filled it was evident that the people were yearning to quench their thirst. The speaker was impressed, when he saw the vast multitudes before him, that the people of the Windy City are not, after all, so indifferent to matters religious and the cause of Zionism as one who does not reside here would be inclined to presume.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0973.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It requires a little stirring, and we have no doubt that the people would follow the movement and through it Judaism would become much strengthened. There is an element in the city of Chicago that is willing to do what Judaism commands, but it is allowed to starve for the want of proper religious food. A young orthodox rabbi with positive convictions, able to speak the vernacular, would soon find a constituency that would rally around his standard, and such a man ought to be put in the new synagogue of the Hebrew Institute, and there is no doubt in our mind that with the genial Dr. Blaustein at the head and a rabbi to stand by his side, the West Side of Chicago would soon feel that there is a revival of Judaism and the interest of matters Jewish would soon be awakened that the new structure would rise from under the ruins. It is up to the people residing in the vicinity of the Hebrew Institute to bestir themselves and what they can do in that direction.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
