<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-01-04">Jan. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Zion Convention Steps Out for Jewish Congress.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0236</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0236.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-01-04">Jan. 4, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">ZION CONVENTION STEPS OUT FOR JEWISH CONGRESS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Zion Convention yesterday accomplished constructive work for the cause of Zion. Excellent reports of great work were given out by the country delegates in reference to their local activities for the cause of Zion.</p>
   <p>Amiable speeches were made at the gathering of the Knights of Zion Convention. Professor H. Collen of Wisconsin, Doctor Shmaryohu Levin and Mr. M. Abrams.</p>
   <p>Professor Collen, spoke on the planning of the Jewish Congress and showed the audience the importance of such a Congress for the Jewish nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0237.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Shmaryohu Levin, in his masterful speech, appealed for the Hebrew language. He pointed out the vital importance of Hebrew culture, appealing to the audience for their support of the cause. Mr. Abrams also appealed for the support of the Hebrew Journal Hasorn which will be published in the near future. He stated, that the main accomplishment of yesterday's convention, was the decision to hold the Jewish Congress.</p>
   <p>Judge Bergston, chairman of the Resolutions Committee, read a resolution which explained, that the convention of the Knights of Zion declared itself for a democratic Jewish Congress, with a donation of $50 to support the cause. The delegates have also donated $100 for the cause.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0238.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The meeting yesterday was held in the Egyptian Hall at the Hyde Park Masonic Temple, with Mr. Kaplan in the chair. Mr. Tictin greeted the convention in the name of the B'nai Zion and the Zion Literary Society. He pointed out the strength and tender feelings of the Zionist philosophy, with its influence in the Jewish homes on the West Side, and expressed the hope that still greater success will follow.</p>
   <p>Mr. Meyer Abrams, orator of the Executive Board, spoke out and made a strong appeal to assist in reviving the Hebrew language in America. He also showed that the Federation of American Zionists has planned the publication of a new Hebrew Journal Hasorn, with Dr. Levin, I. D. Berkovitz, and Dr. Mazamod as its editors, and he desires that the Zionist organizations should assist in this undertaking by buying $10 shares issued by the Federation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0239.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Dr. Levin said: "In Jewish life, the Holy Land, Palestine and the Hebrew language play important roles. These are the only threads which bind our Judaism together. A nation cannot exist without a language and without that, it must become extinct."</p>
   <p>The delegates and the guests were then transferred to another hall, where the ladies and the active members of the Englewood B'nai Zion, together with the Sifrus Zion organization, with the aid of J. Withal, the chairman of the hall, had arranged an excellent lunch with a very fine selected Carmel wine. The audience drank the Palestine Carmel wine to the health and good fortune of all Zion organizations.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0240.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Cantor Milkowsky sang a few Hebrew songs and the entire audience accompanied him. Judge Mack made a strong appeal for the support of the provisional Zionist fund and immediately after his speech approximately $6,000 was pledged and collected for the cause. Nearly every one present at the meeting and banquet, did his part in the way of donations. Special attention was given to Mr. Louis D. Brandeis and Dr. Levin, who sat together close to the toastmaster, Mr. Max Shulman. Mr. Brandeis was a little late in coming to the banquet, on account of a previous banquet, given in his honor by the Chicago Bar Association. He had to cut his speech short, so that he could catch a train at 12 o'clock for his home in Boston....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
