<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
            <date when="1909-10-03">October 3, 1909</date><title level="a">The Poale Zion is Taking Chicago Jews by Great Storm</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0268</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
            <date when="1909-10-03">October 3, 1909</date><title level="a">The Poale Zion is Taking Chicago Jews by Great Storm</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
  <p>Thousands of Chicago Jews came to greet the delegates of the fourth convention of the Poale Zion at the Hebrew Institute.</p>
  <p>The ball last night was a marvelous success byond all expectations. It was a real Jewish holiday, in honor of Poale Zion.</p>
  <p>These greetings of Poale Zion delegates were attended by all classes of Chicago's Jewry. Over 1,500 people participated in this Poale Zion Ball. The stage was decorated with the Jewish colors of white and blue. Zionist flags were fluttering all over the stage and hall. The great masterpiece, a photograph by Dr. Theodor Hertchel, was decorated with Zion flags. Rugs were on display which were hand-made in the art school. Many comrades of the central committee and invited guests from other cities were sitting on the stage. Among those other prominent Jews were such as Congressmen A.J. Sabath, Dr. George Shulman, Mr. Leon Zolothkof, P. Satil, Ph. P. Bregstone, I. Raisborg, M. Nevelov, Dr. N. Sirkin, Mr. A. Goldberg, and other personages.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0268.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Every seat in the hall was occupied by 7:30 o'clock, and by 8 o'clock the chairman of the arrangements committee had to order the doors closed for the evening. Promptly at 8 o'clock the introductions began. Mr. A. Goldberg and Dr. Sirkin were two of the first speakers. They spoke mostly on socialism and unionization, assuring the public that in union there is strength. Never before, in the history of any Jewish organization has such stormy applause been received.</p>
   <p>Congressman A. J. Sabath was the next speaker. As a Jewish congressman he spoke on the future of the Jewish nation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
