<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1908-06-13">June 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Congregational.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0974</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0974.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Jewish Standard</title>,
<date when="1908-06-13">June 13, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">CONGREGATIONAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anshe Dorem Beth Hamidrash Hagodol - 3434 Wabash Ave. Services daily in Hebrew. Sabbath school daily. Cantor J. A. Epstein officiating.</p>
   <p>Anshe Emeth - 349 Sedgwick St. Services, Sabbath and holidays, evening and morning, in Hebrew, German and English. School sessions weekly every morning. Rabbi S. H. Bauer conducting the services.</p>
   <p>Anshe Kanasses Israel - Clinton and Judd Sts. Services daily in Hebrew, Rabbi B. Bernstein and Cantor S. Soloweizig officiating.</p>
   <p>Anshe Mayriv - Indiana Ave. and 33rd St. Services Sabbath and holidays, in English. Sabbath school sessions weekly. Rabbi Tobias Schanfarber officiating.</p>
   <p>Beth E1 - 148 Crystal St. Services Sabbath and holidays, in English and German. Sabbath school session weekly. Rabbi Julius Rappaport officiating.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0975.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>B'nai Abraham - 507 S. Marshfield Ave. Services Sabbath, Sunday and holidays in Hebrew and English. School sessions weekly. Rabbi A. R. Levy officiating.</p>
   <p>B'nai David - 618 N. Wood St. Services daily in Hebrew.</p>
   <p>B'nai Sholem - 44th and St. Lawrence Ave. Services Sabbath and holiday mornings in English. Rabbi Gerson B. Levy officiating.</p>
   <p>Chicago Sinai Congregation - 21st and Indiana Ave. Services Sunday in English. School session weekly. Rabbi Emil G. Hirsch officiating.</p>
   <p>Doresh Tov - 42 Tell Place. Services in Hebrew daily. Cantor M. Alpert officiating.</p>
   <p>Emanuel - Buckingham Place and Halsted. Services Sabbath and holidays in English and German. Rabbi Leo S. Mannheimer officiating.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0976.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>First Hungarian - Polk and Marchfield. Services in Hebrew and German on Sabbath and holidays. Gabbi M. Fischer officiating.</p>
   <p>Galician Aus. Congregation - Tell Place. Ashland Ave. Services daily in Hebrew.</p>
   <p>Isaiah Temple - 4501 Vincennes Ave. Services Sabbath, holidays and Sunday mornings in Hebrew and English. School sessions weekly. Rabbi Joseph Stolz officiating.</p>
   <p>Moses Montefiore - Robey and Thomas Sts. Services Sabbath and holidays, evening and morning. Rabbi Julius Newman officiating.</p>
   <p>N. Chicago Hebrew Congregation - Goethe and La Salle Ave. Services Sabbath and holidays, evening and morning, in Hebrew and English. Rabbi Abram officiating.</p>
   <p>Oheb Zedek - Claremont and Division Sts. Services daily. Cantor Newman officiating.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0977.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Rodfei Zedek - 48th, between Wabash and Michigan Ave. Services daily, Cantor M. Borenstein officiating.</p>
   <p>S. S. Hebrew Congregation - 3433 Indiana Ave. Services Sabbath and holidays, evening and morning, in Hebrew and English. Rabbi A. B. Yudelson conducting the service.</p>
   <p>Zion Congregation - Ogden Ave. and Washington Blvd. Services Sabbath and holidays, evening and morning. Rabbi Jacob S. Jacobson officiating.</p>
   <p>Thephirith Zion - 586-88 N. Lincoln St. Services daily in Hebrew.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
