<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-01-02">January 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Knights of Zion Opened Their 17Th Annual Convention Yesterday.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0252</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0252.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-01-02">January 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE KNIGHTS OF ZION OPENED THEIR 17TH ANNUAL CONVENTION YESTERDAY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday at one p. m. the doors of the large hall of the Chicago Hebrew Institute was thrown open to the two hundred delegates and a large visiting audience which filled the large hall and the balcony.</p>
   <p>Among the speakers were Rabbi Berlin and Mr. Barondes who were highly applauded after their speeches.</p>
   <p>With great enthusiasm the audience listened to the reports of the past year's activities.</p>
   <p>On the platform sat all the Chicago rabbis and well known social workers, among them Mr. Philip Seman, the superintendent of the Chicago Hebrew Institute, who welcomed the delegates in the name of the Institute.....</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0253.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The independent nationalistic sentiment is growing among the Jewish masses who are being urged to arouse themselves to national consciousness and become a nation again equal with all other nations and to cease to be a wanderer among the nations by turning back to his own land.</p>
   <p>The grandmaster then called on the secretary of the Mizrachi, Rabbi Berlin, who was greeted with thundering applause. He spoke of the present Jewish situation, the general condition of the Zionist movement, and as the leader of the Mizrachi movement in America he indirectly pointed out the aims and the principles of this orthodox Zionist alliance. He also pointed out that the sooner Zionism will take to more practical work in Palestine, the sooner this sacred ideal will be materialized.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0254.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After the secretary's report on the past activities of the order the treasurer reported on the financial conditions. Mr. Schulman, the grandmaster, started reading telegrams and letters of prominent men of the Zionist movement such as from the young Straus, in the name of his father, the well known social worker and lover of Zion, Nathan Straus; a second letter from the famous Boston lawyer and Zionist, Louis Brandeis, and one from Professor Boris Shatz of the Bezalel Art School in Palestine, who is now in New York.</p>
   <p>The question then arose as to the language to be taught in Palestine, and it was unanimously agreed that Hebrew shall be the language.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0255.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Last night a large audience gathered at the West Side Masonic Temple at the banquet of the Order Knights of Zion given in honor of the delegates and guests.</p>
   <p>After they were through with the palatable meal they started with the spiritual part of the banquet. Good speakers were heard, the enthusiastic audience pledged large donations toward the Jewish edifice being built in Palestine.</p>
   <p>Mr. Schulman, the toastmaster, introduced the new grandmaster who briefly pointed out the necessity for this great gathering and mentioned the progress of the past year made by the Order, the Knights of Zion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0256.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Then Philip Bregstone, Judge Fisher, Dr. and Mrs. Levinson, in the name of the Hadassah Chapter, spoke.</p>
   <p>Mr. Baronet, the last speaker made an appeal and money and checks came in large sums from all sides. Baronet then declared the convention adjourned and every one went home happy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
