<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-11-01">November 1, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Reform Judaism.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0391</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0391.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-11-01">November 1, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">REFORM JUDAISM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Technically speaking, Reform Judaism is only a little over one-hundred years old. It began in Germany, and while it has spread to various parts of the world, it has attained its greatest potency in the United States.</p>
   <p>Reform Judaism was the logical and psychological result of definite historic causes. It was the product of modernism. The growth and development of scientific research succeeded scholasticism and obscurantism. Accurate observation and logical analysis took the place of superstitious beliefs and practices. In the political world, democracy drove out the despotism of kings and emperors, while in the economic world, metropolitan industrialism with its complexity and greater freedom came into its own. The invention of the steam engine and the telegraph made for less isolation and parochialism. Education became widespread with the improvement of the printing press.</p>
   <p>In such a world, tolerance was bound to grow and the Jew was regarded in a better light. I say this despite the fact that some will remind me of the vast amount of <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0392.jpg" n="2"/>intolerance that still exists in the world. The fact remains that as unfortunate as this may be, the Jew is in the main better off than he was in the past and the proportion of thinking and humane Gentiles is increasing year by year. Everything must be judged comparitively.</p>
   <p>In such a world Ghetto standards were compelled to give way to modern thinking and living. Mendelssohn's translation of the Pentateuch into German marked the beginning of the decline of Yiddish in Central Europe. Greater freedom and recognition endowed the Jew with the ambition to become more like his neighbor. Secular education caused him to challenge some of the beliefs and practices that had been handed down unquestioned through the centuries. Incidentally, some of them were not Jewish in their origin, but had been grafted upon Jewish culture by unconscious imitation of the nations amid whom the Jews lived, and had become so much a part of their own life and practice that their origins were forgotten and they came to be looked upon as sacred.</p>
   <p>When one considers the rapidity with which conditions affecting the political, cultural, and economic life of our people changed, it is little wonder that in the period of transition some mistakes were made. Revolution is never as wholesome as evolution. Chaos is ofttimes the result of suddenly changing historic <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0393.jpg" n="3"/>circumstances.</p>
   <p>Many Jews became assimilationists. This was not the fault of Reform Judaism. It had no place in the philosophy of the movement. Reform itself, possibly ran to extremes here and there. It unconsciously imitated Protestantism and removed from Jewish life a certain amount of the traditional element that should have been retained. This, of course, was most natural and the hostility and opposition of the orthodox rabbis, a perfectly natural and justifiable position from their point of view, probably encouraged the early reformers to assume extreme positions.</p>
   <p>Be this as it may, Reform had to suffer. Judaism was confronted with the choice of standing still and rotting, or going forward. The children would not live like the great grandparents. Reform Judaism made it possible for the modern Jew to remain loyal and faithful to the basic teaching and practices of Judaism,without at the same teime, forfeiting his intellectual self-respect, or causing him to appear like an Oriental or a medieval person. Little wonder that Judaism is more alive in this country today than it is in Europe, or any part of the world. This is an undisputed fact that will be substantiated by an impartial traveler, who has taken the trouble to observe Jewish conditions abroad.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0394.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We began this article by stating that technically, Reform Judaism is a little over one-hundred years old. The fact is, as every student of the Jewish religion well knows, that Reform Judaism began when Judaism first saw the light of this world. Judaism itself, is the product of revolution. The prophets reshaped early pagan Hebraic beliefs. They rid Hebrew life and thought of many primitive and crude beliefs and practices. They altered the entire God conception. They emphasized the ethical note in religion and lifted it to new heights.</p>
   <p>After the exile, Ezra, the scribe, and his associates made many changes. This was the period, in fact, when Judaism first saw the light of day. Ezra's attitude and that of those who surrounded him were more conventional and formal than that of the prophets. They combined the ethical with the ceremonial and brought about a harmonious blending of the two, essential and suitable for their own day and age.</p>
   <p>The sages quoted in the Talmud, and their successors made other changes. They modified the laws to meet new conditions. These scholars were not theorists. They were practical sensible men. They kept Judaism in line with common sense.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0395.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>They too harmonized it with the conditions of their own day and age.</p>
   <p>The Jewish philosophers of the Middle Ages challenged many an old belief and on the other hand attempted to synthesize Judaism with the thinking of the Middle Ages. Some of them did it with great dilicacy, others more boldly. Some were bitterly criticized by their more conservative contemporaries; others were commended. Most of them were criticized in certain quarters and praised in others.</p>
   <p>Ghetto Judaism of the last few hundred years had its poetic and colorful side, but it did not represent the purest flowering of the Jewish spirit. It must be admired in the light of martyrdom and sacrifices of our people, the cruelties they endured, the many handicaps set in their way. But Ghetto life was cramping and narrowing. Without freedom, constantly trembling for his safety, the Jew could not be at his best. Deprived of secular education and cut off from the main currents of world thought, his thinking like his activities were cramped and crude.</p>
   <p>All credit to him for his courage, faith and loyalty. These are no mean virtues. They in themselves prove the value of faith that can beget them and that lived despite everything designed to crush it. But we repeat, Judaism in the <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0396.jpg" n="6"/>Ghetto was more picturesque than ideal. Poor human beings struggling hard to make a bare living and in constant fear of their lives and those of their children can not but fall back upon a certain measure of superstition and primitive practice. The more honor and credit to them for whatever standards of excellenct they were capable of maintaining.</p>
   <p>But the hands of the clock cannot be held back, and so when the light of modern civilization percolated into the Ghetto, it was the beginning of a new point of view for the Jew. Blinded by the rays of the sun he was dazed and could barely see a few paces ahead of him. He staggered and groped for a clear vision. Hence the defects in his life and religious practices immediately following the exodus from the medievalism and persecution. Reform Judaism in its modern form has done very well considering its youth and the circumstances of its origin. It need make no apoligies to anyone. It has been the only salvation for our people who would retain their Jewishness and at the same time live like Occidentals. I predict a future that will fully justify the cisions of Hirsch, Geiger, Einhorn, and Isaac M. Wise. Some changes, of course, will have to be made. I for one, feel that more of mysticism and traditionalism properly practiced and interpreted will do us no harm. Reform Judaism must become less negative <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0397.jpg" n="7"/>and more positive. It is not an excuse to doff the garments of Jewishness at the will and whim of every person. It requires more of discipline and should impose more obligations if it is to command the respect of its followers. These and other changes will take place from time to time, but fundamentally, it is right. Life must move on. Religion, like every other expression of human thought and feeling, must progress, and Judaism is not afraid to progress.</p>
   <p>Judaism does not fear modern science nor the attempt to persecute those who contribute to the wealth of human knowledge. "We welcome all truth, whether shining through the annals of ancient revelations or reaching us through the seers of our own time." (One of the loveliest passages of our Union Prayer Book.) Judaism has stood the onslaughts of every age and clime. It is like a rock, beaten by the waves through countless centuries, yet, unmoved and eternal. Its foundations are secure. It is like one of the giant sequoias of California - old and yet ever renewing its youth, whose foliage changes with the passing years, yet it stands there firmly rooted to the ground, never to be broken or uprooted by the storms or blasts of the elements. And like the giant sequoias it is beautiful to behold, and points ever upward, toward God and the light.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
