<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-08-17">August 17, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">An Outstanding Year for Chicago Avukah.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1357</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1357.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-08-17">August 17, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">AN OUTSTANDING YEAR FOR CHICAGO AVUKAH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The year 1927-1928 promises to be a year of outstanding achievements for Chicago Avukah. Under the leadership of its president, S. William Halperin, an intensive education and practical program is being worked out. A marked improvement has been shown in the calibre of the material presented at the bi-weekly discussion meetings at the Hadassah Clubroom, where carefully prepared papers by various members of the organization are read and discussed. A new feature of Avukah work has been the organization of a Hebrew class for beginners under the direction of Mr. Chizuk, who with Mr. Simon Agranat, the chairman of the Discussion Group, deserve the hearty commendation of the organization for their excellent work.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1358.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Arthur Goldberg and Mr. Harry Iseberg, our debating managers, are both hard at work making preparations for an active year. Miss Ruth Fish, at present serving as temporary corresponding secretary in the absence of Miss Jeannette Rubin, is actively endeavoring to organize an Avukah weekly seminar under the leadership of a widely known scholar in Jewish philosophy and history. Mr. Hymen Smoler, last year's president and one of our most active members, is busy working out plans for the presentation of an Avukah cultural forum. Mr. George Fisher, one of the hardest-working and reliable workers in Avukah, heads a committee to complete preparation for an excellent series of Sunday monthly meetings.</p>
   <p>In addition to these excellent co-workers, Mr. Halperin has to aid him group of faithful and devoted officers and Executive Committee members. With such cooperation and enthusiasm the year should be one of unparalleled success in every way.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
