<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-25">Feb. 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">American Jews' Participation in the War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1204</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1204.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-25">Feb. 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN JEWS' PARTICIPATION IN THE WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to a recently published report which was compiled by a Jewish committee in New York, American Jews furnished more than their allotted quota of the armed forces of the United States during the late war. Although the report is not complete, it establishes that 165,000 to 200,000 Jews served in the army or navy, and constituted four to five per cent of the American armed forces when the Armistice was signed. Since not more than three per cent of America's population is Jewish, American Jewry contributed at least one third more than the number expected from it. This surplus is attributable to the fact that 40,000 sons of Israel volunteered. According to present records, 5,162 Jews served in the army, 206 in the navy, and 40 in the marine corps. [Translator's note: There is a wide discrepancy between the figures given in this sentence and those quoted above. And there is no explanation for the discrepancy. Perhaps a part of the article has been <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1205.jpg" n="2"/>omitted.] The highest rank attained by a Jew is that of a brigadier general in the army and in the marine corps, and that of a rear admiral in the navy. Although only sixty-two percent of the whole armed force of the United States was in the fighting ranks, seventy-two percent of the Jews enrolled as combatants fought in battles. Casualties among Jews numbered about ten thousand, of whom two thousand fell on the field of battle. The courage of the Jews is attested to by the many honorable citations, which record acts of extraordinary bravery, and by the testimony of commanding officers like General Bell, Lieutenant Colonel Whitelsey, and Captain Harrigin.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
