<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-08">Feb. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. H. J. Moss New Superintendent of Maimonedes Hospital</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0904</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0904.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-02-08">Feb. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">DR. H. J. MOSS NEW SUPERINTENDENT OF MAIMONEDES HOSPITAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last evening, at a reorganization meeting in Maimonedes Hospital of the House and Medical Committees, a new superintendent was appointed, who will soon take over the management of the only Kosher hospital in Chicago.</p>
   <p>A committee consisting of Judge Fisher, I. Lurie, and S. J. Rosenblatt, which was sent to New York to find a suitable doctor for this position, recommended Dr. H. J. Moss, assistant superintendent of the Mt. Sinai Hospital in New York. The regular meeting of the hospital, after a lengthy discussion of the activities and qualifications of Dr. H. J. Moss, unanimously approved the recommendation.</p>
   <p>Dr. H. J. Moss, the new superintendent of the Maimonedes Hospital, who is 31 years old,-young in years but aged in experience,-is a Russian Jew of distinction as a physician and executive.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0905.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>After graduating in 1905 from the Jefferson Medical College of Philadelphia, he became assistant superintendent of Mt. Sinai Hospital in New York, under the noted physician Dr. Goldwater, a position which he held for five years. Recently, when Dr. Goldwater was appointed Health Commissioner of New York, Dr. Moss was appointed acting superintendent of this great Jewish hospital.</p>
   <p>In time he gained a good name and was highly praised by the most prominent doctors of New York, who recommended him as the most suitable superintendent for the Maimonedes Hospital. He is an unusual fine man, and his outstanding characteristic is his great knowledge in the medical profession.</p>
   <p>He is also one of those great doctors who do not want to forget the Jewish language, which is so important for a head doctor in a Jewish hospital.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
