<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-09">May 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Work or Go Under</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0489</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0489.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-09">May 9, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">WORK OR GO UNDER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Reform Jews in this country surpass the Orthodox Jews in one respect--organization. When they organize a movement, it is well organized and is productive of results. When they undertake to do something, they do it. When they have a certain definite plan to carry out, they carry it out, and the work as a rule is well done. It is not the theology and not the metaphysics and not the religious conception of the Jews which makes Reform Judaism in this country a success, but it is their organizing ability and the earnestness of purpose of the Reform Jew. Reform Judaism as an organized group is in the ascendancy because the Reform Jew takes his duty seriously. He feels his responsibility and he acts in a responsible manner. Unfortunately, most of the so-called Orthodox Jews are not that way. They are often animated by noble desires and often have great plans, but they very seldom translate their ideas <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0490.jpg" n="2"/>into actions, and when they do undertake to carry out a certain plan, they very seldom do it successfully because they are poor in organization. There are in Chicago a number of well-to-do and thoroughly Americanized Orthodox Jews and altogether they represent a very fine type of humanity, but acting as a group they are a negligible factor in our communal life. For every dollar they raise for communal and public Jewish affairs, the Reform Jews raise one hundred dollars, although they are financially well situated and could, as a group, do much more than they are doing.</p>
   <p>The Reform Jews, for instance, have now undertaken to raise two and a half million dollars, and they will raise it. The Keren Hayesod [exchequer of the World Zionist Organization] people in Chicago have undertaken to raise a quarter of a million dollars and they did not raise it. They may raise it during the year, and the chances are that they will get that amount together before the year is over, but they could have raised it in one week if they had a perfected organization and if they were as responsible to their leaders <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0491.jpg" n="3"/>as the people of the other camp are responsible to theirs. The Orthodox Jewish community of Chicago is in the process of development and it needs one million dollars in cash to complete several institutions and to develop communal life. It is our conviction that they could raise the money among themselves, but they will not do it because their sense of organization is underdeveloped and they do not take public affairs as seriously as do the Reform Jews.</p>
   <p>The Orthodox Jew in America is so situated that unless he works for his position, unless he makes an effort to hold his own, he will certainly perish. The Orthodox Jews in America must work out their own salvation or go under. They must either place their institutions on a solid basis or they will be obliterated as a group in a very short while. They must either provide their children with good educational facilities or they must live to see the rise of a generation blissfully ignorant of Judaism, and a generation ignorant of Judaism cannot be a blessing to the Orthodox Jewish community, and cannot be a blessing to <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0492.jpg" n="4"/>any Jewish community. The Orthodox educational institutions all over America are underdeveloped. They are poorly financed and in many respects also poorly organized, and Orthodox communal life in America is not sound because it is not properly organized, and unless the Orthodox Jew perfects his organization and places his community on a sound basis, there is no future at all for Orthodoxy in America. We therefore can only say to the Orthodox: Work or go under. He must be told day in and day out that unless he makes a special effort to place the community in which he lives and of which he is a member on a solid basis, solid from an organization point of view, solid from an educational point of view, and solid from a spirtual point of view, it is hard to see how Orthodoxy can survive. Before we look around, the Orthodox traditions will be broken and destroyed and the children will be neither Orthodox nor Reform, and the future generation will be expressionless and colorless and can only be led by the power of inertia, a very poor agency indeed to regulate Jewish life.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0493.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>We have made in Chicago a beginning with the establishment of an Orthodox Jewish community. Most of the principal synagogues have united for the sake of establishing a strong Orthodox community, and it is up to the presidents of the synagogues to continue the work until it is completed. But unfortunately they have taken their task very lightly and little progress has been made during the last year. While Reform Judaism in Chicago is going from strength to strength, as far as organization is concerned, Orthodox Judaism is not making any headway in that respect, and it stands to reason that the constant rise of Reform Judaism means the permanent weakening of Orthodox Judaism. The rise of one is at the expense of the other, and when the one camp makes progress and the other does not, one can just figure out when it will be obliterated altogether. We wonder whether the Orthodox rabbis in Chicago and the presidents of the Orthodox synagogues really believe that they can go on forever that way or whether they are not aware of all the dangers to which Orthodox Judaism is exposed, in case the leaders of the <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0494.jpg" n="6"/>community do not work for its welfare and for its perpetuation. We deem it our duty to tell the leaders of the Orthodox community of Chicago again and again that they must work or they will see the community perish, and the only way not only to save the Orthodox Jewish community but to perpetuate it, is to work for it, to work hard, to take the work seriously, to feel the responsibility, to carry the responsibility willingly, and to be as devoted to the cause of Orthodoxy as the Reformers are devoted to their cause. Only then will the Orthodox Jews in Chicago save what there is still to be saved and place the Orthodox community on a strong and solid basis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
