<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-15">Sept. 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Something New in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0882</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0882.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-09-15">Sept. 15, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">SOMETHING NEW IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An Orthodox Jewish congregation has undertaken to provide its rabbi with old-age security, and for this purpose, it is raising a fund of twenty-five thousand dollars! Isn't this surprising? The Jews in Philadelphia are doing this in honor of their venerable and aged rabbi, Rabbi D. B. Leventhal, who has occupied the pulpit of their congregation for the past twenty-five years.</p>
   <p>It is said that a movement toward this end is now on foot. So far as we know, this is the first instance where Orthodox Jews have launched such a campaign.</p>
   <p>This has been done for a long time by our Reformed brothers, but they do not designate it a "movement". Among Reformed Jews, the president meets with the trustees and other officers of the congregation, and they make out a list of contributors and the amount each is to contribute. When the required sum is collected, they send the rabbi a check. At times this is done with <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0883.jpg" n="2"/>pomp, and at other times, no ceremony at all takes place.</p>
   <p>In Chicago, the sisterhood of a temple presented their rabbi with an expensive automobile not so long ago, and immediately afterwards, the congregation raised his salary so that he could hire a chauffeur and keep the automobile in good condition.</p>
   <p>Such incidents are rather new among us in Chicago. Nevertheless, it is a good beginning. We congratulate the Philadelphia Jews for paving the way. This is a noteworthy example. However, we know of only a few rabbis in America who deserves the recognition accorded Rabbi Leventhal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
