<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-01-15">Jan. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Plan for Orthodox Jewish Kehilah in Chicago Adopted</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0805</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0805.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-01-15">Jan. 15, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">PLAN FOR ORTHODOX JEWISH KEHILAH IN CHICAGO ADOPTED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of rabbis, presidents of synagogues, and prominent civic leaders was held yesterday evening at the Grenshaw Street Talmud Torah. The plans for a united Jewish orthodox Kehilah, formulated by the various committees, were considered.</p>
   <p>Here are the accepted plans as to the aims and tasks of the Kehilah which were drawn up by the Plan and Scope Committee; The aim of the Kehilah is:</p>
   <p>a) To organize, unite and strengthen all forces which serve, support and represent traditional Judaism in Chicago and the vicinity.</p>
   <p>b) To establish, support and maintain educational, religious, philanthropic, social, economic and other Jewish national institutions which serve the orthodox community of Chicago.</p>
   <p>c) To delegate representatives in all institutions and to participate in all Jewish activities.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0806.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>d) To adhere to the fundamental principles of Judaism, such as the observance of the Sabbath, holidays, dietary food laws, etc.; to acquaint the Jewish population, from time to time, in written and spoken manner, with all Jewish problems and questions concerning Jewish life, with the object of solving them in a true Jewish traditional spirit.</p>
   <p>In order to carry out the above-mentioned plans we recommend the election of the following committees:</p>
   <p>1) An educational committee, whose duty it shall be to formulate an educational program for all Jewish educational institutions and to strengthen the cultural and financial condition of the Talmud Torahs in Chicago.</p>
   <p>2) A committee to supervise kashruth (dietary laws).</p>
   <p>3) A committee which shall find means to make possible the observance of the Sabbath and holidays in the industrial and commercial establishments.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0807.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We recommend that the organization shall keep a permanent Pinkus (memorandum book) in the old traditional style where all the events of the Kehilah shall be recorded; also that an archive shall be maintained for the preservation of copies of everything that the organization may publish for the purpose of having historical data of the Kehilah's achievement at hand when necessary.</p>
   <p>Paragraph "C" deals with the establishment of a Beth Din (Jewish religious court). This problem was placed in the hands of the rabbis to work out and to formulate a plan for the organization of a Beth Din.</p>
   <p>All plans of the organizational committee concerning the form of election of delegates to the initial meeting and of officers and directors, were adopted.</p>
   <p>It was decided that the separate meetings of the synagogues, at which the adopted plans will be ratified and delegates elected to the initial meeting, should take place on Sunday, February first and the initial meeting of all chosen delegates should follow on Sunday, February fifteenth. [Editor's note: Kehilah is the Hebrew name given to the Jewish community of any given city.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
