<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1894-09-08">September 8, 1894</date>. pp.38-40.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1043</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1043.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1894-09-08">September 8, 1894</date>. pp.38-40.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From a paper read by Dr. Felsenthal before the American Jewish Historical Society.</p>
   <p>"I desire to give here only a few contributions to the work of a future historian of Chicago Judaism. My statements rest partly upon information which I gathered from some of the earliest Jewish immigrants who had settled here, and partly upon my own personal observations and experiences. Living in Chicago since April, 1858, I am in a position to speak as an eye witness in regard to many things and happenings during the past thirty-five years.</p>
   <p>It is very likely that some single Jewish individuals settled in Chicago, or attempted to settle here, between 1830 and 1840, for, in this decade, large numbers of German Jews had come to America, expecting to find here not only better prospects in their various pursuits of life, but also a refuge from the oppressive laws under which the Jews suffered at that time in the old fatherland.</p>
   <p>The first considerable migration of Jews to Chicago, or, to be more exact, to <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1044.jpg" n="2"/>After the Illinois and Michigan Canal and the railroad from Chicago to Elgin had been completed, Chicago became quite a center of attraction for people inclined to trade, and Jewish families in large numbers came to make it their home. Two Jewish families had been residing here in the city previous to this time, and one of them, Mr. Benedict Schubert, had become quite wealthy. It was he who built the first brick house in Chicago. He had been a tailor by trade, and he was very poor when he came to live in the town, but by his industry, he soon acquired sufficient means, and became in his day, the only prominent merchant-tailor in Chicago.</p>
   <p>Mr. Meyer, spoken of before, after becoming advanced in years, and being without grown children old enough to be of help to him, was among those who came to Chicago to live. He had sold his farm and had invested all his funds in Chicago real estate. As a far-seeing man of sound judgment in such matters, he advised all his friends to do the same. By many he was looked upon as eccentric. However, the result proved that he was right.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1045.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Chicago had meanwhile become widely known, especially since it was rumored that it would be a great railroad center, and many Israelites were induced to select this place as their home. Among the first who at that time came to Chicago were the brothers Kohn, Levi Rosenfeld, Jacob Rosenberg, the brothers Rubel, the brothers Greenebaum, Samuel Cole, Mayer Klein, M. M. Gerstley, Fuller, Weineman, Brunneman, Clayburgh, Weigselbaum, Ziegler, etc.</p>
   <p>We now proceed to speak of the origin of the Jewish religious organizations in Chicago. The first time the Chicago Jews entered into a religious organization was in 1845, and the first public act, by which they demonstrated their existence as a body, was the purchase from the city of a plot of ground for a cemetery. This old Jewish cemetery was abandoned in 1856. The city had become so extensive that the cemetery was within the city limits. Not long after this cemetery had been acquired, the society which owned it organized into a regular congregation. This was the first Jewish congregation in Chicago, and very likely of the whole Northwest. It was chartered in 1874 under the name Kehillath Anshe Maarabh (Congregation of the Men of the West). Its first services were held in a hall of an old frame building on the southwest corner of Lake and South Wells street, and Ignaz Kunreuther was its first minister.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1046.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>After the congregation had become strong enough financially, they leased a lot on Clark street, between Quincy and Jackson streets, upon which they erected a synagogue. At the expiration of that lease, they bought a lot on the northeast corner of Adams and Wells streets, where they built another synagogue. Here they remained for several years, until the house became too small for the congregation. Then they sold this property and bought a church on the corner of Peck Court and Wabash avenue, where they remained until the building was destroyed by the great fire in 1871. Afterwards they purchased a church on the corner of Twenty-sixth street and Indiana avenue, and after this building, too had become insufficient for the growing congregation, a new and splendid synagogue was erected on the corner of Indiana avenue and Thirty-third street.</p>
   <p>Not exactly a congregation, but a society of a semi-religious character was also instituted at an early date by a number of young Israelites in Chicago, under the name of The Hebrew Benevolent Society. In its flourishing days, it did a great deal of good in the field of charity. It purchased three acres of <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1047.jpg" n="5"/>ground in the town of Lake View (a little south of Graceland Cemetery) and laid it out as a cemetery.</p>
   <p>Later, other charitable societies came into existence and superseded the old Hebrew Benevolent Society. Nominally, however, it still exists, but merely as a burial association.</p>
   <p>A second Jewish congregation was established in 1851 by a number of Israelites, mainly from the eastern provinces of Prussia, to which the founders gave the name Kehillath Bene Sholom (Congregation of the Sons of Peace). This congregation first rented a hall in a building on the southwest corner of Dearborn and Washington streets. Afterwards they occupied a hall in a building on Clark street near Jackson street, and in 1864 they dedicated their new synagogue on Harrison street near Fourth avenue. On October 9, 1871, it fell a prey to the great fire. The congregation suffered greatly by the fire, but, within a few years, it rallied again and erected a new house of worship on Michigan avenue between Fourteenth and Sixteenth streets. In 1891 the congregation sold this synagogue, and purchased from the Kehillath Anshe Maarabh the synagogue on the <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1048.jpg" n="6"/>corner of Twenty-sixth and Indiana avenue, which it still occupies.</p>
   <p>The third Jewish congregation which was founded in Chicago is the Sinai Congregation. Its first meeting for devotional purposes was held June 21, 1861, in an edifice situated on Monroe street, between Clark and La Salle streets. Here the congregation continued to worship until April, 1865, at which time they consecrated their new temple on the northwest corner of Van Buren street and Third avenue. The fire of 1871 reduced this temple to ashes. The congregation was then without a meeting-house of its own for several years, but in April, 1876, the members dedicated their new temple on the southwest corner of Twenty-first street and Indiana avenue, an imposing structure, which they still occupy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
