<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-19">June 19, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Sinai Congregation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1145</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1145.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-19">June 19, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO SINAI CONGREGATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>....Rabbi [Kaufman] Kohler of the Chicago Sinai Congregation has tendered his resignation; he has been the rabbi of the congregation since September, 1872. He has accepted an offer to become affiliated with the Congregation Bethel in New York, and, therefore, he intends to sever his connections here on August 30. His letter of resignation was not made public at the time [it was offered], and reporters inquiring into the matter were told by Rabbi Kohler that his chief reason for resigning was the lack of interest shown by the community [in religious matters].</p>
   <p>Since 1874 the Chicago Sinai Congregation has offered Saturday and Sunday services in the hope of attracting the younger element, but it has proved as useless an attempt as the building of the magnificent synagogue was, and has served only to burden the Congregation with a tremendous debt.</p>
   <p>The position in New York has been held for eighteen years by Rabbi Einhorn, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1146.jpg" n="2"/>father-in-law of Rabbi Kohler, and when the latter was offered the pulpit there, he accepted, since he had given up hope of a religious revival in the Chicago district.</p>
   <p>The practice of Sunday services actually split the [Jewish] community, and Rabbi Kohler hopes that his successor will be able to unite the dissident factions. He has heard that his resignation caused ill feeling because his withdrawal coincided with the advent of the High Holidays, which, due to their sanctity, have always brought large crowds to Sinai, but so far as the time element was concerned Rabbi Kohler could not help himself. His contract provided that he could resign at any time, although the community agreed to pay his salary until September 1, 1882, in the event that he did not resign voluntarily.</p>
   <p>On Tuesday evening a meeting was held to consider Rabbi Kohler's resignation; Mr. Selz presided. The English newspapers published various interviews with Rabbi Kohler, several prominent members of the congregation had <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1147.jpg" n="3"/>created considerable excitement, and the meeting, therefore, was crowded.</p>
   <p>President Selz opened the meeting with a lengthy address, wherein he attributed the community's sudden indifference to religion to a diversity of opinion on the question of Sunday services. He said that the community was, in effect, two congregations at present and that the main purpose of the meeting was to iron out the dissension which flares up from time to time. He believed that if the situation continued, the religious life of the community would cease; whereas if proper methods were adopted, Sinai could become the greatest Jewish congregation in America.</p>
   <p>The opening speech was not very impressive, but no protest was heard; and then a request was made to have Rabbi Kohler's letter of resignation read to the assembly.</p>
   <p>The secretary, Mr. Felsenthal, read Rabbi Kohler's letter, which gave as the sole cause for his resignation, the indifference of the community to religious service. After the contract was read, it was decided, on the <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1148.jpg" n="4"/>motion of S. F. Leopold, that Rabbi Kohler's resignation should be accepted.</p>
   <p>Henry F. Leopold asked that the resignation go into effect June 30. This motion also passed, after a lengthy debate.</p>
   <p>Julius Rosenthal then made a motion that Rabbi Kohler's salary be paid up to August 30; Rabbi Kohler had always had a summer vacation, and it would appear rather petty if the congregation were to deduct two months of his salary. This proposal caused an exceptionally heated debate and was finally defeated by a large majority.</p>
   <p>On the motion of Berthold Loewenthal, Rabbi Kohler was given free use of the official residence until August 1.</p>
   <p>Leopold Mayer's motion passed; he moved that the executive committee obtain another spiritual leader immediately; someone who had all the <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1149.jpg" n="5"/>proper qualifications and was also thoroughly familiar with English.</p>
   <p>A veritable storm broke loose when Mr. Judah advocated the abolition of all Sunday services and suggested that they be resumed only when a majority voted in favor of them. Before the problem could be resolved, the meeting adjourned.</p>
   <p>Immediately after the meeting, Rabbi Kohler was informed of the outcome by a reporter of the Tribune. Rabbi Kohler said that he would remain until August 30, and would claim payment of salary up to that day. The right to abrogate the contract is not definitely stipulated, but the privilege can be inferred from the correspondence dealing with the agreement. Rabbi Kohler absolutely refused to sign a contract which would bind him to a specific community for a certain length of time, and he regarded the contract merely as a guaranty that he could be the spiritual leader of the congregation for ten years, if he wished.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
