<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-02-02">Feb. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">All Orthodox Synagogues of Chicago Elect Delegates to the Kehilah</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0803</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0803.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-02-02">Feb. 2, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">ALL ORTHODOX SYNAGOGUES OF CHICAGO ELECT DELEGATES TO THE KEHILAH</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Elections of delegates to the organizational meeting of the United Jewish Orthodox Kehilah were held yesterday. The meeting is to take place Sunday, February 15.</p>
   <p>Members of all orthodox synagogues from all parts of the city gathered together to discuss the proposed plans of the temporary Plan and Scope Committee. An extraordinary enthusiasm prevailed. Everyone understood and felt that the cornerstone of a permanent Jewish life was now being laid; that with the consolidation of all Jewish groups in Chicago there would develop a healthy Jewish spirit among the masses.</p>
   <p>The enthusiasm of the audience was particularly evident when the election of the delegates began. Everyone was eager to see that only delegates who <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0804.jpg" n="2"/>understand and sympathize with the purpose of the mandate placed upon them by their synagogues, should be elected.</p>
   <p>Although the election of delegates in all synagogues was supposed to take place yesterday, Sunday, many of the synagogues held their meetings Saturday evening, at which time they elected their delegates.</p>
   <p>According to the recommendations of the temporary Organizational Committee, recommendations which were accepted, each synagogue has the right to elect one delegate for a membership of seventy-five or less, and an additional delegate for every fifty members above that number. The elected delegates will constitute the convention which is being called for February 15.</p>
   <p>The names of the delegates, as well as the names of the synagogues which elected them, will be published during the next few days.</p>
   <p>[Editor's note: Kehilah is the Hebrew term applied to the organized Jewish community of any city or town.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
