<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1900-05-12">May 12, 1900</date>. p.368.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0304</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0304.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
Wk. of <date when="1900-05-12">May 12, 1900</date>. p.368.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following is an excerpt from a speech given by Henry Greenebaum at the banquet tendered to the delegates attending the national convention of the B'nai B'rith.</p>
   <p>"Without arrogance, I may lay claim to the fact that Chicago is the most active center of Jewish interests throughout the United States. Here is the seat of government of the National Council of Jewish Women. The local section comprises over 700 members, earnest, loyal, and true. Here is the Women's Aid Society, a host of women engaged in efforts of philanthropy and culture. Here is Johanna Lodge with a membership of 300 who, since its organization in 1874, have expended over $50,000 in charity. We have here the Y. M. H. C. A. which has made such a bright and excellent record in the field of usefulness that it has become the pride of not only the Jews of this city, but of all Chicago."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0305.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The lodges throughout the United States are to remain under the supervision of the control board.</p>
   <p>The officials elected were: Leo H. Levi, New York, president; Julius Bien, New York, (who has been president of the order for a number of years), Chancellor of Foreign Affairs; Jacob Furth, St. Louis, vice president.</p>
   <p>Among the adopted amendments is one which concedes the right of all the district grand lodges, to adopt by-laws, which would permit the ex-president to vote at all the conventions, held in the districts. The holding of the next constitutional convention, in the year 1905, in the city of New Orleans, was approved unanimously. The chairman was authorized to appoint a committee, to decide on the feasibility of the erection of a non-denominational university by this order. Reports and suggestions should be submitted to the convention, at its next meeting.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
