<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-08-27">Aug. 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Million Dollars to Help Jewish Soldiers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-08-27">Aug. 27, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A MILLION DOLLARS TO HELP JEWISH SOLDIERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American Soldiers and Sailors Welfare League of the B'nai B'rith has already started an active campaign to create a fund of a million dollars to help, in various ways, the Jewish soldiers and sailors in service for Uncle Sam. The welfare league will do the same thing as the YMCA does. The league will build stations near all military camps in America and later build camps also in France.</p>
   <p>The main office of the league is located in Chicago and the work will be directed by Zigmund Levinson of Bloomington, Dr. Gershon B. Levy, general secretary; Moses E. Greenebaum, of Greenebaum Sons Bank and Trust Company, treasurer, and Dr. George Fox, of Fort Worth, Texas.</p>
   <p>Those wishing to contribute towards the fund to help the Jewish soldiers may send their donations to Moses E. Greenebaum, 9 S. La Salle St.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1262.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They attended services in the Ohavah Sholom Congregation, where Rabbi Saul Silber offered an appropriate prayer in English for the success of America, Pres. Wilson and the American Army and Navy, and particularly blessed the Jewish boys to have good luck in their fight for their country, and to conquer the enemy.</p>
   <p>Impressive talks were given by Judge Hugo Pam, Judge Joseph B. David, Judge Harry M. Fisher, and Congressman Adolph J. Sabath.</p>
   <p>Upon leaving they were presented with cigars and cigarettes for which they were very thankful.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
