<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-19">Nov. 19, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Naked Facts</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0736</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0736.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-19">Nov. 19, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">NAKED FACTS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A group of Jewish leaders of Chicago began to organize a kehilah last winter because they realized that without a kehilah, Orthodox Judaism in Chicago was doomed. One of this group, a clever and experienced layman, said that it was not necessary to rush the issuance of a call to the organizing committee because as long as Mr. Ephraim Epstein had not yet left (he was at that time planning to go to Europe), he certainly would obstruct the work and cause trouble.</p>
   <p>The group of leaders, therefore, waited until Ephraim Epstein was gone before they issued the call. The first meeting to organize a kehilah took place. It was successful. All the synagogues and all their rabbis participated in the meeting and pledged their support, energy, money, and work for the great new <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0737.jpg" n="2"/>undertaking. For several months the elected democratic representatives from the Orthodox congregations in Chicago, together with the rabbis, worked diligently for the kehilah. A constitution was drawn up which satisfied both rabbis and laymen. Beautiful and well-attended kehilah conventions were held, and everything went smoothly. The only difficulty which could not be so easily resolved was the [question of the] beth din [Jewish court of law], but finally all parties compromised for the sake of peace.</p>
   <p>When Mr. Ephraim Epstein returned from Europe and began to intrigue against the kehilah, as well as against the beth din, everything began to go topsy-turvy.</p>
   <p>The reader will remember two facts. Before Ephraim Epstein left for Europe, the committee hesitated to inaugurate the work of organizing a kehilah because it was known that he would cause trouble. During his absence, for several months the work of organizing a kehilah proceeded smoothly, but as soon as he <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0738.jpg" n="3"/>returned from Europe, all the intrigues, quarrels, and troubles which had been expected from him, began.</p>
   <p>In the neighborhood of Douglas Boulevard lives Rabbi Ezriel Epstein, the dean of rabbis, a man of vast experience in Jewish law and in the Torah. Ephraim Epstein--and this is known only to a few persons--attempted to oust Rabbi Ezriel Epstein from the beth din so that he, Ephraim alone, could become the head of the beth din, not only of the locals, but also of the central beth din.</p>
   <p>Ephraim's scheme was pretty good. He went with a committee to Rabbi [Simon] Album and suggested that Rabbi Album move into the Douglas Boulevard neighborhood, where a beautiful home would be bought for him, and that Rabbi Album should become the head of the local beth din, which would also serve as the central beth din. Ephraim Epstein thought that since Rabbi Album was an elderly person and found it difficult to travel, he would not participate very much in the activities of the beth din. The wily Ephraim wanted Rabbi Ezriel <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0739.jpg" n="4"/>Epstein, who lived on Douglas Boulevard, to remain in his back yard on Morgan Street and have no affiliation with the Douglas Boulevard beth din. With Rabbi Ezriel Epstein in his own back yard on Morgan Street, far away from the Douglas Boulevard beth din, and with Rabbi Album as the theoretical head of the beth din and unable to participate actively, then, of course, Ephraim Epstein would become the head of the beth din of Chicago.</p>
   <p>This was the scheme of Ephraim Epstein, but it did not succeed, because a few sincere and devoted workers of the kehilah became aware of it in time and prevented it from succeeding.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Ezriel Epstein will learn from these lines that his companion and neighbor attempted to oust him from the beth din, and the rabbis of Chicago, some of whom have been dragged through the mire horribly by this Ephraim Epstein, will also learn for the first time, that their "companion" and "colleague" has resorted to intrigue in order to become their official head. Had it not been <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0740.jpg" n="5"/>for the effort of a few leaders of the kehilah, together with the Courier, the world would now witness a sad spectacle: Ephraim Epstein as the head of the beth din of Chicago.</p>
   <p>When Ephraim Epstein realized that he could not become the head of the beth din of Chicago (he had already had cards printed "Ephraim Epstein, head of the beth din of Chicago"), he wanted to become the head of the Hebrew Theological College, also a "delicate job". Toward this end, he tried to raise one hundred and seventy-five thousand dollars to build a home for a Hebrew Theological College, to drag the Jewish community of Chicago into enormous expenses, and then reign in his own Hebrew Theological College, to be Chicago's counterpart of Dr. Revel and Dr. Schechter. [The latter two were the distinguished presidents of the famous Hebrew Theological Seminary in New York.] But in order to do this, the Hebrew Theological College had to become his property, had to be exclusively under his control, for otherwise, he couldn't play the part which he wanted to play. Thanks to the work of the Courier, this plan of his was <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0741.jpg" n="6"/>also smashed.</p>
   <p>If there is to be a genuine Hebrew Theological College in Chicago, it will be under the control of the city, and the city will choose a suitable person as principal, and not Ephraim Epstein. Now the readers will understand why Ephraim Epstein does not want to release even the present Hebrew Theological College from his control, and why he does not permit any investigation. But nothing will help him. The fact that his synagogue is a large one does not, as yet, make him the head of the beth din, nor the chief rabbi of Chicago. As long as there are rabbis in Chicago like Album, [M.] Zevin, Ezriel Epstein, both Glicks, and other scholars, Ephraim Epstein cannot be the chief rabbi of Chicago. To gain his ambition, he resorts to intrigue and seeks to demoralize the other rabbis by trying to drag them deeper and deeper into the swamp.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
