<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>, 
            <date when="1933-06-30">June 30, 1933</date>.<title level="a">Mayor Kelly Greets American Jewry</title>
        
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1525</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>, 
            <date when="1933-06-30">June 30, 1933</date>.<title level="a">Mayor Kelly Greets American Jewry</title>
        </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
  <p>Chicago is proud to welcome the delegates to the 36th Annual Convention of the Zionist Organization of America, who have come to Chicago from all parts of the United States and Canada.</p>
  <p>The same warm welcome is extended to the B'nai and B'rith Conference as well as to the countless thousands of Jews who are coming to our city to celebrate Jewish Day, Monday, July 3rd.</p>
  <p>Chicago is now celebrating its One Hundredth Anniversary as a corporated city, through "A Century of Progress," showing what progress in art, science and industry has been made during the past century and to what extent it has contributed to that marvelous development.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1525.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Jews have played a conspicuous part and contributed their share to that development. They have won foremost places in the professions of law and medicine. They have brought much to the development of our arts and letters, and have shown genius in the organization and conduct of charitable institutions.</p>
   <p>The Jews of America may well be congratulated upon their patriotism and enterprise in the part they have played in the development of our country, and what they have made of themselves under free government.</p>
   <p>Welcome, stalwart sons of Israel! You whose history is filled with martyrs and heroes, poets and prophets. You, Zionists, who are now spinning the future of your people and helping to re-create a new nation, as well as those who are endeavoring to strengthen their social, religious and philanthropic institutions in our own country, I bid a hearty greeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1526.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Welcome, welcome to Chicago, wonder city of the age, where you are sure to receive a warm and brotherly reception.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
