<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-12-10">Dec. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Young Israel</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0813</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0813.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-12-10">Dec. 10, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">YOUNG ISRAEL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Young Israel is an organization of Orthodox young men and women, recently established in Chicago, with the object of solidifying traditional Judaism and spreading it among the American born or Americanized Jews. The representatives of this movement, though in every respect Orthodox, feel that Orthodoxy in its old garb no longer appeals to the youth, and that in order to be acceptable to the youth it must be modernized in form. The members of Young Israel are anxious to hear a representative of Judaism talking to them on matters Jewish as any old-fashioned Orthodox Jew, but since they no longer master Yiddish, and do not understand an old-fashioned sermon in Yiddish, they want to have it delivered to them in English. They also demand that the forms of Orthodoxy be modernized to such an extent that it satisfy the aesthetic needs of the youth. In addition Young Israel is interested in everything pertaining to Judaism--literature, Jewish learning, Jewish institutions, etc. To them Judaism is not a matter of religious creed only, as it is with the Reformed Jews, because Young Israel differs from old-fashioned Orthodoxy in form only.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0814.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We think that there are vast possibilities for this movement, not only in Chicago, but all over America, and we also think that the representatives of Orthodoxy are in honor and duty bound to support the movement, because it may contribute a great deal to keep the young generation in constant touch with conservative Judaism. Young Israel is not abandoning Orthodoxy of old, but is simply supplementing it.</p>
   <p>Of course, those who think that Yiddish is essential to Orthodoxy and is part and parcel of Judaism, will differ with us, will look upon the Young Israel movement as a semi-reform venture. But the fact of the matter is that Yiddish is not part and parcel of Judaism, just as Ladino or any other jargon spoken by Jews in the one or the other part of the world is not an organic part of Judaism. Every Jewish organization must work out its own salvation, and must adapt itself to the times and modes of life of the times. In the middle ages, the center of Judaism was Spain and Portugal, and Spanish Jewry was much more Spanish than Russian Jewry was Russian, or German Jewry German. In addition the Jews of Spain and Portugal were desirous of remaining in contact <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0815.jpg" n="3"/>with the great cultural agencies of their time, and the Jewish representatives of that period wrote and spoke in Arabic, Spanish and Latin, the three great languages of medieval civilization. The greatest Jewish codifier and philosopher, Maimonides, has written his main work in Arabic. This at least goes to prove that Yiddish or any other vernacular spoken by Jews is not part and parcel of Judaism. If there is any language of which it can be said that it is an organic part of Judaism then it is not Yiddish but Hebrew. One can be as good a Jew in English or in French or in German as one can be a good Jew in Yiddish. Therefore, Young Israel movement, anxious to preserve and perpetuate Jewish traditions, is not a Reform venture, but just an attempt, and a necessary attempt to bring about a synthesis of Orthodox Judaism and modern culture.</p>
   <p>We understand that the leaders of the movement, all young men and women, have already succeeded in enrolling a considerable membership and the movement is making rapid strides on the West Side and the Northwest Side of Chicago. We can assure the leaders of the movement of our sympathy with noble aims and <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0816.jpg" n="4"/>aspirations, and that we, on our part, will do whatever we can to further the great cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
