<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-04-10">April 10, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">A Dedication of a Temple</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats, Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1876-04-10">April 10, 1876</date>.
<title level="a">A DEDICATION OF A TEMPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dedication of a large temple erected by the Sinai congregation on the corner of 21st Street and Indiana Avenue, has taken place. The cost of the temple was $70,000, the lot not included. The style of architecture is mixed Gothic and Oriental, making a very striking appearance. The hall for religious services accommodates one-thousand persons.</p>
   <p>Mr. Adler was the first speaker, saying......regardless ofthe changes of custom, the Jewish people have retained and professed their religious enthusiasm and no matter how much parties and inclinations differ in Israel, the same monotheistic foundation exists. The next speaker was Dr. Felsenthal, who took for his text the psalm verse, "Open to me the gates of righteousness." He attempted to answer the question:- Under which circumstance could the gates of that temple be spoken of as gates of righteousness? He spoke of the Jewish doctrine which will be preached in this house of the Lord which in itself is enlightening. He spoke of the Jewish life in connection with religious services, cultivation of Jewish knowledge and works on loving our neighbours. As an extra-ordinary orator,he sowed ideas of unusual beauty and richness. No doubt many a grain which he has sowed will take root and bloom, and in due time will also bear fruit.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1160.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The next speaker, Dr. Kohler, who delivered his speech in English. He commenced with the words of Jacob: "How reverence-commanding this branch is!" He spoke of the three main pillars as the basis for the Jewish mental life; education; service to the Lord; and charitable work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
