<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929-01-28">January 28, 1929</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1322</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1322.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929-01-28">January 28, 1929</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the most dominant factors in the American Jewish life of today is the B'nai B'rith organization. While the latter is mainly an organization devoted to the betterment of the adult American Jew, it has shown a remarkable wisdom in focusing part of its attention, and resources also, towards the strengthening of the Jewish younger generation. The means for doing this has been incorporated in a nation wide B'nai B'rith organization, known as the Aleph, Zadek, Aleph.</p>
   <p>This national organization has groups throughout the country, with various regional counsels governing them. Among the prominent Chicago groups is the West Town Chapter, which, before its merging with the national movement was the Institute Boys Democracy. The activities of the group, composed of about twenty-five young men ranging in age between eighteen and twenty, are many and varied. While all of them bear some definite universal aspect, each is distinguished by its purpose in bringing about a Jewish consciousness among the membership. The Jewish youth problem is a serious one, and it is an inspiration to see this group of sincere young men, enthusiastically engaged in an intensively Jewish project. The program <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1323.jpg" n="2"/>of the group includes among its many secular forms, a concentrated study of Jewish history, Jewish problems, and Jewish culture.</p>
   <p>Speakers are frequent at the meetings. Typical of the latter was Rabbi David Rosenbaum, who lead an earnest discussion on some modern aspects of Jewish life. Not content with accepting blindly views on a subject so close to them, the members presented numerous questions and logical arguments in refuting or accepting many of the ideas presented to them.</p>
   <p>Debating, too, finds its place among this club's activities, and in this part of the program, there is also evident an intense Jewishness. Typical of the subjects debated, is the following: Can Anti-Semitism Be Eradicated? Before an audience that filled the women's lounge, four of the young men of this club presented the attitude of American Jewish youth to the ever present problem of anti-Semitism, in a manner that showed their full consciousness of the seriousness of the problem.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
