<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1894-03-23">March 23, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">For a New Creed.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1050</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1050.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Occident</title>,
<date when="1894-03-23">March 23, 1894</date>.
<title level="a">FOR A NEW CREED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recent circular call issued by liberal ministers and divines of this city and other localities, entitled For a Closer Cooperation, seems to have elicited replies from a number of eminent men who are disposed to meet at some specified time and place to aid in the laudable work of encouraging a religious union among at least the liberal and thinking people of this country. From a pamphlet before us we learn that nearly 150 responses have been received by the chairman, Rev. H. W. Thomas of the People's Church of this city, from some of the most prominent liberal ministers and pulpiteers, who are outspoken and have broad sentiments regarding this movement which was contemplated at the World's Religious Congress held last September at the Art Institute. The call is issued with the following names: H. W. Thomas, of the People's Church, Chicago; E. G. Hirsch, Sinai Congregation, Chicago; W. S. Crawe, Universalist Church, Newark, N. J., W. I. Shelden, lecturer, Ethical Culture Society, St. Louis; William Salter, lecturer, Ethical Culture Society, Elgin; R. C. Cave, Non-sectarian Church, St. Louis; E. L. Rexford, Universalist Church, Boston; M. J. Savage, Unity Church, Boston; Jenkins Lloyd Jones, All Souls Church, Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1051.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The "Liberal Religious Societies of America" may soon become an organization that will be an indicator of the progress and advancement of this century..... We heartily endorse the project.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
