<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-19">May 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Children's World</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Poale Zion Youth Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1441</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1441.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-19">May 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CHILDREN'S WORLD</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Poale Zion Youth Club</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In these stormy times, when thousands of active Jewish young men are being drafted into the general military service and hundreds of others are enlisting in the Jewish Legion, there is yet so much work to be done! It is a consoling thought--fortunate, if you wish--that there is a group of Jewish boys and girls who are ready to take over and assist in the work of their older friends. They are striving thereby to develop the necessary intelligence, knowledge and feeling to be worthy of participating in the sacred work. I refer here to the forty new members of the Poale Zion Youth Club. A careful scrutiny of the activities of this Club during the last three months will justify beyond any doubt the estimate of them expressed above.</p>
   <p>As soon as the former Young Maccabees Branch 'D' had declared itself to be <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1442.jpg" n="2"/>hereafter "The Poale Zion Youth Club", it decided that its first and paramount task is that of education and study of the sacred ideals for which it stands. For this purpose, the Club under the leadership of the engineer Emanuel Paperno immediately established a class in socialism under the direction of Friend I. Berkenblith. He also engaged Friend B. Sherman to lecture on "The Development of the Zionist Ideal", and Friend Oreshkos on "The Development of Jewish Literature." There have already been given some highly interesting and instructive lectures on these subjects, which will continue for some time.</p>
   <p>On Sunday, April 28, the Club made a visit to the Art Institute where a member of the Institute staff addressed the Club on "Egyptian Art". More such visits to the Art Institute and lectures on art have already been organized. Add to them lectures, discussions, and debates by and among the members themselves, and you will have some idea of the educational activities of the Poale Zion Youth Club.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1443.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The members of the Youth Club also recognize the fact that it is necessary to participate actively in the practical work of the realization of our ideal. Consequently, we see them acting on committees, collecting funds for the Palestine Fund, selling "shekels", seeking signatures on registration cards, and knocking at the doors of Jewish homes on Sundays for the benefit of war sufferers. Perhaps the finest piece of work which the Poale Zion Youth Club has done so far is the resolution of greeting to the local conference of workers for Palestine, a resolution which the club drew up and upon which it obtained the signatures of twenty-five National Youth Clubs comprising a total membership of 2100. Within a week's time the Poale Zion Youth Club was successful in organizing for Palestine 2100 Jewish youths, the majority of whom were far, far away from the Zionistic idea! This is really an extraordinary and praiseworthy accomplishment.</p>
   <p>Considering their achievements, is it any wonder that the members of the Poale Zion Youth Club expect to double its membership during the month of May, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1444.jpg" n="4"/>the month of the campaign for members? For they must realize that Jewish youth respects such work and is anxious to fling themselves into it. And Jewish youth will answer the call!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
