<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-29">Apr. 29, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">130 Delegates at the Labor Conference for Palestine</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0158</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0158.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-04-29">Apr. 29, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">130 DELEGATES AT THE LABOR CONFERENCE FOR PALESTINE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>More than 130 delegates came yesterday to the labor conference for Palestine at the West Side Auditorium. The conference lasted all day and came to a close in the evening with a banquet.</p>
   <p>Mr. D. Ben Gurion, the well-known Poale Zion leader came especially from New York to the conference and in several addresses clearly outlined before the assembled delegates, who represented about eighteen thousand organized workers and members of aid societies, the present situation regarding Palestine and what the workers must do to help; firstly, to rebuild a new life for the Jews in Palestine, and secondly to be represented everywhere in such a manner as to prevent the wealthier class from exclusive domination.</p>
   <p>Mr. William Nathanson, in a powerful address called upon the Jewish workers not to abstain from this sacred work, but to help in building the Jewish <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0159.jpg" n="2"/>homeland on the basis of equality, justice and brotherly love.</p>
   <p>Several resolutions with recommendations to the delegates to the Labor Congress, which will be held next month in New York, were adopted after lively discussion. Similar conferences were held yesterday in almost every part of America.</p>
   <p>Most of the 130 delegates represented sixteen unions, twenty-five lodges, nine Poale Zion branches, eight Workers Alliance branches, and the other delegates represented various radical and progressive societies.</p>
   <p>Among the fifteen elected delegates are many leaders of big unions, as Mr. R. Ukelson, president of United Labor of Palestine and Mr. B. Shafer of the Cloak Makers Joint Board. The other elected delegates are: Mr. Herman, Mr. Shuster, Mr. Ginsburg, Mr. Kaminsky, Dr. Marcus, Dr. Dolnik, Mr. Sherman, Mr. Kleah.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
