<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1925-04-21">April 21, 1925</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1374</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1374.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1925-04-21">April 21, 1925</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Poale Zion Juniors Club is a group of boys and girls between the ages of fourteen and seventeen. The following is a course of lectures to be delivered within twenty weeks:</p>
   <p>1. Beginnings of Peoples - introductory lectures. a. Mankind: Its origin and first achievements. b. Primitive Societies: Hide-bound life and beliefs. c. Tribal origins and births of peoples.</p>
   <p>2. Beginnings of the Jewish Peoples. a. Biblical and legendary lore about Abraham. b. Idolatry: Manifestation of the wondering mind of mankind. c. Monotheism.</p>
   <p>3. The Patriarchs. a. The institution of Patriarchy. b. Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. c. The early migrations of the Hebrews. d. The migration of the Israelites to Egypt.</p>
   <p>4. Egypt and the Return. a. Ancient Egypt: The people and beliefs.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1375.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>b. A sojourn of several centuries - Joseph. c. Contact with Egyptian culture. d. The Exodus - Moses. e. Moses - the first and greatest teacher and leader.</p>
   <p>5. Tribal Organization in the Desert. a. The remaking of the Jewish people in the forty years wandering and fighting. b. Preparation for the land. c. Spiritual acquisition - the Torah. d. Moses, the teacher.</p>
   <p>6. The Israelites in Canaan: Period of Judges. a. Conquest of the land; strengthening of the people. b. Joshua: Cementing of the people. c. The Judges: Lack of central political organization. d. The Judges: Changing fortunes of the union of Israelitian tribes among hostile neighbors. e. Periodic straggling from Mosaic law and form of worship, and imitation of neighboring tribes.</p>
   <p>7. A Kingdom and a Nation. a. The prophet Samuel: A maker of kings. b. King Saul: Foreign conquests. c. King David: Expansion and internal centralization. d. King Solomon: Material prosperity and spiritual development. The Temple.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1376.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>8. The Decline and Fall of the Hebrew Kingdom. a. The division into Israel and Judah. b. Comparison of the two kingdoms. c. The fall of Israel. d. The fall of Judah.</p>
   <p>9. The Prophets. a. The early prophets: Elijah, Elisha, etc. b. The later prophets: Isaiah, Hosea, Amos, Jeremia, etc. c. The Judaism of the later prophets.</p>
   <p>10. Babylon and the Partial Return. a. The Jewish communities in Babylon. b. The Jewish communities left in Palestine. The Samaritans. c. The Return Under Cyrus: Ruler of the Persian Empire. d. The Scribes: Ezra, Nehemia. The rebuilding of the Temple.</p>
   <p>11. Palestine under Foreign Rule. The revolt. a. Palestine, a protectorate under Persia. b. Palestine under Alexander the Great. c. Palestine under the Egyptian Ptolemies. d. Palestine under Syrian rule. e. The Maccabean revolt. Chanukah.</p>
   <pb n="4"/>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1377.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>16. The Jews in Medieval Europe: A recital of woes. a. In Catholic Spain: The inquisition and expulsion. b. In Catholic France: The various persecutions and exiles. c. In Germany: Inferior position of the Jews. d. In Italy: The tempering influence of the Popes. e. In England: The early prosperity and early expression. f. In Finland: The haven of refuge. Menasseh Ben Israel. Spinoza.</p>
   <p>17. The Jews in Medieval Europe: a. The Messianic outbursts. b. The Jews in Poland and Russia. c. Closed inner life: Talmudism and Chassidism. d. Glimpses of America.</p>
   <p>18. The Nineteenth Century. a. Harbingers of Enlightenment: Moses, Mendelsohn. b. The shift of the center of Jewry to Russia and Poland. c. The emancipation of Western Europe. d. The rise of Nationalism. e. Zionism and Theodore Herzl.</p>
   <p>19. The Twentieth Century. (prior to the war). a. The Jews in Russia <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1378.jpg" n="6"/>and Poland. b. The Jews in America. c. Jewish literature: Hebrew and Yiddish. d. Jewish Nationalism.</p>
   <p>20. The War and Today. a. Jewish participation in the war. b. Disastrous effects of the war on the Jewries of Europe. c. The Jews today. d. Jewish participation in modern civilization. e. Anti-Semitism and the answer. f. The logic of Zionism. g. Palestine today.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
