<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-04-19">April 19, 1930</date>, Volume 79, Page 269.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1173</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1173.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Reform Advocate</title>,
<date when="1930-04-19">April 19, 1930</date>, Volume 79, Page 269.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With considerable pride it can be said that most of the things that made the B'nai B'rith prominent and placed the organization on a high plane issued from Chicago. In a booklet recently published by the Ramah Lodge No. 33, I O. B. B., there is the following interesting item which is of sufficient importance to a placement in these pages. The Ramah Lodge was organized in Chicago nine years before District No. 6, was founded, and six years before the Civil War. The item reads: "At the outbreak of the Civil War, under the auspices of Ramah Lodge, a mass meeting of Chicago Jews was called for the purpose of raising money to recruit a company of Jewish volunteers to form a part of the 82nd Regiment of Illinois Volunteers commanded by Colonel Frederick Hecker and Lieutenant Colonel Edward S. Solomon. The meeting was a great success. The sum of eleven thousand dollars was promptly subscribed, from which fund a bonus of one hundred dollars each was given to one hundred and four men enlisting in the company. With one exception, all of the officers of the company were Jews and they achieved a splendid record in the war. Shortly after the enlistment, brothers Henry Greenebaum, Abraham Hart and Joseph Frank went to Camp Butler near Soringfield, to deliver a regimental flag which had been made by Jewish women whose <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1174.jpg" n="2"/>husbands and brothers were affiliated with Ramah Lodge. The flag was entrusted to the Jewish company, Company C. and the same flag was carried throughout the war by a Jewish soldier named Levi. A committee of Ramah Lodge was very active all through the war in seeing to it that the families of the married men in the company were properly taken care of and also carried on a recruiting office to secure recruits. On June 17th, 1865, the 82nd regiment returned to Chicago. The flag was riddled with bullets and out of the thousand members of the regiment, only two hundred and fifty returned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
