<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-15">May 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Jewish Boy of Eighteen Killed in Battle</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1254</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1254.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-15">May 15, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">JEWISH BOY OF EIGHTEEN KILLED IN BATTLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Aaron Chemirovsky, an eighteen-year-old Chicago boy, died a hero's death on the battlefields of France, fighting against the Germans whom with his life he helped to prevent from breaking through the Allies' front.</p>
   <p>Aaron fell in combat on the first of May during a period of great hostilities, and his name appears on yesterday's casualty list issued by General Pershing. Details as to exactly where the young hero was fighting are lacking. Aaron's father received yesterday from the War Department merely a short notice which reads as follows: "With great sorrow we are notifying you that Private Aaron Chemirovsky according to official reports was killed in battle on May first". [sic]</p>
   <p>Aaron came to Chicago five years ago from Odessa with his father, Abraham Chemirovsky. He was then thirteen years old. He went to school for one year, and then began to learn a trade in order to become an electrician. He loved <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1255.jpg" n="2"/>America from the first day of his arrival here; and as soon as America was forced to declare war on Germany, he wanted to enlist.</p>
   <p>His father, who is a bakery worker and lives at 1836 West Taylor Street, had tried several times to keep him from enlisting because of his youth, but a year ago he left home and enlisted, and was sent to a camp in Arizona. Aaron was reluctant to wait until he reached his twenty-first birthday and be drafted. He couldn't rest after he heard the call of President Wilson for the patriotic young men to volunteer, and he enlisted.</p>
   <p>After spending about five months in camp, he was then transported with his regiment to France where he used to write encouraging letters to his father.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
