<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-05-05">May 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">All Jews in Chicago Should Know It.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0968</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0968.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1909-05-05">May 5, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">ALL JEWS IN CHICAGO SHOULD KNOW IT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The success that marked the first mass meeting sponsored by the Congregation Sharei Torah, last Sunday, to raise money for the lots they bought near Douglas Park, and on which a synagogue is to be erected soon. As a result of that meeting we can learn the following:</p>
   <p>1. That our common people must understand, that Judaism cannot exist unless they have a sacred place where they are able to congregate to pray and to learn the Talmud. When Jews congregate at such places they also respond to appeals for aid to charitable institutions supported and maintained by Jews.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0969.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>2. Our young generation would greatly satisfy their old parents, who came here from Europe, by helping them erect places of worship, where they can get together not only to pray, but also for other social purposes.</p>
   <p>3. Our middle-aged Jews try to instill the spirit of Judaism in their children. They support and maintain Talmud Torahs, and private tutors, in order to educate their children in everything pertaining to Jewish religion and Jewish history. Jewish children have to go through a hard ordeal in learning Torah (Bible) not experienced by children of any other nationality. Yet, Jewish children, in order to be truly Jews, have to go through the hard grind. It is worth all the trouble, for <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0970.jpg" n="3"/>the things they learn, sharpen their minds, they become enlightened, and serves them to good advantage when they grow up. Jews turn out more scholars, intellectuals, and professionals, than any other nationality according to its percentage of the population.</p>
   <p>That, naturally, creates envy and jealousy amongst other nationalities, which in turn turns to resentment and hate. But Jews wouldn't be frightened and intimidated by such resentment. They have a mission in life. They'll go on with their work. But in order to go on they must always fall back on the Torah, the text book of our civilization, for courage and inspiration. As long as they do this, they will remain strong and intact, but should they turn away from it, they are bound to stagger and collapse. For that reasons, synagogues are our spiritual sanctuaries, from which we derive strength and unity.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0971.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The mass meeting last Sunday proved that the majority of our people are still responding to the call of the Torah. Eight-hundred ($800) dollars came in, and $1,000 have been promised by our donor, Mr. Williams. It is to be hoped that our Jews who are now settling aroung Douglas Park district, will remember to contribute money in support of our congregation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
