<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-07">Mar. 7, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">"Who Is with God, Follow Me"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Proclamation by Rabbi Judah Leb Gordon)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0455</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0455.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-03-07">Mar. 7, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">"WHO IS WITH GOD, FOLLOW ME"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(A Proclamation by Rabbi Judah Leb Gordon)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Jews of Chicago! This appeal to you is wrung from a heart full of pain and sorrow, caused by the condition of education in our city of Chicago.</p>
   <p>I find it necessary to proclaim that according to the law of the Torah, we must [not] permit the people who have discarded all the laws of the Torah, to become the educators of our children.</p>
   <p>I sincerely believe that Destiny has brought me here in my old age so that I could throw myself into the midst of the efforts [being made] to save the education of our children. I deem it my lifelong task to save Jewish education from the hands of our misguided brothers who, themselves, are alien to the spirit of our holy Torah, and who, therefore, will unconsciously--perhaps their intentions are good--estrange our children from the Torah.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0456.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our fathers would surely have sacrificed their lives in the face of the danger that threatens our children, the danger of [having their education] supervised by strangers.</p>
   <p>[To let] the Jews with whom we can neither eat together nor pray together because they have erased the words "Zion and Jerusalem" from their prayer books (destroyed everything which proclaims God in the land), to let them become the guardians and educators of our children--that is something that has never been heard of among us Jews.</p>
   <p>My dear brethren! I tell you once more that according to the law of the Torah, we have no right to entrust the soul of the people, the children of the community, who bear upon their shoulders our Jewish future, into the hands of those who, themselves, are alien to our tradition and our spirit.</p>
   <p>Stay away! Stay away! It is not for them, nor for us to build God's House. Education must be under the supervision of Jews who are permeated with the <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0457.jpg" n="3"/>spirit of Judaism, and who are not led astray by beautiful promises.</p>
   <p>And to you Jews who have broken away from our Law, I say, Brothers! You have served our people well. You have saved Israel with your money and your work. You have alleviated, by your philanthropic efforts, the want and pain of the suffering people in all parts of the world. You have proven that the feeling of pity lives within you. I, therefore, tearfully beg of you: Have pity; do not touch our sacred possessions. "Do not touch my Messiah, the children of the community." Let us educate our children in our spirit and ideal, for which many generations have bled and suffered. "Who is with God, follow me!"</p>
   <p>And you, the sons of Israel, stand fast and strong! Guard with open eyes the fortress of our holy Judaism!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
