<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929-11-28">November 28, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Sirkin Lodge of Jewish National Workers Association Begins Meeting at Institute.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1318</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1318.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Hebrew Institute Observer</title>,
<date when="1929-11-28">November 28, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">DR. SIRKIN LODGE OF JEWISH NATIONAL WORKERS ASSOCIATION BEGINS MEETING AT INSTITUTE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Beginning Sunday evening, December 1, the Dr. Sirkin Branch of the J. N. W. A. will begin its meetings in the Jewish Peoples Institute. This branch which is named after Dr. N. Sirkin, one of the pioneers of the Poale Zion movement, and well known Jewish publicist, consists of a group of young men and young women who help actively the various progressive movements in Jewish life generally, and the organized labor movement in particular, believing them to represent the most constructive and positive force in the whole Zionist structure.</p>
   <p>The branch has also a cultural program arranged for every meeting, consisting of lectures and discussion on various subjects of Jewish and worldly interest, including current literary events and social and economic problems. A feature of the club's activities is the periodical club newspaper, edited by Dr. R. Hurovitz, with contributed articles by the members. The branch <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1319.jpg" n="2"/>is now arranging a series of public lectures for the Winter months. The first of these lectures will be given Friday evening, November 29, at Roosevelt Hall, 3447 W. Roosevelt Road, by Dr. Jacob Shatsky, well known Jewish scholar of New York, on the subject - Jewish Characters in World Literature. The second lecture will be given Friday evening, December 6, also at Roosevelt Hall, by Dr. Chaim Greenberg of New York, one of the most eloquent speakers of our time. He will speak on - The Philosophy of Job.</p>
   <p>The feature program for the next meeting, on Sunday evening, December 1, 8 P. M., in the Disraeli Room, will be - The Spoken Newspaper. All interested are invited.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
