<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-14">July 14, 1913</date><title level="a">Adas Bnai Israel</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1473</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1473.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1913-07-14">July 14, 1913</date><title level="a">ADAS BNAI ISRAEL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Very few readers know that a society of Jewish orthodox youth exists in Chicago under the name of Adas Bnai Israel of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Very little is heard about them. In winter they can be heard through small announcements in newspapers advertising a lecture. During the summer they are completely dormant.</p>
   <p>The present leaders of this society are apparently far from being business men. They can not and do not know how to popularize their society throughout the city. Most of them are members of a house of worship. Nevertheless, the society itself is very good and laudable in its mission.</p>
   <p>The Adas Bnai Israel was established according to the model of the New York Adas Bnai Israel. The founder's aim was to dissiminate the sublime ideals of Judaism. Their hall is a place for young people who have, at one time, studied and want to preserve whatever they acquired in Hebrew school and Yeshiva. All young men and women belonging to this society are workers and students, and yet they all observe the Sabbath. They are all modern orthodox Jews in the fullest sense of the word.</p>
   <p>On the Sabbath (Saturday) and holiday mornings they have their own quorum of <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1474.jpg" n="2"/>worshipers, their own cantor and rabbi. Everything is conducted according to the traditional Jewish customs.</p>
   <p>It is grand to witness how a group get together on Sabbath and holiday afternoons, many extremely Americanized, and study assiduously in two separate departments. In one department, Pentateuch, Solomon, Yitzhaki's commentary, and the prophets are taught. In the other, Talmud. Their instructors are selected from their own group. From time to time they invite rabbis and other prominent speakers to address them.</p>
   <p>They are in possession of a few books. It can not be called a library. We do not know who donated these books. They lack books. Of those which they have, not one book is of modern literature.</p>
   <p>This society was organized by twelve young men who were graduates of the Yeshiva Eitz Chaim (Tree of Life Theological Seminary). Now the society has more than one hundred good-standing members.</p>
   <p>They all live in harmony. If anyone should be unemployed or lose his job on account of the Sabbath, all members are willing to help him in any possible way.</p>
   <p>In the beginning they held their meetings in the Yeshiva Eitz Chaim, afterwards in the Wood Street Talmud Torah. As they grew in numbers and became richer, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1475.jpg" n="3"/>they rented an apartment on 12th Street.</p>
   <p>In general, it is a good phenomenon. It shows that in this country, in America, where the chief aim of the average man is money, money and money, where the youth spend their time in dance halls, a Jewish movement, which is more than welcome, can spring up.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
