<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-09-23">September 23, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Young Judea Column.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1350</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1350.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-09-23">September 23, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">YOUNG JUDEA COLUMN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have been thinking for some weeks about the wonderful progress Chicago Young Judea is making. We have outlined the plans for the future and have in all ways indicated that the local organization is functioning well. However, since the Young Judea Convention, there has been a noticeable lack of comment on the National Organization. The convention was a glowing one. Plans were made and resolutions passed which we felt would mean a big year ahead, not only for the local organizations throughout the country, but for National Young Judea as a whole. We were happy. We thought that the National Office would continue the good work of last year and that this year Young Judea as a whole would outdo itself in activity. We waited patiently, expecting to hear from our National headquarters about plans for the New Year. Time passes, not a word from the National Office. We thought surely at the beginning of September, we would hear something. Nothing came. Then the question arose, why? What had happened to all the spirit and enthusiasm which had been evident at the convention. Why this sudden death? Here is the answer.</p>
   <p>ZIONIST ORGANIZATION NOT SUPPORTING YOUNG JUDEA.</p>
   <p>The Zionist Organization has refused to give financial support to National Young Judea. An organization cannot possibly exist without funds and surely <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1351.jpg" n="2"/>the members of Young Judea, children, cannot expect to finance it. The Zionist Organization was proud of Young Judea, when that group was organized. Then there were only a few scattered clubs. Now when Young Judea has grown to a group numbering several hundred throughout the country, when it can and is a vital factor in Zionist activity, the parent has seen fit to disown it and to let the child wonder without assistance. The Zionist Organization has seen fit to lay out money for sinecure positions and to aid minor causes, but when it comes to Young Judea, the organization which holds the future of the Zionists in its hand refuses to lend cooperation. Why? That question we would like to have the Zionist Organization answer.</p>
   <p>WILL TEND TO ANTAGONIZE MEMBERS.</p>
   <p>We need a National Office for the National Office acts as a guardian over all local clubs and we need that point of centralization to give our children the feeling that they belong to a live group. But what are we to tell them now? Are we to tell them that the Zionist Organization which they have been taught to honor as the group doing outstanding Palestinian work has refused to support them? Are we to continue to have them raise funds for the Jewish National Fund and for the Keren Hayesod, when Young Judes is crying for funds - for funds which will enable them to carry on the educational work of Young Judea?</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1352.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We have told our boys and girls about the Zionist Organization and in many instances have so inspired them that their enthusiasm has been passed on to the parents and the parents have joined the Zionists. But can we continue to speak in such glowing words about the Zionists when they refuse to aid the very cause which is their life?</p>
   <p>The editor, for one, feels that we cannot do so. We cannot go on honoring the Zionist Organization when they entertain this attitude. And it is not only the children who will be affected. The young men and young women who are giving their time and energy for Young Judea are happy to do so. These young men and women for the most part are the highest type of Jewish individuals, educated and idealistic. In four or five years it will be these young men and women who will be leaders in the Zionist Organization. They too, and the editor has had the opinion of more than one, feel that something is wrong somewhere.</p>
   <p>ZIONISTS SHOULD ACT.</p>
   <p>We don't know what it is. We don't know who is responsible, but if there are any readers of this column who have influence with the Zionist Organization and who know the value of Young Judea, we ask them quite sincerely to <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1353.jpg" n="4"/>approach those members of the Zionist Organization who are balking against giving Young Judea the, to them, small sum needed to maintain the executive offices and to point out to them the mistake of allowing the child to wander.</p>
   <p>We want to see Young Judea progress. We want to see the spirit of the convention come back. We want to continue receiving the services of the National Office. If Young Judea is to live, it needs a central point.</p>
   <p>LEADERS MEETING.</p>
   <p>In spite of the heat, quite a number of workers and leaders gathered last Thursday, September 8, for the meeting at the Young Judea office. Young Judeans were glad to welcome back into their midst Dr. Schom who recently returned to the city with his wife. The two are planning to again become active.</p>
   <p>SENIOR LEAGUE.</p>
   <p>The Senior League is soon to be recognized. Mr. Aronson and Mr. Goldberg are taking this responsiblity upon themselves and will announce the opening <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1354.jpg" n="5"/>meeting soon. Boys and girls, sixteen to eighteen, will be invited to attend the meetings of the Senior League.</p>
   <p>NEW CENTERS.</p>
   <p>The question of the advisability of organizing new centers aroused a lot of conflicting opinions. Mr. Edidon, who has had a great deal of experience in these matters, was of the opinion that Chicago Young Judea should not exert themselves in organizing new centers, but that the energy should be spent in strengthening our present centers. A motion to the effect that no new centers be organized was made but failed to pass. Therefore, attempts will be made to form new centers in various portions of the city, but the old centers will not be neglected.</p>
   <p>LIBRARY.</p>
   <p>Chicago's Young Judean Library will becone an actuality in the very near future, if the present plans are realized. All clubs will be asked to pledge two books and in addition friends and leaders are asked to send whatever books they may care to donate to the Young Judea Office, Room 516, 155 N. Clark St. Mr. Hyman Marcus has been asked to work out ways and means <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1355.jpg" n="6"/>of making the library grow. In addition to our own library, the Public Library will be asked to have a Jewish shelf at the Young Judea office and in any other vicinities Jewish books may be in demand.</p>
   <p>NATIONAL FUND.</p>
   <p>Mr. Louis Agranat is anxious to complete his report of Young Judea's part in National Fund work and asks that all clubs having money in their boxes, get this to him at once. All clubs which have not boxes can secure these at the Young Judea office.</p>
   <p>RALLIES.</p>
   <p>Four get-togethers for the Young Judeans will occur during the coming year. The first of these will be the convention on October 23. This will be followed by a Chanukah rally in December, and by a Spring rally. Details for the conventions are in the process of being formulated.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1356.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>LEADERS' ORGANIZATION.</p>
   <p>The question of the functioning of the Leaders' Organization as a whole, resulted in quite a heated discussion. The group seemed to be about evenly divided into those who thought that an Executive Council should decide all matters for the Leaders and those who thought all matters should be submitted to the group as a whole for ratification. It was finally voted that the Executive Council idea should govern. With this method, each center will be entitled to two representatives at the Executive Council, chosen from the members at large. As it was getting late, the meeting adjourned with many matters of importance still awaiting decision. These other subjects will be thrashed out at the Leaders' meeting, to be held in the very mear future.</p>
   <p>ORGANIZATION OF CLUBS.</p>
   <p>Most of the clubs have already started to meet again but those Leaders who have not called their groups together are requested to do so at once so that all of us will be functioning by the time the New Year arrives.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
