<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-05-15">May 15, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[Funeral Services Held for Jewish Hero]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1281</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1281.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1914-05-15">May 15, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[FUNERAL SERVICES HELD FOR JEWISH HERO]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Jewish hero, Samuel Meisenberg, is not to be found among the living any more. With the greatest honors that any nation can bestow on her beloved son, whose name will forever be read in the history of our mighty nation, he was brought here to Chicago for his eternal rest.</p>
   <p>The governor, mayor, United States and state senators, congressmen, rabbis, and many prominent Chicago citizens, together with several hundred thousands of other citizens have honored the hero by eulogizing the fallen Jewish sailor and the race of which he is a descendant.</p>
   <p>About 9 A. M. the parents, sisters, and brothers of Samuel Meisenberg arrived at the chapel of Weinstein and Neirman for the final farewell to their beloved son and brother.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1282.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The mother could not hold back her tears and her hysterical cries were so heartbreaking to the many thousands in and around the chapel that they also could not hold back their tears.</p>
   <p>The great mass of people remained silent and stood at attention when the body was carried out of the chapel for the funeral procession. The parents and close relatives stood close to the hearse except the mother, too weak to stand, who was placed in an automobile to follow the procession. The streets around, and the street where the procession passed by, were massed with people. On the roofs, and at windows, men, women, and children were waving American flags, honoring the dead hero who had shed his young blood in defense of the American flag.</p>
   <p>Never before in the history of Chicago, has the public paid such great honors to any one of its citizens, as was witnessed yesterday at the funeral procession of Samuel Meisenberg.....</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1283.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The street cars and other activities in Douglas Park came to a standstill. Everybody took an interest in this funeral procession, and stood amazed looking at the great honor given that Jewish youth who sacrificed his young life for his adopted land, which is at present at war with Mexico.</p>
   <p>All military and civilian bodies assembled at Ogden and California avenues, where they met the hearse and the honorary pallbearers.</p>
   <p>The hearse at that point stopped, and Captain Robert Reoh, of the United States Army, rode out at the head of the procession, signaling for a stop. Governor Dunne, Mayor Harrison and Senator Lewis were already waiting at the Marks Nathan Orphans Home. These three officers <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1284.jpg" n="4"/>were received by a committee consisting of Mr. Benjamin J. Schiff, Samuel Phillipson, A. Margolis, A. Turner, and Dr. Switon, the superintendent. While waiting for the funeral these three prominent gentlemen were taken through all parts of the orphans home. When the funeral procession reached the home, the governor, Mayor Harrison, and Senator Lewis, were stationed at their designated places. Then over one hundred Jewish orphans from the home, in their Boy Scouts uniforms, with flags in their hands, and with their band, marched out on the street, and got in line with the other uniformed bodies.</p>
   <p>The participants in the funeral procession were as follows:</p>
   <p>(Military and civic organizations, official groups, social and fraternal organizations, etc., were listed here).</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1285.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Before the funeral procession reached the Anshe Knesses Israel Synagogue, Cantor Millkowsky with his choir met the hearse at a distance of a few blocks, where he stopped at the head of the procession and sang the usual Jewish funeral hymns.</p>
   <p>The procession stopped at the synagogue, and eight soldiers carried the body inside, where the large audience suddenly stood up to pay honor to the dead Jewish soldier. While the casket was being taken in to the synagogue to be placed near the holy ark, the large Chicago band played a funeral march, which made quite a sad impression on the great throng of people who were standing outside waiting for the speakers to get through with their eulogies.</p>
   <p>A holy silence reigned in the synagogue, when Mr. Salk, the president of the synagogue, introduced Mr. B. Horvitz, the chairman of the funeral <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1286.jpg" n="6"/>committee. Mr. Horvitz expressed his deepest sympathy and also the feeling of the entire Jewish public in Chicago, which mourns the loss of this Jewish youth who made the supreme sacrifice. He depicted the ways of Russia and Roumania, who bury their fallen soldiers right on the battlefield.</p>
   <p>No other country in the world pays honor to its dead soldiers like this mighty nation.</p>
   <p>Mr. Horvitz also related how the Jews in Roumania mobilized themselves and went to the battlefields against Bulgaria.</p>
   <p>Roumania, solemnly promised the Jews full equal citizens right as compensation for their patriotism but no sooner had the clouds passed and danger of war was over, than the Roumanian government withdrew its promise, and the Jewish soldiers remained with no equal rights.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1287.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>The rabbi of the synagogue, Mr. Ephraim Epstein, was the next speaker. His eulogy caused many of his listeners to weep.</p>
   <p>Mayor Carter Harrison was the next to eulogize the young Jewish patriot.</p>
   <p>Governor Edward F. Dunne, in the name of the state, expressed the sentiment of all citizens of all classes who are united in this hour of sorrow, over the death of the young patriot, who in such short time in this country, adopted American ways and customs, and got into the habit of such love and respect for his new adopted land that he was ready at a moment's notice to shed his blood in a war against nation who dared to touch the honor of the United States. As soon as the governor was through with his heart-touching eulogy, Cantor Millkowsky and his choir sang some more traditional Jewish funeral hymns. The chairman then introduced our Jewish Congressman A. J. Sabath.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1288.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>His eulogy was as follows:- "There are no words which I can utter, that can add to the gratitude and respect the city of Chicago has shown our hero, Samuel Meisenberg, the defender of the American flag. I must however express my happiness over the fact that these foreign young men, especially the Jewish young men, were the first ones on the list when they were needed to defend the honor of our land and flag.</p>
   <p>"This land of ours is the biggest land under God's Heavens, a land which has done so much for the oppressed and the tortured. It was this spirit that took Samuel Meisenberg to Vera Cruz, Mexico, where he gave his life for the cause of freedom and brotherly love."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1289.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>Mayor Harrison praised the Jews in his eulogy, which was as follows:</p>
   <p>"We have assembled here today to bestow the last honor on a young man, who presented the most cherished gift he possessed to his country. Yes his country, although he was born in a foreign land. It is because he was loyal to the land which adopted him, that we have witnessed in the last few days the respect shown to this young man by the American nation. When his body and those of his comrades reached New York, the President of the United States, members of his cabinet, the army, navy, civil authorities and a million people or more, joined in honoring these fallen heroes. In Chicago, hundreds of thousands of people bowed their heads in sorrow while the procession passed through the streets. Tens of thousands of people passed by the casket of this young Jewish hero while he lay in state at the City Hall.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1290.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>"It is said that the race of which Meisenberg is a descendant, has no homeland, but in this case a Jew who came with his children from Russia to America, in ten years made this his land. This family thought so much of its newland, that one of the children sacrificed himself for its honor."</p>
   <p>Judge Hugo Pam, also gave a eulogy.</p>
   <p>Rabbi Saul Silber spoke as follows:</p>
   <p>"None of us knows what is in store for us, even to the next minute. On the South of us, we see a great crisis, but when the time comes to bring freedom to an oppressed nation, thousands of us assembled here, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1291.jpg" n="11"/>will do the same as this young Meisenberg and his comrades did."</p>
   <p>A few words from Dr. Joseph Stoltz: - "Not since the day when Osser Levy, one of twenty-three Jewish pioneers at New Amsterdam in 1654, applied for military duties, and was refused because he was a Jew, have the grandchildren of the Maccabees shirked military duties. With great pride and happiness, they have taken their part in all war conflicts since the battle of Bunker Hill."</p>
   <p>Senator Lewis also spoke suggesting the inscription for his monument:</p>
   <p>"Samuel Meisenberg, born a Jew, lived like an American and died a patriot."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1292.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>At the end of the services the eight soldiers acting as pallbearers carried the casket out for the funeral procession to the cemetery. Among the many beautiful wreaths of flowers, one of unusual size conspicuously placed, was from President Wilson. The card on the President's wreath bore only two words - "The President."</p>
   <p>At the cemetery further ceremonies and speeches had been arranged. Cantor Reichlin, accompanied by his choir, rendered a vocal selection from a Hebrew prayer. Then the United States Marine Corps played the navy funeral march which was followed by three salutes fired by eight soldiers. Finally the casket containing the body was lowered into the open grave.</p>
   <p>The parents, sisters, and brothers of Samuel Meisenberg, returned to their home where they will observe the week of mourning according to the Mosaic law of Israel.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
