<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-06">Jan. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">House Committee Stops Hearings on Immigration Bill</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1674</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1674.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-06">Jan. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">HOUSE COMMITTEE STOPS HEARINGS ON IMMIGRATION BILL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Washington, January 5: Chairman Johnson of the House Immigration Committee has decided not to hold any more hearings because it is impossible for the House Committee to come to an understanding with the Senate Immigration Committee about the newly proposed bill. Congressman Johnson thinks that until such an understanding has been reached, it is useless to listen to more witnesses.</p>
   <p>Congressman Siegel declared that under the circumstances, it is doubtful whether the Jewish leaders will have an opportunity to refute the false accusations that have been made about Jewish immigrants before the House Committee.</p>
   <p>We learn that the American-Jewish Committee, the immigration committee of the Jewish Congress, The Hias, The A. A. B. A. (Independent Order Brith Abraham), and other Jewish organizations have formed a joint committee which has elected a subcommittee, to co-operate with the non-Jewish representative groups that are interested in killing the planned anti-immigration bill. It is understood <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1675.jpg" n="2"/>that Louis Marshall, Dr. Stephen Wise and a representative of the Hias (Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society) will appear before the Senate Committee to defend Jewish immigration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
