<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-03-05">Mar. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Youth Movement</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1459</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1459.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-03-05">Mar. 5, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE YOUTH MOVEMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is a youth movement on foot for the purpose of improving Jewish life in the community by acquainting themselves with the Jewish language, literature, history, etc. This movement is growing from day to day, and there is no doubt that at least one thousand Jewish youths have organized and joined different Jewish clubs. We can also state that there are already five hundred young Maccabees taking quite an interest in this new movement.</p>
   <p>It is interesting, however, to note the position of the adults, mediators, welfare workers, and others, to the youth movement; the interest they take in the youth, and the attention they give them.</p>
   <p>Now, I will say something special in reference to the young Maccabees' clubs. The young Maccabees' organization is the largest youth organization in Chicago to stand on the top of the ladder in the youth movement. I am personally wrapped up in the Maccabean youth's welfare, and have particularly noticed the position of the Jewish public at large toward the youth and their new movement. I hope that the Chicago Jews will show their interest in this youth movement and understand the importance of the problems of these <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1460.jpg" n="2"/>young people, remembering the old saying, "Our youth is our future, and our youth is our nation." So now, will you Jews take a hand in this movement in behalf of the Jewish youth. And, it would be so gratifying to the children. They would be so thrilled by the phenomenon of new faces in the movement!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
