<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-04">May 4, 1919</date><title level="a">The Convention of the Workmen's Circle.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0089</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0089.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-04">May 4, 1919</date><title level="a">THE CONVENTION OF THE WORKMEN'S CIRCLE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today, in Detroit, is the opening of the annual convention of the Workmen's Circle, which will be attended by hundreds of delegates from many states.</p>
   <p>We cannot, this year, expect a very strong session for there are no new issues and old ones have been exhausted. The rift between the youth and the elders may yet be marked, but not as the main characteristic of the convention. With everything working smoothly there will be the usual administrative routine, and then the adjournment.</p>
   <p>The possibilities are that everything may not proceed as planned, because of the movement on foot among the ranks, which is not comprehended by the older leaders, the movement--Back to Judaism.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0090.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The more the Workmen's Circle becomes Americanized and their members acclimatized, the further estranged they become from the old Bundist traditions, brought here from across the Ocean, and the nearer they get to their Judaism. Many of the prominent members look back on their old Bundist past with varied sentiments. Living here, in the prevalence of religious freedom, they have acquired religious tolerance, and recall, with heartache, those days in which a display of religious intolerance made itself felt even toward their parents.</p>
   <p>Today the Workmen's Circle, we say this to their credit, is no longer Bundist, but an American-Jewish workingmen's organization, with high and noble human aims, becoming, from day to day more Jewish-minded. Their principle purpose is yet, and must continue to be, the material welfare of the members, to help them in time of need and illness, defending the widows and the orphans. Near these purely social-economic <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0091.jpg" n="3"/>and social-ethical activities have sprung up a marked new desire to care, more or less, for the spiritual welfare of their members, and especially for that of the young generation.</p>
   <p>When so strong an organization, as the Workmen's Circle, recalls as its duty the activities of cultural work, it must get closer to Judaism. What other cultural work should it choose? The Japanese, or Arabian? The Polish or Turkish? A Jewish Mass organization desirous of such ends cannot limit itself to a colorless spiritual culture; as, geometry or geography, or other general subjects. Thus, it must align itself with the Jewish. If we are not falsely informed, there are many members who staunchly demand that the Workmen's Circle devote itself to a broad program of Jewish culture.</p>
   <p>These new tendencies, in far circles of the organization, explain why there is this strong interest for Jewish education of the young. Nevertheless<pb facs="5423972_9_1_0092.jpg" n="4"/>the, it will also not be surprising to hear that at the Detroit convention, the desire for Judaism collapsed-in which case the convention will not operate so smoothly. The older, more conservative elements in whom the Bundist traditions are yet strongly imbued, because they have learned nothing and forgotten nothing, will, naturally, be displeased with the development of this new tendency and present a strong opposition. From such an instance, which must not occur, yet which may, the words "old" and "young" derive an entirely new meaning. The old against Judaism, the young for it. Should the young stand steadfastly for an absolute Jewish program, then the spectacular would begin. But should this Jewish tendency, at the convention, hold its own it will act as an important factor at a second or third convention; the development of Judaism in the ranks of organized workers being as yet, without much support.</p>
   <p>But should the Worker's Circle become permeated with Jewish spirit then it becomes the second strongest organization among Jews. We hope the <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0093.jpg" n="5"/>organization can assume this position in American Judaism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
