<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-07-24">July 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Zionist "Revolution."</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0867</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0867.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-07-24">July 24, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A ZIONIST "REVOLUTION."</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An article was recently published in the Courier about the upsetting of the English Jewry, telling how the leaders of the conjoint committee, the real traditions of the English Jewry, lost their power, and how the Zionists came into power of the British Jewry. This announcement was exciting and interesting. Now, two months later, when all the details of the struggle are explained and the facts of the story are known from beginning to end, we are commencing to realize the significance of the revolution, in the complete triumph of the Zionist direction over the group favoring assimilation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0868.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The revolution was caused by the conjoint committee's (a committee in which all Jewish organizations are represented) adopting a resolution declaring the position of English Jewry on the question of Jewish Palestine. The resolution was published in the London Times, and started a storm of protests. The resolution expressed its sanction of a Jewish center but not of a Jewish Palestine.</p>
   <p>The Jews in England may perhaps be non-Zionists and even anti-Zionists, but to oppose Zionism personally is one thing, and to come out in an open statement rejecting the Jewish nation and Zionism, is an entirely different thing. A resolution was submitted by a member of the conjoint committee which expressed the protest of the dissatisfied and the feeling of mistrust and lack of confidence that the resolution has aroused in the minds of the members against the leaders.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0869.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Lord Rothschild and many prominent Jews never formerly connected with the Zionist movement, nor even sympathetic to it, were strongest in the protest against the anti-Zionist leaders' attitude.</p>
   <p>We were deeply interested in the personality of the member of the conjoint committee, who brought in the resolution to criticize the leaders, and in that manner became the cause of the revolution. He was Elias Zeitlin, a son of the Wilno Moreh Harohe (one who decides matters of rabbinical law), born in London. He is a noted attorney and a scholarly Jew, greatly interested in Jewish matters. We had the opportunity to become intimate with him in the office of the Jewish Courier last winter when he visited Chicago on business for a short time and came to the West Side every day looking for a kosher meal.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0870.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Mr. Zeitlin, in short debates we had with him pertaining to Jewish activities, proved to be opposed to Zionism. His opposition was based on personal conversations with some of the Zionist leaders who are not conscientious enough...To argue with a Zionist against Zionism, for this or that reason, is one thing; but to reject Zionism as a national home for Jews is an entirely different thing, Mr. Zeitlin believes.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zeitlin's resolution was accepted and supported by Lord Rothschild, and some of the leaders of the conjoint committee resigned.</p>
   <p>That this Zionist revolution will cause a turmoil in the political representation of Jews in England, can be surmised from an interview, by the London Jewish Chronicle with Lieutenant Commander Wedgeworth, a member of the English parliament. This prominent Englishman urged <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0871.jpg" n="5"/>Zionists to organize and be prepared for the reconstruction of a Jewish state in Palestine. He said, "One turn of the wheel, the least move, will render Palestine to the Jews," and he wants to know if the Jews themselves will be prepared for such an occasion. He urged that the Jewish members of the English parliament head such an organization and if the present members of parliament are not Zionists, then it is time for the English Jews to replace the non-Zionists in parliament.</p>
   <p>When an English member of the parliament makes such statements, then the Jews may surely live in hope.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
