<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-04-21">Apr. 21, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[New Synagogue in Albany Park]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0663</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0663.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-04-21">Apr. 21, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[NEW SYNAGOGUE IN ALBANY PARK]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>You know, don't you, that Albany Park is neither Kamchatka nor Sakhalin, but is a nice neighborhood in Chicago, and that many fine people live in Albany Park, among them being a group of very fine Jews. Though the number of Jews in Albany Park is not as large as the number who took part in the exodus from Egypt, neverthelses they are sufficiently numerous to keep up their own synagogue with a Talmud Torah and to have a rabbi who is the most learned and educated rabbi in Chicago. I refer to my friend and your friend, Dr. Isaac Milner, who knows more languages than you, but is not bald-headed.</p>
   <p>They also have a Jew in Albany Park whose name is Perlstein. This Mr. Perlstein keeps the Jews of Albany Park awake--they need it--and just now he has aroused <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0664.jpg" n="2"/>them to the point where they are ready to build a new synagogue, a new Talmud Torah, and to reorganize the whole Jewish life in Albany Park. I wish the Jews of Sheridan Park and Rogers Park were like that.</p>
   <p>On Sunday there will be a celebration in Albany Park: the ceremony of laying the cornerstone for the new Congregation Beth Itzchok [of Albany Park] will take place. In Albany Park a synagogue doesn't have the same significance that it has on the North Side. A synagogue in Albany Park means a center of Jewish life.</p>
   <p>Mr. Perlstein, the man who keeps the Jews of Albany Park awake, and his friends, deserve our thanks. Thanks are also due to our friend, Dr. Milner. He has helped to build a Jewish community in Albany Park.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
