<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-04">Aug. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[Mr. Weil and Congregation Anshe Sholom]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0653</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0653.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-04">Aug. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[MR. WEIL AND CONGREGATION ANSHE SHOLOM]</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Dr. S. M. Melamed</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>My friend, your friend, our mutual friend, Mr. Joseph Weil, the chief of the [synagogue] presidents, the president of Congregation Anshe Sholom, is very, very busy. Nobody sees him, nobody ever hears of him. I thought at first that Mr. Weil had withdrawn from the limelight to write a book about immortality, but then I learned that he was busy decorating his synagogue, so that the Jews who attend his synagogue would experience spiritual pleasure. I do not mean to say that our friend Mr. Weil has become a decorator or has entered the decorating business. Oh, no! Mendel Brothers are taking care of the decorating because Mr. Weil says that the decoration of the Congregation Anshe Sholom must be really artistic and modern, and not just a smearing of lions and bears on the walls such as one can see in many old-fashioned synagogues. Mendel Brothers are well qualified to do an artistic job because they have decorated theaters, temples of art, and palaces of the rich, and thus can be expected to do a good job of decorating Congregation Anshe Sholom.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0654.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>I can, therefore, imagine that the work of Mendel Brothers will find favor in the eyes of the members of the synagogue, but that will happen after the synagogue is so beautifully decorated that the esthetic senses of the members of the synagogue are satisfied, and Mr. Weil will no longer be as busy as he is now? Will he and his beautifully decorated, large and rich synagogue do something for the Hebrew Theological College; will they help build a few more Talmud Torahs in Chicago; will they start to work in behalf of the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization]? What about the Association of Synagogue Presidents of which Mr. Joseph Weil is the president?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
