<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-05-03">May 3, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">The Convention of the B'nai B'rith.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0306</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0306.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-05-03">May 3, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">THE CONVENTION OF THE B'NAI B'RITH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The question was submitted to the convention for discussion yesterday, whether this order shall continue to operate as a secret society. The debate that followed disclosed that the delegates to the convention, were divided into three camps. The liberals, in favor of discontinuing the rituals, a second group, favoring the continuance of the present ritual, and a third group which insisted, that the old Hebrew customs should be even more pronounced at the ritual than it has been. This last-mentioned group was victorious, although by a small majority. But this is not considered to be final. This subject will be discussed again during this week's sessions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0307.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The program dealing with changes to be undertaken, includes the important one of electing the president. Up to the present time, this official was elected by the executive committee. The recommendation has been submitted, that in the future, the president should be elected by the convention. This change in the constitution, has been submitted by the younger element of the order, with the sole purpose of giving a younger man, worthy of the honor, a chance to assume such responsibility, and to bring about more activity, which is the privilege of the young.</p>
   <p>The association of former presidents of the Chicago Grand Lodge, district No. 6, gave a banquet at the Auditorium last night, in honor of the delegates. Philip Stein was master of ceremonies. The speakers were:</p>
   <p>Julius Bien, New York, president of the order of B'nai B'rith; <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0308.jpg" n="3"/>Miss Della Herzog, Chicago; J. Kantrowitz, New York; Jacob Furth, St. Louis; Jacob Singer, Philadelphia; Jacob Jieto, San Francisco; Lionel C. Levy, Columbus, Ga.; Henry Greenebaum, Chicago; Leo N. Levi, New York; Sigmund Bergel, Berlin; Josiah Cohen, Pittsburgh; and Joseph Rothschild, San Francisco.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
