<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-11">Feb. 11, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Tzdokoh and Torah</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-11">Feb. 11, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">TZDOKOH AND TORAH</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Anyone who investigates the activities of the Reform Jews will soon realize that they place the weight of Judaism, or what appears to them to be Judaism, on Tzdokoh [Translator's note: Hebrew word meaning righteousness, justice, or alms], and not so much on Tzdokoh as on charity. Charity and Tzdokoh are two different things. The difference between charity and Tzdokoh lies in the interpretation of these two concepts. Charity, from the Greek word Charitus (Sic), means love--love in its broadest sense, that is, love of humanity--in contrast to Eros, which means a particular kind of love. Charity--Charitus--is optional, and is not a duty, whereas Tzdokoh is a duty--a duty like any other civic duty from which we cannot escape. Tzdokoh means justice and anyone who does not give Tzdokoh [here Tzdokoh means alms] is a sinner--a person who refuses to pay his debt to the poor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0612.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As Tzdokoh is, according to the Jewish concept, a duty and is not optional, Judaism lays as much weight on Tzdokoh as on any other social and ethical duty, no more and no less.</p>
   <p>The Reform Jews, however, contend that Tzdokoh is not [merely] one of the ethical, religious, or social duties which Judaism imposes upon the individual, but that Tzdokoh is the sole duty, the chief duty, the only and exclusive duty of the Jewish religion; that Tzdokoh is the main issue; that all others are side issues, and that Tzdokoh is actually identified with Judaism.</p>
   <p>If the Reform Jews had in mind the ancient Jewish concept of Tzdokoh, it would not be so bad. One could say then that in one specific sense, they agreed with the ancient Jewish point of view. But what the Reform Jew actually has in mind is not Jewish Tzdokoh, but Christian charity, because Christianity adopted the ancient Greek concept of charity and made it a part of its whole ethic. Consequently, when the Reform Jews emphasize charity above all other things, they not only adulterate Judaism by seeking to narrow it down to merely <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0613.jpg" n="3"/>one of the many Jewish concepts, but as charity is not Tzdokoh, they seek to place Judaism on a Christian foundation.</p>
   <p>Every educated Jew knows that the main thing in Judaism is not Tzdokoh, and certainly not charity; the most important thing in Judaism is the Torah. It is not written [in Scriptures] that Tzdokoh stands above everything, but it is clearly and explicitly written that the Torah stands above all else. Judaism emphasizes, above everything else, the Torah, i.e., intellect, rather than sentiment. Not even the Hebrew conception of Tzdokoh is based on sentiment. Judaism thinks little or nothing of the sentiment of Tzdokoh, i.e., charity which is based on emotions and sentimentality. Only that which we give out of duty; that whch we give with the conscience that we are not giving charity to the poor, but are simply giving that which is due them; that which we must give them; that which they are absolutely entitled to, is highly commended by the Jewish religion. This, however, is not the charity that the Reform Jews have in mind; otherwise they would not separate the work of compassion from the [work of the] community or synagogue, and would not make charity a special <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0614.jpg" n="4"/>issue. Among Jews, charitable work has always been connected with the whole work of the community, with the religious and educational activity. Just as every community has had its synagogues and boards of education, so every community has had its charitable institutions, which constituted an organic pact of the whole. Now the Reform Jews have separated the charitable institutions from the other parts of the community, because they decided to emphasize philanthropy and to declare that philanthropy is the most important thing in Judaism.</p>
   <p>This is a vulgarization of Judaism, because philanthropy, even if it is not charity but is actually Tzdokoh, is not the most important thing in Judaism. The most important thing is learning, and this has been abolished by the Reform Jews who have placed Judaism on an entirely new foundation. By putting Judaism on this new foundation, the strong partition, the only real partition separating Judaism from Christianity has disappeared. Christianity, being an anti-intellectual religion--a religion that does not lay great stress upon knowledge or upon the mind, but rather upon the blind senses--had to make <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0615.jpg" n="5"/>charity its essential basis. If not charity, what could Christianity offer the individuals or society?</p>
   <p>When we see the Reform Jews so intensely engaged in charitable work and laying such great stress upon charity, we often become inspired by their work and become inclined to make peace with them. The truth is, however, that the charity of the Reform Jews is not Jewish but Christian in principle, and must, sooner or later, lead to a peace between Christianity and Judaism. From a peace between Christianity and Judaism, Christianity will gain everything and Judaism will lose everything.</p>
   <p>Charity is not the most important thing in Judaism, nor is the charity of the Reform Jews, Jewish charity. Jewish charity gives secretly, it gives to those with outstretched hands, etc., it is not "philanthropic," nor is it sentimental.</p>
   <p>The most important thing in Judaism is knowledge, and anyone who denies this denies Judaism. The Reform Jews do not believe in this.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
