<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-12-06">Dec. 6, 1905</date>, 18:1.
<title level="a">Bible in School? No</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-12-06">Dec. 6, 1905</date>, 18:1.
<title level="a">BIBLE IN SCHOOL? NO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Strong arguments against the use of the Bible in the public schools, and for the ousting of corrupt politicians, were advanced by Mrs. Henry Solomon at the opening session of the triennial national convention of the Council of Jewish Women in Sinai Temple last evening.</p>
   <p>An informal reception to delegates and friends occupied the afternoon. The council will hold sessions for a week, with delegates from every city of importance in the United States and hundreds of members of the Chicago circle in attendance.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Solomon, who organized the council nearly thirty years ago, and who has been its president continuously, delivered the principal address of last evening.</p>
   <p>Task For Mothers</p>
   <p>"Again and again the plea is made to place the Bible in our public schools, but there is no place for it," she said. "We are still too near Bible idolatry to secure teachers who will do justice to this great literature. It is better in <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0288.jpg" n="2"/>the hands of the mothers or Sabbath schools.</p>
   <p>"We must root our professional destroyers and the dens they infest. If our bad politicians could only undergo a political "Yom Kippur," in sackcloth and ashes, they would exclaim, 'We have grievously sinned.' It is a disheartening field for us. Private charities need state oversight. Aside from a few good charities hundreds are gathering funds spuriously. Look at Chicago free dispensaries as a sample."</p>
   <p>Greeted By Chicagoan</p>
   <p>Dr. Emil G. Hirsch pronounced the invocation and Miss Julia J. Felsenthal, president of the Chicago circle, welcomed the visitors. Harry Hart, president of Sinai congregation, lauded the women of Israel.</p>
   <p>In the annual report of the corresponding secretary Miss Sadie American of New York was told the national growth of the council. "The firm standing of the council may be adduced from the fact that five sections own buildings and one other conducts an <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0289.jpg" n="3"/>institution," she reported.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Josephine Lazarus of New York will read a paper on religion this evening. Other speakers will be Mrs. C. Misch of Providence, Mrs. J. Andrews of Boston, and Mrs. S. M. Blumauer of Portland, Oregon.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Women's Club will receive the delegates Monday afternoon. The original afternoon programme will be given that evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
