<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-13">May 13, 1910</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0264</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0264.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1910-05-13">May 13, 1910</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Public Cook Pot.</p>
   <p>Reign of Schulman in Order, Knights of Zion. - Deborah Organization to hold Installation. - Shekels committee starts working. - Are making arrangements for an excursion. - A May Party for Young Peoples Auxiliary, B. M. Z. - Concert and dance given by Institute Club. - Agudath Achim Auxiliary will hold an open meeting. - 5th annual banquet of Beth Mischa Orphan Home. - A May Party for the Hospital Aid Society. - Theater Party by the South Side Ladies Auxiliary, B. M. Z. - A dance by the Prospect Hospital Society. - People move and neighborhoods change.</p>
   <p>The time when Mr. Max Schulman was Grand Recorder of the Order Knights of Zion was indeed a fruitful period for the Zionists. With his faithful work and undaunted sincerity, he caused the Order to be recognized as a worthwhile federation. New posts were organized and old ones were strengthened. Contributions to Jewish National Fund and everything went along very nicely.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0265.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At the last convention, Mr. Schulman declined to continue as Grand Recorder and refrained from active participation in future activities. As a result, the Order has not accomplished anything worth while to date.</p>
   <p>However, now that the new Grand Recorder has resigned and the Vice-Recorder, Dr. Rosensweig takes his place, we can expect a return to Mr. Schulman.</p>
   <p>Last Wednesday a new Ladies Gate was formed and officers installed. They call themselves, the "Deborah Gate." Installation ceremonies were held at the Henry Booth House and a very fine program was presented.</p>
   <p>The meetings of the "Grand Gate" have been transferred to the Rev. Isaac Talmud Torah Building on Waller St. Last Thursday the Shekels committee met and decided to close the books of last year and start anew with a more ambitious program.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0266.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A Zionist outing is planned. A committee was appointed to arrange an excursion on one of the finest ships in the Chicago Harbor. A good time is assured all who plan to attend.</p>
   <p>This year marks the 50th birthday of Dr. Theodore Herzland, consequently Chicago is preparing a large celebration in honor of the memory of this great Jewish Zionist leader. Next Wednesday, the arrangement committee will meet at the Chicago Hebrew Institute to make complete plans for the occasion.</p>
   <p>The Young Peoples Auxiliary of the Old Peoples Home will, on next Sunday, celebrate their yearly May Party and Dance at the Masonic Temple Hall. The organization is interested in helping the Home wherever possible in the way of human necessities, things that make life easier for the old people.</p>
   <p>A concert and dance will be given by the Institute Club at the Chicago Hebrew <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0267.jpg" n="4"/>Institute next Sunday evening. A very entertaining program has been arranged.</p>
   <p>The auxiliary of the Hungarian Jewish synagogue, "Agudath Achim," will have an open meeting next Sunday, 2:30 P. M., at the Schiller Hall, 103 E. Randolph St. Friends of the synagogue are invited.</p>
   <p>The Hospital Aid Society, of which Miss Hannah Schulman is secretary, announces an open meeting and dance, Monday, Decoration Day. This is its second annual affair of this nature.</p>
   <p>The Prospect Hospital Aid Society will give a prize and a beautiful bouquet of flowers to the one who will sell the most tickets to their dance at the Masonic Drill Hall, on Monday, Decoration Day. The Prospect Hospital will be a Jewish Hospital on the Northwest Side.</p>
   <p>(Signed) The Cook Spoon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
