<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-10-09">Oct. 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A Voice from the Municipal Tuberculosis Sanitarium</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Z. Leibner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0701</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0701.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-10-09">Oct. 9, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A VOICE FROM THE MUNICIPAL TUBERCULOSIS SANITARIUM</title><title level="a" type="sub">by Z. Leibner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A voice full of earnestness and sincerity comes to us from the Chicago Municipal Tuberculosis Sanitarium, and the voice calls on the representatives of Orthodox Jews in Chicago--the rabbis--to become interested in the Jews who are confined in the institution for the sufferers from the white plague. The voice does not demand money, clothing, medicine or food, but a little friendliness, and words of comfort. The voice demands that the representatives of our orthodoxy shall perform the good deed of visiting the sick and let the word of God be heard among them.</p>
   <p>There are about one hundred sick Jews in the Chicago Municipal Tuberculosis Sanitarium, among them forty-five children. The majority are Orthodox, or of Orthodox parentage, who have never dreamed either of being the victims of the white plague or of being estranged from a Jewish environment, from God and his <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0702.jpg" n="2"/>Torah. Says the voice: "We are not criminals, yet we are sentenced to live apart from other human beings because we suffer from tuberculosis. It requires a great deal of effort to be cured even partially. We, of the older generation, who have absorbed a great deal of Judaism in our life, know how to keep up our traditions. We pray, we sometimes read a religious book and we maintain our Judaism as much as possible. But the children--even those children who received some Jewish training are becoming estranged. We, ourselves, and particularly our children, need someone to become interested in us. Our desire is to see here, as often as possible, our Orthodox rabbis. A Reformed rabbi does come around, but we do not like his 'preaching', and what sins have our little children committed that they should have to listen to a long-winded oration by a Reformed rabbi instead of listening to a true, warm Jewish word?</p>
   <p>"Rabbis! The duty of raising children is yours, and the duty of visiting is also yours, you, whom the Lord has blessed with health. 'Make good' then now that which you should have made good a long time ago, and for this deed, may you, your children and grandchildren be safeguarded from sickness and grief--Amen."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0703.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Let us hope that the voice of the sick Jews in the Chicago Municipal Tuberculosis Sanitarium shall not be a voice crying into the wilderness. Our esteemed rabbis should hold a meeting and resolve that one or two of them should pay a weekly visit to the sanitarium. They should also find a teacher to instruct the children a few hours a week. There are many good-hearted Jews in Chicago who would be willing to pay the teacher for his trouble.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
