<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>, 
            <date when="1927-09-23">September 23, 1927</date>.
        
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1563</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily Jewish Courier</title>, 
            <date when="1927-09-23">September 23, 1927</date>.
        </bibl>
   </div>
   <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1563.jpg" n="2"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>But where? Wohin? America bars them with the quota. Canada? Restrictions- limitations- quotas! Mexico? No opportunities. And so much for the places where Jews want to go. Where then shall they go? Wohin?</p>
   <p>Numbers are answering that question by going to South America. Some to Argentine. Some to Brazil, Uruguay, Peru. During 1926, upward of 8,000 went to the republics south of the equator, seeking there the opportunity denied them here and elsewhere. More will go this year, still more the next.</p>
   <p>But in the new countries they have no one to whom they can look for help during the first hard period. The Jewish wanderer needs a powerful organization to guard his interests from the time he takes the wanderer's staff in hand and goes forth.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1564.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This is what Hias, Ica and Emig - have united to do. It will take $500,000 to do this work this year. Hias is your representative in the field of Jewish immigration. It has acted for you during the past forty years. Help it now to extend its activities to meet the new Jewish world need. Chicago is asked to contribute $50,000.</p>
   <p>The New Year will soon be upon us. It will be brighter for you if you will help to make it brighter to multitudes of your brethren to whom without your help it offers little hope or encouragement. Greater than to have is to share. Greater than to ask blessings for self is to scatter blessings to others. Greater than any individual's position in life is service to the needy of his brethren and all mankind. As you meditate on this noble New Year message, we ask you not to forget Hias.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1565.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Appeals will be made in a number of congregations during the holiday services. Adolph Copeland is general chairman of the Chicago drive. Emil Brande is chairman of synagogue appeals. Headquarters are at 1214 S. Clinton Street. Telephone Canal 6469.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
