<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-12">Mar. 12, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">North Shore Congregation Bnai Israel Formally Opened Yesterday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0533</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0533.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-12">Mar. 12, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">NORTH SHORE CONGREGATION BNAI ISRAEL FORMALLY OPENED YESTERDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the past few years, many Orthodox Jews have moved into the North Shore district, which is considered one of the finest residential districts in Chicago. Yesterday the Orthodox community there celebrated the dedication of the first Orthodox congregation in that neighborhood. The North Shore Congregation Bnai Israel, which was organized five years ago by a group of devoted worshippers, has grown since then into a congregation of more than two hundred members. Yesterday, the dedication of the new building at Kenmore Avenue and Argyle Street, took place. When this building is completed, it will have cost more than a quarter of a million dollars, according to the architectural plans; it will be one of the most beautiful religious buildings in the city.</p>
   <p>The first floor of the building was opened yesterday as a synagogue, social <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0534.jpg" n="2"/>center, and Hebrew school. Large sums of money were contributed on this occasion. The first mitzvah of opening the massive wooden doors of the synagogue was sold to Mrs. L. Rosen for $500, while her husband purchased the mitzvah of lighting the Eternal Light [a light that burns continuously above the altar] for $200.</p>
   <p>Keys to open the doors of the classrooms, meeting rooms, and social center, were sold to Mr. and Mrs. Truk, Mr. and Mrs. Zimberoff, Jacob Rosenthal, Mr. and Mrs. Charles Levy, Mr. and Mrs. Burdikoff, and Mr. and Mrs. Stone.</p>
   <p>A donation of $50 for the mitzvah of opening the Hebrew school received a tremendous ovation. The money had been raised by members of the Junior Auxiliary, composed of pupils of the Hebrew classes. The Auxiliary had been organized by Mrs. D. Almond, in the form of an educational club. The mitzvah of opening the door was given to Arnold Cohen, Florence Penkow, Gabriel Almond, and Jeannette Levy.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0535.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The dedication speech was delivered by Rabbi David Almond, rabbi of the North Shore Congregation since the very first day it opened. Rabbi Saul Silber followed with a brilliant talk on "Traditional Judaism".</p>
   <p>The directors of the Congregation decided that no time should be lost in completing the second story [of the building].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
