<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-09">Aug. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">After Ten Years</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1399</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.8"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1399.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-08-09">Aug. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">AFTER TEN YEARS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ten years ago today, a group of young, Orthodox Jews founded the Sons of Israel Association, at 1133 South Ashland Boulevard. The Association was an organization of Orthodox youth, which sought to strengthen Judaism within its own ranks and to spread and strengthen Jewish traditions among all the Jewish groups of Chicago. The mere fact that there is such a group of idealistic young men in Chicago, and that their organization could continue to exist for ten years and to be effective during all those years, inspires as much joy as the sight of an oasis in the desert.</p>
   <p>The Sons of Israel Association has not increased its membership to any great extent during the ten years of its existence. The entire membership of the Association and its four branches is about three hundred. The Association, has, nevertheless, shown itself to be of considerable importance. It has produced <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1400.jpg" n="2"/>a number of rabbis, among them Rabbi [Benjamin] Daskal, Rabbi Rosenbloom, and a few others. The Sons of Israel Association is an active organization. Neither its leaders nor its members are asleep. Representatives of the Sons of Israel Association can be found at every meeting which is devoted to Jewish affairs. Members of the Association can be found at meetings to consider the problem of kosher food, at relief meetings, at Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization] meetings, at Zionist meetings, and so on. They not only perform general Jewish work in Chicago but they do all the Mizrachi [Orthodox group in Zionist organization] work in Chicago because most, if not all, of the members of the Sons of Israel Association are also Mizrachi members, whose basis of activity is the Basel program.</p>
   <p>The young men of the Sons of Israel Association should be given credit for their initiative and activity. For a long time they maintained a Jewish employment bureau for those who wished to observe the Sabbath. They have always shown and proved that they take their Judaism seriously. The young men of the Sons of <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1401.jpg" n="3"/>Israel Association seek to increase and broaden their own knowledge of Judaism, besides being active in all spheres of Jewish life in Chicago. They have a Talmudic study circle every Saturday. They arrange a series of lectures during the year on various Jewish subjects. Many of them are studying and are trying to educate themselves as Orthodox Jews.</p>
   <p>It is a credit to Chicago as well as a credit to these idealistic and serious young Jewish men that the Sons of Israel Association, an active, effective and idealistic group, has lived to celebrate its tenth birthday anniversary. One can be sure that the Chicago Orthodoxy has a future because young active forces live within it, because hundreds of young Jewish men are to be found in Chicago who seriously devote themselves to the Jewish problem and to their own education in Judaism.</p>
   <p>The Sons of Israel Association deserves the sympathy and support of every Orthodox Jew in Chicago because these young men of today will be the leaders and representatives of tomorrow. We congratulate the Sons of Israel Association upon <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1402.jpg" n="4"/>the celebration of its tenth anniversary. We hope that it will continue in the future, as it has in the past, to strengthen Judaism in Chicago and that it will continue to participate in all Jewish affairs.</p>
   <p>The only way to help strengthen Judaism in Chicago is to be active. The members of the Sons of Israel Association have been active up to now and they will surely continue to be so in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
