<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-09-15">Sept. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[Knesses Israel Nusach Sford Synagogue]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0631</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0631.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II F</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-09-15">Sept. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">[KNESSES ISRAEL NUSACH SFORD SYNAGOGUE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dedication of the new Knesses Israel Nusach Sford Synagogue will take place next Sunday at 1:30 P. M. The new synagogue is at 1308 Independence Boulevard.</p>
   <p>The Knesses Israel Nusach Sford Synagogue is the result of an amalgamation of three congregations: Anshe Garaditch Uhabne at Racine Avenue and Taylor Street, Anshe Maarov Nusach Sford, 15th Street and Homan Avenue, and Nusach Sford, 14th and Miller Streets. These three congregations have merged into one congregation, and are building a magnificent new synagogue on Independence Boulevard, which will be the pride of the Lawndale district. The new synagogue will cost about two hundred thousand dollars and will occupy two floors. The first floor will have several rooms and will serve as a large modern Talmud Torah and kindergarten. There will be a room devoted to daily religious services. There will be a dining room and a kitchen where kosher food will be prepared for various public dinners.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0632.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The synagogue will occupy the second floor. It will have sixteen hundred seats. The synagogue is very beautifully constructed. When it is finished, it will be a beautiful building from within as well as without.</p>
   <p>The building committee consists of Mr. A. Friedman, chairman; Nachman Maltz, treasurer; B. Golub, secretary; and I. Korogodsky, Zeb Goldsmith, L. Korogodsky, and Eisenberg.</p>
   <p>The dedication of the new synagogue will begin with a parade. The members of each congregation will gather at their former synagogue and then march to the Anshe Maarov Nusach Sford Synagogue, at Homan Avenue and 15th Street. All three congregations will march from there, preceded by a band, to the new synagogue, where a magnificent program is scheduled. Rabbis Rabinowitz and [Nisan] Budzinski will address the gathering. Cantor Weinhorn, with his choir, will sing several prayers. Refreshments will be served. A big crowd is expected.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
