<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-23">Mar. 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Build a Dam</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1394</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1394.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-03-23">Mar. 23, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">BUILD A DAM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When a river overflows its banks, a flood is unavoidable, but before it overflows its banks, something can be done to hold back the threatening deluge. A dam can be built to check and drive back the rising waters. We Jews in the western countries are in a situation today similar to a house near a river whose waters are constantly rising and threatening to inundate and destroy the house. The fast and turbulent life in the western countries undermines the basis of Jewish life.</p>
   <p>The environment in which we live is washing away section after section of the Jewish nation. The youth is slowly but surely drifting away from us; the Jewish mother has no interest in the Jewish education of her children; the intelligentsia are gradually leaving us, and even the masses of Jews are losing sight of their Jewish consciousness. Around us swirl unfriendly waters <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1395.jpg" n="2"/>and our house stands in danger of being swept away. It is still not too late to build a dam against these unfriendly waters which are rising higher and higher and are threatening to engulf us.</p>
   <p>Truthfully speaking, we have always built such dams. What else have served as fences and walls against unfriendly waters, if not dams? But never have dams been as necessary to protect the Jewish house against unfriendly waters as today, because never have we been so exposed to the danger of assimilation as today. We must help any group of people who wish to build or help build a dam because they are doing the work that every conscientious Jew should do.</p>
   <p>In Chicago there is a group of young Jewish men known as the "Adath Bnai Israel". These men are engaged in building a dam. They seek to attract the youth to Jewish traditions; they are organizing the youth on a religious and nationalistic basis; they are helping to restore the Sabbath and all the other great institutions of the Jewish religion; they are doing everything they possibly can to build a dam, and it is, therefore, the duty of every <pb n="3"/> sincere Jew to help them.</p>
   <p>The Adath Bnai Israel is doing a great deal of good work. It is organizing courses in Jewish studies; it does religious and Zionist work, and it takes an interest in everything that concerns Judaism. It is a small group, but it has a great deal of energy and initiative. At the present moment, the group is engaged in organizing a Jewish center in the Lawndale district. Such a center is definitely needed. In Chicago there are plenty of places where the Jewish youth can dance and amuse itself, but there is not one place where the Jewish youth of Chicago can spend an evening in a strictly Jewish atmosphere. If the members of the Adath Bnai Israel are now working to establish a Jewish center in the largest Jewish district in Chicago, we should help them because we should help all those who are trying to build a dam.</p>
   <p>We do not necessarily have to agree with everything that the Adath Bnai Israel does, but their principle of building a dam is sound, and we must, therefore, support them. If the Adath Bnai Israel had three thousand instead of three <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1396.jpg" n="4"/>hundred members, Judaism in Chicago would assume a different appearance. The stronger such groups like the Adath Bnai Israel become, the better it will be for Judaism and for the preservation of Jewish life. Groups like the Adath Bnai Israel, stand like an iron wall between the Jewish people and the threat of assimilation, because they are building a dam against unfriendly waters which threaten to destroy our house.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
