<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Jewish Labor World</title>,
<date when="1917-12-01">December 1, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Hirsch Steps Out against Zionism.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1721</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1721.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Daily World</title>,
<date when="1917-12-01">December 1, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">DR. HIRSCH STEPS OUT AGAINST ZIONISM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Emil Hirsch, noted reform rabbi of Sinai Temple, opposed Zionism in an article of today's Herald. Dr. Hirsch asserts that Jews are not a nation. His home is in every country where he lives. Now, when Russia is being democratized, the afflicted Jew should find a better home than in Palestine. Dr. Hirsch said that the future of the Jews lies in the nation which they inhabit. The Jews are no nation. Jews fight against Jews on the battle field. The German-Jew fights against the English-Jew. The Jew fights in every army, for the flag that flies above him. He is a citizen of that land, where he obtains citizen rights.</p>
   <p>The democratized Russia is a much better home for the suppressed Jews than Palestine. Democracy, the new order of the world, will break the last barrier between Christian and Jew. "I am against those who want to return to Palestine," said Dr. Hirsch. "If I were informed that there is an opportunity to go there, I would give those people my blessing.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1722.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"First of all, Palestine is the birth of Christianity, Mohammedanism, and Judaism. The Jewish population is approximately 100,000 among a population of 600,000.</p>
   <p>"The religion and the right of ownership by the great majority of those citizens must be respected. The Arabs have a strong national movement. The Jews are morally obligated to consider many things, before they establish such a state, as is planned by the Zionists. Will we be happy there?</p>
   <p>"Until now, Zionism was no more than a dream. Now we stand face to face with the actual problems of the rebirth of a nation, and administer them. The cry for our own home has powerful, sentimental strength. It is a demand that embodies dramatical power. It touches the patient hope that we have had in the days of persecution. However, it is only practicable, when we become undesired and unfortunate citizens in other countries.</p>
   <p>" 'But we shall develop' says Zionists, 'the industries'! Such an assertion sounds nice, but there is no hope in Palestine. In Jaffa, where ships arrive, passengers are descended into small boats and this cannot be done, should a storm occur."</p>
   <p>The Zionists have about 150,000 of the 3.000.000 Jews in America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
