<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-06-22">June 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">More Light</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0163</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0163.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-06-22">June 22, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">MORE LIGHT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 20th annual convention of the Federation of American Zionists, which will open next Sunday in Baltimore, will, clarify to the American Jewry, not only the present condition of Zionism throughout the world, but also the new standpoint of the Jews in general.</p>
   <p>A great deal has already been made clear by the Congress movement, which has served, and is still serving, as a touchstone that separates the multitude, and which helps differentiate between the democratic and the "God-annointed" elements among the Jewry. The Congress movement demonstrated who are willing to go along with the people, and who only want to be rulers to acquire honor and influence for themselves, even if running counter to the people. This was seen by the Union of Hebrew Congregation's (the German Jews who until now have represented the American Jewry) withdrawal from the Congress on one side, and by the group of Forward socialists on the other. Both extremes became frightened by the masses, who apparently have awakened to self-consciousness and intend to march <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0164.jpg" n="2"/>onward and have their say-so on the proceedings.</p>
   <p>Dr. Cyrus Adler has expressed thoughts that others conceal and are afraid to utter. He said that he withdraws because he thinks the Congress is deliberately looking forward to seizing the leadership of the Jewish Institutions. This is the fear of every decrepit leader who does not want to part with the rule in his feeble hands.</p>
   <p>The Baltimore Convention will throw more light upon this situation. The Zionists in America speak in behalf of the entire Zionist movement.</p>
   <p>The resolutions to be adopted at the convention will represent the will of the most predominant portion of the World Jewry. The thoughts that will be expressed will be the thoughts now encompassing the collective Jewry.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
