<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-18">May 18, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">What Are the Principles?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0482</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0482.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-05-18">May 18, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT ARE THE PRINCIPLES?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every intelligent Jew understands that Jewish life and thought are now undergoing great and revolutionary changes. Slowly but surely, old values are losing their significance and new conditions arise to which the old generation cannot adapt itself. Basically, our whole life as Jews is being reduced to a skeleton and confusion prevails in every aspect of it. [Old] boundaries are being wiped out, and new ones have not as yet been fixed.</p>
   <p>Not so long ago, we knew who deserved the name Jew and who did not; what Orthodoxy was and what it was not; what Reform was and what it was not; Reform which was Zionism and [Reform] which was anti-Zionism; what Judaism was and what it was not. Today all landmarks are effaced; especially in America, all landmarks in Jewish life have been blotted out.</p>
   <p>It is not for the first time in modern Jewish history that Jewish life and <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0483.jpg" n="2"/>thinking are entangled in a process of dissolution and degeneration. Sixty years ago, when Samson Rafhael Hirsch, the founder of German [Jewish] Orthodoxy, went from Oldenberg to Frankfort on the Main he found the entire Jewry of Southern Germany, which had been in former generations a large and productive Jewish center, in a state of complete dissolution. The religious life had been completely obliterated, and in all Frankfort, at one time a city and mother of Jews, there were only two families which had kept Kosher homes. In other cities in Central and Western Europe, similar conditions prevailed. The primary task of Samson Raphael Hirsch was to create boundaries in Jewish life. For the daily practice of Judaism he established two principles, to wit: The observance of Sabbath and the practice of circumcision. Whoever violated the laws of Sabbath or did not have his child circumcised could not be a member of the Jewish community. He was no longer a Jew. For the past sixty years the Reform movement in Germany has made definite progress and today there are in Frankfort on the Main not two but four thousand Jewish families who conduct strictly kosher homes. This development of the religious life among the Jews in Frankfort and in Southern Germany forced the Reformers to be moderate in their demands, and the fact is <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0484.jpg" n="3"/>that the German Reform Temples are in many respects more conservative than the conservative synagogues in America. Men and women do not sit together during services. The rabbi does not shave his beard. He does not violate the laws of Sabbath nor does he eat Trefe (food that is not kosher), and he has many other earmarks of the older type of rabbi. This is not so in America. In this country Reform has deviated from its course to such an extent that the leaders of the Reform movement themselves are now afraid of their own skins and are beginning to realize that they have dragged their rank and file into a quagmire.</p>
   <p>We do not say that all principles laid down by Samson Raphael Hirsch are sound or that we, in America, should establish the same principles. But we do say that the great historical merit of Samson Raphael Hirsch consists in his adoption of the principle of establishing boundaries. This does not mean, however, that the boundaries he established are good and proper because his principle of Neo-Orthodoxy is too farfetched. But the fact remains that he did establish boundaries and those newly established boundaries created a new Jewish life throughout Central Europe thus saving the Central European Jewry from total extinction.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0485.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>If we do not attempt to create new boundaries in the Jewish life of America, if we do not establish certain principles for our life as a whole, it is difficult to see how the American Jewry can have a future. Without the creation of new values, which are really old, and without the fixation of new boundaries, which, too, are in reality old, then neither Talmud Torahs (Hebrew schools) nor Synagogues will help us, because everything will be tern asunder by chaos.</p>
   <p>Jewish life must be based upon certain principles, for if it is only based upon certain conventional falsehoods and equivocal compromises, it cannot be assured of an existence.</p>
   <p>Today Jewish life, especially here in America, is built on false and often sordid compromises and on conventional falsehoods, and such a Jewish life cannot guarantee the future of Judaism.</p>
   <p>If our rabbis and educators would look farther than their noses, if they would think in historical terms,this chaos would not at all be possible. As soon as <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0486.jpg" n="5"/>the crisis became visible, they should have adopted means whereby to strengthen Jewish life through the establishment of certain principles and the creation of new ones, i.e, the restoration of old boundaries. A Jew who denies the Jewish God and the Jewish people is not a Jew and must not be recognized as such. The rabbis in America do not understand, or do not want to understand, that radical Reform Judaism is all too radical and has nothing to do with Judaism, much less so than the old Karaites (a Jewish sect which adheres to the literal interpretations of the Scriptures and rejects oral traditions). Theologically, Reform Judaism is based upon a multitude of fantasies, and sociologically it is based upon the principle and aim of assimilation. When an American Christian discards Christianity and desires the dissolution of the American people, he is neither an American nor a Christian and thereby excludes himself from both Christianity and America. Not a rabbi, but Achad Am (Hebrew philospher), established the principle. Whosoever shares not a portion in the Jewish God, he shares not a portion in Israel; and, conversely, whosoever shares not a portion in Israel,he shares not a portion in the Jewish God.</p>
   <p>We ask the representatives of historical Judaism: What are the principles of Jewish life and what are the boundaries? Or do you believe that Judaism can exist in a chaotic state?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
