<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sinai Congregation, Executive Board Minutes</title>,
<date when="1885-12-29">Dec. 29, 1885</date>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1107</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
   <catRef target="#source-association-docs"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1107.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sinai Congregation, Executive Board, Minutes</title>,
<date when="1885-12-29">Dec. 29, 1885</date>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The president (B. Lowenthal) brought to the notice of the Board, that the note of the congregation for $16,000 borrowed from the U. H. R. Association upon a mortgage of our Temple, was maturing on January 26......the following resolution prevailed:</p>
   <p>That the secretary be instructed to write to the U. H. R. Association, that it is the desire of the Board to pay on the above note the sum of $1,000 and to renew the loan of $15,000 - for one year, upon the same conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1108.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>effect has been created throughout the building by the adoption of the Moorish style of architecture. From the main doors to the arched ceiling, in the form of decoration stained glass-work, and in every department, this oriental and attractive style has been introduced. The facade contains, besides the main entrance, and several small windows, one large circular window of stained glass in star-shaped design. The graceful arched ceiling is finely finished, and decorated in pale-blue tints, with small gold figures. The fronts of the gallery, which extend around three sides of the auditorium, have been finished with the latest style of the raised-figure composition decorations, touched up with harmonizing shades of blue, red and bronze. This is very rich. The large windows on each side are filled with stained glass. The pews are fine, the ark superbly finished, and so is the place for the choir. The pulpit of cherry is one of the most elaborate pieces of work of its kind in the city, and was presented to the congregation by the principal contractor of the new building.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
