<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-16">Feb. 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Preachers of Morality</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0598</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0598.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-02-16">Feb. 16, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">PREACHERS OF MORALITY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was our unfriendly enemy, Dr. Samuel Schulman of Temple Beth-el (New York) who made the highly moral proposal at the Reform convention that the Zionist Organization clear out of the way in order that Reform Jews of his calibre (lovers of Zion) shall have free scope to build Palestine. The Zionists are the obstacles to the realization of their long-buried, unrevealed affection for Palestine. They are straining at the leash, but cannot move unless we disappear from the scene. The same noble suggestion was made by the superior moralist who edits the American Hebrew not only in that periodical, but also when he spoke against the Palestine resolution at the hearing before the House Committee on Foreign Affairs. They feel the lure of Palestine so strongly that the existence of the Zionist Organization prevents the exercise of their love, which galls them tremendously. There is so much for them to do, and because of us they cannot do it. For <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0599.jpg" n="2"/>twenty-five years the Zionist Organization worked for Zionist ideals and Palestine, the one served the other. For twenty-five years we have been talking Palestine. The propaganda produced the Balfour Declaration and the Palestine mandate. The American Congress adopted a resolution in favor of giving Palestine to the Jewish people. Because of our successful operations on behalf of Palestine, the Zionist Organization should give up the ghost. It should give place to others. Who are these others? Dr. Schulman and his anti-Zionist, antinational group, who opposed the Balfour Declaration, who were opposed to the American Congress resolution. And who among all the inveterate haters of Zionism has a better right to make this proposal than Dr. Schulman? He has proved his claim to the floor by his persistent and complete immunity from the charge of ever having lifted a finger on behalf of Palestine. When Dr. Ben-Zion Mossinsohn came to America for the Jaffa Hebrew Gymnasium, Zionists interviewed Dr. Schulman and got from him an expression of interest. But his interest was lost in moral reflections, and he did nothing for that institution. Later Nahum Sokolow came to this country. Dr. Schulman was induced to speak in praise of Sokolow as a Hebrew <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0600.jpg" n="3"/>writer. But his interest went no further than this speech. Dr. Schulman was opposed to the American Jewish Congress on account of its Zionist implications. He insisted that unless we make it "a" instead of "the" Jewish Commonwealth, he would have nothing to do with the Congress. When changes were made to meet his viewpoint, he disappeared from the Congress and was not heard from again. He was afraid of the Zionists who were not doing the right thing by Palestine. The Central Conference of American Rabbis last summer adopted a resolution to co-operate in the upbuilding of Palestine together with the Palestine Development Council. The rabbis found--they thought--a sufficiently denationalized body with whom to work for the upbuilding of Palestine. Dr. Schulman now expresses his idea of discipline and loyalty to the Central Conference by opposing the even weaker resolution that was introduced at the Convention of the Union and helping to lay that resolution on the table. Is it possible that Dr. Schulman, Dr. Philipson, and the other lovers of Zion (who hate Zionists) are merely using these resolutions to avoid action? Are all these conditions and demands, explanations and reservations, merely tactics in their long and unsuccessful <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0601.jpg" n="4"/>opposition to Zionism? We are loath to believe this of preachers of morality and spirituality, of which category the gentlemen mentioned are outstanding exemplars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
