<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-21">May 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From Across the Se</title><title level="a" type="sub">Letters from Jewish Soldiers Who Are in Uncle Sam's Service in France</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1250</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1250.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1918-05-21">May 21, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM ACROSS THE SE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Letters from Jewish Soldiers Who Are in Uncle Sam's Service in France</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In previous issues of this newspaper we have published letters from Jewish soldiers in France, which were of great interest to our readers. We are now publishing a letter recently received by Mr. and Mrs. H. Greenberg, 1324 South Albany Avenue, from their son Sam, who is in the service of Uncle Sam in France.</p>
   <p>The letter reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Somewhere in France,</p>
   <p>April 24, 1918.</p>
   <p>"My dear parents: On account of being so very busy in the last two or three weeks I haven't had enough time to write to you. Though I am still busy at present, I am taking a few minutes of my time to write to you and to let you know that I am in the best of health, feeling well and gay, and that in general I am quite satisfied with my present condition.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1251.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Our American ranks here are becoming livelier and more active each day: more men arrive daily in our branch of service from which it may be seen that we are really accomplishing something.</p>
   <p>"I have not received any letters from you in the last ten days. At any rate, I am writing to you because I think that there are some letters for me in the mail.</p>
   <p>"And now, my dears, how is everything with you at home? At this time it is almost spring with you; beautiful and warm weather coupled with [sic] the green parks which I am sure you are enjoying. Here where I am stationed it has been quite cool for the last eight weeks, and it is remarkable that it was much warmer here during the winter than it is now. I think though that the weather will improve soon and it will be very nice around here.</p>
   <p>"I spent a very enjoyable evening yesterday, such as I haven't had in a long time. Some of the boys arranged some kind [sic] of a party and we had a good time. The dishes were prepared in the French style and we enjoyed the meal <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1252.jpg" n="3"/>immensely. I am sending you the menu of the meal which we were served. To my sorrow, I was unable to spend the entire evening there, for I had to go to the office to see if everything there was in order. I was told by my friends this morning that I missed quite a good deal of the fun, and I have therefore decided that in the future I shall manage to spend the whole evening when a party of this sort takes place.</p>
   <p>"Please let me know how Walter is doing in Rockford? Does he write to you? Or maybe he has become a real soldier now and is ready to come over here and be too busy to write?</p>
   <p>"I think that some of the other boys will arrive soon and then we will have some fun, although many of our boys are at the front now and are doing their part. Did you hear about the bunch that left a few weeks ago for the States to boost the new Liberty Loan there? I am interested to know whether they will come to Chicago to induce the folks there to subscribe to the Loan and also [to] tell them about the fun which they had here.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1253.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"That which concerns me personally I have nothing to complain about. I get my three meals daily and a place to sleep: when there is a chance to sleep and everything is well and nice with us.</p>
   <p>"I shall write you again in a few days. With best regards to all of you,</p>
   <p>Yours,</p>
   <p>Sam."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
