<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-05-18">May 18, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Ruben's Funeral Turned into a Patriotic Demonstration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1263</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1263.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1917-05-18">May 18, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Ruben's Funeral Turned into a Patriotic Demonstration</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday the Chicago Jewry arranged a huge military funeral for Morris Ruben, who died while serving Uncle Sam's Navy, which was transformed into a demonstration for America.</p>
   <p>A large crowd gath red around the corner of Oakley Blvd. and North Ave., not far from the undertaker's chapel where the funeral began. The procession marched over Oakley Blvd.,Hirsch Blvd., Division St., and Lincoln St. to the Tifereth Zion Congregation.</p>
   <p>The procession was preceded by motorcycle police and members of the United States Navy. Captains Slowitzky and Lipshultz, of the Illinois National Guard, headed the coffin.</p>
   <p>When the procession reached the Synagogue, the site overcrowded by throngs.<pb facs="5423972_9_1_1264.jpg" n="2"/> The sailors carried the casket into the synagogue, where solemn quietness pravailed.</p>
   <p>B. Hindsel, president of the Congregation, opened the services, after which he introduced Judge Joseph B. David, who pointed out, in a brief talk, how the Jewish peope love America and how the Jews are always among the first to defend with their lives their new fatherland.</p>
   <p>Judge David then introduced Rabbi A.B. Goldenson, who read the obituary. Judge Harry M. Fisher concluded with a fiery patriotic speech, urging the Jewish youth present at the funeral to do their duty in the present crisis in the service of their country.</p>
   <p>Cantor Reichlin chanted a prayer. Then the crowd started to leave the synagogue and headed for the cemetery.</p>
   <p>At the grave, Judge David introduced Captain Slavitzky, of the first Cavalry<pb facs="5423972_9_1_1265.jpg" n="3"/> Regiment, who delivered a patriotic funeral oration. When the casket was lowered into the grave, the soldiers stood in military formation.</p>
   <p>This was the last honor which Morris Ruben's comrades bestowed upon him. The people then read a Psalm of David and the deceased sailor's father said Kadish [prayer for the dead].</p>
   <p>Thus the Chicago Jewry escorted him to eternity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
