<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-29">Feb. 29, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Why the Shekel?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0223</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0223.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1916-02-29">Feb. 29, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">WHY THE SHEKEL?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the Zionist organization in America, and also in all countries where the World War prevented the Zionist activities from flourishing, every effort is being made this year to muster in a big army of Shekel payers, the largest in the history of Zionism. ("Shekel," a coin. The purchase of a ballot to make one delegate vote for delegates to the World Zionist Congress).</p>
   <p>Even in Russia, where every Jewish nerve is strung up to the point of bursting, and where every penny is needed in order to sustain life, Shekels are being sold, and he who is well off financially buys and pays for a friend not financially able to buy a Shekel for himself. Of course, as we all know, in Russia this Shekel buying must be done in secret for it is forbidden by the Russian government.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0224.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Zionist press of Germany report of Shekels being sent in from Jewish soldiers in the trenches. In Romania, Gallcia, and other places where Zionists are found, great efforts are being made to collect more and more shekels this year. This showing of the Zionists from different countries who have joined hand in hand to gather funds for the war sufferers is remarkable, especially because two months ago it looked like this year's Shekel selling would be a failure. No one understands it better than the Zionist that a hundred thousand Shekels more will go a long way toward organization. A Shekel is worth twenty-five cents, and a hundred thousand Shekels will amount to twenty-five thousand dollars. Of course, this is not such a wonderful sum for a world-wide movement, especially when you read about the Jewish Colonial trust and national fund, which, even in time of depression, amounts to over two million dollars. The real reason of the much enthused activities in reference to the sale of the Shekel, is that the large Jewish population feels instinctively that it must immediately answer the call of a national Jewish organization which, it is assured, will play quite a role in national and international politics according to the Zionist's report of two years ago, their representatives proposed certain measures to the Turkish government. The first question asked by the Turkish diplomat, Mr. Tallaat Bey, was how many Shekel payers were there in the Zionist organization. The diplomat understands very well that when you deal with Jews as a nation you can form an opinion from the number of <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0225.jpg" n="3"/>their organizations and their membership.</p>
   <p>Immediately after the war, organized united effort will be the thing that will count. Organizations will have to lay their propositions before the power, or the powers, that will have authority or voice over Palestine in reference to certain concessions for the Jews in that country, immigration, land-ownership permits, the right to found schools, and local self-government in the territory occupied by Jews.</p>
   <p>The first question on this subject, we may expect, is going to be asked: who are you and whom are you representing? If the raising of the Shekel fund is successful, in other words, if one quarter of a million Jews join the Shekel purchasing organization and have their names permanently enrolled, then the Zionist representatives would be in a position to answer, with a clear conscience, that they are representing the whole Jewish race, which wishes to become a nation of the world, have been hoping for the last two thousand years to regain their promised homeland. There are at least a quarter of a million Jews who are regular Shekel paying members, whose names names are registered for the program of getting <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0226.jpg" n="4"/>busy for the task of regaining our homeland.</p>
   <p>Our Jewish population of the world is at present between thirteen to fourteen million souls scattered all over the world. Out of that number there are at least one million organized, who are active in the work of regaining Palestine. This itself shows the meaning of organization.</p>
   <p>Not calling ourselves prophets, we can rest assured that out of such large organization, over a quarter of a million Shekel buyers well organized and active, we will get without fail favorable results.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
