<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-07-07">July 7, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Palestine Gains Told to Zionists</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1521</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1521.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-07-07">July 7, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">PALESTINE GAINS TOLD TO ZIONISTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>More than 5,000 delegates and friends attended the 36th annual convention of the Zionist Organization of America. Dr. Chaim Weizmann, world Zionist leader, was the guest of honor of the convention.</p>
   <p>The plight of German Jews was deplored in forcible language in the report of Morris Rothenberg, president of the Zionist Organization. A message from the executive of the Jewish Agency, the supreme governing body of the Zionist movement, also expressed sorrow over the persecution of German Jewry and the slaying three weeks ago at Tel Aviv of Dr. Chaim Arlosoroff, head of the Jewish Agency in Palestine.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1522.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>DR. WISE DENOUNCES NAZIS.</p>
   <p>Denunciation of Chancellor Hitler and other leaders in the anti-Semitic campaign in Germany as "a group of intellectual perverts and paranoiacs" was delivered by Rabbi Stephen S. Wise.</p>
   <p>Resolutions were passed to begin a campaign to raise $8,000,000 in the next four years to settle German Jews in Palestine.</p>
   <p>Dr.Wise also denounced the Reform rabbis for certain actions at the recent Reform meetings in Chicago and Milwaukee.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1523.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This denunciation resulted in a terrific fight on the convention floor at the Tuesday session when Rabbi William F. Rosenblum of New York City offered a resolution which stated that the convention viewed with satisfaction the growth of Zionism among the Reform rabbinate. The resolution was attacked from many quarters, and finally withdrawn.</p>
   <p>RE-ELECT ROTHENBERG</p>
   <p>Morris Rothenberg of New York City was re-elected president of the Zionist Organization of America and Morris Margulies, also of New York was elected secretary. Other officers elected included Nathan Straus, Jr., of New York, Judge William M. Lewis of Philadelphia, Elihu D. Stone of Boston, Robert Szold of New York, and Rabbi Solomon Goldman of Chicago as vice presidents;</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1524.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Harry P. Fierst of Mount Vernon as treasurer; and Louis P. Rocker of New York as chairman of the Finance Committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
