<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-05-07">May 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Do Not Let Up!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0658</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0658.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-05-07">May 7, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">DO NOT LET UP!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is very seldom that a young organization, which has no bureaucratic apparatus and no regular administration, is able to accomplish great things, particularly to raise large sums for public purposes. The achievements of the Association of Synagogue Presidents, during the short period of its existence, can, therefore, be considered extraordinary. It has united the great synagogues in the campaign for the Keren Hayesod ["exchequer" of World Zionist Organization], and has raised a large sum of money; it has brought the representatives of all the big synagogues under one roof and has thus demonstrated, for the first time, the unity of the Orthodox forces of Chicago; within a very short time it has raised a large sum of money for the Hebrew Theological College.</p>
   <p>Were it not for the united group of synagogue presidents it would be impossible to go on with the building of the Hebrew Theological College. Thanks to its initiative, energy, and resoluteness the building of the College has been <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0659.jpg" n="2"/>assured, and one may expect that when the College again needs help, that help will be forthcoming from the United group of synagogue presidents. Anyway, the Hebrew Theological College can now depend upon the help of the Chicago Orthodoxy.</p>
   <p>Those are achievements which no one should belittle. When one also takes into consideration [the fact] that the same united group of synagogue presidents made possible an appeal for the Keren Hayesod on the last day of Passover, which appeal brought in pledges for forty-five thousand dollars, then the Chicago synagogue presidents will surely be given credit for the successful work which they have done during the last few months.</p>
   <p>It is true that the successful work was done by a small group of synagogue presidents, by Messrs. Salk, Weil, Feinstein, Wilensky, Rabinowich, Jacob Cohen, H. M. Barnett, Marok, Abe Kaplan, Miller, and a few others, who are less active. However, one ought to remember that in every group there are only a few people who are active. If out of a hundred synagogue presidents of Chicago, there <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0660.jpg" n="3"/>are fifteen or twenty who are active outside their synagogues, who participate extensively in the general Jewish life--then one can no longer say that the Chicago Orthodoxy is asleep. During the last few months it certainly was not asleep, but was very active, which fact should be gratefully admitted.</p>
   <p>The representatives of the Chicago Orthodoxy having demonstrated, once and for all, that they can do good work mustn't rest upon their laurels now. They must continue their successful work. It is their duty now more than ever, to develop a regular activity because now one expects good work from them as they have shown what they can do if they want to. There is a great deal of work to be done. Jewish Chicago is still a large village which has to be transformed into a city. The Orthodox forces are not organized, and, not being organized, they cannot be very productive. Jewish education in Chicago is not organized and does not stand upon the broad foundations which it should stand. Jewish philanthropic work in Chicago is still unorganized despite the Jewish Federation of Orthodox Charities, because there are <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0661.jpg" n="4"/>innumerable Jewish philanthropic agencies in Chicago which have nothing to do with the Federated. The spiritual life of the Jews in Chicago is still undeveloped, and something ought to be done about it so that Chicago would no longer be known as the "abandoned" city.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Orthodoxy must finish two tasks: first, it has to carry out the Keren Hayesod plans by organizing the collection of pledges, and second, it must finish the work for the Hebrew Theological College. It is not enough for the Chicago Orthodoxy to have given fifteen thousand dollars for the College when its foundation stone was laid. It must also help finish the building, and it must--which is the most important thing of all--finance the institution. All this is possible if the official representatives of the Chicago Orthodoxy continue their activity of the past three months on an enlarged scale.</p>
   <p>The synagogue presidents have done very little for the last few weeks. First it was the eve of a holiday, then the holiday, then it was too soon after <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0662.jpg" n="5"/>the holiday, but now the holiday is gone and there is no further excuse for not doing anything. The synagogue presidents must now start to work again, and their first task is to put their own organization upon a solid basis. An effort should be made to enroll at least a majority of all the synagogue presidents as members of the organization and permanent committees should be organized for the various activities which the organization must undertake. The organization must have a permanent Keren Hayesod committee, a permanent educational committee which should devote itself to the Hebrew Theological College, a permanent charity committee which should, once and for all, regulate the activity of the delegates who are authorized to collect money, and so on.</p>
   <p>The leaders of the United group of synagogue presidents, Messrs. Weil, Salk, Feinstein, Wilensky, Marok, H. M. Barnett, Jacob Cohen, and others must now make a sincere effort to enroll as many synagogue presidents as possible at the next meeting. They must not let up now. They must work energetically until they put the Chicago Orthodoxy into a good condition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
