<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-29">Oct. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Young Men's Hebrew Association of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1422</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1422.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-10-29">Oct. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">YOUNG MEN'S HEBREW ASSOCIATION OF CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Young Men's Hebrew Association of Chicago is a reality. It has already proven itself a potent factor in Chicago's Jewish community. Young Men's Hebrew Associations are national institutions. Every city that has a Jewish community of average size has a Young Men's Hebrew Association. Some of these associations are housed in small clubrooms, but the vast majority have modern buildings, large and beautiful, with every facility and convenience for welfare, educational, social, and athletic work--in short, every conceivable facility for carrying on the noble work for which the Young Men's Hebrew Associations of the United States have been established. Young Men's Hebrew Associations in the large cities have greatly benefited the Jewry of those cities; they have been recognized as essential institutions in all Jewish communities.</p>
   <p>Chicago has lagged behind every other city for a long time. Jews of other cities, when they visit Chicago, are dumbfounded when they learn that <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1423.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago does not have a large Y. M. H. A. Building. "What in the world is the matter with the Jews of Chicago? Why haven't they recognized the need of a Y. M. H. A.?" they ask.</p>
   <p>The Y. M. H. A. of Chicago has undertaken to answer this question. Only twelve months ago, five young men organized the present Young Men's Hebrew Association of Chicago. The organization now numbers 350 aggressive, ambitious, active members. In the short period of twelve months, these pioneers have accomplished wonders. Their educational, athletic, social, and welfare activities have established them in this city and have brought praise and expressions of appreciation from many men who are well known in Jewish activities in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Young Men's Hebrew Association has purchased a temporary home, a home which will serve their purposes until they can realize their dream, which is to have a bigger, better, more beautiful building--an institution of which Chicago Jewry can be proud. The temporary home is located at 3350 Douglas <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1424.jpg" n="3"/>Boulevard, and will be occupied by the organization during the second week of November, at which time a huge dedication ceremony will take place. But the building needs furniture, and in order to raise funds to purchase the necessary furniture, a dance has been arranged for Saturday night, Halloween, October 30, at the Ashland Boulevard Auditorium, Ashland Boulevard and Van Buren Streets. This hall, also known as the Car Men's Hall, is beautiful and spacious, and will be nicely decorated. The music will be the most delightful modern dance music, furnished by a fourteen piece band under the direction of Cottle and Wagner, masters in the art of syncopation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
