<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-12-05">Dec. 5, 1905</date>, 16:2.
<title level="a">Jewish Women Arrive for Triennial Session</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0290</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0290.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1905-12-05">Dec. 5, 1905</date>, 16:2.
<title level="a">JEWISH WOMEN ARRIVE FOR TRIENNIAL SESSION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Council of Jewish Women, which was organized at the World's Congress of Religions in Chicago in 1903, will hold its fourth triennial convention in Sinai Temple, beginning this afternoon at 2 o'clock and continuing until Wednesday of next week. Mrs. Henry Solomon, who founded the organization, is national president. About one hundred delegates are expected to be present, and as many more alternates and visiting members. The first to arrive came from the two extremes, New York and San Francisco, and others continued to come on every train from the North, South, East, and West. More are expected between seven and nine this morning.</p>
   <p>This afternoon there will be an informal reception in the vestry-room of Sinai Temple, to the delegates, alternates, visiting members, local committee and directors, and to-night at the first regular meeting Dr. E. G. Hirsch will deliver the invocation; Miss Julia I. Felsenthal, president of the Chicago Chapter, will deliver the address of welcome; Harry Hart, president of Sinai Temple, will extend greetings; Mrs. Henry Solomon will deliver the president's address and Miss Sadie American, the corresponding secretary, will read her report.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0291.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Most of the morning and afternoon sessions will be taken up with reports and committee and board meetings. To-morrow night Miss Josephine Lazarus of New York will read a paper on "Religion"; Mrs. C. Misch of Providence will read a paper on "Modern Tendencies on Religion" and "Our Needs"; Mrs. J. Andres of Boston on "An Awakening"; and Mrs. S. M. Blumaner on "Religious Life of the Small Communities."</p>
   <p>Friday afternoon the annual election of officers will be held, and Saturday afternoon will be spent in visiting the University of Chicago, the Jewish Old Peoples' Home, the Jewish Orphan Asylum and the Home for the Jewish Friendless. Sunday evening Miss American will read a paper on "Immigration as It Affects Women and Girls," Miss Sadie T. Wald of Chicago will talk on "Housing," and Edwin Wehle of Louisville on "The Need of the Trained Worker in Settlement Work."</p>
   <p>On Monday afternoon Mrs. Charles Henrotin, who is an honorary member of the council, will lead a discussion "Delinquents," " What We can do Against Tuberculosis," "Vacation Work," "Juvenile Court," and "Committee on Legislation and Child Labor." On Thursday afternoon there will be a formal reception at the Lakeside Club, and on Friday evening Mrs. and Mr. Henry Solomon will be at home informally from nine to <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0292.jpg" n="3"/>eleven to the officers, essayists, delegates, alternates and out-of-town members.</p>
   <p>Reception on Midway</p>
   <p>A reception will be tendered by the Women's Union, University of Chicago, Saturday afternoon from two to four o'clock, at 15 Lexington Hall, and on Tuesday of next week a luncheon will be given at Hull House.</p>
   <p>The officers of the national council are:</p>
   <p>President-Mrs. H. Solomon</p>
   <p>First Vice-President-Mrs. H. Rosenberg</p>
   <p>Second Vice-President-Mrs. M. Goldenberg</p>
   <p>Treasurer--Mrs. J. B. Judah</p>
   <p>Record Secretary--Miss G. Berg</p>
   <p>Corr. Secretary--Miss S. American</p>
   <p>Auditor--Mrs. B. Lowenstein</p>
   <p>The local committee having charge of the arrangement consists of:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0293.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Honorary Chairman--Mrs. H. Solomon</p>
   <p>Chairman--Miss J. Barbe</p>
   <p>Vice Chairman--Miss J. I. Felsenthal</p>
   <p>Treasurer--Mrs. S. W. Rindskopf</p>
   <p>Secretary--Mrs. Isaac B. Lipson</p>
   <p>It is expected that the meetings will be largely attended, as the Chicago chapter is the largest in the country, numbering about 1,400 members, and having had an increase of about 150 members in the last six weeks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
