<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>, 
            <date when="1933-10-20">October 20, 1933</date>.<title level="a">B'nai B'rith Dedicates its New Hillel Foundation at the Northwestern University</title>
        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1312</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.1.d"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 1 d</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>, 
            <date when="1933-10-20">October 20, 1933</date>.
                <title level="a">B'nai B'rith Dedicates its New Hillel Foundation at the Northwestern University</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
  <p>On last Wednesday night over one thousand people crowded into the assembly hall of the First Methodist Episcopal Church of Evanston to listen to the dedication exercises of the Northwestern University B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation. One-half the audience consisted of Northwestern University students and alumni.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1312.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Rev. Dr. Ernest Fremont Tittle, pastor of the church and one of the outstanding liberal Methodist ministers of the country, welcomed those present in a manner which will long be remembered because of its warmth and assurance of his personal pleasure at the opportunity for a partnership between Jew and Christian for the purpose of helping civilization.</p>
   <p>Dr. Albert I. Cohen, one of the younger members of the Northwestern University Faculty under whose guidance the Jewish group was organized last year and who interested B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation Commission in giving Northwestern University a Foundation to the B'nai B'rith Hillel Commission.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1313.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Dr. Philip L. Seman, a member of the commission and the head of the Jewish People's Institute of Chicago, accepted the Foundation in behalf of the commission in the absence of President Alfred M. Cohen, who was unable to attend owing to the trip to Europe which he and Dr. Rubinow are making.</p>
   <p>He told of the work of the Foundation at the various universities as observed by him on his visits and in turn, on behalf of the commission, presented the Foundation to Dr. Walter Dill Scott, president of Northwestern University. Dr. Scott thrilled the audience with his speech of acceptance and accepted the Foundation as an agency of the university to round out the work being done by the university.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1314.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>TELLS OF B'NAI B'RITH WORK.</p>
   <p>Fred Bernstein, representative of District No. 6 on B'nai B'rith Hillel Commission, presided. In his opening remarks he called attention to the fact that B'nai B'rith was celebrating its 90th anniversary; that the dedication exercises were part of the 10th anniversary celebration of the B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundations. Mr. Bernstein stressed the fact that B'nai B'rith represented no particular group of Jews and no particular phase of Jewish life; that after ninety years of active life it still held to its original program of "uniting Israel." "B'nai B'rith," said the chairman, "has no fixed policy and never had unless its program of uniting Israel could be considered a fixed policy. Its activities change with the needs of the times. It sought to defend <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1315.jpg" n="5"/>and protect the fair name of Israel whenever that was necessary. Today, B'nai B'rith has come to the conclusion that the Jew was suffering mostly from ignorance of the Jew. Therefore, the main activities of the order today are through its anti-Defamation League which seeks to keep the non-Jew informed and to make him understand and appreciate the contribution which the Jew has made and still is making to civilization, and through its B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundations it seeks to inform the Jewish students who will be the Jewish leaders of tomorrow, thus preparing them to carry on the traditions which have come down from our ancestors and to better equip them to meet the challenges that come from without."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1316.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>STUDENT COUNCIL HEAD SPEAKS.</p>
   <p>The first president of the Student Council, Marvin Finder, spoke eloquently on the subject assigned to him, "What the Students Hope For," and Rabbi Jacob Singer, the first director of the Foundation, who is giving his services without compensation, delivered the address of the evening. Rabbi Singer said that the exercises were really a rededication and that through the foundations B'nai B'rith was attempting a recreation of the age-old Jewish traditions. He prayed that the child would grow into maturity, bringing joy and satisfaction to the great order which has made possible the splendid work being done among Jewish university students.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1317.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Rabbi Charles Shulman of Glencoe Temple, delivered the invocation and Rabbi A. L. Lassen, president Chicago Rabbinical Association, brought greetings from the Chicago Rabbinical Association pledging their hearty support and cooperation to the new Foundation.</p>
   <p>Both Rabbi Singer and the chairman conveyed to President Scott and Rev. Tittle the appreciation of B'nai B'rith Hillel Commission of the fine spirit of cooperation and the splendid courtesy exhibited in their sincere cooperation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
