<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-01-02">January 2, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Good News for Zion</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0283</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0283.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1907-01-02">January 2, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Good News For Zion</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 9th Convention of the Order, Knights of Zion, was closed with great enthusiasm with the impressive song, "Hatickva", which was sung by the large crowd. The delegates dispersed with order and acquiesence in a great orderly manner, with great satisfaction.</p>
   <p>The third sitting of the Convention opened up at 10 AM, but the seats of Lessing Hall began to fill an hour or so before the opening of this program. The delegates held their caucuses in other rooms of the hall and they were getting ready for a fight in the election of new officers and committees.</p>
   <p>The Nominating Committee, Mr.D. Hurvitz, Chairman, and the Resolutions Committee, Mr. N.D. Caplan, Chairman, were in rooms behind closed doors, with a system of spying; the organization trying to find out what the opposite side was doing in the election of new officer and committees.</p>
   <p>Mr. Leon Zolotockof, in opening the Convention and calling the assembly of delegates together, introduced the first Resolution which was the case of our <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0284.jpg" n="2"/>honored Rabbi Dr. B. Felzenthal. This was as follows:</p>
   <p>Whereas: Our beloved, honored Rabbi, Dr. B. Elzenthal, who, in his 84th year is in too weakened a condition to enable him to participate at this convention, who was ever loyal to his Jewish nation and Zion, and who was always willing and ready to do his part for the Cause of Zion;</p>
   <p>Now, Therefore, it is Resolved that we, the order of the Knights of Zion, in convention, assemble in prayer to our God of Israel to send our beloved Rabbi Felzenthal a speedy recovery, so that he may soon regain his strength to resume his activities in Zion. The newly elected officers are as follows:</p>
   <p>Bernhard Horwitz, Grand Master; 1st Vice-Grand Master, B. Sloan; 2nd Vice-Grand Master, B. Shenfeld, Milwaukee, Wisconsin; 3rd Vice-Grand Master, L. Knitter, Omaha, Nebraska; Honored Vice-Grand Master; Rabbi Glazer, Toledo, Ohio; Grand Recorder Max Schulman; Treasurer, Emil Broidy. Other minor officers, too numerous to mention, were also elected.</p>
   <p>The Directors were as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0285.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Rev. M. Newman, S.L. Ticktin, Miss Bertha Yarisamlinsky, Mrs. Sechton, L. Levinson, I. Glick, B. Twersky, Miss S. Bergston, M. Stein, Mrs. I. Natkin, A. Levinson, J.D. Rosenbloom, B. Bernstein, B. Antwanov, Miss Bernstein, J. Goldman.</p>
   <p>The installation of the officers was very impressive, and when Mr. Zolotockof handed over the Zion gavel to Mr. Hurwitz, who was the first Grand Master of the Order, you could notice tears in the eyes of the delegates. Mr. Hurwitz, addressing the audience with eloquence, extended his many thanks to the delegation, who elected him to this most honored office, and he hoped that those who helped elect him would do all they could in assisting him to bring the order to success, as, with the help of Mr. Zolotockof, another trustworthy officer, we were assured of a great future for the order of the Knights of Zion.</p>
   <p>In closing the Convention, Mr. Zolotockof, as newly-elected Orator, adjourned the meeting by directing the Rev. Newman to sing "Hatickva", with the help of the entire audience.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
