<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-05-01">May 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">B'nai B'rith.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-05-01">May 1, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">B'NAI B'RITH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The convention of the National Grand Lodge of the Independent Order of B'nai B'rith is at present in progress at the Auditorium. Delegates from 10 of this country's grand lodges are taking active part at the convention. Attending also are delegates from Canada, Austria, Germany, Roumania and from other parts of the world. The order has in all 25,000 members. The chairman of the convention is Victor Abraham of Cincinnati. Functioning as secretary is Judge E. C. Hamburgher of Chicago. According to a report given by the president, 47 lodges have been founded since the last National Grand Lodge in the year 1895. During this period 4,756 new members have joined the order. During <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0310.jpg" n="2"/>the same period of time, 2,006 members have been taken by death. The lodge has paid during that period the sum of $2,362,095 for charitable purposes. The important question to be discussed at this convention, is the policy of the "open door." Up to this time, this order has been known, as one of the strictest of secret societies. But it became evident, that public opinion is no longer in favor of such, and is decidedly opposed to secret societies.</p>
   <p>Officers of the National Council of Jewish Women expressed deep concern, that although the lodge is the leader of the reform movement, it shows lack of interest in the Jewish religion. Mrs. Hannah Solomon, president, emphasized, that "it was the mission of Jewish women, to revive the interest in religion among the Jewish people."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
