<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-09-15">September 15, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Jottings by H. L. M.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1492</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1492.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Jewish Chronicle</title>,
<date when="1933-09-15">September 15, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">JOTTINGS by H. L. M.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Now that Max Shulman has been elected president of the Zionist Organization of Chicago, it is hoped that he will put his long experience in the movement to good use and revive the organization. The time is opportune for real intensive and constructive work and all that is necessary for the new incoming executive committee is to plan its work systematically and carry it out with that determination which, in years gone by, has made the Zionist Organization of Chicago the outstanding group in Jewish life in the community.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1493.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We are happy to know that Rabbi Gerson B. Levi is gradually, though reluctantly, falling in line and beginning to think of Zionism and Eretz Israel in the light of the day. It must be a bitter pill for him to swallow, but he is man enough to accept the medicine in the proper spirit. While he cannot free himself completely from his prejudices against Palestine, he nevertheless realizes that it is today the only solution for the Jewish problem, and especially for the present unfortunate situation in Germany. Rabbi Levi is the last of the Mohicans and it is good to see that he is reading the handwriting on the wall so understandingly. He is not the only one. Many other men of his calling, who were bitter antagonists and opponents of the cause of Zion, have "seen the light" and joined the fold. We shall be glad to pay a membership in the Zionist Organization of Chicago, for Dr. Gerson B. Levi, if he will only say the word that he is ready to join. We can assure him he will be received with open arms - and put to work.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
