<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-12-19">December 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Dr. Hirsch on Judaism.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0918</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0918.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1912-12-19">December 19, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">DR. HIRSCH ON JUDAISM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dr. Hirsch was invited to speak at the yearly meeting of the Education Alliance of New York City and he uttered several things there, which should interest the Chicago Jewry, especially those Jews who devote their time and energy to the activities of the Chicago Hebrew Institute.</p>
   <p>The Education Alliance of New York is similar to the Chicago Hebrew Institute. And knowing that that Dr. Hirsch is a Director of the Chicago Hebrew Institute, we can be certain that whatever the learned rabbi said in New York, would be advocated, by him, in Chicago at a Board of Directors meeting of the Chicago Hebrew Institute.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0919.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Hirsch spoke on the activities of the Alliance and had emphasized that the duty of the Directors is not only to Americanize the foreigner, but also to see that they remain true Jews. He declared that religion and ethics are as essential as English and trades.</p>
   <p>"In the time that you are Americanizing them be cautious not to make them into non-Jews. Do not extinguish in them the Jewish flame. Let the Russian Jews study English and modern customs from the Americans, but let the Americans acquire Judaism from the foreigners. Every Jewish institution must be strictly Jewish in a religious sense, if not, it can not be considered as existing."</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0920.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is much better to evade religion in such institutions as the Educational Alliance and the Hebrew Institute as long as they are financed and directed by the Jews who derive their Judaism from religious teachers as Rabbi Hirsch and his colleagues. Should they even apply an orthodox physiognomy to whatever activity, it is no more than a caricature. It is not the division of reform from orthodoxy, it is the spirit, the events of life that make the abyss between both parts deeper and deeper. Times, conditions, and surroundings effect us so, that many will leap over the abyss, and the abyss will remain unfilled.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0921.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>There is no doubt that the opinions of Dr. Hirsch led to the introduction of Friday night services in the Chicago Hebrew Institute, which will probably encounter success. It will make it easier for our youth to shift from orthodoxy to reform. But such a transition is no more than learning to shift from one form of religion to another. And they certainly will not stop at reform; they will proceed further.</p>
   <p>It should not be forgotten that the Orthodox Jews not only complain that their children are drifting from the synagogues, but that the Reform Jews are also witnessing how their children are leaving their temples for the churches.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
