<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-08-03">August 3, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Chapter of Avukah.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1359</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1359.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Courier</title>,
<date when="1927-08-03">August 3, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO CHAPTER OF AVUKAH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The cultural program of Avukah for the year has been initiated through the launching of a series of six discussion meetings for the Summer months. At each of these meetings, papers by various members are read, followed by a general discussion on the part of the audience. The subjects have been carefully selected by a committee, and they cover chiefly two broad ideas - problems of modern Palestinian life.</p>
   <p>The first of these discussion meetings took place on Wednesday evening, 8 p.m. July 13, at the Hadassah Club Room, 8 S. Dearborn St., Room 915. Mr. Aubrey Mallach read a paper on "A Perspective of American Jewry." On July 27, the Hadassah Club Room was the scene of the second discussion meeting. Here Miss Jeanette Rubin read a paper on "American Jews and Zionism" while Mr. S. William Halperin followed with a paper on "American Jews and Zionism." At both these meetings the attendance was excellent, while throughout a very intelligent discussion was maintained. The next discussion meeting will take place at the Hadassah Club Rooms on Wednesday evening, August 10, at 8 p.m. Mr. Harry Iseberg will read a paper on "A History of Jewish Youth Movements in America," and Mr. Simon Agranat will present a paper on the subject, "What <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1360.jpg" n="2"/>can Avukah do for Zionism and Palestine?" All Jewish young men and women are invited.</p>
   <p>On Monday evening, August 1, a meeting of the Avukah Executive Committee took place, with Mr. S. William Halperin presiding. A number of important matters were discussed with reference to enlarging the scope of Avukah's educational and practical program for the coming year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
