<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1907-06-22">June 22, 1907</date>, 1:3.
<title level="a">Dr. Hirsch to Found a Settlement House Plans to Transform Sinai Temple into Great Neighborhood Center Ignores Jewish Traditions Congregation Approves and New Site Is Being Sought for Splendid Edifice</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0985</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0985.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Record-Herald</title>,
<date when="1907-06-22">June 22, 1907</date>, 1:3.
<title level="a">DR. HIRSCH TO FOUND A SETTLEMENT HOUSE PLANS TO TRANSFORM SINAI TEMPLE INTO GREAT NEIGHBORHOOD CENTER IGNORES JEWISH TRADITIONS CONGREGATION APPROVES AND NEW SITE IS BEING SOUGHT FOR SPLENDID EDIFICE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A plan, which will break with Jewish tradition stretching back thousands of years, is being projected by Dr. Emil G. Hirsch of Sinai Temple, one of the most influential Jewish Congregations in America. The plan, which has already passed the formative stage, contemplates nothing less than the transformation of Sinai Temple into a neighborhood center, with multiform activities, focusing about the central religious idea. The working out of the plan involves the abandonment of the present temple, which was erected at Indiana Avenue and Twenty-first Street thirty years ago; the selection of a more sutiable site, probably the southeast corner of Grand Boulevard and Fourty-sixth Street, and the erection of a new building to cost between $250,000 and $300,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0986.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In a sense the development of this idea of Dr. Hirsch will be a tribute paid by his congregation to the long and devoted service, covering more than a quarter of a century, of the rabbi. It will be the first time in the history of the Jewish church that the ancient religious traditions of the race have been modified to meet modern conceptions of neighborhood helpfulness.</p>
   <p>Similar to Lincoln Center</p>
   <p>Dr. Hirsch now is in Europe on his annual vacation, but his scheme for augmenting the social appeal of the church was outlined by Moses E. Greenebaum, president of the congregation.</p>
   <p>"Dr. Hirsch has felt for some time," said he, "that church activities should be multiform in character, that its influence should embrace many kinds of appeal, that it should be a social institution touching the lives of the people at as many vital points as possible.</p>
   <p>"He has believed that where a church sounds too persistently the single note; <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0987.jpg" n="3"/>where it fails to achieve by-ends by recognizing the demands of its members to free and unhampered social intercourse; where the ethical importance of interest in art and letters is ignored or at least not emphasized - he has believed that, in such cases, the church has failed to exercise its best influence in the community</p>
   <p>"It is his conviction that the church should represent and promote every form of wholesome activity; that it should get as close to the lives of the people as possible; that it should tend to counteract the vast commercial atmosphere which everywhere prevails. If the plan now under consideration is carried out the new synagogue will represent all of these elements."</p>
   <p>The new church will house a library, will contain many rooms where the members may meet socially and hear lectures on various subjects of a literary and artistic character. The church will be made the radiating point for the best secular and religious thought of the generation and will be thoroughly modern.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
