<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-15">Feb. 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">A New Scandal Breaks Out at the Congregation Am Abraham Anshe Poland</title><title level="a" type="sub">by D. Loebner</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0466</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0466.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1924-02-15">Feb. 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW SCANDAL BREAKS OUT AT THE CONGREGATION AM ABRAHAM ANSHE POLAND</title><title level="a" type="sub">by D. Loebner</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Congregation Am Abraham Anshe Poland, which has a synagogue on Washburne Avenue and which has already received some unfavorable publicity, has a new quarrel on its hands. A quarrel in the Congregation means not only loud arguments, face-slapping and revolver threats, but it also means courts, deputy sheriffs, police, and arrests. This congregation has already caused the Jewish community of Chicago a great deal of shame. The members of that congregation cannot come to an understanding among themselves, cannot divide up the property of the synagogue among themselves, as the rabbis, headed by Rabbi [Judah L.] Gordon, decided that they should do.</p>
   <p>The Presberg partisans were and remain the stronger element in the Congregation.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0467.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They would be willing to give up their membership in the synagogue, if they could get back the property they have invested in it. However, the Mosher partisans, who promised the rabbis to abide by their decision, declared that they would neither give up their membership in the synagogue nor would they pay out to the Presberg partisans the money that the latter have invested in the synagogue. Mr. Mosher and his partisans are, therefore, held responsible by Jewish public opinion for the scandals that occur in the synagogue.</p>
   <p>There are many rich people among the Mosher partisans. Mr. Itche Mordecai [Mosher] himself could withdraw a few thousand dollars from the bank and thus solve the whole problem. Why doesn't he do it? Why don't the other members who are so embittered against Presberg, do it? Presberg and his supporters have a share in the synagogue and they are entitled to get their share back. It is absurd to say that they can be expelled without being given a single cent. Disregarding the rabbis' decision is a dishonorable act.</p>
   <p>This is the proper place to reprint the decision of the rabbis, which was <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0468.jpg" n="3"/>given out about two months ago. "We, the undersigned, after hearing the claims and counterclaims of both sides, have decided that both parties should separate and divide the property of the synagogue equally among themselves. If one of the parties wishes to remain in possession of the synagogue, it should pay the other party the sum of two thousand dollars within four weeks from the date which appears below, on this document. We have been assured by both parties, before we began to consider this case, that they would abide by our decision. We have also decided that the scrolls of the Torah and other books belonging to the synagogue should be divided equally."</p>
   <p>If the scandals continue, the rabbis will be compelled to call in the members and warn them sternly that the synagogue will be put on the black list, if they do not comply with the decision of the rabbis, in which case there will not be anything there to divide.</p>
   <p>The Jewish community of Chicago cannot afford to have Congregation Am Abraham <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0469.jpg" n="4"/>Anshe Poland included in the list of its synagogues as long as services are held there and the Torah is read there under the supervision of deputy sheriffs and police, and as long as patrol wagons loaded with worshippers are frequently seen leaving for the police stations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
