<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-11-20">Nov. 20, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Women's League of the United Synagogue</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0681</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0681.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1921-11-20">Nov. 20, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE WOMEN'S LEAGUE OF THE UNITED SYNAGOGUE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The above organization is a national body organized in January, 1918 by Mrs. Solomon Schechter, of New York, and now comprises one hundred and twenty-six affiliated sisterhoods representing a membership of twelve thousand, six hundred and thirty-four members at large in all parts of the United States.</p>
   <p>The Women's League works with its parent body and especially aims to further Jewish education among women and children; to publish pamphlets and story books of Jewish value for them; to issue monthly programs for Sisterhood meetings and holiday celebrations in the home and school; to foster the observance of the Sabbath, festivals, and dietary laws; to establish student's houses that shall serve as centers of traditional Jewish life; and Kosher restaurants.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0682.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Chicago Branch of the Women's League was organized in November, 1918 by a small group of women, who elected Mrs. Benjamin Davis as chairman, and Mrs. Joseph Hevesh as Secretary. With the assistance of Mrs. Joshua Ginsburg, nine Sisterhoods were enrolled in the League at the close of the first year. Due to the efforts of Mrs. Joseph Hevesh, Mrs. Leon Waldman, Mrs. Jacob Glasser, and Mrs. C. Wecker, much progress was made. In May, 1920, Mrs. Leon Waldman was called to lead the growing organization, which now consists of fourteen local Sisterhoods numbering thirteen hundred members and one hundred members at large. A scholarship at the Jewish Theological Seminary in memory of Professor Israel Friedlander has been established by the Chicago Branch and it has assisted in all other lines of endeavor. It is now co-operating in giving a benefit for Jewish war orphans on Monday evening, November 21, at the Princess Theater, under the able chairmanship of Mrs. Louis Pitzele and an efficient committee.</p>
   <p>The officers of the organization are as follows: President, Mrs. Leon M. Waldman; Vice-presidents, Mrs. Joshua Ginsburg, Mrs. D. Gorchacof, <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0683.jpg" n="3"/>Mrs. I. Wecker, Mrs. Jacob Kulp, Mrs. Louis Pitzele; Treasurer, Mrs. Jacob Glasser; Recording Secretary, Mrs. David Almond; Corresponding Secretary, Mrs. L. Goldstein; Financial Secretary, Mrs. S. P. Gurwitz.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
