<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Chicago Forward</title>
      <date when="1919-06-01">June 1, 1919</date>
      <title level="a">The Executive of the Defense League Assumes Important Tasks</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0085</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0085.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Forward</title>
     <date when="1919-06-01">June 1, 1919</date>
     <title level="a">The Executive of the Defense League Assumes Important Tasks</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The conference of the 185 Jewish organizations gave a clear mandate to the executive, which met Wednesday evening in the West side Auditorium, that they should widen and enlarge the scope of the League's activity, and also the promise was made that money to cover all expenses will be raised. The inspired conference voted to remain a permanent organization, until the Polish, Rumanian, and Ukrainian Jews will be enabled to live in security without fear of pogroms. The executive decided to conduct a campaign against the propaganda issued by the Chicago Poles. The executive decided that first a well known lawyer should be engaged to protect the interests of the Jews of Chicago and to prosecute those Poles who preach, write, or talk a boycott against the Jews.</p>
   <p>The office of the League will be in the West side at 803 W. 12th St. All who have complaints should bring them to the League office, which will open this Tuesday moreing-Prior to Tuesday one should come to 720 W. 12th St. and ask for M. Shuchter. The executive hired a very capable secretary <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0086.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. Cohen who should be able to fulfill his duties. He has been instructed to publish memoranda regarding the pogroms and to publish the speeches made at the Auditorium. Arrangements are being made to call a mid-West conference of the various Defense Leagues, and further arrangements are being made for a national convention to be held in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
