<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-12">Apr. 12, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">The Weak Side of the Orthodoxy</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0507</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0507.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1923-04-12">Apr. 12, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">THE WEAK SIDE OF THE ORTHODOXY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The temple of Reform Judaism is empty throughout the year, but the membership of the Reform congregation grows from year to year. We must reckon with this fact. Our synagogues [Orthodox] are still packed, but the membership of the Orthodox congregations does not grow. The immigration of German or Austrian Jews has ceased completely, and if the membership of the Reform congregation is growing, it must be admitted that this growth, notwithstanding the German Jews, can be attributed to the Eastern European Jews in America--i.e., to the Orthodox elements who have become Americanized. We have no statistics on the membership of the Reform congregations, but it is certainly no exaggeration to say that the majority of the membership of all Reform congregations in America, at present, consists of Eastern European Jews. Reform in America has already long ceased to be a monopoly of the German Jews.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0508.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Americanized Eastern European Jew joins a Reform temple not because he thinks that Reform is a new Torah, or a better Torah, but since he has lost his religious innocence and perhaps his religious sentiment, he would like to belong to a religious community in which he finds serenity, calmness, decent [human] relationships, respect for his neighbors, etc. If he had sought religion, Jewish religion, he would not have become a member of a Reform congregation. He joins [a Reform congregation] not because he seeks religion, but rather something which is similar to the Jewish religion. He must, after all, belong to some sort of congregation, and at the same time, he would like a quiet, respectable atmosphere.</p>
   <p>Can he not find this quiet and respectable atmosphere in the Orthodox synagogue just as well as in the temple? Unfortunately, we must answer "no". In the Reform temple there is no religion; there isn't a flicker of genuine religious spirit. In the temple there prevails a cold, but serene atmosphere. In the Orthodox synagogue--naturally there are exceptions--one can find a <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0509.jpg" n="3"/>genuine religious spirit, a genuine Jewish religious atmosphere, but there is none of the serenity, or dignity that a holy place should command, nor is there the atmosphere of good breeding.</p>
   <p>In the Orthodox synagogue, the worshipers chatter while the cantor chants or while the reader of the Scrolls reads. In the Orthodox synagogue, a person feels so much at home that he often forgets that he is in a synagogue--a holy place. When the weather is good, one-half of the congregation stands either in the vestibule, or outside on the sidewalk, entertaining themselves as if they were in a club. During a holiday, one-half of the membership is out in the vestibule smoking and running around from one place to another; there is no respect for the [religious] services. One can often hear loud voices and vulgar expressions--naturally from vulgar people--and not infrequently a quarrel arises in the synagogue over an Eliah or Maftir, or other honors [Eliahs and Maftirs are honors bestowed upon worshipers, such as reading the Torah, etc.].</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0510.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This makes a very unfavorable impression on the American or Americanized Jew. He simply cannot stand such behavior, and he stays away from the synagogue, not because he is an opponent of Orthodoxy, but because he cannot tolerate such conduct in the Synagogue, and consequently, he finds his place in the Reform temple. He does not strengthen the ranks of Reform morally or religiously because when an Eastern European Jew becomes a member of a Reform temple, he no longer has a religion. Nevertheless, he strengthens the Reform temple materially, and, above all, his children are lost to us as Jews. In the measure that he strengthens the Reform temple, he weakens the Orthodox synagogue, and materially the Orthodox synagogue is not so strong that it can afford to remain indifferent to this loss.</p>
   <p>As a member of a Reform temple, his children grow up without any knowledge of Judaism. But as long as he remains a member of an Orthodox congregation, he will probably send his children to the Talmud Torah and they [the children] will remain Jews.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0511.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Although he [the Eastern European Jew] is no longer religious, nevertheless, his departure from the Orthodox synagogue is a great loss to the Orthodoxy. Why does he leave the Orthodox synagogue? He does so simply because religious dignity, serenity, good breeding, and respect are lacking in the Synagogue. An American [Jew] may not be pious, but when he is in a synagogue, he is respectful. He has respect for the place that he is in. Unfortunately, however, that respect is absent in the Orthodox congregation. A synagogue too often presents the aspect of a club.</p>
   <p>Can't the representatives and the officials of the Orthodox congregations correct this deplorable condition? Can we not have an Orthodoxy that demands respect? Can't the presidents of the synagogues establish rules to force the worshipers to remember always that they are in a holy place?</p>
   <p>We believe that the heads of the synagogues can do a great deal to put an end to this sad condition which drives thousands of Eastern European Jews in America, who have become Americanized, into the arms of Reform. A single <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0512.jpg" n="6"/>president of a synagogue can do nothing, but if all the presidents in Chicago held a conference to seek ways and means of improving this condition, they would accomplish something. The question is, however, how can we get the presidents together at a conference?</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, the presidents of the synagogues lack the consciousness of their duties to Orthodoxy Jewry. They think that all they have to do is look after their synagogues, and that they have no other obligations to society. How can we prove to them that their conception of their duties is wrong? How can we make them understand that as presidents of synagogues, they are the presidents, i.e., the heads of the whole Orthodox community, and must perform certain duties to the community?</p>
   <p>It would be a good thing if the rabbis were to devote an entire sermon to the question: "The Synagogue President and His Duties to the Orthodox Community". Perhaps the presidents of the synagogues would listen to <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0513.jpg" n="7"/>their own rabbis.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
