<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-27">Jan. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">N. W. Y. W. H. A. Has Big Year Ahead</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1412</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1412.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1922-01-27">Jan. 27, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">N. W. Y. W. H. A. HAS BIG YEAR AHEAD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(In English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The North West Young Women's Hebrew Association plans to do three or four times the work that was done last year. This young rapidly growing organization plans to realize this year their aim of building a Jewish Community Center on the North West side, which is a long felt need in that part of Chicago. This entire district has not now one suitable gathering place. The proceeds of their big program for their annual dance at the Parkway Hotel on December tenth and of their other social affairs have swelled their Building Fund considerably. A centrally located Community Center for the Jewish population of the North West side is much needed, and will be welcomed enthusiastically.</p>
   <p>At the meeting of January twelfth, it was voted that two vice presidents would be needed to carry forward the extensive plans laid down. Mrs. Sadie Smith Siegel, who was elected Vice-President on January fifth, was voted First Vice-<pb facs="5423972_9_1_1413.jpg" n="2"/>President, and Miss Rose Catrum Second Vice-President. Miss Rose Ostrum was appointed Chairman Social Committee, Miss Florence Dick Chairman Membership Committee, Miss Rayda Posner Chairman Publicity Committee, and Miss Helen Lieder Chairman Educational Committee. The new Board of Directors will hold a special meeting on Thursday, January twenty-sixth, to complete plans for the activities of the organization for the coming year. The plans include a "Y. W." monthly paper, a Dramatic Circle, bigger Athletic activities, a Home Nursing Class, and regular dances, and socials and joint socials with the North West Y. M. H. A. There will be a Theatre Party, Bunco Party and Joint Social with the N. W. Y. M. H. A. during February.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
