<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-23">Nov. 23, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Again the Rabbi of Old</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0731</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-04">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0731.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1920-11-23">Nov. 23, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">AGAIN THE RABBI OF OLD</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial in English)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American-born Jew, even if he be Orthodox to the core and an absolutely observing Jew, does not know the type of the rabbi of old. He may be satisfied with the rabbi at his disposal, but he is unaware of the fact that the Orthodox rabbi of old was a man quite different not only in character, but in his world concept, in his conception of things, from the up-to-date Orthodox rabbi.</p>
   <p>The Orthodox rabbi of old was not a worldly man in our meaning of the term. As a rule he knew next to nothing of worldly affairs, and was solely interested in Talmudic and cognate learning. Only in rare cases was he a worldly man too. But on the whole he was the embodiment of scholarship only, and the personification of piety. He had a pure mind and a clean mouth, and talked little about matters not pertaining to his own activities in life. Though only a scholar by <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0732.jpg" n="2"/>profession, and though not exercising many religious functions, he was, nevertheless, a religious personality in so far as he was actually a saint. He was a saintly person, and given only to matters spiritual. His vast influence and the respect he commanded were not only due to his superior scholarship, but also to his saintliness, to his deep piety, and to the beauty of his personality. The old type of the Orthodox rabbi was the embodiment of modesty: he hated notoriety, he hated publicity, and everything pertaining to prosaic daily life. At the same time he was always ready to give advice to anybody who sought it. If he had to sit in judgment and issue a verdict, his judgment was final. True, he was not hasty in his decisions, and was very, very careful before committing himself to anything, but once committed, his judgment was absolute, and both contending parties would accept it without reservation because they knew that the rabbi was the most disinterested person in this world and was the personification of impartiality.</p>
   <p>Sometimes the old rabbi would take a hand in communal affairs, but indirectly.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0733.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If the educational conditions in the community were unsatisfactory, he would call upon the leaders of the community to do something to remedy the situation. And only when a rabbi was desirous of teaching, would he resort to the organizing of a Yeshivah, not with the object of being the head of an educational establishment, but with the object of spreading the knowledge of the Talmud among the youth. The Yeshivah was often enough a source of embarrassment and trouble to the rabbi because in many cases he had to take care of the poor disciples, and would part [i.e., share] with them his last crumble of bread.</p>
   <p>The rabbi of old was courteous, polite, good-natured, and would treat all alike--all with the same courtesy and the same politeness. In addition, the old rabbi was a true philanthropist. His poor salary, consisting of a few rubles a week, he would distribute among those in need. In order to enable the wife of the rabbi to keep some sort of a household and to procure bread for the rabbi's family, they would give her the salary and not the rabbi himself, lest <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0734.jpg" n="4"/>he would give it away to the poor.</p>
   <p>The old rabbi was the type of a man who inspired confidence and respect. Even the freethinkers of the community--and there always were any number of them in every community--would respect the rabbi because they knew that he was a saintly person and the embodiment of sincerity and good-naturedness on the one hand, and of true scholarship and intellectual sincerity on the other.</p>
   <p>Needless to say that the rabbi of old was very exact in his observance of the law, but at the same time, he was a liberal-minded man. Fanaticism was strange to his mind. The more pious he was, the more liberal-minded he was toward others.</p>
   <p>To this type of a rabbi, who is unfortunately a rare bird in this country, but who is still to be found in the old country, we owe the survival of Orthodox Judaism, and a good part of our survival as a people. He was a source of <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0735.jpg" n="5"/>inspiration and made everybody love Judaism and all that goes with it. He was himself the embodiment of true Jewish idealism, true Jewish piety, true Jewish scholarship and learning, and true Jewish philanthropy. He inspired the community not by his sermons, because he would preach only twice a year, and sermonizing as a whole was none of his business, but would inspire the community by his saintly life, by the purity of his character, by the greatness of his personality, and by his great, sweet soul.</p>
   <p>Are there such rabbis today in this country? We wonder.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
