<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-29">July 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">P. O. W. Convention Elects Chicagoan for Grand Master</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_0058</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0058.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-07-29">July 29, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">P. O. W. CONVENTION ELECTS CHICAGOAN FOR GRAND MASTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Samuel Epstein of Chicago, a diamond broker, was elected Grand Master of the Progressive Order of the West at yesterday's session of the convention being held in the Sherman Hotel. He defeated two opponents; Morris Klein, also a Chicagoan, and Samuel Krantzberg of St. Louis.</p>
   <p>A complete group of Grand Lodge officers was elected with Mr. Epstein, many of whom have served the Order in that capacity previously, and others who are very capable workers.</p>
   <p>The convention passed a resolution yesterday, on [the question of] women suffrage for the benefit of the women members of the Order. From now on the women of the Order will be able to vote not only for male delegates, but also for female delegates to the convention. According to a second resolution, one delegate to the convention may be sent for every hundred members. This was one of the recommendations which the Grand Master presented in his message; his other recommendations were not passed.</p>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_0059.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>When the result of the woman suffrage resolution was announced, the women became very jubilant and the men gave them a great ovation. The Order's ladies' auxiliary in Chicago, whose purpose is to help indigent members, has a membership of two hundred. Within its ranks can be found: Jessie Diskin, Rosa Goldstein, Ella Harlin, Ida Julius, Ida Baron, Jennie Halperin, Gussie Fogel, Bessie Hirshberg, Lina Wolf, Ida Horwitch, Anna Karman, and Rebecca Halperin.</p>
   <p>The convention will close today. Many resolutions will be passed. The question of "fraternal rights" within the Order will be put to a vote. Then, as usual, there will be the voting of money for charity and for the Denver Sanitarium. This will be followed by the installation of the Grand Officers, after which the convention will close. The next convention of the Order will be held in St. Louis.</p>
   <p>[Editor's note: No explantion given of "fraternal rights."]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
