<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Daily Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-04">May 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The Attitude of the Repenter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423972_9_1_1705</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-10">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1705.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>JEWISH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sunday Jewish Courier</title>,
<date when="1919-05-04">May 4, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE ATTITUDE OF THE REPENTER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We can accept with certainty that Mr. Jacob Schiff, is not the only one of the former opponents of the Zionist movement who "saw the light" and changed his position. He, unlike the others, however, had the courage to openly proclaim his altered views, not being satisfied with silent approval or a simple declaration that he no longer is of the opposition. He considers it his duty to be the defender of justice for the movement, and to agitate for a Jewish homeland in Palestine.</p>
   <p>This he accomplished last week, when he published, in The Nation, his article on "The Necessity of a Jewish Homeland."</p>
   <p>Mr. Schiff points out the uncertain conditions of Jews in Eastern European <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1706.jpg" n="2"/>territories will be able to support a population of over 5,000,000."</p>
   <p>Mr. Schiff is, however, displeased with Palestinian agitation. It is superfluous, he states, to hold before the eyes of Jews, the ever tremulous question of a Jewish State. When Jews will be the majority in Palestine and all will proceed smoothly, then they will have plenty of time to decide what form of government they desire. A state, he says, cannot be purchased, ready-made; and a nation cannot be created simply on past enlightenments. The main issue is practical work. The sooner practical methods are adopted to make Palestine a homeland for Jews who wish to settle there, the sooner will begin the redemption of the Jewish question. With the first opening of Palestine for the greater Jewish masses, with a constant, although at first,slow stream of the Jewish population from their <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1707.jpg" n="3"/>present places of suffering, then, eventually, the Jewish question in these countries will begin to improve."</p>
   <p>In some paragraphs of this article he calls to mind the One Nation. "Palestine," he says "should become not simply a city of refuge for the persecuted Jew, but a land of opportunity, extending the possibilities of life under better moral conditions. Free of materialistic influences of the Western World, the Jew will have the opportunity to fully develop those assets which enabled him to sustain himself in the past, even to the highest pinnacles of mankind. A Jewish homeland in Palestine, will mean a place for the convening of Jewish learning and Jewish wisdom; for development of literary gems such as the world has already witnessed."</p>
   <p>The beauty of Mr. Schiff's assertions in this article, lie in the following: <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1708.jpg" n="4"/>Mr. Schiff makes these statements with the belief of a man giving the results of his own research, uninfluenced by previous works. He reminds us of a diligent man who betook himself to his work, and discovered for himself the formula of Isaac Newton's "Law of Gravitation," not knowing that Newton had already discovered that for him.</p>
   <p>He naturally expresses many things Lou Pinskey, Dr. Herzel and others have said before him, but the thoughts he expressed were original with him. At least, he thinks so. In this lies something very significant.</p>
   <p>Although, Mr. Schiff is against political agitation in Zionism, yet he pays high tribute to it in saying that it fulfilled an important mission. "Their leaders have earned a place among the Jewish people; the movement they built <pb facs="5423972_9_1_1709.jpg" n="5"/>and sponsored, awoke, in the Jew, self-respect, self-consciousness, and a justifiable pride. It drove before it 'indifference' and retained in Judaism many who would long have been lost to us."</p>
   <p>But from now on, Mr. Schiff sees before him mainly the practical reclamation of Palestine. He hopes for a system of irrigation to make the land fruitful; a system of education that will enable the Jewish youth to cope with the struggle for existence; the revival of the Hebrew language; and the use of all instruments necessary to rebuild the country.</p>
   <p>In other words, Mr. Schiff desires what every earnest Zionist advocates. We may expect many more of Mr. Schiff's caliber to follow his good example.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
