<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-24">Oct. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">News of the Czech Stage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0656</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0656.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-24">Oct. 24, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS OF THE CZECH STAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Karel Capek's utopian drama, "R. U. R." (Rossums Universal Robots) had its Bohemian-American premiere last Sunday on the Ludvikovo Divadlo stage (Frantisek Ludvik Bohemian Dramatic Association). The presentation [actually] occurred on the stage of Sokol Chicago Hall. [Translator's note: The Ludvikovo Divadlo used this stage in most of its productions.] Simultaneously "R. U. R." was played by the Cesko-Americke Narodni Divadlo (Bohemian-American National Theater) on the stage of the Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs. Those who feared that the production was a risky experiment were pleasantly surprised. They learned that their doubts as to the abilities of our stock companies lacked foundation as much as their claims that Capek's dramatic work would be misunderstood by our playgoers.</p>
   <p>Both our dramatic associations considered the Sunday performance a festive occasion, and it seemed as if every member of both companies had put his whole soul into his role. The audiences followed the play with ever- <pb facs="5418478_3_0657.jpg" n="2"/>increasing tension and excitement. If, as was believed, the production of this play was a dangerous experiment, then the victory of our Chicago [Czech] theaters is the more to be admired; the Ludvikovo Association and the Lawndale theater deserve our full recognition for producing this original Czech novelty, which is now gaining recognition on the stages of the entire world. Capek's brilliant work received copious mention on the occasion of its American premiere in New York, where this extraordinary creative effort led to immediate recognition by the foremost dramatic critics of the eastern metropolis. [Translator's Note: Here follows a somewhat detailed description of the plot of "R. U. R.," which, since it is rather well known to readers and playgoers, the translator did not consider it necessary to include.]</p>
   <p>This is only a succinct outline of this fantastic plot, and one must actually see the play to appreciate it fully, to observe with what dramatic meaning the substance of it is endowed, to evaluate at their true worth the literary gems which have been inserted into the text, and to realize with what mastery <pb facs="5418478_3_0658.jpg" n="3"/>the individual roles have been worked out in order to excite and to captivate the audience.</p>
   <p>The Ludvikovo players have given such attention to the play as may be expected only of a first-class stock company. It may therefore be looked upon as an example of honest dramatic stagecraft.....The entire production and the [technical] handling of the play do honor to Mr. Horlivy, the stage manager.</p>
   <p>The Narodni Divadlo group may easily place "R. U. R." among its greatest triumphs, not only for the purely dramatic handling of the play by the members of the company but also for the scenic effects produced.</p>
   <p>The play was finally staged after a long series of preliminary rehearsals which guaranteed perfect teamwork free of undesirable flaws. Although each role was most punctiliously studied by the players, one may say more about the individual performer's work; for it far surpassed the ordinary run of stage action.....Mr. Havelka may be fully satisfied with his accomplishment as manager.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0659.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We have often had occasion to remark the interest displayed by our theater-going public. The Sunday performances were attended by audiences which gave the most eloquent proof of their quality. It certainly requires a highly developed public to sit breathlessly and in almost sepulchral silence through a play lasting till five minutes past midnight.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
