<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-02">May 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Old, Experienced Business Men</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0258</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0258.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-02">May 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">OLD, EXPERIENCED BUSINESS MEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Messrs. Novak and Stejskal, who operate the first Bohemian Mortgage Bank, a real estate business, insurance and steam-ship ticket agency at 1817 South Loomis Street, have so many years of business experience behind them and can boast of such success and general good will, that their place of business is sought out by our countrymen from all parts of Chicago and vicinity.</p>
   <p>Whoever comes to Novak and Stejskal, either to buy or sell property, to borrow money with which to purchase property, to lend money, or who needs insurance with a reliable company, is always satisfactorily served.</p>
   <p>The firm also administers estates, and transfers money to Bohemia, and anywhere else in Europe. These old, experienced experts in all matters of this kind have satisfied thousands of clients in the past, and will satisfy all those who turn to them in the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0259.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>and in addition to this, we will open a branch salesroom in the department store of Albert Lurie and Company on Blue Island Avenue.</p>
   <p>We have arranged this branch, having in view chiefly the convenience of the Bohemian and other Slavonic public, thereby giving them an opportunity to buy all their needs without any unnecessary loss of time.</p>
   <p>We will conduct our enlarged business in such a manner that butchers will be able to turn to us with the fullest confidence that they will be given the best terms to be found anywhere. We have special prices for inn-keepers and restaurant owners.</p>
   <p>Deliveries will be made to the home of all orders, whether made in person or by telephone. The greatest care will be given to all orders, large or small. Against all this, we cherish the firm hope that our Bohemian <pb facs="5418478_3_0260.jpg" n="3"/>public, in recognition of our efforts, will give precedence to a Bohemian store before that of any other nationality.</p>
   <p>All out-of-town orders are filled carefully, and as quickly as possible.</p>
   <p>Bohus Hak and Emil Kohn.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
