<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-17">July 17, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Theatrical Amateurs of Chicago Join in the Proposal to Organize a National Theatrical Amateurs Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1190</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1190.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-17">July 17, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THEATRICAL AMATEURS OF CHICAGO JOIN IN THE PROPOSAL TO ORGANIZE A NATIONAL THEATRICAL AMATEURS ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of the Chicago theatrical amateurs was called last Saturday, chiefly those old amateurs who for many years past have been and still are active upon our amateur stages. The occasion being the picnic of Sokol Slovanska Lipa, headed by our old amateur theatrical pioneer, Mr. Joseph Jurka.</p>
   <p>The following named persons were present in response to a special circular sent out: Mmes. Libuse Bilek, Doskocil, Fligl, Frelich, Hladovec, Nechansky, Piper, Stejskal, Stolf, Uher, Vanek, Zarobsky, Zeman, Messrs. Bartizal, Cerny, Cizkovsky, Dusek, Fligl, Frrcek, Hospodsky, Legat, Nechansky, Ort, Vanek, Jar. Mayer, Vlach and Jurka. Those present made known their approval to such an organization, and those absent sent an excuse in writing by Messrs. Filip, V. Nemravek <pb facs="5418478_3_1191.jpg" n="2"/>and A. Pregler.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jurka began the meeting in the open air of Mr. Opatrny's park. He explained that the organization of Bohemian theatrical amateurs in the United States is a necessity in order to concentrate amateur theatrical forces and attach our youth to the heart of Bohemian Thalia. He spoke in favor of taking steps toward that end, mentioning that in the organization of a Bohemian Amateur Theatrical Association there would be given a more forceful expression to the honoring of the memory of Jindrich Mosna, the greatest Czech comedian on the legitimate stage. Mr. Hospodsky then spoke, saying that in this respect that the entire West looks to Chicago, to that center of large communities and colonies of the West, where there are so many theatrical societies and associations in need of sources of new talent.</p>
   <p>The proposal of the amateur associations of New York, which is as follows, <pb facs="5418478_3_1192.jpg" n="3"/>was adopted: "Let the various amateur theatrical associations in Bohemian America unite after the example of the Central Amateur Association of Bonemia into one family, lead by an organization under the name Central Union of Bohemian-American Theatrical Amateurs Jindrich Mosna in order to work toward the regeneration of amateur acting in Bohemian America."</p>
   <p>It was then decided that Mr. Joseph Jurka temporarily perform the office of president and secretary, transacting all matters which come up and call the next meeting.</p>
   <p>A motion by Mr. Jurka was unanimously adopted that the amateurs gathered here express deepest sympathy and sorrow over the tragic death of one of their most zealous members and also a friend of the Bohemian theatre, Mr. Vaclav Cervenka, who died in Lipska, Germany. This expression of sympathy is sent to his immediate family and all surviving friends. The meeting was then adjourned.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
