<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Czechoslovak Review</title>, Vol. III, No. 1, pp. 22-23,
<date when="1919-01">Jan. 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Chamber of Commerce Proposed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0125</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0125.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Czechoslovak Review</title>, Vol. III, No. 1, pp. 22-23,
<date when="1919-01">Jan. 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CHAMBER OF COMMERCE PROPOSED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The campaign for close commercial relations between the United States and Czechoslovakia was opened at a conference of Czechoslovak business men, who met in Baltimore Dec. 10th, the occasion of the Southern Commercial Congress. After the session was over, about thirty visitors and prominent Baltimore Bohemians met at the Emerson Hotel to discuss ways and means of helping the economic progress of the old country. Some of the foremost Bohemian-American business men were present. From Chicago came Frank Hajicek, president of Lawndale National Bank; John A. Cervenka, president of the Pilsen Brewing Company, and a member of the Board of Directors of the American State Bank; John A. Sokol, food importer; Josef Dusek, one of Chicago's biggest commission merchants; and Frank Skala, steamship ticket agent.</p>
   <p>Everyone present was agreed as to the advisability of establishing at once a Czechoslovak-American Chamber of Commerce. The one great service <pb facs="5418478_3_0126.jpg" n="2"/>the Czechoslovaks in this country could render to the newly formed Republic is to find markets for Czechoslovakian products in the United States. While the principal markets for Czechoslovak exports will be found in Russia and the Balkans, many things are produced in Bohemia for which demand can be found in America.</p>
   <p>It was decided at the Baltimore conference to take important steps for the establishment of a Chamber of Commerce. This institution will issue bulletins and booklets on Czechoslovak industries, will give financial ratings of importers in Bohemia, will maintain permanent commercial exhibits in New York, Chicago and probably other cities. The formal constitution of the American-Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce will take place in Chicago, at a great convention of Bohemian and Slovak business men from all parts of the United States on Feb. 3rd and 4th.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
