<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-03-29">Mar. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Rare Artistic Treat</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0868</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0868.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-03-29">Mar. 29, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">RARE ARTISTIC TREAT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every year the Chicago Irish colony celebrates, in a glorious and pompous manner, the name day of their national patron, Saint Patrick; they boast about their Saint Patrick. Local Italians also have a significant day of the year, a day when in a most demonstrative way they celebrate the memory of Christopher Columbus, the discoverer of America. In Chicago also reside Poles, Croatians, Jugoslavs, Swedes, French, English, Japanese, Chinese, Hungarians, Germans, and members of many other nationalities who, on a certain day of the year, either justly or unjustly, proudly expand their chests, merely to show their sublimity to those who do not belong to them, at least in this way.</p>
   <p>In Chicago, there are also Czechoslovaks. They too have their own national holiday--October 28, when they celebrate the Czechoslovak Independence Day. Besides this, there are also other national holidays.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0869.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Although these are not regular and frequent, nevertheless, they are here. On these days, local Czechoslovaks do not arrange great demonstrative manifestations, but, nevertheless, being governed by their own hearts, by their own sentiments, not being encouraged and forced, they spontaneously participate in these holidays and manifest their national pride and adherence. When I mention these holidays I have in mind Czechoslovakian art, that quiet and modest art, which because of its genuineness is equal to any in the world. I especially mean the musical and vocal arts, which by themselves are convincing the whole world of the superiority of the Czechoslovaks.</p>
   <p>Yesterday we had such a Czechoslovak national holiday in Chicago. The Česko Dělnický Pěvecký Sbor (The Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society), under the leadership of its excellent conductor and well-known local artist, Mr. Joseph Houdek, arranged its springtime concert, which was held in the assembly hall of the Carter H. Harrison High School. We may <pb facs="5418478_3_0870.jpg" n="3"/>say, that is, we must say in advance, that it was a first-class musical event. Credit for it is given not only to the conductor, Mr. Joseph Houdek, who, by an excellent selection of the entire vocal program, gave proof of his artistic taste, but also to the Cesko Delnicky Pevecky Sbor, which sang in pure intonation and beautiful, dynamic modulation.</p>
   <p>What I am most thankful for to the Česko Dělnický Pěvecký Sbor is its careful selection of the soloist. The soloist was the famous Czechoslovak tenor, Otakar Marak, late member of the Bohemian National Theater in Prague, Czechoslovakia, who for many years has been propagating the glory of Bohemian art throughout the world. Otakar Mařák's appearance in the concert yesterday was the best part of the program and it will be remembered for a long time to come. For that treat the Česko Dělnický Pěvecký Sbor deserves our most sincere thanks.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0871.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The assembly hall of the Carter H. Harrison High School began to fill shortly before 1 P. M. The throngs of people were not scared away by the storm which passed over Chicago shortly before that time. Before 2 P. M., the large assembly hall was filled to capacity. It is with pleasure that we find we must state that members of many other nationalities attended. The concert was also attended by Jan Masaryk, of Washington, D. C., who spoke a few words. He said that he is proud of the fact that he is a Czechoslovak. The words he had read on the program, "Concert of the Česko Dělnický Pěvecký Sbor," were for him a great inspiration. He could not imagine anything more idealistic than a singing Bohemian worker. He also remarked that during the past war people were forbidden to speak the Bohemian language in our old country, but songs were sung in Bohemian because Bohemian song could not be taken away by anyone. Finally, he said that he was glad he had come to Chicago, but he would be even more pleased if he could stay longer with us. He concluded his speech by saying that everyone knows where he is located, <pb facs="5418478_3_0872.jpg" n="5"/>and, therefore, anyone who has something in his heart should come to see him. His short speech created a strong impression and much enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>The opening number of the program was a splendid composition for male chorus, "Pochod Taboritu" (March of Taborites), by Karel Bendl, which made a deep impression upon the audience. The Česko Dělnický Pěvecký Sbor then sang "Pět Sboru" (The Five Compositions), by Dr. Antonín Dvořák. We are not expert critics, therefore, we refrain from criticism, and we present only our report. But taking our impressions into consideration, we judge these compositions to be of great musical value.....</p>
   <p>The moment Otakar Mařák appeared on the stage, he was greeted by a veritable storm of applause. He proved that the fame which preceded his appearance was not exaggerated. He demonstrated his rare art to the <pb facs="5418478_3_0873.jpg" n="6"/>audience in all its genuine beauty and purity as an opera singer by singing the aria of the prince from the opera "Rusalka," composed by Dr. Antonín Dvořák.....</p>
   <p>Yesterday's concert was a first-class artistic event which can be an encouragement for further enthusiastic and artistic work, not only to the Český Dělnický Pěvecká Sbor, but also to the remarkable conductor, Mr. Joseph Houdek, who deserves the fullest recognition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
