<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-16">Oct. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Last Day of the Carnival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1516</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1516.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-10-16">Oct. 16, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE LAST DAY OF THE CARNIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Carnival week will end today. This circumstance will certainly induce large crowds of people to take advantage of the opportunity to see something they will not see soon again.....</p>
   <p>The success of last night is indisputable. From early evening the sidewalks and both traffic lanes of 26th Street were filled with men, women, and children, mostly our countrymen, of course, and the crowds did not seem to be diminishing even at hours when, under normal circumstances, the street is practically deserted. You could not find a single sad, gloomy, or frowning face among these thousands; fun and pleasure were everywhere.....</p>
   <p>The attraction was the masked and costumed men and women.....</p>
   <p>The organizing committee, and the judges who awarded the prizes for the <pb facs="5418478_3_1517.jpg" n="2"/>costumes, estimated that there were close to two thousand costumed people in the crowd, all of whom marched in the parade.....</p>
   <p>Altogether thirty-eight prizes were awarded, nineteen for men and nineteen for women.....</p>
   <p>Some of the prizes were distributed last night, but the majority will be given to the fortunate winners tonight on the corner of 26th Street and St. Louis Avenue. All holders of the following lucky numbers should therefore be present to receive prizes.....</p>
   <p>The prizes are mostly appropriate souvenirs, but there are many practical articles among them, and the committee hopes that everybody will be satisfied.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
