<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-07">July 7, 1918</date>,
<title level="a">Sokol Festival</title><title level="a" type="sub">Slight Interest Shown in Gymnastic Contests (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1399</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1399.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-07">July 7, 1918</date>,
<title level="a">SOKOL FESTIVAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Slight Interest Shown in Gymnastic Contests (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The two-day festival of the Stredni Zupa (Middle Group) of Sokols was initiated yesterday. The group was created last year by combining various local groups under one banner. This was the first public appearance of the merged groups. Since extensive perparations were made for the occasion, the result may be called satisfactory in every respect. The first day of the rally was held in Pilsen Brewery Park. There were gymnastic contests of senior members and junior classes. They closed with a "Beseda," an evening with a brilliant program. Today again, a public drill will be held by members and the youth. It will be preceded by a parade.</p>
   <p>As far as the gymnastic contests are concerned, it must be admitted that they are a mere shadow today of what they used to be. There are 114 <pb facs="5418478_3_1400.jpg" n="2"/>contestants, mostly veterans and seniors. The reason for this is that the pick of the Sokols is in the Army and Navy. Altogether eighty-five per cent of the members are in military uniform. There were, in fact, only a few young men in the contest.</p>
   <p>The contestants were divided into three grades, the higher, medium, and lower. Some of the junior Sokols also took part.....</p>
   <p>The technical direction was in the hands of Mr. Jaroslav Kosar and some members of the technical committee. Since the program was carried out at a high rate of speed, the contest was completed in the forenoon. Mr. Thomas Vonasek acted as recorder of the score.....</p>
   <p>A bustling crowd filled Pilsen Brewery Park in the evening. The program was long and varied. A band of twenty-four, under Mr. Vaclav (Venzeslaus) Husa, opened by playing Mach's "Festival Overture," and Dr. Anton Mueller welcomed the gathering, being followed by Mr. Anton J. Cermak, who is now at the <pb facs="5418478_3_1401.jpg" n="3"/>head of the Sokol Community in America. The Cesko-Delnicky Pevecky Sbor (Czech Workmen's Singing Association), under the direction of Mr. Joseph Houdek, and the choir of the Croat Sokol, under Mr. A. Mario Kess, were rewarded with hearty applause. Our well-known amateur actress, Mrs. Antonia Cervenka, recited Kosar's poem, "V Dobe Nejtezsi" (In the most serious time). Mr. Hess sang, with the accompaniment of the orchestra, Wilbur D. Nesbitt's American march, "Your Flag and Mine," translated into the Czech language by Dr. J. Salaba Vojan.....</p>
   <p>Pupils of the Klaus-Mikuta school of dancing executed their numbers in perfect fashion. Sokol pupils from Racine, Wisconsin, gave an exhibition of Czech and Moravian dances. Mrs. Slavka Krejci sang Vojta Benes's "Song of the Czech Volunteers," and "Hej Slovane, Vzhuru Hlavy!" (Ho, Slavs, keep your heads high!) by F. L. Musil. J. Cestmir Svoboda drew sketches on the board to the accompaniment of music. "On the Fourth of July," a march by Arno Mario Hess, made a great hit.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1402.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The evening was a get-together and entertainment in true "Beseda" style, and was enjoyed in brotherly harmony and joviality.</p>
   <p>The second day of the rally will be held in Pilsen Brewery Park today.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
