<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-28">July 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Invited by the University</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1473</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1473.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-28">July 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">INVITED BY THE UNIVERSITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>If ever we were given an opportunity to make an appearance before the American intelligentsia, the invitation extended to the Czechs by Professor Pratt Judson, president of the University of Chicago, is unquestionably the best. To be introduced to a galaxy of personages such as the four hundred professors and to a body of twelve thousand students is of paramount significance for us. It will, therefore, be our task to represent ourselves in a dignified, impressive form. The occasion will be the Czech Day which is to be held at the University next November.</p>
   <p>What should be exhibited there? The best of everything on which our people may pride themselves. Samples from the art shop of the plain people of Moravia will, of course, be among the first items considered for exhibition. The Vzdelavaci Slovacky Klub (Slovak Educational Club) will associate itself with the Sokol Komensky, a jovial set of Moravian Slovaks. These two organizations and many members of the local Slovak colony are ready to busy themselves for the success of the great event.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1474.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"What have the Slovaks to offer?" This question will be asked by many Czechs who have not had closer associations with them. You would be astonished at the mass of beautiful things which the Slovaks claim as their own. You may have seen their costumes, those charming assortments of colors, just as they were painted for us by Uprka, Frolka, and many other artists. Can you remember the front of the poster used as an advertisement for the Posviceni (Feast) that was given by the Czech National Alliance last year? Those were figures of Slovaks, created by the brush of a native son of Slovak lands, the painter Tomanek. Just think of those embroideries! You surely remember them from the Posviceni where they were offered to patriotic buyers. Think of the jackets, a product of workmanship in which the Slovaks excel! The harmony of colors in their handwork is delightful. There is almost no nation in the world that could compete with the Slovaks in this particular branch of home industry. The artistic accomplishments of the Slovaks will not play the part of Cinderella on Czech Day at the University; they will appear in the luster worthy of a queen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
