<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-28">Mar. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Antagonized by His Fellow-Countrymen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-28">Mar. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">ANTAGONIZED BY HIS FELLOW-COUNTRYMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the most enterprising building contractors that ever came from our midst was our fellow-countryman Joseph A. Holpuch. It is to be regretted that we are compelled, on this occasion, to use the word "was", for he is no longer what he was. The reason will be given at the end of our biography of the man, whose loss may be felt before long by the community of our businessmen.</p>
   <p>Holpuch was born in the United States, in Chicago; but his start in life was not an easy one. He had to work hard to attain results, and he succeeded mainly by his energy and persistency, which could not be daunted by temporary failure. He was born at South May and West Nineteenth Streets, in 1876. His parents, Antonin and Anna Holpuch, occupied a position uncommon in those days, for the father was one of the first Czech contractors in the United States. Though he could not be called prosperous, the elder Holpuch did all he could for his son within the limits of his income; he <pb facs="5418478_3_0160.jpg" n="2"/>gave him the best education that could be gotten in the Chicago public schools.</p>
   <p>The son went to the old Throop School, then to West Division High school. After graduation, his ambition led him to Ann Arbor, Michigan, where he studied law with remarkable success.</p>
   <p>He did not, however,engage in the practice of law, but became interested in real estate instead, in accord with his natural instinct for the business. Still, seeing even greater opportunities elsewhere, he founded the Western Casket Company, and became its first president and general manager. He did not remain in this position very long, but sold out, pledging himself not to enter the casket business again. His next position was that of a representative of the Hines Lumber Company, covering their western district. About this time, in 1899, he married Paula Panos, with whom he lives in happy wedlock. They have two children, Helen and Joseph.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0161.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Holpuch finally tired of the lumber business, and wished to be in a business for himself. He became a building contractor in 1906, and remained one until January 1, 1917. This vocation made him feel happy. He began with little, but fought his way to success, not thinking then of the disappointments he was to meet at the end of this period. The misfortune which impeded his career was no fault of his own. It was the oversensitiveness, the vanity, the hurt pride, and especially the envy on the part of his fellowcountrymen which caused him trouble. These adverse influences made themselves felt acutely from the moment he was installed as a member of the Chicago School Board, by appointment of former Mayor Carter H. Harrison, to fill the vacancy left by Architect Dibelka.</p>
   <p>Holpuch's work as a member of the School Board attracted city-wide attention to his capability, his courage, and his frank manner. The English-language press, and also the Czech newspapers, gave publicity to his name, and it was this which seemed to irritate some of his fellow-countrymen. These people were of the opinion that he had accumulated for himself more earthly goods <pb facs="5418478_3_0162.jpg" n="4"/>than were due him; they set out to damage his business, which he had been forced to neglect in order to devote time to his official responsibilities, although these yielded no emoluments and were purely honorary. Moreover, they commenced to trouble the quiet of his home, whose welfare he had subordinated to his good will toward the commonwealth and particularly toward the people of his own race. They failed, however, to get the intended results, at least as far as his finances were concerned.</p>
   <p>Under these conditions Holpuch's longing to serve the people began to fade; he felt no desire to work further for the good of the schools, among which Carter H. Harrison High School stands as a memorial to his earlier efforts. He became convinced that his own fellow-countrymen did not ask for any open, honest, and unselfish handling of their school affairs; that they loathed the sight of one of their own race standing upon his own feet; therefore, he decided to give up his business as a contractor. He collected the money invested therein and deposited it as a fund for a new enterprise, which he knew would not be looked upon as an obstacle and an eyesore by his "friends", <pb facs="5418478_3_0163.jpg" n="5"/>against whom he wishes to warn any young man desiring to devote his energies to the benefit of the public. He has chosen refrigeration as his new field of activity, and will be at the head of the firm of Joseph A. Holpuch Company, Refrigerating Machines, with offices at 3113 West 22nd Street.</p>
   <p>Joseph A. Holpuch intends to give up his position on the School Board, which will mean a serious loss for the latter; his time henceforth will belong to his business and his family. It is assumed that he will remain the man who always proudly acknowledged his descent from Czech parents, and who, in spite of a momentary discord caused by slanderous tongues, will stand among us as one who has thousands of friends, and who is a defender of our Czech interests, as he was during his term as a member of the School Board.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
