<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-04-02">Apr. 2, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Skolni Rada</title><title level="a" type="sub">At the Bidding for the Decorative Work on the Vestibule of the Harrison Technical High School, Mr. Oldrich Farsky's sketch was Pronounced the most Artistic and Beautiful, but nevertheless was not accepted</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0622</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0622.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-04-02">Apr. 2, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">SKOLNI RADA</title><title level="a" type="sub">At the Bidding for the Decorative Work on the Vestibule of the Harrison Technical High School, Mr. Oldrich Farsky's sketch was Pronounced the most Artistic and Beautiful, But nevertheless was not accepted</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Skolni Rada (The School Board), as we previously said, had allowed $4,500 for the decorative work on the auditorium and vestibule of the Harrison Technical High School which, as is well known, is attended mostly by pupils of Bohemian descent.</p>
   <p>For that reason we would have been very happy if the work had been allotted to one of our Bohemian artists, so that it could have always remained as a remembrance of Bohemian art, and a lasting proof of the contention that this branch of Bohemians cannot and must not be considered inferior to any other nation living in America, not even excluding the Americans.</p>
   <p>This work for the Harrison Technical High School should have remained more <pb facs="5418478_3_0623.jpg" n="2"/>than an eloquent proof of the maturity of the Bohemians in the United States, it was to denote the maturity of the Bohemian people in the United States, and it was also to show the intellectual and artistic ripening taking place in music and art, to which we had called attention many times.</p>
   <p>Since Mr. Farsky did not work alone on his work of art, he did not receive the assignment for the work, but his design will be used in another part of the school building.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
