<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-12-04">Dec. 4, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A Bohemian Opera</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Pevecka Spolecnost "Bedrich Smetana" Triumph in Sokol Chicago Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0971</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0971.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-12-04">Dec. 4, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">A BOHEMIAN OPERA</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Pevecka Spolecnost "Bedrich Smetana" Triumph in Sokol Chicago Hall</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many of our countrymen had a very wonderful, and a long-awaited treat in the Sokol Chicago Hall last night. The treat was prepared by the Pevecka Spolecnost (Singing Society) Bedrich Smetana, which gave them an opportunity to hear again--after a long, long time--a Bohemian opera on a Bohemian stage. The Society presented the well-known and very popular comic opera "V Studni" (In the Well) by Vilem Blodek.....</p>
   <p>We do not hesitate to say that the performance was one of which even the Narodni Divadlo (National Theater) in Prague might justly have been proud. The performance was perfect in every detail, and the performers sang and acted very well. [Here a column and a half is devoted to the description--mostly laudatory--of the individual performances of the amateur singers and the parts they sang, the make-up, stage arrangements, etc.]</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0972.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A large orchestra, under the able direction of Mr. Adolf Erst, played. The rendition of Anton Dvorak's Ma Vlast (My Homeland), with which the evening of music opened, was enough to guarantee the success of the evening.</p>
   <p>Without exaggeration it may be said that the Pevecka Spolecnost Bedrich Smetana has in its membership a large number of genuinely talented people, of amateurs who are artists deserving of praise from the critics. We do hope that after this success the Society will not hesitate to attempt something even more ambitious. Perhaps--anyway, rumors have been heard to the effect that we may yet hear our "Prodana Nevesta" (Bartered Bride), during this season. We have the artistic material; all that we need is courage. With such a conductor as Mr. Erst, things may be accomplished which would otherwise be considered impossible. How about suggesting that all our singing societies take up this idea and do something about it?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
