<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-24">Feb. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">From Our Singing Societies</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Few Sincere Words in Regard to the Proposed Concert (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0882</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0882.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-24">Feb. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FROM OUR SINGING SOCIETIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Few Sincere Words In Regard To The Proposed Concert (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday we received a communication from Mr. Bendlak, an ardent supporter of singing clubs. It is addressed to the president of the Ústřední Pěvecká Jednota (Central Singing Union) and is meant for all members of our singing societies. Because of the interesting and important ideas contained in it, we do not hesitate to publish it for the benefit of the entire community of our readers. It runs as follows:</p>
   <p>"Mr. S., perhaps the best known person in Czech New York, is kind enough to send me letters frequently describing New York Czech society life. Whenever I open one of these letters, I ask myself just why we in Chicago do not have a man like Mr. S., or rather, and better, ten of them at once, for there is an ever-growing need for them here. Mr. S. is one of the most enthusiastic <pb facs="5418478_3_0883.jpg" n="2"/>Czech patriotic workers in New York, and at the same time a man who is both stern and open in his manner.....</p>
   <p>"Only a short time ago I received the news about the merger of all dramatic societies of Czech New York into one Amateur Actors' Association. The impulse for this step was given by the war; the knowledge that by collective and united activities the cause of our subjugated old homeland can be aided in the most efficient way prompted this action.</p>
   <p>"The introduction to the program of the first performance of the united amateurs extols the unification: "We have united our forces and want to demonstrate in a forceful, dignified manner that we are ready at this great time." This they proved within a short time on every occasion.....</p>
   <p>"These lines apply not to Chicago alone, but to all our associations.....</p>
   <p>Theoretically we Chicago Czech singers have been joined for a long time in the Pěvecká Jednota (United Singing Societies), in which, however, every <pb facs="5418478_3_0884.jpg" n="3"/>singing club and association preserves its individual independence.</p>
   <p>"But how does this unification of ours look in reality? The New York Amateur Actors' Association intends to testify to its union by its readiness to benefit the motherland. Let us make an allowance for the fact that our United Singing Societies emptied their treasury, so to speak, to the bottom, at the very beginning of the movement started by the Czech National Alliance. Let us further assume that by doing so, we have done the part allotted to us, which is far short of all that our singing societies are able to do for the welfare of our motherland.</p>
   <p>"How, then, do we wish, or are we able, to 'attest to our readiness'? If we do not act in the manner in which the New Yorkers do, how then can we show our readiness for singing? This question should be answered today by every one of the four hundred and fifty active members of the United Singing Societies.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0885.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"I cannot help recalling the days in the Coliseum, in Grant Park, and elsewhere. Though it was cheerful to see and hear our singers then, the memory is painful when I compare their activities then and now. It is true that not every member can always be at his post, but on the other hand, it is inexcusable that at the present time only one tenth of the members are really active. This is the situation, in spite of their awareness of the task they have taken upon themselves and the necessity for everyone's co-operation, whether he considers himself first or last in the ranks of the singers. We must not only assert, but also demonstrate in a patriotic manner, our allegiance to Czech song, the most precious heritage of our forefathers.</p>
   <p>"I believe that many who read these lines will be displeased at what I say. I wish to assure them, however, that it gives me no pleasure to vent my old grief over these conditions again. I would much rather state that we were present at rehearsals to the last man, or that at least ninety per cent of us met! How much better reading that would make, and how much higher an opinion our general public, which must always pass the ultimate judgment upon us, will have of our singers!</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0886.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"Everything can be rectified, nevertheless. Let us recall the declaration of the New York singers and say: 'We may be late, but, by strenuous, untiring effort, we shall make up for our neglect.'</p>
   <p>"Let us not only promise, but also prove by our deeds that we are singers.</p>
   <p>"Signed: Bedlák."</p>
   <p>We have further been informed by our singers that preparations for a big concert by the Central Singing Union to be given this coming spring are in full swing. There will be orchestral accompaniment, and gems of Czech music will be presented.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
