<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-23">Dec. 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Czechs Are a Music-Loving People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0222</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0222.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-23">Dec. 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE CZECHS ARE A MUSIC-LOVING PEOPLE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Czechs have a reputation among all peoples of the world for their love of music and song. Although we are a people numerically weak, we have composers and musical artists who are the cause of envy among the great nations. Every countryman of our likes to sing, likes to hear good music, and Czech children like to learn to play musical instruments. Czech parents, if it is possible, provide their children with musical instruments and have them trained by experienced teachers so as to assure them of a refined means of amusement and to start them on the road to a profitable life calling. Especially now, before and during the holidays, do we see plainly this endeavor on the part of Czech parents. Musical instrument stores among us have many customers at present. When Czech parents wish to provide their children with real and permanent enjoyment; when they wish to secure really valuable instruments for their households, they can confidently turn to the establishments of our countrymen which are located in all Czech communities of Chicago. In the Pilsen district <pb facs="5418478_3_0223.jpg" n="2"/>we have the old reliable establishments of Mr. Thomas Kosatka and Company at 1425 West 18th Street and Mr. Joseph Jiran at 1333 West 18th Street; in the California district the richly stocked establishment of Mr. Alois Solar at 3558 West 26th Street; in the Town of Lake and on the northwest side, the Georgi and Vitak Music Company, with one store at 4663 Gross Avenue and another at 769 Milwaukee Avenue; Mr. A. J. Turek with stores at 3641 West 26th Street and 1848 Allport Street. In all these establishments instruments may be selected in accordance to needs and means. Prices are moderate and money spent for such articles bring gladness and enjoyment to the families.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
