<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-04-12">Apr. 12, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">To the Attention of Bohemian and Slovak Organizations of Chicago and Vicinity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1312</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1312.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-04-12">Apr. 12, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">TO THE ATTENTION OF BOHEMIAN AND SLOVAK ORGANIZATIONS OF CHICAGO AND VICINITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The arrangement committee for the Ceskoslovensky Karneval (Czechoslovak Carnival), which will be arranged by the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe (Czechoslovak National Alliance of America), May 21 and 22, 1921, at the Ashland Avenue Auditorium, Van Buren Street and Ashland Boulevard, recently sent invitations to all the Bohemian and Slovak organizations of Chicago and vicinity to attend a special meeting. This meeting will be held on Wednesday, April 13, at 8 P. M., in the Bohemian-American Hall, 1440 West 18th Street, Chicago, and each organization will be asked to appoint a delegate to represent in the said meeting. We again call the attention of all the presidents and the secretaries of these organizations to this meeting, and ask them to attend it as delegates of those organizations which, in the meantime, had no opportunity to hold a meeting and elect regular delegates.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1313.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At this meeting, very important preparatory work will be discussed and no one will be obligated by attending. We also invite all our self-sacrificing national workers, whether they are representatives of any organization or not, to attend this meeting.</p>
   <p>This Ceskoslovensky Karneval will be arranged for the purpose of gaining the greatest possible amount of money which will be used for educational purposes--for the establishment of a modern educational institution in Czechoslovakia where such a institution is badly needed if our nation is to succeed in the fields of international competition with other nations, and in all phases of human endeavor. This year's Carnival will be something altogether different, and by it we will step before the American public in a very dignified way. The Carnival will be visited by many famous persons.</p>
   <p>Therefore, attend this meeting on Wednesday April 13, at the Bohemian-American Hall, and help us show what the united Czechoslovaks of Chicago can do!</p>
   <p>The arrangement committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
