<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-12-15">Dec. 15, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Exhibition by the Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Havlicek (Gymnastic Union).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1567</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1567.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-12-15">Dec. 15, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">EXHIBITION BY THE TELOCVICNA JEDNOTA SOKOL HAVLICEK (GYMNASTIC UNION).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1--The astonishing growth and prosperity of Bohemian California, a striking proof of energy and earnest effort, demonstrates that the Bohemian-Californians are attached to everything that breeds strength, vigor, and enterprise. For that reason they are especially all the Telocvicna Jednota Sokol Havlicek (Havlicek Gymnastic Union), which, although it is one of the youngest gymnastic unites, is nevertheless one of the strongest and most active. This gymnastic organization does honor to the name of Sokol and also to the great man for whom it is named. In the national and social fields it has plowed many a deep furrow and has sowed it with good seed which will surely bear good fruit, When so deserving and so well-liked a gymnastic organization holds an exhibition, it is only natural that it should enjoy the greatest popularity, as is now the case with the exhibition by the Havlicek Sokol held in Kafka's Hall, at the corner of Avers avenue and Twenty-sixth street. Every evening since Sunday great crowds have gathered there to enjoy themselves and also to promote the early realization of the Sokol's plan to build a stately gymnasium.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1568.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have already written about the adornment which the new gymnasium will be for Bohemian California, and what a good influence it will have upon our national life. For that reason the success of the Havlicek Sokol's exhibition gives us great pleasure, and we are convinced that its closing days will be most successful of all. A different band plays every day, and a new program is arranged daily. Mr. Kolar's band played yesterday, today Mr. Kaspar's band will play; on Friday the California Band will furnish the music.</p>
   <p>The exhibition will close on Saturday with a dance, with music by Mr. Kolarik's orchestra. Saturday afternoon will be dedicated to the children. Admission to the exhibition is free. Admission to the dance on Saturday evening will be twenty five cents for individuals and thirty five cents for couples.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
