<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1909-12-27">Dec. 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Amateurs Please in Comedy.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1196</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1196.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1909-12-27">Dec. 27, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">AMATEURS PLEASE IN COMEDY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 2--"Palackeho Trida Cis. 27," a comedy by the never to be forgotten actor and playwright Samberk, was presented by the Amateur Players to an appreciative audience at the hall of "Slovanska Lipa," the evening before last.</p>
   <p>The success of the performance was guaranteed by the excellent humoristic features of the play, and in no less degree by the artistic skill of the Amateurs. Throughout the performance the audience was shaking with laughter. The individual players outdid each other. Let us take, for instance, the character of "Bunka," the owner of four tenement houses; did not Mr. Mulac act the landlord in an ideal manner, just as Samberg had intended him to be? In the impersonation of the ruler over forty-seven tenants--of the bloated rich man--who is innocent of his success, there is hardly any professional actor who could excell or even equal the achievement.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1197.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This should not mean, however, that he alone deserves praise. Mr. Drmola, in the role of the public porter-messenger "Fersky," used the would be diplomatic language of the flunkey, prescribed in the play, in an inimitable manner. Mr. Jurka as "Kulisek," the orderly, honest member of the shoemakers' guild, Mr. Vanek as "Vroubek," his plaintive and enamoured help, Mr. Lang as the shoemaker's apprentice with the urchin's behavior and the constant smirk on his face, they all played their parts with a humorous natural ease. Other players also were in their own element.</p>
   <p>Among the actresses there was Miss H. Ruzicka as "Nanynka," the master shoemaker's daughter, who attracted general attention by her talent and charming appearance.</p>
   <p>During the intermission a band of six musicians led by Mr. Kostka entertained.</p>
   <p>The success of the affair naturally calls for more frequent theatrical performances by the ambitious Amateurs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
