<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-10-18">Oct. 18, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">Foundation of the Bohemian Saloon-Keepers Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0339</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0339.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-10-18">Oct. 18, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">FOUNDATION OF THE BOHEMIAN SALOON-KEEPERS ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday there was held in the "Vorwaerts" Hall a meeting of the Bohemian saloon-keepers under the chairmanship of Vil. Rust. Among the others was State Secretary, Time, and a secretary of the saloon-keepers district union. This meeting is especially significant to us Bohemians, because there was discussed the idea of founding the Independent Association of the Bohemian West Side Saloon-Keepers, the majority of whom were members of the West Side Union, but they had intended for a long time to found an independent Bohemian Union. In yesterday's meeting there was shown an ardent desire to fulfill this idea. It was discussed whether it would be possible for the independent Bohemian Union to join the state organization. The decision was that the Bohemian saloon-keepers must organize, elect a delegate to the district management and, at the same time, appoint a representative. - The present Bohemians went during the deliberation to the adjoining separate room for a private discussion and where they decided to organize the "Bohemian Saloon-Keepers Association" as quickly as possible. Thirteen of them signed the charter petition. Then it was resolved to join the state organization, to conduct all business transactions in the Bohemian language, and to agitate to gain members from all parts of the city. -</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0340.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The special constitutional meeting was appointed for a week from tomorrow in the hall of the Bohemian English school on 18th Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
