<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-11-26">Nov. 26, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Central Bohemian Singing Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1004</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-croatian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1004.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 a (Croatian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-11-26">Nov. 26, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">CENTRAL BOHEMIAN SINGING SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From all indications, the Česka Ústřední Pĕvecká Jednota (Central Bohemian Singing Society) is hastening to a long desired goal. Saturday's entertainment by the Lyra Singing Society, the second of a series of entertainments arranged by the singing societies, was a big step forward, because the participation of singing societies was quite large and the singers and their friends enjoyed an evening such as can only be spent among singers.</p>
   <p>There were ladies and gentlemen from Lyra, Bendl, members of the Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society, Lumir, Volnost, Fourth Ward, Marx, and finally, as guests, brothers of the Croatian Singing Society Zora, who came in such large numbers that they could really serve as an example to all singing societies. It was very lively Saturday in Mr. Doušek's cozy place, at Kedzie Avenue and 24th Street, and song resounded until the early morning hours.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1005.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Dr. Leopold Wedeles, to whom fell the honorable function of welcoming the guests, discharged his duties like a true songster. Welcoming the guests, he said, among other things, that it was the jealousy of the choirmasters, especially toward the central society, which in former days retarded the work of the singing societies, and that this hate and jealousy extended even to the members of the choruses who often were strangers to each other. He rejoiced because today everything is being done in a friendly way to reach a common goal, which will only be to the advantage of all groups and the whole society.</p>
   <p>After the greeting, the Singing Society Zora sang a beautiful Croatian song which was received with a storm of applause, altogether deserved. In the course of the evening, the Zora chorus sang several very fine songs and we can say without fear that the Central Bohemian Singing Society will have in Zora one of the best of organized choruses, whose singers cling with real affection to that beloved song.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1006.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The president of the Central Society, Mr. Anton Vanek, who explained the purpose of these gatherings before several singing societies, was called upon to say a few words. He laid stress upon the fact that singers must, in the first place, depend upon themselves and through mutual support [they must] insure moral and financial success for themselves. Choirmaster Jan Kalas, having been invited to say a few words, complained of how difficult the work is in our singing societies, where the majority of the members changes year after year thereby making possible only mediocre success. He called upon the older members to remain active in their societies and asked the singers to be helpful to the directors of the Central Bohemian Singing Society, since the success of the singers is important above all else.</p>
   <p>Several vocal selections were rendered by the singers during the course of the evening, and, needless to say, the jovial innkeeper Mister Doušek, with clam chowder, excellent ham, frankfurters, and beer ingratiated himself with the guests. The entertainment was a success in every respect, and the singers <pb facs="5418478_3_1007.jpg" n="4"/>and their friends hope to enjoy themselves at the third entertainment which will be given on Saturday, December 19, 1911, by the Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society in Mister Radovs' hall at 18th and Laflin Streets.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
