<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-04-06">Apr. 6, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Twenty Years of the LudvÍKovo Divadlo</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0807</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0807.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-04-06">Apr. 6, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">TWENTY YEARS OF THE LUDVÍKOVO DIVADLO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To speak in these days about the cultural importance of the theater is unnecessary. Every wide-awake man and woman knows that the theater is a school of life, and it is needless to reason about this truth, because it is recognized by all civilized people. The development of theatrical art is a criterion of a people's progress and cultural life. Since it is of great importance to a whole nation, its significance for a mere branch transplanted into a foreign soil cannot be overestimated. It is a fountain from which new life continuously flows into the whole body. With this in mind we must come to the conclusion that the establishment of the Bohemian Ludvíkovo Divadlo (Ludvík's Theater) in Chicago was one of the most important events of our national life. All things strive for perfection; progress is evident at every turn. Things that aroused our enthusiasm some years ago have retreated into the background and have now been replaced by new achievements, new acquisitions. The years of dilettantism have passed, and the present times call for better treats. In the natural general evolution, the theater must not be an exception, nor is <pb facs="5418478_3_0808.jpg" n="2"/>it one. It is happily forging ahead, and it is to the credit of the Bohemian community of Chicago that a prosperous and permanent Bohemian theater in this city is assured.</p>
   <p>It is to the amateurs, who celebrated the fiftieth anniversary of their first performance a short while ago, that the recognition is due for having spent years in preparing the ground for and spreading interest in the theater. Every one of them may justly be proud and pleased that he has made his contribution to the establishment of a permanent stage in our midst. Today Ludvikovo Divadlo stands on the threshold of its second score of years of work. It will commemorate its arrival in Chicago [from Bohemia] by a gala presentation of J. K. Tyl's "Strakonický Dudák" (The Bagpiper of Strakonice) in the Garrick Theater on Randolph Street, April 20. The staging of the play will be carried out along the lines adopted for the performance by the National Theater in Prague. The dances by Misses Petrtyl, Hak, Hurt, Bidles, and Číha will be under the direction of Miss Mayme Fiala. Professor H. Čapek, who composed a festive overture for this performance, <pb facs="5418478_3_0809.jpg" n="3"/>will direct the soloists and chorus.</p>
   <p>Our picture shows the members of the original group at the time of their arrivals in Chicago with their leader and director, Mr. František Ludvík. The majority of the original group, including the irreplaceable Director Ludvík, have left us. Through the years new members, who of course are not in the picture, have been added to the personnel. We shall bring out a supplement in our next number.</p>
   <p>[Translator's Note: The picture referred to in the text is five columns wide and ten inches long.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
