<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-01-19">Jan. 19, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Podskalak</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1162</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1162.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-01-19">Jan. 19, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">PODSKALAK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In Chicago Sokol Hall Mr. Ludva Rausar was [recently] honored with a benefit dramatic performance provided by his many friends and well-wishers. Mr. Rausar is one of the most popular of our amateur actors in our so-called "California" section; he is also a prosperous businessman and a sincere Sokol and as an amateur actor has many friends and admirers who yesterday, by their large attendance, showed their acknowledgment and sympathy.</p>
   <p>Mr. Rausar chose the well-known Samberk play, "Podskalak" (Log Raftsman), a comedy in three acts, with prologue, which depicts life in Prague, Bohemia. The choice of this play showed excellent judgment. It is a lively and popular play, purely Samberkian, which will live a long time on the Bohemian stage, as will all the works of this dramatic writer.</p>
   <p>Mr. Rausar appeared in the charming role of the mason "Saturnia Brambora," <pb facs="5418478_3_1163.jpg" n="2"/>and he played the part successfully, which proves that he had studied diligently. The popular amateur actress Mrs. L. Friedl proved her ability as the energetic wife of "Brambora, and this clever couple kept the audience in almost continuous laughter and applause. The play was very well produced, just as it should be at a benefit performance and left a very favorable impression with the audience.</p>
   <p>Besides the above-named persons the cast included Mr. Mikulas as "Vaclav," Mr. Sulac, Mr. Weidner as the country gentleman, "Sommerfeld," Mr. Otcasky as the banker, "Iserstein," and Mrs. Svoboda in the part of "Bozena Brambora". Mr. Mikulas was perfect both in acting and in delivery; he is known as a good dependable actor. An excellent figure was Mr. Sulac as the barber, "Jaroslav Angrest"; he played the part in his own inimitable way and with great success.</p>
   <p>There are many small parts in "Podskalak," and even these characters were generally well portrayed. Mr. Rausar may well be satisfied with yesterday's <pb facs="5418478_3_1164.jpg" n="3"/>benefit performance and with the greetings and the sympathy accorded to him. Many floral pieces were presented to him at the close of the play, and no doubt this attention will spur him on to continued interest in our amateur theatricals, which in the past he has so well supported. It may be noted that all the proceeds of yesterday's performance are donated to the Ladies' Auxiliary of the Chicago Sokol.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
