<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-19">Oct. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Capek's "R.U.R." at the Ludvikovo Divadlo</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0661</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0661.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-19">Oct. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CAPEK'S "R.U.R." AT THE LUDVIKOVO DIVADLO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"R.U.R." is a play which has caused a terrific sensation. Josef Capek, the newest star on the horizon of Czech dramatic literature, a man of remarkable imagination, placed this, his masterpiece, before the public. It inundated all the stages of Czechoslovakia like a veritable avalanche. Translated into all of the European languages it victoriously crossed the boundaries of our homeland, gaining in reputation everywhere. It finally crossed the Atlantic and was received with an unwonted enthusiasm on the New York stage. "R.U.R." is a play with a world reputation. How proud every Czech must be in the knowledge that the author of "R.U.R." is a son of our homeland, who drew the attention of the entire world to himself, who proved that our new republic, which grew out of the ruins of the World War...., is capable of producing such a genius....who by the work of his pen is able to reach the hearts of the whole world.</p>
   <p>"R.U.R." is a difficult play, difficult because of its technical requirements, <pb facs="5418478_3_0662.jpg" n="2"/>and equally so because of the demands it places upon the actors. But the competent personel of the Ludvikovo Divadlo (Frank Ludvik Bohemian Dramatic Association) will surely be equal to the task. The public will breathlessly follow the plot of the play: The manufacture of robots--human machines without a soul--how these robots behave, how they improve their behavior, how finally they destroy the last members of human society, the directors of the gigantic factory for the manufacture of robots; how they endeavor to save the last human being who, they believe, has the secret formula for the manufacture of robots--this is the theme of the play. The public will finally see the modern Adam and Eve who, after the last remaining member of the old human race passed away, and after every robot, too, has died, are to give life to a new humanity.</p>
   <p>The management of the cast and the stage is under the charge of Mr. Frantisek Horlivy who, during his visit to Bohemia, saw the play acted on all the great stages of Prague. He will supervise production so that the scenery, the dramatic <pb facs="5418478_3_0663.jpg" n="3"/>team work of all the actors, etc., will be blended into a harmonious whole. This production by the Ludvikovo Divadlo will therefore be a festive event for all our Chicago theatre-going Bohemians, and it is advisable that tickets be secured in advance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
