<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-23">Nov. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">News of the Stage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0647</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0647.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-23">Nov. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS OF THE STAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The name of F. F. Šamberk the actor-genius of Prague, will always be spoken with great respect. Samberk's abilities as a playwright were no less brilliant than his acting. He bequeathed to the nation a great many valuable works which were staged by the Bohemian theaters of Chicago times without number, and which will continue to be played here as long as we have our theaters.</p>
   <p>The Ludvíkovo Divadlo (František Ludvík Dramatic Association) has this time made use of one of Šamberk's best works, the "Potrhlý Švec" (Demented Cobbler), which in itself is a splendid portrait of contemporary life. The plot is ingeniously worked out, and the play, full of spicy humor a la Šamberk,becomes serious as it proceeds to picture the father of a family crushed by the weight of life's difficulties. And no wonder, the happiness of his only child is at stake. But the serious scenes are not long; soon the plot brings the audience back to situations full of humor.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0648.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>To assign the roles properly was in itself a task; the roles required competent histrionic abilities, so that the play would turn out as it was originally intended by its author. The entire company of the Ludvikovo Divadlo was employed in the production of Šamberk's masterpiece. The title role of the shoemaker, Drchota, was played by Mr. F. Horlivý whose unquestioned ....talent and ability guaranteed its success. The role of the crack-brained wife of the cobbler was played by Mrs. Kozlanský who was loyal to her art. [Translator's note: Fourteen lines of the column space in this article are given to the description of individual roles and the names of the actors who played them.] The music was under the direction of Mr. Jurena, and the stage management under that of Mrs. Ludvík.</p>
   <p>.....The play was given at the Sokol Chicago Hall; it has always filled the house and will surely draw the audience again when it is given next Sunday. Because of the many inquiries at the box office since last week, the public is advised to secure all seats well in advance at the usual places where tickets are sold, or by telephoning Canal 7102.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
