<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-20">Sept. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Amateur Theatricals</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1150</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1150.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-09-20">Sept. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">AMATEUR THEATRICALS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Dorostovy Klub Vesna (Junior Spring Club) Number Four of the Cesko-Slovanske Podporujici Spolky (Bohemian-Slavonic Benevolent Societies) has already several times presented very successful theatrical performances. The last one especially, played Sunday, August 29, was so well liked that the Club has decided to repeat it. It was the "Rychtaruv Poklad" (Judge's Treasure), a very pleasing three-act play taken from life in the time of serfdom.....</p>
   <p>The members of Vesna, all graduates of the Jan Neruda Bohemian School on Crawford Avenue....did very well indeed;....they are justly proud of their success.....</p>
   <p>II</p>
   <p>The Chicago Sokol hall was enlivened by a carefree, gay French spirit yesterday. It was the host of a well-known French team of playwrights, Hennequin and Weber, <pb facs="5418478_3_1151.jpg" n="2"/>in the form of one of their best three-act plays.....</p>
   <p>The team of Hennequin and Weber is not only wildly gay; it is frequently quite indiscreet. Like Guy de Maupassant in his Darling, in which he cannot help making light of the Cross of the Legion of Honor, Hennequin and Weber show no respect for the dignity of a French minister of justice. They let the head of that refined department of government capitulate before the negligee and the little satin slippers of an attractive free lady who changes the palace of the ministry of justice into the playground of a crowd of very low-necked and rather thoroughly underdressed young women.....</p>
   <p>It is of no use to discuss the dramatic value--or the lack of it--of such plays. But they are good for the box office, and it was no doubt for this reason that the management of the Chicago Sokol made it their choice, although it cannot be said that it was a success this time. The name of the play was "Pani Presidentova" (The President's Wife).....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1152.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The performance was at the usual level of such amateur nights.....The attendance should have been much greater.....</p>
   <p>It is one of the delightful moments which carry you away from the medium in which you spend your daily life when you see, no matter if it is only on the stage, a bit of pure Bohemian life. It has a charm which only one of us Bohemians can fully appreciate, one of us who doesn't see in it only a bit of folklore but the whole diapason of temperaments so familiar in our own dramatic literature.....</p>
   <p>Such charm flows from Jirasek's [historical and patriotic writer of the end of the nineteenth and the first three decades of the twentieth century] "Vojnarka" (Widow Vojnar) and the romance of her life.....</p>
   <p>That a play of this kind is able to hold Bohemian audiences both in the old <pb facs="5418478_3_1153.jpg" n="4"/>country and in Chicago was proved yesterday by its successful presentation by the versatile dramatic group of Sokol Karel Jonas in Morton Park.....</p>
   <p>The play was very well presented.....</p>
   <p>All the roles were in good hands.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
