<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-21">Mar. 21, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Young People's Performance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0853</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0853.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-03-21">Mar. 21, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">YOUNG PEOPLE'S PERFORMANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An interesting performance by Czech young people was presented yesterday afternoon on the stage of the Sokol Chicago Hall. The spacious hall was filled to capacity. Participating in this performance were the former and present pupils of Mr. and Mrs, Jan Kovar who for a number of years have taught at the Vojta Naprstek Free Thought School.</p>
   <p>The program consisted of musical and vocal numbers and recitations, together with a number of short scenes which were truly impressive. A number of children of various ages appeared in individual numbers on the program. By their performance, the children have shown what can be accomplished by the good will and diligence of conscientious and patient teachers. All the children performed very well and pleased not only their teachers and parents, but all those who came to see the performance. The program was so extensive that it was impossible for us to give the names of all the performers. Special recognition was <pb facs="5418478_3_0854.jpg" n="2"/>deserved by everyone. But unquestionably the greatest of praise must be given to Alfred Kovar who, in spite of the fact that he is only seventeen years old, attracted the attention of all those who were present by his unusual talent. He skillfully conducted the children's orchestra which received very rigid training under his direction. He also performed as a bass viol soloist. In his presentation of Schwabe's "Romance" and Simandl's "Fantasie na Ceske Narodni Pisne" (Fantasy on Bohemian Folk Songs) he drew attention to himself as a greatly talented musician who in the near future will surely ripen into a great artist. His present teacher, the well-known bass viol virtuoso, Mr. Vaclav Jiskra, and a member of the Chicago Symphony Orchestra, may be justly proud of young Kovar......</p>
   <p>Mr. and Mrs. Kovar may congratulate themselves upon the success attained yesterday afternoon.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
