<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-04-30">Apr. 30, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Sokol Exhibit.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1582</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1582.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-04-30">Apr. 30, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">SOKOL EXHIBIT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.--A very lively and invigorating atmosphere prevailed in the hall of Mr. Krsky, at 26th street and Homan avenue, during the entire afternoon and evening of last Sunday. This animation lasted far into the night. The Sokol Havlicek held their exhibition in this hall during the afternoon. The exhibition proper was followed by various forms of entertainment. This was responsible for the hilarity.</p>
   <p>The exhibition will be continued throughout the coming week, and from the large and enthusiastic patronage present on the first day it is apparent that the exhibition will be a huge success. The large patronage has proved that Sokol Havlicek has many well wishers and that they contribute not only by words but also by deeds.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1583.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The exhibition is very well arranged and conducted, affording an excellent opportunity to all visitors to amuse themselves. The program is diverse, very absorbing, and presented in the best possible form. The exhibition consists of many subjects all of which are valuable and practical. In fact the arrangment committee planned everything carefully, taking into consideration the amusement of their guests and at the same time the necessity of maintaining perfect order and harmony.</p>
   <p>Monday, the second day, was set aside to be "Business Mens' Day," for which special features were prepared that attracted a crowd which filled the hall to capacity.</p>
   <p>Equally enjoyable evenings are assured during the remaining days of this exhibition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
