<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-17">May 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Chicago Bohemian Artist Makes a Success in the Old Country</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0459</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0459.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-17">May 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A CHICAGO BOHEMIAN ARTIST MAKES A SUCCESS IN THE OLD COUNTRY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last year, in September, the young but very talented violinist, Mr. Milan Lusk, said good-by to Bohemian Chicago and went to Bohemia to study with the famous Professor Ševčík.</p>
   <p>Milan Lusk is the son of Attorney Charles D. Lusk and the painter Mrs. Koupal-Lusk. He received the foundation of his musical education in Chicago, under the direction of Jospeh H. Čapek, professor of music and violin virtuoso. Even here he was considered one of the most talented young men. No doubt he will return to us an accomplished artist and, by his interpretations, will spread in America the fame of his great teachers.</p>
   <p>At present Mr. Lusk is studying diligently under Professor Ševčík's direction in Pisek, where he is progressing by such strides that his great teacher is prevailing upon him to join the Vienna Kaiserliche Meisterschule (Imperial <pb facs="5418478_3_0460.jpg" n="2"/>Master School), which has among its members the greatest artists in the world.</p>
   <p>Mr. Lusk has been using his spare time for concerts arranged in the different cities of Bohemia, and his virtuosity is receiving due recognition.</p>
   <p>The newspaper Chodský Prapor (Chod Flag), printed in the old renowned City of Domažlice, has published a very interesting article about Mr. Lusk's appearance at a series of concerts arranged by students of the academic society Tuhošté. The article speaks very flatteringly of our young virtuoso and is of such interest that we reprint it here in its entirety:</p>
   <p>"This year, the society Tuhošté has undertaken the task not only of presenting examples of creditable musical accomplishments by our own students, but also of offering our audiences a higher artistic enjoyment. By inviting Mr. Milan Lusk this aim has been achieved.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0461.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"The audience that filled the hall of the Hotel Černý Kun (Black Horse) met with a great surprise. They certainly had not come in such large numbers to hear just our local talent, but were, no doubt, attracted by the reputation of Mr. Milan Lusk, a young artist whom they desired to hear. They were not disappointed in their expectations.</p>
   <p>"The young virtuoso immediately won the whole audience, which listened in rapt attention to his playing of the Bruch 'Concerto'. The interest of the audience grew as he played on with his incomparable tone and as with apparent ease, which spells virtuosity, he overcame all the difficulties of the compositon. Bruck's 'Concerto' cannot claim much in musical values but it is filled with technical difficulties and assures recognition for the player who masters them.</p>
   <p>"Our artist received a full measure of that recognition when he showed his versatility and mature technique. With unwavering sureness and a rare clarity of tone he brought out nuances of great difficulty, and won the admiration of all those who were lucky enough to hear him.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0462.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"His presentation of Walter's song from Wagner's 'Die Meistersinger,' and Dvořák's Humoresque' was similar to that of other players. He played the 'Humoresque' in a slower tempo, with a tone which was somewhat plaintive, but fully expressed the happiness of the composition, and which, we believed, was well suited to the 'Humoresque'.</p>
   <p>"When the violinist played the dance 'Skočná (The Bounder) from the opera 'Prodaná Nevĕsta' (The Bartered Bride) in Ondříček's difficult arrangement, he made use of all his artistry. The audience was moved to an extraordinary enthusiasm, and the artist was presented with a palm.</p>
   <p>"The audience gave evidence of the young man's great success when he added-- upon request--two of his own selections.</p>
   <p>"Mr. Lusk is a pupil of Professor Šefčík, and his was the most outstanding concert ever to take place in this city."</p>
   <p>The above report shows that Mr. Lusk is receiving full recognition for his <pb facs="5418478_3_0463.jpg" n="5"/>fine artistry, which no doubt makes happy not only his parents but also Professor Joseph H. Čapek, who, in so many years of active service among us, has given a good foundation to many a promising student.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
