<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-11">May 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A Rare Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0798</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0798.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-05-11">May 11, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">A RARE ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Karel Splavec, one of the foremost Bohemian-American actors, celebrated the thirty-fifth anniversary of his activity on the stage yesterday evening--so many years of service to Thalia!</p>
   <p>We say "Bohemian-American actor," although Mr. Splavec spent about one third of this period as an actor in Bohemia. Nevertheless, he grew up artistically in America with the Ludvikovo Divadlo (Ludvik's Theatrical Company) where he has risen to great artistic heights.</p>
   <p>Mr. Splavec is well known to every lover of the Bohemian theater in Chicago. He is an actor of highest caliber, an artist who, in the years of his activity, created many a fine character on our stage, and whose artistry can be judged only by those who often visit the Ludvik Theater.</p>
   <p>In that way only can we evaluate the development of his artistry and his versatility in the presentation of the many contrasting characters which he <pb facs="5418478_3_0799.jpg" n="2"/>depicts so realistically: at one time a tragic type, and then just the opposite, a figure full to overflowing with so-called inborn comedy.</p>
   <p>In each of these roles Mr. Splavec excels by his distinctive and carefully worked out characterization. The result is that a person who has seen him in one role fails to recognize him in another. And it is not exclusively the leading roles in which he excels: The presentation of certain inconsequential episodes also enables him to reveal his real artistry.</p>
   <p>We could name a whole series of remarkable characterization	s by which Mr. Splavec has endeared himself to the hearts of all true friends of the Bohemian theater, and has proved that he realizes with due seriousness the requirements of his difficult profession, and clings to it by choice.</p>
   <p>His playing is never based on a superficial study of a role, but always on a deep, thorough study of the character to be portrayed. In his accomplished working-together of speech and action every figure portrayed by him really comes to life.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0800.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Yesterday Mr. Splavec again gave proof of his artistry by his portrayal of the farmer "Juan" in the classical comedy "Kral A Sedlak," (The King and the Farmer), by Lope De Vega, as translated by Jaroslav Vrchlicky.</p>
   <p>Our audience had had the opportunity to see this comedy only once before, and that was many years ago, when a member of the Narodni Divadlo (National Theater) in Prague, Mr. Josef Smaha, was the guest of Bohemian Chicago. From that time until the present, the play had not been produced until yesterday, when Mr. Splavec chose the comedy for his anniversary celebration.</p>
   <p>As is the case with all the plays written along these lines, it is very difficult to produce and hardly ever is selected, except when a showy part is needed to display the exceptional ability of an actor. To play the part, a real artist must be secured if the comedy can really be called a success--and this is especially true among us.</p>
   <p>Mr. Splavec's characterization of "Juan" was not soon to be forgotten, for it <pb facs="5418478_3_0801.jpg" n="4"/>was thought out in every detail. The actor seems to grow on you from one act to the next, and in the last two acts he attained great dramatic heights.</p>
   <p>The supporting cast gave of their best efforts to help in a well-rounded play.</p>
   <p>The attendance was enormous. Every seat in the house was sold, and the audience filed out well pleased.</p>
   <p>For the success of yesterday's performance, credit is due also to the excellent performance of Professor Čapek's orchestra.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
