<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-03-09">Mar. 9, 1903</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">Umirov's Concerts Were Pleasing to Large Audiences.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0549</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0549.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-03-09">Mar. 9, 1903</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">UMIROV'S CONCERTS WERE PLEASING TO LARGE AUDIENCES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Both concerts of the celebrated Bohemian singer, Boza Umirov, and the hopeful young artist Milada Cerny, were enjoyed by a large and enthusiastic audience.</p>
   <p>The Fine Arts Hall on Michigan Ave., was filled to capacity at both afternoon and evening concerts. Although the majority were countrymen, lovers of song and music, there were quite a number of foreigners who came to hear the rapturous production of Bohemian song, such as the afternoon and evening programs afforded.</p>
   <p>Boza Umirov, pleasing in appearance, charmed everyone who had the opportunity to hear him. His beautiful ringing voice, clear and understandable in both the upper and lower registers, enraptured all his listeners, who made it known to him through the oft repeated and long applause which broke out in the hall after each number. In the afternoon he was presented with a precious gift, and in the evening with a large bouquet of fresh flowers, bound in the national colors, by the Club.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0550.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He was accompanied by Paul Vyskocil. The young artist of the future, Milada Cerny, surprised and enraptured the audience with her piano playing, Just as Umirov did with his singing. Her playing is exceptionally matured. Although she is only nine years old, she plays many difficult compositions that only the greatest artists attempt. It is especially to be noted that she played these compositions from memory, with ease and technic; successfully putting into them as much feeling as the greatest artists.</p>
   <p>At both the afternoon and evening performances she was presented with bouquets of flowers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
