<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-11">Mar. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Spectacular Closing of the National Bazaar</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1480</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1480.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-03-11">Mar. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SPECTACULAR CLOSING OF THE NATIONAL BAZAAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The biggest national festival ever held by our people was the CzechoSlovak bazaar, which closed last night with a briliant carnival at which thousands mingled with thousands. The spacious hall of the pavilion of the Pilsen Brewing Company, was the scene of entertainment. Previous to the closing day patriotic visitors had thronged in and around the booths and stands. These had been cleared away for a dance floor, while the salable exhibits were offered in the galleries.</p>
   <p>The election of the queen of the bazaar was the main topic of the day, for there were many ups and downs during the voting, which had been going on every day publicly. One half an hour was reserved for the casting of the secret ballot which spread an intense suspense among all <pb facs="5418478_3_1481.jpg" n="2"/>present. The price for the voting tickets had to be paid in cash. The result was as follows; Mrs. Antonia Cervenka 171,265 votes, she was proclaimed queen; Miss Bozena Triner 95,560 votes, received the second prize; Miss Libuse (Libby) Zdenek 41,080, and Miss Helen Lonkova 39,270 votes received the third and fourth prize, respectively. Twelve other candidates received votes, ranging from 31,475 to 5,860. The contest yielded $5,349.40.</p>
   <p>The triumphal march of the queen, and her subsequent crowning, offered a highly impressive spectacle. The cabaret and dancing provided splendid entertainment.</p>
   <p>Finally the bazaar was closed. The crowd slowly began to leave in a roseate mood, many still discussing the beauties of the diadem with which <pb facs="5418478_3_1482.jpg" n="3"/>the queen was crowned, and the regal cloak with which she was bedecked.</p>
   <p>An entertainment will be given next Saturday at which all the persons who have donated their services for the building up and maintenance of the bazaar will be guests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
