<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-11">Feb. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czech-Americans in Fine Arts</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0619</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0619.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-02-11">Feb. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH-AMERICANS IN FINE ARTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An opinion was prevalent several years ago that a person from the poorer classes had no opportunity to develop his artistic gifts in a school of arts because he was lacking in funds with which to pay for tuition. These notions have proved fallacious in recent times. Art has penetrated many strata of our people, and established itself as a spiritual necessity. This is a result of a vigorous popularization of subjects and objects connected with it in lecture halls, concert halls, and expositions.</p>
   <p>In order to make the public become acquainted with the conception of beauty, many institutes have been established in which anybody having an appreciation for things beautiful will find himself in the proper atmosphere. One of the great institutes devoted to art has been founded in the city of Prague, Bohemia, in the year of 1796.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0620.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was only natural that art should find a fertile field in America, a land rapidly developing all of its resources.</p>
   <p>Wealthy people used to buy objects of art in foreign lands, but their craving for more has raised the demand, and thus gave a mighty impulse to creative art right here. There are many academies for the cultivation of art in America. The State of Illinois possesses one, the Art Institute, founded by the Society of Friends of Art in 1879. Many of our readers have certainly been impressed with the exterior of the building on Michigan Boulevard and Adams Street, and with its rich artistic contents in a larger degree. But very few are familiar with the details of it's maintenance, with the teachers, and with the dignified representation the Czech people can boast of in the seat of Fine Arts of our state.</p>
   <p>Two of the main departments of the Chicago Art Institute are entirely <pb facs="5418478_3_0621.jpg" n="3"/>under the direction of Czech teachers: Sculpture under Prof. Albin Polasek, and Drawing under Prof. Anton Sterba. Professor Polasek is a former student of the Academy of Arts of Pennsylvania, and of the American Academy in Rome, Italy. Prizes in great numbers, and many high distinctions have come to him. Professor Sterba is a former student of the Art Institute; he also studied in Paris, France for some time. There is a goodly percentage of students of Czech descent in all of the departments; some of them have reached a considerable standing in the field of their endeavor.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
