<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-09-24">Sept. 24, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">Hamlet on the Bohemian Stage.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1216</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1216.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-09-24">Sept. 24, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">HAMLET ON THE BOHEMIAN STAGE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday the society, Jednota presented "Hamlet". The main character was played by one of the best amateurs, Josef Kerner, who bade us farewell. This explains the extremely large attendance. - The Bohemians have proved that they understand how to honor an amateur, who always has offered his services with extreme zeal and unselfishness, and always responded, when he was summoned for a public appearance.</p>
   <p>Not long ago we expressed a decision on the serious responsibility of featuring Shakespeare on the amateur stage, and we have decided not to write any criticism of similar enterprises. But to our surprise the play of last night was exceptionally excellent. It was a quiet glorification of our most diligent worker of the stage and, at the same time , the farewell to him.</p>
   <p>That Mr. Kerner had studied, especially, the part of "Hamlet" was easily seen from his interpretation and only yesterday, we understood what a big portrayer of dramatic character will be lost to our Bohemian amateur theater.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1217.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is too bad, so much the worse, as we never will have an amateur who would sacrifice so much. Mr. Kerner's interpretation of any character was absolutely conscientious. - He was, so to say, a white raven, a blessed exception. - We are very sorry to be losing such an authority. The audience expressed its satisfaction by loud applause, and Mr. Kerner was much applauded after each appearance on the stage, but that was all.</p>
   <p>Anyhow, the world is ungrateful. For so many sacrifices, for such faithful work for our people, not a little wreath, not a green leaf, was presented to our beloved amateur as a proof of the gratitude and appreciation of our community.</p>
   <p>The Bohemians are not sensitive, they have good will, but must be animated by someone.</p>
   <p>In another city, where there is, maybe, one half of the numbers of Chicago's Bohemians, such an occasion would not pass so coldheartedly.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1218.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Our amateur earned, certainly, an open public gratitude, and yesterday was the right day to show to him our appreciation and gratitude. In spite of unfavorable weather the hall was filled to capacity. There was no room to stand. "Hamlet" was a surprise to us. We never expected such a good performance.</p>
   <p>While we don't intend to spoil the good impression we will not mention the mistakes, which in many instances were, alas, not small, that's why we are finishing this article with our heartiest wishes to Mr. Kerner for best success and prosperity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
