<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-06-22">June 22, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Official Unification Achieved</title><title level="a" type="sub">Pevecka Spolecnost Lyra Unites with Cesky Delnicky Pevecky Sbor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0859</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0859.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-06-22">June 22, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">OFFICIAL UNIFICATION ACHIEVED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Pevecka Spolecnost Lyra Unites with Cesky Delnicky Pevecky Sbor</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some time ago we reported in our newspaper that the Pevecka Spolecnost Lyra (Singing Society Lyra), which has proved its great value to our musical, cultural, and artistic life by the meritorious work of several of its outstanding members, primarily Dr. Leopold Wedeles and the late Dr. Jan D. Novak, has decided to unite with the equally deserving singing society, the Cesky Delnicky Pevecky Sbor (Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society). The unification, which we reported some time ago, was a known fact at that time, but it had not been officially approved. The unification was officially approved at the semiannual meeting of the Cesky Delnicky Pevecky Sbor held last Friday evening at the clubhouse of the above-mentioned society on Ashland Avenue near 18th Street. At the meeting it was resolved that these two singing societies be merged into one body under the name of Cesko-Delnicky Pevecky Sbor Lyra (Bohemian Workingmen's Singing <pb facs="5418478_3_0860.jpg" n="2"/>Society Lyra).</p>
   <p>Since that time both of these societies have ceased to exist as separate units, but under their own original names they will live long in our memories. In this regard the memories are not only interesting, but also beautiful and worthy. We hope sincerely that both societies, now merged into one body under a new name, will work together with redoubled efforts and enthusiasm toward the same goal, and that greater success may be attained than that which we witnessed during the many years of their separate existence. And for this, many opportunities can be found. Each of these societies excelled in splendid vocal material which, now combined, will make it possible to work under more favorable conditions.</p>
   <p>The ladies' auxiliary of the Pevecka Spolecnost Lyra, consisting of thirteen members, united with the Maj (May) ladies' auxiliary of the Cesky Delnicky <pb facs="5418478_3_0861.jpg" n="3"/>Pevecky Sbor. Even this unification will be of importance and must not be underestimated. Mr. Joseph Houdek, who will be the conductor of this united group, is a proved and enthusiastic leader, and his name should guarantee the success of each and every public appearance of the Cesko-Delnicky Pevecky Sbor Lyra and the Maj. In conclusion, we must mention that the following have been elected officers of the new group: Mr. Antonin Bobisud, president; Mr. Stanislav Bilek, secretary; and Mr. J. Wolf, treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
