<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-11">May 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Last Appeal to Our Singers</title><title level="a" type="sub">Only Two More Rehearsals for the Demonstration for the Return of Masaryk</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0411</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0411.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-11">May 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">LAST APPEAL TO OUR SINGERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Only Two More Rehearsals for The Demonstration for the Return of Masaryk</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>He who witnessed the parade for the reception of Professor T. G. Masaryk last Sunday not merely as a spectator but as one of the tens of thousands who participated actively in the magnificent celebration can form an opinion of what a gigantic event will be the first appearance before the American public of the father and leader of the Czechoslovak revolution.</p>
   <p>This public reception will take place in one of the largest halls of Chicago in the last week of this month. It must be of such magnitude and such character that it will not only inspire our own Czechoslovak people with the determination to make the utmost efforts to help secure liberty for our old motherland but will also create a lofty and indelible impression upon the many thousands of other nationalities who will be present, thus shedding a brilliant lustre upon our Czechoslovak nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0412.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Our singers have always emerged victorious from contests with those of other nationalities and have represented the maturity and artistic soul of our nation with brilliant success. To them will be allotted a very important task in this coming celebration. It is imperative that they appear in the largest possible numbers, several hundred in force. They should also be thoroughly prepared to give performances that will compel the admiration of the multinational audience.</p>
   <p>There is no question but that our singers are able to accomplish this. They are fit, but are they willing and ready?</p>
   <p>The Ustredni Pevecka Jednota (Central Unit of Singers) sent out several invitations for the purpose of gathering all our singers for the great event. The response was most gratifying. So many made their appearance in the hall in Shedd Park that they could not be accommodated, and the large hall in the quarters of the Sokol Chicago had to be rented for future rehearsals.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0413.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Next Monday the singers will assemble again, to be coached for the performance. This will be the last opportunity for singers to join who have not heretofore attended rehearsals but are capable of mastering the choruses that will be sung. No singer should fail to report, so that we may count on several hundred. The large numbers that we can muster will impress the public in the Auditorium Theater or the Coliseum and will show the strength and the maturity of our nation. Those who fail to heed this call need not attempt to join later. This regulation is necessary to insure the best possible results at the concert.</p>
   <p>Probably the last rehearsal will be held on May 22. Remember well the two days, May 13 and May 22! Let us celebrate the presence among us of our dear "Daddy," the leader of the Czechoslovak revolution, in the most dignified manner! Let us display before America our fairest possession--Czech song!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
