<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-10-02">Oct. 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A Meeting of Building and Loan Associations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0218</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0218.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-10-02">Oct. 2, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">A MEETING OF BUILDING AND LOAN ASSOCIATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting of representatives of building and loan associations, called for the purpose of discussing important questions concerning all such associations, was held in the La Salle Hotel yesterday.</p>
   <p>It is well known that the principal problem of interest to building and loan associations now is the so-called Mobile bill, the passage of which would imperil their very existence. This bill has already been passed in sixteen states, and it is generally believed that it is being backed by rich insurance companies which are trying to damage the building and loan associations' business.</p>
   <p>According to statements made in the meeting, the delegates of the sixty-five participating associations represented the enormous capital of nine billion dollars. Bodies of such immense power will certainly not permit the interests of thousands of their members and the members' families to be impaired.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0219.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Resolutions in this respect were adopted in the meeting and a protest was issued against the Mobile bill and any other legislative measures aimed against building and loan associations.</p>
   <p>Representatives of our Bohemian Podporující Spolky (building and loan associations) participated in the meeting and agreed to form one solid front in the fight against the bill, and against any and all attempts to harm our organizations or promote the interests and profits of rich insurance companies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
