<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-03-11">Mar. 11, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">For Our Institutions.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Tenth Year Jubilee Celebrated by Bohemian Branches of W. W. Kimball Co., a Piano Firm in Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0303</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0303.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-03-11">Mar. 11, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">FOR OUR INSTITUTIONS.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Tenth Year Jubilee Celebrated by Bohemian Branches of W. W. Kimball Co., a Piano Firm in Chicago.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1, col. 4.. The well known piano firm of W. W. Kimball Co. has decided to celebrate the ten year duration of their Bohemian branches which they have established among the Bohemian people. These branches have a very promising future in the Bohemian districts of Chicago. The firm also wishes to show its appreciation to the Bohemian people of Chicago for their wonderful patronage during the past ten years.</p>
   <p>To celebrate their jubilee and at the same time show this appreciation, the firm has chosen a course which is quite novel and very dignified. They have decided to let the Bohemian people decide for themselves by which method their firm could do this best. Therefore all Bohemian benevolent societies in Chicago were notified of this noble intention offered by this firm and were requested to send a representative to a meeting, at which plans for this occasion would be made.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0304.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The meeting was held at a designated date. Representatives of more than a hundred Bohemian benevolent societies were present including also many individuals interested in benevolent work.</p>
   <p>Representatives of W. W. Kimball Co. were also present and expressed their desire stating that their firm wished to stage something on a grand scale, which would aid the Bohemian benevolent institutions of Chicago. They requested advice and any suggestions which would be most appropriate for such an occasion.</p>
   <p>After many suggestions the representatives decided to hold a grand concert in one of the larger halls of Chicago, the proceeds of which would be donated to the Bohemian Old Peoples Home and Orphanage. It was understood that W. W. Kimball Co. would pay all expenses involved in presenting this concert, as their contribution to the Bohemian people.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian benevolent societies were given the task of arranging the concert; this they easily managed by asking the cooperation of the many Bohemian singing (vocal) and musical clubs which were always willing to do their share in benevolent undertakings.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0305.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Committees of prominent Bohemians were picked who were given the authority to rent a suitable hall and proceed with the arrangements of the program. One committee went to work immediately and rented the Auditorium Theater, while the other worked feverishly on program arrangements.</p>
   <p>There is no doubt that the day of the grand concert will be a holiday among Bohemians of Chicago, reason for that being that it deals with out benevolent aims. We must show and prove to the world that the progress and success of these benevolent societies is cherished in the hearts of all Bohemian people in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The point which must be stressed is that all expenses will be paid be the W. W. Kimball Co., therefore leaving the entire proceeds of the concert to the Bohemian institutions. W. W. Kimball Co. employs many Bohemian people whom they know to be good workers, therefore the noble act of this firm is largely due to them. This concert also reflects upon the benevolent activities of the Bohemian people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
