<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-15">July 15, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">United States Mail Order House</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Largest Bohemian Mail Order Business in America is Liquidating</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0237</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0237.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-15">July 15, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">UNITED STATES MAIL ORDER HOUSE</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Largest Bohemian Mail Order Business in America is Liquidating</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Write an Obituary." That was the brief reply of one member of the Board of Directors, when a reporter of this paper visited him yesterday and asked him what was the condition of the United States Mail Order House on Marshall Boulevard and Twenty-first Street, which has been on the down grade for quite some time.</p>
   <p>This means that this business which began with so much promise six years ago, is practically buried. The Company is liquidating so as to disband, and there is no hope that the twenty-three shareholders will get back any part of their one hundred fifteen thousand dollars which they put into the business.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0238.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We have been informed that the Company has ceased doing business. At present, only old orders are being executed, all new orders are being returned. As soon as all accounts have been collected and bills which probably will be covered by these collections paid, the Company will close its books and disband. There is not much hope that anything will be left for the stockholders unless the building which the Company owns is sold advantageously.</p>
   <p>The United States Mail Order House was incorporated in October 1905 with a capital of $100,000. The incorporators were: Messrs. Anton J. Zahrobsky, Jakub Kandlik, Edw. J. Winternitz, Anton Kokes, Matej Kara, Frantisek Wawak, and William Stuchlik.</p>
   <p>Later, the capital was increased to $500,000 and subscriptions for shares at $100 each were received. Only $115,000 worth were sold among twenty- <pb facs="5418478_3_0239.jpg" n="3"/>three shareholders, who took fifty shares each. Two of them sold their holdings to Mr. Kara, so that at present the company consists of twenty-one members. They are:</p>
   <p>The company opened business on Jackson Boulevard, but after a few months it was forced to seek larger quarters in order to expand the business. It rented the third floor of its present building on Marshall Boulevard at Twenty-first Street. About four years ago, it purchased the building from the Western Sand Blast Company, paying $41,500. There is still an incumbrance of $27,000 remaining on the building. The business prospered best during the second and third years, but after that it began to decline.</p>
   <p>"It was a costly experience," said the shareholders, one like another. "That five thousand dollars, which each of us put into the business, we must forget about, but we will not put in anymore. It would be a pity to throw away any more money."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0240.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>As can be seen, the shareholders have no confidence in the undertaking, and in view of the condition in which it now is, it would be extremely difficult to get any new stockholders and capital; therefore, there is nothing else to do, but go out of business, and that is what the company decided.</p>
   <p>The business is at a complete standstill, for as has been said before, all new orders are being returned unfilled. Mr. Josef Kokes, the treasurer of the firm, is still acting in the capacity of his office. Almost all the clerks and other employees have been released, as they are no longer needed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
