<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1881-02-08">February 8, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">Band Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0567</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0567.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1881-02-08">February 8, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">BAND CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several times in the past we have given it as our opinion, that Bohemian musicians would benefit not only the Bohemian public, but themselves as well in an artistic and material manner, if they would take an example from the musicians of other nationalities, namely the German, and unite themselves into a well organized band. We said at that time, that there were plenty of Bohemian musicians in our city and that it would require nothing more than a little good fellowship, patience and industry, so that an understanding of such importance as an independent Bohemian band could exist and do well, serving us and itself with honor. Many otherwise reasonable musicians merely smiled at this suggestion and insisted that in no way was it possible to even think of organizing and maintaining anything of the kind.</p>
   <p>The desired organization of Chicago Bohemian musicians into a band, did not materialize and we took it for granted that there was no use giving it any further thought.</p>
   <p>We were mistaken however and graciously acknowledge that same. Several musicians belonging to the "C.S.P.S." (Czecho-Slavak Benefit Society) united to form the <pb facs="5418478_3_0568.jpg" n="2"/>nucleus of a band and it did not take long before they were strenghtened by the addition of other musicians. As leader of the new band was found the well-known composer and musician, Mr. Jen Koula.</p>
   <p>The very first performance in public by this band was an honor to them and last Sunday's concert was played in the hall of "Ces. Am. Sokol" (Bohemian American Sokol.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
