<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-27">June 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Our Outings, Now and of Yore</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1531</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1531.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-06-27">June 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">OUR OUTINGS, NOW AND OF YORE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The beginning of the outing season cannot fail to remind every old settler that our outings are not what they used to be. This does not mean that they are not as successful as they used to be, because they are. But there is something lacking, and you cannot find what it is until you think of the "marches" without which an outing was unthinkable. Yes, it is the missing "marches" that deprive our present day outings of a good part of their color. True enough, we still go on our outings every Sunday, but they are somehow tame, without the "hurrahs" of which we used to be so fond. No more do we wait until we hear the music under our windows, in order to get up and run to the depot. Now we simply leave when we please, and the car takes us where we are going and brings us home from the picnic again exactly when we please. Now we do not even have to carry the old lunch basket because next to every picnic ground all kinds of facilities can be found to feed the hungry and <pb facs="5418478_3_1532.jpg" n="2"/>refresh the thirsty, perspiring, shirt-sleeved dancers. Our picnickers do not have to make any preparations at all nowadays, because they go only a mile or so away, to a place that could be walked to in a pinch, a method that would obviate crowding in streetcars. You may not leave the house until after dinner, and come home in time for supper, and if you are still outing-minded, you may go out again for a moonlight walk. Now all that is not as it used to be, and small wonder that we are getting to be more and more lazy, and more and more lacking in "pep". When there was a picnic, there was no half-way preparation for it. Picnic grounds were far away, and nobody would have thought of it as an outing if it did not take at least twenty miles by rail and one mile of walking to reach the grounds. Such an outing needed days of preparations, and getting up early on Sunday morning in order not to miss the train. Saturday was a busy day for the mothers, roasting meats and baking cakes so that their marriageable daughters could show off with their culinary skill before their dancing partners. The food was so good that very few of them could resist thoughts of marriage licence and honeymoon. As a rule, the meal was a huge <pb facs="5418478_3_1533.jpg" n="3"/>banquet, as you could learn from the fathers and lovelorn lads who used to tote heavy baskets, full of food, to the depot early Sunday morning.</p>
   <p>Most of the picnickers used to walk to the depot, occasionally stopping on the way and waiting for the parade on the sidewalk to pass by, forming in that way a colorful frame for the marchers. This meant getting up rather early because the outing trains used to leave mostly at eight, and never after nine in the morning, and for those who missed that train there was nothing left to do but eat their lunch at home and make a firm resolution to get up earlier next Sunday. It is quite different these days. Trains are hardly ever used for a trip to the picnic grounds any more, and nobody needs to be afraid of missing a streetcar when he wants to go to Riverside or Willow Springs.</p>
   <p>Perhaps, after all, it is nothing to be sorry for that we have discontinued patronizing railroads and have thereby made our outings more convenient and more easily accessible. But all of us certainly miss the parades without <pb facs="5418478_3_1534.jpg" n="4"/>which a picnic could hardly be imagined. No matter what lodge or association held a picnic, it was certain that the parade would march to the depot, and the organizing society never went alone. Many other lodges and associations were invited to join the parade, especially when they had uniforms. The hosts reciprocated by marching, in uniform, in the parade of their guests when they held their outings. Uniforms were much more popular in those days than they are now, because there were more frequent opportunities to parade them, and associations which had uniforms were very popular during the summer time. One Sunday they would be invited to march in the parade of a picnic the following Sunday they would be invited to a flag dedication or some other such affair, and there was hardly a Sunday that they did not have an invitation to some affair. To attend such events was almost considered a patriotic duty by the invited association, and a refusal was almost considered a minor form of national treason. Perhaps you still remember the picnics of the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov (Bohemian National Cemetery) held every year in the adjacent garden. That used to be a kind of national holiday attended by all associations, with the uniformed one in first place. That was in the early <pb facs="5418478_3_1535.jpg" n="5"/>days when we had to take a train to the Cemetery, and were happy to get there even in that inconvenient way. The parade used to march to the Northwestern Depot, from where a number of special trains took the picnickers to Irving Park, where the parade was reorganized and marched to the Cemetery. For those who have never had that experience we suggest that they picture unpaved streets, which either had no sidewalks at all or had merely board walks, and to remember that the old non-Bohemian settlers in Irving Park never looked with particular favor on the Bohemian picnickers. To this we add that such outings were frequently made shortly after a rain, and that the Irving Park mud is not any better than any other mud, so you should be able to visualize the beauties and fascinations of such a march. But just the same, thousands of our people participated in such parades at least twice a year, once on Decoration Day and once when the Narodni Hrbitov had its outing, which last was considered a full-fledged festival. There have been no such parades since that time, except on the occasion of some really great national holiday, or, for the Catholic part of our people, an important church holiday. There really has not been a "thorough" parade since the World's fair, with the single exception of the one to the unveiling of Havlicek's monument, and there will <pb facs="5418478_3_1536.jpg" n="6"/>be none until a really big celebration chances to come our way. But marching to picnics? Why, look here, it was too much effort to walk for two days during the recent streetcar strike. The fare is just a wee nickel, and the car will take you almost to the end of the world, that is the end of the world situated somewhere in the neighborhood of Berwyn.</p>
   <p>We are not quite sure that the end of the "magnificent" picnic parades is greatly regretted, but we know that our old settlers and those fond of group activities remember them every summer and recall how many miles they had to march with picnic parades to which they decided to give added prestige by their presence.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
