<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-01">Sept. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A Czech Dancer's Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0842</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0842.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-01">Sept. 1, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">A CZECH DANCER'S SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Municipal Pier, with its musical recitals and other high class entertainment, is gaining in attraction day by day. Its ideal location on the lake affords relief and relaxation to Chicago's populace, sweltering in the hot weather, and the activities arranged there regularly, offer a pleasant recreation.</p>
   <p>On Fridays, especially, the spacious premises are the scene of activities which are a genuine delight to the large gatherings. The celebrated Dramatic League, headed by Mrs. Lyman A. Walton, has taken charge of the evenings. Last Friday night a recital was arranged on the Pier in honor of the Greek consul general in Chicago, who was appointed minister to the United States from Greece, and is to leave our city within a short time.</p>
   <p>A program on a high artistic level was offered. It consisted of music, drama, and dancing. We would not have paid any attention to it but for the fact that <pb facs="5418478_3_0843.jpg" n="2"/>Mrs. Bozena Pondelicek a Czech artist well known in local circles, appeared as a soloist. Hers was the greatest success of all the performers on that evening. She gave several classic dances, among them her own version of Brahms' "Gipsy Dance".</p>
   <p>The Dramatic League then produced a pantomime, "Columbia's Message". Mrs. Pondelicek's art was reviewed in a highly flattering style by our English language local press. It has furnished a new contribution to the appreciation of Czech-American art, and that is the reason why we are giving it mention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
