<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-09">Nov. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">News of the Frantisek Ludvik Bohemian Dramatic Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0649</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0649.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-09">Nov. 9, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS OF THE FRANTISEK LUDVIK BOHEMIAN DRAMATIC ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Is there one among us who is not acquainted with those hard, stiff-necked peasant natures of our Bohemian peasants? Those peasants who would rather spend their last penny in litigation than settle some petty legal matter out of court. And yet their innermost nature is kind and filled with love for the native soil. Out of these incongruous elements, the great Czech playwright, Ladislav Stroupeznicky,has painted a masterful picture of the Czech village life. No painter could have done it better than he; no painter could have portrayed the characteristic personality of the Czech peasant as sharply as Stroupeznicky did in his now famous "Nasu furianti" ("Our Braggarts"). You will find all the varieties of peasant pride in this work--the aged retired Peter, proud of his ability to manage horses; the hardheaded Vaclav, who proudly declares that if he does not get his beloved girl Verunka he will forthwith join the army as a dragoon; the old veteran Blaha, who wages an unequal fight with the sly tailor Fiala--both of them having their eyes on the vacant night watchman's job. It is Fiala who complains that he is obliged to feed seven stomachs, <pb facs="5418478_3_0650.jpg" n="2"/>[support seven members of his family] and is, therefore, entitled to get that job.....All in all there is so much human material in this play that a whole newspaper column would not suffice to give an adequate description of it. The Narodni Divadlo (National Theater) of Prague places the "Nasu furianti" among the best Czech plays, such as fully portray human nature. The comical situations and variegated scenes enhance the value of this charming dramatic portrait of our Czech countryside. The Old Czech songs issuing from the mouths of the players seem to bring back the good old times. The cast of "Nasu furianti" has been excellently managed by the amateur actors of the Bohemian lodge of the Independent Order Of Odd Fellows. The Sunday production is really an annual event given by the combined Bohemian lodges of the Odd Fellows organization, and the receipts are to be diverted to the press and publicity fund and utilized for organizational purposes.....Tickets may be obtained from many lodge members and from Brother Josef Macek, Jr., 2214 South Spaulding Avenue, or one may telephone Canal 7102.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
