<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-13">May 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Program of John Huss Celebrations</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1539</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1539.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-05-13">May 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE PROGRAM OF JOHN HUSS CELEBRATIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The committee for a joint celebration of the John Huss anniversary has been working [for a period of] over a year, quietly but very seriously, because it is well aware of the significance of the task entrusted to it. Important decisions were made at its last meeting, which was attended by twenty-three representatives. After the reading of the minutes of the previous meeting, and the presentation of a statement for $132 from the Narodni Tiskarna (National Print Shop) for 3,000 pictures of John Huss, and another statement for $96 from Kusta &amp; Mejdrich, for picture post cards and sundries, the reports of the various subcommittees were read.</p>
   <p>The program subcommittee reported that it had worked out the following program for July 6: (1) musical selection; (2) speech by the chairman of the joint celebration of the quincentenary anniversary of John Huss' death; (3) speech in <pb facs="5418478_3_1540.jpg" n="2"/>English by Professor Josef Jiri Kral; (4) oratorio, "John Huss," Part I; (5) oratorio, "John Huss," Part II (both by the Cesky Pevecky Spolek Bedrich Smetana--Bohemian Singing Society Bedrich Smetana); (6) speech in Bohemian by Dr. Frantisek Iska; (7) tableau, a lifelike representation of John Huss' death at the stake.</p>
   <p>After some explanation and a short discussion, this program was approved. The same applies to the program worked out for the celebration in the Pilsen Park Pavilion, July 5, which will be as follows: (1) musical selection; (2) opening of festivities; (3) singing by the Ceska Ustredni Pevecka Jednota (Federation of Bohemian Singing Societies); (4) speech in Bohemian by Mr. Joseph Cermak; (5) music; (6) singing; (7) four tableaux, during which Mr. J. Kosar will speak; (8) music.</p>
   <p>It was unanimously agreed to order from Bohemia two thousand pamphlets "Hus Kacir" <pb n="3"/><gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/><pb facs="5418478_3_1541.jpg" n="4"/>Sunday, so that marching in a parade must have lost its attraction.....In consideration of the entirely different character of this parade--a parade in honor of John Huss, instead of one advertising a "hop" of one kind or another--it was agreed, by fifteen votes against five, that the parade should take place. We wish to call the attention of all our Free-Thought societies, and of all our freethinkers to this decision, so that they may emphasize their disapproval of the clergy by having as large a participation as possible in this parade. The announcement of when and where the parade will take place, will be made later.</p>
   <p>The press committee reported that the Bohemian pamphlet written by Professor J. J. Kral is ready and its price will be five cents a copy. The same price was fixed for the English pamphlet, also by Mr. Kral. The English pamphlet will be ready at the end of this month. Pictures of John Huss, 8 1/2 by 13 1/2 inches, are also ready and will be sold for fifteen cents apiece. Mr. Prudinek was charged with the sale of the pamphlets outside of Chicago, Mr. Martinek here in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
