<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-14">June 14, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Silver Jubilee of Klub Boleslav Jablonsky</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1211</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1211.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-06-14">June 14, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">SILVER JUBILEE OF KLUB BOLESLAV JABLONSKY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.1--The commemoration of the foundation of our Bohemian dramatic society, the Klub Boleslav Jablonsky, was celebrated yesterday. It was an event of great importance not only for the club itself but for all amateur players as well. It cannot be denied that there is a cessation of activity among our amateur actors; gone are the delightful evenings which they so often used to provide for us. The amateurs have gone to sleep, it seems, either because of their own lack of interest or on account of unfavorable circumstances. But the Jablonsky Dramatic Club still holds up the banner of amateur art. Not even in times most adverse to their activities has that banner ever wilted; it has reared itself with virile sturdiness as if proclaiming to all Bohemians: "Our amateur art still lives and with God's help will never perish!"</p>
   <p>And for twenty-five years the Klub Boleslav Jablonsky has kept on in grand style. What a countless number of performances have been arranged; what a wealth of education and entertainment has been provided for our people! The Club has gained unusual favor and affection among Chicago Bohemians of all <pb facs="5418478_3_1212.jpg" n="2"/>classes; what wonder, therefore, that a multitude gathered last night in the Bohemian-American Hall on Eighteenth Street to show their appreciation of the tireless activities of its members!</p>
   <p>The meeting was opened by Mr. Joseph Beran, who in sincere and unaffected phrases described all the Club's activities, referring to its foundation twenty-five years ago, its frequent struggles for existence, and its final victory.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
