<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-15">Mar. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Report of the Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce of Chicago Submitted at the Annual Meeting on March 12, 1922.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-03-15">Mar. 15, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL REPORT OF THE CZECHOSLOVAK CHAMBER OF COMMERCE OF CHICAGO SUBMITTED AT THE ANNUAL MEETING ON MARCH 12, 1922.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since its last annual meeting held January 30, the Česko-Slovanská Obchodni Komora (Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce) has made decided progress, which will be appreciated in days to come. When we consider the small financial support this organization received during the last year, and when we compare its activity with its scant financial resources, we are amazed by the progress it achieved in spite of all its difficulties. The Komora nevertheless keeps up the high quality of its work, which is not only appreciated by competent persons, but also greatly admired by them.</p>
   <p>This report would not be complete if we were to omit the activities of the Komora during the fiscal year of February 1, 1921, to February 1, 1922.</p>
   <p>The organization received 237 letters and other communications, and answered <pb facs="5418478_3_0060.jpg" n="2"/>237 of them. According to the records of the secretary, there were 500 letters, reports to newspapers, and other sundry activities. The Česko-Slovanská Obchodní Komora facilitated commercial intercourses or supplied pertinent information concerning the following: Machinery for the manufacture of cigarette holders, machinery for the manufacture of cigarettes, cigar making, clothing, paper, cotton; addresses of Czechoslovak bankers in the United States, addresses of exporters in Plzeň (Pilsen), Brno (Brunn), addresses of manufacturers of musical instruments, mimeographic work, furniture, patented chairs, patented watch-chain charms, ploughs, millstones, notions, effervescent powders, oriental candy, tachographs, express rates, customs, whips and whip handles, coral jewels, toys, dolls, machinery for sugar refineries, films, wigs and toupeés, chemicals, laces, embroideries, national costumes, pencils, commercial publications, wicker work, patents for artificial limb manufacturing, etc.</p>
   <p>The board of directors of the Česko-Slovanská Obchodní Komora held twelve <pb facs="5418478_3_0061.jpg" n="3"/>regular monthly meetings and five extra ones. The committees held several meetings in which some very important matters were discussed. The Česko-Slovanská Obchodní Komora was instrumental in having the office of commercial attache to the Czechoslovak Consulate of Chicago abolished. It did this by dealing directly with the Minister of Foreign Affairs in Prague. The Česko-Slovanská Obchodní Komora assumed responsibility in a propaganda campaign for Prague wholesalers and made it possible for them to have their samples reach the American market. This activity was conducted under the direct supervision of Mr. John A. Sokol, who is one of the directors of the organization.</p>
   <p>Contacts were established between the government of Czechoslovakia and the cotton farmers of Texas, who were thus enabled to ship their goods directly. Czechoslovak commercial houses were encouraged to send their samples so that a sample room could be established here. At the direct request of the members of the Komora, a company called The Worlds Products Trading Company was <pb facs="5418478_3_0062.jpg" n="4"/>organized with a capital of $500,000; during the month of March the members of the Česko-Slovanská Obchodní Komora were called into a meeting for the purpose of joining that company.</p>
   <p>The board of directors of the Komora effected a contact with the Czechoslovak Ambassador in Washington, D. C., Dr. B. Štĕpánek. During Dr. Štĕpánek's visit in Chicago, ways and means were discussed for the development of systematic progress of work which could benefit all Czechoslovak commerce.</p>
   <p>The Komora printed six bulletins during the past year, and these were mailed to all members, to consulates, to chambers of commerce in Czechoslovakia, to exporters, and to other influential organizations. On October 14, a lecture was given to the members of the organization in the pavilion of the Pilsen Brewery Company. It was well attended.</p>
   <p>The Komora can boast that it was able to establish contacts by correspondence <pb facs="5418478_3_0063.jpg" n="5"/>with all of the influential organizations not only in America, but also in the entire Czechoslovak Republic, and it is able, therefore, to furnish any kind of information upon request. It is absolutely necessary that every Czechoslovak in America support the work of the Česko-Slovanská Obchodní Komora; that he become a member thereof, so that our organization may establish a permanent office, a reading room, and additional space in which Czechoslovak businessmen may meet for conferences touching not only upon local business, but also upon foreign commerce. It is recommended that individual trading companies and individual businessmen order their goods jointly for their respective concerns and thus face the competition of large capital which, by its inconsiderate and cut-throat methods, pushes the small dealers to the wall. With united effort, it would be easier to face such competition, and the Česko-Slovanská Obchodní Komora, by its widespread propaganda, would be able to serve the interests of Czechoslovak businessmen best. Thus, every industry could appoint a committee which would deal with matters peculiar to it and would control its own propaganda while in association with the mother organization <pb facs="5418478_3_0064.jpg" n="6"/>and the rest of the committees representing other businesses; rules could be formulated which would be satisfactory to the whole organization. The Czechoslovak businessman in America needs his own organization now more than ever before, and it is for this reason that the above plan is recommended.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
