<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-28">Jan. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Art Triumphs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-28">Jan. 28, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH ART TRIUMPHS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There was a concert by the American Symphony Orchestra in the Studebaker Theater yesterday afternoon. It was directed by Glenn Dillard Gunn and sponsored by the Chicago Tribune. The program is of special interest to us, since it was made up of Czech music almost exclusively, and also because two well-known Czech artists appeared as soloists. They were George Hrusa, violin virtuoso, and Miss Hattie Kovarik, piano virtuoso. Czech music was therefore excellently represented, and we may admit at the outset, without showing bias, that Czech music stood the test splendidly. It conquered everyone and scored a success more brilliant than has been witnessed by our public for a long time.</p>
   <p>It is to be regretted that a change was made in the program. The overture to "Prodana Nevesta" (The Bartered Bride) was ommited, and thus none of Bedrich Smetana's compositions were presented to the audience.</p>
   <p>The theater was fairly well filled when the orchestra opened the concert, at <pb facs="5418478_3_0419.jpg" n="2"/>3 P. M., with the American national anthem. A suite, "Americana," by our fellow countryman, Mr. Kolar, concertmaster and assistant conductor of the Damrosch orchestra in New York, was played. It is based on American folk songs and is outstanding because of its polyphonic wealth and skillful orchestration, in which effects for the violins are particularly conspicuous.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hrusa played the difficult concerto for violin by Antonin Dvorak. He surmounted the difficulties of the technical part with ease and exhibited deep musical sentiment. Mr. Hrusa may well feel gratified with the success he achieved.</p>
   <p>Two pieces followed, played by the strings only: "Valtz," by Dvorak, and "Serenade," by Prochazka. The latter was presented in Chicago for the first time and made such a hit that an encore had to be given.</p>
   <p>Miss Kovarik was no less successful than Mr. Hrusa. She played a "Concerto" by Beethoven. Her mastery of the piano brought forth thunderous applause <pb facs="5418478_3_0420.jpg" n="3"/>and gifts of flowers. The "Nutcracker-Suite" by Tchaikovsky closed the concert.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
