<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-04">Nov. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">He Did Not Forget the Poor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0044</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0044.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-04">Nov. 4, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">HE DID NOT FORGET THE POOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. J. J. Svoboda, the chief stockholder of the Grand Leader Department Store, West 22nd Street and California Avenue, was known to be an enterprising and successful businessman throughout his very active life. It now appears that he also was a man of a good heart who did not forget, even at the hour of his tragic death, his lowly origin; his regard for the poor was brought to light by his last will and testament which, as we already announced yesterday, was presented to the Probate Court by Attorney Otto Kerner. In this will Mr. Svoboda provided for several very generous bequests which will forever characterize him as a Maecenas. [Translator's note: The Czechs, in using the term "Maecenas" have not in mind a patron of arts, but any very generous person who endows or otherwise fosters a cause or an institution.]</p>
   <p>Mr. Svoboda was born in Bohemia, coming to the United States as a little boy. When, during the early nineties, the district now known as Bohemian <pb facs="5418478_3_0045.jpg" n="2"/>California began to shape up, he felt instinctively that here in due course of time there would be one of the most populous Czech neighborhoods in Chicago, and that here an opportunity was offered to an enterprising mind. It is because of these great possibilities that he founded a department store in that neighborhood, a business known by the name of Grand Leader, an enterprize which flourished from year to year. Fortune was kind to Mr. Svoboda, so that he could, toward the end of his life, show the results of his commercial endeavors. His will reveals that his total bequests amount to $300,000.</p>
   <p>When he realized that a treacherous illness undermined his health, he called for the banker, J. J. Salat, entrusting him with the making of a last will in which the Utulna A Sirotcinec... (Bohemian Old Peoples Home and Orphanage) was bequeathed the sum of $5,000, the Bohemian Catholic Saint Joseph's Orphanage at Lisle, Illinois, receiving likewise the sum of $5,000, and the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) $1,000. Besides the above bequests he left $10,000 to various relatives, and the balance of his <pb facs="5418478_3_0046.jpg" n="3"/>wealth to his widow, Mrs. Bozena Svoboda. The last will was made out in Mr. Svoboda's Oak Park residence at noon, attested by the signatures of witnesses, and several hours later Mr. Svoboda was dead. In a fit of despair caused by his poor health, he took his own life voluntarily but not before performing a noble and a charitable deed for those to whom the fate was unkind.</p>
   <p>The executor of his last will is the Lawndale State Bank. It was presented to the Probate Court by Mr. Kerner who was Mr. Svoboda's legal adviser and attorney. There were several protests made against the testament, but as we already announced yesterday, Mr. Kerner proved the genuineness of Mr. Svoboda's signature by cancelled checks bearing the deceased's signatures ....The handwriting [in both cases] was eloquent in itself and the will was therefore accepted as genuine.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
