<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-16">Oct. 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">An Art Exhibition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0630</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0630.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-16">Oct. 16, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">AN ART EXHIBITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The exhibition which the Cesky Umelecky Klub (Bohemian Artists' Club) has been preparing for some time was opened last night in the two large halls of the Dvorak Park building. The exhibition consists principally of works by our Bohemian-American painters, sculptors, and architects. However, our musicians, and writers have been active in connection with the exhibition by arranging concerts and lectures. Thus, the exhibition offers the Umelecky Klub an excellent opportunity to prove that it not only exists, but that it is really making progress not only in Bohemian circles, but also among Americans to whom art is somewhat more accessible than to us because they have much greater means and a larger variety of talent at their disposal. The exhibition has been advertised for some time by posters made by the Bohemian-American painter, Mr. Rudolf Bohunek.....</p>
   <p>But let us enter the building. There are no disappointments because the <pb facs="5418478_3_0631.jpg" n="2"/>exhibition is really good and well arranged. The stairway is beautifully decorated with flowers loaned by the West Park Commission.....</p>
   <p>Among the most impressive exhibits are the paintings by August Petrtyl.....Especially attractive pieces by Mr. Oldrich Farsky....and Mrs. Bozena Hess.... form a group surrounded by the works of Mr. K. A. Wilimowsky....R. Bohunek....J. Fraula, E. J. Krasa, R. Vacik, Jaroslav J. Zmrhal, and Mrs. Irma Schroeder. Among our sculptors, only C. Jurecek, of Chicago, and J. Krupka and J. Rudolf, of New York, are represented.....The other room is occupied by the work of our architects Messrs. James Dibelka, A. Charvat, K. V. Kallal, J. M. Mrazek, F. Randak, J. B. Rezny, and Jos. Zidek.....</p>
   <p>The exhibition will last from October 15 to October 31, and during this period there will be two concerts in connection with it. The first will be given this Sunday at 3 P. M.....The second concert will be held on the following Sunday at the same time.....Finally, there will be four lectures presented <pb facs="5418478_3_0632.jpg" n="3"/>during the exhibition. The first is tonight and will deal with the artistic beauties of Paris. The speaker is Mr. Jaromir R. Psenka. The second lecture will take place Wednesday, and Mr. Jaroslav Zmrhal will speak on the subject, "How to Look at Art". Friday, October 23, Mr. A. J. Melichar will discuss "Art in the Home". The last lecture, on "Several Chapters in the History of Bohemian Art," by Dr. Jaroslav E. S. Vojan, will take place Wednesday, October 28. There is no admission charge for the exhibition or the concerts and lectures. The Umelecky Klub is arranging all this without a thought of profit, and donations given by visitors for the beautiful catalogues will go to the war relief fund for suffering countrymen overseas.</p>
   <p>The exhibition is good and well worth seeing. No visitor will be disappointed, but everybody should regard it as an art exhibition, not as a place for entertainment or fun. Go there with the idea that in arranging it, the Umelecky Klub had only one aim in mind: To popularize art and bring it close to the general public so that the people would finally learn not only to respect art, but to understand it as well. And those of us who care and have <pb facs="5418478_3_0633.jpg" n="4"/>the necessary means should select a painting or a sculpture, or both, something we especially admire, and purchase it for our homes after the close of the exhibition, or give it as a gift to someone who appreciates art. That is one way to promote Bohemian-American art, which would develop and grow much more rapidly if there were enough people who appreciate it and could support it.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's vernissage was well attended in spite of the bad weather. The chairman, secretary, and many members of the West Park Commission were present. They were astonished by the high degree of development of our Bohemian art, and they were not reluctant in voicing their admiration. There were also a number of art-loving American friends of the Klub.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian public may justly be proud of this exhibition and should show this by visiting it in large numbers during its two weeks' duration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
