<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-02-29">Feb. 29, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">Twenty-Five Year Jubilee Celebration.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1596</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1596.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1904-02-29">Feb. 29, 1904</date>.
<title level="a">TWENTY-FIVE YEAR JUBILEE CELEBRATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Saturday's twenty-five year jubilee celebration of the uniting of Vlastimil Club with Osveta Lodge #27 C.S.P.S. (Czechoslovak Benevolent Society) was again proof, that our countrymen on the northwest side are capable of entertaining themselves heartily and cordially.</p>
   <p>The celebration was arranged in honor of the remaining members of the former Vlastimil Club, which joined the C.S.P.S. twenty-five years ago, and thereby became an aid in overcoming the difficulties with which the lodges of those days were forced to contend. The celebration was attended mostly by brothers of the Order and their families, and the hall was filled to capacity in spite of the unfavorable weather conditions.</p>
   <p>The celebration was begun by the band under the direction of Mr. Jan Votava. After the visitors had danced a bit, Mr. Jan Votava. After the visitors had danced a bit, Mr. Longin Tuma, chairman of the entertainment committee, appeared on the stage and spoke a few words about the reasons for the celebration. He mentioned how Vlastimil Blub joined Osveta Lodge in 1879, which had then <pb facs="5418478_3_1597.jpg" n="2"/>been in existence only a year, in that manner strengthening it. Then he spoke about the Union of C.S.P.S., which had been organized over fifty years ago and now numbers fourteen thousand members. He told how twenty-five years ago, twenty six members of Vlastimil Club joined Osveta Lodge. The speaker named those members of the club, still alive and belonging to the lodge now, at the same time presenting them to the audience.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
