<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-05">July 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">John Huss' Martyrdom Commemorated in the John Huss Memorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1279</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1279.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-07-05">July 5, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN HUSS' MARTYRDOM COMMEMORATED IN THE JOHN HUSS MEMORIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Free-Thought community commemorated the martyrdom of John Huss in a celebration which took place in the Jubilejni Husuv Dum (John Huss Memorial) yesterday afternoon. The memorial, which is located at 4236 West 22nd Street, was also the scene of the July Fourth celebration, commemorating the Declaration of Independence of the United States of America, as well as the celebration in memory of the famous battle of Zborov (July 2, 1917), and in commemoration of the death of Karel Havlicek Borovsky on July 29. [Translator's note: Karel Havlicek Borovsky was Bohemia's most famous publicist who was persecuted by the Austrian government because of his inflammatory nationlistic articles and speeches, and was finally imprisoned.] The celebration was a dignified affair attended not only by the regular members of the Svobodna Obec (Free-Thought community) but by a great many men and women freethinkers as well. The program began at 2 P.M.,with a speech of welcome delivered by the president of the Free-Thought community, Mr. Josef W. Egermayer. Grill's orchestra then <pb facs="5418478_3_1280.jpg" n="2"/>played several compositions.... after which the chairman introduced the main speaker....Mr. Vaclav J. Petrzelka. The speaker mentioned four significant events which took place during the month of July. He said that these events were similar in character because the same basic idea motivated all of them: Faith in the victory of truth, justice, and human rights; [faith] in an ideal. "John Huss insisted," the speaker said, "that truth must never be abandoned. Though he was imprisoned for eighteen months at Constance, though he was ill and worn from imprisonment, he defied the council again and again, and refused to recant..... John Huss, a native of that part of Bohemia which has been characterized by a people of unflinching and stanch character [Southern Bohemia], looms up before us as he goes to his death at the stake. He met physical death, but morally, he gained eternal victory." [Translator's note: Much of this speech, which is devoted to a discussion of the life and heroism of John Huss, is omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>"Here is a lesson to be learned: To speak the truth and to defend it, even if it cost us our lives, and damned be he who for a crust of bread, abandons the <pb facs="5418478_3_1281.jpg" n="3"/>truth." [Translator's note: The speaker then discussed the battle of Zborov (July 2, 1917). I have translated one short paragraph to convey the general tenor of the speech.]</p>
   <p>"The Czech people must never forget the significance of the great battle of Zborov; it was a remarkable struggle of our border armies in Russia against the armies of Karl [the Hapsburg], and Wilhelm [the Hohenzollern], and their glorious victory....."</p>
   <p>Two poems were recited; "Svetlo V Temnotach" (Light Shineth in the Darkness) by Svatopluk Cech, was recited by Miss Miluse Splichal, and "Americka Neodvislost (American Independence) by Miss Anna Mirosovsky.....The audience than sang the [famous nationalist song] "Hranice Vzplala Na Brehu Ryna" (A Pyre Blazed on the Banks of the Rhine). [Translator's note: The song referred to has become one of defiance against the Roman Catholic Church.] This very successful festival ended with a speech made by the chairman. The band played again, and as a final gesture, Miss M. Zeman recited a poem describing the tragedy which took <pb facs="5418478_3_1282.jpg" n="4"/>place on July 21, 1621, on the Staromestske Namesti (old town square) at Prague. [Translator's note: Shortly after the battle of the Bila Hora (White Mountain) in which the Catholic army was victorious, twenty-seven Bohemian nobles, all of whom were Protestants, were beheaded.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
