<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-04-23">Apr. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Concert at the Auditorium.</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Clear Profit Which Amounts to about $3000 Will Be Divided Equally between the Old Peoples' Home and St. Joseph's Catholic Orphanage.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0529</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0529.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-04-23">Apr. 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERT AT THE AUDITORIUM.</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Clear Profit Which Amounts To About $3000 Will Be Divided Equally Between The Old Peoples' Home And St. Joseph's Catholic Orphanage.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1.--The spacious Auditorium hall, where our Bohemian artist, Jan Kubelik, celebrated his triumphs several weeks ago, and at his side our wonder-child, Milada Cerny, demonstrated her extraordinary musical talent, was selected for this concert.</p>
   <p>In the halls of this colossal structure, thousands of the Bohemian public gathered yesterday to pay homage to their countrymen artists who appeared on the Bohemian benefit concert arranged by the W. W. Kimball Piano Company.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0530.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Although the attendance at the concert was quite numerous, it could have been better. However, if we take into consideration existing circumstances, then we must admit that this concert met with a brilliant moral and financial success.</p>
   <p>Crowds of visitors began to gather before the Auditorium shortly after two o'clock; an innumerable multitude of people, like a dark cloud, drifted toward the hall, toward that place of fame where our people several times already have paid homage to the beautiful art brought forth by our great master.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's concert was for us not only an artistic treat, it contributed at the same time to Bohemian charities, which will receive the net proceeds.</p>
   <p>The splendidly arranged program of this concert was opened shortly after three o'clock by the famous Bohemian pianist Mr. Rudolf Friml, who unveiled for the general public his great musical talent.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0531.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Others appearing on the program were: Mr. Bernhardt Listeman violinist, Mrs. Mabel Sharp Hardien, singer; the Bohemian bass viol virtuoso, Vaclav Jiskra, appeared in a well arranged selection in which he demonstrated his extraordinary talent.</p>
   <p>All in all, it can be said that the benefit concert arranged for the benefit of Bohemian charitable institutions by the W. W. Kimball Company was a financial asset for these institutions, and the company gained much favor with the Bohemian people of Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
