<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-20">May 20, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A Strawberry Festival in Pilsen Park Pavilion</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1309</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1309.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-20">May 20, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">A STRAWBERRY FESTIVAL IN PILSEN PARK PAVILION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It has been a long time since the Pilsen Park pavilion was host to such a select group of ladies as gathered there yesterday at the strawberry festival arranged by the Damsky Odbor Ceske Dobrocinne Spolecnosti v Chicagu (Ladies Auxiliary of the Bohemian Charitable Association of Chicago). The noble and beautiful purpose for which the festival was arranged attracted so many enthusiastic workers from all of our societies that the spacious pavilion was overcrowded. This enormous attendance was a satisfaction to the arrangements committee as it shows that the work and significance of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost is being understood and supported by our people. Such evidence of public support will also be an encouragement to further energetic work which will be so much needed this year.</p>
   <p>The excellent program which was prepared by the chairman of the arrangements <pb facs="5418478_3_1310.jpg" n="2"/>committee, Mrs. Antonie Cervenka, started shortly after 2 P. M. The president of the Ladies' Auxiliary, Mrs. Josephine Beranek, delivered a brief speech and welcomed the audience. First on the program was the zither virtuoso, Mr. Vaclav Fisher, who played two beautiful solos. He was rewarded by a storm of applause. The next number was an aria from the opera "Mignon," which was sung in real operatic style by Miss Helena Weiner. Mrs. Novy-Fiala was the accompanist. The ballet solo of little Miss Vlasta Vesely was a real surprise for the audience, and her performance gave proof of dilligent training and the great progress of our future prima ballerina. Miss Frances Adamek then sung an aria from the Bohemian opera "Rusalka". Miss Adamek and Mr. J. Janota sang a duet entitled "Ty, Ty, Ty" (You, You, You).</p>
   <p>The Armour Ladies' Orchestra, consisting of twenty-five pieces, was the main attraction at the festival, and held the attention of the audience. In the meantime, when a group of little dancers was preparing for the last two <pb facs="5418478_3_1311.jpg" n="3"/>numbers of the program, Mr. Charles Novak, chairman of the tag day committee, spoke a few words on the significance of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost. The pupils of Miss Libuse Bartuska's dancing school appeared in the last numbers of the program. It was really a charming miniature ballet and Miss Bartuska, as an arranger and teacher, may be justly proud of it. Mrs. A. Cervenka then thanked the audience and a real strawberry feast followed, lasting until almost 6 P. M.</p>
   <p>The arrangements committee was completely satisfied with the results because the proceeds of the festival were great. We congratulate the arrangements committee on their success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
