<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-04-08">Apr. 8, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Builders and Contractors Have Founded a Brickyard Which Promises to Be a Notable Success.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-04-08">Apr. 8, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN BUILDERS AND CONTRACTORS HAVE FOUNDED A BRICKYARD WHICH PROMISES TO BE A NOTABLE SUCCESS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1--Lately our countrymen have manifested creditable spirit of enterprise.</p>
   <p>We have a whole group of genuine Bohemian enterprises of various kinds, and most of them rest upon good, firm foundations, so that money invested in them is assured suitable profit.</p>
   <p>A promising undertaking, guaranteeing safety of investment and considerable clear profit, is the Builders Brick Company, whose product will soon be on the market. This company is deserving of detailed mention for it is a truly Bohemian undertaking.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0299.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The idea of its organization originated among Bohemian builders and contractors.</p>
   <p>Bohemians are managing it, Bohemian money is invested in the undertaking, and Bohemians will be its main supporters.</p>
   <p>A meeting was held last Thursday by the company at which interesting and encouraging reports were made.</p>
   <p>The company is capitalized at $75,000 of which almost $46,000 has been subscribed for and paid in.</p>
   <p>At the above mentioned meeting it was resolved to forty acres of land in Chicago Heights, Ill.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0300.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These grounds embrace an almost inexhaustible deposit of fine brick clay, and trade experts estimate that it will be possible to operate at least thirty years, at a daily production of one hundred and fifty thousand bricks.</p>
   <p>The cost of the ground and the furnishing of the factory in which the most modern and practical machinery will be installed is estimated at $75,000. A further outlay of about $25,000 will be needed for wagons, horses, etc. The company will issue bonds to raise the additional sum needed.</p>
   <p>Anyone may become a shareholder in the company by purchasing stock which costs $100 per share and which is limited to twenty shares to any individual. Almost all Bohemian builders, contractors and architects are shareholders, so that the company's product is assured a market; and there is no necessity of spending any money on advertising in order to secure business.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0301.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The profit on brick at present prices is very great and will be satisfactory even if the price should drop.</p>
   <p>About one hundred Bohemian citizens, who have acquired shares of the company, have taken advantage of the benefits offered by the company and all of the shares will surely be subscribed for very soon.</p>
   <p>As soon as the business is in operation, the value of the shares will rise.</p>
   <p>At the quarterly meeting, sample bricks, made of clay, from the ground which will be bought, were exhibited, and met with the approval of experts in every respect. It should also be mentioned that Chicago Heights and the future Bohemian brickyard are situated conveniently on a railroad, and transportation from there is rapid and at low cost.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0302.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>As is known, The Chicago Terminal Railroad extends from Chicago Heights through our California and Pilsen, and our builders and contractors can be supplied with brick at low cost.</p>
   <p>The board of directors is composed of the following: F. C. Layer, president; T. B. Dibelka, vice-president; Adolf Lonek, secretary; Richard Dusil, treasurer. Members of the board: A. F. Rusy, Frank Sedlak, Frank Novy, John Haisman and John Rus.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
