<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-30">July 30, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The "Jindrich Mosna Theatrical and Benevolent Club"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1188</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1188.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-07-30">July 30, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE "JINDRICH MOSNA THEATRICAL AND BENEVOLENT CLUB"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several days ago, we published a report about the developing of unusual activities of Bohemian amateur actors, even in the newest local communities. Today, it should be mentioned that in the very midst of our own Czech element, in Pilsen, quite a number of young enthusiasts of both sexes have organized so that in the coming fall season they intend to give theatrical performances, lectures, and recitals for the entertainment and mental recreation of our Bohemian people. The membership consists of persons to whom the stage is not new for they have appeared on various stages of the old homeland long before this. Many of them attended the dramatic schools of the foremost actors, and there is no doubt that even now they will be able to demonstrate their talents, if their efforts are sufficiently appreciated by our countrymen.</p>
   <p>This theatrical club will appear under the name: "Jindrich Mosna <pb facs="5418478_3_1189.jpg" n="2"/>Theatrical and Benevolent Club" and will give its performances in the Lad. Klacel Bohemian-American School at Nineteenth and Leavitt Streets. That which Mosna was to the theater-loving people of Bohemia, these amateurs, with their endeavors and unselfishness in this sphere of human activity, want to be for all Bohemians who have chosen this land as their new homeland. They aim to furnish them with sufficient entertainment in their mother tongue, the Czech language.</p>
   <p>This club really will not be only theatrical, but benevolent also, which is best proven by its last resolution, which states that the net profits of its first performance is to be donated to the Bohemian Charitable Association.</p>
   <p>Officers of this club are: Frank Brazda, president; Mrs. M. Riha, secretary; Bohuslav Linka, treasurer; J. Stoces, director. We wish these industrious, unselfish workers much luck so that their efforts may be crowned with success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
