<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-19">Sept. 19, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Culinary Arts in the Coliseum</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1296</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1296.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-19">Sept. 19, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">CULINARY ARTS IN THE COLISEUM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the first week of October the opening of the exposition "Kitchens of the Nations" will take place in the Coliseum. The exhibition is being given for the benefit of a fund for the building of a home for deserted girls, or girls arriving in Chicago in their search for employment, who have no friends in this city and no means with which to pay for lodgings. Such girls will be taken care of in the home and will be given help and advice in their search for work. A similar institution is now in existence in San Francisco, and it renders most valuable services there. The organizers or the exhibition, all of them ladies who are well known in Chicago society, are hoping that they will assure the building of the home from the profit of the "Kitchens of the Nations". There will be real kitchens in the exhibition, and they will be run by almost all nationalities whose settlements are in Chicago. In these "national" kitchens dishes will be served that are the most tasty and most popular, as well as characteristic of each individual nation. Also the best of bakery goods will be prepared and served there.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1297.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Czechoslovak section will be in charge of Mrs. Bessie E. Jirka, a lady who is very well known both in Czech and American circles in the city. Mrs. Jirka is the widow of the late physician and School Board member, Dr. F. J. Jirka, and mother of the popular Czech physician. She will certainly see to it that the Czech kitchen surpasses all the rest of them.....</p>
   <p>The individual nations will have their own "days," and the Czech day will be October 5.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
