<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-30">Jan. 30, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Z Umeleckeho Klubu</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0624</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0624.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>II B 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-30">Jan. 30, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Z UMELECKEHO KLUBU</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Cesky Umelecky Klub (The Czech Artistic Club) in Chicago held its regular meeting January 26, 1916, with which it closed its fourth year of active service.</p>
   <p>A vote of thanks was extended to the following outgoing officers for work well done: Mr. Charvat, chairman; Mr. Petrtyl, vice-chairman; Mr. Kryl, secretary; Mr. Mrazek, treasurer, and Mr. Svoboda, librarian.</p>
   <p>We wish to make known the future activities decided on at this meeting: the club publication, Jednou Za Cas (Once In A While), which now has twelve pages, will be published in the same form, and Artists Petrtyl, Sterba, Ingerle, Froula, Bohunek, and others have promised to work energetically for the publication.</p>
   <p>The following action was taken with respect to Dvorak Park, which is named in <pb facs="5418478_3_0625.jpg" n="2"/>memory of the great composer Dvorak: a committee of two was selected to investigate the particulars regarding the portrait of Dvorak which the Cesky Umelecky Klub expects to furnish by means of donations for that purpose. This portrait is to remain in Dvorak Park as long as the park bears the great musician's name.</p>
   <p>The following activities, the April Shakespearean celebration, the March artists' evening in Mr. Sterba's atelier, and the cycle of popular lectures, all will be acted upon at the next club meeting, February 9.</p>
   <p>The officers elected for the year 1916 are as follows: Chairman, unanimously elected, Mr. J. E. S. Vojan; vice-chairman, Mr. A. Sterba; secretary, Mr. Frantisek Horlivy; treasurer, Mr. V. A. Cerny, and librarian, M. J. M. Mrazek. The gentlemen named represent the following art divisions: literary, productive, dramatic, musical, and architectural.</p>
   <p>The next meeting will be held Wednesday February 9, and will commence the fifth <pb facs="5418478_3_0626.jpg" n="3"/>year of the club's activity. The participation of all members in the next meeting is greatly desired.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
