<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-12-05">Dec. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Round an Important Anniversary</title><title level="a" type="sub">History of the Cesky Delnicky Pevecky Sbor whose Anniversary Celebration is Being Prepared</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0932</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0932.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-12-05">Dec. 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ROUND AN IMPORTANT ANNIVERSARY</title><title level="a" type="sub">History of the Cesky Delnicky Pevecky Sbor whose Anniversary Celebration is Being Prepared</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The convention of Bohemian workingmen held in Chicago October 2, 3, and 4, 1890, recommended, as one among the measures for publicity and propaganda, the founding of singing societies. Attempts to organize such societies had been made before but, due to unfavorable conditions, had not been successful.</p>
   <p>Realizing that times were getting better and aware of the definite need, the Cesky Delnicky Vzdelavaci Spolek (Bohemian Workingmen's Educational Association) agreed in its meeting of October 11, 1890, to repeat the effort to found a singing society. Citizens Jos. Hosek and Jos. Hrusa were put in charge of this effort. They called a meeting of music-loving countrymen for December 14, 1890. It resulted in the foundation of a body to which the name "Cesky Delnicky Pevecky Sbor" (Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society) was given and which, at that meeting, secured twenty-two members. After the necessary committees had <pb facs="5418478_3_0933.jpg" n="2"/>been appointed, a meeting was held December 19, 1890, in which the following officers were elected: President, Jos. Hrusa; Vice-President, Tom. Motys; Secretary, Jos. Malinsky; Financial Secretary, Vac. Schaufel; Treasurer, Jan Miller; Conductor, Jan Simonek; Assistant Conductor, Fr. Krumpos; Librarian, Jos. Hosek.</p>
   <p>Without delay, the hall of Mr. Ant. Belsky at the corner of 18th and Laflin Streets was engaged for every Friday night for practicing. There the Sbor did its rehearsing and put on occasional modest entertainments up to the year of 1902, when it moved to its own building on Ashland Avenue.</p>
   <p>The singing practice started January 2, 1891, and on March 14 of the same year, the Sbor made a successful public appearance at the entertainment "Paris Commune" [sic] in Hoerber's Hall. Since then, the Cesky Delnicky Pevecky Sbor has been active in all national or workingmen's affairs, and has always been not only willing but glad to help in connection with activities for the benefit of needy countrymen, both here and abroad.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0934.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Sbor held its first big concert in the hall of the Cesko-Anglicka Svobodna Skola (Bohemian-English Free Thought School) January 17, 1892, when it sang before a large audience. The gross receipts amounted to $304.01, and expenses to $154.90, leaving a net of $149.11--a most respectable amount as well as a very encouraging beginning. Similar concerts were put on every year, and the Sbor always tried to present compositions of true value, sung as well as the Sbor possibly could. It sang in connection with the presentation of the operetta "Boccaccio" at the world's fairs in Chicago and St. Louis, in the great concert in the Coliseum, where Mrs. Maturova [Translators note: a noted member of the Narodni Divadlo (National Theatre) in Prague] sang, and in Dvorak's "Stabat Mater".</p>
   <p>Ever since the beginning, the Sbor has been interested in song-loving youth, and it founded, upon the initiative of Joseph Hrusa, a singing and violin school for Bohemian boys and girls which in later years became very successful. The school was started in the fall of the year of 1898, when one hundred and twenty pupils were enrolled, which number soon grew to two hundred.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0935.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>To keep the school going has required considerable financial sacrifices on the part of the Sbor. However, in this it was not alone. It was supported by many generous lovers of song and music....</p>
   <p>The graduates of the school organized, in August, 1901, the Pevecky Sbor Maj (Maj Singing Society).....</p>
   <p>January 15, 1905, the Sbor was strengthened by a merger with the Pevecky Sbor Hlahol. At that time also the popular Ceske Kvarteto....made its beginning.....</p>
   <p>The membership of the Sbor, though opinions in it may frequently have varied, has worked ever since its beginning up to the present day for the good of the body.....</p>
   <p>The first conductor of the Society, as mentioned before, was Jos. Simonek. He pulled the Sbor through difficult beginnings....resigning in 1897 because of <pb facs="5418478_3_0936.jpg" n="5"/>illness. He was followed by Jan Kalas, who led the Sbor until 1907, and who brought both the Sbor itself and its school to a new, high level of perfection....</p>
   <p>In regard to finances, the Sbor fared for many years the same as many other singing societies--it was glad to be able to pay its debts. When the school was founded thought was already being given to a home of its own. Concerts and public recitals were held the profits from which made the purchase of Mrs. Jirka's house on Ashland Avenue near 18th Street possible. It was bought in 1902 for six thousand dollars. Half of the price was paid in cash, and soon after the balance was also paid, so that now the property is clear of all indebtedness.....</p>
   <p>The second floor of the building of the Cesky Delnicky Pevecky Sbor consists of a meeting room and a room for rehearsals and small entertainments. The reception hall and library are on the first floor, and the basement serves as a recreation room for teachers. It also has two bowling alleys.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0937.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>In its twenty-fifth year, the Sbor has 40 active and 205 contributing members.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: List of officers and members of various committees is omitted in translation.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
