<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-18">Oct. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Bohemian-American National Theater Produces Capek's Famous Drama</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0664</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0664.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-18">Oct. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN NATIONAL THEATER PRODUCES CAPEK'S FAMOUS DRAMA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After careful preparation, and diligent study and rehearsing the Cesko-Americke Narodni Divadlo (Bohemian-American National Theater) is ready to present to the Czechoslovak theater-going public, Karel Capek's famous drama "R.U.R." (Rossum's Universal Robots). Since its premiere at the National Theater at Prague, and its triumphant reception at Brno, this pearl of dramatic creativity has now invaded every civilized country. Its recent first-class production on the American stage in New York has brought recognition to the actors and to the author by both the public and the press. It brings a feeling of happy satisfaction to us Czechs to know that even in the field of drama our comparatively little nation has thus become recognized through the work of Karel Capek, who occupies a significant position in the estimation of the American public. The Czech public of our metropolis will surely not let the opportunity go by to see this <pb facs="5418478_3_0665.jpg" n="2"/>drama played, and hear it in the original Czech--our mother tongue; this is a play which by its setting and its content goes outside the current traditions of the stage. [Here follows a description of the plot of the "R.U.R." which, being known to the American theater-going public, need not be translated.]....It is conceded that an unusual play of this kind required a special and careful preparation on the part of the actors and the management, and both of these have done justice to it. Individual roles have also been placed in the hands of competent players. The leading parts are the following: Mr. Havelka (Domino); Miss M. Kozderka (Helen Glory); Mrs. Winkler-Vodak (Nana); Mr. Krejci (Alquist); Mr. Skalicky (Dr. Gall); Mr. Mikolas (Hallemcier); the newly engaged actor, Mr. Anton (Fabry). Other roles have been assigned to: Miss Kostrbaty, Mr. Vanek, Mr. Saranek, Mr. Zavrel, and Mr. Zanda. Original costumes have been designed by Professor Sneiberk, managing director of the Narodni Divadlo at Brno, Czechoslovakia, and executed by Mrs. Slavka Krejci of Chicago. The modern stage setting has been furnished by The Sheppard Studio. The <pb facs="5418478_3_0666.jpg" n="3"/>musical melodramatic interludes have been studied and directed by the orchestra leader, Mr. [Frantisek] Fiser.</p>
   <p>Because of the increased demand for seats on the part of those who wish to see the play, we advise the public to secure tickets well in advance by phoning Lawndale 0485, or by purchasing them at the [usual] places.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
