<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-01">Nov. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A Convention of the Ceska Ustredni Pevecka Jednota</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0938</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0938.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-01">Nov. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">A CONVENTION OF THE CESKA USTREDNI PEVECKA JEDNOTA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This years' convention of the Ceska Ustredni Pevecka Jednota (Federation of Bohemian Singing Societies), one of our foremost national singing organizations, one which has accomplished such a great deal in our national and cultural life, and which no doubt will find proper recognition not only in Bohemian Chicago but all Bohemian America, opened yesterday at 2 P.M. in the hall of Mr. A. Francik on West 22nd Street and Sawyer Avenue.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Anton Vanek, who was unanimously elected convention chairman, welcomed the twenty-four delegates representing the following eight Bohemian singing societies: the Cesky Pevecky Sbor (Bohemian Singing Society) Lyra, the Delnicky Pevecky Sbor (Workingmen's Singing Society), the Dalibor, the Volnost, the Marx, Bendl, Maj, Zora.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0939.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Secretary Koks read a very comprehensive report on the activities of the Pevecka Jednota during the past year.....</p>
   <p>Treasurer Vanek presented the financial report, which showed the total income of the Jednota, $694.06, and expenses, $198.57, leaving a net balance of $495.49 deposited in the Lawndale State Bank. In addition to this the Jednota has lent some money to some individual societies, to wit: $200 to the Cesky Delnicky Sbor, and $25 to Dalibor. Thus, if the travel fund, amounting to $22, and the library of music, the value of which is over $1,000, are added, the assets of the Jednota amount to $1,742.49.</p>
   <p>The librarian reported that a number of valuable volumes have recently been acquired, of which Rud. Vohanka's oratorio "Jan Hus" (John Huss), merits special mention.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
