<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-03-19">Mar. 19, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">For the Bohemian Old People's Home</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1030</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1030.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-03-19">Mar. 19, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE BOHEMIAN OLD PEOPLE'S HOME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Art and charity joined hands last evening at the music festival for the benefit of the poor in the Pilsen Sokol Hall.</p>
   <p>Several gatherings of this type will not only assure the survival of our [Bohemian] charitable institutions but will also gain the interest of select groups of Bohemians.</p>
   <p>A large hall was used for this occasion in anticipation of a large attendance, but even this proved far too small for the crowd.</p>
   <p>The hall was filled to capacity, but more and more kept arriving, causing a problem for the reception committee, which was trying hard to accommodate everyone.</p>
   <p>All previous records of attendance at festivals of this nature were shattered.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1031.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>This was due partly to the rich program in store but more to the presence of Marie Ziegler, a visiting Bohemian opera star from Prague, Czechoslovakia, who participated in the program. Her presence made possible the success and the drawing power of this festival, which could not be duplicated or equalled by any one in any way. Mme. Ziegler must also receive the credit for the financial success of this festival, the profit of which will be given to the charitable institutions. The proceeds plus the contributions added by clubs and private individuals amounted to several hundred dollars.</p>
   <p>The program was very well conducted and held the attention of the audience from start to finish. The majority of the numbers were performed by artists who know how to attract and to please their audiences. They all contributed their time and talent to this worthy cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
