<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-09-29">Sept. 29, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Bazaar.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Grand Opening of Well Stocked Store at Noon To-day.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0292</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0292.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1906-09-29">Sept. 29, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN BAZAAR.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Grand Opening of Well Stocked Store at Noon To-day.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1.--Bohemian Chicago, rich in variety of social recreation, in nationalistic and benevolent organizations, has, in the past year, made progress in the economic field which will represent our people in a notable manner before the American public and contribute effectively to our national community. The Bohemian Bazaar, in which are associated a number of our countrymen, to-day will open its richly stocked store, located at the corner of Twenty-second street and Kedzie avenue, which promises the shareholders large financial rewards, especially if it is managed by experienced men. The store, in which is found more than $30,000 worth of general household merchandise, is a warehouse for products of fine quality, and excellent service is provided by employees of the establishment who have had a great deal of experience in their lines.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0293.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Because of the impossibility of finding an experienced Bohemian, the general management of the entire business was entrusted to a non-Bohemian, Mr. H. E. Shean, who has held responsible positions with the foremost department stores of Chicago. Mr. F. Schroeder, who worked most effectively for the organization of the Bazaar, was placed in charge of the clothing department, and Mr. Aug. J. Hubek has charge of the shoe section. More than sixty persons, most of whom are Bohemians, are engaged in the business.</p>
   <p>The store was open for inspection yesterday to numerous visitors, however, beginning at noon to-day. Sales will be made in all departments.</p>
   <p>Our countrymen living on the southwest side will have an excellent opportunity to buy their necessities in a genuine Bohemian enterprise, which was founded by the people--for the people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
