<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-15">May 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">An Open Letter to the Chicago United Czeoh Singing Societies</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0909</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0909.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-05-15">May 15, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AN OPEN LETTER TO THE CHICAGO UNITED CZEOH SINGING SOCIETIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>...."During recent years Czech singing societies have begun to exist is name only. It is not my intention to slight the work done by various arranging committees....but I am unable to restrain a smile whenever I hear the words 'singing societies' mentioned. A few recollections on the part of the readers will explain my attitude....The present stagnation in the singing societies is due partially to the indifference of the general public.</p>
   <p>In the contest arranged for the various singing societies in the Coliseum five years ago, only the Swedes and the Czechs participated; at the concert given by the latter there was present hardly one per cent of native Americans <pb facs="5418478_3_0910.jpg" n="2"/>among an audience of over six thousand! Four years ago, a concert was given in Grant Park for the benefit of our Sokol gymnastic societies. Antonín Dvorak's oratorium "Stabat Mater" was presented there by members of the Czech singing societies, who, however, had never sung it for the general American public. Yet the Americans learned to know that work, not from a performance by Czech singers, the logical interpreters, but by American singing societies! Is there not a fair degree of irony in this situation?</p>
   <p>Years ago Czech song was effectively presented by the Smetana Society. I mean literally 'years ago,' for what this society attempts to achieve today, although its efforts are praiseworthy exceeds its strength; it fares no better than the United Czech Singing Societies....and so it appears that we lack the courage to stand on our own feet and to perform as an independent group. The appearance of the Český Dĕlnický Spĕvácký Spolek (Czech Workingmen's Singing Society) before the City Press Club was an isolated incident, and those singers now seem to be <pb facs="5418478_3_0911.jpg" n="3"/>resting on their laurels."</p>
   <p>....It is suggested that, if the Czech singing societies fear to risk a performance before the American public, they might attempt to gain the support of some large American musical body, e.g., the Chicago Symphony Orchestra. Dvořák's composition "The American Banner" would be a highly appropriate work to perform, both for its intrinsic musical value and in view of the present critical situation.......</p>
   <p>"Favoritism seems to have played some part in the selection of compositions for performance by American musical organizations. I shall not attempt to estimate the number of worthless compositions that have found their way upon our concert platforms. Dvořák does not need this sort of boost, and Mr. Frederick Stock, the conductor, will certainly be responsive to suggestions.....,so that a performance of "The American Banner" by Czech singers with the Symphony Orchestra may materialize.......</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0912.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This would introduce us to the broad masses of the American musical public who, as yet are strangers.</p>
   <p>But let us not lose sight of the prestige that would result from having sung under the baton of the conductor of one of the foremost orchestras of the world. Moral satisfaction would come from having fulfilled our duty. At the same time, the perfromance would acquaint the American public with a musical form that is less known here. The financial success of such a concert would be assured. Last but not least, the enterprise would act as a much-needed stimulus for the future activities of the Chicago Czech singing societies. The United Czech Singing Societies ought to give it due consideration.</p>
   <p>(Signed) Bendlák</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
