<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-07-20">July 20, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Prize Contest of the Pilsen Brewing Company</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-07-20">July 20, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">PRIZE CONTEST OF THE PILSEN BREWING COMPANY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The balloting in the prize contest of the Pilsen Brewing Company ended July 5 at 9 P. M. The ballots were sealed at the American State Bank in the presence of representatives of the Ceska Utulna A Sirotcinec (Bohemian Old People's Home and Orphanage), the Sirotcinec Sv. Josefa (St. Joseph's Orphanage), Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association), the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice (Bohemian-American Hospital), and Mr. Frank J. Nedbal, a representative of the Pilsen Brewing Company. The ballots were then brought to the offices of the Pilsen Brewery for counting.</p>
   <p>The Ceska Utulna A Sirotcinec received 16,199 votes; the Sirotcinec Sv. Josefa, 21,144; the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost, 6,649; and the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice, 37,520. Altogether 82,739 ballots were received, of which 1,227 were void.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0200.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first prize of $300 was awarded to the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice, the second prize of $200 to the Sirotcinec Sv. Josefa, the third prize of $100 to the Ceska Utulna A Sirotcinec, and the fourth prize of $50 to the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost.</p>
   <p>The first prize of $25 to individuals for the largest number of ballots for the Ceska Utulna A Sirotcinec went to Mr. Wm. Ferd of 2949 South 40th Avenue for 729 votes; the second prize, $15,to Mr. Vaclav Svejda of 2230 South Albany Avenue for 526 votes; and the third prize, $10,to Mr. Alois Hauzer of 1900 Allport Street for 525 votes.</p>
   <p>To voters for the Sirotcinec Sv. Josefa, the following prizes were awarded: Mr. Fr. Cicha of 2552 South Albany Avenue, a prize of $25 for 1,342 votes; Mr. Jan Kreisl of 5138 South Robey Street, $15 for 1,032 votes; Mr. Ig. Turek of 900 North Western Avenue, $10 for 1,015 votes.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0201.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>To voters for the Cesko-Americka Nemocnice, the first prize of $25 went to Mr. Wm Decauer of 3001 South Central Park Avenue for 1,874 votes; the second prize of $15 to Mr. Adolf Hrusa of 2836 West 21st Street for 1,658 votes; the third prize of $10 to Mr. F. G. Chaloupka of 2040 West 19th Street for 1,341 votes.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Evidently the Cesky Narodni Hrbitov refused to participate in the contest, but no notice to this effect could be found in the paper.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
