<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-19">Sept. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">News of the Frank Ludvik Dramatic Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0674</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0674.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-19">Sept. 19, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS OF THE FRANK LUDVIK DRAMATIC ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Ludvikovo Divadlo (Frank Ludvik Dramatic Association) opened its thirtieth theater season by producing the patriotic play, "Vlastencove z Boudy" (Shanty Patriots), on the Sokol Chicago stage. This number was adapted to stage use from J. J. Stankovsky's novel bearing the same name. It is one of Stankovsky's most valuable literary works, picturing the humble beginnings of the Czech stage at a time when the first theatrical performances were given in a poorly built wooden structure called a "shanty". The stage adaptation was made by Mr. J. Kubik and Mrs. D. Hall. In it appear several founders and builders of the Bohemian stage, the foremost of whom was Vaclav Tham, a novelist and actor whose romantic career is much better portrayed in Alois Jirasek's work about the years of our national awakening--the "F. L. Vek". The other interesting but less known figure is the stage director and actor, Brumian, besides whom there appear a number of the chief <pb facs="5418478_3_0675.jpg" n="2"/>characters, all taken from Jirasek's novel. The play, however, lacks much that gave charm to the novel. Neither the comical figures nor the very fine songs are able to cover up the deficiencies of the play if it is regarded from a purely dramatic standpoint.</p>
   <p>In spite of these deficiencies, however, the play was enjoyed by the audience which loudly applauded the patriotic utterances and songs of Miss Zdenek, Mrs. Ludvik, and Messrs. Prokop, Wagner, and Bezdek.</p>
   <p>The novelty was staged by the very able manager, Mrs. B. Ludvik, and distinguished itself by its exemplary teamwork and by its close characterization of the main individuals playing the title roles. This was particularly true of Mr. Prokop as "Tham" and Mr. Horlivy as "Brunian". Their acting was true to life and very effective.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
