<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-12-08">Dec. 8, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Have Our Own Music</title><title level="a" type="sub">Comments on the Program of Today's Concert of the Český Dĕlnický Pĕvecký Sbor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0478</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0478.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1912-12-08">Dec. 8, 1912</date>.
<title level="a">LET US HAVE OUR OWN MUSIC</title><title level="a" type="sub">Comments on the Program of Today's Concert of the Český Dĕlnický Pĕvecký Sbor</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The concert of the Český Dĕlnický Pĕvecký Sbor (Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society), the program of which has been selected with unusual care and there-fore is up to the highest musical requirements and standards, will take place in the hall of Sokol Chicago on Kedzie Avenue today. For that reason we hope that the concert, which starts at 2:30 P. M., will enjoy an excellent attendance. The director of the chorus is Mr. Viktor Liška, and the piano accompanist is Mr. A. V. Černý.</p>
   <p>The raison d'etre for Bohemian singing societies is the cultivation of Bohemian music. This also applies to all concerts and other public appearances of all allied Bohemian groups and associations. Programs patched together with the various "Lucias" and "Trovatores," must finally disappear forever from Bohemian concerts if we want to progress. Just for this particular <pb facs="5418478_3_0479.jpg" n="2"/>reason we welcome the program of the Sunday concert of the Český Dĕlnický Pĕvecký Sbor as an exemplary one.</p>
   <p>This being a concert of Bohemian music, it is only natural that its principal selections are from Smetana and Dvořák, to which a few compositions by other composers have been added.</p>
   <p>The program will start with "Utonulá" (The Drowned One) by Pavel Křížkovský....Křížkovský's work is the culmination of the pre-Smetana period--a period of preparation for modern Bohemian music, whose creator is Smetana. Křížkovský's great choral compositions still retain their full freshness and will always retain their value and effectiveness. "Utonulá" is based on an old Moravian folk song....and was presented for the first time in Brno on December 4, 1860.....</p>
   <p>The concluding number on the program will be Smetana's chorus, "Tři Jezdci" (Three Horsemen). We have made a jump from the opening number to the last <pb facs="5418478_3_0480.jpg" n="3"/>number of the program for historical reasons: Smetana wrote this chorus under the influence of "Utonulá". "Tři Jezdci" is Smetana's first choral composition, but the critics now give it a prominent place among his works. It is full of passionate emotion, and without a doubt, it is much better than his well-known "Vĕno" (Dower). Written in 1862, its first public presentation took place February 27, 1863 in Prague. It is based on a poem describing the historical ride of three Bohemian noblemen to Constance on a mission for King Wenceslaus IV in 1414....</p>
   <p>Between these two numbers, there will be seven compositions, including the sextet from B. Smetana's "Bartered Bride" in choral form by Novotný, and the aria "Noc Je Tichá" (The Night Is Still) from Smetana's opera, "Braniboři v Čechách" (The Brandenburgers in Bohemia). These two will be sung by the Bohemian-American Octet. The Démsky Pĕvecký Sbor Máj (Ladies Singing Society May) will sing Málat's "Zpĕvy Lidu Českĕho" (Bohemian People's Songs).....</p>
   <p>There will be two selections for solo voices. Mr. Liška will present....an aria from Dvořák's first opera, "Jakobín" (Jacobin), first performed in <pb facs="5418478_3_0481.jpg" n="4"/>Prague on February 9, 1889.....Messrs. Malík and Glaas will present a duet from Smetana's opera, "Hubicka" (A Kiss), first performed in Prague on November 7, 1876.....</p>
   <p>Chamber music will be represented by two selections, Kassmeyer's "České Písnĕ" (Bohemian Songs) and B. Smetana's "Z Mého Života" (From My Life). Both are quartets of very unusual musical beauty.....</p>
   <p>Those of you who love Bohemian music should come to the concert of the Český Dĕlnický Pĕvecký Sbor today.</p>
   <p>Signed: Česko-Americká Tiskova Kancelář</p>
   <p>(Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
