<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-30">Sept. 30, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">From the Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0073</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0073.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-09-30">Sept. 30, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE CZECHOSLOVAK CHAMBER OF COMMERCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce held a special meeting under the chairmanship of Mr. K. V. Janovsky in order to receive the reports of members who have lately returned from the old country.</p>
   <p>The first among them was Consul J. F. Smetanka who talked about conditions in Czechoslovakia. He said that things are looking up in the old country, that conditions are getting better from day to day, and that a splendid future for our Republic is assured.</p>
   <p>Also Banker Frank G. Hajicek said that he was surprised with the progress of the Czechoslovak Republic, and similar impressions were expressed by Dr. Joseph P. Pecival.</p>
   <p>Mr. Laadt recommended that the Chamber continue to enlarge the scope of its work and, if it should prove to be necessary, to impose higher membership dues <pb facs="5418478_3_0074.jpg" n="2"/>so that a fund for the upkeep of a permanent office may be raised. Messrs. Turek, Jalovec, John A. Sokol, and others proposed that meetings with an educational program be held and made accessible to the general public. These would be the best means to make our people acquainted with the aims and activities of the Chamber of Commerce. The exchange of opinions which followed resulted in a decision to hold a public meeting October 14, and the committee on arrangements reported later on that the dining room of the Pilsen pavilion had been secured for that meeting.</p>
   <p>It was further agreed to compile a directory of all Czechoslovak business and industrial men in the United States, a proposal which received the sanction of the commercial department of the Czechoslovak Legation in Washington, which promised to co-operate in the undertaking. A committee was appointed consisting of Messrs. Louis Jalovec, Arthur Y. Huysler, and S. K. Turek to take charge of this matter and to begin at once collecting the data for the directory. The editorial work on the directory will be done by Mr. V. Hnatek. Czechoslovak business and industrial men will help the progress of the work by sending <pb facs="5418478_3_0075.jpg" n="3"/>their names to Mr. Hnatek at 2533 South Springfield Avenue, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
