<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1900-02-08">Feb. 8, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Stockholders Act in Nick of Time.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0334</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0334.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1900-02-08">Feb. 8, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">STOCKHOLDERS ACT IN NICK OF TIME.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.. Mr. Josef Vrba, general manager of the Hudson Coal Co., a Bohemian-American owned concern, left for Farmersburg, Ind., the coal mine district, last night with a genuine smile on his face; he had money on him, enough to satisfy the most pressing demands, as e. g., those of the constable, who was about to confiscate some implements for the payment of debts incurred for powder, taxes and rents. This was of paramount importance to avert imminent bankruptcy, and was made possible by a committee of four, appointed in last Friday's meeting, which has been successful in raising the necessary funds. How big these are, and how great the sacrifices of the contributors, we have been unable to find out, but the amount in question must have touched the $10,000 figure, or the rescue from impending disaster could not have been effected.</p>
   <p>Today, therefore, work in the mines will be resumed, and the gentlemen stock-owners can breathe a sigh of relief, for the worst has passed. They have gone through a severe ordeal; the fate of their company hung on a very thin thread with a possibility of its rupture at any instant. We are not attempting to teach the directors, however, in mentioning that the Roth mortgage seems to us to be a heavy burden on the finances, and a constant menace to <pb facs="5418478_3_0335.jpg" n="2"/>the very existence of the company. As long as that pernicious liability is not thrown off there is scant hope for the stockholders' ever drawing any dividends.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
