<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-01-21">Jan. 21, 1903</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">New Teacher of Violin Music</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0551</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0551.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-01-21">Jan. 21, 1903</date>, p. 1
<title level="a">NEW TEACHER OF VIOLIN MUSIC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mrs. Augusta Vitak, a country woman, until recently a resident of Canton, Ohio, where her husband Mr. Louis Vitak, had a wholesale business in musical instruments, has now located in Chicago. She has decided to act as a teacher of the violin. The decision of this well known violin virtuoso, offers Bohemian parents a rare opportunity to have their children taught the violin with certainty of success, because of Mrs. Vitak's successful teaching career in the Old-Country.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Augusta Vitak has studied the violin since her eigth year. After five years devoted to the art, the celebrated Bohemian master Frant. Ondricek heard her and recognizing her talent, insistently urged her to continue her studies. As a young girl Mrs. Vitak went to Prague, where she studied under the direction of professor Bennewitz. Later, after a successful concert tour throughout Europe, she completed her studies with the Stuttgart teacher of violin, E. Singer.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0552.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Returning to Prague she became a successful teacher of the violin, and among her pupils, gave Master Kubelik his preparatory education for the conservatory. In the year 1893, she married Mr. Vitak and immigrated to Canton, Ohio. Her meeting with Kubelik was particularly touching, and became an important topic of discussion at the time.- This new teacher of the violin will open her school of music in the Fine Arts Building on Michigan Ave., and applications of pupils will be accepted in the office of her husband Mr. Vitak, at 204 S. Wabash Ave. Bohemian parents are again urged to take advantage of this rare opportunity to have their children taught violin by this teacher, whose artistry, and thorough musical education guarantee success,</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
