<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-11-12">Nov. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Dignified Representation Assured</title><title level="a" type="sub">Rehearsal of Program for Czech Day at University of Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1454</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1454.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-11-12">Nov. 12, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A DIGNIFIED REPRESENTATION ASSURED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Rehearsal of Program for Czech Day at University of Chicago</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of the largest halls of the University of Chicago will be the location of an exhibition and the scene of performances on the occasion of Czech Day, which opens next Wednesday. This event will afford Americans a survey of our cultural maturity; it is the direct result of a conference held between Chicago Czech leaders and professors of the University headed by President Harry Pratt Judson. The obvious objective of this event is to make native Americans acquainted with the cultural achievements of Czechs and Slovaks. Ample seating accommodations will be reserved for the native American visitors, and for this reason only those Czechs and Slovaks directly connected with the exhibition and the performers will be admitted on the University premises.</p>
   <p>In order to give our people an opportunity to view what will be presented to <pb facs="5418478_3_1455.jpg" n="2"/>a select public at the University, a preliminary performance was arranged in the center of our settlement yesterday afternoon, in the auditorium of Sokol Chicago, South Kedzie Avenue and 24th Street. It was a sort of overture to Czech Day. The response by our public was overwhelming; the hall was filled to capacity.</p>
   <p>Antonin Dvorak's cantata, "The American Flag," was the first number on the program. It was sung by one hundred and twenty-five members of the Ceska Ustredni Pevecka Jednota (Federation of Bohemian Singing Societies), under the baton of Mr. Joseph Houdek. This musical piece offers great difficulties, so that prior to yesterday's performance none of our singing societies had ventured to approach it. The brilliancy with which it was rendered is a credit to the untiring zeal which Mr. Houdek evinced during the rehearsals. Mr. Richard Adamira and Mr. Hurt excelled in the main solo parts.</p>
   <p>When the curtain was raised the second time, there were twenty-five girls in Sokol attire upon the stage. They were members of various groups of our Sokol societies. Some of their performances of light athletics were repetitions <pb facs="5418478_3_1456.jpg" n="3"/>of an exhibition at the Sixth Sokol Rally held in Prague, capital of Bohemia, in the year 1892. The display was directed by Jarka Kosar, well-known worker in Sokol circles, while Miss Kamila Cermak played the piano. If this number goes off at the University as smoothly as it did yesterday afternoon, we are certain that our Sokol organizations will fulfill their mission before the American public.</p>
   <p>The girls' performance was followed by one given by twenty male Sokol members. It was a pleasure to observe their broad chests and sinewy arms, which seemed to be built of rock. They gave vivid testimony to the perfection of the system used by Sokols in body culture. One of their drills suffered somewhat by the impatience of some of the boys. The effect in general, however, was highly gratifying, and there is no need to mention that thunderous applause rewarded the young athletes. Jarka Kosar was again the director.</p>
   <p>Professor Jaroslav J. Zmrhal, the speaker of the afternoon, declared that since the United States has always stood in the foreground whenever the right to liberty of small nations was to be upheld, the present sympathies of this <pb facs="5418478_3_1457.jpg" n="4"/>country also go to the Czechoslovaks struggling for freedom. The American public, he repeated, is well informed on Czechoslovak aspirations and takes a friendly attitude towards them. But we should not appear before the American forum only with our woes and complaints. It will also be necessary to attest to our strength and our cultural maturity. The former is demonstrated by our volunteers who enthusiastically join the Allied and the United States Armies. The latter must be brought into the limelight on occasions like Czech Day at the University of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Czech Day, the professor continued, will be a first attempt, or rather the first of a series of efforts, to promote information among the American intelligentsia. We shall have to work persistently in this direction throughout the future.</p>
   <p>The speaker closed by expressing his gratitude to all those who gave their time and energy and helped in any possible manner to make the exposition and performances an accomplished success. He particularly thanked the singers, the Sokols, and our brothers, the Slovaks.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1458.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The performance of the Slovak Educational Club was one of the high points of the event.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
