<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-27">Sept. 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The Last Day of the Bazar Svobody</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1337</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1337.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>IV (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-09-27">Sept. 27, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE LAST DAY OF THE BAZAR SVOBODY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our boys of the local Czechoslovak legionnaire groups, on many occasions, had convinced themselves that they enjoyed the confidence and favors of our people. This had been proved by the large attendance at every project so far undertaken by them. The same has been proved again, this time by the greatest project undertaken by our legionnaires--the Bazar Svobody (Liberty Bazaar)--by which our boys submitted themselves, in a certain sense, to the test of public opinion. The Bazar Svobody really was such a test. From Wednesday until last night our people have been voicing their opinions, and they finally have spoken out in such manner that, although it will be vexatious for somebody, it will encourage our boys to further work, which, if crowned with the same success, will bring the utmost satisfaction to our legionnaires.</p>
   <p>This last Bazar Svobody has brought just such satisfaction to them today. According to the results, the people are apparently backing our boys. Our people offered not only their moral support in this project, but also--and this <pb facs="5418478_3_1338.jpg" n="2"/>is the most important thing--they gave financial support which will be a great help to the widows and orphans of our fallen legionnaires who at present are suffering in Czechoslovakia. Just how large this assistance will be is impossible to state today. But it may be said now that it will be much larger than anybody had ever expected. An accurate statement of the total proceeds will not be available for several days until all the bills are audited. Temporarily we can say that the total proceeds will exceed the sum of fifteen thousand dollars.</p>
   <p>Yesterday was the final day of the bazaar and therefore one of the most successful. Notwithstanding the fact that yesterday was a torrid day with threatening storm clouds, throngs of people gathered in Pilsen Park in the early hours of the afternoon.</p>
   <p>At the same time, still greater throngs of people assembled in front of the Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs Hall and formed a gigantic parade which started to move for-ward at about 2 P. M. The parade was headed by a strong detail of mounted police, followed by the mounted marshal of the parade, Mr. Goldstein, a colonel <pb facs="5418478_3_1339.jpg" n="3"/>of the regular United States Army. To the tune of brisk marches by Mr. Rudolph Rubringer's band, the various sections of the parade marched by, stirring the enthusiasm of the great throngs of people who crowded the sidewalks of every street through which the parade passed. Our legionnaires, of course, were strongly represented and were greeted with real joy. They were accompanied by three allegorical floats portraying "War and Mobilization," "Our Soldiers at All Battlefronts," and "Captivity and Final Liberation". Besides this they also had with them a mounted machine gun. It also deserves mention that even a battle tank was to be seen at the head of the parade.</p>
   <p>The legionnaires were followed by veterans, of whom two Civil War veterans, Messrs. William Kaspar and Stejskal, drew the greatest attention. Fairly represented also were the veterans of the Spanish-American War and American legionnaires of the World War. Ladies of the Bohemian section of the American Red Cross marched in blue uniforms with white caps. Strongly represented were the Sokols of the Central District of the Bohemian-American Sokol Union, dressed in their uniforms. Further, we saw among the marchers many of our benevolent societies, organizations, and various clubs, which would take too much space to mention individually.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1340.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The parade moved south to 27th Street, west to Crawford Avenue, north to 26th Street, east to Albany Avenue, and finally, at about 3 P. M., to Pilsen Park. At the Park all the marchers came to a halt before the main pavilion and listened to the strains of the American, Bohemian, and Slovak national anthems....</p>
   <p>The popularity contest aroused a great deal of interest among our people, as it is apparent from the number of votes given to individual politicians. Democrats received the following number of votes: John A. Cervenka, 82,055; John Toman, 21,210; Anton J. Cermak, 20,860; Michal Rosenberg, 8,750; Joseph Placek, 1,260; Adolph J. Sabath, 1,240; John McAndrews, 640; and J. W. Rainey, 560. Republicans: Joseph Z. Klenha, mayor of Cicero, 15,140; Frank Houcek, town clerk of Cicero, 7,000; August W. Miller of Chicago, 1,750; Eugene Debs, a Socialist, received 5,790 votes; and Mr. Frantisek Urban, who ran independently, received 25,380 votes. When the result of the contest was publicly announced, Mr. Frana Klepal called Mr. John A. Cervenka to the stage and decorated his breast with a gold star set with a ruby. Mr. Cervenka thanked the audience and assured them that this recognition given to him will force him to still greater <pb facs="5418478_3_1341.jpg" n="5"/>efforts for the benefit of the legionnaires and for the whole Czechoslovak nation. Messrs. Klenha and Urban each received a gold star also. The announcement that a gold star will be sent to Mr. Debs, a Socialist, aroused great enthusiasm among the people.....</p>
   <p>Yesterday's attendance at the bazaar was colossal and did not dwindle even when threatening clouds appeared overhead and several squalls passed over.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
