<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1909-02-02">Feb. 2, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Create the Amateur Actors' Union.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1198</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1198.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1909-02-02">Feb. 2, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">CREATE THE AMATEUR ACTORS' UNION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 12--When the Chicago Bohemian amateur-actors recently commemorated the hundredth birthday of Joseph Kajetan Tyl, the founder of Bohemian literature, they unanimously expressed their opinion, that the celebration should be the impulse to new and organized activities for the perpetuation of the name of the great Czech, and also to instill into their work the ardor of former times.</p>
   <p>It was suggested to unite the amateurs into a solid organization, first in Chicago, and gradually to propagate the idea among the Bohemians of the whole country.</p>
   <p>The respective appeals we had made before proved not in vain, and we are glad to announce that an unification is anticipated in the near future.</p>
   <p>The time-honored association "Ochotnici Slovanske Lipy," has undertaken the task of centralizing the diverse groups of amateurs.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1199.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These pioneers of Bohemian amateurdom met Sunday in their old home on De Koven street and after a chat about former times of theatrical life, settled down to ponder over the means for the recuperation of their art which admittedly is not prospering now as it had in former years.</p>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Jurka, one of the oldest amateurs, spoke words as can only he who has known the Bohemian stage thoroughly, and who firmly believes that the theatre is the mainstay of Bohemian national sentiment.</p>
   <p>After the discussion Mr. Kapsa was elected chairman, Mr. Jos. Lang, secretary, and Mrs. Ant. Cervenka, treasurer. First consideration was given to the question of how to keep the cash box of the amateur organization from being perpetually empty. It was pointed out that the actors very often forgot their own needs while devoting their time and labor to the entertainment of others. It has happened that when one from their ranks was called into the great unknown there was not money enough left to put a note of condolence into the newspapers, to buy flowers for the dear departed colleague, or to pay for the most primitive burial.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1200.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It was decided to arrange a performance for which the Sokol-organization would furnish the hall in the Slovanska Lipa rent free. Then Mr. Horacek proposed the creation of an amateur-union and all those present agreed upon its absolute necessity if amateur-acting is not to be doomed to gradual but certain disintegration.</p>
   <p>A committee of three is to select amateurs for the formation of a body of actors worthy to represent the new union.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
