<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-08-11">Aug. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A Conscientious Worker</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-08-11">Aug. 11, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">A CONSCIENTIOUS WORKER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are not too many citizens of Chicago who can boast of a record in private as well as in public life that is without the slightest blemish..... Our Czech community in Chicago possesses men like these, and is justly proud of them. Our Czech community knows these men, and it also knows that Joseph I. Novák is one of them.</p>
   <p>Mr. Novak was born in Chicago in 1877, born of parents who had had a hard start in life before they attained any comparative degree of prosperity. They saw to it that their son received a good education, not only in public schools, but also in the college, which at that time was known by the name of Westside Business College. The young man had early evidenced a liking for matters of commerce. He dealt in various commodities, such as coal, hay, and grain. He even ventured into the <pb facs="5418478_3_0141.jpg" n="2"/>restaurant business with pronounced success. He quit this branch after a time as he found that it was not conducive to a success in public life which he preferred.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Novák has always been a staunch Democrat. In the election in 1913, he won the aldermanic seat of the Twelfth Ward. Mayor Harrison recommended him for the office of a member of the Board of Local Improvements, and the City Council indorsed his choice. This was in 1915. Mr. Novak was also appointed a jury commissioner. In his capacity as alderman, he proved very helpful to his Czech-American fellow-countrymen. Though born in America, he has preserved a warm feeling for his maternal language.</p>
   <p>Mr. Novak is married and father of six children. At present, he is conducting a real estate business at 4010 West 26th Street, which he combines with insurance. He also functions as notary public. He is a member of numerous clubs and societies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
