<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-01-27">Jan. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Fiftieth Anniversary of Bohemian Amateur Theatricals in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1555</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1555.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-01-27">Jan. 27, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIFTIETH ANNIVERSARY OF BOHEMIAN AMATEUR THEATRICALS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since the days of fifty years ago when for the first time in Chicago--in March, 1863--a Bohemian theatrical performance was given on the stage, our amateurs have made an invaluable contribution to our national life and its development. Their work was particularly of great importance at the beginning of our national existence in Chicago, when Bohemian theatricals were the principal focal points of national endeavor. In those days an amateur performance was a festivity at which the first settlers assembled, exchanged ideas, experiences, and strengthened each other for the daily struggles. Today, when Bohemian Chicago has become a huge community, conditions have changed. The credit, however, which is due to Bohemian amateurs for their contribution to the development of national life in Chicago, should never be forgotten. If it were not for yesterday's meeting of the amateur actors of Slovanska Lipa (Slavonic Linden Tree), this anniversary might have been overlooked. It is generally known that Slovanska Lipa is the oldest Sokol <pb facs="5418478_3_1556.jpg" n="2"/>(Bohemian Gymnastic Association) unit in Chicago, and its hall is perhaps the only existing witness of our first efforts.....The anniversary will be properly commemorated in March with a festive performance in which the oldest amateurs of Slovanska Lipa, some of whom have been active for thirty or forty years, will take part.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
