<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-05">Sept. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Our Theatricals</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0794</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0794.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-09-05">Sept. 5, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">OUR THEATRICALS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our theatrical season is just ready to open, and there are all indications that our theater-loving public will be amply satisfied as far as its need for this kind of clean entertainment is concerned. It is certain that our three permanent theaters will open and play regularly, just as they have for the past few years. In addition, no doubt, many amateur groups will give their performances; there will be occasional plays by our youth; and thus none of our theater fans will have an opportunity to complain about a lack of variety from which to satisfy his tastes. As far as we are concerned, we wish success, prosperity, and popularity to every theatrical undertaking which takes the mission of the stage seriously.</p>
   <p>Of course, the theater is entertainment. But it is also, and perhaps primarily, an educational,cultural, and character-building institution, and it is quite <pb facs="5418478_3_0795.jpg" n="2"/>unnecessary to stress its great importance. It is not without significance that the theater is called "school of life". Particularly here in America, it has done a great deal of excellent work in the cultural aspects. The late Bittner remarked most fittingly in one of his lovable essays on amateur theatricals that the theater is one of the few places where our American-born youth has an opportunity, once in a while, to hear good Bohemian, learn something about Bohemian ways and customs, or in one word Bohemian life.</p>
   <p>But this can be applied nowadays not only to youth, but perhaps to everyone of us who has for decades followed our peculiar, different, specifically Bohemian-American life, and to whom the Bohemian customs and ways are gradually becoming foreign, forgotten, and strange. Let us just remember what a warm reception was accorded to the play "Přástky" (Spinning Bee), that little fragment of Bohemian country life.</p>
   <p>The theater, then, has its importance, its educational features, but of course, only when the proper kinds of plays are presented to the public. The role of <pb facs="5418478_3_0796.jpg" n="3"/>the theater would assume much greater importance in our life under present conditions if our various stages would always give preference to good, clean plays, and particularly to original Bohemian dramatic productions, instead of all kinds of trash with the French trade-mark which, in most cases, is not even worth translating. In this mistake we have gone to the extreme. We know, for instance, that the repertoire of one of our theaters was so full of such spicy plays that our esteemed police authorities found it advisable to honor it with a visit. A theater with such a"cultural" program just does not educate, but does debase; does not ennoble, but does degrade. A public which pays comparatively large admission fees should be entitled to expect something better for its money than vulgarity, scantily covered with a dramatic garb. But that is just one of several points that could be raised in talking about the educational values of dramatics. There are people who take their children to the theater. What an influence on children's minds such "dramatic education" can have is more than obvious. Let us hope that at least for this season, we shall be spared such "artistic productions".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
