<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-28">Feb. 28, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Second Concert of Chamber Music</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0437</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0437.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-02-28">Feb. 28, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE SECOND CONCERT OF CHAMBER MUSIC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The efforts exerted to raise chamber music to a higher level have passed the trial stage, and today there is no difficulty in getting an audience for this type of music.</p>
   <p>The best proofs of this are the concerts arranged at Stiles Hall on Millard Avenue and 22nd Street. The second concert of the season was held there yesterday, and, like the first, had an attendance which filled every seat in the hall with an audience appreciative of artistic creations.</p>
   <p>To Mr. A. V. Cerny, who figuratively is the very soul of these musical recitals, all thanks are due for his careful arrangement of the program.</p>
   <p>The audience was addressed by Dr. J. E. S. Vojan, after which the Cerny Trio, composed of violinist Mr. Eduard J. Freund, pianist Miss Florence Forst, and <pb facs="5418478_3_0438.jpg" n="2"/>cellist Mr. A. V. Cerny, presented Dvorak's piano trio in B Major, Opus 29, in which is hidden the young, but nevertheless deeply creative perception of the great Czech artist.</p>
   <p>This monumental work was written by Dvorak at the age of twenty-four, and notwithstanding the fact that this composition was announced as a novelty, this is not exactly true, for excerpts from the trio have been played here on many occasions; the entire four movements were performed at Ondrisek's concert at the Pilsen Sokol Hall on February 23, 1896, by Messrs.J. H. Capek, Jan Kalas, and the late Bohumil Holub.</p>
   <p>The Dvorak Trio was rendered brilliantly, and the artists were heartily applauded. Miss Libuse Zdenka sang Smetana's "Mekamenujte Proroky" (Do Not Stone the Prophets), Friml's "Zastavenicko" (Serenade), Vymetal's "Me Drahe Dite" (My Dear Child), and an English song, "The Old Fashioned Home," by Squire. Miss Zdenka's presentations were the best in the second and fourth numbers; Mr. Cerny was the accompanist.</p>
   <p>Trnecek's Capriccio, Opus 2, a trio, was a real gem. It was played by the</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
