<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-14">Sept. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">The Most Significant Event of the Season</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1257</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1257.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (2)</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-09-14">Sept. 14, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">THE MOST SIGNIFICANT EVENT OF THE SEASON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The times in which we live are full of surprising phenomena and events, some of which act depressingly upon the human mind while others exalt the soul. In the latter category belongs the "Staroceske Posviceni" (Old Czech Country Festival) which is a joyful and refreshing event for our entire Czech colony of Chicago.</p>
   <p>The Posviceni which was planned by the Sdruzeni Ceskych Svobodomyslnych Skol v Chicagu (Federation of Bohemian Free Thought Schools of Chicago) for the benefit of the Free Thought school system, will be held on Sunday, September 17.</p>
   <p>Many an aged Czech grandfather or grandmother looks dreamily upon the charming cover design by Mikolas Ales which we have utilized for our <pb facs="5418478_3_1258.jpg" n="2"/>publication, the Svobodna Skola (Free [Thought] School); this wistful look is accompanied by sigh when the grandad or grandmother in question tries to recollect his or her childhood. And what of our Czech schools in America, the schools which implant in the souls of our children and adolescents a feeling of respect for the nationality of their parents; schools which endeavor to sow the seeds of the highest Bohemian idealism in the hearts of children brought up in an English-speaking school?</p>
   <p>Surely everyone will find it most refreshing next Sunday to spend his time among the romping youth, to be amused by the charming folk dances, to taste the delicacies of Bohemian cooking. "O posviceni vsecko to voni" (At a country festival everything smells good [Translator's note: This is the first line of an old Czech folk song]) will be intoned by many a gourmet on this occasion when passing the booths filled with gingerbread, and others exuding the odors of smoked meats and sausages, and, finally, when he lands in the cozy dining hall [of the pavilion]. Fishermen will be given an <pb facs="5418478_3_1259.jpg" n="3"/>opportunity to fish for a small fee, and the fattest possible carps will be swimming around in the tank on this occasion.....There will be many thousands of our people who will watch the parade of our children whose procession will start at 1:30 P.M., pass over West 26th Street, and end in Pilsen Park.</p>
   <p>Nobody will regret having acted as a host to our children, but anyone who stays at home on this occasion will be sorry. Therefore, let our next rendezvous be at the Pilsen Park pavilion, Sunday, on the occasion of the Posviceni arranged by the Bohemian Free Thought school system. We know, indeed, that the joys of that day as well as the net proceeds of it will belong to those who are dearest to us--our children.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
