<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-02-06">Feb. 6, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Jaroslav Kocian and Marie Kryl Prepared a Truly Artistic Feast for the Music-Loving Public Yesterday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0501</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.K"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0501.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I K</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-02-06">Feb. 6, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">JAROSLAV KOCIAN AND MARIE KRYL PREPARED A TRULY ARTISTIC FEAST FOR THE MUSIC-LOVING PUBLIC YESTERDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's concert, given in the Pilsen Sokol hall, Ashland Avenue at 18th St., by Jaroslav Kocian, world-famous violin virtuoso and the young artist Miss Marie Kryl, who displayed such ability at the piano as to call forth admiration, met with huge success in every respect.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kocian, with his masterful artistry enraptured the public from the very moment his eloquent violin was heard in the concerto for violins in D major, op. 35 by Tschaikovsky, consisting of "Allegro Moderato," Canzoneta" and "Finale." It would be superfluous to refer to the perfection of his playing or the ease with which he governed his instrument in difficult compositions, because this is already known from his first appearance, before the Bohemian-American public, ten years ago. However it is certain that <pb facs="5418478_3_0502.jpg" n="2"/>into his concert yesterday he put all of his artistic power, strength and feeling. The "Finale" especially, affected the listeners to such a degree that at its conclusion the applause did not cease until the artist took several curtain calls.</p>
   <p>The second number of the program was a piano solo by our young artist Miss Kryl, daughter of the famous cornet virtuoso, Mr. Bohumir Kryl. She played the "Second Scherzo" in B flat minor, op. 31 by Chopin. Miss Kryl greatly surprised the audience with her performance, for hardly anyone expected such technique and absorption from such a young lady. Miss Kryl played all her selections from memory. She plays her instrument with grace and at the same time is capable of putting great feeling into her performance.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0503.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As the third number of the program, Mr. Kocian played his own picturesque composition "Humoresque," "Ach neni tu neni" by Friml and "Holku Modrookou," as arranged for violin by Prof. Sevcik, (two popular Czech folk songs). He was called back several times and finally added "Ukolebavku" by Nesvar. Another number was the "Fantasy" from Faust by Wieniawski, the performance of which was astonishing.</p>
   <p>Then he was again relieved by Miss Kryl, who played, as the fifth number of the program, "Fantasy-Impromtu," op. 66 by Chopin, a number requiring great technique; "Hraci Strojek" by Liadov, a delightful composition, into which she put a great deal of feeling. She also played "Etude V" by Paganin-Liszt, the performance of which resulted in her being called out several times, the applause continuing until she responded with "Bonne Dandy" by Willie Pape and "Blackie" by Chopin.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0504.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This grand concert was crowned in the final section of the program by Kocian playing the "Hexentanz," by Paganini and when he laid aside the bow, which he controls so beautifully that its strokes call forth admiration, a new storm of applause sounded. The audience showed no sign of being willing to depart before hearing once more the bewitching sounds of the artist's precious instrument. Mr. Kocian generously complied and played "Zefyr" by Huboy and the Spanish dance, "Zapateado," and finally that number for which everybody was waiting, "Kde domov muj?"</p>
   <p>We must admit, that Mr. Kocian made an everlasting impression upon the listeners, that yesterday's artistic feast will long be remembered and that we will await with expectancy his return to America. Miss Kryl also gained a great name through this appearance, because she proved that we have reason to look upon her as a great artist. She will surely gain world fame if she continues on this eminent road with this same success.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0505.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Mr. Kocian was accompanied by Mr. M. Eisner, who proved to be an excellent artist, for his accompaniment was faultless and combined with the violin rendition into one perfect whole.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's concert was Kocian's last one in Chicago during his present tour of America. His last American concert will be given on Thursday in St. Louis, Mo.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kocian returns to Bohemia after the St. Louis concert. It has not yet been decided if he will return to his home from St. Louis by way of New York, or whether, he will undertake the journey by way of Honolulu, Japan and Siberia. It is said that he longs to become better acquainted with the Siberian steppes. He spent about a year in Moscow and he likes Russia very much.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
