<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-02">Jan. 2, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Establishment in New Building Lawndale State Bank Starting Business Tomorrow</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, three column-quarter of a page, picture of front of building at 3205-3207 West 22nd Street.]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0176</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0176.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-02">Jan. 2, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN ESTABLISHMENT IN NEW BUILDING Lawndale State Bank Starting Business Tomorrow</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, three column-quarter of a page, picture of front of building at 3205-3207 West 22nd Street.]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lawndaleska Statni Banka (Lawndale State Bank), a well-known banking establishment doing business for many years in Ceska Californie [a Bohemian district in Chicago], is a bank which has gained such an enviable record not only among our countrymen, but also among the foreign language and American groups, that its quarters became too cramped for the amount of business transacted.</p>
   <p>Therefore, the directors, who had had in mind for some time the building of a new home to house the bank, agreed to build the new bank home, which could take care of a greater volume of business and, with its structural beauty, would be a credit to the neighborhood.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0177.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>For that reason a site was found in this locality. Immediately plans were drawn by order of the bank directors, and the many contracts for the work on the building were awarded; but the completion of the bank was delayed for almost a year on account of unforeseen conditions.</p>
   <p>The building will be opened to the public within the next few days and tomorrow, for the first time, business will be transacted in its new home.</p>
   <p>The new building of the Lawndale State Bank at 3205-3207 West 22nd Street stands on two lots, and is constructed of stone, brick, and steel.</p>
   <p>The first floor is reserved for banking business. The second floor is divided into offices, all of which are rented.</p>
   <p>Stepping through the grand entrance, we walked through bronze doors into the vestibule, which is made of marble. At both sides of this entrance <pb facs="5418478_3_0178.jpg" n="3"/>offices for the directors may be seen.</p>
   <p>From the vestibule we were able to see a large hall, fitted with a skylight. This hall is supported by pillars; between these pillars are benches, seats, and writing tables placed there for the convenience of the bank's patrons.</p>
   <p>At the sides of this hall are wings, which are divided into twelve sections.</p>
   <p>To the rear of the large hall is an enormous safe, fitted with a time clock weighing twenty-three tons. This time clock is of the self-adjusting type, and can be regulated very easily. Inside of this safe, at both sides the safety boxes can be seen, and farther to the rear there is a smaller safe which holds the daily receipts of each clerk.</p>
   <p>The main rear hall wall is fitted with a large looking glass. In the rooms <pb facs="5418478_3_0179.jpg" n="4"/>behind the last wall, the directors will hold their meetings. Near this last wall are the ladies' rest rooms and small private rooms for the bank's customers, a room reserved for bank clerks, and a dressing room.</p>
   <p>To the right of the wall are more safes for storing books and valuable papers. To the left is a large table for the telephone operator, and here also are twelve public telephones.</p>
   <p>The decorations are plastic designs, marble imitations, and mosiacs.</p>
   <p>The furniture is mahogany; the electrical lighting is indirect. The light is thrown from large rounded globes to the ceiling and then reflected downward.</p>
   <p>A combination electrical heating system has been installed, automatically controlling the heating of the building and ventilating as well. In this <pb facs="5418478_3_0180.jpg" n="5"/>respect, this system is entirely new to Bohemians.</p>
   <p>The front of the building is decorated with a clock, which will be automatically regulated with two others in the building.</p>
   <p>The cost of the building is $65,000, and it deserves to be mentioned that all the work on the building, wherever possible, was done by Bohemian contractors, or at least by Bohemian workingmen.</p>
   <p>This bank is an absolute Bohemian institution, whose leaders are the following officers: president, F. G. Hajicek; vice-presidents, J.J. Salat and J. F. Polak; cashier, J. Kopecky; assistant cashier, F.J. Krajic. The directors are: R. Dusil, R. F. Hajicek, E. Klicka, J. Kopecky, Charles B. Pavlicek, J.F. Polak, J. J. Salat, J. J. Svoboda, and F. G. Hajicek.</p>
   <p>The Lawndale State Bank is connected to some extent with the Lawndale <pb facs="5418478_3_0181.jpg" n="6"/>National Bank, 3337-3339 West 26th Street, because all the stockholders of the Lawndale State Bank are also directors of the Lawndale National Bank.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
