<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-31">Dec. 31, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Bohemian Art Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0998</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0998.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-12-31">Dec. 31, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">BOHEMIAN ART CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The meeting to organize the Bohemian Art Club, the need for which has been felt, and the creation of which will aid in carrying out many worth-while projects, took place in Chicago on December 27.</p>
   <p>It was unanimously agreed upon by all who were present that this new society, which in no way competes with any existing Czech society, because Czech artists of Chicago have thus far been without any sort of an association, will develop into a desirable, friendly community in our city devoted to Czech art. It will be able to perform very important services for our cultural development.</p>
   <p>The following individuals participated in a discussion dealing with the problem of organizing the Club: representing the musicians were Messrs. Adolph H. Capek, Vaclav Machek, and Jiri Hrusa--requests to be excused were received from Joseph Vilim, Stepan Erst, A. Novak, Mario J. Korbel and Rudolph F. Ingerle; the creative artists, Professor Antonin Sterba, August Petrtyl, Joseph Patek; <pb facs="5418478_3_0999.jpg" n="2"/>the architects, Messrs. A. Charvat and James B. Rezny; the stage, Mr. F. Horlivy; and the literary men, Messrs. Enrique S. Vraz, Dr. Jaroslav E. S. Vojan, J. Tvrzicky-Kramer and Bretislav Jonas--requests to be excused were received from Messrs. R. J. Psenka and Bartos Bittner. Temporary officers, who are to serve until the regular election will be held on January 10, 1912 were elected. They are: Dr. Jaroslav E. S. Vojan, president, and Jiri Hrusa, secretary. With the unanimous consent of those present, the president announced the establishment of the new society. It will be called the "Bohemian Arts Club". On a motion of Mr. E. S. Vraz it was unanimously agreed that the Club will also be known as "The Art and Literary Department of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada (Bohemian-American National Council) of Chicago". The president and secretary, therefore, will serve on the executive committee of the Cesko-Americka Narodni Rada. The Arts Club, however, will be a self-governing independent body.</p>
   <p>It was then decided that the Club be divided into five departments: music, creative painting and sculpture, architecture, drama and literature. The <pb facs="5418478_3_1000.jpg" n="3"/>Club committee will consist of the five representatives from these departments, and the president and secretary who will be elected by the members. The committee for the preparation of the bylaws elected was composed of Messrs. Charvat, Petrtyl, Capek and Vojan. The next meeting will be held on Wednesday, January 10, 1912 in Mr. Welky's place. After the constitution and bylaws have been accepted, the public will be furnished with detailed information regarding the purposes of the Club. In many ways its program will be much the same as that followed by the Prague Arts Club; but, of course, many adjustments will be made to suit our own Bohemian-American conditions. On a motion of Mr. F. Horlivy one of the bylaws will provide that great care be taken by the Arts Club to preserve its genuine Czech characteristics--a purpose naturally desired by the Bohemian Arts Club.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
