<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-07">Apr. 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Announcement from Bazaar Offices</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czech Milliners Co-operate</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1427</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1427.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-04-07">Apr. 7, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">ANNOUNCEMENT FROM BAZAAR OFFICES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czech Milliners Co-operate</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Southwest Milliners' Association has resolved to work for the [Liberty] Bazaar. Their products will be exhibited in their own tent. These ladies have not been urged to do this; their decision proves their good will to help.</p>
   <p>The Czech Barkeepers' Association will also be represented. Their tent will function as a sort of "first-aid station for cases of dizziness, fainting, sudden weakness, disgust, ill humor, etc." All our organizations are vying with each other in preparing for this benefit....Over one thousand collectors' books have been distributed to this day, and many more are in demand. Organizations are contributing liberally, according to their prosperity or size. The Club Zobak (Club Beak), for instance, subscribed fifty dollars.</p>
   <p>The Bazaar committee, consisting of members of the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics, is predicting that the Pilsen Brewery <pb facs="5418478_3_1428.jpg" n="2"/>park will not be adequate to accommodate the tents and visitors, so that adjacent premises may have to be procured.</p>
   <p>This year's Bazaar is expected to be extraordinary and will offer unexpected attractions. Some of them are designed to be quite unique. For example, there will be a café where old-fashioned potato pancakes in true Bohemian style will be served.</p>
   <p>Our Chicago Czech bakers are busy with extensive preparations, some of which will produce very amusing results. Besides a rich selection of delicious samples of ordinary goods, they will offer titbits made of gingerbread, among them a whole galaxy of Hindenburgs, Kaisers, and Crown Princes, whom we are going to swallow with great relish.</p>
   <p>Our fellow countrymen from the sunny state of California have promised lively participation and they plan to arrange a stand with goods from their home state. These people, and others for whom hundreds and even thousands of miles of <pb facs="5418478_3_1429.jpg" n="3"/>distance are no barrier to a demonstration of their patriotism, will stay with us for the duration of the Bazaar.</p>
   <p>What are you Chicago Czechs doing, and how are you preparing for the Bazaar? Hasten to do your bit if you are lagging behind!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
