<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-09-04">Sept. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">An Old-Fashioned Czech Feast--A Plain People's Festival</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czech Freethinkers and Czech Catholics Join Hands for National Cause (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1466</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1466.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-09-04">Sept. 4, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">AN OLD-FASHIONED CZECH FEAST--A PLAIN PEOPLE'S FESTIVAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czech Freethinkers and Czech Catholics Join Hands for National Cause (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"For the only thought, sacred to all....." These flaming words from the Czech poet Svatopluk--Czech famous "Songs of the slave"--provided the inspiration for one of the most beautiful national festivals that Czech Chicago has ever seen, and which may justly be compared with "Czech Day" on August 12, 1893, at the Chicago World's Fair. The festival was held yesterday, September 3, in the Pilsen Brewery Park, 26th Street and Albany Avenue. The Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics were the sponsors. Beneath the name "old-fashioned feast" there lies a deep significance. The beacon light, the guiding spirit for the arrangement of this festival [in the style of an old-country annual celebration in honor of a Saint of the church] was the united effort of <pb facs="5418478_3_1467.jpg" n="2"/>Catholic and Freethinker (free-religious) societies, and individuals advocating the liberation of Czech lands from Austrian rule. People of all Slavonic nationalities from all corners of Chicago and the outlying districts flocked to this festival to show their kin sentiment. Dressed in their native attire they presented a scene of multicolored pageantry.....</p>
   <p>The Czech"California" district revealed at the first glance that extraordinary things were to occur. Almost every house displayed a flag. Twenty-sixth Street, that main artery of business in the largest Czech settlement of America, was literally buried under a mass of flags in the national colors. The Czech red and white mingled with the Stars and Stripes, the Union Jack, the French Tri-color, the Belgian flag, and banners of all other Allied nations.</p>
   <p>An impressive parade ushered in the festival proper.....The great wealth <pb facs="5418478_3_1468.jpg" n="3"/>of colors and the variety of dresses evoked visions of scenes and landscapes in the old homeland.</p>
   <p>....The overwhelming number of participants caused the festive parade to move far behind its scheduled time. The rallying point of the groups was the home of the Sokol Chicago Gymnastic Society, Kedzie Avenue and 24th Street. Headed by Rubringer's band, the parade moved along 24th Street west to Crawford Avenue. Mounted Sokols in blue shirts escorted the endless serpentine group composed of men and women of all walks of life. There were the members of the Czech National Alliance, groups of children in typical old country peasant costumes, male and female members of the American Czech Sokol Community, the Slovak League, delegates to the Chicago rally of the Czechoslovak Union, the Czech Butcher Employees' Educational Club, automobiles with representatives of the Allied nations headed by Messrs. James F. Štěpina, Frank G. Hájíček, and Jaroslav Pšenka. There was a cavalcade of mounted youngsters in Jugoslav costumes, the Czech Catholic Sokols, the lodges of the Czecho-Slavonic Aid Society, the <pb facs="5418478_3_1469.jpg" n="4"/>Czech-American Union, the Czech-American Foresters, Catholic Workmen's Associations, and many others. The Czech Catholics were conspicuous by their large numbers. The parade arrived at Crawford Avenue and turned into 26th Street, continuing east.</p>
   <p>Its arrival at Pilsen Brewery Park created nothing short of pandemonium. The pavilion and the park were so crowded that it took more than one hour before the stragglers of the parade were able to gain entrance.</p>
   <p>Mr. Jedlicka greeted the gathering in words of patriotic ardor. The open-air camp in the park garden was crowded until a late hour in the night; choruses of songs filled the air. A great variety of entertainment was provided. Anyone wishing to make his contribution to the patriotic cause had a thousand opportunities to do so...There were also many forms of amusement.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1470.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>"That sad countenance, the face of the Kaiser, also made an appearance. For a nickel anyone who aimed well could take a whack at him. It is needless to report that his Imperial Majesty received even more that afternoon than has already been handed to him by the British 'Tommies' and the French 'Poilus'. Reportorial conscientiousness and accuracy prompts us in connection with this to make mention of one of the many episodes that bordered on comedy. One lady with an especially sharp appetite for introducing herself to the Kaiser's effigy, bought a heap of balls. She threw them without hitting the mark even once. Then there was but one left. Under the compulsion of an irresistible desire, she crawled through the ropes, took a stand just in front of the picture, and cried out: 'Just wait, you scoundrel, I'm going to get you yet!' Then, with the one remaining ball, she hit the Kaiser squarely between the eyes, almost knocking his head off. Needless to say, the lady's skillful handling of her part was rewarded with tumultuous applause."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1471.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>....A Buick automobile valued at $825 and donated by the Club Rieger, was raffled late that evening. An eleven-year-old girl drew the lucky number from a box placed upon a table in clear sight of the thousands of on-lookers. The winner was not present, for, having despaired of winning, he had returned home and was sound asleep. Mr. Joseph Pantlík 2452 South Clifton Park Avenue, an emigrant from Bohemia, who came to this country just four years ago, was the winner. He is an employee of Sears Roebuck &amp; Company, twenty-four years of age, married, and the father of a three months old daughter. He had bought three chances on the auto from his scant savings just to do his bit. He was awakened and brought back to Pilsen Park in triumph to be shown to the multitude as the winner.</p>
   <p>....The festival was a success, not only financially, but what is more important, morally, for it was a mighty manifestation on the part of the Czech-Americans who have thoroughly grasped the aim of liberating the old homeland from the German yoke....The proceeds, which will be turned <pb facs="5418478_3_1472.jpg" n="7"/>over to authorized groups in charge of the liberation movement, are estimated to have reached fifteen or twenty thousand dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
