<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-02-27">Feb. 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">We Know What We Are Writing About</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Few Comments of the Denní Hlasatel Concerning the Sale of the Pilsen Auditorium Building</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0086</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0086.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-02-27">Feb. 27, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">WE KNOW WHAT WE ARE WRITING ABOUT</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Few Comments of the Denní Hlasatel Concerning the Sale of the Pilsen Auditorium Building</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Recently, we reported in our newspaper that the building known as the Pilsen Auditorium, which was the property of the Bořivoj Building and Loan Association, was sold to a new Bohemian concern, the Lawndale Amusement Company, which bought the building for the sum of $32,500. We also remarked that, in this way, the building was sold for an amount which is much smaller than the price which was offered to the building and loan association at one time, but was rejected by the old board of directors. We also mentioned the price which had been offered for the building, that is $60,000.</p>
   <p>The next day, we received a letter from our countryman, Mr. Frank Vykouk, 1948 South Turner Avenue, who writes in part as follows:</p>
   <p>"In reference to your report, which was published in your newspaper on February <pb facs="5418478_3_0087.jpg" n="2"/>23, in which you reported that the association will not receive as much for the building as could have been obtained sometime ago when the sum of $60,000 was offered by a large downtown real-estate office, but which offer, at that time, as you say, was rejected by the board of directors, I have this much to say:</p>
   <p>"I was a member of the board of directors of the Bořivoj Building and Loan Association from May 1916 until August 1920. You will surely recognize the fact that I am interested in your report because on several occasions, I have been asked by my friends why we did not sell the building at that time, etc. From people who did not know me personally, I have heard criticisms which were not exactly favorable for the board of directors. Therefore, in the interest of truth and the Bohemian people, and especially in the interest of members of the Bořivoj Building and Loan Association, I take the liberty to proclaim that never, during the time when I was a member of the board of directors, was such an offer made in earnest. Besides, the board of directors <pb facs="5418478_3_0088.jpg" n="3"/>never priced the building as high as was mentioned in your report.</p>
   <p>"Respectfully yours,</p>
   <p>"Frank Vykouk, 1948 South Turner Avenue."</p>
   <p>In reference to this communication, we only make the following remark: In our report we never mentioned the exact time when such an offer was made. We only published those facts which were dictated to us by our conscience in the interest of truth, the Bohemian people, and especially in the interest of members of the Borivoj Building and Loan Association. And that we knew very well what we were writing about is proved by excerpts from the report on the proceedings of the meeting of the Borivoj Building and Loan Association held in the Pilsen auditorium, Sunday afternoon, January 16, 1920.</p>
   <p>The report reads as follows: In the meeting, which was unusually stormy, Mr. Evžen Frýdl, president of the association, took the floor and spoke on the financial situation of the association. He also mentioned the lack of <pb facs="5418478_3_0089.jpg" n="4"/>economy which existed in the association until recently. His speech was a chain of accusations against the former members of the board of directors and several of those who are members of the board of directors right now, with the exception of those directors who were elected recently and who strive to bring about a better economy in the association. The old board of directors was accused of imprudence and neglect of its duties. The old board of directors was censured, because in order to cover up the loan given to the late Bazaar [Translator's note: A Bohemian enterprise which failed], they took over the building for an unreasonable price. The old board was also blamed for the fact that the directors of the Bazaar were absolved from personal responsibility. By this action, the association lost a great deal, and the board of directors did not act with good judgment. The total expense connected with this purchase of the Pilsen auditorium and its equipment amounted to $117,000. Today, the building brings in practically nothing; in fact, it is a losing proposition. There is no possibility of leasing the place, not even if concessions are given. And "when recently there was a prospect on hand who was willing to pay the sum of $85,000 for the building, several members of <pb facs="5418478_3_0090.jpg" n="5"/>the old board of directors would not permit the deal to go through."</p>
   <p>These were the words spoken at that time before the assembled members of the association by the president, Mr. Evžen Frýdl, and not by us.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
