<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-05-28">May 28, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">The First Czechoslovakian Bazaar and Exposition Is Open</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1373</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1373.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-05-28">May 28, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIRST CZECHOSLOVAKIAN BAZAAR AND EXPOSITION IS OPEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is a Sacred Duty of the Czechoslovaks of Chicago to Bring it to a Successful End and to Prove Their Gratitude and Love for the Czechoslovak Legionnaires</p>
   <p>The First Czechoslovakian Bazaar and Exposition was opened in the Pilsen Park pavilion yesterday. The promoters may well be proud of their accomplishments. Now it is up to our people to recognize this work; to use it for their information, amusement, and inspiration so that they can be proud of the proceeds which will be donated toward the fund to support widows and orphans of our fallen legionnaires, the best sons of our nation.</p>
   <p>The Bazaar and Exposition was opened at 2 P. M., although the program did not start until 8 P. M. when the chairman of the Bazaar committee, Mr. Karel Kouba, explained in his brief, distinct speech the purpose of the Bazaar and announced its official opening. The well-known dramatic artist, Mr. Frantisek Horlivy, presented a melodrama, "Kde Domov Muj" (Where Is My Home), and into his presentation he put all his artistry, his love, and longing for his native land.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1374.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Joseph P. Pecival, president of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v America (Czechoslovak National Alliance of America), then introduced the speaker of the evening, Mr. Jan G. Masaryk, diplomatic representative of the Czechoslovak Republic at Washington, D. C., who came here officially to open the Bazaar and Exhibition. When the enthusiastic applause with which Mr. Masaryk was greeted quieted down, he commenced his speech amid a deep silence, and he brought forth many wonderful ideas. We regret that it is not possible to quote his speech, and that we have to be satisfied to print only what seemed most significant to us.</p>
   <p>He said, "I am one of you, one of those who are willing to work for the benefit and happiness of our Czechoslovak Republic. Work and only work is the need in the present state of affairs. We overcame all obstacles and difficulties which arose during our struggle for independence, and today we are a free nation. We have a republic which has the most democratic constitution possible under present circumstances. We have gathered today to pay tribute to our legionnaires to whom, in the first place, we must be thankful for all that we have gained.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1375.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>We have met today to bring help to those who were very dear to them in this world--their wives and children. These widows and orphans must be taken care of by their country and nation, because their supporters sacrificed their lives for the country. I am convinced that in this respect the Bazaar and Exposition will fully accomplish what is expected of it. However, we also have sacred obligations to our whole nation and to our native land. The democratic ideals for which the legionnaires fought, suffered, and died must be carried out first. We must not split for worthless reasons, and we must not forget the great causes and tasks. Elections in Czechoslovakia are over....."</p>
   <p>If only a matter of little importance were being considered, we would call yesterday's attendance large; but because the project ahead of us is so important, we cannot deny the fact that we had expected a much greater attendance. We firmly believe the attendance during the next few days will be much larger and that the Bazaar and Exposition will be crowned with deserving success not only because of its purpose, but also for its beautiful arrangement.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
