<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-19">May 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Nedelni Beseda (To Be Read on Sunday)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1405</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1405.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-19">May 19, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">NEDELNI BESEDA (TO BE READ ON SUNDAY)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Almost every one has had his day at our bazaar--Sokols, Catholics, brother-hoods, businessmen, innkeepers--but the politicians day was left for today. Election is coming, and adherents of the Democratic, Republican, and other parties know what that means.</p>
   <p>We are used to electing aldermen, Congressmen, and other public officials. We do these things with much pomp and hubbub, with vigorous speeches, heated controversies, and many other tokens of our political maturity. The first fight comes with the primary, the second with the election, and the third at the end. When everything has come out well, we have nothing else left but to collect money for a diamond star for the official elected and for flowers to decorate his office with on the day of induction. You can see how much strain is necessary, how much energy is expended, for the election of some comparatively insignificant official.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1406.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Today, however, there will be an election of the largest caliber. We are going to elect the "mayor of the Chicago Czech community". Chicago is the Czech metropolis of America, and to become its Czech mayor really means something. We should therefore give to this election [at the Czech bazaar in Pilsen Brewery Park] our undivided attention. The man elected will be the primate (meaning the "first gentleman") of our community, which comprises the neighboring settlements of Cicero and Berwyn and some others. We have never had such an official as a "mayor of the Czech community" in Chicago. Our neighboring settlement, Cicero, has been, truly enough, enjoying since last year the prerogative of having a mayor of Czech descent duly elected by law. They did not get that mayor overnight. No Czech won a mayoralty election in Cicero until Czech votes were gradually augmented by migration from other communities. The last campaign, in which Cicero got a mayor of Czech descent, took several weeks.</p>
   <p>We, however, are faced with the problem of electing our mayor after a campaign <pb facs="5418478_3_1407.jpg" n="3"/>of only a few days! Just let us consider that we are about to elect a Czech mayor not only for Chicago, for he will at the same time be mayor of Cicero, Oak Park, and Berwyn--in fact, of all the Czech settlements around Chicago, the smallest hamlet not excluded! None of these communities has ever had its Czech mayor except Cicero, which is always different and always clamors for something extra and special. After today's election Cicero will again have something extra--two [Czech] mayors, one for itself only and one whom it will have to share with the other Czech settlements.</p>
   <p>It is peculiar how different the campaign for today's election is from our political campaigns. We have for today as many candidates as in any regular election, true enough. To whomever you give your vote today--you cannot go wrong. Yet, in summing up, today's election will lack political color.</p>
   <p>In any other campaign the candidate declares himself as supporting a platform and promises improvements and reforms. Let us, for instance, consider the <pb facs="5418478_3_1408.jpg" n="4"/>case of the mayor of Chicago, William H. Thompson. Before his election he promised to be a "liberal-minded" mayor, and he subscribed to the platform of the United Societies. He also promised the people to cause the People's Gas and Light Company to refund what was overcharged in gas bills--an item which has become superannuated, and which has almost faded from the memory of most of the utilities' customers. How Mayor Thompson kept his promises is very well known.....</p>
   <p>The candidates competing for the office of mayor of the Czech community do not come to us with any platform or with promises by which one might infer how they would handle the agenda of the office. Today's candidates know that every one of our community is well informed about their activities and their individual values from many years of close observation of national and social life.</p>
   <p>There is one question which may be in the minds of our voters today: Whom will the mayor of the Czech community take into his cabinet? Who will be his <pb facs="5418478_3_1409.jpg" n="5"/>chief of police, his fire marshal, and so forth? Should one of our Czech ladies be elected "mayoress," will she appoint a woman as chief of police? All these queries of paramount importance will not be answered until tonight, when the mayor, or the mayoress, is installed in office, festively and triumphantly.</p>
   <p>It is needless to say that just as in any other election the voters are expected to do their duty by appearing at the polls within the appointed hours. The voter today may cast several votes. No States' attorney will prosecute him for it, and no authorities will have to investigate vote fraud, for the election will be honestly conducted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
