<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-19">May 19, 1911</date><title level="a">Bohemian National Cemetery Association Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0245</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0245.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-05-19">May 19, 1911</date><title level="a">BOHEMIAN NATIONAL CEMETERY ASSOCIATION MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Bohemian National Cemetery Association held a special meeting last night in the C. S. P. S. (The Czecho-Slovak Benevolent Society) hall on 18th street, in which the construction of new greenhouses at the cemetery, and the amendment of the by-laws of the National Cemetery were discussed.</p>
   <p>After the chairman, Mr. Pech, brought the meeting to order, bids for the construction of a greenhouse according to the plans of Mr. Rusy were read. The secretary, Mr. Stan. J. Halik, announced that the Foley Manufacturing Company at 26th and Western Avenue offered to build the greenhouse according to the plans for $5,400, but would do it for $4,500 according to their sketch.</p>
   <p>The firm of J. C. Moninger Company made a bid of $2,625 to build according to their own sketch, in which, to a certain extent, the <pb facs="5418478_3_0246.jpg" n="2"/>original plans would be considered. In this price, is included the work of removing the old greenhouse. The representatives resolved that the management should award the contract to this company, but should ask for specifications, so that it will be known in what manner the construction is to be carried out. The company must also assume all responsibility for the safety of the men working, so that the Cemetery will not be liable in case of injuries suffered by any worker. Mr. Rusy is to inspect the construction work, and see to it that it is done well.</p>
   <p>The next order of business was the discussion of the proposed amendments to the by-laws. The secretary introduced the following motions made in writing: Motion No. 1: made by V. Ruzicka and <pb facs="5418478_3_0247.jpg" n="3"/>V. H. Filip; Motion No. 2: made by Rudolph Kapsa; Motion No. 3: made by Frant. Vykouk. All three motions were defeated after a lengthy debate, and the by-laws of the organization remained as they were.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
