<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-03-07">Mar. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Ladies Benevolent Circle Holds a Social</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1020</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1020.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-03-07">Mar. 7, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">LADIES BENEVOLENT CIRCLE HOLDS A SOCIAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.2--A large attendance participated in a rendezvous at the Sokol Chicago Hall, yesterday afternoon.</p>
   <p>The Ladies Benevolent Circle held this social affair for the benefit of the Old Peoples' Home and the Orphanage. The arrangements committee, provided such a program as would satisfy every popular concert. The names of the foremost people of our artistic world were on the program. The purpose of this undertaking and its execution, were powerful magnates for our art loving and charitably inclined public.</p>
   <p>The ladies of the benevolent circles are working quietly, it is true, but energetically and their work is meeting with best results.</p>
   <p>Thus, yesterday afternoon, the hall was filled to capacity, the guests enjoyed themselves immensely and our charitable and national institutions will be enriched by a considerable amount. The program started, with the march from the "Bartere d Bride," by Bedrich Smetana, which was very well <pb facs="5418478_3_1021.jpg" n="2"/>played by E. Brabec's orchestra. After that, Mr. Otto Fuerst, spoke of the significance of the Old Peoples' Home and the Orphanage and the applause which interrupted his speech and the long continued applause at the conclusion, was proof, that his words reached their hearts. Then, the Bohemian American Quartet appeared, namely, Messrs, Richard Klas, Charles Malik, Joseph Radous and Anton Vanek.</p>
   <p>Hardly had the applause died away, when Miss Henrietta Zajicek, appeared on the stage and sang an aria from the "Bartered Bride." Miss Zajicek, has a beautifull, sweet and in every respect, pure soprano voice. The control she showed yesterday over her silvery tones surprised everyone. Miss Zajicek, was prompted to give an encore. Then our unsurpassed violin master, Mr. Frank Hladky, replaced Miss Zajicek. He played the Cavatina from Lauterbach and Humoresque by Dvorak.</p>
   <p>Messrs, B. Sulc and Albert Novak, then sang a comic duet and they were successful in causing the entire audience to laugh. Such was also, the success of Mrs. Ludmila Friedl. With the close of the program the audience partook of coffee and indulged in friendly conversion.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1022.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Yesterdays affair, which was sponsored by the Ladies Benevolent Circle, will remain in the memory of the participants for a long time, aand we are convinced, that there is no one, who does not look forward with expectancy to another such affair, in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
