<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-08">July 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Art Exhibited by American Press</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0353</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0353.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-07-08">July 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH ART EXHIBITED BY AMERICAN PRESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We may not sympathize with the Chicago Herald-Examiner, yet we consider it our journalistic duty to make mention of an item which appeared on the pictorial page of that paper yesterday. Prominence is given to several photographic studies by our young Czech-American artist, James W. Pondelicek, whose parents live, if we remember correctly, somewhere near the intersection of West 20th and South 41st Streets. The artist and his charming wife live there with his parents.</p>
   <p>The artist's wife is well known in circles where classic dancing is fostered. She was, until recently, a member of the artistic group headed by Mme. Ludmila and Sergej Oukrajinsky, dancers.</p>
   <p>The studies singled out by the American newspaper are telling proofs of Mr. Pondelicek's high standards in photographic art. There are four pictures, <pb facs="5418478_3_0354.jpg" n="2"/>each more beautiful than the last. The first is named "Spirit of the Lake". The artist's wife had posed for the second, "Bacchanale," with Vasilej A. Kanellos. Two Indians, standing upon a rock and peering into the vast spaces, are the subject of the third, "Scouts". The fourth is a beautiful study of summer time, and is named "Narcissa".</p>
   <p>We wrote about Mr. Pondelicek once before, when he came to our offices and showed a series of his works of art. We are convinced that he has a splendid future, and that his works will materially help to spread the repute of Czech art in native American circles, for he is almost entirely dependent upon recognition from them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
