<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-28">Oct. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Prepare for Czech Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">Professors and Students of University of Chicago Will Be Given an Exhibition of Accomplishments and Maturity of the Czechoslovak People</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1459</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1459.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-28">Oct. 28, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">PREPARE FOR CZECH DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Professors and Students of University of Chicago Will Be Given an Exhibition of Accomplishments and Maturity of the Czechoslovak People</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The conference held by the foremost Czech patriotic workers and the heads of the faculties, together with Professor Harry Pratt Judson, president of the University of Chicago, has produced remarkable results.</p>
   <p>Chicago Czechs will be given an opportunity to promote valuable propaganda precisely where it is needed most--among the educated strata of the American people, the present and future teachers of the nation.</p>
   <p>In the conference it was decided to hold an exhibition on November 14. It will be located in the halls of the University of Chicago; it is to last three days and will be known as "Czechoslovak Day". It will be opened <pb facs="5418478_3_1460.jpg" n="2"/>in the greatest seat of higher learning between the Atlantic and Pacific on American soil. There the Czechoslovaks will demonstrate their accomplishements and cultural level. They will acquaint professors and thousands of students with their national aims and efforts. They will do it in such a manner as to create a deep and lasting impression.</p>
   <p>For three days the University will extend its hospitality not only to the works of Czech and Slovak artists, but also to the products of careful handwork, which have their particular indigenous beauty.</p>
   <p>Czech books are sure to attract the attention of teachers and students. Old books will be exhibited to indicate the age of early Czech culture and books of a recent vintage to show the present high mental level of our nation.</p>
   <p>One large table will be devoted to plastic art, painting, drawing, engraving, and etching. The works of our artists--Manes, Ales, Hynais, Schwaige, <pb facs="5418478_3_1461.jpg" n="3"/>Svabinsky, Marold, Mucha, Kaspar, Jansa, Engelmueller, Simon, Panuzka, Stretti, etc.--will be shown here in the originals or reproductions.</p>
   <p>The exhibition of Slovak art will occupy a special section which will certainly attract many visitors and excite genuine interest. Embroidery, porcelain painting, wood carvings, and other objects of art will be shown.</p>
   <p>On the opening day there will be a program devoted to Czech and Slovak music, instrumental and vocal; to the presentation of national dances; and gymnastic productions executed by Sokol societies. The program for this evening will be as follows.....</p>
   <p>This first evening will be reserved for a native American audience exclusively, chiefly professors and students. Our own Czechoslovak fellow countrymen, except active participants, will not be admitted, since they might easily fill the space available in Mandel Hall, where this "Academy" [gala evening] will be held.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1462.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In order to let our people also enjoy the splendid program, a sort of general rehearsal will be held in one of the large halls in our settlement several days before the performance in Mandel Hall. An admission fee will be charged. One part of the proceeds will be used to defray expenses for the exhibition at the University; the other will serve to increase one of the funds for the pursuit of our national aspirations.</p>
   <p>The entire series of these festive performances and exhibitions is expected to bring great moral and material gain to Czech propaganda in America, of which it will represent one of the most brilliant phases. It has been prepared by and will be held under the sponsorship of the Czech National Alliance, a body composed of our foremost patriotic workers from Sokol associations, circles of our literati, artists, pedagogues, professional men, and businessmen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
