<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-04">Nov. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">On the Altar of Humanity</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1511</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1511.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-04">Nov. 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE ALTAR OF HUMANITY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great many visitors passed through the gates of the brilliantly lighted Pilsen Park last night. As in previous years, the usual annual ball of the Ceska Dobrocinna Spolecnost (Bohemian Charitable Association) was held there, the ball of an organization which has done such a great deal of valuable work toward alleviating misery among our countrymen.....</p>
   <p>Among the members of the organizing committee were John A. Sokol, Anton J. Cermak, Frank G. Hajicek, Jan Chrastka, R. W. Dvorak, Louis Solar, Karel V. Janovsky, and others, but in addition to these there were many other men and women who, in all parts of the ball room, attended to the various needs of their visitors.....</p>
   <p>The spirits of the public attending the ball were excellent indeed....also around the bar, although that part of the entertainment had a mighty close shave--by Mayor Thompson. It is generally known that for its balls the Dobrocinna Spolecnost has never needed to take out the so-called "bar permit," and it never has done so <pb facs="5418478_3_1512.jpg" n="2"/>in order to save the money the permit costs. Since it is well known that all the money made by the ball goes to charity, it has never entered anybody's mind to inquire whether or not a bar permit had been applied for or issued, that is, in the past. But Mr. Thompson, for reasons which it is not necessary to go into at this time, has a somewhat different opinion in this matter. So we are informed that he issued an order yesterday that without a permit no alcoholic beverages might be dispensed at the ball of our Dobrocinna Spolecnost. And, since an application for a bar permit must be filed at least two weeks ahead of the time of the entertainment at which it is to be used, the Mayor's order was a most unwelcome surprise to the organizers. Only upon the urgent request of a number of directors of the Dobrocinna Spolecnost who called on him yesterday afternoon, did the Mayor agree to recall his order, and--the bar was merrily busy, without a permit, just as in past years. The Mayor's stop order was, of course, considered in various ways in various places, but that none of the opinions passed on these occasions was particularly flattering to the Mayor goes without saying.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
