<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-23">Dec. 23, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Success Guaranteed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-12-23">Dec. 23, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">SUCCESS GUARANTEED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Lively activity was in evidence in our memorial Pilsen Park pavilion yesterday during the early forenoon. Legionnaires, members of the Bazar Svobody (Liberty Bazaar) committee and members of the Ladies' Auxiliary of the Czechoslovak Legionnaires of Chicago were busy classifying and putting in order articles which arrived, after some delay, and which must be sold before Christmas. The sight of all these notions, beads, miniature statues, legionnaire emblems, glassware, articles of porcelain, etc., really electrified everyone of those workers who were present, and inspired in them the desire to finish the hard task of preparing such an enormous number of articles for sale in a short period of time. Taking into consideration the fact that the goods were received late Tuesday night and that yesterday, at noon, the sale was merrily going on, we must acknowledge that our legionnaires still retain a sense of duty toward their brothers beyond the sea.</p>
   <p>Beginning at about eleven o'clock in the morning, individual buyers were coming <pb facs="5418478_3_1320.jpg" n="2"/>in with the intention of purchasing some of the articles on exhibition. Most of them came through curiosity. But they were so very surprised with what they saw that they bought until their pocketbooks were exhausted. The laughter and shouts of juniors and grownups echoed from all sides. At the sight of the articles on exhibition, the children, especially, could not be restrained, and they begged until their fathers or mothers bought something for them.</p>
   <p>Yesterday's weather was detrimental to the efforts of the arrangements committee. But toward evening, when the rain ceased and it began to snow, throngs of prospective buyers came in, and soon the spacious auditorium was crowded. When finally, late in the evening, the pavilion was almost empty, the managers of this Christmas sale stated with smiles that almost half of the articles were sold. Today, weather permitting, the legionnaires hope to bring this sale to a close, and in the knowledge of a well-accomplished duty, they intend to wish a joyous Christmas to all goodhearted Czechoslovaks.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1321.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Therefore, whoever intends to visit the pavilion today to soften the misery of orphans and poor cripples with pennies, should take a good hint and go there at once while there is still a chance to buy something.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
