<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-05-26">May 26, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Bazaar Tomorrow Night</title><title level="a" type="sub">The First Czechoslovakian Bazaar and Exposition to be Held in Chicago Will Open Tomorrow, May 27, in Pilsen Park Pavilion</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1368</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1368.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-05-26">May 26, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">BAZAAR TOMORROW NIGHT</title><title level="a" type="sub">The First Czechoslovakian Bazaar and Exposition to be Held in Chicago Will Open Tomorrow, May 27, in Pilsen Park Pavilion</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only a few hours' time remains until the opening of the First Czechoslovakian Bazaar and Exposition tomorrow, Thursday, May 27, at 8 P. M. Mr. Jan Masaryk, ambassador of the Czechoslovak Republic to the United States, will be present.</p>
   <p>The Bazaar and Exposition will be held in the Pilsen Park pavilion, and final preparations will be completed tonight by many of our generous men and women, national workers from the following organizations: the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americae (Czechoslovak National Alliance of America), the Slovenska Liga v Americe (Slovak League of America), the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe (National Alliance of Bohemian Catholics of America), the Cesky Umelecky Klub v Chicagu (Bohemian Arts Club of Chicago), the Vcelky (Bees), the Priadky <pb facs="5418478_3_1369.jpg" n="2"/>(Spinners), and the Cesko-Americka Obchodni Komora v Chicagu (Bohemian-American Board of Trade of Chicago). The pavilion, under the skilled hands of the architects of the Bohemian Arts Club, has been changed beyond recognition, and the unanimous opinion of those who watched the preliminary work is that nothing of the kind has ever been accomplished before. Among the various attractions there is an imitation of the "Prasna Brana Prazska" (Prague Powder Tower); replicas of Bohemian and Slovakian cottages; and a special section reserved for the Bohemian Arts Club of Chicago exhibition, the decoration of which has been a matter of great importance to our architects.</p>
   <p>Various booths will be occupied and taken care of by the following organizations:</p>
   <p>1: The Pilsen and California branches of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe; <pb facs="5418478_3_1370.jpg" n="3"/>2: Cicero branch of the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v Americe;</p>
   <p>3: Priadky;</p>
   <p>4: Vcelky;</p>
   <p>5: Slovenska Liga v Americe;</p>
   <p>6: Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe;</p>
   <p>7: Cesko-Americka Obchodni Komora v Chicagu;</p>
   <p>8: Smoked meat products and not dog stand;</p>
   <p>9: Cesky Umelecky Klub v Chicagu, whose members will exhibit about one hundred sculptures, paintings, and other artistic works.</p>
   <p>The Ceskoslovenska Obchodni Komora v Chicagu will exhibit luxurious, imported, handmade articles recently received directly from Czechoslovakia. These will be for sale and ten per cent of the gross receipts will be donated to the legionnaires' fund.</p>
   <p>The Bazaar and Exhibition will be open from Thursday, May 27, until Sunday, May 30. Tomorrow will be the day for the Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni v <pb facs="5418478_3_1371.jpg" n="4"/>Americe; Friday is reserved for the Cesky Umelecky Klub v Chicagu; Saturday will be the day for the Slovenska Liga whose president, Mr. Albert Mamatej of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, will come to Chicago to address members of the League. Sunday will be the day for the Narodni Svaz Ceskych Katoliku v Americe. Reverend F. W. Jedlicka, who recently returned from Czechoslovakia, will be the speaker.</p>
   <p>Net proceeds will be donated to the "Svaz Ceskoslovenskych Legionaru" (Czecho-slovak Legionnaires' Alliance) of Prague for the fund which is used to support the widows and orphans of fallen heroes. These widows and orphans deserve general aid, and therefore we expect that our people will patronize this project wholeheartedly. The proceeds will be used to dry the tears of those who are in want, the poorest of the poor in Czechoslovakia. Let there be none of us who would retreat, who would not contribute to so sacred a cause as this one. Today it is our duty to give aid to those whose supporters--husbands and fathers--sacrificed their lives upon the altar of the homeland; who by their blood and their lives helped to restore the liberty of the Czechoslovakian <pb facs="5418478_3_1372.jpg" n="5"/>nation and the independence of their country. Therefore we say, "Success to the Bazaar!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
