<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-18">Nov. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A Festive Bohemian Day in the Harrison High School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1236</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1236.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-11-18">Nov. 18, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">A FESTIVE BOHEMIAN DAY IN THE HARRISON HIGH SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Czech students of the Carter H. Harrison High School, in co-operation with the faculty of that school, have prepared a splendid program for a Czech festival day. The Czech Festival is to entertain the members of a conference of high school principals and teachers of Chicago which is to be held next Friday, November 24. There will be about two thousand school superintendents and teachers attending this conference. This occasion is of particular significance for us, since the program prepared by the Czech students is to be purely Czech in nature, as the management of the Harrison High School is desirous of presenting to the great number of guests examples of Czechoslovak music, song, and folk art. The [concert] will be given between the hours of 12 noon and 2 P.M. on the day mentioned above,and also on the day preceding the conference the same program will be presented to the general public in the assembly hall of the school. It will consist of the following numbers:</p>
   <p>1. Czech melodies by Safranek played by the Czech students of the school; <pb n="2"/><gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/><pb facs="5418478_3_1237.jpg" n="3"/>Three things: Their love of truth, and an unshakable faith that some day that truth would finally be victorious; their love of beauty, which they saw in nature and reproduced in the folk ornament and the folk song; and, finally, their love for their native soil, which they cultivated by the sweat of their brow and with their eyes full of tears, until the plains, the hills, and the valleys blossomed out like a garden.</p>
   <p>"In this exhibit one will have an opportunity to see samples of folk art, as much of it as could be obtained in this city, an art which originated under the thatched roofs of the Czech, Moravian, and Slovak peasants, and was handed down from one generation to another. These simple peasant huts were the studios, and the peasant mothers living in them were the art teachers of this sort of folk expression. The natural scenery surrounding these people furnished much inspiration to these 'schools of art'. America has a right to hope that this spirit of Czechoslovak art will not die in the hearts of those who come to our shores, but that it will enrich American life and culture.</p>
   <p>"Besides these creative arts, there was also music and song. The Czechoslovak <pb facs="5418478_3_1238.jpg" n="4"/>folk songs are rightly placed among the best [examples of folk song]. Only the Irish and the Scotch tunes equal them in beauty and in feeling, and none surpass them in these respects. No wonder that the Czechoslovak nation has contributed so much to the music of the world! Its great composers, Smetana, Dvorak, Novak, Fibich, and many others, found inspiration for their work in the songs of the folk.</p>
   <p>"The greatest of all the ethnic characteristics of the Czechs is their passionate love of truth. Bohemia was almost annihilated for its ideals of progress; it may be that it will suffer again for the same reason, but the love of these people for truth will never be destroyed, no matter how great their suffering and the sacrifices which they have to face. I have presented the highlights of the Czech character, traits which ought to be cultivated and utilized in the creation of the American character."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
