<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-17">Oct. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">News of the Karel Jonas Sokol Dramatic Association</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1069</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1069.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-10-17">Oct. 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS OF THE KAREL JONAS SOKOL DRAMATIC ASSOCIATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dramatic association of the Karel Jonas Sokol of Cicero, Illinois, has a great many reasons to feel elated over the results of its activity for the past season. Every one of its theatrical performances was a huge success. Moreover, the theater-going public was highly satisfied with these dramatic productions, thus ever widening the circle of friends and votaries who support that well-known Cicero organization.</p>
   <p>To open the autumn season the Karel Jonas Sokol produced an operetta titled "Almo, Kde bydlis?" (Alma, Where Dost Thou Live?) Every single seat in the house was sold, and people had to be turned away by the box office. The performance did honor to the amateurs. The play was smooth, and the songs <pb facs="5418478_3_1070.jpg" n="2"/>well sung. Everybody was enthusiastic about the play and manifested his delight by long and almost continuous applause, which often shook the building to its foundations.</p>
   <p>The role of "Alma" was sung by the popular soprano Mrs. Louisa Topinka, whose guest appearance on the Cicero stage was hailed and acclaimed by the local theater-going public. The rest of the players were: Mrs. John Sedlacek, Mrs. Smiricky, and Mrs. Mrazek; Mr. Smiricky, Mr. Novak, Mr. Stefl, Mr. Sverak, Mr. Kukla, Mr. Huml, and Mr. Hromadko. Each one of the actors tried to do his best by close attention to the role assigned to him or her. The whole of the play was therefore harmonious. The production itself was good from a technical point of view. The reaction of the audience will no doubt encourage the players to continue their good efforts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
