<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-04">Aug. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">John Klucina Requests Patent for His Flying Machine</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0232</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0232.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-08-04">Aug. 4, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">JOHN KLUCINA REQUESTS PATENT FOR HIS FLYING MACHINE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Prior to 1898, when aviation was in its feeble beginnings, no aeroplane had succeeded in rising without the aid of a balloon. This can readily be understood for every machine represented a body heavier than air.</p>
   <p>In November, of the year 1898, as the readers of this paper will remember, Mr. John Klucina, our countryman and well known architect, appeared with a model of a flying machine that for the first time in the history of aviation made use of a means of gaining momentum, consisting in principle of two wing surfaces resting upon three light weight wheels.</p>
   <p>That flying machine was described by the English newspapers as well as by the Czech papers. To be sure, the machine appeared unfinished and unsightly, but in spite of all this it was the first correct theory, by which Mr. Klucina demonstrated that a machine heavier than air must <pb facs="5418478_3_0233.jpg" n="2"/>develop sufficient ground speed in order to rise from the ground; consequently, we can rightfully say that Mr. Klucina was the first man in the history of aviation to come upon the correct idea, that is, of using some means of giving momentum to an aeroplane before taking off.</p>
   <p>This idea soon became known and although Mr. Klucina's efforts were unsuccessful at that time, we cannot find an aeroplane today that does not employ the original idea.........</p>
   <p>Today, this old pioneer of aviation is once again coming before the public. This time with a plane that incorporates his original ideas with the newest theories and co-operation of the Engineer Prosek.</p>
   <p>The plane will be equipped with 140 horsepower motors, driving two propellers having a diameter of nine feet.....</p>
   <p>Mr. Klucina has completed all his plans and is endeavoring to secure a patent for his machine. The construction of the plane will require in the <pb facs="5418478_3_0234.jpg" n="3"/>neighborhood of $12,000, which sum will be subscribed for by Mr. Klucina's friends. The power plant alone will cost $6,000 and has been ordered from Paris.</p>
   <p>The plans and model of the plane were shown to us by Mr. Klucina and we hope that his efforts may be successful this time, for in that way the inventor would receive recognition. Mr. Klucina also informed us that he intended to demonstrate the model with actual power. Receipts from this source to be turned over to the Vojta Naprstek School.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
