<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-08">Feb. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">AlbÍN PolÁŠEk Receives High Honor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0589</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0589.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-02-08">Feb. 8, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ALBÍN POLÁŠEK RECEIVES HIGH HONOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Arts Club awarded a silver medal to Professor Albín Polášek for his masterpiece, "Man Hewing Out His Own Destiny", which is now being exhibited in the Chicago Art Institute. This prize, the highest given by that club, was awarded to Polášek on Monday night. Mr. Polášek's studio is located at 4 East Ohio Street.</p>
   <p>In our previous issue, we published the fact that Professor Polášek was also honored by the art jury [of the Chicago Art Institute], which decided to award the Logan medal to him, This award is also accompanied by a cash prize of $500.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0590.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Own Destiny' in many ways reminds one of the work of Rodin. This, too, perhaps is true since the work is a finished product, although it looks unfinished. The upper part represents a figure of man freed from the surrounding stone. The lower limbs are not free and are waiting for the liberating blows of the chisel, which is poised in the outstretched hand of the man at the moment when he is at war with difficulties but still is filled with a desire to attain complete freedom. There is strength in that figure which covers up all the little or trivial things. One feels that the man must liberate himself. Behind each blow of the chisel, there must be the strength of his own muscle directed with the certainty of his own mind. The message which is conveyed by this rings true.....Every man should hew out his own fate and destiny, be a captain of his own soul, a master of his own fate.....Polasek's figure brings to mind all these characteristics, and because of this it is a remarkable piece of work.</p>
   <p>"The most important award offered at this exhibition was given to this piece of sculpture, and justly so. That award is the medal of Mr. and Mrs. Frank G. Logan and a cash award of five hundred dollars. Other awards which were <pb facs="5418478_3_0591.jpg" n="3"/>granted to various artists in this exhibit were much smaller and have a subordinate value.</p>
   <p>We rejoice because of the honor that has been bestowed upon Professor Albín Polášek, and we are sure that every sincere Czechoslovak and votary of real art....not only in Chicago, but also in the entire country, will rejoice with us. And, we believe that although Professor Polášek called great attention to his work, "The Sower," and again to his "Man Hewing Out His Own Destiny," he will soon create another work of beauty and [artistic] depth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
