<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-05-04">May 4, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">Pan-Slavic Day and the Old People's Home and the Orphanage Ten Thousand</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1587</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1587.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 4</item>
     <item>II D 5</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1905-05-04">May 4, 1905</date>.
<title level="a">PAN-SLAVIC DAY AND THE OLD PEOPLE'S HOME AND THE ORPHANAGE TEN THOUSAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p/>
   <p>P.4--Not less than ten thousand enthusiastic compatriots of ours gathered in the Coliseum last Sunday. We say, ten thousand! So large a number of Czechs and Slovaks had never before, in this city, been gathered under one roof. It was demonstrated that we can accomplish much--if we only want to Every loyal and sincere Bohemian, every Slovak, must rejoice in this success.</p>
   <p>How our hearts would have been thrilled if we could have recorded a like success for the recent bazaar for the old people's home and the orphanage! What a pleasure it would be if we could say that ten thousand of our countrymen had visited the bazaar in the entire period of it's existence! Well, it did not happen; however, we firmly hope that it will happen the next time because by this Pan-Slavic Day we demonstrated that in us there exists a love for everything good and noble, and that we are inspired by everything which tends to awaken our national consciousness.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1588.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Only those people who are consistent in everything, who neglect nothing, have the right to claim the respect and the admiration of the world. Well, if the Sokols develop our youth into sturdy, fearless men and women, there must also be some one who will look after our old folks and our orphans. This also is a sublime task, and it should never be forgotten. Let us hope that the Pan-Slavic celebration, which surely did an endless amount of good for our people, will also do much good for our national benevolent project, the erection of the old people's home and the orphanage.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
