<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-12">May 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Bazaar Opened Festively</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Greatest Czech-American Enterprise," Consensus of opinion-The Hindenburg Statue</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-12">May 12, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">BAZAAR OPENED FESTIVELY</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Greatest Czech-American Enterprise," Consensus of opinion-The Hindenburg Statue</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Well, our bazaar, the result of the combined efforts of all the Chicago Czechs, regardless of creed or political affiliation, was opened last night.</p>
   <p>Many thousands of our fellow countrymen came to take part in this, the greatest enterprise ever ventured upon by American Czechs. They overcrowded the Pilsen Brewery Park pavilion, which had been rearranged so as to accommodate a larger number of people. It was an enthusiastic crowd that had come to view the work of many weeks done by the committee, which is composed of the most ardent workers of the community. People came to see and to hear and to give vent to patriotic emotions. Their hearts were filled with love and devotion for their motherland and with equal affection for their adopted homeland. They are longing for the <pb facs="5418478_3_1418.jpg" n="2"/>victory of liberty and democracy over the German robbers and murderers.</p>
   <p>We regret that the deadline set by our newspaper does not allow us to do to this event full justice in our columns. We shall have to complete our report in the next number, and today we present only first impressions and outlines.</p>
   <p>The pavilion was hedged in all around by an endless chain of tents, booths, and stands, conducted by our patriotic societies, who vied with one another in offering their goods for sale, an immense variety of attractive, useful, and even very valuable objects. In the center of the pavilion also there were stands forming an island, leaving ample room to the visitors for promenading and lounging under a flood of lights. The spectacle filled observers with admiration.</p>
   <p>In the southeastern part of the pavilion stands a statue, the center of attraction. It is obviously the work of a master hand, and yet every one will <pb facs="5418478_3_1419.jpg" n="3"/>burst into laughter at the first sight of it. This statue, to which we are going to devote more space later, was unveiled in a most ceremonious manner, and the crowds shouted exultantly and applauded frantically. The purpose of placing the statue there was to make the man whom it represents atone for all that he has perpetrated by helping fill the coffers of the bazaar. The only function for the public to perform is to buy a nail and drive it into the statue. The price of the nail is determined by its size and by the spot selected to drive it in. There will surely be none of our fellow countrymen who will not find a place for his nail in the body of the "good-looking" man girded with a sword, labeled "made in Germany" and wearing a decoration "for distinguished service".</p>
   <p>Great activity was displayed in a unique contest, vie., the rivalry for the honor of being elected "Mayor" or "Mayoress" of the Czech Chicago community. Groups of organizations elect their representatives, and from the latter the two honorary dignitaries will be elected in the final contest. The competition <pb facs="5418478_3_1420.jpg" n="4"/>in the primaries among the groups is extremely keen. Precious gifts are in store for the winner.</p>
   <p>A place with very strong attractions is the "Dining Room in the Trenches," at which one can arrive only by walking through an exact replica of the trenches on the battlefield. In the spacious room there are numerous trophies from the war, displayed in brilliant light and surrounded by waves of the Allied nations' colors. The "dining room" is managed by the ladies of the Pilsen Brewery Company under the leadership of Mrs. Cervenka.</p>
   <p>A highly interesting surprise for the visitors was prepared in the arrangement of the main platform, which is located at the northern end of the pavilion and represents a dugout. It was constructed free of charge by our patriotic Czech carpenters after the plan of Architect A. Lonek and under the supervision of the creator of the bazaar, V. Dlouhy, decorated by the Czech Artists' Club, and <pb facs="5418478_3_1421.jpg" n="5"/>equipped for [stage] performances by Director Jindrich (Henry) Weidner of the Sokol Chicago Theater.</p>
   <p>The first performance took place at 10 P. M. The public responded enthusiastically. Mr. J. Psenka, head of the program committee, showed by this presentation that the artistic and entertaining phase of the bazaar will be splendidly taken care of. More about it will be reported in tomorrow's issue of this paper. Besides Czechoslovaks there will be artists of other nationalities to contribute to the program.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
