<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-03">Sept. 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Czechoslovak Posviceni</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1384</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-slovak #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1384.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3) (Slovak)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-09-03">Sept. 3, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHOSLOVAK POSVICENI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Translator's note: The Posviceni, formerly an annual feast commemorating the consecration of a Catholic church, and in honor of its patron saint, is now celebrated as a people's festival of national character.]</p>
   <p>One of the most unsympathetic persons in Chicago yesterday was undoubtedly the weatherman. He upset all the beautiful plans for outings, picnics, and other outdoor recreations. He also marred the success of the parade which preceded our Posviceni. This popular festival was held in the Pilsen (Plzen) Brewery Park yesterday, for the third consecutive year. It was intended to be of a national patriotic character, and was arranged under the auspices of the Czech National Alliance, the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America, and the Slovak League.</p>
   <p>The rainy weather spoiled the parade. That it did not do so completely, was <pb facs="5418478_3_1385.jpg" n="2"/>due to the fact that some of the patriotic participants braved the untoward elements and marched on, determined not to let this manifestation, which was to usher in one of our most beautiful and noble national enterprises, be a complete failure. The procession was scheduled to start at 12:30 P. M. from the home of Sokol Chicago, Kedzie Avenue near 24th Street. Had it not been for the inclement weather, the parade would have turned out to be one of the most magnificent spectacles in our national life, since very large numbers of organized and individual participants had announced their intention of co-operating. However, it happened that just when the paraders were beginning to assemble, a rain came pouring down which transformed the streets into veritable pools. Thus the manifestation became only a faint reflection of what our people of the Czech California district saw on other festive days. Most of our organizations were missing, and so were the crowds of friends and sympathizers who used to view the parades from sidewalks and windows.</p>
   <p>Czech and Slovak Sokols, including many girls, marched in the colorful Sokol <pb facs="5418478_3_1386.jpg" n="3"/>attire. There were some brotherhoods and glee clubs in automobiles decorated with the national colors. The Sokol Komensky appeared in a particularly attractive group, featuring "The Ride of the Kings"; the Slovak Club, always zealous and sacrificing, represented a "Group of Harvesters". Three "policemen" in medieval garb acted as funmakers. They let their presence be known by frowning at people and mumbling in an uncanny voice: Kdo Smeje Se.. (Whoever is caught laughing is going to get arrested and locked up!) By incessantly repeating these words in a threatening tone they reminded us of the unforgettable Mosner, unsurpassed comedian of the Czech National Theater in Prague. Later they asserted their authority in the Brewery Park; arresting violators of their injunction by the dozens, and without warrant.</p>
   <p>The marchers reached the gates of the Park in a downpour of rain, and, thoroughly soaked as they were, hastily sought shelter in the Park pavilion. When, finally, the weather cleared up in the late afternoon, the prospects seemed better for the festival. Crowds of people began to arrive and gather in <pb facs="5418478_3_1387.jpg" n="4"/>clusters in and around the pavilion. Booths and stands were besieged by eager buyers. The downpour of the afternoon was transformed into a rain of gold for patriotic aims. Every possible provision was made for the personal comfort and pleasure of the visitors. The stands and tables abounded with solid and liquid foods, including marchpane, ice cream, and other delicious edibles. Those who believe in the ancient Roman proverb In Vino Veritas (There is truth in wine) vied with each other in putting it to test. They gathered around the booth of the Korbel Brothers, where Mr. J. E. Stach, acknowledged authority in the realm of the grape, conducted business. The inn, operated by the Slovak Club, was another strong attraction. Members of the Association of Czech Brewers took charge of dispensing their beverages.</p>
   <p>War food, which was in accordance with the ruling of the Federal Food Administration, was sold in the tents of the Catholic Men's Central Unit, Czech-American Foresters, Workingmen's Council, the Czech-American Unit, and the Voelky (Little Bees), which is the Czech National Alliance women's auxiliary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1388.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Several regular restaurants were operated by ladies of our Free Thought and our Catholic organizations. In a tent operated by the Catholic Ladies, embroidery and various other kinds of handiwork were sold. Ice cream was distributed by ladies of the Royal Neighbors.</p>
   <p>In spite of the large crowds clamoring for accomodation, service was first rate in every respect, and everything went off smoothly, without the slightest disturbance. On this latter point, however, the opinion of the three medieval constables obviously differed widely from ours, for hundreds of offenders were arrested and penalized.</p>
   <p>The great popularity of the Posviceni may be seen by the fact that two people voluntarily undertook the ungrateful roles of impersonating Kaiser William II, and his superhangman Hindenburg. Both these sworn enemies of the Slavonic element rendered highly valuable service to our cause and contributed materially, against their will, to the financial success of our festival. Their pictures, <pb facs="5418478_3_1389.jpg" n="6"/>perfect representations of the crowned head of his nutty "Majesty," and Hindenburg's piggish anatomy were raffled. They became prisoners of the Slavs, and the lucky winners will keep them as souvenirs of this year's national festival.</p>
   <p>This people's festivity may be called a very good financial success, although the proceeds will not reach the high figures of the similar affairs of last year and two years ago.</p>
   <p>Our Catholic organizations and our brothers, the Slovaks, have certainly done all in their power to support the enterprise. They made their appearance in impressive numbers. The pleasant sound of the Slovak language filled the pavilion all afternoon and evening. Slovak native costumes and dances helped to lend color to the scene. The dances were executed by members of the Slovak Educational Club, who were rewarded with reverberating applause. Our Czech national dance Beseda was also presented.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1390.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Sincere Czechoslovaks celebrated a get-together, all inspired by one idea, and fully convinced that only combined efforts spell success for our cause and a better future; that all the sacrifices made by us in our new homeland are placed upon the altar of our most beautiful ideal, which is Czechoslovak independence.</p>
   <p>Several speakers addressed the crowd: Mrs. Julia Hrygh for the district committee of the Czech National Alliance; Reverend Vaniscak for our Slovak brothers; Reverend Jedlicka for the National Alliance of Czech Catholics, and Mr. Vojta Benes, school teacher, for the main office of the Czech National Alliance. Every one of the addresses evoked stormy applause.</p>
   <p>Unlike last year, a pleasant hour will be observed next Sunday in the Park pavilion with yesterday's features repeated, so that those who were unable to take part last Sunday may participate in the pleasant hour, which will be designed as a sort of replica of the festival. Large crowds are again expected.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
