<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-18">June 18, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">[Red Cross Benefit]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0904</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0904.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-06-18">June 18, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">[RED CROSS BENEFIT]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The evening given by the Česká Beseda [Czech Club] in the hall of Harrison High School last night was a splendid affair attended by a crowd that filled every inch of space. The purpose was a humanitarian one--for the benefit of the American Red Cross.</p>
   <p>Mr. Triner opened the evening with a declaration of the aims of the Red Cross. The "Star-Spangled Banner" was sung while the student cadets raised the flag and then gave an exhibition of military drills commanded by Sergeant S. L. Woodword. A selection by Mrs. Valerie Walker Marshall, soprano, was the first number on the program. Mrs. G. E. Gross followed with a lecture on "The Significance of the Red Cross." This took almost fifty minutes and had a fatiguing effect upon the audience, for our Czech groups are excellently informed as to the purposes of the Red Cross and fulfill their duties conscientiously.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0905.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Miss Libuše [Libby] Bartušek, an expert in the classic dances, performed to the music of Chopin and Tchaikowski. Her excellent accompanist was Mr. Edward Vlačiha. Miss Elly R. Kolář sang Czech folk songs and our anthem "Hej Slované!" [Ho, All Ye Slavonic Peoples!], which is now sung everywhere. Mr. V. J. Freund, violinist, played the "A Major Polonaise" by Wieniawski with admirable technique. He encored by playing "Poem" by the Czech composer Zděnek Fibich to the delightful accompaniment of the piano played by Mr. V. J. Černý. Miss Bartušek again appeared on the stage to dance to the folk song "Sil Jsem Proso" [I sowed millet...] which was used by the famous Czech orchestra conductor and composer Oscar Nedbal in his fairy opera "Hloupý Honza" [Silly Hans]. Miss Mary Kryl, daughter of the well-known cornet virtuoso and orchestra leader Bohumir Kryl, rendered "Polonaise, opus 53" by Chopin and "La Campanella" by Paganini-Liszt. Her highly artistic performance ended the program. Mr. Triner thanked the audience for their participation and generosity. The receipts of more than one thousand dollars will go to the Red Cross.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
