<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-21">June 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The Bohemian Section of the Fourth of July Parade Is to Be the Most Magnificent</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1563</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1563.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I F 4</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-06-21">June 21, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOHEMIAN SECTION OF THE FOURTH OF JULY PARADE IS TO BE THE MOST MAGNIFICENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting was held last night by the committee for the Fourth of July celebration. The meeting was attended by many of our prominent and fore-most countrymen.</p>
   <p>The meeting was called to order by the chairman of the committee Mr. John A. Cervenka. The secretary Mr. Ort, read the minutes of the previous meeting, which were accepted as read.</p>
   <p>The secretary read a communication from the singing society Lyra, announcing that the society will be unable to participate because it has already agreed to be present in Svatopluk Cech Park on that day.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1564.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society also declined to take part in the celebration, excusing itself by saying that the Bohemian public knows of the society only when it is needed to serve as a business fanfare for this or that purpose.</p>
   <p>Mr. Karel Vopicka reported that he was successful in securing the services of former Alderman Aling, as speaker. Mayor Harrison also assured Mr. Vopicka that if his wife postpones her visit to the country on that day, that he will also appear. Mr. Vopicka also announced that there will be music in all parks that come under the jurisdiction of the West Parks Commission.</p>
   <p>Mr. Cervenka moved that the allegorical float used on that day be preserved for the Karel Havlicek monument ceremonies. The motion was enthusiastically approved. Mr. Cervenka was then authorized to deal with the Industrial and Historical Company and to find out for what sum this company would rent the <pb facs="5418478_3_1565.jpg" n="3"/>float till the time of the celebration. Mr. Cervenka announced at the same time that the work of constructing the float already has been started and that the skeleton has been completed.</p>
   <p>Mr. Linhart promised to supply caparisons for the horses without charge.</p>
   <p>The election of a marshall for the parade was next taken up. Mr. Karel Vopicka nominated for this honor the chairman Mr. John Cervenka, who was unanimously elected. The selection of his aides was left to the Sokol Gymnastic Unity and the Fuegner Tyrs Circuit.</p>
   <p>In the meantime Dr. J. Vojan, manager of the Bohemian-American Press Bureau, arrived at the meeting and the letter from the Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society was placed before him. He said that the letter, which bore no date, evidently had been written before the last convention of singing societies, where it was definitely decided that the society would take part in the <pb facs="5418478_3_1566.jpg" n="4"/>celebration, chiefly in Svatopluk Cech Park, where several American national songs will be sung.</p>
   <p>Mr. Otto Fuerst and Mr. Petru reported that contributions for the celebration are coming in satisfactorily and there need be no fear so far as finances are concerned.</p>
   <p>There will be excellent band concerts in all parks on the Fourth of July, from three o'clock in the afternoon until seven o'clock in the evening.</p>
   <p>Bohemian societies and participants in the parade will gather at eight o'clock sharp, in the morning, in Svatopluk Cech Park, where both the women and the men can prepare themselves, and from where the women and girls will be transported to Twenty-sixth Street and Wabash Avenue, from which place the parade will proceed along Michigan Avenue to the city.</p>
   <p>Programs of the celebrations in the parks and elsewhere will be published in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
