<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-16">Aug. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Extensive Preparations for the National Pilgrimage</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1271</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1271.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-08-16">Aug. 16, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">EXTENSIVE PREPARATIONS FOR THE NATIONAL PILGRIMAGE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before we know it, the time for our Narodni Pout (National Pilgrimage) will be at hand. In feverish activity the days pass; all preparations are completed, and all that remains now is our concern about the weather. Will it rain? That is the question now, for we have arranged a parade, a parade of such magnitude and variety as has not been witnessed since the days of the liberation of our old homeland. Now, that pageantry will be repeated. Men and women in their peasant costumes will take part in the parade which will also be under police protection. Should any one get hungry while marching, even that exigency has been provided for, there will be pretzel vendors and wiener sausage vendors along who will supply fresh and delectable food furnished by our butchers who were always helpful whatever our national problem happened to be.</p>
   <p>Our friends from Moravian Slovakia will march in the parade together with our brothers, the Slovaks. The whole parade will be flanked during the marching by the sokols, both men and women. Under the banners of the sokols, the parade <pb facs="5418478_3_1272.jpg" n="2"/>will wend its way to its destination--Pilsen Park. Ample provisions have already been made to care for the comfort and refreshment of the marchers after their arrival at the park.</p>
   <p>....There will be enough to drink should thirst bother you, and should hunger disturb you, that too, will easily be cared for, for we shall have a fine variety of foods: roast beef, ham, and sausages galore.</p>
   <p>We have not forgotten the youngsters; they will have their fill of ice cream, popcorn, and whatever else there is that makes a child's heart glad. The older boys and girls will find dancing their chief attraction, but there will be other attractions besides, which will fill your time with pleasure so much so that when the time arrives to go home you will want to stay. The aesthetic needs of man have likewise been provided for. The program prepared by the sokols will be truly grand. There will be folk dances by the Sokol HavlicekTyrs; the now famous "sixteen" by Erben, [Translator's note; A choregraphic gymnastic feature] in which sokols of both sexes will take part; there will <pb facs="5418478_3_1273.jpg" n="3"/>be precision drills by the Pilsen Sokol; "balloon" dances by the members of the Karel Jonas Sokol; the drill of the junior teams; Indian club exercises; in short, it is a program such as one sees on rare occasions. A cabaret has been provided for the older gentlemen, something truly glamorous! Besides our old Rubringer's band, music will be furnished also by the music department of the Sokol Slavsky, and you will have an opportunity to hear them and be convinced of how soothing they are! There will be a circus, something to look forward to; a harmonica player, a "King's shoemaker"; vendors of pickled cucumbers, and the rest of the picturesque falderal usually found at a county fair....You may be certain that everything will keep you cheerful....And when you consider that all this has been arranged for the benefit of the sokols, that is, for the benefit of the whole Zupa Stredni (Central District [of the American Sokol Union]); when you further consider that the admission is a mere fifty cents, you will not wish to stay away, and, indeed, there will not be any [of our people] who would wish to remain at home on so significant an occasion as this. The parade will start promptly (and we mean it!) <pb facs="5418478_3_1274.jpg" n="4"/>at 1 P.M. from in front of the Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs. Let your slogan be therefore: "To Pilsen Park next Sunday; to the National Pilgrimage. "Na Zdar!" (To Success!)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
