<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1909-12-02">Dec. 2, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Harp Virtuoso K. Attl Gives a Concert.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0515</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0515.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1909-12-02">Dec. 2, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">HARP VIRTUOSO K. ATTL GIVES A CONCERT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 1.--No advance advertisements had boosted the name of Kajetan Attl, yet the hall of the Pilsen Sokol was filled to capacity by the music loving public which came without having heard of the youthful harp-soloist, and left with loud praise of his art. They heard him perform on an instrument as ancient as the Bible, but rarely singled out for solo-play. The first number on the program was Trnecek's arrangement of the symphonic poem "Vltava" by Smetana; the excellent recitation assured the success of the concert. The applause following drew the first encore--a transcription of the song "Ach Neni Tu, Neni Tu" for the harp, also by Professor Trnecek; a second encore was the "Majurka in E-flat minor" by E. Schielker. Thunderous handclapping and rich floral offerings rewarded the artist. After this, the phantasy on "Prodana Nevesta" (The Bartered Bride) from the opera by Smetana, for harp solo by Prof. Trnecek, created a sensation, so that the artist encored "Concert Valse" and "Serenade" by Haselman.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0516.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Before, and between these numbers, other artists assisted. The trio Hladky (violin), Kalas (violoncello) and Dr.Greif (piano) gave splendid renditions of the "Elegy" by J. Jiranek, and "Slavonic Dance No. 12" by Dvorak. Mr. Adolf Verst, well known popular tenor and teacher, enriched the program by the recitation of "Ty Hvezdicky," "V Nejiste," and "Oko Tve" by Karel Bendl, as also by "O Thou Art Like a Little Flower," composed by the singer's son Stephen Erst, who is now developing his budding talent in the conservatory of Prague.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hladky's playing of a Nocturno by Chopin evoked salves of applause. The concert was interesting throughout, distinguishing itself from others in that no one of the numbers was even partly tedious to listen to, or too lengthy.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
