<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-01-02">Jan. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">From the Bohemian-American Artistic World</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0506</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0506.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-01-02">Jan. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">FROM THE BOHEMIAN-AMERICAN ARTISTIC WORLD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The famous Czech violin virtuoso, Jaroslav Kocian, rested over Christmas at the cozy fireplace of his manager, Mr. Bohumir Kryl, and is now on a tour from Oklahoma City to San Diego, Cal. He is scheduled for a concert in Chicago, in Pilsen Sokol hall, on Feb. 5, when Miss Marenka Kryl, pianist, will be his assisting artist.</p>
   <p>The exhibition of etchings by the Czech artist, T. F. Simon, at Mr. Roullier's, in the Fine Arts Building in Chicago, on which we reported early in December has closed after having achieved and unusual success. The rows of exhibits grew thinner by leaps and bounds; on the tenth day of the exhibition two-thirds of the etchings had been sold and now decorate American salons. Mr. Roullier proclaimed to us, with joyful satisfaction, that he had not had such success with any other artist. Simons works will often travel to America in the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0507.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Bohemian-American artist, Mario J. Korbel, is now working on a monument for the family Beranek; it will be finished before Decoration Day, when it will be duly admired at the Bohemian National cemetery. It is to be in the shape of a statue over life-size, symbolizing mourning. Another work by Korbel arrived for the Ansonia hotel - a bust of Emmy Destinn. It has evoked much admiration among art lovers, and enthusiasm in the artist herself.</p>
   <p>Boza Umirov, the famous Czech singer, sends greetings to America through this column. We acknowledge by our, and the Bohemian American Press Bureau's best wishes for the artist, who is now curing an ailment, on the shores of the Adriatic sea in sunny Dalmatia;</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
