<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-05">Apr. 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">Comic Opera "V Studni" Presented by the Bedrich Smetana Singing Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0865</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0865.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1920-04-05">Apr. 5, 1920</date>.
<title level="a">COMIC OPERA "V STUDNI" PRESENTED BY THE BEDRICH SMETANA SINGING SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great enemy of every real artist is he who praises everything which is presented to us under the name of art and who writes about every common and sometimes very poor production only in superlative phrases. He quite often awakens vanity, supports a very dangerous grandiosity, and what is worse, destroys young talent right in the formative stage, driving from the temple of arts many who have real talent. This last is almost an unforgivable sin. For a really artistic accomplishment, the usual exaggerated praise is merely censure, because with the continually repeated phrases even the best artistic productions become commonplace, and are brought to the level of average simplicity. The truth about art, more than about anything else, is that that which deserves praise, praises itself. Nothing annoys a real artist more than undeserved praise.</p>
   <p>The Bedrich Smetana Singing Society, which successfully presented the "Prodana Nevesta" (The Bartered Bride) last year, and which decided to present the comic <pb facs="5418478_3_0866.jpg" n="2"/>opera "V Studni," (In the Well), by Blodek, this year, has documented thereby that it considers its own artistic potentiality as first-class and that its aspirations are aimed directly toward the highest and really artistic goal "art for art's sake". No material profit whatsoever accrues to the members from attending the endless and tiresome rehearsals and if it occurs that there is any monetary profit, then they generously waive it beforehand for the benefit of orphans of the legionnaires in Czechoslovakia. Their only reward is that each individual lives through a period of happiness created by the knowledge that he himself has unselfishly contributed his talent upon the altar of the Muses. Therefore, it is only proper to use a different comparison than that which is used for the average commonplace production. But in every case it is necessary to strictly differentiate such a comparison from one-sided reasoning and analytical criticism, because even its main purpose is "art for art's sake" and not to praise in order to be praised.</p>
   <p>Even by such comparison it is proper to label yesterday's presentation of the opera "V Studni" as very successful; and as far as Mrs. Marie Matejicek Ort, as "Lidunka," <pb facs="5418478_3_0867.jpg" n="3"/>and Mrs. Slavka Krejci, as "Veruna," are concerned, it was actually remarkable, although even the other soloists and the chorus itself sang beautifully and were often applauded. Mrs. Matejicek Ort by her personality and by her appearance is pleasing to the eye, and her singing is equally agreeable to the ear. Therefore, each of her appearances should be greeted by us from both viewpoints.....</p>
   <p>Mrs. Slavka Krejci was also excellent in her part as "Veruna". With her full and true alto voice she at once aroused the attention of the whole audience..... Mr. Arno Mario Hess performed his tenor role as "Vojtech" with honor..... Mr. Joseph R. Krejci, as "Janek", also acted and sang well.....Not only the soloists, but also the chorus was remarkable and bore evidence of unusual advancement. The orchestra, under the direction of Mr. Stepan E. Ernst, can with-stand the most severe criticism.....</p>
   <p>In closing, it should be mentioned that despite the unfavorable weather, the Sokol Chicago Hall was sold out and no one regretted that they had not allowed the unfavorable weather to frighten them away from this artistic treat.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
