<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-03-23">Mar. 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Jiskra's Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0497</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0497.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-03-23">Mar. 23, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">JISKRA'S CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday, we had the opportunity to listen to the joint concert of three well-known artists, each of whom individually, is a recognized master on his instrument, and each of whom was able to arouse the enthusiasm of the music-loving public.</p>
   <p>A concert was given in the Pilsen Sokol hall by our artist of the bass violin, Vaclav Jiskra, assisted by his wife, Marketa, who is an artist on the harp, and Alexander Zukovsky, a fellow pupil of Kubelik at Sevciks conservatory, and famous violin virtuoso in Czech circles in Prague. The program began with selections from "Prodana Nevesta" (The Bartered Bride), by Smetana, and the overture, "Vlasta," by Ed. Napravnik, played by Rubringer's orchestra, and augmented by several members of Thomas' orchestra for this occasion. Then followed a solo for the bass violin, "Fantasy of Bohemian National Songs" by <pb facs="5418478_3_0498.jpg" n="2"/>Simandl. In this number, our familiar "Nad Berdunkou Pod Tetinem," played in flageolet tones enthused the audience so that the artist was obliged to add Kukla's Impromptu as an encore. The orchestra then played Dvorak's "Slavanic Dance No. 8," after which Mrs. Jiskra played with deep understanding the Adaggio by Tedesky. The second part of her number was the "Spring Song," by Gounod, which also was received with thunderous applause. Next on the program was Alexander Zukovsky, the Russian artist, who with his beautiful rendition of Wieniawski's "Memories of Moscow" immediately captivated the hearts of the public. As an encore, he played Dvorak's "Humoresque," and took several curtain calls. After Illner's selection "Cechuv Sen," (A Czech's Dream), played by the orchestra, both artists rendered Variations of a Bohemian song by Kukla, solo for the bass violin with harp accompaniment. The enthusiastic applause of the public caused them to respond with an encore, "The Evening Star" from Tannhauser.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0499.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Zukovsky then played Wieniwski's "Legend," Sarasata's "Spanish Dance," and Mozart's "Minuet." The orchestra followed with the Fantasy, "Radhost," by Hausman. Mrs. Jiskra then played a fantasy of American National Songs.</p>
   <p>The last and most effective number on the program was Mr. Jiskra's rendition of a medley from "Prodana Nevesta," and "Hubicky" by Kuchynka. To hear these familiar tunes, lured by the master hand of the artist from his instrument, so rarely used for solo-performances, was a real artistic treat.</p>
   <p>All of the participants received many floral gifts. Mrs. Jiskra was almost overwhelmed with floral offerings. The Circle of Friends, "Z Dvorilost," presented Mrs. Jiskra with a diamond ring and a floral piece.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0500.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Our music-loving public proved by its attendance that it knows how to appreciate the art of our countrymen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
