<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-20">May 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Mayor-Elect of Czechs Inducted into Office on Last Day of Bazaar</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1403</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1403.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-05-20">May 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">MAYOR-ELECT OF CZECHS INDUCTED INTO OFFICE ON LAST DAY OF BAZAAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday was the last day of the bazaar, which had been held for one week and was sponsored by the Czech National Alliance and the National Alliance of Czech Catholics of America. The election of the "mayor of the Czech community" was the center of interest for all those who wished a signal success for the bazaar. The last day was expected to be the most impressive. This hope proved vain, for the bad weather kept many from attending and witnessing the crowning event of the patriotic enterprise. The Pilsen Brewery Park was overcrowded, true enough, during the first hours, but a storm, accompanied by rain which lasted several hours, drove many from the Park, and the last part of the program had to be presented in the pavilion.</p>
   <p>The final contest in the election centered upon three candidates, one man and two women. When at 9 P. M. sharp the result was announced, Mr. Vaclav <pb facs="5418478_3_1404.jpg" n="2"/>(Wenceslaus) Hauser, member of the Sokol group of the Town of Lake,was revealed as winner. He had received 77,990 votes. Next was Mrs. Clara Klaus, member of the Jednota Ceskych Dam (Czech Ladies' Union), with 57,110 votes. Mrs. Anna Stolfa, representing the Sesterska Podporujici Jednota (Sisterhood Aid Society), got 51,930 votes. [Follows a list of candidates with less votes.]</p>
   <p>The winner and the other candidates were greeted with lusty acclaim. They were presented with costly prizes, described in earlier reports.</p>
   <p>A joyful spirit reigned till the bazaar closed. The proceeds of the enterprise will no doubt be large.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
