<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-12">Apr. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">News from the Ludvikovo Divadlo</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0683</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0683.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-12">Apr. 12, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">NEWS FROM THE LUDVIKOVO DIVADLO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The best proof of the popularity which the serial novels published by the Denni Hlasatel enjoy is their utilization in dramatic work. Among them is Klicpera's "Jindra" (Henry), which at the present time is being carefully read by our subscribers and readers. The industrious stage management of the Ludvikovo Divadlo (Frantisek Ludvik Bohemian Dramatic Association) does not allow any opportunity of presenting modern and progressive plays to escape. Impelled by this attitude it secured a work by the authoress, Karla Luzansky. The work in question is the aforesaid "Jindra" which Miss Luzansky dramatized according to a novel of the same name from the pen of Klicpera and published by the Denni Hlasatel. This stage novelty contains all the advantages of dramatic plays, and its production has been effectively worked out. Especially the personalities which appear in the play have been well portrayed by the authoress. No details have been <pb facs="5418478_3_0684.jpg" n="2"/>omitted, and the audience inadvertently experiences the feelings, successes and failures, of the individual characters in the play.</p>
   <p>....In the meantine, the rehearsals continue and guarantee every detail of the play to receive due attention on the part of the players of the company. ....The interest which has been evoked by the play is evidenced by the large number of tickets which have been sold in advance.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
