<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-17">June 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">One of Our Oldest Bohemian Banking Institutions Celebrates the Formal Opening of its New Building</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0057</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0057.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-06-17">June 17, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ONE OF OUR OLDEST BOHEMIAN BANKING INSTITUTIONS CELEBRATES THE FORMAL OPENING OF ITS NEW BUILDING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today, the state bank of Novak A Stejskal, one of our oldest and most reliable banking institutions, celebrates the formal opening of its new offices located at 1817 South Loomis Street, near Blue Island Avenue. It must be remembered that this is not the beginning of a business career, for the firm of Novak A Stejskal has been operating successfully for a great many years. This is only the opening of a new building which will be provided with all the up-to-date features of a modern banking institution, such as safe-deposit boxes, etc.; in short, it will be equipped with everything that a modern bank should have. The bank, having been founded in 1886 as a real-estate, insurance, steamship agency, and mortgage concern, is well known by a great many of our countrymen. Since its inception the business prospered because of its honest dealings, gaining an increasing number of clients from year to year....The business continued to grow so that on January 1, 1921, it became a state bank and was organized according to the laws of our state. Even after this last move the business <pb facs="5418478_3_0058.jpg" n="2"/>continued to grow, and to accommodate its growing clientele its management decided to enlarge its building and equip it with a sufficient number of safe-deposit boxes and other features for the benefit and comfort of its clients. All of the old and new friends of the bank will surely come to inspect the new premises today, and we are sure that they will be pleasantly surprised. For that reason, the bank will be open from 9 A.M. until 8 P.M. and the members of the firm will be happy to greet their old friends.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
