<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-14">Oct. 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Time to Act</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czech Catholics Urged to Attend Festival (Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1463</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1463.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-10-14">Oct. 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">TIME TO ACT</title><title level="a" type="sub">Czech Catholics Urged To Attend Festival (Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The time has come when sincere Czech men and women must do their utmost to help our poor subjugated old motherland, and our work has to be efficient to crown it with success.</p>
   <p>"The sweetest words are mere sound, and love, be it ever so heartfelt, remains but a hollow sentiment. Action is the thing! The war has brought on extraordinary conditions which will require heavy sacrifices from which certainly nobody will be spared. Calls for aid are coming in from all sides. Who would not lend an ear to them? A little bit done by a person will not hurt him much, but will materially help the cause.</p>
   <p>"Not one sincere fellow countryman, therefore, should miss the Czech Catholie National Festival which is held at the Pilsen Brewery Park, 26th Street and Albany Avenue, tomorrow. We all have one common aim--to help accomplish the <pb facs="5418478_3_1464.jpg" n="2"/>liberation of our old homeland!</p>
   <p>"The festival will open with a parade from the Sv. Anezka Ceska (Czech St. Agnes) church, 27th Street and Central Park Avenue, at 1 P.M. tomorrow. The following organizations will be represented: Sokol societies, male and female members, with pupils of the various classes; Slovak societies with Slovak Sokol members; Club Rieger; members of the Roman Catholic First Central Union; the various orders of Catholic Foresters; the Catholic Working-men's Union; school children and various men's clubs and associations.</p>
   <p>"Mr. J. L. Martinka, Mr. Anton Linhart, the members of the subcommittees, and members of the executive committee of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics will head the processions preceded by a band. The parade will move west on 27th Street to Lawndale Avenue then turn into 26th Street, and march east to the Pilsen Brewery Park pavillion.</p>
   <p>"Mr. Hynek Dostal, head of the Catholic Sokol community, Dr. Fr. Jedlicka, vice-president of the Narodni Svaz (National Union), Dr. Milan R. Stefanik, and the Reverend Gregor Vaniscak, O.S.B., will speak.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1465.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"There will be exhibitions by the pupils of Sokol societies from Racine, Milwaukee, and Cudahy, Wisconsin.</p>
   <p>"There will be many entertainments and features of a comic character."....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
