<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-25">Feb. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">First Presentation of Smetana's Masterpiece</title><title level="a" type="sub">Performance of "The Bartered Bride" is a Complete Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0877</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0877.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-02-25">Feb. 25, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FIRST PRESENTATION OF SMETANA'S MASTERPIECE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Performance of "The Bartered Bride" is a Complete Success</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A new and significant chapter has been written into the history of the Chicago Czech singers. After a lapse of twenty-five years, Smetana's ever-stirring "Prodaná Nevňsta" (The Bartered Bride), a comic opera in three acts from the libretto by Karel Sabina, was presented again. It has frequently been stated, and justly so, that this work is the pride of the Czech people--the very symbol of Czech opera. The Pňvecká Spolecnost Bedřich Smetana, a group of conscientious singers, deserves commendation for having promoted the presentation of the opera. This group has initiated and carried out many musical performances which stand high above the plane of our standard presentations. As evidence of this, we need only recall the excellent production of Blodek's "V Studni" (In the Well), Loewe's oratorio "Jan Huss," Dvořák's "Svatební Košile" (The Bridal Shirt), "Golgotha," and others.</p>
   <p>"The Bartered Bride" was sung and played in a manner worthy of a professional <pb facs="5418478_3_0878.jpg" n="2"/>performance. There are performances which are never to be forgotten. There are moments when emotions soar high above the ordinary level. To these belongs last night's performance. The auditorium was filled to capacity; the atmosphere was surcharged with joyous anticipation. All this demonstrated how our public prepared to pay homage to the memory of the tragic giant, the creator of modern Czech music, the ill-fated Bedrich (Frederick) Smetana.</p>
   <p>When Stepan A. Erst, the conductor, drew from the orchestra the first bars with which the immortal overture begins, our hearts began to throb and tears stole into our eyes. We felt instinctively that at last we were presenting this marvelously beautiful, this flower of Czech operatic creation, for ourselves. This was the first Czech opera to melt the ice of unfavorable opinion [held of us] foreign lands, and the only one to herald, in America, the maturity of Czech art.</p>
   <p>The overture to "The Bartered Bride" is a masterpiece, which is played by orchestras all over the world, including our own Thomas Orchestra [now the <pb facs="5418478_3_0879.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago Symphony Orchestra], which keeps it on its standard repertory. Since Mozart composed the overture to the "Marriage of Figaro," nothing as ingenious and perfect has been written in the realm of music. The overture excellently fulfills its purpose; it evokes a merry, genial mood and presents in condensed form the action of the opera. Mr. Erst performed veritable miracles with his orchestra of but twenty-four pieces, composed of members of the Thomas Orchestra and some of our local Czech virtuosos. The overture sparkled with all the colors of Smetana's score.</p>
   <p>As the curtain went up, and groups of boys and girls in the colorful attire of Czech peasants sang the introductory chorus, "Proc Bychom Se Netesily?" (Why Shouldn't We Rejoice?), the audience was visibly moved. Despite a shortage of male voices, the chorus seemed well-balanced and removed any misgivings about the ability of the singers to succeed in so great an undertaking as the presentation of "The Bartered Bride". Every listener felt that this was due to the efforts and tireless rehearsing of the singers and conductor alike.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0880.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The choice of the soloists must be called a stroke of luck. The role of Marenka (Mary) in which some of our greatest grand-opera singers have starred, was sung by Miss Jessie K. Zeman, who possesses all the necessary qualifications; she is pretty, she is a charming actress, and, above all, she has a gorgeous voice, beautifully trained. Last night's appearance was surely the greatest success the young artist has won up to now. The applause showered upon her throughout the evening was only the reward of sincere and conscientious artistic efforts.....The part of Jenik was sung by Arno Mario Hess, that of Vašek by Mr. Adolph Erst, Kecal by Mr. Joseph R. Krejcí, and Esmeralda by Mrs. Slávka Krejxí. Everyone of these, as well as the minor parts, was well sung. The role of Principál was played with delicious humor by Mr. Suva.</p>
   <p>The dances had been rehearsed under the direction of Mr. Paskovský. The stage was under Mr. Jindrich Weidner's masterly direction.....</p>
   <p>Many visitors had come from other cities. There was a party from the Chicago Grand Opera Company, led by Mr. Francesco Daddi.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0881.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Dr. J. S. Vojan, one of the real connoisseurs of Smetana's music, was very helpful in the preparations for the evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
