<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-02-03">Feb. 3, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Veteran Actor Honored</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0820</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0820.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-02-03">Feb. 3, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">VETERAN ACTOR HONORED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P.2--The flower of Bohemian society is expected to be present at the Garrick Theater next Sunday to render homage to a most deserving man and to celebrate a jubilee the like of which we have never before seen, and which even in the land of our origin, is of rare occurrence. On this occasion Frank Ludvik's completion of fifty years of activity as the director of the permanent Bohemian theater in Chicago will be commemorated.</p>
   <p>It will be honor accorded to one to whom honor is due. Mr. Ludvik began his artistic career when Bohemian sentiment and national consciousness needed to be awakened, and it is certain that he has accomplished very much along this line. In those days Bohemian books and Bohemian actors were the only friends to cheer Bohemian immigrants and save them for a better future. And for Bohemian-Americans this Bohemian theater still remains an important national and educational institution. Our veteran artist had the ambition and the energy to make his foundation accomplish the utmost possible good, and the effect of its activities penetrated all strata of our people and perpetuated their love for the land of their birth.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0821.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>However, not only as a national worker but also as an artist Mr. Ludvik deserves that his jubilee shall be a magnificent manifestation of the gratitude which the Bohemians of Chicago owe to him. Whoever has attended the performances in our theater--and what Bohemian has not?--must inevitably remember with pleasure, those delightful characterizations, informed with life and elaborated in their minutest details, which Ludvik has created on the stage. In both comic and serious parts he has proved himself to be, the talented, assiduous artist; and as such, he should be saluted on next Sunday.</p>
   <p>The personal, human side of Mr. Ludvik's character is so attractive, that every one who comes in contact with him becomes his friend. His modest manners, cheerful temperament, and sincere address, win for him daily the good will of new acquaintances.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
