<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-06-26">June 26, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The Homan Theater</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0698</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0698.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-06-26">June 26, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE HOMAN THEATER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After several unsuccessful attempts, Mr. Brecka, proprietor of the Homan Theater, finally succeeded, thanks to his spirit of enterprise, in establishing of a permanent Bohemian vaudeville theater, where Bohemian vaudeville artists appear daily on the stage. The best proof that his efforts were crowned with success is the fact that this popular theater is filled to capacity every day.</p>
   <p>The success of this enterprise can be attributed to the carefully selected programs, but more so to our clever actors of whom Mr. and Mrs. Suva, Miss Adamek, Mrs. Stritecky, Mr. Keclik and Mr. Janota, are the most notable. Let us hope that our art-loving people will patronize this theater regularly and that they will see to it that this enterprise, so beautifully started, will not meet the fate of many others which were forced to close down because of public indifference.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0699.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The play presented was the well-known life portrayal "Zlata Svatba na Fare" (Golden Wedding at a Parish House) which, on several occasions, has been presented by the Ludvikovo Divadlo with great success. In this play Mrs. Kozlansky takes the part of a charming aged woman whose golden wedding anniversary is the most touching scene in this very interesting play. She presented it with a great feeling.....</p>
   <p>On several occasions we had occasion to mention this play, and it needs be added only that last night, too, it was fully appreciated, thanks to excellent stage management.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
