<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-08">May 8, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">The First National Bank of Cicero</title><title level="a" type="sub">Celebrates Grand Opening</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0077</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0077.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1921-05-08">May 8, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIRST NATIONAL BANK OF CICERO</title><title level="a" type="sub">Celebrates Grand Opening</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Despite his age, the old gentleman, Mr. William Kaspar, president of the Kaspar State Bank, Blue Island Avenue and 19th Street, is still a young man. He proves it by his spirit of enterprise and by his agility. He knows very well that the Bohemians are thrifty people. He also knows that the Bohemians are slowly moving westward, and that, in the near future, the largest Bohemian settlement will be in Cicero. Therefore he was convinced that this new settlement some day would be in need of a strong banking institution where the people could deposit their savings. He conceived the idea of establishing a bank for that purpose. Being farsighted, he bought a piece of land at 22nd Street and Austin Boulevard. He could have selected a more thickly populated location, but he did not do so because he was sure that once he began to build at 22nd Street and Austin Boulevard he would be followed by many others. And he was not disappointed in his expectations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0078.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Today, the bank building stands, and in its neighborhood great building activity can be seen. The construction of the First National Bank of Cicero cost Mr. Kaspar the sum of five hundred thousand dollars. It is a beautiful building facing 22nd Street.....</p>
   <p>The president of the new bank is Mr. William Kaspar, a well-deserving countryman, who has been in banking business for the past thirty years. The vice-president and the chairman of the board of directors is his son, Mr. Otto Kaspar, and his second son, Mr. Evzen Kaspar, is the cashier.</p>
   <p>Yesterday the First National Bank of Cicero celebrated its grand opening. There were many floral gifts brought by the people who came to congratulate Mr. Kaspar and his family.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
