<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-11-23">Nov. 23, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">Silver Jubilee a Significant Celebration of the Knights of St George Lodge #39.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1601</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1601.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1903-11-23">Nov. 23, 1903</date>.
<title level="a">SILVER JUBILEE A SIGNIFICANT CELEBRATION OF THE KNIGHTS OF ST GEORGE LODGE #39.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A society, which can boast, that it has operated beneficiently for twenty-five years, and that through the entire period all of the brothers of said lodge have stood steadfast and true in a powerful, compact organization, so that after twenty-five years it stands in the forefront of other lodges, as in humanitarianism so in patriotism; such a society decidedly is deserving of the respect and admiration of all. Glancing in retrospect upon the long activity of the Knights of St. George, it is impossible to say otherwise than that they always proceeded in the manner their duty dictated, that is; charitably and patriotically.</p>
   <p>The celebration began at eight o'clock in the morning. The lodges, taking part in the Czechoslavak American Hall on 18th Street and from there marched to the elevated railway, where the arrival of the Knights and Cadets of the <pb facs="5418478_3_1602.jpg" n="2"/>St. Louis and Cleveland lodges were awaited. Thereafter the entire imposing parade moved to the St. Procopious Church, where mass was celebrated for both the departed and the living members of the society. The parade was lead by the celebration marshall, Mr. J. Cermak, and his assistants. Following them was a company. of police after which came nine lodges with Jos. Macha's band at the head. Then the parade marched again to the Czechoslovak American Hall, where it disbanded. The celebration was continued in the evening in the Czechoslavak American hall. Although the start of the special program of the celebration was set for 7.30, the hall was almost overfilled with invited society long before 7.00 o'clock. At 7.30 a concert was begun by the orchestra under the direction of able Mr. Dostal. Mr. J. Mathaus, the chairman of St. George Lodge No. 39, was then introduced to those present, whom, he welcomed in the name of the lodge. The speaker of the occasion was Rev. Jan Vranek. Rev Vranek is a speaker to whom, it is a pleasure to listen. Timely and energetically, in truth with knightly words, spoke Mr. Jan Cermak. Jan Cermak has been commander of this society for over twenty years and is well liked by his fellow-members.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1603.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Several more speakers followed one another and the program was ended. A particularly profound impression was made by the rendition of our national hymn Hej Slovane, which the orchestra intoned after Rev. Vranek's speech. At midnight the majority of those present left to partake of an exceptional supper, after which, a pleasant and hearty entertainment was renewed in the hall and lasted until the early morning hours.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
