<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-03-27">March 27, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">The Loan Association and Their Pioneers - the Bohemians.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0341</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0341.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1883-03-27">March 27, 1883</date>.
<title level="a">THE LOAN ASSOCIATION AND THEIR PIONEERS - THE BOHEMIANS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Sunday's Tribune brings much information of the loan associations founded in Chicago and prospering successfully until now. In the first lines of the correspondence the Tribune states that the Bohemians are pioneers in these associations and writes verbatim:</p>
   <p>"In the last nine years there were founded in Chicago more than twenty loan associations. None of them was struck by any misfortune or disaster, and the continuity of the success of these associations is so well known that new ones are still being organized.</p>
   <p>"The Bohemian citizens in Chicago are the first to prove the usefulness of this mutual aid and cooperation. One of the Tribune's reporters was yesterday informed by Vaclav Kaspar, an intelligent and well to do Bohemian who has been living in Chicago over twenty years, that there are in our city fifteen "Bohemian Loan Associations." The first of these associations was founded nine years ago and exists until now under the name "The Chicago Bohemian Building and Loan Association, No. 1."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0342.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Its capital amounted to $250,000, however, there were sold shares for only $150,000. All the shares were redeemed and the first series put on the market four years ago. The second series is right now in progress and represents a capital of $250,000. This will be redeemed in eight months. The second association of the same kind was founded by the Bohemians and denominated with No. 2. Its shares are limited to $250,000, and of this amount $230,000 is already redeemed. After this, followed the organization of associations No. 3 and 4. As it seems, those four associations are the most wealthy ones among the Bohemian Building and Loan Associations." All associations founded later reduced the amount of invested capital and grew popular and so as to be easily distinguished called themselves by well known Bohemian names. The last founded association is "Tabor," which name is extremely popular among all Bohemians; it is four months in existence. Its limited capital amounts to $500,000 and $200,000 are already secured.</p>
   <p>Mr. Kaspar further furnished the following data: In the last nine years the Bohemians have erected over 600 buildings, in all cases subsidized by the Bohemian Building and Loan Associations, which are operating with a deposited amount of money close to $2,700,000. All of them are honestly and expertly managed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0343.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There are in Chicago over 35,000 Bohemians and all have a great tendency to buy real estate and to build a little house, to be able to call it their own homestead. Our main idea in the loan association is to help each other, consequently we lent the money to our members. The success of the loan association is based on economic and honest management; we don't pay high salaries, and every member of the committee supervises the regularity of the deeds and inspects, that not a single dollar is wasted and that sufficient security is given for the loaned money. These loan associations have increased in membership over the whole City of Chicago. Germans and Irishmen started to organize them after our model and there exists even an English loan association called "The Garden City Equitable Loan and Building Association." "In my opinion," says Mr. Kaspar, "all those associations must achieve a desirable success if they are managed cautiously and carefully. The money should not be wasted on expensive printing, for magnificent offices, for high salaries, and the money should be loaned only to such people who offer a sufficient and sure security. The Bohemians are a very economical people and their loan associations operate well and profitably for their members, because they are managed with experience, economy, and skill."</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0344.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>This article in the Tribune will certainly concern the local financial circles because many of our countrymen have withdrawn their substantial savings from the local banks.</p>
   <p>It is worthwhile to mention that the founder of the first loan association was Mr. Bobacek who came to Chicago from Cincinnati ten years ago and persuaded the three Novak brothers, Joseph, Francis, and Anthony, to found a loan association in Chicago, modeled on the same kind of institutions operated by the Germans in Cincinnati. They all four organized an association and the first secretary of it was Alexander Purer, at present a notary public and real estate and insurance agent.</p>
   <p>Lately there were dissolved three "Bohemian Building and Loan Associations:" Ceskylev, Vlastimil, and Slovan, principally on account of insufficient number of members.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
