<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-12-11">Dec. 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Grand Concert Given by the Czechoslovak Tailors' Union</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0392</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0392.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-12-11">Dec. 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">GRAND CONCERT GIVEN BY THE CZECHOSLOVAK TAILORS' UNION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Pilsen Park pavilion was the scene of an unusually large throng of people yesterday afternoon, on an occasion which will not soon be forgotten. It was a grand concert arranged by the Ceskoslovenska Krejcovska Unie (Czechoslovak Tailors' Union) Local No. 6 of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. The throng attested not only to the workers' solidarity which exists among the members of this Czechoslovak union, but it also was proof of a universal feeling of friendship which is borne for this organization by our people.</p>
   <p>The Krejcovska Unie has on several occasions appeared before our public, and its concerts are always a season event. But as regards yesterday's performance, we may say without exaggeration that it surpassed all previous ones, and that the Krejcovska Unie never before presented anything <pb facs="5418478_3_0393.jpg" n="2"/>so imposing. It is seldom that an entertainment committee is able to compress within one afternoon such a variety of artistic numbers as was the case yesterday. It was really several concerts rolled into one. And all this was done with the utmost good taste. No wonder the attendance was great, and that, there was standing room only.....The orchestra, which was under the superb direction of Kapellmeister Rubringer, played the compositions of Rossini, Flotow, Smetana, and von Suppe..... The selection of soloists was no less fortunate; we might say that it was exceedingly fortunate. The following well-known artists vied with each other for the plaudits of our public: The violinist, Mr. Eduard Freund; the contrabass viol virtuoso, Mr. Vaclav Jiskra; the incomparable mistress of the harp, Mrs. Marketa Jiskra; the vocalistic phenomenon, Mr. Arno Balda; the congenial team of ballet dancers, Mrs. Lora Sadursky and Mr. M. Kuderoff; and the excellent cornettist, Mr. Eduard Masacek.</p>
   <p>A very appropriate poem titled "Bud praci cest" (All Honor to Labor) was recited by Sister Pavia Prochaska, and our representative choral society, the <pb facs="5418478_3_0394.jpg" n="3"/>Cesko-Delnicky Pevecky Sbor Lyra (Lyra Bohemian Workingmen's Singing Society) gathered its laurels again. There were about forty singers from that Society. They sang B. Smetana's ever beautiful composition, "Veno" (Bequest), a work of art which will remain impressed on our hearts as has everything else that that great master of ours composed. The Lyra Society also sang several effective folk melodies.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
