<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-05-29">May 29, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">"May Pole Dance" Entertainment Given by Pilsen Sokol School</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1569</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1569.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1910-05-29">May 29, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">"MAY POLE DANCE" ENTERTAINMENT GIVEN BY PILSEN SOKOL SCHOOL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A splendid entertainment was held last Saturday evening in the large auditorium of the Pilsen Sokol Hall, on Ashland Avenue, near 18th Street.</p>
   <p>The hall was decorated with various kinds of flowers, colored lights and flood lights which set off its beauty very effectively. The women who took part in the decorating of the hall certainly are deserving of credit for their painstaking efforts and also the girl gymnasts who helped to make this a gorgeous decoration.</p>
   <p>The reception committee consisted of Maria Hora, Antonia Stulik, Orgo Vrana, Marty Fiala, Matilda Blaha, and Emily Vytlacil.</p>
   <p>Many thanks to the arrangements committee and the favorable weather for this successful entertainment. The most interesting event of the evening was the "May Pole Dance".</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1570.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was indeed a pleasure to see the twenty four girls of the Pilsen Sokol gymnastic class perform the dance, all dressed in white.</p>
   <p>It certainly will be remembered in the minds of those who attended this affair. The twenty four "May Pole" dancers were: Martha Fiala, Bertha Knaizl, Lillian Zima, Julia Kopat, Olga Vrana, Frances Godfried, and Misses Scheffel, Levi, Petak, Jennie Rehak, Ella Donat, Mildred Sokol, Josephine Zahrobsky, Jean Kraml, M. Kudrna, Jennie Hora, Francis Kadlec, Anna Pavlicek, Tillie Blaha, Emma Vytlacil, E. Stulik, Rose Hurt, Victoria Hurt, and Anna Donat.</p>
   <p>At midnight a delicious luncheon was served in Bohemian style and it was enjoyed by everyone. After luncheon, the hall was open to those desiring to dance. The affair lasted till daybreak.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
