<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-04-09">Apr. 9, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The American State Bank</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0264</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0264.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1911-04-09">Apr. 9, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE AMERICAN STATE BANK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The new Bohemian enterprise, "The American State Bank," enjoys the confidence of our public, as was indicated during the very first days of its existence. The receiving tellers of the bank have their hands full accepting deposits, the president, Mr. John Karel; the vice-president, Mr. C. R. Walleck; and the cashier, Mr. J. F. Stepina, can hardly keep up in welcoming; their old business friends, who come to the new undertaking, bringing their savings and entrusting them to the new bank with the conviction that they will be safely deposited. The names of the officers of this new financial institution, the large capital at its disposal, and the names of all the shareholders are a guarantee of the soundness of the bank. Our foremost businessmen, our most distinguished citizens, joined their forces in order to provide our public with a modern banking service, so that Bohemian capital deposited in their bank might be safeguarded <pb facs="5418478_3_0265.jpg" n="2"/>better, and at the same time be used to support Bohemian enterprises, and increase Bohemian prosperity. Everyone who visits the bank can convince himself as to its practical arrangement, its excellent management, and its equipment with all modern safety devices.</p>
   <p>The activities during the first few days of the bank's existence are definite proof that such a bank is needed among us, and that it is assured a great success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
