<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-01">Nov. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Sokol Komensky Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1513</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1513.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1915-11-01">Nov. 1, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">SOKOL KOMENSKY FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Due to the efforts of a few energetic enthusiasts, a new Sokol unit was founded here five years ago. Its particular purpose was to give the youth from Moravia an opportunity to concentrate under a Sokol flag and to follow together the great aims set for us by the modern heroes of Bohemian history, Fuegner and Tyrs. The brother founders have given evidence of their national enlightenment by giving the new unit the name of the great teacher of nations, Jan Amos Komensky (Johannes Amos Comenius), and the evidence of their thorough understanding of the Sokol ideas might have been seen in any of the festivals and public drills of the units.</p>
   <p>The Sokol Komensky crowned its activities yesterday when, with a large attendance of the public, it celebrated its fifth anniversary and unveiled a gorgeous new flag.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1514.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The festival was held in the park of the Pilsen Brewing Company at the corner of 26th Street and Albany Avenue, and its success clearly indicates the public sympathies which the Sokol has known how to gain in the short five years of its existence.....</p>
   <p>The festival proper was preceded by an imposing parade in which a multitude of members of brotherly Sokol units marched, and many deputations, automobiles, and carriages joined. It started from Pulaski Hall on Ashland Avenue, and marched to the martial music of a number of bands.....</p>
   <p>The program of the festival started about half-past three o'clock in the afternoon in Pilsen Park pavilion, which was filled to overflowing with the public.....</p>
   <p>After the speech of the Matka Praporu (Mother of the Flag), the most important part of the festival took place--the unveiling of the flag itself. The flag is a thing of singular beauty. Made by Mr. Dittert's <pb facs="5418478_3_1515.jpg" n="3"/>well-known firm, it is adorned, in addition to many other ornaments and embroidered slogans, with a bust of Komensky....</p>
   <p>After its unveiling, the flag was placed in the hands of standard bearer, Brother Chalabala.....</p>
   <p>The next event on the program was a public drill of the pupils of the Sokol school, young boys and girls.....</p>
   <p>The success of the festival will no doubt be repeated by many a similarly successful undertaking in the future years.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
