<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-14">July 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Czech Artist Honored by the Governor</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0359</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0359.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-07-14">July 14, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">CZECH ARTIST HONORED BY THE GOVERNOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Tribune reported in yesterday's issue on the appointment by Governor Frank Lowden of Prof. Albin Polášek as a member of the State Art Conservation Council. It is surprising that not one Czech language newspaper of Chicago took notice in its columns of this item. The Denní Hlasatel was unable to print the news as it learned about it after its deadline.</p>
   <p>Albin Polášek was born in Frenštát in Moravia. He showed signs of artistic inclinations at an early age, devoting himself to wood carving, and later to the creation of ornamental work.</p>
   <p>He came to the United States in 1901, landing in New York, from there he moved to Minnesota, and later to La Crosse, Wisconsin. In this town he <pb facs="5418478_3_0360.jpg" n="2"/>specialized in carving wood statues for churches. He was a wood carver up to that time. Not until 1905 did he begin to study the art of sculpturing. This he did in Philadelphia, and after one year of study, he was awarded a first prize. He held the Cressen Traveling Scholarship from 1907 to 1909, which enabled him to visit the main art centers of Europe.</p>
   <p>In 1910, while working in Rome, Italy, he was awarded the "Prize of Rome," the highest distinction within the reach of students of the Academy of Art in Rome. It carried with it not only a yearly stipend of $1,000, but free lodging, light, heat, and free tuition. Polášek enjoyed these extraordinary privileges for fully three years. He returned to America in 1913 to settle in New York, where he established himself at 9 McDougal Alley. After a brief sojourn in Baltimore, Maryland, he received and accepted a call from Chicago to become a professor and director of the Department of Sculpture at the Art Institute. In this capacity he still functions. His predecessor was the well-known artist, Mulligan.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0361.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Honors galore were showered upon Polášek; among them: at the Paris Exposition, the San Francisco World's Fair, and at other occasions. He is a member of the Metropolitan Museum of New York, the Academy of Arts of Philadelphia, of the Society of Sculptors, and the Architects' League of New York. He opened his studio in Chicago at 6114 Stony Island Avenue.</p>
   <p>He enjoys great popularity among his students, not only for his great artistic achievements, but for his quiet, unassuming ways as well. He is a sincere son of the Czech people, representing himself as a Czech on every occasion. In a recent interview, granted to a representative of this paper, he declared himself to have been an enthusiastic member of the Sokol associations.</p>
   <p>[Translator's Note:- At present, Polášek's studio is located adjacent to the Medinah Temple. The statue of "Music" and the desk, representing musicians of the Chicago Symphony Orchestra, are his work. They are placed in front of the Art Institute.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
