<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-01-28">Jan. 28, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Friml's Recita</title><title level="a" type="sub">Famous Bohemian Pianist and Composer.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1034</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1034.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1907-01-28">Jan. 28, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">FRIML'S RECITA</title><title level="a" type="sub">Famous Bohemian Pianist and Composer.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p.1-Col.1--Yesterday evening Mr. R. Friml gave a recital at the Pilsen Sokol Hall. This was his first public concert, and to judge by the enthusiasm of the audience, it was very successful. All who attended this concert wonder why Mr. R. Friml has not given them such a treat long before this. His selections were some of the most difficult compositions, which only a few pianists in the world can play.</p>
   <p>Mr. R. Friml has attained great fame and can by no means be compared with an ordinary pianist. He is considered one of the finest concert pianists in the world. Many of his compositions are also gaining him fame.</p>
   <p>His interpretation of the songs which he played was so sympathetic that the audience was tense and spell-bound through the greater part of the recital. Mr. Friml is an artist when it comes to concert or classical music which requires sound effects.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1035.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In one of his numbers he reproduced the sounds of rippling water, rolling thunder, and the lightning-stroke. Into each number, in fact he introduced tone-color to make it realistic, thereby rendering his performance pleasing to the ear and easily understood.</p>
   <p>Mr. Friml's recital was one of the finest which the public has ever had the good fortune to hear. The audience included many prominent Bohemian persons, critics of music, and talented musicians who marveled at the pianist's technique and thoroughly enjoyed his performance.</p>
   <p>Mr. Friml played not only with the music touch of the trained virtuoso, but also with his soul, putting deep feeling into his interpretation.</p>
   <p>This feeling was what made his performance distinguished and fascinating.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1036.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Those who attended last evening's recital hope that this is not the only concert which Mr. Friml has planned to give. They want to hear more recitals like it and their enthusiasm was displayed in the tremendous applause which they accorded to the artist.</p>
   <p>The Bohemian people of Chicago are very proud of Mr. R. Friml's achievements.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
