<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-12-11">Dec. 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Famous Czech Music Pedagogue Gives a Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0390</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0390.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-12-11">Dec. 11, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">FAMOUS CZECH MUSIC PEDAGOGUE GIVES A CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Jiri Hrusa, who has won flattering renown in our Bohemian art colony as a famous virtuoso, and also as a conscientious music pedagogue and conductor of symphonic orchestras. He arranged a series of concerts during the past season, and appeared before the Czechoslovak public again yesterday. This time the scene of his musical activity was the Sokol Chicago Hall on South Kedzie Avenue. The symphonic orchestra consisted of about fifty members, all of whom were his pupils, two of them being famous musicians in their own rights: Mr. Vaclav Jiskra and Mr. Jaroslav Gons. Besides these local talents, the orchestra was composed of some of the foremost members of the Chicago Symphony Orchestra; thus achieving, as a group, a selection of artists truly outstanding and, more important, excellently teamed up.</p>
   <p>To listen to their presentations would, no doubt, be a rare treat even to those whose standards of music appreciation are very high. The contents of the program itself bore witness to the high artistic caliber of the conductor of the symphonic concert. The numbers were mainly classical though many of them were <pb facs="5418478_3_0391.jpg" n="2"/>popular. The program contained the following works: Nikolai's overture from "Merry Wives of Windsor"; [Peter Illich] Tschaikowsky's "Andante" from his "Fifth Symphony"; Delibes "Valse Lente," "Pizzicato Polka" and "March"; Anton Dvorak's "Indian Lamont" arranged for orchestra; Glazunov's "Meditation"; Jensen's "Serenade"; Rimsky-Korsakov's "Chanson Indou" (Rimsky is best known for his opera "Smiegurotchka") ; Sir Edward Elgar's ensemble work, "Pomp and Circumstance". Each of the numbers was characterized by faultless presentation and perfect harmonization, all of which gave proof of a series of conscientious rehearsals.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
