<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-24">Jan. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Next Bazaar of the Czech National Alliance</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1435</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1435.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1918-01-24">Jan. 24, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">NEXT BAZAAR OF THE CZECH NATIONAL ALLIANCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A meeting was held in the hall of Sokol Havlicek-Tyrs last Monday at which the arrangements committee took charge of the preparations for the next bazaar under the auspices of the Czech National Alliance.</p>
   <p>Mr. Frank J. Kubec, president of the district branch of the Czech National Alliance, opened the session, since Mr. Otto Pergler, chairman of the arrangements committee, was absent. He explained the purpose of the meeting, i. e., to elect officers for the bazaar. He further stated that a vacant store at 3242 West 26th Street has been rented for fifteen dollars per month and is to serve as an office and also as storage place for gifts for the bazaar.</p>
   <p>The bazaar will be held in the Pilsen Brewery Park from May 11 to May 18 of <pb facs="5418478_3_1436.jpg" n="2"/>this year.</p>
   <p>The following officers were elected: Joseph Martinek, 3502 West 26th Street, chairman; Mrs. Julia Hrych, 5721 South Hamlin Avenue, vice-chairman; Joseph Novak, 1825 Loomis Street, secretary; Vaclav Paveza, 2809 South Clifton Park Avenue, bookkeeper. No treasurer was elected. However, it was decided to ask Mr. F. J. Hajicek, a banker, to accept this office. The bookkeeper and the treasurer will receive one dollar for their services for the entire duration of the bazaar. Committees on economy and entertainment were named.</p>
   <p>Secretary J. Novak wanted to know how the proceeds of the bazaar will be handled. Mr. Kubec answered that the district committee of the Czech National Alliance had decided to send the money directly to Europe to be delivered to Professor T. G. Masaryk. Mr. Martinek added to this that the Catholic organizations [members of the National Alliance of Czech Catholics in America <pb facs="5418478_3_1437.jpg" n="3"/>co-operating with the Czech National Alliance] agree with this method of disposing of the money. It was decided that the proceeds from the bazaar would be sent to Professor Masaryk "as a gift from Czechs of Chicago and suburbs to support the action for liberation".</p>
   <p>The secretary was instructed to request the Czech-language newspapers to send representatives to all meetings of the bazaar committee. These will be held the first Monday of each month and will be announced in the Czech dailies.</p>
   <p>Mr. Frydl pointed out that the Czech National Alliance should publish all of its financial reports, since this would promote the success of the bazaar. After a lengthy debate the committee took cognizance of the announcement that the Czech National Alliance will publish the financial reports in its conference at Chicago, February 9 and 10. It was finally resolved to publish the reports on the bazaar at the earliest date possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
