<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1896-12-05">Dec. 5, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">In Unity Is Power, in Power - Health.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0559</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0559.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svornost</title>,
<date when="1896-12-05">Dec. 5, 1896</date>.
<title level="a">IN UNITY IS POWER, IN POWER - HEALTH.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Several patriotically inclined singers have succeeded in originating a new organization, - including all local Bohemian musical artists. This much promising organization started its existence Nov. 1st, under the name of the "Artistic Musical Club." The club was located in the hall of Mr. Belohlavka, a very artistically arranged place and qualified for its purpose. The problems of the new organization are: To congregate in Chicago, all living Bohemian musical artists, to preserve mutual friendship and patriotism, to encourage the activity of musical artists in general, and especially of Bohemian music.</p>
   <p>Among the members of the club are such names as J. Capek, K. Otradovec, V. Machek, F. Hladky, L.Novak, J. Vilim, B. Holub, J. Halamicek and others.</p>
   <p>Chairman - Mr. Capek, vice-chairman, Mr. Halamicek, secretary, Mr. Kasas. We are sure that everybody will congratulate this honorable new organization with great pleasure, so much more so, as until now we were in need of such an organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0560.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The founding of the "Artistic Musical Club" is of enormous importance, when we take into consideration that the day of our patriotic and national resurrection is still far away and we are not so easily intimidated by strange elements.</p>
   <p>Look out, we have in our veins the same Bohemian blood that we were born with and that our hearts are always turning in the direction of our country.</p>
   <p>There is another impulse that perhaps stimulated our musical artists to the great idea of union. Remember that the majority of them are gaining their daily bread from strange hands. -</p>
   <p>If we will organize this way in all professions, we will see very soon a time, where we will represent a nation, capable in any direction and more to better the miserable life of our community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
