<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-23">Apr. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Activities of the Bedrich Smetana Choral Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0680</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0680.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1922-04-23">Apr. 23, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">ACTIVITIES OF THE BEDRICH SMETANA CHORAL SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Pevecka Spolecnost Bedrich Smetana (Bedrich Smetana Choral Society) is actively engaged in the study of the great Czech operas. To secure more funds for the continuation of this study, the Society is now rehearsing for a concert to be given on Sunday May 14, 1922 in the hall of the Sokol Chicago. By its quality the concert promises to be a unique event in our artistic life. The Choral Society is well known to our general public by its production of Bedrich Smetana's "Prodana Nevesta" (Bartered Bride), and also the oparas "V Studni" (In the Well) [by Blodek], and "Hubicka" (The Kiss) [by Smetana]. All these operas have been presented to the local Bohemian-American public in a dignified manner. Not only has the Society played before Czechs, but also before American audiences in the Chicago's Loop (The Garrick and Blackstone Theaters).</p>
   <p>This time the Society has somewhat broken its tradition of playing only <pb facs="5418478_3_0681.jpg" n="2"/>classical operatic works, and is rehearsing a work of a lighter vein. The opera is, nevertheless, to be thoroughly artistic in its presentation and in a sense more elaborate than the usual operatic pieces. The number that the Society is studying now is called "Faust A Markyta" (Faust And Marguerite). Its resemblance to Gounod's work lies only in its name, however. In reality it is a sharp satire which lashes one of the current American problems. Besides Faust, Marguerite, and the obligatory Memphistopheles, two new personalities appear in this new work. They are the daughter of Mephistopheles, called Satanella, and a mysterious pilgrim whose name has for many years been on the lips of every American, a name accompanied by curses or by blessings but never by indifference.</p>
   <p>The most talented local Czech artists have been engaged for the performance, the management of the work rests in expert hands and, therefore, it is truly a promising venture.....Tickets may be secured from Foucek's, Honsik's, <pb facs="5418478_3_0682.jpg" n="3"/>and Pelkan's pharmacies, and in Placek's restaurant. The prices range from seventy-five cents to two dollars.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
