<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-25">Oct. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Art Exhibition Proves Popular</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0627</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-30">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0627.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1914-10-25">Oct. 25, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE ART EXHIBITION PROVES POPULAR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We are pleased to report that the art exhibition at Dvorak Park, which is nearing its close this week, is proving to be very popular, and its popularity is no doubt fully deserved.</p>
   <p>The attendance, although not as good as it should be, has been considered satisfactory, particularly if we keep in mind the prevailing circumstances in our community and the fact that the exhibit presents art, and not fun.</p>
   <p>It is of particular interest that there are good prospects that some of the exhibited works will be sold. This applies especially to the excellent works of Mr. Oldrich Farsky. We are told that Reverend Vaclav Vanek selected three paintings which he expects to buy for the new building of the Bohemian settlement on Lawndale Avenue which is now nearing completion.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0628.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was certainly touching to hear that one of the exhibited paintings is being bought by a simple, poor servant girl. Thus, she has shown much more understanding for art than our nabobs.....She is parting with money earned by hard work and drudgery thus proving that a maid has much better taste and greater love of beauty than many a "great lady"......</p>
   <p>....The exhibition will be open until the end of this week, and if by any chance some of our wealthier people find their way into it, let them show that along with full pockets, they also have a bit of soul and heart by buying a painting....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
