<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-06-11">June 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">The Slavonic Day of Chicago Olympic Games</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1547</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1547.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1913-06-11">June 11, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">THE SLAVONIC DAY OF CHICAGO OLYMPIC GAMES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(From the Bohemian-American Press Bureau)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is significant that the Slavonic Day of the Chicago Olympic Games happens to mark the first anniversary of festivities connected with last year's Sokolsky Slet (Gymnastic Festival) held in Prague.....</p>
   <p>The whole Bohemian nation will be celebrating this great event....and we here in Chicago shall have a splendid opportunity to commemorate it with proper dignity and seriousness. This is the very first time in America when the Sokols have been given a wide open field, an excellent chance to make a public appearance and perform before thousands of non-Bohemian people. Never before have the Sokols been invited to show their strength, their discipline, their national spirit, and their readiness to give all they have for a common interest.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1548.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Prior to this, in staging a performance before the general non-Bohemian public, it was necessary to overcome such difficulties as the securing of an adequate place at a convenient time and the meeting of heavy expenses. All this, what with the only too well-known indifference of the American public, meant taking the risk of large losses.</p>
   <p>In the present case, all this is changed. We have a most suitable place offered us--a huge stadium on the lake front in the shadow of the Michigan Avenue sky line. We have succeeded in securing the most advantageous time conceivable, the best day of the whole Olympic Games period--the first Sunday of this great festival. The management, which has been giving huge publicity to the games for more than a month, will not properly advertise the Slavonic Day and arouse public interest. As it is, the opening of the whole festival has thus been put almost entirely in our hands.....</p>
   <p>Our Sokol units and singing societies have nothing else to do but to come <pb facs="5418478_3_1549.jpg" n="3"/>and fill all Bohemian hearts with pleasure and pride by an exact, well-prepared performance, a thing which they did on a much larger scale just a year ago in Prague. Such a performance as our Sokols can put on is something quite new to the American public. So there is no doubt that with united effort and the good will of all participants, the Slavonic Day will make a strong impression and secure new recognition and prestige for us.</p>
   <p>Things being as they are, it certainly is not necessary to express the apprehension that there might be one single Sokol, man or woman, or one Sokol fledgling through whose veins the Sokol blood is just beginning to pulsate, who would not wish to be among those who will win new laurels for our Sokols and singers and advance the renown of our whole nation on that memorable day, Sunday, June 29.</p>
   <p>As to our singers, there is not one among them who would forget how our Prague and Moravian singers spread the fame of the Bohemian nation by their art, and who would not do his best to see to it that Bohemian song <pb facs="5418478_3_1550.jpg" n="4"/>reverberates with glory here in this distant land, and gains new recognition for our nation among our co-citizens of non-Bohemian origin.</p>
   <p>He who would not thrill with joy over the opportunity of contributing personally to the success of this great event is not worthy to be called a Sokol or a Bohemian singer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
