<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-06">Jan. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The New Year Celebration of the Matice Skolska</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_1488</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1488.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1916-01-06">Jan. 6, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEW YEAR CELEBRATION OF THE MATICE SKOLSKA</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The usual New Year celebration--this is the thirty-third--was held in the hall of the Czecho-Slavonic Benevolent Societies, on 18th Street, by the Matice Skolska (The Central Scholastic Union) in Chicago; and the many well-wishers filled the spacious hall to capacity.</p>
   <p>No one need have regretted his or her appearance at this celebration, because the sprightly pupils of the Matice Skolska saw to it that a program of entertainment and instruction was in store for all who came; the exercises were under the direction of the efficient teacher, Miss Zeman.</p>
   <p>The evening program was divided into two parts; the first included an address, national songs, and comical acts.</p>
   <p>The address was delivered by one of the pupils, Emilie Uxa, and we must admit that she did justice to her theme, "Free Thought Schools".</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_1489.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It must be said that this young lady is a third-generation American, and the beautiful Czech language she used in this address was a pleasant surprise to everyone who heard her.</p>
   <p>Sylvia Zikmund sang a number of very expressive national Czech songs. It is not difficult to listen to her trained little voice. We need hardly say that her songs were well received, and applause not stinted.</p>
   <p>A comic act followed, called "Straspytlicek" (Afraid of His Own Shadow), presented by Bozena Spal and Millie Vitek.</p>
   <p>A second playlet, called "Bazlivy Janek" (Faint-hearted Johnny), was played by Eduard Spal and Olga Cermak and a class of pupils.</p>
   <p>The act was presented by the principals and pupils in such a finished manner that one could not but feel admiration for the very young amateur actors. The polish of their performance is evidence of the drill the little actors went <pb facs="5418478_3_1490.jpg" n="3"/>through to please the audience, which they did very satisfactorily.</p>
   <p>A real treat was forthcoming in the second part of the program, the play "Cinme Dobre Chudym" (Treat Well the Poor). The play is a picture of a Christmas episode, with songs and dances written by the teacher, Miss Zeman, in such a way as to give the more advanced pupils a chance to show their advancement in Czech declamation, in its many verbal and stylistic figures of speech.</p>
   <p>And, last but not least, we must mention the graceful dances and the lovely songs of this Christmas play.</p>
   <p>The play "Treat Well the Poor" was acted by Miss Zeman's pupils with the exception of a few difficult parts, which were filled by more mature boys and girls, graduates from Miss Zeman's classes.</p>
   <p>The cast of the play included a rich woman, played by Blanka Cermak; her children, played by Emilie Uxa and Jan Spal; school friends of the two children just <pb facs="5418478_3_1491.jpg" n="4"/>mentioned, played by Millie Vitek, Jennie Hudec, Josef Zikmund and Jaroslav Cermak.</p>
   <p>The part of a poor widow was played by Anna Cermak; her children, by Sylvia Zikmund, Bozena Spal, Milada Zarobsky, and Helena Zarobsky. Eduard Spal, Stanislav Nosek, Frantisek Nigric, and Ottokar Zarobsky were football players in the play.</p>
   <p>All the actors and actresses had their roles well memorized; so the first scene, showing Christmas bliss, and the second scene, depicting Christmas gloom, both rang true, being very vivid pictures of well-written scenes.</p>
   <p>A group of girls playing the parts of fairies behaved in a fairy-like manner and were very graceful. The fairies were enacted by Olga Cermak, Lillian Fort, Helen Hruska, Louisa Uxa, Marie Shenekl, and Olga and Leola Hudec.</p>
   <p>The forest dwarfs, with their humorous songs, were enjoyed very much; they were <pb facs="5418478_3_1492.jpg" n="5"/>Arnost Zikmund, Raymond Budil, Jaroslav Kolar, Josef Shenekl, Ottokar Zarobsky, Frantisek Migric, Stanislav Nosek, and Eduard Spal.</p>
   <p>After the curtain dropped on the last scene, one of the older pupils, a boy, addressed his teacher with nicely chosen words and commended her for her good work in the interest of the public and indirectly for the public at large. He said that members of her classes had organized a new club, called Jaro (Spring) Number 2; this club expects soon to produce a play called "Zakleta Princezna" (The Enchanted Princess).</p>
   <p>This play, also, was written by the teacher, Miss Zeman, and the speaker asked everyone present to attend the first performance, which will be very soon.</p>
   <p>Then Miss Zeman stepped upon the stage dressed as Saint Nicholas, and every pupil received an appropriate gift.</p>
   <p>The committee deserves credit for the interest shown in this celebration. Those <pb facs="5418478_3_1493.jpg" n="6"/>on the committee were Frantisek Zarobsky, Jenie Schorik, Mrs. Beranek, and Mr. Rosecky. Chairman Nadherny presided at the meetings of this committee.</p>
   <p>The Matice Skolska, with this celebration, has won the plaudits of all right-thinking people, and we desire to express our own approval.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
