<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Czechoslovak Review</title>, Vol. III, No. 4,
<date when="1919-04">April, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce in the United States</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0120</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0120.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Czechoslovak Review</title>, Vol. III, No. 4,
<date when="1919-04">April, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CZECHOSLOVAK CHAMBER OF COMMERCE IN THE UNITED STATES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the present time, all of the Allied Powers have recognized the right of the Czechoslovak nation to independence and sovereign statehood. By virtue of this recognition, there is in existence a Czechoslovak Government. It has been suggested by leading financiers and business men in the United States that in order to strengthen the bonds between this newly recognized nation and America, a Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce be established in this country. The possible functions of such an organization are unlimited. A few of the more important are briefly suggested below:</p>
   <p>To stimulate trade relations between the two countries. It is a well known fact that before the war, Germany was the intermediary for both the export and import trade with the region which forms the new state in question. With this factor removed, it will be the purpose of the proposed Chamber to exert every legitimate effort to promote the interchange of export and imports between the two countries.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0121.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>All available business information of mutual value will be acquired, properly tabulated, and distributed to those interested. This will include trade statistics of such a nature as will enable American manufacturers to determine those products which should find a ready sale in Czechoslovakia; also keep them in touch with industrial, economic, and financial conditions which would have a vital influence upon sales and credits.</p>
   <p>Every effort would be made to inculcate just and equitable principles of trade, and to aid in the passage of beneficial laws pertaining to the commerce between the two countries. Reciprocity and a fine sense of justice and helpfulness should be observed in administering such matters as tariffs, protection of trade marks and patents, ocean freights, import and export duties, postal and parcel post regulations.</p>
   <p>To arbitrate in the event of any commercial misunderstandings or disputes, due to the dissimilarity of language and lack of past commercial relations, a possibility of occasional misunderstanding presents itself. By referring such matters to the Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce to adjust with the <pb facs="5418478_3_0122.jpg" n="3"/>corresponding business organization in the other country litigation, with its attendant expenses and possible loss of good will, may be avoided.</p>
   <p>To promote a medium for bringing together private business interests, organizations, and Conventions between Czechoslovakia and America for the purpose of Advancing their mutual interests. This would be accomplished by bringing before the public matters of educational interest concerning the tremendous trade possibilities with Czechoslovakia and her wide range of resources. Every effort would also be exerted to bring together in conferences such parties as would be interested in initiating business relations with each other, with an aim towards increasing the volume of trade between the two countries.</p>
   <p>To inspire in its members a sense of individual civic responsibility, and an active interest in all national affairs which would tend to strengthen the bonds between the United States and the Czechoslovak Nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0123.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The channels of commercial relations are gradually being opened up with Czechoslovakia and although there are no direct connections at the present moment, it is only a question of a short time when these connections will be opened. Firms interested ought to be preparing now to enter this promising field. As per our former notice, the war trade board announced Feb. 16th, that trade with Czechoslovakia had been reopened subject to the rulings and regulations which apply at present.</p>
   <p>Other good news is that on March 28th, the postal connections have been reopened between Czechoslovakia and America. Also recommendations have been recently made to the peace conference, that the ports of Hamburg on the North Sea and Stettin on the Baltic Sea, which have good boat and rail connections with Czechoslovakia, be opened and made neutral ports of entry to Czechoslovakia. It is hoped that soon American exporters will be able to make regular shipments.</p>
   <p>The Czechoslovak Chamber has men investigating trade conditions abroad and will be able to be in a position to give valuable trade information. Manufacturers and exporters are requested to join our association as sustaining members at $25 per year. Application may be sent to the Secretary.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0124.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Czechoslovak Chamber of Commerce of America, John A. Sokol, Sec'y., 60 East South Water St., Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
