<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Denní Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-03">Dec. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Singers Hold Meeting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418478_3_0889</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-bohemian #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-11-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-31">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0889.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>BOHEMIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Denni Hlasatel</title>,
<date when="1917-12-03">Dec. 3, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">SINGERS HOLD MEETING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our singers are determined not to allow our beautiful Czech songs to be lost. In spite of the burdens which these serious times have laid upon them, our singers are convinced that Czech song should still echo lustily through our new homeland to inspire the people with courage and enterprise. At the annual meeting held by the Ustredni Pevecka Jednota (United Singing Societies), extensive plans were made for the future activities of the Societies.</p>
   <p>The gathering took place at the home of Mr. Hacha, 26th Street and Harding Avenue, and a large number of delegates were present. Some members of the dramatic section of the Societies also took part. Among the singing societies represented were the Karel Marx, the ladies' singing society Maj, the educational and singing society Karel Bendl, and Volnost (Freedom). The session was opened by Mr. Frank Kostka, president of the United Singing Societies.</p>
   <pb facs="5418478_3_0890.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Kostka and Mrs. Antonia Mueller were elected president and vice-president respectively. Mr. Vaclav (Wenceslas) J. Roucek became secretary and Mr. Anton Vanek, treasurer.</p>
   <p>One of the main issues before the assembly was the question of whether the Chicago Symphony Orchestra could be induced to assist in a concert of the United Singing Societies. Mr. Joseph Houdek, musical director of the Societies and of the Cesky Delnicky Pevecky Sbor (Czech Workingmen's Singing Society) and also a member of the Symphony Orchestra, answered that this body's co-operation might be difficult to obtain, but that it is within the realm of possibility. He promised to get in touch with some influential persons to win their good will in this matter.</p>
   <p>The issue concerning the Symphony Orchestra was broached in connection with the planned springtime concert. Mr. Houdek, while visualizing the enhancement of the general qualities and compass of the concert if the Orchestra <pb facs="5418478_3_0891.jpg" n="3"/>took part, declared that the latter, in order to be effective, would have to have at least forty-six musicians, which would increase the costs considerably. The delegates, nonetheless, decided to hire a first-class orchestra, for they are determined to make their springtime concert the most spectacular event of all musical programs ever arranged by the Society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
