<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<!--<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="flpsview.css"?>-->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="FLPSXSLdisplay.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>CFLPS Code Book Electronic Edition</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>Transcribed from the Final Narrative Report, Foreign Language Press Survey
                    Project, 1940.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey, Code Book for Use of Editors and
                        Supervisors</title>
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation marks="all">
                    <ab>All quotation marks retained.</ab>
                </quotation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="hi">Used to mark underlined text in original, except in cases of
                        foreign words (tagged <gi>foreign</gi>), which should also be
                        underlined.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>In the body, the <gi>div</gi> element usually contains a distinct code section
                    within the hierarchy of the FLPS, including the title of the section (marked
                    with a <gi>head</gi> element) and any subsections. Subsections also use the
                        <gi>div</gi> element, so the overall XML tree structure mimics the structure
                    of the code sections.</p>
                <p>The exception to the above includes all <gi>div</gi> elements with a
                        <att>type</att> attribute with the value "description." These <gi>div</gi>
                    elements contain the prose descriptions of their corresponding codes. The
                        <att>corresp</att> attribute is used with these <gi>div</gi> elements to
                    associate the description with the appropriate code section title(s) via the
                    unique ID (<att>xml:id</att>) defined in the <gi>head</gi> element.</p>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2011-06-28">Initial TEI markup by Daniel G. Tracy</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <head>
                <bibl>
                    <title> Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey, Code Book for Use of Editors and
                        Supervisors </title>
                    <respStmt>
                        <name>Thomas R. Hall</name>
                        <resp>Project Superintendent</resp>
                        <resp>Compiler</resp>
                    </respStmt>
                </bibl>
            </head>
            <div type="preface">
                <head>Preface</head>
                <p>When the Foreign Language Press Survey was set up in the autumn of <date
                        when="1936">1936</date>, it was necessary to formulate an integrated system
                    of general subject headings under which the material translated by the project
                    could be classified. This outline had to be sufficiently general in order that a
                    large variety of material from many <gap/> could be placed together; at the same
                    time, of necessity, it had to follow a logical development which would permit
                    persons using the file at a later time to find their material with a minimum of
                    trouble and labor. The project supervisors were fortunate in securing the use of
                    the outline of subject headings prepared by <persName
                        ref="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/2435.html">
                        <roleName>Prof.</roleName>
                        <forename>Bessie</forename>
                        <surname>Pierce</surname></persName>, <orgName>Department of
                        History</orgName>, <orgName>The University of Chicago</orgName>, for
                    research assistants translating material for her <title level="s">History of
                    Chicago</title>. <persName><roleName>Miss</roleName> <surname>Pierce's</surname></persName> 
                    outline, expanded and systematized to suit
                    the project's needs, has served as the basis for the classification of the
                    material translated by this project. Before being placed in use it was submitted
                    to <persName><roleName>Prof.</roleName> <surname>Pierce</surname></persName>, 
                    a member of the project's <gap/> Committee, and received her approval.
                    Since then the only changes have been the addition of a few headings which were
                    found necessary from time to time.</p>
                <p>This code outline serves translators as a guide for selection of material for
                    translation and enables the editors to classify translated articles. The letters
                    and figures provide a system for filling the source material prepared by the
                    project. It is the foundation of the project and the key to the work which it is
                    doing.</p>
                <p>Naturally, during the years that this outline has been in use certain rules for
                    the classification of various types of material have arisen. In order to codify
                    them and, at the same time, provide an explanation of each section and
                    subsection of the outline, this Code Book has been prepared, All persons editing
                    material for this project are expected to refer to it constantly. Uniformity in
                    coding is a vital necessity and editors must not rely on their memory alone for
                    the proper code. Space has been provided after each code for pencil notes and
                    interpretations of the outline so that the book may be kept up to date. Editors
                    are also expected to check the files of prepared translated material to provide
                    themselves with precedents in coding. But this Code Book, if they will refer to
                    it constantly, will be of the greatest assistance in maintaining that uniformity
                    of codes and cross references which is so essential to the project.</p>
                <signed><persName><forename>Thomas</forename> R. <surname>Hall</surname></persName>. Project Superintendent</signed>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Cross References</head>
                <p>Almost every article translated by this project concerns more than one subject or
                    contains certain implications which may be valuable in other connections. For
                    example, an article on the study of foreign languages in parochial schools, in
                    addition to expressing an attitude on a phase of education, may be valuable
                    material for a study of the efforts of the language group to preserve its
                    individuality (segregation). It would consume too much time to look through
                    every note in the files in order to find all the material on any subject.
                    Therefore, a system of cross references has been provided to assist researchers
                    in locating available material which is not coded directly under any one subject
                    heading. These sub-codes are reproduced on 3 x 5 cards, together with the source
                    line of the article and the under which the article is filed. Anyone wishing to
                    get all available material on any subject, after he has examined the articles
                    filed under the main codes dealing with his subjects, can by consulting the
                    cross reference file locate all other articles in the file which contain
                    references to the question he is investigating.</p>
                <p>The principal subject of every article gives it the chief, or main code.
                    Sub-codes are assigned all minor phases of the article which are considered
                    important enough for cross references. It is the responsibility of the editors
                    to select the principal theme of the article, assign the main code in conformity
                    with it, and <gap/> the important minor themes, giving them the codes which <sic>constitutes</sic>
                    the cross references.</p>
                <p>Certain codes will be used quite frequently as cross references (<ref target="#code-III.B.2">III B 2</ref> or
                    <gap/>), others only rarely. One code (<ref target="#code-V.B.">V B</ref>) is never used as cross reference.
                    The only code for which cross reference cards are made when it is the main code
                    is <ref target="#code-IV">IV (Representative Individuals)</ref>. This exception is made so that all material
                    concerning persons placed in this file will be easily available.</p>
                <p>The editor must be the judge of the need for a cross reference. It is impossible
                    to assign an oblique code for every theme of the article, if only because the
                    size of the cross reference file must be kept within reasonable bounds. But, on
                    the other hand, there is no desire to restrict editors in assigning all
                    necessary cross reference codes. Constant reference to the Code Book while editing
                    will make the task of assigning cross references much more simple.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head xml:id="code-I">I Attitudes</head>
                <div type="description" corresp="#code-I">
                    <p>Each foreign-language community in this city has developed certain attitudes
                        toward the institutions of the new home and the problems which it has had to
                        face as a group or as part of a great nation. This is not to contend that
                        each is unanimous in its opinions; divergent interests, different economic
                        strata, and factionalism have brought about differing attitudes on many
                        questions within each group. There is, however, a certain unity in the
                        opinion of each group. <gap/> attitudes toward problems of life in this
                        country, the conflicts which have arisen because of differences between
                        inherited <foreign>mores</foreign> of the old homeland and the of life of
                        the new, are of particular interest in a study of the history of
                        foreign-language communities in <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                        </placeName> and their part in the development of the city.</p>
                    <p>The impact of their influence on the life of <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                        </placeName> and the course of its development is tremendous. Their
                        attitudes toward public questions, customs, and ways of life have had an
                        overwhelming influence. Whether these attitudes are in organized fashion in
                        the polls or whether they are reflected in the daily political, social,
                        economic, artistic and moral life of a great metropolitan center such as <placeName>
                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement></placeName>, they have had much to do with the course of its development,
                        resulting in social phenomena which are not to be seen in more homogeneous
                        "American" sections of the nation. Of course, all of these people are
                        American; they have merely brought with them points of view differing from
                        those earlier immigrants.</p>
                    <p>In order that historians and sociologists may chart the development of our
                        cosmopolitan city, it is necessary that we should collect a great wealth of
                        material which reflects the attitudes of these groups, that is, those
                        thought patterns which influence and mold public opinion among them.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-I.A">I A Education</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.A">
                        <p>The education of youth has, perhaps, created more problems in the various
                            foreign-language communities than any other subject. The nature of this
                            education, its relation to old-country customs, and the questions
                            involved in organizing life in a new environment have been most
                            difficult of solution.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.A.1">I A 1 Secular</head>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.A.1.a">I A 1 a Elementary, Higher (High School and
                                College)</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.A.1.a">
                                <p>The attitude of religious groups in various communities toward
                                    the American public schools has been an important factor in
                                    their life. Some denominations and sects have opposed secular
                                    education and have openly opposed its progress within their
                                    community. Other factions have supported it as a means of
                                    getting ahead in the new country and becoming
                                    "Americanized".</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.A.1.b">I A 1 b Foreign Languages</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.A.1.b">
                                <p>It was natural that many immigrants wished their children to
                                    learn their old language. Some of the more populous communities
                                    felt that their position and strength entitled them to have the
                                    language of the home country taught in the public schools in
                                    their neighborhoods. The controversy between the <ref
                                        target="#grp-bohemian">Czechs</ref> and the <ref
                                        target="#grp-german">Germans</ref> regarding public
                                    instruction in their languages during the last years of the 19th
                                    century <gap/></p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.A.1.c">I A 1 c Taxation for Public Schools</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.A.1.c">
                                <p>Opposition to publicly-supported education has called forth
                                    protest against taxation for public schools. Opponents of public
                                    schools tend to look with disfavor on taxation for their
                                    support.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.A.1.d">I A 1 d Special Endowments</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.A.1.d">
                                <p>This division of the outline applies especially to schools of
                                    higher learning, although financial and other support to all
                                    accredited secular schools is to be <gap/> here. Gifts and
                                    endowments of any sort tend to show the attitude of at least a
                                    part of the community toward education, and also provide a clue
                                    to its economic status.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.A.2">I A 2 Parochial</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.A.2">
                            <p>Parochial schools have played a very important part in the
                                development of the foreign-language communities. Great effort has
                                been made to build <gap/>, in some localities they are used to
                                transmit much of the culture of the homeland.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.A.2.a">I A 2 a Elementary, Higher (High School and
                                College)</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.A.2.a">
                                <p>Those elements which have opposed the public school have <gap/>,
                                    in most instances, the parochial schools. In many cases, the
                                    reverse is true. The desire of the churches to retain a hold on
                                    the youth has produced serious conflicts in the communities. For
                                    these reasons, the attitude of the community or its various
                                    parts toward its parochial schools is deeply significant.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.A.2.b">I A 2 b Foreign Languages</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.A.2.b">
                                <p>Parochial schools are often the vehicle for the transmission of
                                    the old culture, including the language of the old country. For
                                    example, the schools in many <ref target="#grp-polish"
                                        >Polish</ref> parishes teach American-born youngsters the
                                        <ref target="#grp-polish">Polish</ref> language.</p>
                                <p>Conflicts arising between the young born in this country and
                                    their parents who grew to maturity in a different environment
                                    have greatly influenced the development of every
                                    foreign-language community. Therefore, any expression of opinion
                                    <gap/> to the study by the children of the parents' language,
                                    the medium for the transmission of the culture of the homeland,
                                    is most important.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.A.2.c">I A 2 c Contributions</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.A.2.c">
                                <p>This section bears the same relation to parochial schools that
                                        <ref target="#code-I.A.1.c">the section on taxation</ref>
                                    bears to public schools. The feeling which any group or part of
                                    a group may have toward parochial schools is reflected in their
                                    financial and other contributions for the support of such
                                    schools.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.A.2.d">I A 2 d Special Endowments</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.A.2.d">
                                <p>Gifts to parochial schools, for buildings, etc., or in the form
                                    of scholarships, show in what esteem they are held by the
                                    community, or parts of it.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.A.3">I A 3 Adult Education</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.A.3">
                            <p>The problem of giving adult immigrants an opportunity to improve
                                their education has always been an important one, particularly in
                                those communities in which the educational level is extremely low.
                                Many had little or no schooling in the old country and got their
                                first real chance for training in <placeName>America</placeName>.
                                Not all countries have appreciated the necessity of raising the
                                educational level of their members. But awareness of the advantages
                                of additional education for adults is <gap/>.</p>
                            <p>All expressions of opinion for or against adult education should be
                                given this code or cross reference. This includes efforts to get
                                persons interested in night school, free classes, etc. Material
                                coded <ref target="#code-II.B.2.f">II B 2 f (Special Schools and
                                    Classes)</ref> and <ref target="#code-II.B.2.g">II B 2 g
                                    (Forums, Discussion Groups and Lectures)</ref> which refers to
                                adult education should be given this cross code.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-I.B">I B <foreign>Mores</foreign></head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.B">
                        <p>Each nationality brought to this country certain ingrained customs, of
                            which, despite the new environment, it could not rid itself in a day.
                            Certain human ways, common to all peoples, are looked upon by each in
                            different fashion. There was a tendency to pass such customs along to
                            the succeeding generation; even today they are strong in each community.
                            Therefore, it was but natural that these inherited outlooks should
                            influence every foreign-language community in its approach to the
                            problems which were encountered in the new home. Nowhere is this
                            tendency to follow the old ways so strong as in those practices which
                            touch the family and personal life of the individual. For this reason,
                            the reaction of each community to certain problems which are common to
                            all cultures has been influenced by the methods which were used in the
                            old country when these same questions arose. The responsibility of
                            establishing here the moral sanctions which were invoked in the <gap/>,
                            and the great difficulty in adjusting to those of a new society have
                            widened the difficulties faced by the individual in his efforts to fit
                            himself into American life.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.B.1">I B 1 Temperance</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.B.1">
                            <p>Each community has its own point of view on the use of alcoholic
                                liquors and <gap/>, which it has not hesitated to express. In many
                                sections the point of view of the homeland has been transferred to
                                this country more or less completely. It should be noted, however,
                                that this section of the outline has reference to temperance and
                                total abstinence. In other words, the practice of the individual and
                                the practice of the community, not the law of the land, is the point
                                at issue.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.B.2">I B 2 Blue Laws</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.B.2">
                            <p>From the time of their settlement, the colonies which coalesced to
                                form the United States tried to solve certain questions of human
                                conduct by legislative <gap/>. It is not a long step from the
                                compulsory church attendance laws of the <placeName>Massachusetts
                                    Bay Colony</placeName> to the prohibition of alcoholic beverages
                                in our <gap/>.</p>
                            <p>This tradition is different from that of most of the foreign peoples
                                who came to live in <placeName>America</placeName>. Their reactions
                                have influenced the course of our legislation to a great degree. In
                                large part their attitude accounts for the anti-prohibition movement
                                which flourished in large cities while the Eighteenth Amendment was
                                part of the Constitution.</p>
                            <p>This section refers not only to the prohibition of alcohol, but to
                                Sunday Laws and all sumptuary legislation.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.B.3">I B 3 Family Organization</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.B.3">
                            <p>Contemporary <placeName>America</placeName> has seen many problems
                                arise which are closely connected with the family unit. An increase
                                in divorce, the changed relationship of the younger to the elder
                                generation, the employment of women in industry have forced a
                                revision of seemingly age-old standards, with resulting bitter
                                debate. Many migrants find themselves torn between the practices of
                                the society in which they live and traditions which they brought
                                with them from other lands, usages which are often completely at
                                variance with those of their present home. Naturally compromises
                                between these differing traditions have developed.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.B.3.a">I B 3 a Marriage</head>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.B.3.b">I B 3 b Parent-Child Relationship</head>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.B.3.c">I B 3 c Family Economic Organization</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.B.3.c">
                                <p>American business life and standards of living have brought about
                                    many changes in the economic organization of the family. In
                                    part, these very immigrants who are affected have been partly
                                    responsible for this change through their participation in the
                                    development of our industry.</p>
                                <p>Formerly, here as elsewhere, the man was the breadwinner. In a
                                    space of several decades all this has altered. Wives and
                                    daughters have won a place in <gap/>; old-country customs have
                                    not been able to stand up against these rapid developments.
                                    Immigrant parents are bewildered at the sight of their working
                                    daughters; and attempts to re-establish the customs and ways of
                                    the homeland have failed almost completely.</p>
                                <p>Although this development is not peculiar to this country, it is
                                    strongest <gap/>. Psychological and economic problems of the
                                    greatest import have arisen as a result. The judgments which our
                                    alien-born citizens and their descendants have formulated
                                    covering these generations are of considerable value in arriving
                                    at an understanding of our American civilization.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.B.4">I B 4 Religious Customs and Practices</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.B.4">
                            <p>Many groups, such as the <ref target="#grp-jewish">Jews</ref> and
                                    <ref target="#grp-russians #grp-greek">Greek Orthodox
                                    Christians</ref>, brought with them religious customs which they
                                prized and desired to follow. Some of these had to be fitted into a
                                new culture, which resulted in many difficulties. For example, <ref
                                    target="#grp-jewish">Jewish</ref> dietary laws have resulted in
                                a Kosher food industry. The <ref target="#grp-russian">Russian</ref>
                                Orthodox Christian cannot have in this country the tremendous number
                                of religious holidays he enjoyed at home, since American industry,
                                in which most <ref target="#grp-russian">Russians</ref> work, does
                                not permit so many vacations. All these things affected the outlook
                                of the immigrants, were discussed by them, and were taken up by
                                their <gap/>. We want to know how they adjusted themselves, what
                                compromises were necessary, and what syntheses the generations born
                                in this country have effected.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-I.C">I C Own and Other National or Language Groups</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.C">
                        <p>The animosities and friendships which have developed among various
                            nationalities and language groups in their homelands have been reflected
                            in this country. Thus, during the World War, <ref target="#grp-bohemian"
                                >the Czech people</ref> of <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                            </placeName> opposed everything <ref target="#grp-german">German</ref>. These relationships played a
                            large part in our political, economic, and social life. The <ref
                                target="#grp-italian">Italians</ref> and <ref target="#grp-german"
                                >Germans</ref> of <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                            </placeName> have condemned <ref target="#grp-irish">Irish</ref>
                            politicians; various groups are accused of religious bigotry or
                            dangerous economic practices. In a city where each national group is
                            something of a little world such opinions are important.</p>
                        <p>This section of the outline will receive a large number of
                            cross-references <gap/> the group opinion may be but a minor phase of an
                            article concerned chiefly with other subjects. It should be borne in
                            mind that an action may reflect an opinion of one group toward another
                            which has not been expressed in words. Thus, a demonstration of one
                            group against another may show the attitude of the demonstrating
                            group.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-I.D">I D Economic Organization</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.D">
                        <p>Many millions came to <placeName>America</placeName> because they could
                            not earn a decent living at home under conditions prevailing in their
                            homelands. In this country the peasant became a factory-worker, while
                            the intellectual was often forced by circumstances into manual labor.
                            Arriving with certain attitudes toward the modern industrial system, or
                            perhaps with no clear cut idea of it at all, these immigrants were
                            thrown into an entirely different economic environment.</p>
                        <p>The effect has been tremendous. At first the raw industrial worker, who
                            but lately had been a peasant, thought that his wage represented the
                            acme of wealth and well-being, a belief which his employer oftentimes
                            fostered zealously. As his acquaintance with
                                <placeName>America</placeName> grew, this feeling passed away; the
                            worker became more Americanized in his outlook and began a struggle for
                            better living and working conditions.</p>
                        <p>If the immigrant had been an industrial worker in the old country he was
                            likely to transfer to <placeName>America</placeName> the outlook of his
                            fellow-workers at home. This was often socialism more or less extreme,
                            anarchism philosophical or active, or some form of syndicalism. At any
                            rate, a considerable degree of class-consciousness was generally
                            evident.</p>
                        <p>All of these factors have influenced the immigrant and his children in
                            their theories of economic organization in
                                <placeName>America</placeName> and, therefore, have become a part of
                            our political life.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.D.1">I D 1 Capitalistic Enterprise</head>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.D.1.a">I D 1 a Big Business</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.D.1.a">
                                <p>American opinion concerning the efficiency and value of huge
                                    corporations is <gap/> and, furthermore, has changed many times
                                    since these mammoth organizations <gap/> to change the course of
                                    our life. The attitude of the man who works for a corporation is
                                    likely to be entirely different from the man who controls it,
                                    although few persons except those in the larger foreign
                                    communities with great economic strength occupy these latter
                                    positions. Such opinion as is expressed is usually influenced by
                                    the theories of society held by the individual. <ref
                                        target="#code-I.E">(See I E)</ref></p>
                                <p>Please note that this section of the outline and <ref
                                        target="#code-I.D.1.b">the one following</ref> are much more
                                    specific than <ref target="#code-I.E">I E (Social
                                        Organization)</ref>. Sections <ref target="#code-I.D.1.a">I
                                        D 1 a</ref> and <ref target="#code-I.D.1.b">I D 1 b</ref>
                                    apply to discussions of large or small business in general or to
                                    lessons drawn from specific examples.</p>
                                <p>Include under this heading any expression of opinion on the value
                                    of trusts, <gap/>, large corporations, as well as federal and
                                    state laws enacted to promote competition. For the purposes of
                                    this study, any corporation or firm doing a gross business of
                                    more than one million dollars a year will be considered big
                                    business.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.D.1.b">I D 1 b Small Business</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.D.1.b">
                                <p>Thousands of those immigrating to <placeName>America</placeName>
                                    were independent artisans and were used to a type of economic
                                    organization which gave great freedom to the individual. The
                                    artisans had their own traditions and standards, which often
                                    were at variance with those of this country. Such people had a
                                    stake in small business; therefore, their attitude toward it is
                                    important.</p>
                                <p>In this country there has long been a group which supported small
                                    business on the theory that it was a healthier form of
                                    organization for American society. How have the foreign-language
                                    communities of a large city such as <placeName>
                                        <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                                    </placeName> been influenced by this view; to what extent have
                                    they brought about modifications in theories? On this subject
                                    uniformity of opinion will be a rarity. But the <gap/> will show
                                    the currents that have flowed through the communities.</p>
                                <p>Bear in mind that the last two paragraphs of the explanation of
                                        <ref target="#code-I.D.1.a">I D 1 a (Big Business)</ref>
                                    apply to this section of the outline as well.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.D.2">I D 2 Labor Organization and Activities</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.D.2">
                            <p>Labor organizations have wielded great influence in most of the
                                foreign-language communities since their members are strongly
                                represented in industry. Sometimes in national union, oft-times in
                                locals of their own nationality, the immigrants have fought for
                                better working conditions and higher wages. Of course, there are
                                sections in some communities, particularly the older and
                                economically stronger, which oppose unions in the same fashion as
                                the "American" bourgeoisie. Some groups, however, are simply not
                                interested in them. But, on the whole, the labor union plays an
                                important part in the foreign-language community.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.D.2.a">I D 2 a Unions</head>
                            <div>
                                <head xml:id="code-I.D.2.a.1">I D 2 a 1 Company</head>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head xml:id="code-I.D.2.a.2">I D 2 a 2 Craft</head>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head xml:id="code-I.D.2.a.3">I D 2 a 3 Industrial</head>
                                <div type="description"
                                    corresp="#code-I.D.2.a.1 #code-I.D.2.a.2 #code-I.D.2.a.3">
                                    <p>These sections of the outline are devoted to various types of
                                        unions whch have been developed in this country. It is
                                        possible that all three may be discussed in the same
                                        article; if that is the case, code the article under that
                                        item which is most thoroughly developed and cross reference
                                        it to the other subsections. Bear in mind that attitudes may
                                        be shown by action, in the case of both unions and
                                        <gap/></p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head xml:id="code-I.D.2.a.4">I D 2 a 4 Strikes</head>
                                <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.D.2.a.4">
                                    <p>Although strikes are generally connected with labor unions,
                                        such is not always the case. Code references to strikes of
                                        any sort under this subsection, remembering that people's
                                        actions are often the best expression of their attitudes and
                                        opinions. Actions against strikes and expressions of opinion
                                        hostile to them should also be coded under this
                                        subsection.</p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.D.2.b">I D 2 b Cooperatives</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.D.2.b">
                                <p>Various groups in the foreign colonies have from time to time set
                                    up cooperative organizations in many fields. Food stores,
                                    printing presses, and other types of cooperative enterprises
                                    have functioned for longer or shorter periods and with more or
                                    less success. Ofttimes the precedent for these organizations has
                                    been similar cooperatives in the homeland (for example, the
                                    Scandinavian countries). Whatever may have been the cause for
                                    their establishment (social philosophy or merely the desire to
                                    reduce the cost of living) they are a significant social
                                    phenomenon.</p>
                                <p>In some cases it may be necessary to cross-reference articles on
                                    this subject to attitudes toward big and little business and
                                    various other subsections.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-I.D.2.c">I D 2 c Unemployment</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.D.2.c">
                                <p>One of the most vital problems facing that large class which
                                    works for wages or salary in a capitalist economy is recurring
                                    unemployment. In foreign-language communities, where an
                                    extremely large percentage are employed on this basis, lack of
                                    work and its accompanying social and economic consequences are
                                    most important. For this reason, the attitudes of persons in
                                    these communities toward this problem and its possible solutions
                                    are significant.</p>
                                <p>This section of the outline was set up because the economic
                                    crisis which began in 1929 has aroused an intense interest in
                                    similar crises in the past. How have the vocal elements of the
                                    foreign-language communities reacted to the large scale
                                    unemployment which accompanied the panics of past decades?</p>
                                <p>Some of the material coded here must, of necessity, be cross
                                    referenced to the subsections concerning unions and attitudes
                                    toward business. In other cases it will be necessary to give
                                    this as a cross code for articles which have been given a main
                                    code in one of the sections just mentioned.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-I.E">I E Social Organization</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.E">
                        <p>Varying theories of the proper organization of society are widely held in
                            many foreign-language communities. Also, such beliefs tend to change
                            with time, becoming more or less radical. Thus, in the thirty years
                            following the Civil War there was a strong socialist movement, mixed
                            with anarchist elements, among the <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                            </placeName>
                            <ref target="#grp-german">German</ref> community. The <ref
                                target="#grp-russian">Russian</ref> community has experienced
                            socialist, anarchist, and communist movements of varying intensity
                            during the past fifty years. We must not make it appear that any one
                            community held one point of view. Many currents ran through each. But we
                            can assemble our material so that the varying theories of social
                            organization in each commmunity can be for different periods of
                            time.</p>
                        <p>Evaluations of capitalism should be coded or cross referenced here. This
                            section is not to be devoted to radical or reactionary principles
                            exclusively. <gap/>, phases of social organization other than the
                            economic may be included.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-I.F">I F Politics</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.F">
                        <p>The participation of immigrants in American politics is a significant
                            aspect of our development in the late nineteenth and early twentieth
                            centuries. What has been their influence on our government, particularly
                            in the large cities? Has it been good or bad? Are they bringing "alien"
                            concepts into American political life? These questions have been
                            vigorously debated throughout the <gap/>. This section of the outline
                            has been set up to show the reactions of these communities to American
                            political life. Note that this does not include general themes of
                            national scope; rather it relates to the ways in which they have made
                            their influence felt and to the programs (generally local or state) put
                            forward by the communities themselves. Note also that this section
                            applies primarily to <placeName>
                                <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                            </placeName> and <placeName>
                                <region>Illinois</region>
                            </placeName>, with the exception of <ref target="#code-I.F.6">the
                                subdivision on graft.</ref></p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.F.1">I F 1 Voting as Blocs</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.F.1">
                            <p>Attempts are made at each election to swing foreign-language
                                communities as for one party or the other. Under this section of the
                                outline should be all material which reflects the opinion of the
                                groups concerning bloc voting. Of course, opposition to such voting
                                should be included as well.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.F.2">I F 2 Part Played by Social and Political
                            Societies</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.F.2">
                            <p>In every group societies have been formed which were frankly devoted
                                to politics, or which had a social "front" but pursue political aims
                                before elections. <gap/> are firmly established; others are the
                                property of ambitious men anxious to <gap/> into the campaign funds
                                of the great parties. What is their relation to the political set-up
                                within the community; what do the people think of them; do they
                                exercise real leadership? This subsection of the outline is devoted
                                to these problems.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.F.3">I F 3 Programs and Purposes</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.F.3">
                            <p>The political aims of the community, primarily as they relate to the
                                city and state, are to be placed here. Often the question may arise
                                as to whether the group or its leaders has had any integrated
                                program at any given period of a community's history. Any program
                                which the community is asked to adopt as a special interest, such as
                                opposition to prohibition among <ref target="#grp-german"
                                    >Germans</ref> and <ref target="#grp-bohemian">Czechs</ref>, may
                                be considered a group program.</p>
                            <p>Please note again that this subdivision relates to the aims and
                                purposes of foreign-language communities, not to the policies of
                                prominent political figures outside the groups or political parties
                                in general.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.F.4">I F 4 Extent of Influence</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.F.4">
                            <p>We wish to discover all evidence of the extent of the political
                                influence of various communities. For example, the <ref
                                    target="#grp-polish">Poles</ref> have become so powerful that
                                both of the major parties invariably nominate <ref
                                    target="grp-polish">Polish</ref> candidates on their city and
                                state tickets. Street names have been changed to suit the wishes of
                                the <ref target="grp-polish">Polish</ref> community (<ref
                                    target="http://www.encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/1427.html"><placeName>
                                        <district>Pulaski-Crawford Avenue</district>
                                    </placeName> controversy</ref>). Over a period of years it
                                should be possible to trace the development of the influence of
                                various communities. On the other hand, some of these have little or
                                no political power and care must be taken to code (or cross
                                reference) under this subsection all opinions regarding this of
                                influence or other material bearing on it. This subdivision also has
                                reference to the political influence of individual members of the
                                community.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.F.5">I F 5 Political Leadership</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.F.5">
                            <p>Here we desire to assemble material showing the political leadership
                                (or lack of it) exercised by the community or its individual members
                                in city and state affairs. Thus, <persName>
                                    <forename>Anton</forename>
                                    <surname>Cermak</surname>
                                </persName> is the outstanding example of a <ref
                                    target="#grp-bohemian">Czech</ref> political leader. By
                                political leadership we mean the ability to conduct public affairs a
                                course which seems desirable to the groups, or to individuals within
                                it.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-I.F.6">I F 6 Graft and Corruption</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.F.6">
                            <p>This subsection is the widest in the section devoted to politics. It
                                includes graft in city, state and national governments. What is the
                                attitude in the community toward the "fix", the stealing of public
                                funds, or the use of public office for private gains? Naturally,
                                opinion on these matters differs widely within each community and we
                                want to show the varying shades of thought <gap/> these issues.
                                Actions are important here. If <persName>
                                    <surname>Zintak</surname></persName>, a <ref
                                    target="#grp-polish">Pole</ref>, can admit the theft of city
                                funds and still keep a large part of his political influence, there
                                must be a section of that community in which the man himself
                                outweighed deeds.</p>
                            <p>Under this subsection should be coded all notes showing an attitude
                                toward honesty in public office.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-I.G">I G War</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.G">
                        <p>Place under this heading all references to war in the abstract and
                            individual wars in particular. Thus, the attitudes toward the
                                <ref>Franco-Prussian War</ref> and the War which might be found in
                                <ref target="#grp-german">the German community</ref> would carry
                            this code. <gap/> and succor rendered to war-torn countries by various
                            communities must carry a cross reference to this code, even though the
                            main code is different. Also, code attitudes toward the <ref>Russian
                                Civil War (1918-23)</ref> here, or cross reference them if another
                            code is the main one. References to the <ref>American Neutrality
                                Act</ref> should carry this code, or be cross referenced to it.
                            Accounts of the participation of foreign-language communities in wars
                            carried on by the <placeName>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName> should also be cross referenced here, carrying <ref
                                target="#code-III.D">III D</ref> as the main code.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-I.H">I H Social Problems and Social Legislation</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.H">
                        <p>This section is a most difficult one and care must be exercised in order
                            to keep it from becoming a catch-all. Only broad problems of a social
                            character and laws or regulations to correct them, or to bring about
                            needed changes, are to be placed in this section. Such problems may
                            refer to city, state, or national life, although the latter will
                            predominate. By social problems reference is made to child labor, the
                                <ref>Wagner Act</ref>, the shorter working day, slavery, etc. Be
                            certain that the note fits this section before you give it this code or
                            cross reference.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-I.J">I J Interpretation of American History</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.J">
                        <p>Almost every immigrant community will offer its own especial
                            interpretation of the history of the <placeName>
                                <country>United States</country>
                            </placeName>. Often they are influenced by the environment of the old
                            country and show the mingling of the two cultures. Sometimes the
                            interpretations show a startling break with the old memories. Thus, the
                                <ref target="#grp-chinese">Chinese</ref> declared, "After signing
                            the Declaration of Independence our forefathers adopted the
                            constitution." A <ref target="#grp-german">German</ref> paper, the
                                <title level="j" ref="5418474_6_0464">Abendpost</title>, claimed
                                <ref target="#grp-german">German</ref> ancestry for <persName>
                                <forename>Abraham</forename>
                                <surname>Lincoln</surname>
                            </persName>. A <ref target="#grp-polish">Polish</ref> writer <ref
                                target="5423968_2_0307">stated that atheism is forbidden by our
                                constitution</ref>.</p>
                        <p>This section is the complement of <ref target="#code-III.F">III F,
                                Special Contributions to Early American Development</ref>, but
                            covers more ground than that division. Here the emphasis is on
                            interpretation of the broad range of American history, not specific
                            contributions to the nation in its younger years.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-I.K">I K Position of Women and Feminism</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="code-I.K">
                        <p>Women in <placeName>America</placeName> occupy a position which is almost
                            unique in the world today. Their struggle to achieve this status is a
                            most interesting phase in the development of our nation in modern times.
                            Immigrant women coming to the <placeName>New World</placeName> found
                            themselves in the midst of a bewildering series of changes. The struggle
                            for common suffrage, the increased importance of this sex in business
                            and industry, and efforts to remove legal disabilities under which they
                            had labored in the past were things which, except in the case of a few
                            intellectuals, had not entered the sphere of the immigrant's interests.
                            Tradition, and in some cases religion, shut women out of the man's
                            world.</p>
                        <p>As economic conditions, accelerated by the <ref
                                target="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/1383.html"
                                >World War</ref>, began to change the conditional status of the
                            sexes the immigrant communities found themselves faced with new
                            problems. The experience of seeing his wife and daughter enter business
                            offices and factories, through economic necessity or the desire for more
                            spending money, was something new to the head of the household, and
                            sometimes it was a rather fightening experience to his womenfolk. The
                            reactions of the varioius peoples to this new (to them) phenomenon are
                            significant. Their discussions of questions, their judgments of its
                            effect on family life, morals, and the female sex are valuable material
                            for an understanding of this sociological change.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-I.L">I L Agriculture in the <placeName>United
                            States</placeName></head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.L">
                        <p>The American farmer has always had, and has today, an overwhelming
                            significance in national political and economic life. Therefore, his
                            relation to the city dweller and the opinion of the latter regarding
                            American agriculture are of national importance. Many of the members of
                            our foreign-language communities were peasants in the old country. How
                            much have the traditional peasant attitudes influenced the city man's
                            consideration of farm problems? What does the immigrant in our cities
                            think of American agriculture? Bear in mind that this section related
                            not only to the politics of the farmer but to the problems of American
                            agriculture as a whole.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-I.M">I M Health and Sanitation</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-I.M">
                        <p>The question of health is a vital one to the man living in the
                            over-crowded of our city. Many of the immigrants live in slum areas,
                            with consequent high mortality rates. The great mass of these people
                            work in industries where many face the hazard of occupational diseases.
                            Unfortunately, most of them do not appreciate this problem, but much has
                            been done by members of the varioius communities who have struggled
                            (sometimes almost alone) to ameliorate these conditions.</p>
                        <p>This section of the outline is designed to include opinions and attitudes
                            on this problem, as it applies both to general living conditions and to
                            specific industries. Discussions of such conditions as dirty streets,
                            contaminated drinking water, and venereal or occupational diseases
                            should be given this code or cross referenced to it. All attempts to
                            prey on the credulity of the naive and ignorant in the communities in
                            matters of health should carry this as the main code or be cross
                            referenced to it, depending upon the content of the note. However,
                            routine health information is not to be included; in fact, no
                            translations of health columns are to be made, and if they come to your
                            attention should be rejected.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head xml:id="code-II">II Contributions and Activities</head>
                <div type="description" corresp="#code-II">
                    <p>The activities of the <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                        </placeName> foreign-language communities have been multi-<gap/> and their
                        contributions to the life of the city almost too numerous to catalogue.
                        Their activities are even more significant than their attitudes, since they
                        are of a more positive character, affecting every phase of life. The <gap/>
                        "contribution" must not be misunderstood; it applies to activities generally
                        considered undesirable as well as those looked upon with favor. Criminal
                        <gap/> are as much contributions to the life of <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                        </placeName>, albeit not regarded as favorably, as work in music or the
                        organization of schools.</p>
                    <p>Newspaper records of the enterprises of these communities are of prime
                        importance for historical and sociological studies. Indeed, newspapers are
                        the principal source of information concerning the foreign-language
                        colonies. In no other place is the life of the close-knit community so well
                        portrayed.</p>
                    <p>The activities of the groups will demonstrate their economic position in the
                        city, the cultural levels of their members, their intellectual interests,
                        and to some degree, the extent of demoralization and crime among them. From
                        <gap/> raw material we can reconstruct, in part, a connected record of the
                        history of each foreign-language community of <placeName>
                            <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement></placeName>.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-II.A">II A Vocational</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.A">
                        <p>Under the subdivision of this section should be placed references to the
                            activities--trades and professions--by which members of the community
                            earn their living.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.A.1">II A 1 Professional</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.A.1">
                            <p>The participation of members of the communities in any of the
                                recognized professions, such as medicine, law, and teaching, are to
                                be coded here. If the matter is in doubt as to whether any activity
                                is a profession he must get a ruling on the question from his
                                supervisor.</p>
                            <p>The material under this code is important since it gives significant
                                data <gap/> the economic and social position of the community at
                                various periods. Most immigrants, upon arrival in
                                    <placeName>America</placeName>, went into the ranks of common
                                labor or small business. It was only after their economic position
                                was more firmly estalbished that they were able to enter the
                                professions. In this country professional status has always carried
                                a certain social prestige. Therefore, many immigrants were anxious
                                to gain this position, which made them of even more importance
                                within their own communities.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.A.2">II A 2 Industrial and Commercial</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.A.2">
                            <p>All items concerning the participation of immigrants and their
                                children in American business and industry, in the capacity of
                                skilled and unskilled labor, white-collar help, or in executive
                                capacities, should be coded or cross-referenced here. The same code
                                should be given to businessess and industrial establishments owned
                                and operated by members of any community. Material concerning the
                                construction of factory buildings, business buildings (stores,
                                offices, <gap/>), and two or more dwellings by the same person
                                should be given this code as cross reference. They will be given
                                    <ref target="#code-II.F">II F</ref> as the main code.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.A.3">II A 3 Aesthetic</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.A.3">
                            <p>Contributions made to the artistic life of <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                                </placeName> by the foreign-language communities have been extremely
                                significant. Exhibits, All-Chicago Music Festivals, recitals, and
                                concerts have brought to the people of this city the native <gap/>
                                of many of the communities within its borders. That this rich and
                                variegated display is not better known is a serious indictment of
                                our cultural <gap/>, and is partly the fault of the communities
                                themselves since they have not always tried to attract the interest
                                of the remainder of the city.</p>
                            <p>Only items dealing with professionals--persons who make all or part
                                of their living these pursuits--should be coded in the subsections
                                under II A 3.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.A.3.a">II A 3 a Arts and Handicrafts</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.A.3.a">
                                <p>All references to occupations involving a high degree of artistic
                                    skill, other than those mentioned below, should be coded here.
                                    Wood-carving, embroidery, and fine sewing are examples of some
                                    of the items to be placed in this subdivision.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.A.3.b">II A 3 b Music</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.A.3.b">
                                <p>Concerts and recitals given by professional musicians, singers,
                                    opera companies, orchestras and bands, including dance bands,
                                    which are full-time organizations are given this code. The
                                    activities of instructors in music, both private and organized
                                    in schools, are also to be placed here.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.A.3.c">II A 3 c Painting and Sculpture</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.A.3.c">
                                <p>Artists and sculptors, while not as numerous as musicians, are to
                                    be found in many of the communities. Be certain that any artist
                                    coded in this subdivision is a professional.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.A.3.d">II A 3 d Theatrical</head>
                            <div>
                                <head xml:id="code-II.A.3.d.1">II A 3 d 1 Drama</head>
                                <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.A.3.d.1">
                                    <p>At various times several of the immigrant communities, among
                                        them the <ref target="#grp-german">German</ref> and <ref
                                            target="#grp-jewish">Jewish</ref>, have maintained
                                        professional theatres to present plays in their own
                                        languages. Such theatrical companies are an important
                                        element in the cultural life of the city and are an index of
                                        the cultural and economic strength of the various
                                        communities.</p>
                                    <p>Individual and professional performances should have this as
                                        the main code or cross-reference.</p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head xml:id="code-II.A.3.d.2">II A 3 d 2 Dancing</head>
                                <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.A.3.d.2">
                                    <p>Here reference is made to professional dance groups, ballets,
                                        schools of the dance and individual artists. Ballroom
                                        dancing and dance halls are not to be included.</p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-II.B">II B Avocational and Intellectual</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B">
                        <p>Many avocational and intellectual interests are to be found in the
                            immigrant communities. Music has been an especially important factor
                            <gap/> leisure time activities. All of these pastimes are connected with
                            the cultural background of the foreign-language group and, therefore,
                            exercise a tremendous influence, not only on recreational activities but
                            on the aesthetic life of this city.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.B.1">II B 1 Aesthetic</head>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.B.1.a">II B 1 a Music</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.1.a">
                                <p>Music is an important factor in the life of most immigrant
                                    peoples; not jazz or popular tunes, but the folk music which has
                                    been a part of their lives for generations. The more serious
                                    forms have been such cultivated. But the greatest influence has
                                    been exercised by the choruses and choirs which, for the pure
                                    enjoyment of it, have gathered to sing the music of their
                                    homeland.</p>
                                <p>All musical entertainments of a nonprofessional character, as
                                    well as articles on the importance of musical expression to the
                                    people, should carry this code, or be cross-referenced to
                                    it.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.B.1.b">II B 1 b Painting and Sculpture</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.1.b">
                                <p>Reference is made here to painting and sculpture which is not
                                    professional in scope, and which is pursued as an avocation or
                                    recreation.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.B.1.c">II B 1 c Theatrical</head>
                            <div>
                                <head xml:id="code-II.B.1.c.1">II B 1 c 1 Drama</head>
                                <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.1.c.1">
                                    <p>Amateur theatricals, whatever may be their deficiencies from
                                        the point of view of dramatic criticism, have proved of
                                        great recreational and cultural benefit to actors and
                                        audiences alike. They are also an important means of raising
                                        funds for any causes since every type of organization
                                        produces plays, revues, and musical comedies</p>
                                    <p>Such nonprofessional efforts should be coded here. In some
                                        cases, when the emphasis in the note causes it to be coded
                                        elsewhere, it should be given this cross-reference.</p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head xml:id="code-II.B.1.c.2">II B 1 c 2 Dancing</head>
                                <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.1.c.2">
                                    <p>This subsection has been set up to provide space for the
                                        activities and interests of nonprofessional dancers. Only
                                        such amateur groups (and individuals) are to receive this
                                        code. Bear in mind that ballroom dancing and dance halls are
                                        not to be included.</p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head xml:id="code-II.B.1.c.3">II B 1 c 3 Festivals, Pageants, Fairs
                                    and Expositions</head>
                                <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.1.c.3">
                                    <p>Many organizations and groups organize festivals and pageants
                                        to celebrate jubilee and important events in the life of the
                                        community and the old homeland. Frequently churches have
                                        processions or celebrations when cornerstones are laid and
                                        anniversaries are celebrated. All such items should receive
                                        this code, or be cross-referenced to it.</p>
                                    <p>Participation of foreign-language communities in city-wide
                                        festivals and pageants or in expositions (<ref>Chicago
                                            World's Fairs</ref>) should likewise receive this
                                        code.</p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.B.1.d">II B 1 d Literary Societies</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.1.d">
                                <p>Intellectual elements ofttimes combine to promote literary
                                    expression and appreciation in their community. Although these
                                    societies are generally little known and are rarely of great
                                    significance, they do show a striving for self-expression and a
                                    love of culture which is worthy of consideration.</p>
                                <p>Only societies which are purely literary in their aims should
                                    receive this code.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.B.1.e">II B 1 e Literature</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.1.e">
                                <p>This subsection is designed to include material on the literary
                                    development of the foreign-language colonies. All items relating
                                    to litarary interests, and the development of writing in the
                                    various communities, with the exception of items given the
                                    preceding code (<ref target="#II.B.1.d">II B 1 d</ref>), should
                                    be given this code.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.B.2">II B 2 Intellectual</head>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.B.2.a">II B 2 a Libraries</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.2.a">
                                <p>Every type of foreign-language organization has furthered the
                                    creation and improvement of libraries for the benefit of its
                                    members or the community at large. Radical parties have
                                    organized collections of books on their social, political, and
                                    economic theories; and many clubs and organizations have opened
                                    libraries as a service to their group. The more powerful
                                    colonies have succeeded in obtaining the establishment in the
                                        <orgName
                                        ref="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/261.html"
                                                ><placeName><settlement type="city"
                                                >Chicago</settlement>
                                        </placeName> Public Library</orgName> of collections in
                                    their languages.</p>
                                <p>This desire to promote special aims or to organize libraries for
                                    general educational purposes has been an important influence in
                                    the development and education of the various immigrant
                                    communities.</p>
                                <p>All items relating to the establishment and financing of
                                    libraries, as well as statements as to their usefulness, should
                                    be coded here or given this cross-reference.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.B.2.b">II B 2 b Museums</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.2.b">
                                <p>Museums portraying the history of the homeland and the
                                    development of the immigrant groups in
                                        <placeName>America</placeName> and in <placeName><settlement
                                            type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                                    </placeName> show an awareness of cultural continuity which is
                                    significant. Whether it be the collection of a few relics in a
                                    club- <gap/>, or a museum and archive such as that of the
                                        <orgName
                                        ref="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/985.html"
                                            ><ref target="#grp-polish">Polish</ref> Roman Catholic
                                        Union</orgName>, the attempt to link the colony to the old
                                    country and to other communities of the same nationality in
                                        <placeName>America</placeName> demonstrates a sensitivity to
                                    history which is the most important factor in the development of
                                    cultural self-consciousness. Some of the communities, such as
                                    the <ref target="#grp-polish">Polish</ref>, have collected
                                    material to show their connection with this nation in its early
                                    years.</p>
                                <p>Perhaps the best museum in any foreign-language community is that
                                    of the <orgName
                                        ref="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/985.html"
                                            ><ref target="#grp-polish">Polish</ref> Roman Catholic
                                        Union</orgName>, on <placeName><district>Milwaukee
                                            Avenue</district></placeName>. Well-organized displays
                                    portray the course of <ref target="#grp-polish">Polish</ref>
                                    history during the last centuries and the development of <ref
                                        target="#grp-polish">Polish</ref> communities in
                                            <placeName><settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                                    </placeName> and other parts of the <placeName><country>United
                                            States</country></placeName>. Many objects recalling
                                            <placeName><country>Poland</country></placeName>'s
                                    relation with the <ref>American Revolution</ref> and the early
                                    years of this country are on exhibit.</p>
                                <p>Only material relating to museums organized by the communities in
                                            <placeName><settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                                    </placeName> should receive this code. Exhibits and materials
                                    sent from <placeName><settlement type="city"
                                            >Chicago</settlement>
                                    </placeName> to museums in the homelands must be coded <ref
                                        target="#code-III.H">III H (Relations with the
                                        Homeland)</ref>.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.B.2.c">II B 2 c Scientific and Historical
                                Societies</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.2.c">
                                <p>All bodies created for scientific research, whatever their
                                    nature, are to be placed here. It is necessary to bear in mind
                                    that these organizations may not be as "scientific" in their
                                    work as some of the more firmly established academic and learned
                                    societies with national reputations. Especially may this be true
                                    of historical societies, which are sometimes one-man
                                    organizations despite their high-sounding names. But we must
                                    give some credit. A few persons, at least, have appreciated the
                                    need of such organizations and strove to create them, although
                                    the community at large may not have appreciated their
                                    efforts.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.B.2.d">II B 2 d Publications</head>
                            <div>
                                <head xml:id="code-II.B.2.d.1">II B 2 d 1 Newspapers</head>
                                <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.2.d.1">
                                    <p>This subsection is designed to include information on the
                                        foreign-language press as such--the history of individual
                                        papers and the whole press of the community, material on the
                                        purposes and value of the press, its function in the
                                        community and city, and the problems which have faced
                                        it.</p>
                                    <p>This code will receive many cross-references since there will
                                        be much material concerning the press which will be coded
                                        elsewhere but which must be noted here.</p>
                                    <p>The foreign-language press is, perhaps, the most significant
                                        institution in the community, with the exception of the
                                        church. Therefore, we must pay close attention to all
                                        material concerning its development and role in the
                                        colony.</p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head xml:id="code-II.B.2.d.2">II B 2 d 2 Periodicals</head>
                                <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.2.d.2">
                                    <p>A community which supports periodicals is further advanced
                                        intellectually and economically than one which depends upon
                                        newspapers alone. Periodicals provide an opportunity for
                                        more extended discussions than is given by the daily press
                                        and are generally of a higher intellectual level. Those
                                        published in the foreign-language communities are generally
                                        serious organs, magazines of the "confession" and "pulp"
                                        type being virtually nonexistent.</p>
                                    <p>Code under this heading material concerning periodicals of
                                        all types, published in the language of the community, or in
                                        English but devoted to community <gap/> nationality
                                        interests.</p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head xml:id="code-II.B.2.d.3">II B 2 d 3 Books</head>
                                <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.2.d.3">
                                    <p>When a foreign-language community absorbs a number of volumes
                                        printed in its mother tongue it has reached a relatively
                                        high intellectual and economic level. Comparatively large
                                        sums are required to publish and market books and a
                                        sufficiently large market must be assured to make such
                                        commercial ventures a financial success. Therefore, in
                                        colonies where such markets are not available books must be
                                        published by subscription or subsidized by individuals,
                                        churches, and organizations. It is much easier to publish
                                        volumes in Polish than in Russian, since <ref
                                            target="#grp-polish">the first community</ref> is large,
                                        economically strong, and has many intellectual forces. On
                                        the other hand, <ref target="#grp-russian">the Russian
                                            colony</ref> is small, poor, and has no large
                                        intellectual group.</p>
                                    <p>Code or cross-reference here all material concerning the
                                        publication of books in the native language of the
                                        communities, whatever may be the nature of the volumes.</p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.B.2.e">II B 2 e Radio Programs and Cinema</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.2.e">
                                <p>This section applies to radio programs in foreign languages,
                                    including commercial radio "hours". Do not include regular radio
                                    programs, as these should not be translated.</p>
                                <p>All material relating to the cinema should receive this code. The
                                    opening of motion picture houses for the showing of pictures in
                                    the old-country language and the organization of companies in
                                    the communities to produce films are examples of available
                                    material. Discussions of the cinema as a form of art and its
                                    affect on the life of the community and the nation should also
                                    be given this code. However, some of the discussions of the
                                    effect of motion pictures on children can be more properly coded
                                    under <ref target="#code-I.B.3.b">I B 3 b (Parent-Child
                                        Relationship)</ref> or <ref target="#code-II.E.5">II E 5
                                        (Crime Prevention)</ref>.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.B.2.f">II B 2 f Special Schools and Classes</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.2.f">
                                <p>Many organizations have opened schools and special classes for
                                    the education of both children and adults. These should not be
                                    confused with the regularly accredited parochial institutions.
                                    In general, these schools supplement the child's public school
                                    education, and are designed to give him some knowledge of his
                                    parents' native language and the literature and history of their
                                    native land. Their purpose, in many cases is to prevent the
                                    complete Americanization of the younger generation. Although the
                                    standard of instruction is uneven, and in many cases is quite
                                    low, these schools do perform and important function in the
                                    community. To a certain degree, they bring the older and younger
                                    generations closer together and help to relieve the strain
                                    arising from the rapid assimilation of the children.</p>
                                <p>Likewise, some schools are devoted to the training and education
                                    of adults, teaching them English and, in some cases, trades.</p>
                                <p>All schools and classes except accredited schools are to be coded
                                    here. Accredited schools, secular and parochial, are to be
                                    placed in the proper sub-section under the <ref
                                        target="#code-I.A">I A</ref> code.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-II.B.2.g">II B 2 g Forums, Discussion Groups and
                                Lectures</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.2.g">
                                <p>Educational work in many communities is not limited to formal
                                    instruction. Lectures and discussion groups, particularly for
                                    adults, are widespread. These talks, often given by
                                    well-informed and educated persons (but frequently devoted
                                    entirely to propaganda for political and social goals), have a
                                    particularly strong hold in communities where, although the
                                    level of education is not high, there is a lively desire for
                                    self-improvement. <ref target="#grp-russian">The Russian
                                        colony</ref> is an excellent example. Many persons have
                                    sacrificed their time and convenience to help the uneducated
                                    peasants who form the majority in the
                                                <placeName><district><settlement type="city"
                                                >Chicago</settlement>
                                            <ref target="#grp-russian">Russian
                                            settlement</ref></district></placeName>. The subject
                                    matter of those lecture is as wide as human
                                    knowledge--philosophy, history, science, health, literature, and
                                    a host of others.</p>
                                <p>All lectures, whatever their content, should be coded or
                                    cross-referenced here. If a lecture is, for example, given to
                                    raise funds for certain purposes, it may be necessary to give
                                    the article another code as the main one, but it should receive
                                    this one as a cross-reference. Political speeches and rallies
                                    are not to be included.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.B.3">II B 3 Athletics and Sports</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.B.3">
                            <p>Most foreign communities have completely assimilated the American
                                interest in sports of all kinds. Athletic clubs have been organized
                                to keep the children out of the street, to promote physical
                                well-being, and for pure enjoyment. The young people are
                                particularly influenced by activities of this nature.</p>
                            <p>All reference to athletics should be coded here. In some cases
                                cross-references will be necessary, since there will be a connection
                                between this code and <ref target="#code-II.E.3">II E 3 (Crime
                                    Prevention)</ref>. Routine reports of athletics, unless they
                                have especial significance, should be rejected. Opinions of the
                                value of sport activities should also be placed in this
                                subsection.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-II.C">II C Permanent Memorials</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.C">
                        <p>Some colonies have been able to secure memorials to members of their
                            group who have rendered service to the city and nation, or who have been
                            outstanding in various fields. These may be statues or public buildings;
                            sometimes parks and streets are named for such persons. Examples are
                                    <placeName><district>Riis Park</district></placeName>,
                                    <placeName><district>Pulaski Avenue</district></placeName>, and
                            the large number of streets named for individuals prominent in various
                            communities (<ref>Cermak</ref>, <ref>Diversey</ref>, <ref>Damon</ref>).
                            Such memorials are important in tracing the growth of the
                            foreign-language colonies.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-II.D">II D Benevolent and Protective Institutions</head>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.D.1">II D 1 Benevolent Societies</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.D.1">
                            <p>The immigrants, particularly those who came to this country for
                                economic reasons, soon realized the insecurity of the American
                                industrial system. Although their wages represented undreamed wealth
                                in the old country, there was no certainty of employment and savings
                                were rapidly exhausted when there was no work. On the other hand, at
                                home the close-knit peasant family had aided its destitute members
                                when misfortune resulted in hardships.</p>
                            <p>To protect themselves and their families in times of economic stress,
                                the newcomers developed the <ref
                                    target="http://www.encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/866.html"
                                    >"Mutual Benefit Society"</ref>. Such organizations are based on
                                the principle of the strength of numbers. If each member, when he is
                                able, pays a small sum at regular intervals into a central fund,
                                then when he needs aid the fund can render assistance through
                                lump-sum or periodic payments. Such organizations have had
                                tremendous influence in almost every immigrant community. A large
                                number of organizations, created for other purposes, have added this
                                feature; others have been created for this purpose alone. They
                                render every type of aid: Burial assistance, sick benefits, and
                                payments at the death of members. In the latter instance the
                                organization resembles an insurance company (see next code). In some
                                instances members make specified payments; in others they are
                                assessed when funds are needed. Some organizations make lump-sum
                                payments, others make payments periodically for a stated time.</p>
                            <p>It must be remembered that these bodies quite often engage in other
                                activities--educational, political, and social, etc. In order to
                                make available all the activities of mutual aid societies notes on
                                these other phases of their work should be given this
                                cross-reference. For example, a play presented by the
                                    <orgName>"Russian Independent Mutual Aid"</orgName> should
                                receive <ref target="#code-II.B.1.c.1">II B 1 c(1)</ref> as a main
                                code and II D 1 as a cross code.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.D.2">II D 2 Insurance Companies</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.D.2">
                            <p>As communities gained in numbers and strength insurance companies
                                organized within the groups began to take over some of the functions
                                of the mutual aid society, although they have not ousted this type
                                of organization. Sometimes considerable research may be necessary to
                                discover whether the organization is an insurance company in the
                                true sense of the term or a mutual benefit society. In general,
                                insurance companies must be firmly established bodies, incorporated
                                as such (although mutual aid organizations also are usually
                                incorporated), operating under the insurance statutes of
                                        <placeName><region>Illinois</region></placeName> and
                                employing recognized actuarial practices.</p>
                            <p>Again, it should be remembered that organizations pursuing other aims
                                have recognized insurance sections. <orgName
                                    ref="http://www.encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/984.html"
                                    >The <ref target="#grp-polish">Polish</ref> National
                                    Alliance</orgName> is an excellent example. Be careful to
                                distinguish between the insurance company and the mutual aid or
                                burial assistance society.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.D.3">II D 3 Hospitals, Clinics and Medical Aid</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.D.3">
                            <p>All types of medical assistance which the groups have developed
                                should receive this classification. Frequently the more formal types
                                of medical aid--hospitals and clinics--are beyond the community's
                                financial power. But in many such colonies physicians make a special
                                effort to improve health standards and do a tremendous amount of
                                charity work. A good illustration of this is <ref
                                    target="#grp-russian">the Russian community</ref>, where the
                                physicians, who are high among the leaders of the group, have done
                                much to help the pitifully ignorant immigrants. Some religious
                                denominations have organized hospitals and nursing orders.</p>
                            <p>Emphasis here should be placed not on prevention of disease (for this
                                see <ref target="#code-I.M">I M</ref>) but the organization of
                                medical aid, whether for charity or for profit.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.D.4">II D 4 Orphanages and Creches</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.D.4">
                            <p>Considerable effort has been made to provide care for orphans,
                                especially by organizations and religious denominations. Many of
                                these maintain large orphanages which care for the children of their
                                deceased members.</p>
                            <p>Creches where working mothers can leave their children have been set
                                up in a few instances. Such institutions are important in a
                                community where many wives are forced to seek employment.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.D.5">II D 5 Homes for the Aged</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.D.5">
                            <p>Such institutions, as well as orphanages, are an evidence of a sense
                                of social responsibility and a sign of economic strength. Old
                                people's homes, as is the case with institutions for orphans, are
                                usually financed and administered by societies and churches. In some
                                cases organizations are set up for this specific purpose.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.D.6">II D 6 Settlement Houses and Community
                            Centers</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.D.6">
                            <p>Efforts have occasionally been made to establish a center where
                                members of a community could read, play games, hold study groups,
                                exercise, and give entertainments. Such centers, in order to be
                                successful, require financial support and group cooperation. Note
                                that only material on <ref
                                    target="http://www.encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/1135.html"
                                    >settlement houses</ref> and community centers established in
                                whole or in large part by group funds are to be coded here. Such
                                institutions as <placeName
                                    ref="http://www.encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/11199.html"
                                    >The University of Chicago Settlement</placeName> and
                                    <placeName>Northwestern University Settlement</placeName>
                                receive their support chiefly from outside the communities they aid
                                and are, therefore, not to be given this code.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.D.7">II D 7 Organizations for Legal Assistance</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.D.7">
                            <p>Immigrants in a strange land or poor persons unable to pay for
                                assistance are at a great disadvantage when dealing with the courts
                                and police. When the individual is unfamiliar with his rights and
                                does not have the money to hire legal talent grave miscarriages of
                                justice may result. In many foreign-language communities legal aid
                                organizations have been formed which furnish assistance free or for
                                a nominal charge.</p>
                            <p>Editors must be careful not to include in this section articles
                                devoted wholly to legal aid bureaus established outside the
                                community (newspapers, settlement houses).</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.D.8">II D 8 Employment Agencies</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.D.8">
                            <p>Difficulties in obtaining employment have been partially smoothed out
                                by employment agencies established in the colonies. These are
                                sometimes private enterprises, but more often are sponsored by
                                organizations as a service to their members and the public. If he
                                seeks employment through an agency directed by persons of his own
                                nationality, the applicant avoids many of the troubles arising from
                                lack of familiarity with the English language, American industrial
                                life, and national prejudices.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.D.9">II D 9 Extra-Legal Organizations</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.D.9">
                            <p>Among certain nationalities there has developed a type of extra-legal
                                organization which has wielded great and often illegal power. An
                                excellent example is the <ref
                                    target="http://www.encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/776.html"
                                    >"Mafia" or "black-hand"</ref> in the <ref target="#grp-italian"
                                    >Italian</ref> communities in this country. This organization,
                                imported from the homeland, at one time exercised such influence as
                                to be considered almost an invisible government. However, do not
                                confuse the <ref target="#grp-italian">Italian</ref> organization
                                with the <ref target="#grp-bohemian">Czech</ref> "mafia", which was
                                a revolutionary organization set up during the <ref
                                    target="http://www.encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/1383.html"
                                    >first World War</ref>.</p>
                            <p>Gangs and other criminal groups are not to be considered as
                                extra-legal organizations but are to be coded <ref
                                    target="#code-II.E.1">II E 1</ref>.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.D.10">II D 10 Foreign and Domestic Relief</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.D.10">
                            <p>Foreign-language communities in <placeName><settlement type="city"
                                        >Chicago</settlement>
                                </placeName> have raised and expended huge sums for the relief of
                                distress in their old homelands and among persons of their
                                nationality in the <placeName><country>United
                                    States</country></placeName>. <ref target="#grp-polish">The
                                    Polish colony</ref> collected money to aid in the restoration of
                                        <placeName><country>Poland</country></placeName> after <ref
                                    target="http://www.encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/1383.html"
                                    >the World War</ref>; <ref target="grp-jewish">Jews</ref> have
                                raised millions to help their people throughout the world; and <ref
                                    target="grp-russian">Russians</ref> have helped their
                                compatriots who were driven into exile after <ref>the
                                    Revolution</ref>. Sometimes these contributions have been
                                expanded through the <orgName>Red Cross</orgName>; on other
                                occasions it was given through organizations in the homeland or
                                directly to the needy.</p>
                            <p>Many kinds of such assistance--relief of war devastation, famine,
                                disasters, and many others--will be coded or cross-referenced here.
                                Editors should bear in mind that such contributions need not
                                necessarily be large. They may be made for the assistance of single
                                individuals or small groups as well as for a whole people. An
                                excellent illustration of such assistance is the fund raised by
                                        <placeName><settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement>
                                </placeName>
                                <ref target="#grp-swedish">Swedes</ref> to assist <ref
                                    target="#grp-swedish">Swedish</ref> and other victims of the
                                        <placeName><settlement type="city">San
                                        Francisco</settlement>
                                </placeName> earthquake.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-II.E">II E Crime and Delinquency</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.E">
                        <p>Crime and delinquency are a "contribution" that no one wishes to
                            acknowledge, yet they are important factors in the life of
                                    <placeName><settlement type="city"
                                >Chicago</settlement></placeName>. Juvenile delinquency is a
                            particular problem in many foreign-language communities. The children of
                            these communities, sometimes living in depressed areas, are often
                            "Americanized" more rapidly than their parents since their roots in the
                            old culture are not as firm. At the same time, however, in their homes
                            they are subjected to the influences of the old country--its language,
                            customs, and mores--which are considerably at variance with those of the
                            school, the street, and the playground. Conflict between parents and
                            children is the inevitable result. The young people, often deprived of
                            proper guidance, drift into crime and anti-social practices.</p>
                        <p>American individualism, which is in strong contrast to the closely-knit
                            social organization of many European communities, has often been an
                            influence for the deterioration of the individual. In the homeland (for
                            example <placeName><country>Poland</country></placeName>) the individual
                            was usually kept in line by the social and economic pressure which a
                            community with traditional standards was able to extort. In
                                <placeName>America</placeName> this is not so true; consequently
                            there is less desire or need to conform to accepted standards. Ofttimes
                            the colony here does not interest itself in the demoralization of its
                            members. As a result, the prevalence of crime and delinquency is
                            frequently quite high.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.E.1">II E 1 Organized Crime</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.E.1">
                            <p>Gangs, syndicates, and similar organized criminal groups are to be
                                given this code. Do not use this code unless you are certain that
                                the note concerns organized groups. Crimes committed by several
                                individuals are not necessarily organized crime. Organized
                                prostitution should be given this code, but individual cases receive
                                    <ref target="#code-II.E.2">the next code</ref>.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.E.2">II E 2 Individual Crime</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.E.2">
                            <p>Crimes committed for whatever reason, if they are not the result of
                                the activities of especially organized bands, are to be given this
                                code.</p>
                            <p>Naturally, we cannot list every crime committed, but particular
                                attention must be paid to those which are spectacular and
                                significant. Great care must be exercised, however, in cases
                                involving juvenile delinquency. We are particularly anxious to get
                                all available information on juvenile delinquency prior to 1905,
                                when the reports of the <ref
                                    target="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/682.html"
                                    >Juvenile Court</ref> were first published.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-II.E.3">II E 3 Crime Prevention</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.E.3">
                            <p>Much of the material receiving this code will have to be
                                cross-referenced elsewhere--under subsections of <ref
                                    target="#code-I.B.3">I B 3 (Family Organization)</ref> for
                                example. Crime prevention activities among young people will often
                                involve construction or playgrounds, supervised recreation, etc.
                                Parents will also be advised by the press how to help their children
                                avoid the pitfalls of the city. Especial care must be exercised to
                                make certain that all items dealing with the prevention of crime,
                                either through training, change of environment, or otherwise,
                                receive this code or cross-reference.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-II.F">II F Real Estate Transfers and Building
                        Activities</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-II.F">
                        <p>Many newspapers report periodically the building activities and real
                            estate transactions of members of their communities. Although the method
                            is far from infallible, a study of real estate transfers and building
                            permits will give considerable information concerning the legalities in
                            which the various nationalities have settled and their economic status
                            and the businesses in which they have engaged.</p>
                        <p>All notices of permits for the erection of buildings or purchase of real
                            estate for business purposes must be cross-referenced to <ref
                                target="#code-II.A.2">II A 2 (Industrial and Commericial)</ref>. A
                            similar cross-reference must be made for permits granted to the
                            individual to erect two or more dwellings since in most cases such are
                            built for sale and hence are business ventures.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head xml:id="code-III">III Assimilation</head>
                <div type="description" corresp="#code-III">
                    <p>The problem of the assimilation of the foreign-language groups living in the
                                <placeName><country>United States</country></placeName> is a most
                        important and difficult one. Those Americans whose people came to this
                        continent many generations ago, who have forgotten that their forbears were
                        originally foreign or who keep alive a pride based on the nationality of
                        their immigrant ancestors, are quite likely to view this question with
                        misgivings.</p>
                    <p>In the communities composed of recent immigrants two general tendencies, on
                        the whole, can be distinguished. The desire to become "American" in every
                        sense of the word, to become completely identified with this nation, is very
                        strong. This wish (coupled with the desire to avoid the prejudice often
                        shown to things foreign) has led many to Anglicize their names. On the other
                        hand, among those who grew to maturity in the homeland there is a strong
                        desire to save inherited cultural values and many of the old customs. Severe
                        strains result from the conflict of these tendencies.</p>
                    <p>Assimilation in the sense of the disappearance of the foreign-language
                        communities in a sea of "Americans" will never take place. The
                            <foreign>mores</foreign> of many of these communities are becoming a
                        part of the American tradition; this fusion of cultures, mellowed by time,
                        will produce an "American" culture unlike any one of those which entered
                        into its composition.</p>
                    <p>It is to provide for an analysis of source material on the question of
                        assimilation of immigrants that this section of the outline has been set
                        up.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-III.A">III A Segregation</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-III.A">
                        <p>Almost always immigrants of the same nationality and language have
                            settled together in communities on their arrival in this city. The
                            strangeness of American life, the difficulty of making themselves
                            understood by strangers, and the problem of finding employment have
                            caused new arrivals of the same language and nationality to live in the
                            same area when possible. The location of these settlements was
                            determined by many factors: type and availability of employment, the
                            price of land, and previous settlement in the same region by persons of
                            the same nationality. As the immigrants and their descendants are
                            assimilated these communities often lose their national quality. But
                            even today certain parts of the city are considered <ref
                                target="#grp-german">German</ref> or <ref>Scandinavian</ref>,
                            although these groups in <placeName><settlement type="city"
                                    >Chicago</settlement></placeName> have lost most of their
                            distinctive features.</p>
                        <p>All material which shows a tendency toward community segregation or
                                <hi>the opposite</hi> should be coded or cross-reference here. This
                            may consist of detailed accounts of individual communities, attempts at
                            community self-sufficiency, efforts to promote a study of the language
                            of the homeland, emphasis on religious differences, etc.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-III.B">III B Nationalistic Societies and Influences</head>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-III.B.1">III B 1 Effect upon <placeName><country>United
                                    States</country></placeName> Government and State
                            Policies</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-III.B.1">
                            <p>In many communities there have been formed societies whose purpose,
                                in whole or in part, is the aggrandizement of their particular
                                nationalities. This may be accomplished through publicity,
                                education, propaganda, or direct pressure upon governmental bodies.
                                Such pressure may be used for many purposes: to secure legislative
                                approval for projected monuments and memorials, obtain changes in
                                the immigation laws and statues affecting aliens, or in an attempt
                                to bring about changes in internal policy (national prohibition of
                                alcoholic beverages). Persuasion has been exercised by petition,
                                personal appeals, and the ballot. The power of the foreign-language
                                communities and their nationalistic organizations is shown by the
                                care with which they are treated by all politicians.</p>
                            <p>Editors should note that material relative to the interests and
                                influence of the foreign-language communities in city affairs will
                                receive an appropriate code or cross-reference in the <ref
                                    target="#code-I.F">I F</ref> section. Sometimes items coded <ref
                                    target="#code-I.F.3">I F 3</ref> will be given this code (III B
                                1) as a cross-reference, or vice versa (when reference is to
                                    <hi>state</hi> policies). Material showing the effect upon
                                national and state policies of societies with nationalistic aims
                                should be placed here. "Nationalitistic" is interpreted as a primary
                                devotion to a particular national or language group, although it is
                                not meant to imply disloyalty to the <placeName><country>United
                                        States</country></placeName>.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-III.B.2">III B 2 Activities of Nationalistic
                            Societies</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-III.B.2">
                            <p>This subsection is designed to include all source material on the
                                activities of nationalistic societies other than that given other
                                codes, and shall be used in other cases for cross-references.</p>
                            <p>It must be remembered, however, that all societies and organizations
                                in the foreign-language communities are not nationalistic. Bodies
                                whose aim is assimilation are not likely to pursue such aims;
                                organizations whose purposes are international in scope in all
                                probability will have little interest in nationalistic goals. Some
                                political groups whose philosophy would appear not to be
                                nationalistic, are such in fact. Thus, the <ref target="#grp-polish"
                                    >Polish</ref> and the <ref target="#grp-lithuanian"
                                    >Lithuanian</ref>
                                <orgName
                                    ref="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/1161.html"
                                    >Socialist Parties</orgName>, branches of parties in the
                                homeland with little interest in American politics, were definitely
                                nationalistic in character. Many <ref
                                    target="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/1400.html"
                                    >Zionist</ref> bodies have a philosophy of <ref
                                    target="#grp-jewish">Jewish</ref> nationalism.</p>
                            <p>Many items - for example, collections for relief of destitution in
                                the homeland - which will be given other codes, including
                                subdivisions of the assimilation section, should be cross-referenced
                                to this one.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-III.B.3">III B 3 Commemoration of Holidays</head>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-III.B.3.a">III B 3 a National</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-III.B.3.a">
                                <p>The extent to which the national holidays of the homeland and of
                                        <placeName>America</placeName> are celebrated in
                                    foreign-language communities will give some idea of the degree
                                    of their assimilation. Many will celebrate the national holidays
                                    of both countries, or observe the festivals of the old country
                                    in a sentimental fashion. The ideas expressed on such occasions
                                    are often important. Such American holidays as July Fourth and
                                    Thanksgiving Day are to be classed as national holidays. This
                                    code shall also be given to
                                        <placeName><region>Illinois</region></placeName> state
                                    holidays.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head xml:id="code-III.B.3.b">III B 3 b Religious</head>
                            <div type="description" corresp="#code-III.B.3.b">
                                <p>The <ref target="#code-III.B.3.a">preceding paragraph</ref>
                                    applies to this subsection. It should be remembered that,
                                    although the religious holidays of some nations have a national
                                    significance, if the festivals are primarily religious they
                                    should receive this code. Christmas and Easter should be classed
                                    as religious holidays. In some cases it may be necessary to make
                                    an investigation to discover the nature of the festival.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-III.B.4">III B 4 Conventions and Conferences</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-III.B.4">
                            <p>All conventions and conferences of nationalistic societies, purely
                                local or nation-wide bodies with branches in this city, should
                                receive this code or cross-reference. It includes the actual
                                business of the meetings as well as the fact that such were
                                held.</p>
                            <p>The purpose of this code is to permit the segregation of source
                                material on conventions and conferences of all nationalistic
                                organizations.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-III.C">III C National Churches and Sects</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-III.C">
                        <p>Of course, none of the foreign-language communities has an established
                            church. But certain denominations have become identified with various
                            peoples to such an extent that they may be considered national churches.
                            Thus, most <ref target="#grp-polish">Poles</ref> are <orgName
                                ref="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/1090.html">Roman
                                Catholic</orgName> and the majority of <ref target="#grp-russian"
                                >Russians</ref> are <orgName
                                ref="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/407.html">Greek
                                Orthodox</orgName>. But we must not neglect other denominations
                            identified with various nationalities, such as the <orgName><ref
                                    target="#grp-polish">Polish</ref> National Catholic
                                Church</orgName> and various protestant groups among the <ref
                                target="#grp-russian">Russians</ref>. "National Churches and Sects"
                            is to be interpreted as meaning church groups which are identified with
                            various nationalities and language groups - churches which have been
                            brought to <placeName>America</placeName> by immigrants or religious
                            denominations which have gained a foothold in the immigrant communities
                            here.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-III.D">III D Participation in <placeName><country>United
                                States</country></placeName> Service</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-III.D">
                        <p>Every community is proud of the service given this government by persons
                            of its nationality. They consider--and rightly--that such service
                            identifies them with the <placeName><country>United
                                States</country></placeName>. Data relative to participation of any
                            individual in the civil or military branches of our government is to be
                            coded or cross-referenced here, as seems appropriate. Service rendered
                            the <placeName><country>United States</country></placeName> during the
                                <ref target="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/2379.html"
                                >Civil War</ref> and since by individuals and groups is included in
                            this code. An example of such early activities is <persName
                                ref="5423967_4_1708"><roleName>General</roleName> J. B.
                                    <surname>Turchin</surname></persName>, a <ref
                                target="#grp-russian">Russian</ref> resident of
                                    <placeName><settlement type="city"
                                >Chicago</settlement></placeName>, who commanded various units of
                            the <orgName>Federal Army</orgName> in the <ref
                                target="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/2379.html"
                                >Civil War</ref>. There will be much material relative to the
                            participation of members of immigrant communities in the <ref
                                target="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/1383.html"
                                >World War</ref>. References to posts of the <orgName>American
                                Legion</orgName> among foreign-language groups should also be given
                            this code or cross-reference.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-III.E">III E Youth Organizations</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-III.E">
                        <p>Organizations of young people are an important element in each community.
                            <gap/> youth feel most strongly the American influences which are
                            shaping the foreign-language colonies. It is they who are synthesizing
                            the old and new cultures. For this reason, a special section devoted to
                            youth activities of all <gap/> has been set up. Sometimes non-national
                            settlement houses, such as <placeName
                                ref="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/615.html">Hull
                                House</placeName>, organize youth groups in the various
                            nationalities. This information is of great value for our file. All data
                            relative to youth organizations and activities in every sphere is to be
                            coded or cross-referenced here.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-III.F">III F Special Contributions to Early American
                        Development</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-III.F">
                        <p>From the colonial period some foreign nationalisties have been associated
                            with American life. The activities of
                                    <persName><roleName>General</roleName>
                                <forename>Casimir</forename>
                                <surname>Pulaski</surname></persName> and
                                    <persName><roleName>Baron</roleName> von
                                        <surname><sic>Stueben</sic></surname></persName> are well
                            known. Some <ref target="#grp-croatian">Croatians</ref> have claimed
                            that the word "Croatian" carved on a tree near the site of
                                    <persName><roleName>Sir</roleName>
                                <forename>Walter</forename>
                                <surname>Raleigh</surname></persName>'s lost
                                    <placeName><region>Roanoke Island</region></placeName> colony
                            was proof that a <ref target="#grp-croatian">Croatian</ref> ship picked
                            up the colonists. Most immigrant nationalities have made special efforts
                            to show an early connection with the <placeName><country>United
                                    States</country></placeName>.</p>
                        <p>For this project, "Early American Development" will include the period
                            from the first settlement in what is now the <placeName><country>United
                                    States</country></placeName> to the beginning of the <ref
                                target="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/2379.html"
                                >Civil War</ref>.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-III.G">III G Immigration and Emigration</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-III.G">
                        <p>It is only natural that problems involved in immigration and emigration
                            should be of considerable concern to the foreign-language communities.
                            This was especially true before the virtual suspension of immigration
                            after the <ref
                                target="http://encyclopedia.chicagohistory.org/pages/1383.html"
                                >World War</ref>. Increased immigration meant greater strength for
                            each colony. Many community businessmen dependent upon the patronage of
                            the immigrant, such as employment agences, newspapers, and steamship
                            agencies, had a real interest in promoting the settlement in
                                <placeName>America</placeName> of persons of their nationality.</p>
                        <p>All expressions of opinion regarding immigration and emigration, the
                            value of the immigrant to <placeName>America</placeName>, and similar
                            material, should receive this code or cross-reference.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-III.H">III H Relations with Homeland</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-III.H">
                        <p>An old interesting feature of community life is the relations which are
                            maintained with the old country. These may be active and close or merely
                            sentimental in character. In some cases they may be more or less
                            negative, as among <ref target="#grp-russian">Russians</ref> forced to
                            leave their country for political reasons. Occasionally the connection
                            is maintained to promote revolutionary activity.</p>
                        <p>Such relations are quite varied. They may involve exchange of students,
                            financial aid to persons in distress, lecture tours, and many other
                            forms of intercourse. All material concerning ties with the old homeland
                            should be given this as the main code or cross-referenced if the note
                            relates primarily to other subjects.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head xml:id="code-IV">IV Representative Individuals</head>
                <div type="description" corresp="#code-IV">
                    <p>Each community has developed leaders in every phase of human activity, men
                        and women whose careers are worthy of notice. In order to segregate all
                        information concerning these persons this special code (IV) has been set up.
                        Such a <gap/>tice makes readily available to biographers or others
                        interested in the career of particular individuals that material concerning
                        them which is in our files.</p>
                    <p>In setting up a section such as this one great care must be exercised to make
                        plain that truly representative individuals are included therein. Only those
                        who have achieved an important place in community affairs can be given such
                        space. Such a file cannot be allowed to grow to unwieldy proportions through
                        the inclusion of every person who has made any sort of contribution. For
                        this reason the translators, who are charged with the task of selecting the
                        names to be placed in this file, must exercise especial care in making their
                        choice.</p>
                    <p>Translators and editors must make certain that the initials or first name of
                        everyone selected for this file are in the note, so that they may be
                        reproduced on a cross-reference card. If the translator has not given them
                        the article must be returned to him for this additional information. In
                        cases where this material was not included originally, the editor must
                        enclose it in brackets. The following is an example: <persName>[J. M.]
                                <surname>Konkowski</surname></persName>. Such common titles as
                        Doctor, Professor, Reverend, <gap/>, must be given.</p>
                    <p>If editors doubt the advisability of including certain names in this file
                        they are at liberty to question the article and return it to the translator
                        for justification. Such a procedure should be followed when a large number
                        of names is underlined, unless it is clear that the translator was justified
                        in his selections. Editors are also entitled to ask translators why certain
                        persons, who appear worthy of this designation, have not been included in
                        this category. If the translator requires advice it can be obtained from a
                        cooperating sponsor in his language group.</p>
                    <p>Great care must be exercised at all times by translators and editors to be
                        certain that this file includes all individuals of sufficient importance,
                        <gap/> it must not be overloaded with relatively insignificant names. From
                        time to time revised lists of the persons whose names are in this file will
                        be issued to translators in each language group and to all editors, to aid
                        them in selecting individuals to be included. Translators must watch for
                        cases where names have been Anglicized, so that duplication may be
                        prevented.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head xml:id="code-V">V Miscellaneous Characteristics</head>
                <div type="description" corresp="#code-V">
                    <p>Under this heading are included material on foreign origins of immigrant
                        communities in <placeName><settlement type="city"
                            >Chicago</settlement></placeName> and a few items which fit nowhere
                        else. Editors are warned that this section is not to be made a catch-all for
                        matter difficult to code.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-V.A">V A Foreign Origins</head>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-V.A.1">V A 1 Geographical</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-V.A.1">
                            <p>All material relative to the particular areas <hi>within</hi> their
                                old homeland from which immigrants came are to be given this code or
                                cross-reference. Thus, articles which show that the majority of <ref
                                    target="#grp-russian">Russians</ref> in <placeName>
                                    <settlement type="city">Chicago</settlement></placeName> came
                                from the <placeName><reg>Russian
                                    <country>Ukraine</country></reg></placeName> or the greater part
                                of the <ref target="#grp-jewish">Jews</ref> from <placeName>
                                    <region>Russian <country>Poland</country></region></placeName>
                                would be placed here. Please note that this subsection does not
                                refer to countries of origin but to localities within those
                                countries.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="code-V.A.2">V A 2 Social and Occupational</head>
                        <div type="description" corresp="#code-V.A.2">
                            <p>This subsection is designed to include source material concerning the
                                social classes and occupational groups in the country from which the
                                immigrants came. Most of the <ref target="#grp-russian"
                                    >Russians</ref> in <placeName><settlement type="city"
                                        >Chicago</settlement></placeName> were peasants; therefore,
                                material bearing on their social class in the old country received
                                this code or cross-reference. Similar material relative to any other
                                social class or occupational group furnishing immigrants to this
                                nation should receive this code.</p>
                            <p>Occupational groups will generally be found to be subdivisions of a
                                social class. Many <ref target="#grp-russian">Russians</ref>,
                                classified as peasants under Russian law, were in actuality factory
                                workers, either on landlord's estates or in the cities.</p>
                            <p>Source material on this subject and <ref target="#code-V.A.1">the one
                                    preceding</ref> is most important and care must be taken to
                                provide necessary cross-references when another code is made the
                                main one.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head xml:id="code-V.B.">V B Picturesque Miscellanies</head>
                    <div type="description" corresp="#code-V.B.">
                        <p>This subsection is designed to include interesting and picturesque
                            details of life in the foreign-language communities which are worthy of
                            translation and <gap/>servation but which cannot be fitted into any
                            other subsection of the code.</p>
                        <p>Editors must be extremely careful in using this code. <hi>It should not
                                be used as a cross-reference.</hi> The supervisor must be consulted
                            before a V B code is placed on any article.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
