<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-10-19">October 19th, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">"The Librarian"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0249</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0249.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-10-19">October 19th, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">"The Librarian"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This farce was played Sunday night before a crowded house in Mc Vickers Theatre. The play itself was not very much appreciated and only the skillful acting of the players saved it. As with many other plays, this farce suffers from an unnatural element and it is therefore very far fetched but, the individual effects are excellent, and so, through the artistic acting of the Collmer's ensemble, this farce of Moser's draws from the house geniune applause. Mr. Rickard in the character of "Lothair" was capable and characteristic of the frivolous "Lothair". Miss Frebachs who played "Edith" excelled herself, so gave her a chance to show her rare talent with roguish frivolity and comical depth of sentiment. Fraulein Scherzel Eva was worthy of her and Mr. Heinemann as the tailor was in his element and as the comedian did his best. Mrs. Markham played the role of governess with gusto to the delight of the audience. Mr. Engel received great applause. He played the role of Mac donald in a masterful way and through exaggeration in elocution and acting won approval till the finale. Mr. Rodenberg played Harry Marsland, but with too emotional gestures, so made many parts of his best scenes ludicious.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0250.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. Meyer played the gentlemen farmer well. Messrs. Waldorf and Kvoener took the parts of Armadale and John to the satisfaction and delight of an appreciative audience, and so through the acting of the players, the farce was saved, and so, in the Grand finale, the curtain rang down with the audience applauding.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
