<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-16">July 16, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Stock Im Eisen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1183</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1183.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-16">July 16, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">STOCK IM EISEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From early in the afternoon until late in the evening, Elm Tree Grove was the destination of large crowds of people who gladly accepted the invitation of the Austrian Sick Benefit Society, Stock im Eisen, (The Iron-Studded Pole), to the summer fest they celebrated this year, knowing that they would spend a few hours there in pleasant company and that they would be well entertained.</p>
   <p>This time, as on many previous occasions, care was taken to permit no tedium to overtake the guests and to provide amusement for everyone. Of the many attractions, mention must be made of the spacious dancing hall which was often filled to capacity, and of the large beer garden in which concerts were played by Franz Holz's orchestra and also a Hungarian gypsy orchestra. It was in the latter place that it was most comfortable to tarry beneath shady trees with a good glass of beer. In general, the fest committee did its best to provide pleasant drinks and good food, so that even those who did not equip themselves with the necessary provisions were not slighted. How many children were there could be seen when the <pb facs="5418474_7_1184.jpg" n="2"/>first procession began shortly after 7 P.M. Preceded by Holz's orchestra, from the dance hall, and the gentlemen of the fest committee, the children marched gaily through the park, and at the end every child received no less than three handsome gifts, one of which was a small American flag.</p>
   <p>Among the guests, one could see quite a number of officials and members of kindred organizations. Among others, there was also the president of the German Day organization, Gustave A. Brand, and many members of the board of directors and persons prominent in public affairs.</p>
   <p>The successful organization of a festival of this kind required the assiduous co-operation of all members as well as that of an experienced and tireless committee. The latter was composed of the following gentlemen: [There follows a list of the committee members.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
