<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-11">Sept. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">German Singers in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1450</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1450.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-11">Sept. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN SINGERS IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The war exposition in Grant Park has been, throughout the fourteen days of its existence, the occasion for a continued patriotic demonstration by the people of Chicago. The closing day, on September 15, has been turned over to the foreign-speaking department of the committee for Liberty Bonds. No other group of citizens could so well represent the varied composition of the American nation, which the war has welded together as no previous incident in American history ever was able to.</p>
   <p>We Americans of German origin make up more than one tenth of the total population. Our sons and our brothers are fighting gloriously in General Pershing's army, the organization, welfare, and achievements of which are the subject of this exposition. We can demand full recognition of our achievements. Our unquestioning loyalty, once again confirmed by the sacrifice of <pb facs="5418474_7_1451.jpg" n="2"/>our blood and our substance, as in all other times in American history, could only be doubted by those who are filled with stupid hate.</p>
   <p>Our fellow citizens of other national origins will gladly grant us the position which we deserve--unless we stay away on our own accord. If we do this, because we feel that we are misunderstood, or because we suffered some injustice during the first period of the war, or for any other reason, we are missing an opportunity the like of which will never come again, either for us or for our children. In order to demonstrate that Americans of German origin are as much a part of the community as anybody else, a representative of the German nationality will be present on the evening of the fifteenth when the roll call of nationalities takes place. This representative will unfold a flag with the old German colors, black, red, and gold, in front of the statue of liberty in front of Columbia. Singers of German origin, whose co-operation has been requested, will also be present.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1452.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The German singers must not stay away from this occasion. They must not stay away from their fellow citizens of other nationalities; they must be represented in as splendid a manner as at the unforgettable meeting in Wicker Park Hall for War Savings Stamps. As Mr. Charles Wacker has so fittingly said: Americans of German origin have always shown their loyalty to the country. Nobody could doubt it. But this knowledge must not keep them away from meetings whose purpose is to demonstrate the general American patriotism. Such meetings of organizations of citizens of German descent should be attended in numbers worthy of their importance.</p>
   <p>Singers of German origin, do not let this call go unheeded! If you respond to it, you will not only do your patriotic duty to your country, but you will also assist your own organizations by allowing them to occupy a clearly defined position in a united nation. You will fulfill your duty to all your fellow citizens of similar origin by heeding their call to be their <pb facs="5418474_7_1453.jpg" n="4"/>representatives in the cultivation of the noble art of choral singing. Help to restore full confidence. Come on the evening of September 15 and gather around the symbol of that liberty for the sake of which your forefathers came to this country. In the presence of your fellow citizens of varied origins, testify with the harmony of your choruses, that only by harmonious co-operation of all her elements will this nation rise to the greatness which she shall and must achieve as your nation and the nation of your descendants.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
