<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-03">Dec. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Harmonie and Orpheus Singing Societies Unite in Great Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0393</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0393.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-03">Dec. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">HARMONIE AND ORPHEUS SINGING SOCIETIES UNITE IN GREAT CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Gesangverein Harmonie (Harmony Singing Society) and the Concordia Maennerchor (Male Chorus) gave a joint concert yesterday at the Lincoln Turner Hall, 1005 Diversey Parkway. The concert was excellent, and will long be remembered by the many people who were present. Both singing societies are under the excellent leadership of Mr. Karl Reckzeh.</p>
   <p>The first number on the program was Beetheven's "Die Himmel Ruehmen," sung by a mass chorus composed of both societies. This was followed by Schubert's "Wie Schoen bist Du". At the end of the concert they offered Biehl's "Es Zog der Maienwind" and Baumann's "Korsaren-Gesang".</p>
   <p>That these numbers were received with full appreciation was shown by the <pb facs="5418474_7_0394.jpg" n="2"/>enthusiastic applause given the singers.</p>
   <p>Continuing the skillfully arranged program, the Gesangverein Harmonie sang Orth's "Wenn man vom Liebsten scheiden muss" and Schmoelzer's "Komm Lieb mit in die Gondel". The Orpheus Maennerchor sang Spicker's "Im Grase taut's" and Gericke's "Wach auf, du schoene Traeumerin".</p>
   <p>It was apparently difficult for the audience to determine the respective merits of the two choruses, and so they did not stint their applause for either. Both organizations did well, and proved that their members foster German song, not only with gladness and joy, but also with understanding and talent.</p>
   <p>Joe Keller, Jr., soloist, with his powerful yet flexible baritone voice, contributed most enjoyably to the concert. First he sang Gound's "Valentines Gebet," then Pinsuti's "I fear no foe". So well were these numbers received, that he had to consent to an encore before the concert could proceed. The piano accompaniments of Frau Reckzeh were executed with her usual skill.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0395.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Riemeier's orchestra deserves much praise and credit for the instrumental part of the program.</p>
   <p>A gay ball, which lasted several hours, concluded the evening.</p>
   <p>The fest committee was composed as follows [Translator's note: Names omitted in translation].</p>
   <p>The present officers of the Gesangverein Harmonie are: Hermann Loesicks, president; Charles Pattlock, vice-president; Hugo Sievertsen, recording secretary; Otto Huelsman, financial secretary; Max Runge, treasurer; Paul Eischstedt, Keeper of the archives; F. Eber, vice-conductor.</p>
   <p>The Orpheus Maennerchor is managed by the following officers: W. Frankel, president; J. W. Miller, vice-president; A. Henze, corresponding secretary; Wm. Christmann, recording secretary; John Scholtes, treasurer; C. Krap, <pb facs="5418474_7_0396.jpg" n="4"/>keeper of the archives, and Joe Keller, vice-conductor.</p>
   <p>After the opening number, the presidents of the two organizations cordially welcomed the audience and expressed the hope that all guests would spend a few enjoyable hours with the Harmonie and Orpheus singers, and would not fail to come to future concerts.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
