<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-04-12">Apr. 12, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The German Group Celebrates its First Anniversary</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. Allen D. Albert Delivers an Interesting Lecture on World's Fairs</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1355</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1355.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-04-12">Apr. 12, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN GROUP CELEBRATES ITS FIRST ANNIVERSARY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Dr. Allen D. Albert Delivers an Interesting Lecture on World's Fairs</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The group known as the German Group of the Chicago World's Fair of 1933, which includes 1,300 members, met at the Bismarck Hotel last night to celebrate its first anniversary.</p>
   <p>Ernest J. Kruetgen, chairman, thanked the German Group for the splendid activities which it had carried on during the first year of its existence. And again he made an impressive appeal to the German-Americans of Chicago to join that organization, because only through a large membership can they expect to obtain their rightful place in the activities of the World's Fair. The suggestion made by the German Group to hold a singers' festival in Chicago with the participation of every German-American singing society at the time of the Exposition will not be followed, since the proposal did not arouse sufficient interest. The business reports, which was then read by Captain A. F. W. Siebel, revealed the fact that the German Group was the most active <pb facs="5418474_7_1356.jpg" n="2"/>and therefore the most successful among racial group organizations.</p>
   <p>Miss Gertrude Clauss followed with an extremely lovely rendition of a vocal solo from "Madame Butterfly" and several German songs, after which Dr. Allen D. Albert, secretary of the World's Fair, delivered the principal address.</p>
   <p>As chief assistant to Rufus C. Dawes the speaker was in a position to give many interesting details of the preliminary work in connection with the Century of Progress Exhibition. Dr. Albert commenced his address by pointing out the fact that the experience derived of previous expositions indicates clearly that success can be achieved only if the population of the city which plans the enterprise extends its wholehearted support to the plan. Furthermore, said the speaker, the management must guard against possible repetition of the mistake of the Philadelphia Fair management, namely, that extensive propaganda for the Exposition was made throughout India and Egypt, while the city's own population was utterly disregarded during the major part of the time of preparation. According to statistics of the San Francisco World's <pb facs="5418474_7_1357.jpg" n="3"/>Fair only five million visitors coming from a distance passed through the gates, but it was estimated that visitors from the hostess city accounted for thirty million admissions. No further proof is required to show that the success of a world's fair depends largely on the attitude and the support of the city's population.</p>
   <p>Men like Rufus C. Dawes, Samuel Insull, and George Woodruff, chief executives of the Exposition, who enjoy the highest reputation for their honesty, speak with confidence of the forthcoming Fair. The organization's extensive preparations have made a deficit practically impossible. Furthermore, the best is not regarded too good for Chicago's hundredth birthday anniversary. This city, which has grown in the short space of a hundred years from twenty-eight settlers to more than three million of population at the present day, is the work of those first pioneers who began to lay the foundation for a great Chicago in the lonely prairie country.</p>
   <p>In contrast to the City of San Francisco, which spent $250,000, St. Louis, <pb facs="5418474_7_1358.jpg" n="4"/>which spent $115,000, and New Orleans, which spent $300,000 before Congress had sanctioned their respective World's Fairs, Chicago has spent only $17.50, a fact which reflects credit on Mr. Dawes. The cost of the Chicago Exposition will equal the cost of an enormously large picnic, at which beer and frankfurters are the great attraction. Chicago must thus show its progress to the world; the windy city must show its prevailing spirit. Only architects of excellent reputation have been selected for the task, regardless of nationality. Among these are two Germans, who have united with the other architects in the effort to make this the most magnificent fair in the world. Industrial exhibits, it is announced, will be sent from every State of the Union.</p>
   <p>Concluding his address, Dr. Albert exclaimed:</p>
   <p>"German-Americans! Extend to us your co-operation and assist us in your own behalf."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
