<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-01-25">Jan. 25, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">German Free-Masons Celebrate Winter Festival.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1724</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1724.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1889-01-25">Jan. 25, 1889</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN FREE-MASONS CELEBRATE WINTER FESTIVAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Free-Mason Lodges of our city have celebrated but one festival annually for the last ten years. This mutual celebration takes place in honor of their patron saint; it is called "Midsummer Day", and is held in the latter part of June. Because of the brilliant success of these festivals the seven local Free-Mason Lodges readily accepted the proposal to have a mutual festivity during the winter also. This affair, for which elaborate preparations had been made, took place, last night, at the "North Side Turnhalle".</p>
   <p>The festival was not a so called American "reception", but a genuine German affair, where the well-known and often misunderstood German joviality prevailed, and where all were impelled to be cheerful and happy.</p>
   <p>The Turnhalle was most attractively decorated. Large posters with inscriptions such as: "Virtue, Morality, Fraternity"; "Peace and Unity"; "Let there be Light", reminded the visitors of the high aspirations of the Free-Masons, namely to cultivate among themselves noble sentiments, and to promote the ennobling and moral perfection of mankind in general. Free-Masonry is promoted by the Alliance, <pb facs="5418474_7_1725.jpg" n="2"/>which includes all separate organizations.</p>
   <p>At 8 o'clock, sharp, the director of music, Mr. Kretlow, andhis orchestra, composed of forty of the best German musicians, played the overture, "Poet and Peasant", and several other pieces with excellent success.</p>
   <p>At twelve o'clock the banquet was served. John Feldcamp welcomed the guests. Later, H. Pomy spoke about the importance of Free-Masonry. "The best men," he stated, "are associated with this order, and only men of honor can join it." Free-Masonry is not bound to any language, race, nation, or class, but belongs to the whole world, and the world belongs to it." The dignified Grand-Master of the state lodge remarked that he was grateful to his creator for a society, in which obedience is the first duty, in view of the lawlessness, corruption, and vice now prevalent among men. After explaining more fully the purpose of Free-Masonry, he extoled the wives who assist their husbands in their noble endeavor. He called the Germans pioneers of true sociability, and expressed the wish that the Anglo-American brethern would follow their splendid example. Mrs. Loeb then paid a tribute to the men and Free-Masons, who, she said, esteem friendship, spread truth, and protect the helpless and needy.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1726.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>F. Wenter proposed a toast to the city of Chicago, and mentioned some of the achievements of the Germans in particular the introduction of German in public schools. Major Roche responded to the toast rather humorously, and proudly boasted that the 250,000 Germans of this city were his friends.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
