<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1929-03-31">Mar. 31, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Efforts Not in Vain--The German Theatre Won its Battle</title><title level="a" type="sub">The "German Popular Stage of Chicago" Supports the Idea of a German Theatre for Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1003</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1003.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1929-03-31">Mar. 31, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">EFFORTS NOT IN VAIN--THE GERMAN THEATRE WON ITS BATTLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">The "German Popular Stage of Chicago" Supports the Idea of a German Theatre for Chicago</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When Director Bach of the German Theatre resigned early this year, the German people accepted that incident as a bad omen for the future of German dramatic art in Chicago. It was, however, glad tidings to most of the German theatre lovers that the ensemble, under the direction of Angelo Lippich, will continue its scheduled programs throughout the season. The ensemble of the German theatre was aware of the difficult problem it was facing, due to the utter indifference of the majority of the German element toward German dramatic art, therefore, this group of artists hardly expected to earn more than just enough to prevent a further deficit. The unexpected occurred; namely, the sacrificial efforts of the company found an echo in the German public, which showed that the spark for German art was permanently extinct. The ensemble reassures us of continued performances throughout this season. The members are willing to contribute if financial aid is necessary. This is, of course, a sacrifice which <pb facs="5418474_7_1004.jpg" n="2"/>deserves recognition, and the public could show its appreciation by frequent attendance of the plays.</p>
   <p>A movement designed to perpetuate the German drama has been brought to life by the German Popular Stage of this city. It is patterned after the Free Public Stage of Germany. This organization has assumed the task of enlisting members. The small contribution of one dollar per month would entitle each member to witness one performance every four weeks....In addition, the German Popular Stage will sell coupon books, the profit of which will be used to create a guarantee fund, to be put at the disposal of the company.....</p>
   <p>If success should crown this worthy movement--which is highly desirable--since it embarked on the mission of promoting art and cultural endeavors, then funds will soon be available to secure a more centrally located playhouse. Moreover, it is a step forward in the direction toward uplifing German dramatic art in Chicago to its accustomed glorious accomplishments. Therefore, to achieve this goal, every citizen of German extraction must deem it an honor as well as his duty to contribute toward the realization of this goal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
