<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-09-14">Sept. 14, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">"German Theatre"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0259</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0259.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-09-14">Sept. 14, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">"GERMAN THEATRE"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German theatre season has begun at McVickers theatre. The first night play was Von Putlitz's "Rolf Berndt." The managers Collmar and Isenstein could not have made a better choice; it was a very advantageous introduction for the artists. Rolf Bernt represents the son of a bankrupt merchant who returns to his home after an absence of twelve years, having paid his father's debt to save his honor. The sad experience of his youth has made our hero morbid and dissatisfied, and even the love of a young and beautiful widow of nobility cannot awaken the goodness of his wonderful character. Only by a number of complications and, at times, very daring situations the sad veil is lifted, and so, at the end of the play we recognized at last a very loyal and honest character. Around him is a group of men who, for the most part, are taken from the better classes of a small town in Germany, and so perhaps for that reason are not so well understood here. Rolf Berndt was found a very skilled performer and Mr. Richard, whose acting is the result of long study, left little to be desired. He managed <pb facs="5418474_7_0260.jpg" n="2"/>the difficult part with great proficiency and won great applause. Mr. Richard seemed to feel the strain of the strenuous part alloted to him, but finally overcame this and won the admiration and applause of the public. The big contrast in the character may have stood in the way so that he could not develope his talent. Miss Trautman was the sweetheart of Rolf. Her impressive presentation in the second act, though past her juvenile sentiments, won the general applause of the public. The way she played her part in the hide and seek scene with Count Eberhard gave ample proof of her great ability as an actress. She has an imposing appearance, a clear modulated voice and dramatic perfection.</p>
   <p>Miss Hanno acted the timid mother of Roy Bernt with great talent. Miss Fiebach, as Marianne, was in her element as a young girl in love, expressing joy and misery alike understrained, not having yet learned to control her emotions, she had the advantage of being known to the public, so met with much applause at her first appearance. The play had been well rehearsed. Taking it all round, it was well played and so it goes a long way for good plays to be given in the near future at the "German Theatre."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
