<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-11">June 11, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">To Cincinnati</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0947</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0947.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-06-11">June 11, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">TO CINCINNATI</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Members of Chicago singing societies were quite excited yesterday.....Representatives of our Chicago singers were to be sent to Cincinnati....where several thousand Germans will appear in a great song festival. Some Milwaukee singers arrived in Chicago yesterday, among them forty-five members of the male chorus of the Milwaukee Musik Verein. They are on their way to Cincinnati....The Milwaukee singers left for Cincinnati yesterday evening, accompanied by the Liederkranz Eintracht.</p>
   <p>The three clubs--Germania, Orpheus, and Harugari Maennerchor--occupied several coaches on the fast train of the Illinois Central, which left Chicago at eight o'clock last evening. The Harugari Maennerchor did its share in providing a festive appearance, although the club did not send many members to the song festival. The members of the Harugari Maennerchor met at Taeubert's Hall, at the corner of Twelfth Street and Third Avenue, at five o'clock, and then marched, with banners flying, to the music of a brass band toward Lake and Clinton Streets, to meet the members of the Orpheus at their hall and accompany them to the railroad station.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0948.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>On the way the singers stopped at the Illinois Staats-Zeitung Building to serenade the mouthpiece of the Chicago Germans. The band played "Die Wacht Am Rhein" and other melodies Germans like. Finally the singers saluted and greeted with a cheer the staff of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung, who gathered at the windows and waved farewell to the crowd.</p>
   <p>The Harugari club members wore wide-brimmed gray hats and gray dusters. Their president, Philipp Koehler, was dressed likewise, with a broad, blue and white sash as his insignia.</p>
   <p>The uniforms of the members of the Orpheus Society were similar. After taking a parting drink at the hall of the Orpheus Society the parade proceeded with music and banners to the Illinois Railroad station, where the members of the Germania Club greeted them.....</p>
   <p>The Germania members met at their hall at seven o'clock; all of them wore white hats with a black brim, and a blue "beer ribbon" with the inscription," Germania <pb facs="5418474_7_0949.jpg" n="3"/>Maennerchor." At half past seven o'clock the members of the Germania Maennerchor marched to the station, with the banner bearer leading the parade. The bridge tender at Clark Street had a heart and did not hold up the parade. Soon after they arrived at the station, the marchers began to display the festive spirit, so that even a few sedate American traveling men exclaimed, "Those Germans are fine chaps!" The women were likewise well represented, giving good advice to their departing spouses. The departure was by no means a sad affair and....it was only....regrettable that we could not join them....</p>
   <p>Germania Male Chorus</p>
   <p>First tenor: Gustav Blothardt....[eight names, altogether]. Second tenor: T. H. Arnold....[eight names, altogether]. First bass: Eduard Carqueville....[eight names, altogether]. Second bass: Carl Bremer [nine names, altogether].</p>
   <p>Furthermore, the president, Louis Huck, and of course, the chorus conductor, Hans Balatka were there; and a considerable number of nonparticipating members.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0950.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Orpheus</p>
   <p>First tenor: Gergard Huessen....[nine names, altogether]. Second tenor: T. Arnold....[eight names, altogether]. First bass: H. C. Beseler.... [nine names, altogether]. Second bass: F. Horn....[six names, altogether]. Also present were Conductor Gustav Ehrhorn and a large number of nonparticipating members.</p>
   <p>Liederkranz Eintracht</p>
   <p>First tenor: P.Kastler....[four names in all]. Second tenor: E. Roos....[three names, altogether]. First bass: P. Maas....[three names, altogether]. Second bass: A. Blettner....[Altogether, five names]. These with their conductor, B. L. Roos, were present.</p>
   <p>Harugari Maennerchor</p>
   <p>Philipp Koehler....[altogether fourteen names].</p>
   <p>More than one hundred nonparticipating members of the clubs and friends went to <pb facs="5418474_7_0951.jpg" n="5"/>Cincinnati yesterday, and another large number are expected to leave this morning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
