<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-12-21">Dec. 21, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">North Side Turner Hall.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0650</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0650.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-12-21">Dec. 21, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">NORTH SIDE TURNER HALL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At yesterday's concert of the Philharmonic Orchestra in the North Side Turner Hall a number of people besides the regular visitors appeared to whom these concerts were new, and whom the desire to hear easily understandable popular music induced to attend. They were not disappointed, because the program was arranged according to the general taste. The names of Wagner, Verdi, Bizet, Schubert, Suppe and Sousa exercised their attraction anew. The orchestra under its new conductor, Richard Czerwonky, played excellently, and was not stingy with extra numbers, whenever the public asked for them.</p>
   <p>The opening number, the Tannhauser March was played wonderfully. The audience was also pleased with the Massenet compositon, the Phaedra Overture. Another number by Massenet, the second part of "The Virgin's Last Dream", was played. The program did not offer anything new, consisting mostly of selections of well known pieces, in a desire to offer to the public something melodious and easily understandable. The charming Suite "L' Arlesienne" by Bizet, was reproduced with great delicacy. "Flowers Whispering" by Blom, and Suppe's piquant Overture "Poet and Peasant" found sincere and lasting applause.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0651.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Mr. William Schwartz, a tenor, was the soloist, at this concert, and as in previous appearances aroused again loud applause. He sang Verdi's aria "Celeste Aida" and one song each by Schubert, de Moya and Bradsky. Mr. Schwartz posseses a powerful tenor voice, which can sing an Italian coloratur aria just as well as a Schubert song. Miss Mildred Allen was an excellent accompanist on the piano.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
