<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-30">July 30, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Picnic of South Side German-Americans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1174</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1174.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I F 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-30">July 30, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">PICNIC OF SOUTH SIDE GERMAN-AMERICANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first large picnic given by the Illinois Federation of Germans and Austrians in Frank Simon's Grove, 117th Street and Homan Avenue, was successful, and many guests were present. We were not surprised at the large crowd, due to the fact that the membership of the organization is chiefly derived from political circles of the Fourteenth, Fifteenth, Sixteenth, Seventeenth, Eighteenth and Nineteenth Wards.</p>
   <p>The Illinois Federation of Germans and Austrians was founded about two years ago and already it has a membership of twelve thousand. It is planning to expand its activities to other districts of the city. The aims of the Federation are political in so far as the support of candidates of German and Austrian origin is concerned; its party affiliations are of secondary importance. The Federation believes that in this way it can effectively help citizens of German blood to gain political recognition, so that German-Americans need no longer forego the position which they deserve in political <pb facs="5418474_7_1175.jpg" n="2"/>affairs.</p>
   <p>The entertainment committee presented a program which included various types of amusements--games for young and old. Beautiful presents were awarded to the winners of the contests. Later in the afternoon there was a parade in which all the children took part; favors were given to every youngster who participated, as a reminder of this and next year's picnic.</p>
   <p>Devotees of the dance were able to enjoy this form of entertainment; the thirst and hunger of every guest was fully satisfied; and the guests finally departed, happy to have spent a few pleasant hours among Germans and Austrians of the Illinois Federation.</p>
   <p>The members of the Federation's central committee, John Hotwagner, president, and John Deutsch, secretary, made up the arrangement committee, and we are indebted to them for the entertaining features of the picnic.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1176.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The present officers of the Federation are: Rudolph Schoeppe, president; J. Muth and D. Jaeger, vice-presidents; George Beier, secretary; John Hotwagner, secretary-treasurer; and John Hoff, treasurer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
