<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-01-22">Jan. 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Singverein Again Scores Brilliant Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0506</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0506.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-01-22">Jan. 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SINGVEREIN AGAIN SCORES BRILLIANT SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The concert of the Chicago Singverein (Singing Society) on Saturday was both an artistic and a social success.</p>
   <p>This mixed chorus was founded almost a quarter of a century ago by William Boeppler, and is now under the leadership of Walter H. Steindel. It counts among its members and friends many prominent German-Americans, who did not fail to come to the Germania Clubhouse and thus show their interest in the chorus. They were richly rewarded, for the concert was of a quality not often encountered.</p>
   <p>In spite of its rather small membership, the chorus has at its disposal a good and well-balanced group of voices. The singers take their assignments seriously, and gladly follow the leadership of their director, so that their success is assured.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0507.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Good phrasing and precise timing marked the presentation of the different numbers on the program, all of which were accompanied by a good symphony orchestra, which also furnished an excellent introduction to the program by playing the overture to "The Merry Wives of Windsor". It is difficult to say which of the compositions presented was most pleasing to the audience; it is certain that Beethoven's reverent "Vesper Hymn" and the chorus from "Prinz Tgor" received just as enthusiastic applause as the concluding number on the program, the choral and the finale from "Die Meistersinger".</p>
   <p>Albin Steindel is no stranger to the music-loving public, and his performance on Saturday evening gave new evidence of his great artistry. He is a master of his instrument, the violin, and knows how to hold his audience enchanted. He had selected for his performance Mendelssohn-Bartholdy's "Concerto in E-major, Opus 64," and had to repeat the last movement, the applause was so great. His brother, the director, provided him with <pb facs="5418474_7_0508.jpg" n="3"/>masterly accompaniment on the grand piano.</p>
   <p>Before the start of the last part of the program President A. F. W. Siebel gave a short, but loudly applauded speech, in which he thanked the members of the chorus, the soloists, the director, and the orchestra for their distinguished performance, and the audience for its attendance in such numbers. At the same time he expressed the hope that the German community in Chicago would continue in the future to show its good will for the Singverein, and support it. Mr. Siebel also mentioned the festival which the Singverein, the German Club, and the Germania Club are to give in the Germania Clubhouse on January 30 in connection with the Roosevelt birthday celebrations which are to be held all over the country. In conformance with the wishes of the chief executive of the nation, the proceeds of these affairs are to go for certain charitable causes.</p>
   <p>The successful evening came to a harmonious close with a solemn festival ball.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
