<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-18">Dec. 18, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">German Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1280</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1280.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1932-12-18">Dec. 18, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Please do not take the following as untoward criticism or faultfinding. I am of the opinion that we owe recognition and gratitude to those who took pains to bring about German Day, devoting to it many a personal sacrifice of time, effort, and money. And yet it cannot be denied that the festive mood has been subsiding in the last few years; the number of visitors has decreased, there is, in short, a general letdown.</p>
   <p>I would say that for the celebration of German Day, the best talent should be employed. From its local limitations it should be advanced to a wider and higher field of activity. It should be so reshaped that every American, born here or elsewhere, should be glad to take part in the celebration, because he is persuaded and he knows that here is something to hear, to see; an opportunity to experience something that cannot be experienced elsewhere in America or in Europe. The festival as a whole should make an unforgettable and lasting impression.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1281.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Above all, the festival must not be made tiresome by great length and by repetitions of what has already been said a hundred times. It should, in detail as well as in its entirety, be dramatically formed and enhanced, like a tremendous creation of art which keeps growing from the day it begins to the day it ends. It should not deal so much with the past, with pride in our ancestors' achievements, but it should bear witness to the present and future in strength, in freedom, and in beauty. It should in reality bring something new, something that will enrich American life. Each individual festival would have to have a guiding force all its own--its own aspect of what is essentially German.</p>
   <p>The German Day may become submerged in mediocrity and dullness; then it would be better to save time and effort and do away with it; but it also has great possibilities. For this it needs preparation and sufficient means. Should the latter not yet be available, it would be better to wait a year or two. German Day should become a day of creativeness which invigorates American culture and enriches it, deepens it. "Never retreat!" should be its slogan! always onward and upward!" It may make appeals, but not by means of sober <pb facs="5418474_7_1282.jpg" n="3"/>resolutions, which always remain ineffective; but it should mirror the demands and express them by artistic performances; in a plea for German speech and German welfare that is permeated with simple beauty, victorious strength, and fine feeling for the best in the American character.</p>
   <p>German Day must continue to give a better and clearer expression to the German voice within the symphony of the American nationalities; it is up to it to show that the essence of what is German is, in its true conception, not working for separation, for disclaiming, importuning, or making positive assertions, but for union, conciliation, and clarification; that there is among its other qualities a breath of world citizenship, a suggestion of cosmic breadth and of metaphysical depth. In this way it may be instrumental in a veritable union of nations out of the American conglomerate of peoples, wherein the various national individualities will not be molded to a shallow level and removed, but harmoniously incorporated into the whole. It is not proper to look continually and sentimentally to Europe, but rather to show the world something new, something that is our own and is valuable; the reshaping of the German and <pb facs="5418474_7_1283.jpg" n="4"/>American spirit into a higher unit.</p>
   <p>These thoughts of mine merely represent ideas of a lonely dreamer who thinks that one must grasp the impossible like a visionary with the eyes of the spirit, in an effort to make goodness and beauty altogether possible.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
