<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-15">Aug. 15, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">An Investment Opportunity.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0142</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0142.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II C</item>
     <item>II F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-15">Aug. 15, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">AN INVESTMENT OPPORTUNITY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German Opera company, or the Schiller Theater company, as it is more popularly known, has decided recently to issue $125,000 in 7 per cent interest bearing bonds of $500 denomination, to pay the balance of its indebtedness. These bonds with accrued interest are now available from C. P. Dose &amp; Co. in the Schiller Building.</p>
   <p>The cost of the building was $925,000. Stockholders provided $500,00, and the owners $300,00 of the 6 per cent bonds; a part of the 7 per cent interest bearing bonds have already been sold; both issues mature in ten years.</p>
   <p>The income of the Schiller Building is ample to cover this expenditure and leave a margin for the stockholders, as any one can ascertain by comparing the leases and the bills. The bonds are therefore absolutely safe and provide a splendid investment opportunity, particularly for the small investor who, prompted by fear, hoards his money in his sock and thus has helped to create the present depression.</p>
   <p>His money is a part of the $177,000,000 withdrawn from the national banks <pb facs="5418474_7_0143.jpg" n="2"/>during the last two months, according to the bank controller's statements; in addition to these are the inestimable sums which were removed from the savings and private banks. The total amount probably reaches $400,000,000.</p>
   <p>This is dead capital and produces no interest whatever; it means an annual loss of $24,000,000 alone in interest and infinitely more, if one considers the values which could have been created through the use of this money.</p>
   <p>Of what benefit are funds when they are deposited in your sock? Capital which is not working is akin to the loafer who steals time from the good Lord. Instead of being beneficial it becomes injurious to others and eventually punishes its owner.</p>
   <p>Here then is a splendid and absolutely safe opportunity to open the sock-bank and make the money earn a high interest rate, besides bringing it back into circulation. - Adv.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
