<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-12-20">Dec. 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Choral Conductor H. A. Rehberg's Long Career</title><title level="a" type="sub">Silver Jubilee of the Conductor of the Vereinigte Saenger and the Vereinigte Damenchoere</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0545</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0545.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-12-20">Dec. 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">CHORAL CONDUCTOR H. A. REHBERG'S LONG CAREER</title><title level="a" type="sub">Silver Jubilee of the Conductor of the Vereinigte Saenger and the Vereinigte Damenchoere</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Vereinigte Saenger (United Singers) plan, as has already been announced, to join the Vereinigte Damenchoere (United Women's Choruses) in celebrating the silver jubilee of their conductor next Saturday evening in Wicker Park Hall. They are anxious to honor the man who has worked with them for the quarter of a century, and, they wish to prove to him how much they appreciate his efforts to promote German singing.</p>
   <p>Rehberg's Early Musical Career</p>
   <p>H. A. Rehberg was born in Frankfurt in the year 1874. He began his musical studies on the violin at the age of nine. When he was fifteen years old, he attended the music school at Weimar, and after studying two years he <pb facs="5418474_7_0546.jpg" n="2"/>came to Chicago at the time of the World's Fair in 1893. In Chicago he studied violin under Adolf Rosenbecker, played with Rosenbecker in the concerts at the North Side Turner Hall, and finally founded his own orchestra, with which he had great success. But Rehberg was not yet satisfied; he yielded to his desire for further education and studied composition, counterpoint, and orchestration, until a call as choirmaster to the singing section of the Plattduetsche Grotgilde Lake View Number Three, which became the Reuter Singing Circle in 1899, offered him a new vocation, that of choral conductor.</p>
   <p>Rehberg as Conductor</p>
   <p>A large number of Chicago singing societies were directed by Mr. Rehberg in the long period of years which ensued. In 1901 he became conductor of the Arion Maennerchor (Men's Chorus); in 1902 of the Garfield Park Men's Chorus; in 1903 of the Forest Park Harmony Club, and in 1904 of the singing section <pb facs="5418474_7_0547.jpg" n="3"/>of the Schwaebischer Frauenverein (Swabian Ladies' Club). In 1905 Rehberg founded the Damenchor Lyra (Lyra Women's Chorus), which is still under his direction; in 1906 he took over the direction of the Franz Abt Maennerchor. In the same year, 1906, he undertook the direction of the Harlem Maennerchor. Mr. Rehberg has directed the Steire Damenchor (Styrian Women's Chorus) since 1929, and he also conducts the Polyhymnia Damenchor and the Frauenchor Freiheit (Liberty Women's Chorus).</p>
   <p>Rehberg and the Vereinigte Saenger</p>
   <p>In the year of his election as director of the Vereininigte Saenger, a new success in the great concert of singers in Schoenhofen Hall was his reward. Concerts in the Chicago Opera House and in the Medinah Temple followed, and after the combination of the Vereinigte Maennerchoere with other organizations, Rehberg and Hans Biedermann, and later Reckzeh, conducted the united chorus of a thousand voices.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0548.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>In the year 1925 Rehberg succeeded in organizing the Vereinigte Damenchoere, an organization of three hundred voices.</p>
   <p>The Vereinigte Damenchoere belong to the organization of the Vereinigte Saenger and as part of this society attended the singing festival of the Northwestern Singing Society in Milwaukee. The Vereinigte Saenger and Vereinigte Damenchoere are looking forward with great pleasure to the song festival in St. Paul.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
