<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-08-06">Aug. 6, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Festival of the Verein Deutscher Weltkriegs-Veteranen a Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1158</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1158.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-08-06">Aug. 6, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">FESTIVAL OF THE VEREIN DEUTSCHER WELTKRIEGS-VETERANEN A SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This year the Verein Deutscher Weltkriegs-Veteranen (Association of German World War Veterans) held its outing and rifle match in Link's Grove in Glenview. The festival was well attended and, because of the ideal weather, was very successful. The death of President von Hindenburg was not without effect upon the mood of those present, but it was impossible for the Association to shift the festival to another, more suitable day.</p>
   <p>Many of those at the outing had already taken part in the automobile parade. This set out for the festival in the morning; others followed, and soon the place was filled with a happy crowd which joyously took part in the many entertainments. There was shooting for prizes and for the title of best shot; rifle games, and entertainment for old and young. Beautiful prizes were provided for the best performances. The Association and Stahlhelm (Steel Helmet) bands were kept busy playing, and music was also provided for those who wished to dance. The Marine-Verein (Marine Association) and the Veterans <pb facs="5418474_7_1159.jpg" n="2"/>of Foreign Wars were also present, so that right up to the close of the festival there were lively goings-on, which provided engrossing entertainment for young and old. Nor was physical comfort neglected. Those who had failed to bring provisions with them found refreshments of every sort right there. In the morning it had looked a little like rain, but in the course of the day the sky cleared up, so that the affair turned out very well. The success of the festival is due not least to the committee in charge, which not only made excellent preparations for the festival, but during the course of the affair did everything in its power for the comfort and entertainment of the guests and the success of the festival.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
