<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-26">Nov. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Great Fest in Traditional Fashion</title><title level="a" type="sub">Fall Concert of the Liedertafel Eintracht Well Attended</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0410</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0410.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-26">Nov. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">GREAT FEST IN TRADITIONAL FASHION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Fall Concert of the Liedertafel Eintracht Well Attended</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A band of singers from whose attitude one could see that, after careful preparation, they were glad to be able to show what they had learned; a conductor who, to all appearances, is steeped in German song; a hall filled with tensely listening people; a hall whose decorations and architecture have the effect of putting everyone at ease, three soloists well worthy of attention; a small but fine orchestra--given all that, the Liedertafel Eintracht could not fail to achieve success at yesterday's fall concert. The tenors wore white gardenias, the bassos red ones.</p>
   <p>Director Gustav Berndt arranged a program which was characterized by its brevity. The musical numbers were performed in the best and most enjoyable manner. The only thing to which one might perhaps take exception was that the bassos' force at times drowned out the tenors. The old, white-haired gentlemen of the bass section have powerful voices; two of the gifted soloists <pb facs="5418474_7_0411.jpg" n="2"/>are numbered among the bass singers. Director Berndt has his band well in hand....</p>
   <p>That the public was highly satisfied with what was offered was proven by the heavy applause. The first choral number was "Morgen im Walde"; breathless quiet prevailed when the old and always beautiful "Spinn, Spinn" was sung. Herr Paul Donelly sang the second verse of the song, as a solo, with his trained baritone. Next, as an a cappella number, came Ziegler's "Der Abend," a very dignified composition; this was followed by the serene waltz song, "Castles in the Air".</p>
   <p>The selection however, in which the force of the chorus came into full play, was the Scotch ballad, by A. Thelen, "Der Than von Dunbar," in which Herr Donelly again sang the beautiful solo part. The final number was "Donauwellen Walzer," by Ivanovici, sung with gusto. No amount of applause, however, could move the director to give one more encore.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0412.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The three soloists, Herr Albert Peters, tenor, Paul Donelly, baritone, and Fritz Mischke, basso, added much to the richness of the musical entertainment, and all had to consent to encores. The organization may be proud to count such soloists among its members.</p>
   <p>At the head of the fest committee, which deserves all the credit for the success of the concert, was Herr R. Borgwardt, who, towards the end of the concert made all guests welcome. Assisting him were William O. Conrad, Emil Knoebel, A. W. Fiedler, Fritz Rischke, Carl Heck, and A. Penzhorn.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
