<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1929-06-03">June 3, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Muhelman Opera Performance in Auditorium a Great Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0601</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0601.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1929-06-03">June 3, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">MUHELMAN OPERA PERFORMANCE IN AUDITORIUM A GREAT SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The sixth Opera performance of the Muhleman Opera ensemble, took place last night in the ballroom of the Auditorium Hotel. The program was exceedingly interesting with performances from the first act of "Lakmc", the third act of "Lucia" and scenes from "S Pagliacci". Besides the members of the Muhleman ensemble, two other well known artists took part in a prominent way, namely Rudy Hille of the German Theater and the concert and opera singer Rollin Pease.</p>
   <p>"Lakmc" with Rudy Hille as Gerald and the excellent Virginia Kingman as "Lakmc" proved greatly enjoyable. With these two prominent artists and the excellent cast of minor roles, the first act of the Delibes Opera was performed in a way that would have been a credit to any experienced opera ensemble. Mention should also be made of the strong bass voice of Otto Brunke as Nihalanta.</p>
   <p>The insanity scene from Douizetti's Opera "Lucia" brought Ruth Crum great triumphs. The climax of the evening was the performance of Leoncavallo's immortal opera "S Pagliacci", with Clauda Giras as Caneo, Rollin in Pease as Tonio, <pb facs="5418474_7_0602.jpg" n="2"/>Rudy Hidle as Beppo, and the Misses Mabel Gettelson and Gladys Le Vanque as Nedda. Everything heard before was surpassed. Especially Claude Giras' "Canio" was a msterly piece of art giving rise to the greatest hopes for the singer. Giras has a rich and already well cultivated voice, which in its strength and clearness of tone is fascinating. He positively is an artist of special gifts. The ballroom resounded with applause. Rudy Hille and Rollin Pease were also well liked. The performance was directed in an excellent manner by Adolf Luhleman. Zuiaida Alexkorskaya at the piano was a splendid accompanist. At the banquet following the performance Mr. Muhleman in a humorous speech thanked his pupils for their splendid performance, and at the same time the pupils honored their teacher.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
