<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1933-08-13">Aug. 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The First German Day in Chicago, June 15, 1893</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, three columns-quarter of a page, view of the celebration of German Day in 1893]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1250</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1250.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1933-08-13">Aug. 13, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIRST GERMAN DAY IN CHICAGO, JUNE 15, 1893</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Half-tone, three columns-quarter of a page, view of the celebration of German Day in 1893]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There are not many periods in the history of a people in which a few generations may witness events which not only bring with them a revolution in the political and economic structure of the country but also have a very great effect upon the lives of individuals.</p>
   <p>For many people a special celebration, a special honor, or some other event which they have experienced, is a landmark in their lives. The lives of many have sped by, however, without any landmark of this sort.</p>
   <p>In Germany the generations of the last sixty-three years saw an empire come into existence, took part in the mighty growth of this empire, then went through the World War, which brought the destruction of this empire and led to the <pb facs="5418474_7_1251.jpg" n="2"/>German Republic; today, after about fourteen years, they are faced with a new development of Germany, into a National Socialist State.</p>
   <p>Fundamentally, all this belongs to the history of Germany; it is the affair of the Reich and its subjects. Yet history also shows that Germans abroad, that citizens of German stock in foreign lands, have shared more ardently in the fate of their homeland than have those who actually dwell in Germany. It can scarcely be denied that the German people abroad grew greater and more influential the more powerful the motherland became, and that the great changes that resulted from Germany's greater power were not without their effect upon the fates of those who had emigrated.</p>
   <p>The German people of Chicago have had the privilege of seeing and taking an active part in two world's fairs within a period of forty years.</p>
   <p>For Germans the high point of the Columbian Exposition in 1893 was the German Day on June 15. The high point of this year's world's fair, A Century of <pb facs="5418474_7_1252.jpg" n="3"/>Progress, is this Sunday, August 13.</p>
   <p>Many of those who saw the Columbian Exposition are still alive. They probably have not yet forgotten June 15. For all those who were not yet in Chicago at that time there should be a brief description of the size and spirit of the celebration on that day.</p>
   <p>Large and imposing was the German House in Jackson Park. The German Village was one of the chief attractions of the Exposition.</p>
   <p>The German Reich had sent a big exhibit to the fair. The Commissioner of the Reich was Privy Counsellor Wermuth, who was accompanied by a staff of representatives of the diplomatic service, commerce, and industry.</p>
   <p>The representative of the German Reich was the German Ambassador, Baron von Holleben. The Reich was represented in Chicago by the German Consul <pb facs="5418474_7_1253.jpg" n="4"/>Dr. Karl Buenz.</p>
   <p>The chairman of the festival committee was E. G. Hall; the secretary, Max Stern; the chairmen of individual committees, Harry Rubens, Hermann Pomy, Louis Kurz, Adolph George, Frank Wenter, Wilhelm Vocke, and Charles H. Wacker.</p>
   <p>The program was divided into four parts: the parade, which was in eight divisions; the official ceremony in front of the German House; the concert in the Music Hall, at which Theodor Thomas, the founder of the Chicago Symphony Orchestra, was conductor, while G. Katzenberger led a mixed chorus and Henry Schoenfeld led a male chorus; and the turner display in the arena, in which turners Hartung, Kobelly, Kindervater, Sputh, Groth, Koenig, and Kinterling played important roles.</p>
   <p>The festival closed with a celebration in the German Village and an illumination of all the areas set aside for German exhibits at the fair.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1254.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The chief speaker at the festival was Carl Schurz. As he remarked, he had had to "overcome some reluctance when he received the invitation, but then his German heart spoke."</p>
   <p>Probably no one has ever spoken again as he did. His whole address was lighted up with one thought, "The German again has a fatherland". He once fought against reaction, then left his fatherland and made himself a home in the New World, but with regard to its exhibit at the Exposition he found words only of the highest praise and recognition for his native land. To a certain extent he made his peace with it.</p>
   <p>The following words may be remembered: "On this day we honor Germany in the peaceful contest of nations on the hospitable soil of the American Republic. From near and far we have come here to render homage to the genius of the German nation....[Translator's note: Here and in the following the dots are indications of omission reproduced from the Sonntagpost.]</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1255.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"How little our kinsmen over there know us if they believe that the heart of the German-born American has grown cool from the selfish pursuit of the dollar, and that he no longer feels love for the old homeland. Today they hear our hearts speak....The man who does not revere his old mother will not be capable of loving his young bride faithfully. The man who does not honor his old fatherland does not deserve the new one....</p>
   <p>"The war of 1870-71 was a glorious time. Every German heart, all over the world, beat with admiration and gratitude for the kinsmen in the old fatherland; and wherever the German tongue was heard the joyous chorus resounded, 'At last Germans again have a fatherland!' Every German breast thrilled with a bolder self-respect, and every drop of German blood was warmed by the newly risen sun of German honor and greatness.</p>
   <p>"Many years have passed since that time, and again we see Germania wearing the wreath of victory. This time she does not have the bloody laurel won on distant battlefields, but she is adorned with the civic crown which she won <pb facs="5418474_7_1256.jpg" n="7"/>in the peaceful contest of invention, of art, of creative labor, of fruitful endeavor, of civilization. Here she stands, not merely one of the throng, but among the winners in the contest. All the world now sees what Germany can do in peace.</p>
   <p>"The policy of underbidding was characteristic of Germany in Philadelphia (Editor [of Abendpost]: World's Fair of 1876). Germany's diffidence was the sad aftermath of the days long ago, the days of the dismemberment, of impotence, of pettiness, of self-depreciation, of doubt in her own strength. The policy of outbidding is characteristic of Germany at the White City in Chicago, the Germany of modern times, of the powerful empire, the mounting patriotism, the self-respect, the great inspirations, of mighty power, of lofty aspirations, great in its glory of war but no less great in peaceful achievements.</p>
   <p>"It is this Germany that we now greet. With proud consciousness of accomplishment Germany can say to the nations of the earth, 'Come and behold!'</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1257.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>After the German victories in the Franco-Prussian War it was said: 'That was not mere brute force. That was the work of the German schoolmaster.' The same may be said here, if under the term 'Schoolmaster' we include the German university."</p>
   <p>Then he burst forth with those words that are printed elsewhere as a reminder of that which stirred the hearts of all Americans of German stock at that time, and which won for Carl Schurz applause such as no speaker ever had either before or since that time.</p>
   <p>The booklet containing the program which was, for its time, in the best of taste, breathes the same spirit.</p>
   <p>There is vigor in the verses which those in charge of the festival dedicate to the exhibitors. The sentences of the program dedication ring out with dignity and pride.</p>
   <p>Parts of this, also, deserve to be remembered:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1258.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>"....And in these brilliant achievements we German-Americans have done our full share. The products of Germany which make up its exhibit are the fruits of the German spirit, and in spirit we too are German. Woe unto us and unto our adoptive land if we cease to be so. The German nature is the leaven which animates the American people and give it zest [Translator's note: The literal translation is, "which preserves the American people and makes it palatable"]. The German spirit is the foundation on which the structure of the American nation is gradually developing into a firm and completed whole. Were it not for both of these the new structure would have collapsed long ago.</p>
   <p>"The land of social equality and political freedom is the land of the future. It is now our task, as bearers and harbingers of German culture, to see to it that the instruction which America and the world have received from Germany's exhibit bears further fruit in this country. And this is not merely the duty of German-Americans in general, but each individual German-American should do his best, in his own circle, to see to it that in vigorous materialism the ideal is not lost sight or, that in the effort to make a living the enjoyment <pb facs="5418474_7_1259.jpg" n="10"/>of life is not forgotten, and that in the effort to be practical and useful beauty is not lost. We for our part, however, must practice not only self-assertion but self-denial, as everyone must admit who knows the weaknesses of the German.</p>
   <p>"....Let us be proud of our fatherland, but let us not in our pride set our-selves above our fellow citizens and fellow men, for in that way we would become incapable of our sublime cultural mission and unworthy of it.</p>
   <p>"But good luck to Germany and the German people, and may success attend the German spirit everywhere, especially in the United States and in our city, which leads the nation! To accomplish this may you find assistance in the German Day!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
