<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1932-10-09">Oct. 9, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Diamond Jubilee of the Concordia Maennerchor</title><title level="a" type="sub">Jubilee Concert under the Direction of L. Lohmiller on October 23</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0531</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0531.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1932-10-09">Oct. 9, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">DIAMOND JUBILEE OF THE CONCORDIA MAENNERCHOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">Jubilee Concert Under the Direction of L. Lohmiller on October 23</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Concordia Maennerchor, the oldest German singing society of Chicago, founded in 1857, celebrates its diamond jubilee Sunday, October 23, at 3 P.M., at the Vorwaerts Turner Hall, 2431 West Roosevelt Road. It will be conducted by its director, L. Lohmiller.</p>
   <p>It sounds like a fairy tale of days gone by when we learn, from the history of the organization, that its founders used to assemble at the corner of Morgan and Eleventh Streets for their first singing sessions in which Mr. D.F. Schilling acted as director and teacher of English.</p>
   <p>The motto of the first constitution was:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0532.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"There is truth in light,</p>
   <p>Clarity is the only right,</p>
   <p>In unity there is strength</p>
   <p>And might for the good deed!"</p>
   <p>At the outbreak of the Civil War many singers could be seen in the ranks of the brave men who gave their possessions and their blood for the cause of the North. Among them was Mr. D.F. Schilling, who met a hero's death on the field of honor.</p>
   <p>The Concordia Maennerchor was gravely hit by this bitter loss and also by the business depression. But the indomitable will power of the surviving members and the excellent leadership of the next director, Mr. J. Ritter, revived the organization.</p>
   <p>The names of the founders that are still preserved are: L. Stark, J. Nothnagel, A. Beisebarth, G. Stahl, F. Zieger, A. Vollbracht, W. Conenz, <pb facs="5418474_7_0533.jpg" n="3"/>W. Groth, H. Deininger, H. Noesner, T. Raub, L. Schorr, and J. Prechtel.</p>
   <p>On November 18, 1879, the Maennerchor became affiliated with the North American Saengerbund; it later became the co-founder of the Vereinigte Maennerchoere of Chicago.</p>
   <p>In 1907 the Concordia Maennerchor celebrated its golden jubilee under its president, Adam Mader. In 1911 it celebrated the dedication of its flag.</p>
   <p>The directors were: D.F. Schilling, John Ritter, W. Scherer, C. Wolter, Gustav Ehrhorn, E. Zott, B.L. Ross, C. Lotz, F.N. Hesse, H. Hartmann, C.A. Boehler and, at present, Ludwig Lokmiller [elsewhere spelled Lohmiller].</p>
   <p>Mr. W. Thuering has occupied the office of president for sixteen years. This is proof of his intelligent and satisfactory administration, and it is surely to his credit and to that of the organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0534.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The committees nominated for the festival consist of the following singers: [The several committees and their members are now listed.]</p>
   <p>All Germans of Chicago, and particularly members of singing societies; all friends of members of the Maennerchor, are cordially invited to the Diamond Jubilee of the Concordia Maennerchor. In spite of bad times, or perhaps because of them, all Germans should come together to show the organization which is holding this celebration that we Germans have the fate of our singers at heart, and that we appreciate the fact that with our singers the German tongue and German song have found a safe refuge.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
