<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-10-28">Oct. 28, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">The German Theater</title><title level="a" type="sub">Schnitzler's "Love Affair" Draws Large Crowd</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0036</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0036.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-10-28">Oct. 28, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN THEATER</title><title level="a" type="sub">Schnitzler's "Love Affair" Draws Large Crowd</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first literary performance of the season was given yesterday afternoon at the German theater. Schnitzler's "Liebelei," a profound drama with an involved plot showing deeply etched characters, has been written with the assumption that artists of first rank are available. To produce the play on a small stage--and our German theater happened to attempt just that--is tantamount to a great risk, and therefore, it is gratifying indeed that the performance was a success.</p>
   <p>The two main characters of the play show a Viennese love-scene among certain circles in an open unperturbed manner; a most gripping presentation. The portrayal of "Christine" by Hela Lindelof, was of rare sincerity, and very aweinspiring. This new personage of the German theater undoubtedly deserves credit for the play's great success. Particularly in the final terrifying scene, this talented actress found an opportunity to show her art to its greatest advantage. Excellent in expression and diction, her work must be recorded as an exceptional <pb facs="5418474_7_0037.jpg" n="2"/>accomplishment.</p>
   <p>Very impressive also was Hans Muenz, in the role of "Fritz," a part requiring diverse qualifications. He imparted to this character the right degree of dejection, and thereby, also displayed his unusual ability. With the acquisition of this new member, Angelo Lippich apparently made a good choice.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Holstein, as the little, jovial, care-free "Mizi," gave us a charming dialectical presentation of the young Viennese girl. Obviously she enjoyed this natural, vivacious part. Angelo Lippich, as friend "Theodore," was good and sympathetic as always. The musician and father of "Christine," was portrayed by Kurt Kupfer, who imparted a fine understanding to his work by adding a proper artistic conception.</p>
   <p>Ernst Robert did well, but somehow was not satisfying in every respect so far as the role of "The Master" is concerned. Originally cold and disdainful, his portrayal proved effective, but his attitude, his characterization of the part was somewhat unconvincing.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0038.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Moreover Johanna Eisemann, as "Kathrine Binder," was not temperamentally adapted to this type, regardless of her versatile artistic qualities. Her part demands anything but laughter, and as a comical old woman, she did not do justice to the serious nature of this character.</p>
   <p>The performance under the capable and skillful direction of Hans Muenz rested on solid pillars of genuine artistry, giving a highly meritorious ensemble. It was a successful beginning, giving assurance of many a delightful hour in the future.</p>
   <p>All actors were accorded a most deserving reception at the final curtain call.</p>
   <p>The house was well filled. The few vacant seats were attributed to the very fine weather.</p>
   <p>A. PH.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
