<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-12-16">Dec. 16, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The German Theatre in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0103</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0103.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-12-16">Dec. 16, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN THEATRE IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The so-called German theatre of Chicago is in poor financial condition. The Sunday evening, as well as the semi-monthly performances on week-days were poorly attended. The management is losing money and may be compelled to close. Therefore, an appeal will be made to all friends and patrons of the German Theatre, and to other Germans of the city, and for this purpose a meeting will be held next Tuesday, to discuss ways and means to arouseean interest among the people for the German plays, thereby assuring the continuation of the theatre. We hope they will succeed in doing so.</p>
   <p>We do not know what proposals the management of the theatre will make, but it is easy to assume that they will appeal to the generosity of the nationalistic-minded Germans of the city. They will require a sacrifice for the good cause. It is to be regretted that the German theatre is being considered as a nationalistic endeavor, depending on the generosity of patriotic-minded citizens. We hope it will be the last time that they have to ask for contributions, because as long as this is necessary there will be no real German theatre. One performance per week and that on Sunday evening is not sufficient to arouse the interest of the people for the German theatre. It is unreasonable to assume that the Germans of Chicago are not able or <pb facs="5418474_7_0104.jpg" n="2"/>willing to support a German theatre without being asked for contributions. Chicago can maintain a German theatre, but it must be a real one and not be dependent upon generosity. It must be managed in a business-like way. It must give performances every night and special plays Sunday nights. To give one performance and that on Sunday only, is not convenient for the German population, because of their club-festivals, which are usually held Saturday or Sunday night.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
