<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-02-20">Feb. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Westside Singing Circle Gives Concert on 44th Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0515</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0515.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-02-20">Feb. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">WESTSIDE SINGING CIRCLE GIVES CONCERT ON 44th ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In large numbers, the members and friends of the West Side Singing Circle assembled at the Vorwarts Turner Hall to celebrate the 44th Foundation Day of the society. It can be well said in the outset that all spent a very pleasant evening. Not less than five guest societies, five men's and two women's choruses, participated on the program. There were present the singing section of the German Mutual Aid Society, the Elmhurst Men's chorus, the Concordia Men's chorus, the singing section of the Suabian A. C; also the Women's chorus Lordec; under the leadership of Mr. Ludwig Lohmiller.</p>
   <p>The Richard Wagner men's chorus and the Lyra Women's chorus were <pb facs="5418474_7_0516.jpg" n="2"/>directed by the senior master A. H. Rehberg. The societies acquitted themselves nobly as shown by the applause.</p>
   <p>Selections from the Strauss Waltz "An Der Schoenen Blaven Donau" by the West Side Singing Circle and the singing section of the Suabian A. C., accompanied by the Bardeleben Orchestra, closed the program. In behalf of the society, president Fritz Koester extended greetings to all present, and expressed the hope that every one would spend a pleasant evening.</p>
   <p>Speaking also was the president of the United Singers of Chicago, Mr. A. C. Wehrween, who congratulated the West Side Singing Society <pb facs="5418474_7_0517.jpg" n="3"/>on its 44th anniversary, and expressed appreciation to the other societies for their cooperation.</p>
   <p>By order of the Central Union of the German Military Societies of Chicago and suburbs, president H. Blick, of the German war veterans society, called attention to the memorial ceremonies scheduled for March 12, honoring those who lost their lives in the World War and invited all to participate.</p>
   <p>The performance by the Bardeleben pupils' orchestra is worthy of recognition; also vocal selections by Mr. Frank Larwin accompanied by his daughter, Miss Caroline Larwin. The circle honored its conductor by presenting him with a beautiful baton.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
