<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-12">Nov. 12, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Beautiful Concert of Young Men's Chorus</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0430</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0430.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-12">Nov. 12, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">BEAUTIFUL CONCERT OF YOUNG MEN'S CHORUS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the proud leadership of Conductor Ludwig Lohmiller, and with the co-operation of several associated organizations, the Young Men's Chorus last Saturday night gave a great fall concert at Northwest Hall, which was exceedingly well attended. It will remain a pleasant memory to all the guests for a long time.</p>
   <p>As opening numbers, the organization sang "Morgenruf", by Wengert and "Der Lindenbaum", by Schubert, and later "Minnelied", by La Hale and "Waldluft", by Fuellekruss. With these, it proved that even a small chorus can be productive of something good, if it has the right zeal and good conductorship. The applause given the singers by the audience was well deserved. The ladies' chorus "Lorelei" and the "West Side Saengerkranz" were both present as guest organizations, as well as a few members of the Elmhurst Men's Chorus. The ladies' chorus "Lorelei" sang "Mein Heimattal", by Sonnet, and "Der Geiger <pb facs="5418474_7_0431.jpg" n="2"/>von St. Valten", by Orth and, as a final song "Veilchen ans Albazia" together with the host organization and chorus accompaniment, whereas the West Side Saengerkranz gave a gay potpourri "Wein, Weib und Gesang", and then, together with the Young Men's Chorus and the Elmhurst Men's Chorus, sang as a mass chorus, the "Matrosengrab" (mariners' grave) by Sonnet and the folk song (in American) "Jolly Blacksmith". As a testimony to their performance the singers, both male and female, of the four organizations may be told that they show diligent work and sincere fostering of the German song.</p>
   <p>At the start of the program, President Fred Hofmann gave a hearty welcome to the numerous guests that came. Among them was a delegation of the United Men's Choruses, headed by their president Joe Keller. Nor did he forget, before the final number was done, to give hearty thanks to all those--especially to the host organization--who contributed to the success of the program.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0432.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>As good dance music and good food and drinks were provided, all guests had a really good time, following the close of the official program (sic), which they spent in the midst of the men and women singers. The committee which so excellently prepared the fest, consisted of the following singers: Horst Schneidenbach, fest president; Fred Hofmann, president of the organization; George Keil, Kurt Rahnfeld, Hermann Heinisch, Adolf Hund, Fritz Dummert, and George Lehner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
