<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-03">Dec. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Concert of the Ladies' Club "Lorelei"</title><title level="a" type="sub">Successful Performance Directed by Ludwig Lohmiller</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0397</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0397.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-03">Dec. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERT OF THE LADIES' CLUB "LORELEI"</title><title level="a" type="sub">Successful Performance Directed by Ludwig Lohmiller</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What the Ladies Chorus "Lorelei" offered its audience yesterday, at its concert in the Northwest Hall, was the best proof that the still relatively young chorus has serious ambitions, and that it had diligently rehearsed under the experienced direction of its conductor, Ludwig Lohmiller. The Lorelei group has reason to be satisfied with the success of its concert.</p>
   <p>The host organization first sang two a capella choruses--Beethoven's "Hymme an die Nacht" and Becker's "waldesrauschen"--with good voice quality and clear pronunciation. One could notice that the conductor had his singers well in hand, and that they followed his leadership willingly. Lohmiller's arrangements of Schaefer's "Die Post in Walde" and Penschel's "Rosenwalzer" were sung by the ladies, with orchestral accompaniment. They were received with merited applause.</p>
   <p>Four men's choruses, singing under Director Lohmiller, kindly offered their <pb facs="5418474_7_0398.jpg" n="2"/>co-operation, and contributed their share to the success of the evening. The West Side Saengerkranz sung "Rose Marie," by Muehlberg, and "Rheinglaube," by Sonnet; then, joined in a mass chorus by the Arion Club of the South Side, the Elmhurst men's chorus, and the Young Men's chorus, they sang Bren's "Sonntag list's" and Zoellner's "Einkehr". Finally, together with the host organization, they gave the "Glueckswalzer," from Gilbert's Tango Princess"--another special Lohmiller arrangement.</p>
   <p>The singers of the four organizations named, together with the Richard Wagner men's chorus, under the direction of Max Schuh, offered their best by singing O'Hara's "Die Schoene Zeit der Minne" and Ulrich's "Kann ich naschen". The applause they received was well deserved.</p>
   <p>Gerry Witt, only 19 years old, son of the well-known singer and former president of the singing section of the German Aid Bund, Carl Witt, turned out to be a quite promising basso; the young man sang two songs with a well-trained, clear voice. Bardeleben's orchestra acquitted itself well as usual first by <pb facs="5418474_7_0399.jpg" n="3"/>playing the accompaniments, and later by furnishing excellent dance music.</p>
   <p>Besides the organizations mentioned, which took part in the program, there should be mentioned the Concordia Ladies' Singing Society, the German-Hungarian Ladies' Chorus, the Saxonia Ladies' Organization, the Swabian-Badensian Ladies' Society, and the Swabian Sick Aid Society of the South Side. They were all well represented by their officers and members.</p>
   <p>The president of the Lorelei Club, Frau Wittinger, made the guests cordially welcome later in the evening, thanking them, and particularly the organizations which had lent a hand in co-operation. A beautiful wreath of autumn flowers was given her by Frau Witt.</p>
   <p>The committee which arranged the evening in such a successful manner was composed of the following ladies: Frau Wittinger, President; Frau Witt, treasurer; Frau Lohmiller, secretary; Frau Ackerberg, Frau Preuss, Frau Schoenke, Frau Relieu, Frau Wetorsky, Fraeulein Blind, and Fraeulein Kampf.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
