<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-06-04">June 4, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Memorial in Honor of Karl Schurz</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1526</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1526.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1906-06-04">June 4, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">MEMORIAL IN HONOR OF KARL SCHURZ</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday Whitsunday the great mourning ceremony took place in the Auditorium for the famous German - American thinker and orator Karl Schurz. A great number of associations and organizations took part. The front of the stage had been transformed into a forest of plants and in the center stood a bust of the dead to be commemorated. Behind the plants the singers of the combined men's choirs had taken place. The ceremony was opened with a prelude by the organist Middleschulte and followed by the speech of the Chairman of the meeting. President Wm. Bocke of the Schurz Memorial Association.</p>
   <p>"We are assembled he said," to honor one who has earned the admiration of the people, whom he served for the last 50 years with the highest qualifications of a citizen and for whose benefit he has given his best endeavours with patriotic zeal. We over and honor Karl Schurz for the sincerity of his character for the truthfulness of his principles with which he always upheld the ideals of life. We love and honor him for the heroic courage, which he has shown for our country at the times of danger by his services and on the battle-field and for his great political wisdom in bringing about native reforms. He <pb facs="5418474_7_1527.jpg" n="2"/>has been an example to millions of foreigners in the acknowledgment of their new duties." Mr Bocke then introduced as first speaker Mr. Benjamin Terry, Professor of History of the Chicago University. His theme was "Karl Schurz, cosmopolitan and patriot", Karl Schurz the German fighter for liberty of 1848 was and remained an idealistic enthusiast, but one of the right kind, who staked all to realize his ideals. His ideals were no utopias but right and justice, honesty in the administration of public affairs on account of his eminent mental capabilities, his splendid oratorical ability, he a stranger soon made his way to success. Ten years after he left the old country as a deserter we see him as a recognized leader of the reigning party in the new country. He played an eminent part in the Senate as a great Politician. The serious public scandals under Grants administration are not excused by him. He does not wish the people to be burdened with war costs during times of peace. He does not wish that under the pretext of developing and protecting the home industry, a capitalistic group will be formed which sooner of later will have the power to suppress the people. It was not Schurz, who left the Republican party in 1872 for they had already given up their original principles.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1528.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Greeley campaign though not victorious had this effect. The Republican party had their lesson and started improvements and Schurz wished to help. Nominated by President Hayes as administrator of the Interior he conducted his office with such honesty and capability as none did before him. He introduced civil service reform in his department six years before it was lawfully established. He fought against the great timber thieves and he improved conditions in the Department of Indian affairs, where corruption had celebrated orgies. After his leaving the Department of the Interior Karl Schurz took no other public office but agitated indefatigably in the public interest. He was editor of the New York Evening Post and co-founder of the "Civil Service Reform League", of which he acted as president for 10 years after the death of George William Curtis. If Karl Schurz would have remained with his party he would have taken a permanent lead and with the exception of the office of the U. St. President, would have been offered one honorable office after another. As second speaker Mr. Bocke introduced the well-known Lawyer Harry Rubens, who in his younger years was closely connected with Karl Schurz. The speech was in the German language. "In the forenoon of February 27, 1872 the people came by thousands to the Capitol in Washington to hear Senator Karl Schurz speak about the disgraceful breach of neutrality made by the Grants <pb facs="5418474_7_1529.jpg" n="4"/>In a speech held at the 50 year jubilee of the New York Liederkranz he said: "As American citizens we must Americanize but that does not mean a complete deviation from everything German. We perform the highest service to Americanism by combining the best qualities of the German with the best one of the U. St. of America. Schurz came from Germany as a deserter, having participated in the revolution of 1848 and having achieved in an heroic manner the liberty of Kinkel from the fortress at Spandau. His glorious activity in the U. St. of America also gave him great honors in the old country. The German emperor was greatly interested in the Great German-American and honored him with the donation of he his portrait in life size. The President of our country, who a few days after his inauguration told Professor Munsterberg that he felt the sincerest friendship for Germany, knew how to honor and acknowledge the eminent historical importance of our hero. Karl Schurz was the greatest and most ideal German-American of his time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
