<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-05">Dec. 5, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Evening of Entertainment</title><title level="a" type="sub">Good Attendance of a Show of the South Side Organization in the South Side Ballroom</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0994</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0994.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-05">Dec. 5, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">EVENING OF ENTERTAINMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">Good Attendance of a Show of the South Side Organization in the South Side Ballroom</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The twelve German Societies of the South Side, united into a working community, all gathered last night at the South Side Ballroom, 302 West 47th Street. They spent a few pleasant hours with their countrymen, with two gay and entertaining dramatic shows and one moving picture.</p>
   <p>The entire show, excepting the film, was in the field of humor, having been made after Voss' novel "Zwei Menschen". There was hearty laughter. Also given were the original couplets of the humorist, Georg Denhofer, and the two one-act dramas "Er Laesst Nicht Locker" (He does Not Let Go) and "Tante Lotte".</p>
   <p>The public gathered in such large numbers before the show began that there were scarcely any chairs left. Music was furnished by the "Hungry Five", <pb facs="5418474_7_0995.jpg" n="2"/>who know how to create proper moods by playing familiar tunes from home, as they are wont to do. All this was supplemented by the comic actor, Georg Denhofer, with his humorous declamations. The performers were accompanied on the piano by the director of the South Side Saengerbund, Helmuth Steinmetz. The players in the two dramas gave a vivid performance and somewhat bashful intimacies, which evoked salvos of applause from the audience. The ladies' parts were taken, for the first one-act, by Therese Predel, Kammerer, Emma Kollaritsch, and Mary Jaeger and the men's roles by Sam Geigner, Joe Kammerer, and Michael Lipp. For the second one-act piece, "Tante Lotte", Eva Arndt, Joe Walter, and Michael Geiger shared the honors.</p>
   <p>The entertainment ended with the showing of the film "Zwei Menschen" of the Foreign Talking Picture Company which was brought from the South Side by A. Teuter.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
