<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-04-14">Apr. 14, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Marked Success Reported by the Popular Stage.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Satisfactory Growth of Membership</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0041</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0041.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-04-14">Apr. 14, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">MARKED SUCCESS REPORTED BY THE POPULAR STAGE.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Satisfactory Growth of Membership</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Following is the report published by the German Popular Stage of Chicago: During the short period of its existence, the German Popular Stage of Chicago is said to have won a most satisfactory success. The addresses delivered in the theatre last Sunday night by Leopold Saltiel, president, and Julius C. Hoch, vice-president, had an inspiring effect on the audience; as a result fifty more devotees of artistic drama became members of the organization.</p>
   <p>In addition, the receipts from the sale of coupon books will be used for the creation of a guaranty fund for the German Theatre. This fund in its turn will serve to assure the continuance and expansion of this temple of art.</p>
   <p>Notwithstanding the fact that our efforts have been crowned by success, we realize that the great task has only begun. The German Popular Stage of <pb facs="5418474_7_0042.jpg" n="2"/>Chicago is not at all like a club; it is a German movement, guided by principles which affect all of us. No person who is a member of the German race can maintain an apathetic attitude toward this cultural mass movement. Infinite benefits may be expected from this organization, when adequately recognized by the German-American people. And in view of the fact that the prestige of that racial group which carries on the movement increases as the movement is strengthened, our urgent plea is: Join the organization!</p>
   <p>It would be needless to emphasize that this group observes strict political neutrality. Cultural development is the sole interest and aim of this movement. A sufficiently large membership will provide a guarantee for the future of the German Theatre in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
