<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-07-22">July 22, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Another Visit to the Art Palace of the Worlds' Fair</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1628</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1628.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-07-22">July 22, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">ANOTHER VISIT TO THE ART PALACE OF THE WORLDS' FAIR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is odd, that, either by intention or by accident historical and also battle pictures are barely represented - - - - - -</p>
   <p>There is no lack of flowers and fruit pieces, breakfast pictures and fishes, lobsters etc.</p>
   <p>Adolph Hirschl's "Prometheus" impresses us with the extraordinary fineness of the tune. This son of the gods is pictured forged to the rocks, and a mighty eagle eating his liver, is covering a large part of his body. But the noble head with the pain-disfigured face is excellently sketched and painted. Very interesting are the nymphs where the artist overcame all the technical difficulties caused by the water, between the figures, with a admirable skill.</p>
   <p>A small simple looking painting hangs in the German department. The limits of Genre and landscape is blended in this, but what calls attention to its wonderful perspective, is the vigor and vivacity in which it is executed. It is Kallmorgen's "Fruehling Anfang" (Springtime). The barefooted girl, the tender <pb facs="5418474_7_1629.jpg" n="2"/>lawn, the zigzagging river, the village the tree tops gold-dipped by the spring sun - all this is combined in harmony. But in spite of their artistic Value, pictures like these receive little attention, which does not look very flattering for the visiting public. In general the public is struck by the spaciousness, the vivacious coloring or the represented extraordinary event of a picture but it is also a fact that thousands of the visitors see real art works for the first time in their lives and no not even know how to look at them.</p>
   <p>A painting of William Ritter Which shows the market place in Nuremberg in the 15th century is in the Nuremberg Department at the Industrial Palace, where it covers the rear wall on and certainly is a masterpiece in its genre.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
