<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1933-08-20">Aug. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">German Day Alliance by Herman Brandau</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1215</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1215.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1933-08-20">Aug. 20, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN DAY ALLIANCE By Herman Brandau</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At yesterday's meeting of the directors the section heads reported on their activities. President Bernard De Vry expressed the opinion that every delegate who held a position had really worked in an enthusiastic and harmonious manner. He will make more explicit reference to this in his concluding report.</p>
   <p>It was pointed out that the success of the day is indicated by the attendance at the World's Fair alone, and it has been established that German Day resulted in the second largest number of paid admissions, more than 212,000. If we add the thousands of singers and those who took part in parades, all of whom received free admission, German Day might even stand in first place with respect to the number of visitors.</p>
   <p>It is very unfortunate that there was not a suitable place within the Exposition grounds for the mass choruses, and also that there were seats for less than one- <pb facs="5418474_7_1216.jpg" n="2"/>fourth of the expected audience. Most of these came to the Fair early in the morning, while others came with the parade, and the majority remained on the Fair grounds, first, in order to see as much as possible for the fifty cents they had paid, and, second, because many were unable to find the single entrance into the stadium. The German House was crowded all day long, and it is said that more than 35,000 persons registered in the guest book, and these were almost all from out of town.</p>
   <p>Therefore we may well be satisfied with the success of German Day, all the more since, in spite of all expenses, there is surplus. As soon as the outstanding sums have been paid a meeting of delegates will be called and accounts submitted. The executive committee decided to send letters of thanks to all societies and individuals who co-operated, and to request the affiliated societies to participate fully in the German-Austro-Hungarian Day, which will be held on Sunday, August 27.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
