<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-04-06">Apr. 6, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Easter Concert of the Chicago Zither Club a Great Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0565</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0565.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-04-06">Apr. 6, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">EASTER CONCERT OF THE CHICAGO ZITHER CLUB A GREAT SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Zither Club considers it an honor that its Easter concert gave a few hours of entertainment to its members and their friends.</p>
   <p>With the co-operation of the Styrian Singing Society under the leadership of Ludwig Schwartz, and the Chicago Mandolin Orchestra, under Fritz Brockmuller, a performance was presented which consisted of overtures, marches, etc.</p>
   <p>Conductor F. Stabla cleverly solved the task. President Kurt Reichel's welcome address was followed by the Chicago Zither Club's orchestra, which played two selections.</p>
   <p>The evening's success may be credited not only to the quintet, quartet, <pb facs="5418474_7_0566.jpg" n="2"/>and trio, but also to the soloists, all of whom did their best to make a success of the performance. Miss Frances Kaufmann (Zither), Miss Sophie Wellitz (Mandolin), and Mrs. Johanna Eicherl (Zither) played the "Gnome Dance" and an original "Lander" in a remarkably clever way. They received great applause from the audience, which they rewarded by playing an encore. The "Isar Phantasy" found a splendid interpreter in Max Schiels. Miss Therese Eschbach sang two soprano solos, "Quiet as the Night" and "Zillerthal, you are my joy," She was accompanied on the piano by Miss Ida Eschbach.</p>
   <p>The management of the performance was in charge of a committee consisting of Mr. Kurt Reichel, president; Max Schiele, secretary; Richard Nehls, treasurer, and Max Blatz, cashier of ticket sales.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
