<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-08-06">Aug. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Old Settlers' Picnic</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1370</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1370.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-08-06">Aug. 6, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">OLD SETTLERS' PICNIC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Amidst ideal weather, the 54th "festival of the old settlers" or as it is generally called, the "Old Settlers Picnic," was celebrated at Noon in the large Picnin Grove of Riverview Park. At 1 o'clock, several hundred people gathered on the spacious Picnic grounds, to write their names in the register. The officials of the Turner society were making the last preparations for the reception of several thousand guests, who participate every year in the old settlers' festival. Somewhat shaky, but full of pride, the old settlers wrote their names in the book, and received their insignia, which showed the year of their arrival in Chicago.</p>
   <p>In the meantime, the band played music for dancing, vendors called out their wares, and children were gleeful; the 54th festival of the old settlers has begun. There is no doubt that it will prove very successful if the weather remains pleasant.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1371.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At 4 P. M. the famous prize dancing contest for the old people will begin. The orchestra starts with the quadrille, and daintily the old ladies and gentlemen will dance to the tunes of the music.</p>
   <p>The Distribution of Prizes</p>
   <p>At 7 o'clock, when the registration, is over, the distribution of prizes will begin. As in former years, there are a large number of prizes for the following:</p>
   <p>The oldest settlers of Chicago and Cook County, man and woman;</p>
   <p>The oldest settler born in Germany, man and woman;</p>
   <p>The oldest settler born abroad (except Germany), man and woman;</p>
   <p>The oldest settler, who has been employed in Chicago for the longest</p>
   <p>time in some business, and is still holding his job.</p>
   <p>The oldest settler, who without interruption, has lived in Chicago in one and the same home, and who is still living there;</p>
   <p>The couple of settlers, whose combined ages are greatest;</p>
   <p>The family head, who has the greatest number of children and grandchildren <pb facs="5418474_7_1372.jpg" n="3"/>present on the grounds;</p>
   <p>The oldest Veterans of the American Union army.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
