<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-27">Aug. 27, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The Fourth Connstatt Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1748</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1748.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-27">Aug. 27, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">THE FOURTH CONNSTATT FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In spite of the great sorrow felt by the nation at the critical condition of President Garfield, the Schwabenverein gave its festival yesterday and held a parade. Though the latter was not much of an affair, it provided an opportunity for Americans to comment on the callousness of the German beer guzzlers. The affair certainly was not favorably received. The Schwabenverein [Swabian Society] would have done better if it had adopted the policy which the picnic committee of the Song Festival pursued under similar circumstances and had refrained from holding a parade. Sunday parades, a German custom, are not looked upon with much favor by Americans, and if such diversions are indulged in at a time when the entire nation is kept in suspense because of the President's approaching death, than the procedure can only be regarded as a display of absolute indifference. In the minds of Americans, even the most liberal, yesterday's Swabian parade increased the prejudice against German Sunday celebrations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1749.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>However, the festival at Ogden's Grove was well attended. The attendants, in the main, were respectable, but the rabble was not lacking, and as the crowded street cars left the park in the evening, there were many persons aboard of whom the Swabians surely could not be proud. But the society made money, and that, apparently, was the principal thing.</p>
   <p>Joseph Schoeninger, president of the society, delivered the address of welcome, and C. F. Gaus, formerly a preacher and now an employee of the United States Revenue Department in Chicago, spoke on the importance of the Swabians in the world's history in general and on their influence on America in particular in dancing, music, parades, etc.</p>
   <p>A pillar made of fruit [a harvest festival custom] was greatly admired. The festival will be continued today if it does not rain. It will provide diversified amusement for all who like lively festivities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
