<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-09-26">September 26th, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The German Day.</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Magnificent, Huge Celebration at the Coliseum.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1469</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1469.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>ABENDPOST</title>,
<date when="1910-09-26">September 26th, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">The German Day.</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Magnificent, Huge Celebration at the Coliseum.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>More than 8000 Germans participated in the celebration of the German Day which had been arranged by the Chicago branch of the German-American National League. The majority of visitors arrived before 3 P. M. to take part in the first part of the program. For the second part additional crowds increased the number of guests.</p>
   <p>Dr. C. H. Hexamer of Philadelphia, the founder and president of the German-American National League and Mr. A. Timm, Secretary of the League, having been invited as guests of honors, were present.</p>
   <p>The musical part of the program was ushered in by the Bachmann's Orchestra playing with powerful, sonorous tones Richard Wagner's ("Kaisermarsch") March of the Emperor.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1470.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The audience reacted with thunderous applause. Next followed the "Jubilee Overture" by C. M. V. Weber. This piece was not less effective and contributed largely to the exulting festival mood. A special prologue, composed for this festival, and describing the prestige and the power of the German element in the United States, was given by Mrs. Minna Schmidt.</p>
   <p>Judge M. F. Girten, the president of the local branch of the National League, gave a brief address to explain the importance of the occasion. He introduced himself as a native representative of the German element of the people and exhorted his listeners not only to hold fast to the rich inheritage of their race, but to preserve it in its vigorous individuality for their descendants, in spite of all opposing powers. The speaker finished with these words: "They( the other nationalities) must get to know us. We are descendants of a noble people, a people of thinkers and poets and we must live up to our German inheritage. May we preserve the traditions and principles of true family life, the high regard for German training based on dignity <pb facs="5418474_7_1471.jpg" n="3"/>and authority. May we not forget the German song and music, nor the depth of the emotional life. We will hold in high esteem our vigorous and intimate German Language. No other Language is equal to her wealth of treasures; no other, so fervent, so rich, so vigorous, so beautiful! Because we possess such a great inheritance, we must do our best to cultivate German ideals and enthusiasm for the arts and sciences and to support them. Our duty is not done by merely celebrating a day like this. Let us support our German presses, our German schools, our German theaters and our German churches, because we need one another. We will celebrate together this German Day with music, songs, gymnastics, with descency and cheerfulness, free and openhearted, in a geniune German way."</p>
   <p>The audience expressed their appreciation and consent with enthusiastic applause. The United Men's Choir under the competent direction of their able leader, Mr. Ehrhorn, sang two well-known songs: (Schaefer's Sonntagslied) "The Shepherds Sunday Song" by Kreutzer, and (Der Lindenbaum) "The Lindentree" by Schubert.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1472.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A section of the athletic clubs demonstrated their skill in gymnastics, which they had obtained by practice. The orchestra now played three numbers: "Prelude to Ave Maria" by Bach, "The heavens declared the Glory of the Lord", taken from Haydn's Creation, and "At the Ocean" by Schubert. A thunderous applause followed these brilliant performances...</p>
   <p>The president of the league, Mr. Hexamer, was introduced as the speaker for the occasion. The audience listened with great interest and interrupted him frequently by applause.</p>
   <p>"It is indeed a rare priviledge to speak as the representative of two million member of the German-American National League, as well as to extend their sincerest regards to such a magnificent gathering."</p>
   <p>"Permit me to-day to speak primarily of the historic importance of the German- <pb facs="5418474_7_1473.jpg" n="5"/>Americans; but since we are unjustly accused, in particular in Chicago, of being the defenders of breweries, saloons and similar interests, I will briefly explain our attitude and standpoint; although this matter plays no important role in the endeavors and aims of the league."</p>
   <p>"As patriotic citizen of our country we do not take a back seat to any one; either in matters of temperance or real moderation, nor in matters concerning the purity and sacredness of the home and family. We also defend the dignity and order of the state, but we oppose with all out power the making of such, laws, which destroy our rights to personal freedom. We stand united for the protection of such rights."</p>
   <p>"One of the wisest regulation of our forbears is the separation of church and state. We deeply regret the irresponsible agitation of certain ecclesiastic organizations in the realm of politics. We believe in having the right to live our life in a way which will please us the most. Are we not free human beings and are we not members of a free and sovereign people?"</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1474.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We consider it our personal right to drink our wine or beer, just as we feel free to purchase any kind of food. The divine right of each individual, to choose for him-self what he considers best, should not be sacrificed to baseless apprehensions, nor to that fanaticism, which considers drinking a crime.</p>
   <p>"Never will we permit ourselves to become excessive in eating and drinking. Nor do we neglect our duties as citizens. We consider prohibition an infringement of our rights as men and citizens and of the personal liberty of all people. We Americans of German birth and descent protest against prohibition, because it violates one of the basic principles of justice. These principles must be sacred to every true individual."</p>
   <p>What is in danger?. Let us not be blind to the fact that the divine right of personal liberty is in danger. Herbert Spencer the philosopher defines this right in the following words, 'Every man is free to do what he pleases, as long as he does not violate the same right of all the others.' Let us hope that the spirit of freedom and the American sense of "fair play" will soon produce a reaction against this <pb facs="5418474_7_1475.jpg" n="7"/>wave of fanaticism, threatening our country. May no further laws be enforced, which would suppress the individual liberty of an intelligent minority! The spirit of the present age is opposed to intolerance. Every lover of Republican institutions and every one familiar with the history of men will agree that intolerance is out of date. We must all beware of the influence that is emanating from the hysteric propaganda of fanaticism. In reality and truth we are the standard-bearers of Order and true moderation. It is our motto to be sanely moderate in all things.</p>
   <p>"If I were requested to mention the characteristics of the American citizen of German blood so would I reply: "The German-American is industrious, moderate, thrifty, respectable, loyal, honest and thorough in public and private life, and possesses a strong individuality."</p>
   <p>"Emerson remarks strikingly." Every man is a citation from the life of his ancestors. " <pb facs="5418474_7_1476.jpg" n="8"/>The German-American can be justly proud of his ancestors; he descends from a powerful race. This race defeated the Romans and destroyed ancient Kingdoms. It sat upon the throne of the Caesars for centuries; it explored the farthest ends of the then known world. Out of this Germanic race came the two tribes which were ordained by providence, to constitute the nucleus of the British empire.</p>
   <p>Germans gave to the world the art of printing. They produced Kant, Fichte, Schlegel, Schelling, Shopenhauer; men who dedicated their lives to the most difficult and abstract problems of human existence and infused into the world by means of their marvelous intellectual accomplishments- The German philosophy- the spirit of the new age. The Germans produced a Bach, Haydn, Mozart, Beethoven and the Shakespeare of musical dramas, Richard Wagner. Germany also produced a Lessing, Schiller, Goethe. She emancipated youth from scholastic shackles in giving her modern pedagogy. She is still adding to the great treasures the results of her extensive researches and tireless experimentations and the most astounding triumphs of modern science in chemistry, pathology, physics, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1477.jpg" n="9"/>
   <p>"It has been often pointed out, that Germans have visited America before the first successful colonization, which took place October 6th, 1683 at Philadelphia. German colonization is, as a rule, dated from that point on. However, Thytker came with the vikings centuries before Columbus. At Port Royal, So. Carolina a settlement took place in the year 1562, which did not succeed. Many Germans came with the Swedes, Dutch and English, as for instance J. Lederer, whose interesting descriptions of his explorations from Maryland to Florida in 1672 was published in London."</p>
   <p>"Since we have a dependable Census, we know, that Germany has furnished about 30 % of our so-called "foreign population", and England, inclusive Wales, about 11 % only. To comprehend to some extent the situation in some of the colonies, as for instance pennsylvania, I quote the state Governor, Mr. Thomas, who wrote in 1748 as follows: "The Germans in this state comprise about 3/5 of the population. They were the chief instruments in the development of the state to the present prosperous condition, because of their industry and moderation."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1478.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>"The Germans have always possessed and manifested a sane and practical common sense, and have always been fair in the recognition of the rights of others. At the time when the Puritans of New England mistreated the unfortunate Quakers, falling into their hands, and" burnt witches", the first successful German colony at Germantown entered a protest in 1688 against slavery--the first of all such protest on record."</p>
   <p>"The first German paper factory was established in 1690 by W. Rittenhouse. This soon developed into a large publishing center. Before the American revolution the Germans in the state of Pennsylvania possessed more printing presses and published more books than all New England combined. It was Pastorius, a German, who composed the first school-book, and it was a German, Ch. Saur, who printed the first Bible in America in an European language. " The German convent "Ephrata" had its own printing press, paper factory, and Bindery in 1743, and in 1749 it was the largest printing and publishing concern in the American colonies. Shortly before the Revolutionary War there were the German Newspapers published in Pennsylvania and only eight in <pb facs="5418474_7_1479.jpg" n="11"/>English. The scripture was printed in German three times and the New Testament seven times in the United States, before being once printed in English.</p>
   <p>"The Germans have always been ready and willing to defend their land. The 'Royal American Regiment's which came into existence by parliamentary command, consisted for the most part of Germans, inclusive the officers. This regiment fought against the Indians, as they overran the colonies in 1756...Again it was a German, N. Herchheimer and his German troops, which were fighting at the front against the Indians, as the latter overran the Mohawk valley and threatened the City of New York." The German-Moravian missionary, F. Post it was, who succeeded to win for our side the Indian Chiefs near Fort DuQuesne by his eloquent speeches and this happened at a most critical moment of our colonial history.</p>
   <p>"The German colonists never hesitated to fight for the cause of liberty, when the storm broke loose and the revolution followed. Somebody made the statement recently that the influential German population of Philadelphia organized an association in <pb facs="5418474_7_1480.jpg" n="12"/>1772 already, which was called "The Patriotic Society of the City and County of Philadelphia." The purpose of this organization was to support the opposition in the colonies against British authority. When Great Britian threatened to close the harbor of Boston, because of the tea-affair, the Germans in Philadelphia called a meeting to discuss this matter. They appointed a Committee of Correspondence whose duty it was to get in touch with Germans in other colonies, and to encourage them to prepare for the coming inevitable conflict. To the provincial meeting, held in the same year, Germans from Pennsylvania came for the most part. Even more numerous they attended the convention in January, 1775. Being invited in their intentions, they insisted at every opportunity upon separation from the "mother-country", which to them was no mother country. Since they were no blood-relation of the English colonists, they did not hesitate to show a bold front toward their English masters. Later the Correspondence-Committee issued a pamphlet in which was stated: "The German in Pennsylvania have observed with satisfaction that the people accepted unanimously the resolutions of Congress, regardless of race, religion, nationality or social <pb facs="5418474_7_1481.jpg" n="13"/>standing. The Germans in particular have made preparations for war and formed new military organizations, which in case of war can be used wherever they are needed. These Germans, however, who can not bear weapons for any reason whatever, are expected, to do what they can for this patriotic cause.</p>
   <p>"All this happened before the war started. At the outbreak of the war the Germans were the first to defend their country and the last ones in laying down their weapons at the end of the conflict. In his History of Revolution" Bancroft says, "The Germans of pennsylvania were to be found on the side of liberty."</p>
   <p>At the beginning of 1775 the Germans organized armed troops to support congress. The German Society and the German Churches issued appeals to resist with the force of arms. German Clubs and Societies started to train soldiers....a patriotic drama took place at Woodstock, Va., where a young German minister, P. G. Muhlenberg, exchanged his pulpit for a sword and became Colonel of a German regiment. Because of his courage he advanced rapidly and finally became Major-General of the American <pb facs="5418474_7_1482.jpg" n="14"/>army. (His monument adorns the Hall of Fame at the capital city of the nation.) If we mention actions of bravery by Americans, then we must not forget the magnificent battles fought by Germans under Colonel Nicolaus Herchheimer against the Britons and Tories at Oriskany, N. Y.</p>
   <p>The first battalion of New York consisted mostly of Germans, and Baron Weissenfels, a German, was commander of other troops from New York...</p>
   <p>"Sacred to every American is that parcel of soil, where the noble German Baron De Kalb shed his blood for our liberty. A grateful people can never forget the great service of Baron von Steuben. Under Frederick, the Great, he was trained in the skill of war and became the training master and general inspector of the American Army. He was called "Washington's right hand."</p>
   <p>"During the winter of 1776 the army of Washington was reduced to 3000 men. <pb facs="5418474_7_1483.jpg" n="15"/>In this terrible condition Washington considered retreating back of the Alleghenies, but in the most critical moment his discouraged soldiers received reinforcement of 15000 recruits. This made it possible for Washington to win the battles at Trenton and Princeton. Upon the pages of our history the fact should be engraved with letters of gold, that every one of these men came from Pennsylvania, where nearly everybody is German or of German descent.</p>
   <p>"When Washington's army was hungering and starving and $100,000 had to be borrowed to purchase provisions, again it were nine Germans who gave security for this loan-a large sum in those days. It was a poor German baker, who contributed 200 lbs (sterling), while others debated negatively about the resolution to collect money publicly for the purchase of munition."</p>
   <p>"During the year 1787 the conventions were held which resulted in forming the <pb facs="5418474_7_1484.jpg" n="16"/>constitution-so profoundly important in our history. Mr. F. A. Muehlenberg, a German, and a brother of the General was elected president of the convention of Pennsylvania. Later he became the "speaker" of the first and third Congress, and due to his vote on April 29th, 1796, the acceptance of "Jay's Treaty" was decided. For this action moral courage was necessary, because he thereby exposed himself to the hate of the masses. Although the acceptance of the constitution was of vital importance to our existence as a nation. There prevailed serious doubts whether it would or would not be finally accepted. Again they were German-Americans, who following their sound judgment, made a powerful appeal for immediate ratifications."</p>
   <p>"Germans in great numbers fought in the front lines and defended their adopted country in the wars of 1812 and 1346. Already in 1688 the Germans protested against the crime of slavery, and it was therefore quite naturally that they accepted more than their share in the struggle for freedom and abolition of slavery at the outbreak of the Civil War. Thousands of Germans sacrificed their life to keep our national banner <pb facs="5418474_7_1485.jpg" n="17"/>High and intact and to keep the stars and stripes waving 'Over the land of the free and the home of the brave.!</p>
   <p>"It is a well-known fact that the Germans were responsible for winning the State of Missouri for the Union. But only a few know, how to appreciate the fact that Germans enlisted enthusiastically for our national defense during the bloody Civil War of 1861-1865. In the armies of the North 200,000 of them participated in the fighting. The first volunteers coming to the rescue of the nation during its darkest moments, when Fort Sumter was lost to the Confederates and the hearts of brave men shuddered, were 531 men from German regions in Pennsylvania.</p>
   <p>"However, the greatest triumphs the German settlers were seeking and also achieved, were peaceful endeavors. They took up weapons only when it was necessary for defense, but not in lust of blood.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1486.jpg" n="18"/>
   <p>Their fields blossomed as a rose and their farms were called the "Garden Spots" of the country. In every department of human endeavor are the results of their knowledge and their full devotion to their work recognizable.</p>
   <p>"Germans constructed the first waterworks of our country, the first smelting furnaces, textile and glass factories. They built the first paper factory and chemical works; they made the first pianos, watches and astronomical instruments, etc."</p>
   <p>The Brooklyn Bridge, the eighth wonder of the world, was built by a German, John Roebling. The great Nevada tunnel was designed and built by a German engineer, Adolf Sutro.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1487.jpg" n="19"/>
   <p>"German influence has been decisive in our educational systems, beginning with the "Kindergarden" up to our universities. Even the name "University", is used in the German sense and not in the English. The German-American teachers look back upon a glorious past." Let me remind you of the great pioneer, Pastorius, who in 1683 taught German, English, Spanish, French, Greek and Latin."</p>
   <p>The first work about pedagogic, which was published in America in 1770, was written by the German, Chr. Dock.</p>
   <p>"The Germans organized Sunday-schools and printed Sunday-school cards thirty six years before they were introduced in England by R. Raikes, who is usually considered as being the originator. It is conceded by many that Germany has been a "mother-country" for us intellectually."</p>
   <p>"Very few seem to understand, to what extent the influence of old German customs <pb facs="5418474_7_1488.jpg" n="20"/>have been felt in our daily life and how important this has been for the cultural development of our people. We may mention in this connection two of our most beautiful festivals, Christmas and Easter...."</p>
   <p>"Some writers have accused the German-Americans that their inactivity in politics is due to their incompetence and ignorance in regard to these matters. However, it is not difficult to explain this. First of all, it is the strange language, which he must learn. Then it is his honesty and love for personal liberty that make it almost impossible for him, to submit to a strict control of any political party and obey their political bosses, irrespective of other consideration. There again, almost without exception he masters a trade or profession; he is naturally thrifty, economical and industrial. It is therefore no advantage for him to join the "practical politicians" and to follow in their somewhat uncertain paths."</p>
   <p>The very reasons, which prevented him accepting brilliant roles in political <pb facs="5418474_7_1489.jpg" n="21"/>life, are exerting a beneficial influence in general. A careful, conservative, and independent constituency has been recruited from the ranks of the Germans. The Germans desire a loyal, just and patriotic government for the people and by the people. He can not be bought by any political party, whatever the consequences may be.</p>
   <p>"It is our duty as patriotic Americans to preserve and cultivate those lofty traditions, which have come to us from our ancestors."</p>
   <p>"What Greece was for Rome, that has Germany been for our beloved country with only one exception in our favor and that is: the German brought with his culture, a clean and happy homelife, honesty and superior moral laws."</p>
   <p>Great indeed are our opportunities to be inspired by what our ancestors have done and to do follow their steps in this country where freedom reigns and the banner of liberty waves over us."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1490.jpg" n="22"/>
   <p>A most brilliant impression made the recitals of the children's choirs. They sang under the direction of G. Katzenberger the following: "Deutschland uber alles" (Over all is Germany), "Muttersprache" (Mother Language), "Stimmtan mit hellem hoheu Klang" (Sing with a clear and lofty tone), and "My Country, 'tis of Thee". "Lohengren Phantasis" was magnificently rendered by the Ballmann's Orchestra. One more recital by the Men's Choirs brought to a close the first part of the program. The second part of the program furnished excellent musical enjoyment. Ballmann's Orchestra commenced with two compositions by Wagner: The brilliant prelude to "Maistersingeru", and the "Tannhaeuser Overture". The followed recitals of songs by the Katzenberger's Woman's Choirs: "Mutterseelenallein" (Alone like a Mother's Soul), and "Das, Panier der Freude" (The Banner of Joy). The United singers of Chicago" tendered two excellent numbers. Active gymnastics displayed marvelous accomplishments. Towards the close of the evenings program specially selected musical pieces offered a splendid variety: "Scenes from great operas" and "Light Cavalry."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1491.jpg" n="23"/>
   <p>With thundering tones pealed forth four German war marches. Several national and popular songs were played; also a German and an American watch parade. The festival closed officially by singing: "The Watch On The Rhine" and "Star Spangled Banner."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
