<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-11-04">Nov. 4, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">Charity Concert of the Vereinigte Maennerchoere Meets Approval</title><title level="a" type="sub">Delegates of the Larger Societies Promise Their Support Further Meetings</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0573</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0573.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1930-11-04">Nov. 4, 1930</date>.
<title level="a">CHARITY CONCERT OF THE VEREINIGTE MAENNERCHOERE MEETS APPROVAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Delegates of the Larger Societies Promise Their Support Further Meetings</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Forty-five delegates of the larger German societies assembled yesterday at the Steuben Club to plan additional preparation for the great charity concert which will be given by the Vereinigte Maennerchoere (United Men's Choruses) at the Medinah Temple on December 7. The net receipts will be handed over to the German Society and will be distributed among unemployed and destitute Germans.</p>
   <p>As representative of the German Society, its president, Consul General Michael F. Girten, attended the meeting. Mr. Girten explained to his listeners that the German Society's help is very much in demand, and that somehow or other it must get over a critical year. Not only is it short of cash; it is also in need of all useful articles of clothing, bedding, etc. <pb facs="5418474_7_0574.jpg" n="2"/>The delegates present promised, without exception, the active cooperation of their organizations in the preparations for the charity concert, and it was resolved to continue to make arrangements for the concert.</p>
   <p>At yesterday's meeting attention was called to the fact that it was not advisable for newly arrived immigrants to seek help at the various County agencies or at those of the United Charities because of the danger of their being reported to the immigration authorities and eventually deported as aliens who have become a burden to the public.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
