<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-12-06">Dec. 6, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">A Song Recital.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0652</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0652.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-12-06">Dec. 6, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">A SONG RECITAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Singing Society, presented yesterday evening, in the large ballroom of the Germania Club, a song recital, to which the public looked forward with great interest, the more, because this society appeared before the public in the past, mostly with larger choral works. And nobody was disappointed; on the contrary, those present, and they were many, were delighted by the variety of the songs offered, and rendered to the society, as well as its distinguished conductor, Wilhelm Boeppler, new and well merited praise.</p>
   <p>The program was not a very extensive one, and about one half of the numbers were conceded to two soloists, the cello virtuoso, Hans Hess, and the pianist, Miss Agathe Haenel. The evening was started with a pensive piece, "The Song" by Louis Spohr, the almost forgotten violin virtuoso, arranged by the conductor in a very tasteful manner for the chorus. The somewhat old fashioned song sounded quite modern in its new guise and met with great applause.</p>
   <p>There followed three songs dedicated to the singing society by Heinrich Johannsen: "Homeland", Holstein Landscape", and "Good night". This song by Theodore Storm was especially pleasing. There was such applause, that the <pb facs="5418474_7_0653.jpg" n="2"/>chorus had to repeat same. "A Legend" by Tschaikowsky, and an old English "Dancing Song" by Thomas Marley, were also of great beauty. A women's choir, "Moonlight" by Hugo Kann, and Saint Saens well known and often heard "Swan", also the closing choir, "Ring Out, Wild Bells", by Gounod, deserve to be mentioned as excellent performances.</p>
   <p>Miss Hanel had a difficult task in her opening number "32 Variations in C Minor" by Beethoven. This master composition of Beethoven's, which like his other variations have fallen into oblivion, require a lively technique and musical conception, and its excellent production proved that the pianist possesses both. Of her other performances, Chopin's "Nocturne Op. 37 No. 1" and Liszt's "E Major Polonaise" should be especially praised.</p>
   <p>Hans Hess enjoys with right, the reputation of a maestro on the cello, and he could not have opened his performance more appropriately than with Mozart's "Larghetto". There followed the piquant "Scherzo" by Dittersdorf, arranged by Kreisler, and "Harlequin" by Popper. This composer was represented in the last part with "Nymph Danz" and "Scherzo" by Brahms, which require an excellent technique. Continuous applause rewarded this virtuoso.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0654.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Miss Juul Rosine and Miss Mary Stange, took over the accompaniment on the piano, the former for Hess, the latter for the choir. We can not close our report, without mentioning the conductor. Mr. Boeppler added a new leaf to his glorious wreath with this song evening. The performances not only went well together, but they were musical masterpieces, which well deserve such designation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
