<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-05">Nov. 5, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Flag Dedication and Concert of the Singing Club Erinnerung</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1098</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1098.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-05">Nov. 5, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">FLAG DEDICATION AND CONCERT OF THE SINGING CLUB ERINNERUNG</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The male singing club Erinnerung, the youngest German Chorus in the city, received its outward signs of independence with the dedication of the new organization and national flags yesterday at a concert in the Englewood Masonic Temple, 64th Street and Loomis Boulevard. The chorus was successful in its first appearance before the public as an organization, giving a festival under the leadership of its director, H. A. Rehberg. The concert was aided by the Chicago Zither Club under its director, J. Waldherr, the Columbia Ladies' chorus of the South Side, the United Ladies' Choruses of Chicago, and the United Singers of Chicago, who with their singing added to the dignity and success of the evening.</p>
   <p>The young singing organization Erinnerung consists of a handsome group of singers, and is conducted by their leader, H. A. Rehberg, with a steady <pb facs="5418474_7_1099.jpg" n="2"/>and determined leadership. They sang "Ein Rheinisches Maedchen", "Die Bettelmaid", "Rheintrene", and the American national anthem.</p>
   <p>The Chicago Zither Club opened the program with a spiritual rendition of the "March of the Knights Templar", by P. Schwarz and by the concert overture "Sounds from Lake Erie", by H. Wormsbacher. It was accurately and effectively rendered under the conductor, J. Waldherr. In this connection, mention must be made of the South Side Columbia Ladies' Chorus, which quite successfully contributed its share at the dedication of the flags and distinguished itself in song, too, with the mixed chorus, by the singing of the fest song.</p>
   <p>The climax of the performance was the dedication of flags which were presented to all present in a most interesting form.</p>
   <p>With the singing of "The Star-Spangled Banner", the veiled American flag was carried into the hall by the ladies of the Columbia Ladies' Choir, <pb facs="5418474_7_1100.jpg" n="3"/>accompanied by maids of honor and conducted by the flag mother, Frau Marie Wehrwein. Here the surrender of the banner was made by County Clerk Robert M. Sweitzer, acting for Mayor Kelly, to the president of the organization. The coronation march from the opera "Le Prophete" was the cue for bringing in of the organization flag, still veiled; it was given over to the organization by the flag mother, Frau Marie Graf, for safe keeping.</p>
   <p>The job of giving over the flag to the president of the organization, John Reinish,was taken over by Dr. Otto L. Schmidt. The latter had already gained special honor by giving the new American flag to the organization. Giving a brief historical survey about the development of German singing in the United States, he then spoke of the significance of a special flag for the organization, admonishing the members to remain faithful to their flag.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1101.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Then came congratulations by Frau Ida Huch from the United Ladies' Choruses. Frau Schroeder from the Columbia Ladies' Chorus of the South Side, Philipp Behrens from the Schiller Tafel Vorwaerts, Max Hirsch from the United Singers of Chicago and Wilhelm Reichert from the Swabian Society. They all brought gifts in the shape of flag ribbons and parade gloves.</p>
   <p>Then festival president A. C. Wehrwein, who deserves special credit for the success of the fest, took the floor to present Frau Thiel, the designer of the flag, with a bouquet of flowers. The wife of the fest director, Mrs. H. A. Rehberg, also received a bouquet of flowers from the president as a token of appreciation. The two honorary members, Dr. Otto L. Schmidt and John E. Conroy, were given diplomas of distinction.</p>
   <p>The recitation of Wengert's "Sonntagfeier" by the United Ladies' Choruses, and of Dohring's "Saengerloebms" by the United Singers concluded the official <pb facs="5418474_7_1102.jpg" n="5"/>part of the fest. It was followed by a dance. Wilhelm Bartz, Jr. was at the organ during the entire concert.</p>
   <p>The fest committee was composed of: A. C. Wehrwein, fest president; John Reinisch; E. F. Schwarz, secretary; Adolf Hendler, ticket treasurer; Nicholaus Conrad, treasurer; E. Wangrin, chairman reception committee.</p>
   <p>The officers of the organization are: John Reinisch, president; Ernst Wangrin, vice-president; Emil F. Schwarz, secretary; Bernhard Hurlebusch, financial secretary; Ignatz Thiel, treasurer; Otto Drathner, keeper of archives; Arthur Metzger, "bummel" treasurer; John Reinisch, vice-director.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
