<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-01-10">January 10, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">German Theater. Der Kilometerfresser (The Mile Eater i. e. Speeder)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0111</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0111.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-01-10">January 10, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN THEATER. DER KILOMETERFRESSER (THE MILE EATER i. e. SPEEDER)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Farce in 3 acts by Karl Kraatz. The announced humorous farce, the successful laughter-piece by Kraatz also justified itself in Chicago. The audience was convulsed; it was so silly, one was simply compelled to laugh. At all events the "Speeder" accomplished its mission; it produced an exceptionally humorous evening and a nearly sold out house. The capable author followed the French examples to a certain extent and aside from this gave a pair of caricatures which were well drawn; to wit, the ultra-realistic author and the conceited actor. With the remaining figures he reverted to the "henpecked- husband," mother-in-law and Don Juan but he undertook to enshroud them in a whirl of mistaken identities, perplexities, comic situations and jokes which were as effective as sneeze-powder. A play of such caliber can only achieve this effect by rapid acting which gives insufficient time to the public, to realize the improbability of such occurances, and this was the case, yesterday.</p>
   <p>Exceptionally good were Miss Beringer, as mother in law, Mr. Bolten, Mr. Kleeman as poet and Miss Lizzie Forster.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
