<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-10-26">Oct. 26, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Die Fledermaus (The Bat)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0247</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0247.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-10-26">Oct. 26, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">DIE FLEDERMAUS (THE BAT)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In McVickers Theatre the Collmer-Isenstein Institute presented the night before last the "Fledermaus" (The Bat), the famous opera by Strauss before a completely filled house. The "Fledermaus" is more a musical comedy than an opera and excels by a well balanced and interesting action as well as by intoxicating music in which its producer, Johann Strauss is without doubt at present the Master Composer, from the very moment that the orchestra begins with the overture, till the end of the last act the listener is charmed by this enchanting music. Rosalinde von Einstein the wife of this frivolous banker, was represented by Miss Wassermann and this role gave the lady an opportunity to demonstrate her highly trained good voice, and her superb play. The demonstration of the character was a little too serious, so that all the chances of her play did not materialize. The honors of the evening were carried off by Miss Bertha Fribach as "Adele" the clever frivolous chambermaid who could adapt herself so well to the ensemble of the better class society found in her an exceedingly capable actress in play and song <pb facs="5418474_7_0248.jpg" n="2"/>even though her voice at times might have been a little bit stronger. Miss Fribach had to sing several songs da capo and brought the auditorium into ecstasies with the champagne song in the second act. Miss Scherzel played "Prince Orlowsky" very well. Her movements might have been a little more manly. Mr. Moritz Wassermann had a real triumph though he did not come up to his role in Gabriel von Eisenstein, by Strauss. The act was played too much like a dilettante so that we would advise the actor Wassermann to take an example from the singer Wassermann. His voice gives the expectation, that by good treatment it will give much better results. Mr. Selig represented the teacher "Alfred" in the play very well; also Mr. Heinemann the director of the prison "Frank." Both gentlemen were good singers and received much applause. Mr. Waldorf as notary, "Falke" did not come up to the mark. Mr. Meyer as prison warden "Frosch" well understood the principal points of his role. Attorney Blind has been portrayed by Mr. Kriner with a well balanced interpretation. The choirs and ensemble were passable; they could have been stronger as well as the Orchestra. The regie did its very best and it can be said, that taken as a whole it was a very successful entertainment, and well presented performance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
