<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-12-10">Dec. 10, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">Adolph Gill Re-Elected President of German Day Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1927-12-10">Dec. 10, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">ADOLPH GILL RE-ELECTED PRESIDENT OF GERMAN DAY FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Adolph Gill was again unanimously re-elected as president of the German Day Festival organization, which he has served faithfully for so many years. Attorney Leopold Saltiel was elected first vice-president; and Dr. William C. Teichmann, second vice-president; and six other vice-presidents were nominated and unanimously elected. They were; Mrs. Marie Wachtel, Mrs. Marie Weuchlinger, Lorenz Schlegel, William Jauhs, James Maschek, and Harry Schlosser.</p>
   <p>Justus Emme again took over the office of corresponding secretary; Dr. Jack W. Kobalter as recording secretary, Herman Loesicke was elected treasure, and Bruno Knecht was elected financial secretary. The agenda of the meeting, which was held yesterday at the Northside Turner hall, was extensive and several hours were required for its transaction.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1383.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The date for next year's festival was set for the first Sunday of June, 1928. The festival location will be the stadium in Grant Park.</p>
   <p>The report of the treasurer showed that the entire receipts amounted to $7,888.85 against expenditures of $6,032.98, and after $1,400 had been assigned to benevolent institutions, the balance of $1,008.25 remained.</p>
   <p>President Adolph Gill prefaced his yearly report with the remark that the German day festival of the year 1927 had been a glorious success, of which the Chicago German element can be justly proud. Highest appreciation is due the different committees for their tireless efforts through which this success was possible.</p>
   <p>Complete harmony was established through the offices of Dr. Kobalter, Joe Maschek, Gabriel Jung and Michael Schaid, in the Austrian, Hungarian and <pb facs="5418474_7_1384.jpg" n="3"/>Sudeten-German circles, and all prevailing misunderstandings were successfully ironed out. The yearly report praised the excellent co-operation of the Turners, of the sporting clubs, of the military societies, and last, but not least, of the singers.</p>
   <p>The highest compliments are paid to the two official speakers of the German day celebration: Senator Charles S. Deneen, of Illinois, and the Editor, Paul H. Ortmann.</p>
   <p>In regard to a possible intervention in local politics, the report states: "We should be very careful not to become affiliated with any of the local political controversies. The German citizenry of Chicago might be split through party controversies and political hatreds, and the great work which, to the present, has been successfully carried out through our efforts, would be considerably impaired."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1385.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The report closed with another expression of gratitude to all those who helped to make a success of this German day festival.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
