<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-23">Feb. 23, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">German Press Club's Entertainment a Great Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1006</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1006.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-23">Feb. 23, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN PRESS CLUB'S ENTERTAINMENT A GREAT SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The show given yesterday evening by the German Press Club at the Bismarck Hotel was a pronounced success, according to the unanimous verdict of the audience, and the gentlemen of the newspaper fraternity may congratulate themselves upon their having provided a most unique and acceptable entertainment. Even the most blase critics--and there are several in the ranks of the association--were not only silenced but overcome by the contagious hilarity and enthusiasm.</p>
   <p>Who could have remained serious in the presence of the good old midway dances, which even strained the tolerance of our Chicago censor, the honorable commissioner of public morals, who happened to be there. He considered it "the limit, and protested, whereupon he was promptly given the air, unceremoniously kicked out. And what about the songs and dances of graceful Yvette Guilbert, or that pantomine, "Wash Day in Paradise," followed by "An Hour in the Editorial <pb facs="5418474_7_1007.jpg" n="2"/>Chambers"?</p>
   <p>There were also, of course, more serious artistic offerings. Friends of the Club dedicated their versatile talents to the cause, thereby providing an exceptionally varied and interesting program. In this respect the Club is greatly indebted to Miss Jolanthe Pressburg, the well-known singer, who appeared in costume and regaled us with German and Hungarian songs; Mrs. Nanny Oesau for her effective recitation of Martin Drescher's prologue, especially written for the occasion, and her acting in the role of the society lady, "Frau Duennbier" (Thin Beer), in the "Editorial Chambers"; and also to Mrs. Hermann Meyer and Miss Herz for their delightful Hungarian dances; likewise to Paul Nelva, of the German Theater, for his inspiring tenor solos.</p>
   <p>The other artists were all active club members; in keeping with the inherent modesty of newspapermen, they prefer to remain incognito. We might mention, therefore, that aside from the Greek and French ladies, Professor X-Ray's scientific lecture, "The Cable and Wire Tapper, and the singing of "Pictures of <pb facs="5418474_7_1008.jpg" n="3"/>the Moment," or "Hu is Hu," in the Press Club, were very successful.</p>
   <p>Judge Girten, as "A Member at a Conference," gave a very capable presentation. Ballmann's music was excellent, as usual. The Chicago Stage Lighting Company helped with the illumination. The Watryheidkamp firm and the Chicago Telephone Company were also of assistance, for which the Club expresses its appreciation and thanks.</p>
   <p>It is very gratifying to note that, in spite of a relentless downpour, the audience was exceedingly large and was good-humored. Both of these factors must be a source of profound satisfaction to the gentlemen who gave unstinting effort and time to the necessary preparations. An informal dance was given after the performance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
