<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1880-04-19">April 19, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">German Drama.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0265</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0265.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1880-04-19">April 19, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN DRAMA.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Schillers great tragedy, "The Bride of Messina" was produced by M. Hoechsters German Dramatic Company at McVicker's last evening. This is one of Schillers greatest works. It is written in exquisit language in both blank and rhymed verse. But, like most of Schiller's, it is very difficult of production, as it is more of a reading than an acting play. This one differs from his others, inasmuch as it introduces speaking choruses just as singing choruses are introduced in opera, which makes its performance rather a novelty to most theatre-goers. To make a performance any kind of success it must be given by a capable company, for in the hands of an inferior one it would be sure to be butchered. There are six leading characters in the play, of each of whom great requirements are made; and, as sufficient first class material is not often found in a German company in this country, the play is very rarely given. As far as can be learned this tragedy has been performed here but once, and that was when Mlle. Janascheck first made her appearance here. Owing to the engagement of Miss Trschick, the renowned German tragedienne, M Hoechster was enabled to bring it out this time especially as in Messrs. Rodenberg, Ravene, Helmer and Klotz he had the actors fitted to take the male parts.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0266.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Messrs Rodenberg and Ravene were particularly well suited for the difficult parts of the two immical brothers. The character of Donna Isabella, Mother of the two brothers, is especially well adopted to the peculiar abilities of Miss Irschick, as it affords great chances for powerful and emotional acting.</p>
   <p>The performance surpassed the most sanguine expectations. It was really one of the very best given Since Miss Irschick's engagement while it was not altogether faultless, yet the few short-comings could be easily overlooked. Miss Irschick, at the unfortunate Mother, was unusually effective, and the applause she received showed how well she was appreciated. The parts of the two brothers, Con Caosar and Don Manuel, could hardly have been in better hands then those of Messrs. Rodenberg and Ravene. The former particularly showed such unusual power that he fairly shared the honors of the evening with the great tragedienne.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
