<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-05">Nov. 5, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Schiller Liedertafel Holds its Fall Concert</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-05">Nov. 5, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SCHILLER LIEDERTAFEL HOLDS ITS FALL CONCERT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Friends of male singing, who last Sunday, on the occasion of this year's fall concert given by the Schiller Liedertafel, filled the Wicker Park Hall to the last seat, will long remember the musical productions, which fulfilled the highest artistic expectations.</p>
   <p>The concert was opened with Beethoven's chorus, "Die Ehre Gottes". It was powerfully rendered under the leadership of the director, Reinhold Walter, with orchestra accompaniment. For the orchestral part of the program, the Schiller Liedertafel engaged the orchestra of W. Hebs which, after the close of the performance, also played for the dance. Several a cappella numbers bore witness to the efforts and care with which the musical part of the program was prepared by the director of the organization. Mrs. Sylvia Peterson Tiller, soprano soloist, sang "Elsa's Dream" from the opera "Lohengrin", by Wagner, and "Widmung", by Schuman. She was rewarded with rich applause for her work. Following the orchestral presentation of "Auf der Wacht," in which Herr Hebs played a trumpet solo that was received with approval, <pb facs="5418474_7_0444.jpg" n="2"/>the chorus and orchestra offered "Am Altar der Wahrheit," by Mohr; this concluded the elegant program that was presented with talent and artistic taste. A ball that followed the concert brought to those who wanted to dance, especially to the young folks, hours of pleasant entertainment.</p>
   <p>Just as the concert program took care of solid spiritual enjoyment, so did the host organization and its fest committee provide bodily enjoyment, in adequate form.</p>
   <p>The committee was composed of the gentlemen: Henry Kating, president; Fritz Rosen, treasurer; Reinhold Reinecke, secretary. and Kurt Reinecke, Karl Steidle, Max Jakowsky, August Niebling, Walter Tiller, Tony Bischoff, Max Lane, Emil Bahnmeier, Albert Freund, and Paul M. Wagner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
