<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-09-28">Sept. 28, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">German Theatre</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0253</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0253.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-09-28">Sept. 28, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN THEATRE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday's performance in Mc Vickers Theatre gave an opportunity to the artistic ensemble of "Collmer-Isenstein" to show themselves in their most superb light, and the success and applause they gained was the more deserved as it has been caused exclusively by the magnificent action of their play. The anacted piece, "The Demented Woman" comedy in four acts by Hugo Buerger, is a rather superficial play without any deeper sentiments, even offending against the existing rules of stupidity, and it can only be made enjoyable by an extra good performance by principal actors.</p>
   <p>There is no trace of unity of action in the play. It refers to two love intrigues which are far apart and both different in their development and solution. The Demented Woman or the Narrow Minded Girl, which latter might be a better title, cannot be considered the main attraction of the play. The character of the piece is a very agreeable one, " a loving girl with all the tenderness of the female sex," The representation of this love is much too simple to make it a foundation of a comedy. Furthermore, it is very risky to present to the public a young, beautiful, rich, educated, amiable girl, <pb facs="5418474_7_0254.jpg" n="2"/>who out of love to a narrow minded father also represents herself demented. The faults of the piece, however, were counteracted by the excellent acting of the artists. Miss Fiebach, the demented girl "Stefians," gave a poetical charm to her superb play.</p>
   <p>She received repeated applause from the public, which was well deserved. Miss Trautmann excelled by her effective, well-balanced play as the lady of the drawing room and also by the effects of her devoted womanly love. Miss Van Kaselowska and Mrs. Meyer mastered their acts well. Mr. Richard demonstrated, in the part of Werner, the perfectly educated artist as he is already known to the Chicago public. The good-acting talent of Mr. Meyer repeated itself in yesterday's performance. Messrs. Engel Waldorf and Redenberg did their best for the success of the entire piece.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
