<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1892-08-29">August 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">To the German Song Clubs and German Singers of Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0812</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0812.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1892-08-29">August 29, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">To the German Song Clubs and German Singers of Chicago.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Executive Committee of the Allied Men's Choirs of Chicago has received an invitation from Mr.Tomlin, musical manager of the Worlds Fair, to have all German Singers participate in the inauguration festival on October 21.</p>
   <p>Mr.Tomlin expects a participation of about 1000 singers and songstresses. Let us all try to make this festival a great success for the German singers and let us try to excel this number of singers asked for as much as possible. On September I we will receive the musical notes (they can be obtained free of charge in the Detmer's Music Store in the Schiller Building) and it will be desirable that all clubs make a start. The musical notes are not very difficult. It is anticipated to have three principal rehearsals, two in the auditorium and the last one on the place of festival.</p>
   <p>Everybody, who can sing, should make it a point of honor to participate and join a song club to study the songs. Song clubs, which have a mixed chorus are asked to strengthen same and the German ladies especially are invited to join same or to join the ladies chorus of Mr.G.Katzenberger.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0813.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There will be no expense to any of the participants. The last rehearsal takes place on the morning of the festival in the singer's hall of the Fair and free transportation and refreshments are granted. The singers can remain on the place of the festival to wait for the beginning of the opening of the Fair.</p>
   <p>Allied Men Choirs.</p>
   <p>Franz Amberg, Pres.</p>
   <p>Henry Detmer, Sec.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
