<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-11-28">Nov. 28, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">German Group at World's Fair Asks for Co-Operation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-11-28">Nov. 28, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN GROUP AT WORLD'S FAIR ASKS FOR CO-OPERATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German group of the 1933 Chicago World's Fair has invited all Germans of Chicago to a meeting Saturday evening in the Knickerbocker Hotel. The group is attempting to launch a campaign to collect money to present a dignified representation of the Germans of Chicago and the United States at the Fair. A company of about one hundred ladies and gentlemen, representative of the German element, its organizations, and larger clubs, responded to the summons.</p>
   <p>Mr. [Ernest J.] Kruetgen, chairman of the German group; Dr. Otto L. Schmidt, Fred Zimmermann, the ex-Governor of our neighboring state, Wisconsin; and Otto Reich sat at the table of regents. The first three men were the speakers of the evening.</p>
   <p>Following a brief welcome Mr. Kruetgen recalled the World's Fair of the year 1893, and declared emphatically that the Century of Progress exposition will positively be opened on June 1 of the coming year.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1299.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The German Government," the speaker continued, "will hardly be able to participate. It therefore remains for us Germans to see to it that the German element is worthily represented, at least on a basis of equality with all of the other groups. If we are not to bask in the splendor of the German exhibit as in 1893, we should at least show the other nations what we have contributed to the building up of the land. We must demonstrate our achievements in such a manner that the visitors to the Fair cannot overlook them, but may see with their own eyes what America owes to the Germans. If only we did not continually under-estimate ourselves! We are proud of our German fatherland and our German blood, and we intend to do our best to show the world our capabilities. In Chicago alone there are approximately six hundred thousand persons of German descent; added to these are the many millions in other parts of the United States who are called upon to lend a hand. For the affair with which we are concerned is not local, but national. The German button or pin of the Fair should be worn everywhere in the country as a badge of honor. It should be a pleasure for every German to lend his aid, and, out of love for the old fatherland, to contribute to the success of the German department."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1300.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Dr. Otto Schmidt, the historian, stated briefly: "We are at fault when we are forgotten. But now is our chance to show what we were--what we are." Dr. Schmidt recalled the days before the Revolution when they spoke in Pennsylvania of "ignorant and stupid Germans," referring to them as people whose language "one did not understand". But in the course of the years it was a German who manufactured the first paper. Germans were masters in the weaving of woolens, in printing the first Bible in a foreign language, and in farming, for they excelled in the field of agriculture. Germans gave the country great men--to name only a few of the many names mentioned by Dr. Schmidt: Zenger, the apostle of a free press; Pastorius, Lieber, the friend of gymnastics; [Major General] Osterhaus, [General Franz] Sigel, Carl Schurz, Steuben, and many others. They have made great inventions, and have contributed many products of industry, but in politics they have played no part.</p>
   <p>The history of the German element in America from the time of its immigration is to be shown at the Fair in pictures, documents, and manuscripts.</p>
   <p>Ex-Governor Zimmermann boosted the purchase of Fair buttons and pins. He attacked <pb facs="5418474_7_1301.jpg" n="4"/>the subject like a cavalryman, and indorsed the sale of these emblems to collect money, not only from Chicago, but from all over the country, for the use of the German group at the Fair. He declared, amid boisterous mirth, that he felt stimulated by the "Chicago spirit," and he singled out ladies and gentlemen whom he saw there, calling them by name. He praised their propensity for working together for a common good, and their interest in the Chicago World's Fair and in the German cause. He said that forty-four nations have agreed to participate in the Fair, and that we Germans must not be missing.</p>
   <p>"When the fifty million Fair visitors return home," said Mr. Zimmermann, they will have seen that in America there is a strong and self-conscicus German element, and in Chicago, a good citizenry.</p>
   <p>"Begin now the work of soliciting for the German honor badge of the Fair," the ex-Governor continued. "Start here in this city wish its six hundred thousand Germans, its great organizations and clubs, its churches, social gatherings, and circles of friends. Then go farther, to cities, towns, and country places to create interest in the three-point German program: The World's Fair, Chicago, <pb facs="5418474_7_1302.jpg" n="5"/>and the German cause." These three points were expressed decisively and saliently, not unlike three other points: German Art, Literature, and Industry.</p>
   <p>Mr. Zimmermann pleaded ardently for interest and co-operation. "To each and every German, the Fair's pin and the button must be of worth: it must by no means be regarded as merely a receipt for a dollar paid, but as a badge of honor for having helped toward German success."</p>
   <p>A short moving picture was shown between the speeches. These pictures, taken from an airplane, showed what was being done at the site of the Fair. There were also pictures of Chicago--the mecca of mankind's pilgrimages from every part of the world in the coming year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
