<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-12">Feb. 12, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Thirty-Sixth Annual Festival of Frauen Kranken Unterstuetzungs-Verein Fortschritt</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1190</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1190.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-12">Feb. 12, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THIRTY-SIXTH ANNUAL FESTIVAL OF FRAUEN KRANKEN UNTERSTUETZUNGS-VEREIN FORTSCHRITT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p/>
   <p>Yesterday, in the Soziale Turner Hall, the Frauen Kranken Unterstuetzungs Verein Vortschritt (Women's Sick Benefit Society Progress) held a festival to celebrate the thirty-sixth anniversary of its founding. The eleborate entertainment, and the ball which concluded the affair, won new laurels for this society, which is generally popular in German circles. The attendance alone was ample evidence of this, for early in the evening the hall was filled to capacity. The festive spirit, which became evident very early, was a further indication of the successful efforts of an extremely active festival committee.</p>
   <p>The ladies Augusta Heide--who is president of the Society--Sadie Hildemann, Kaethe Wolf, Anna Hegenscheidt, Regina Schneeweiss,H. Wede, Christine, Mass, <pb facs="5418474_7_1191.jpg" n="2"/>Marie Grosch, Clara Gruhn, Minnie Koch, Adele Petschke, Bersha Klar, Therese Kehrens, Lucie Lehmann, Marian Duekert, Therese Cottschalk, and Amalie Kirch, were active on the committee.</p>
   <p>The extremely varied program suited the taste of every visitor, and was extremely well presented. After President Augusta Heide and o ened the festival with an eloquent speech, the singing section of the Fortschritt Society, under the direction of Karl Reckzeh, entertained the company with a few selections, which were not with such enthusiastic approval that the singers were forced to give several encores.</p>
   <p>The Saengerbund Freiheit (Freedom Singing Association and the La Salle Frauencher ( women's Chorus), also under the direction of Mr. Reckzeh, were responsible for part of the program, and acquitted themselves of their task with great skill, earning well-deserved recognition. They, too, were compelled <pb facs="5418474_7_1192.jpg" n="3"/>to give encores.</p>
   <p>The same can be said of the Alpenlaender Maennerchor (Alpine Male Chorus), which, under the leadership of its well-known director, Woldemar (sic) Christoph, furnished proof that it need not be ashamed of its performances. These singers, also, were prevailed upon, by the applause, to give encores.</p>
   <p>The entertainment was concluded with the performance of a short play, "Oceania Elastica," under the direction of Anna Weiss. Thanks to the excellent cast, the performance was a complete success. Those who took part in the play were Marie Wulter, Lina Hesse, Louise Deulig Anna Waechter, Fannie Wagner, and Marian Duckert.</p>
   <p>The ball which followed, for which Henke's Orchestra furnished excellent music, as usual, gave all the guests an opportunity to dance to their heart's <pb facs="5418474_7_1193.jpg" n="4"/>content. Delicious refreshments ere served.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
