<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-13">Apr. 13, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Gay Anniversary Celebration</title><title level="a" type="sub">Eichenstamm Royal Hungarian Society Holds Successful Celebration at North Side Turner Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1404</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1404.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-13">Apr. 13, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">GAY ANNIVERSARY CELEBRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Eichenstamm Royal Hungarian Society Holds Successful Celebration at North Side Turner Hall</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>All branches of the Royal Hungarian Society Eichenstamm (Oak Trunk) held their eleventh anniversary festival last Sunday at the North Side Turner Hall. It was a great success in every respect. The number of participants at the festival was quite satisfactory, and the excellent program found general applause.</p>
   <p>Numbers by various song organizations, dances by tap dancing organizations (Schuh-Plattler) in mountain garb, and a good orchestra, all contributed to furnish some pleasant hours for the participants. With the close of the official program, there began an easygoing program with dances and all sorts of solo performances by first-class artists, who received universal recognition.</p>
   <p>The German aid society "Evig Treu" (Forever Faithful) celebrated its great <pb facs="5418474_7_1405.jpg" n="2"/>Spring festival in the Social Turner Hall. They presented humorous dramas, comic recitations, and dances. The mixed chorus "Eintracht" (Harmony) took active part at the celebration and provided pleasure with its excellent program. All the humorous scenes, duets, and solo dramatizations (including a number of musical offerings) incited the audience to general mirth and great applause. Following these performances a dance, with music furnished by an excellent orchestra, brought the evening to a happy close for all the guests.</p>
   <p>That the Bunco game enjoys general popularity in German circles may be proved by the number of social organizations which, each Sunday find recreation from the week's toils in the little game. The following organizations had Bunco games for their members: Society of avarians, from the Town of Lake, in the Sachs Hall; the Thuringian Women's Club of Chicago, at Immel's Hall; Branch No. 1 of Eisenburg German-Hungarian Sick-Aid Society of Chicago, at St. George School Hall; the North Side Mixed Chorus, in Koch's Hall; the Columbia Ladies' Club and the District No. 495 D. U. B. (German-Hungarian Bund) at the Lincoln Turner Hall; Society of German Comrades in Arms, at the Vorwaerts (Forward) Turner Hall; <pb facs="5418474_7_1406.jpg" n="3"/>Viola Ladies' Club, at Fleiner's Hall and the Ladies' Club Fidelia, at the Armitage Hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
