<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-03-30">Mar. 30, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">Recognition</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">German Actors Present Laurel Wreath to an English Colleague</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0291</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0291.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Der Westen</title> (Sunday Edition of Illinois Staats-Zeitung),
<date when="1879-03-30">Mar. 30, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">RECOGNITION</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">German Actors Present Laurel Wreath to an English Colleague</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the yellow fever ravaged the South last September, the malady claimed Mrs. Methua-Scheller, who lived in Vicksburg, Tennessee at the time, and two days later her husband and sixteen-year-old son also succumbed. All who knew Mrs. Methua-Scheller, as an artist or personally, were greatly grieved. Among the sorrowing friends was Milton Nobles, who is appearing at Hamlin's theater. In Vicksburg he found the forgotten grave of the artist. As a token of affection and appreciation, he provided a monument, and last evening his kindness was rewarded. As the end of the second act, during the performance of the play "Phoenix," Messrs. W. Meyer, Hans Ravene, and Julius Rodenberg presented Nobles with a laurel wreath on a blue silk pillow. A white silk ribbon bore the legend: "A token in recognition of Milton Nobles, by the German actors of Chicago". A gold ring, engraved with Nobles' name, was included in the girt. Mr. Meyer, in a short speech, explained the motives for the present, whereupon Nobles, <pb facs="5418474_7_0292.jpg" n="2"/>deeply moved and scarcely able to suppress his tears, replied that what he had done he considered merely a sacred obligation to the artist who advised and guided him when he was but a neophyte in art. He never thought of recognition, nor did he seek it. He thanked his colleagues who are serving the same Muse, though in another language.</p>
   <p>Such an emotional scene probably never was presented at Hamlin's theater. The public listened breathlessly, and appeared deeply affected.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
