<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-10-12">Oct. 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Brilliant Outcome of the German Day.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1459</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1459.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-10-12">Oct. 12, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">BRILLIANT OUTCOME OF THE GERMAN DAY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A festival of great importance took place in the Medinah Temple yesterday, a celebration which will form an honorable page in the history of local Germans. The German Society celebrated its 60 year Jubilee, in conjunction with the German American National Alliance in a festive Manner, and the correct supposition, that the Medinah Temple which can hold 5,000 people, would not prove large enough for all the guests who wished to attend the performance of the allegoric musical festival play. "Humanity". An afternoon as well as an evening performance were arranged.</p>
   <p>After the beautiful voices of the men's chorus died away, Judge M. F. Girten ascended the stage, and in few words pointed out the importance of the day, and the special purpose fatherland put in their appearance to participate in the charitable work of the German society. We German Americans, among whom I count myself, have to be clear about the fact that to us, as Americans, the welfare of this country must be close to our hearts, but at the same time we should not forget, that we are of German descent, that it is our duty to honor and respect our race. As a good American citizen, we can remain good Germans; unfortunately, <pb facs="5418474_7_1460.jpg" n="2"/>the German thought has been put into the background, the European war has shaken up many Germans, and it leaves the impression, that the Germans are being considered as old coats, which were not in style any longer. One should with great pride, admit himself to be a German. Since the outbreak of the war, they have been inciting against everything that is German, they have even gone so far as to assert, that, if Karl Schurz would be alive today, he would stand on the other side, because according to his views, it is Germany that has provoked this bloody war, from desires of conquest, but none of us will ever believe such accusations. Much already has been done by the Germans to clear up this distortion, so that today, even if Germany has not yet won the final victory, it has certainly gained moral victory. The speaker reminded his listeners that Karl Schurz made a speech on August 12, 1870, in which he pointed out, referring to the war going on at that time, that Germany was not capable of any conspiracy, as its enemies would have us believe, and that therefore, he is sure that Karl Schurz would stand by our side, today if he were alive. The German people are numerous, more than six million Germans came to this country, and although not pure and unmixed, this number has greatly increased through family growth. We are not new arrivals, no hirelings, but we have co-operated in the bloom of this, our new home.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
