<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-18">Aug. 18, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">... Austrian Day.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1616</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1616.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-18">Aug. 18, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">... AUSTRIAN DAY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4.. Throughout Chicago and America there is no distinction between the two separate political entities of the new German empire and the Austro-Hungarian monarchy. They all are American fellow-citizens faithfully united to uphold our traditional rights and to promote the beneficial German influence which has done so much for the welfare of this nation.</p>
   <p>Even abroad in their homeland one notes this fellowship of Germans from the empire and the Austrian-Germans, although the world's history has traced a political boundary between them for the last 27 years. The status of German Austria today does not conform to Ludwig Uhland's speeches in the first German parliament, wherein he demanded that "Austria should be an integral part of Germany."</p>
   <p>Nevertheless today the Germans of the two separate empires have only one heart and although there exists a distinct political division, they have that satisfying assurance that they are united and protected against aggression.</p>
   <p>These then are the reasons why the 18th day of August, the specific Austrian <pb facs="5418474_7_1617.jpg" n="2"/>day now held at the World's Fair, is as much a typical German day as June the 15th... both are synonymous of Germanism.</p>
   <p>The Austrian and German artistic and industrial accomplishments at the exposition are a brotherly competition which brought works of transcending beauty and reached the apex of perfection.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
