<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-16">Feb. 16, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Allied Singers of Chicago Annual Great Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0754</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0754.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-16">Feb. 16, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">ALLIED SINGERS OF CHICAGO ANNUAL GREAT FESTIVAL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Allied Singers of Chicago held their festival yesterday in the large hall of the Wicker Park Building. About 250 singers and a number of guests were present. Theodore G. Behrens, president of the Alliance, opened the evening festivities with a solemn prologue, in which he welcomed the guests and expressed his satisfaction at the large attendance. Judge George Kersten, who agreed to act as master of ceremonies, could not be present due to some indisposition. Therefore the president selected the vice-president of the Singers Alliance of the Northwest to take up the function, and Mr. Albert Roos performed his official duties most admirably throughout the evening. Then followed several songs, veritable treats, under the leadership of H. A. Rehberg; an exceedingly humorous monologue, by Leo Schlegel, which won much acclaim; and a jovial instrumental recitation by Franz Larwin. Wilhelm Arens, president of the United Male Choral Societies <pb facs="5418474_7_0755.jpg" n="2"/>of Chicago, was present as one of the guests. He was cordially received, and upon being given the floor expressed his pleasure in being able to bring greetings from the other large choral alliance.</p>
   <p>The mutual understanding of these combined associations to help each other whenever a large public affair is under consideration, is indeed excellent and laudable. The next number on the program consisted again of combined choral offerings and many solo numbers in which Max Frahm, baritone, Emil Bertholt, C. Laube, Hermann Hirsch, and others participated. A few fitting words were also added by Mr. Rehberg. The entire festival deserves credit as having been an exceedingly delightful social event among friends.</p>
   <p>The Allied Singers of Chicago represent the following clubs: Chicago Liedertafel, a singers' club; Concordia Liedertafel, of the German Veterans of Town of Lake; Fidelia, Harugari Liedertafel, Northwest Liederkranz, <pb facs="5418474_7_0756.jpg" n="3"/>Richard Wagner Male Chorus, Saengerlust, West Side Saengerkranz, Harlem Male Chorus, and Harmony, of Forest Park. This year's grand concert will be given on Sunday, April 23, in Cohan's Grand Opera Mouse.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
