<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-10-09">Oct. 9, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The German Floats on Chicago Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1596</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-polish #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1596.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II A 3 c</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3) (Polish)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-10-09">Oct. 9, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN FLOATS ON CHICAGO DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Two illustrations, about 5" x 7", appear in this issue. The first shows a group of soldiers and a flag with the inscription Valley Forge to the left. On the right side are a number of Germans of Chicago in their gymnasium uniforms, and a banner with the inscription of "Chicago Turngemeinde." A log house with an American flag appears at an elevation, slightly to the left of the center. Further back and still higher, forming the center, is a pedestal on which the Goddess of Liberty stands with the American coat of arms and flag. Prophetically, and in conformity with modern trends, she looks to the left, pointing the flag that way. A number of American flags, arranged as a fan, are in front and below the log house and pedestal, forming the true center of the design. At a lower level is an eagle with a wing spread of about seven feet, inclining its head and holding in its claws, an equally large, open book with the years 1776 and 1861 on its pages. The scene or ground is a rock-covered mound. The dimensions are not given. Using the figure in the foreground as a gauge <pb facs="5418474_7_1597.jpg" n="2"/>and assuming this soldier to be five feet eight inches tall, the float would be thirty feet long and about nineteen feet high. This coincides with the available proportions of the Chicago float, which was twelve feet wide and thirty feet long. Both illustrations are linework sketches. There will be twenty-five floats in the parade, including the two German displays. England's float is to be drawn by twelve horses, likewise the panorama of Sweden; the latter having a mythological theme. Ireland will present St. Brendan aboard a fragile boat. According to Hibernian folklore, he is the discoverer of America. The second float will be the spirit of Erin. Poland will have four floats.... France, two..... Almost all nationalities will be represented.</p>
   <p>For the last float a huge dragon has been tentatively selected. The grewsome reptile will be illuminated by 2,000 alternating green and red incandescent lights installed by the Edison Company. Also, the famous fire engine, "Old Economy," of the Chicago Fire will be there, manned by five veteran members of the original volunteer company of nine..... Germans in connection with the above are: N. Dubach, captain; John Stoltz, leader <pb facs="5418474_7_1598.jpg" n="3"/>of the fire hose crew; R. Stringer, teamster. The article covers about five full pages and is continued through two editions.]</p>
   <p>Float 1. "The Spirit of Music," surrounded by a select female chorus of fifty in costume conducted by Prof. G. Katzenberger. In the foreground there are three young girls; the girl in the center is beating time with a silver baton, the ones on either side of her carry a triangle and a flute. To the rear there are allegorical figures with lyre, reed fife and tambourine. During the parade the chorus will sing S. G. Pratt's hymn, and Liberty," as well as other patriotic airs.</p>
   <p>Float 2. "Chicago I Will!" This float is surrounded by all the States of the Union welcoming the people of the earth. On the four corners are the muses of sculpture, music, science, and literature. "Chicago" is enthroned on an elevated platform mounted upon the globe. The predominating color scheme of this assembly is gold, framed with silver and white. It was built by Mr. A. Steidle, 106 Randolph Street, and is twelve by thirty feet. The float will be drawn by eight horses, supplied by the James Kirk Company.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1599.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Float 7. "Commerce of Chicago,".... Drawn by eighteen horses, three abreast, led by men in mediaeval array.... a contribution of the Chicago Stock Exchange.</p>
   <p>Float 8. "Columbus at the Spanish Court." This portrays the well-known scene in which Isabella decides to pawn her crown jewels to raise the necessary money for the expedition.... This work of Aloys Loeher will be drawn by six black horses loaned by the Seipp Brewery.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
