<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1892-09-30">September 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Schiller Theatre.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1681</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1681.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1892-09-30">September 30, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The Schiller Theatre.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The doors of the Schiller Theatre have been opened yesterday for the first time to the great public. Shortly after 8 p.m. the curtain rose, solemn music filled the hall, and Liberian Gans recited the festival prolog composed by himself. The impressiveness was immense. The Orphans Mens' Choir sang the sacred song by Mohr with splendid results. The Chairman, Mr.Franz Amberg, presented the principal speaker of the evening, Mr. A. C. Hesing and pointed out that he deserved the greatest praise in bringing about this superb undertaking, which is the pride of the Germans in Chicago and an ornament to the city. He not only gave the idea for the building of the theatre, but also took the greater part of the work involved, on his shoulders.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hesing in a splendid speech, gave a description of the theatrical conditions in Chicago, their previous difficulties, the alliance of the Chicago - Milwaukee stage and finally the completion of the present undertaking, which he hoped will have the full support of the German public.</p>
   <p>Several more speeches were made and beautiful songs given and an excellent living picture was presented.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1682.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The building itself is a gorgeous affair. From every point in the theatre a splendid view of the stage can be obtained. The decorations in gold seagreen, and lightbrown have a very pleasant effect. Two large paintings, one representing poetry and another one a scene from the life of Homer "give a pleasant relief". The middle figure represents Schiller on the Pegasns with three allegorical figures at his side, whose genius represents poetry and truth. Other figures represent strength, beauty, etc.</p>
   <p>The left group representing the old hero singer, Homer in the midst of his listeners, warriors, women, students, and children. Allegories representing music, painting and sculpture complete the figures of this masterpiece. Both paintings were executed by the artist Rich. Bock.</p>
   <p>The painting on the side walls have been made by Arthur Fendel and represent Faust meeting Gretchen coming from church and a scene from Maria Stuart, kneeling before Elizabeth, her royal enemy.</p>
   <p>The stage decorations have been done by Messrs.Grover and Barridge and are superb. The whole installation offers the best and most modern, that can be supplied.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
