<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-07-04">July 4, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">All's Well That Ends Well</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Singers' Picnic, a Real German Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1766</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1766.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-07-04">July 4, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">ALL'S WELL THAT ENDS WELL</title><title level="a" type="Sub">The Singers' Picnic, a Real German Festival</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Singers' Festival is over! Most of the participants are homeward bound, and the few stragglers are making preparations to leave. As a fitting finale to the Festival a picnic was held at Wright's Grove, and at least 25,000 people were present. There were no disturbances of any kind; every-thing progressed smoothly, and the weather was very favorable.....Songs, flags, and club emblems all helped to enliven the assemblage.....[Translator's note: Descriptive matter omitted; titles of songs not mentioned in the original text.]</p>
   <p>About five o'clock the Germania Chorus, joined by hundreds of guests, marched toward the band stand. Harry Rubens then announced that Mayor Harrison could not appear because he did not feel well. Smiles appeared everywhere--after all, had not the "best Mayor Chicago ever had" made an awful blunder a few <pb facs="5418474_7_1767.jpg" n="2"/>days ago, when he cracked jokes about other cities while visitors from them were present at the banquet? And so Harrison could not deliver his speech in this instance as he had promised. Mr. Rubens introduced Emil Hoechster as the principal speaker, whereupon the latter mounted the platform and spoke about as follows:</p>
   <p>"Ladies and gentlemen! I have grown accustomed to speaking whenever some other speaker fails to keep his promise. But I am too much of a German to complain about it. After all, we are here in the interest of German art and German traditions, and 1 am always ready to do anything to promote the cause, to protect our traditions against American arrogance, and to defend art against the intrusion of bunglers.</p>
   <p>"The Song Festival a few days ago was typically German in character despite all efforts to Americanize it, and I hope that Buffalo will keep its promise and renounce all attempts to make the next song festival an American affair. (Applause.)</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1768.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Our Festival exceeded our expectations in so far as the musical aspect was concerned, but we all felt that not enough emphasis was placed on German songs.</p>
   <p>"Only one discordant note interrupted our Festival and threatened to terminate it abruptly, the news from Washington that an assassin had attacked our beloved President, James A. Garfield, who now hovers on the brink of death. However, the latest news shows that he is improving and revives our hope that he will live.</p>
   <p>"This, then, ladies and gentlemen, gives us greater reason than ever to celebrate this festival. Let our joy be unbounded, and let us show the Americans that we can enjoy festivals without degrading ourselves.</p>
   <p>"Let us give three rousing cheers for our beloved President and hope for his speedy recovery!"</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1769.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The crowd shouted boisterously, and the picnic continued in conformity with the speaker's suggestion.</p>
   <p>Order prevailed everywhere, and the police, commanded by Major Heinzmann and Lieutenant Baus had only one job to perform; they were kept busy catching the youngsters, who climbed over the fences to filch a little grub here and there, and [the officers had] to put them outside the enclosure again.</p>
   <p>The committee on arrangements had selected dancing sites in the places which were least shaded by the trees, and as a result of the warm weather only a few couples danced, despite the highly inviting tunes played by the band. With the approach of cooler temperature in the evening dancing was generally indulged in, and fully as many couples danced on the rough sod as on the platforms.</p>
   <p>During the evening thousands of lights illuminated the place; calcium lights, ascending balloons, apparently aglow, and rockets lent to the affair a most <pb facs="5418474_7_1770.jpg" n="5"/>fantastic aspect.</p>
   <p>Among the guests was Mrs. Peschka-Leutner, who rested on the lawn, since there was a dearth of chairs.</p>
   <p>The following clubs were represented at the picnic:</p>
   <p>From Out of Town</p>
   <p>Buffalo; Liedertafel; Turner Maennerchor, Cincinnati; Sozialer Maennerchor, St. Louis; Nord St. Louis Bundeschor, St. Louis; Cleveland Gesangverein; Germania Maennerchor, Cincinnati; Beethoven Liederkranz, Richmond, Indiana; Liederkranz, Columbus, Ohio; Orpheus, St. Louis; Sozialer Maennerchor, Louisville; Buffalo Saengerbund.</p>
   <p>Chicago Clubs</p>
   <p>Nord Chicago Maennerchor, Germania Maennerchor, Schiller Liedertafel, Freier <pb facs="5418474_7_1771.jpg" n="6"/>Saengerbund, Sennefelder Liederkranz, Druiden Maennerchor, Liederkranz Eintracht, Gesangverein Frohsinn, Concordia Gesangverein, Teutonia Maennerchor, Chicago Turngemeinde, Schwabenverein.</p>
   <p>Side Lights</p>
   <p>.....[Translator's note: Description of the departure of the various clubs, in substantially this manner: "They regretted to leave!" All together one half column of it, all omitted.] The reporter for the Cincinnati Volksblatt complained that the singers from his city did not receive a proper reception. He is mistaken, or let us say misinformed. The committee members appeared on horseback and afoot and even had a corps of musicians to welcome the Germania Maennerchor of Cincinnati, but the Chicago band did not play because the Cincinnati singers had a band of their own.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
