<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-10-07">Oct. 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">German Veterans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1600</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1600.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-10-07">Oct. 7, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN VETERANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Preparations have been completed for the gala celebration of German veterans, to be held on Oct. 8 in the German Village of the World's Fair, and if the weather man favors the former German soldiers, success will be assured. The management of the German Village has offered to waive its customary admission charge for all veterans that participate in the parade. This arrangement will undoubtedly attract a large attendance.</p>
   <p>Mr. B. A. von Manstein is the festival marshal and first speaker. Comrade Massow, of the German Veteran's Association of Chicago, will be marshal of the First Division, and Adjutant Marsch, of the South Chicago Veteran's Club, will be his assistant.</p>
   <p>Comrade Reichert and Adjutant J. Valentin, of the Town of Lake Veteran's Club and the Waffengenossenverbein (Arms Fraternity), will be in charge of the Second Division. The Ordre De Bataille is subject to correction, as <pb facs="5418474_7_1601.jpg" n="2"/>out of town applications are still arriving. In regard to the latter, reports have been received from: Landwehrverein, of Cincinnati [Land Defence Club, in reality a definite classification specifying a certain age limit; men not older than thirty-nine years. This ruling in effect from 1859 to the World War. Other standards prevailed in Germany during the Napoleonic era. Transl.], Military Club of Elgin, Veterans Clubs of Elmhurst, Joliet, Davenport, Dubuque, Allegheny City and Kriegerkameradschatt (Warriors Comradery) Kenosha.</p>
   <p>The village will be brilliantly decorated. Dr. Richter, German Commissioner and member of the Government Board, and his staff have been invited.</p>
   <p>In spite of all the preparations the veteran's festival entailed, the management of the German Village has not forgotten Chicago Day, to be held Monday, Oct. 9, when the village will again be colorfully adorned....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
