<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-19">Sep. 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of the Schiller Theater.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0808</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <!--                    
                        <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.2"/>
    -->
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0808.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-09-19">Sep. 19, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF THE SCHILLER THEATER.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Without song and fanfare the building of the German Schiller Theater continued uninterruptedly. The founding festivities, incidental to the laying of the cornerstone were dispensed with by the directorate and for a good reason - they wished to assure themselves of its realization before indulging in the customary celebrations. The main problem of their goal will soon be past history, since the Schiller Theater will stand completed within the next 10 days. Thursday evening, Sep. 29, will be the first celebration of the founders and promoters who have given Chicago this imposing monument of German energy and German enterprise. True friends of Germanism and German art will rejoice in this accomplishment, even if they are notable to attend in person.</p>
   <p>The completion of this theater opens new channels for us and relieves us of difficulties we endured heretofore. Even until last spring, the German Theater management had to beg the English theaters to condescend and to grant to them, so that German performances could be given on Sundays and ... they paid high rentals for the privilege. Performances which required special scenery could not be given, since such equipment was not available and to transport it from the Milwaukee stage was also impossible, because of the time element, only a half day being available. And many German plays could not be produced, because <pb facs="5418474_7_0809.jpg" n="2"/>no theater was available.</p>
   <p>After Oct. 1st we will have a permanent remedy. German art will then have a stage of its own where it may flower to perfection. Not only will German art flourish but its enthusiastic friends .... will be able to exclaim: "This house is also a home, built for you, that you may be comfortable therein. No speculative mania but German enterprise prompted this work and gave it a solid financial foundation, healthy and secure, which precludes any apprehensions.... Here you may satisfy your longing for German art, for edigication or education, after the day's arduous labors permit a resting period.</p>
   <p>It is destined to be a family theater in the true sense of the word.</p>
   <p>On Thursday evening the stockholders will have the first opportunity to enjoy the successful work .... on Saturday will be the public opening.... The directorate regrets that it cannot extend an invitation to all its German friends... and supporters to the dedication.... The theater holds only 1,300 persons...</p>
   <p>The program at the dedication ceremony lists the following selections and <pb facs="5418474_7_0810.jpg" n="3"/>speeches:</p>
   <table>
    <row>
     <cell>1.) Jubilee Overture by</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Carl Maria Von Weber.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>John Hand's Orchestra.</cell>
     <cell/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>2.) Prolog</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>E. F. L. Gaus.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>3.) Benediction by</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Herman Mohr</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Orpheus Male Chorus.</cell>
     <cell/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>4.) Address by the President..</cell>
     <cell>Mr. A. C. Hesing.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>5.) Festival Overture</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Lentner</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>John Hand's Orchestra.</cell>
     <cell/>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>6.) Speech by Hempstead</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Washburne, Mayor of Chicago.</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell>7.) "Song-poem to the artists".</cell>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Lyric by F. Schiller,</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Composed by Mendelsohn Bartholdy</cell>
    </row>
    <row>
     <cell/>
     <cell>Orpheus Male Chorus.</cell>
    </row>
   </table>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0811.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>8.) Speech by Emil Hirsch.</p>
   <p>9.) Pantomine, the work of F. Welb, Theater Manager.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
