<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1880-11-12">Nov. 12, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">The Saengerfest</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0931</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0931.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1880-11-12">Nov. 12, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">THE SAENGERFEST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>About one hundred representative German residents of Chicago met last evening at Uhlich's Hall in response to a call to consider the preliminaries of the great National Saengerfest, which meets in this city next June. The Germans are deeply interested in the success of this grand musical feast, and propose thus early to provide means to entertain their brethren from abroad.</p>
   <p>Mr. William Floto was elected chairman and in taking the chair, made a few remarks upon the necessity of prompt and efficient action on the part of the musical fraternity of Chicago, looking to a successful reunion. He advised a spirit of liberality in all their arrangements, to the end that the Saengerfest of 1881 might be a grand success.</p>
   <p>Mr. Alfred Bucher was called on, and stated that it had already been ascertained that St. Louis, Cincinnati, Cleveland and other cities would send delegations of singers; and that although nothing like the necessary amount of money had geen raised to properly carry out the elaborate program which would be arranged, yet there was a fund of $900 on hand to commence with. He advised the appointment of a committee of forty-five to solicit contributions, and also several <pb facs="5418474_7_0932.jpg" n="2"/>smaller committees on transportation, entertainment, etc. Mr. Bucher also moved the appointment of a committee on permanent organization.</p>
   <p>Mr. Rubens thought the time had not arrived for such organization. He, therefore, moved that the question of permanent organization be deferred until a meeting could be held at which the various elements could be united, whose cooperation was necessary to insure success; and without whose cooperation, in his opinion, success could not be attained.</p>
   <p>The matter was discussed at some length, and it was finally determined to postpone action until a later day.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
