<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-11-11">Nov. 11, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Schwaben-Verein Honors the Memory of Friedrich Von Schiller</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1095</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1095.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-11-11">Nov. 11, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SCHWABEN-VEREIN HONORS THE MEMORY OF FRIEDRICH VON SCHILLER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Following an old tradition, the Schwaben-Verein (Suabian Society) of Chicago paid homage to their great countryman, Friedrich von Schiller, by celebrating the one-hundred-and-seventy-fifth anniversary of his birth.</p>
   <p>On Friday evening, at Lincoln Turner Hall, 1005 Diversey Parkway, an impressive memorial celebration took place which brought together the members of the Society and their wives to honor Schiller's memory. There was also a public ceremony yesterday afternoon at the Schiller monument in Lincoln Park. The high point of this ceremony was the laying of a wreath on the monument.</p>
   <p>On this occasion Mr. Curt Benisch recited one of the most beautiful of Schiller's poems, "Die Teilung Der Welt". [Editor's note: The correct title of this poem is "Die Teilung Der Erde" (The Sharing of the Earth).]</p>
   <p>During the main ceremony the president of the Society, Mr. Julius Klein, gave a short speech in which he pointed out, with a pride that was quite justified, that the Schwaben-Verein of Chicago had never, in the whole course of its existence, <pb facs="5418474_7_1096.jpg" n="2"/>failed to commemorate Schiller's birth with a suitable ceremony. He assured his listeners that this statement would hold true for the future also, as long as Chicago possessed a Schwaben-Verein.</p>
   <p>The festival in the Lincoln Turner Hall was opened by Bernie Hartwig's orchestra, which played the overture to "Wilhelm Tell". This was followed by President Klein's address of welcome. Curt Benisch then delivered a thoughtful prologue, which he himself and another member of the Society, Julius Schmidt, had composed. This was rewarded with well-deserved applause from the audience, which filled the hall to capacity. The well-known Chicago singer, Lucie Westen, followed with the singing of three of Schiller's lyrics, "Des Maedcnens Klage" (The Maiden's Lament), "An Die Freude" (To Joy), and "Der Fiscnerknabe" (The Fisher Boy) which brought her new laurels and, at the same time, showed the virtuosity of Director Otto Vandsburger, who accompanied her on the piano.</p>
   <p>The Senefelder Liederkranz, led by its experienced director, Karl Reckzen, sang the two songs for male choruses, "Wie Die Wilde Ros' In Wald" (Like the Wild Rose in the Wood), by F. R. Mair, and "Mein Ist Die Welt" (The World is Mine), by Curti. The first part of the program was concluded with a few more numbers <pb facs="5418474_7_1097.jpg" n="3"/>by the orchestra.</p>
   <p>In the second half of the program "Wallensteins Lager" (Wallenstein's Camp) was performed. Like the earlier performance this year at the Cannstatter Volksfest (Popular Festival) of the Schwaben-Verein, this was under the capable direction of Curt Benisch. The Schwaebische Saenger-Bund (Suabian Singing Society) co-operated in making the performance an outstanding success..... [Translator's note: At the end of the article there is a list of these who took part in the play. It is also states that Mr. M. Girten, the Austrian Consul General, was guest of honor.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
