<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-12-16">Dec. 16, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">The Benefit Performance for the German Dispensary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0341</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0341.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 3</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1875-12-16">Dec. 16, 1875</date>.
<title level="a">THE BENEFIT PERFORMANCE FOR THE GERMAN DISPENSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The highly publicized performance of Wilbrandt's comedy, "Die Maler" (The Painters) was given yesterday at the North Side Turnhalle.</p>
   <p>Although [Alexander] Wurster's theatrical company may have done its share in attracting the Chicago public, one must, nevertheless, attribute the financial success to the directorate of the dispensary, since these gentlemen showed great readiness to make sacrifices, and were patient and untiring in their devotion to the cause, doing everything within their power to sell tickets in order to increase receipts. The total income of the performance was somewhere between a thousand and eleven hundred dollars; the net proceeds will be about half this amount.</p>
   <p>Last night's very select audience followed the performance with rapt attention.</p>
   <p>"Die Maler," like most of the newer plays, is not entirely devoid of improbabilities and occasional instances of superficial treatment, but nevertheless it won <pb facs="5418474_7_0342.jpg" n="2"/>public approbation.</p>
   <p>Miss Marie Wolff was very impressive and delightful As "Leonore von Seefeld". She played her difficult and thankless part to great advantage, being successful even in trifling details. At the end of the second act she was presented with a lovely bouquet and an expensive diamond ring, the gift of several patrons of art who wished to show Miss Wolff by their act that her efforts in behalf of the German stage in Chicago are appreciated.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Claussen was excellent as "Else". Her sincerity and understanding of the part were rewarded with repeated applause, and she was given many bouquets of flowers.</p>
   <p>Among the gentlemen were some who had not memorized their lines very well, but, all in all, this did no noticeable harm. Messrs. Donald Hoch, Meyer, Louschner, and Wolkestein were very good.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0343.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>If one considers the small dimensions of the Turnhalle stage and the limitation to free movement that this entails--its interference with proper grouping--then it would be impossible to overpraise yesterday's performance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
