<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-04-18">April 18, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The German Theatre.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0233</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0233.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-04-18">April 18, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN THEATRE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last evening offered a variety of excellent entertainment, and the attendance to"Fereol", presented by the Collmer-Isenstein Theatre Company, was very good indeed. The guest artist demonstrated that it is not so all-important to interpret the principal role in order to find appreciation for his or her art. The audience exhibited an intense interest throughout the performance, an indication that the Germans of Chicago like and appreciate a good drama.</p>
   <p>"Fereol"is a highly effective drama; it may be said one of the best that Sardou wrote. The subject of this highly interesting play is typically French,"Gilberte", the principal female character, although of secondary importance, was impersonated by Miss Ida von Trautmann.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0234.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We cannot quite comprehend why the management did not select a more prominent character impersonation for this genial artist's first guest performance.</p>
   <p>Nevertheless, there was ample opportunity afforded Miss Trautmann to prove herself an artist of high caliber. Excellent was her portrayal of intense fear at the discovery of her past, climaxing in the still greater agony, the eventful separation from her daughter. She gave a noble tinge to that lovable character in the confession of her guilt. She was great and convincing.</p>
   <p>The management deserves praise for the very good performance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
