<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-03-21">Mar. 21, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[A Concert]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0973</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0973.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-03-21">Mar. 21, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[A CONCERT]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Yesterday the dedication of the new hall of the Orpheus took place in presence of a select audience. An orchestra consisting of the best artists of Chicago gave a brilliant rendition of Beethoven's "Prometheus"...and then Louis Meyer, president of the Orpheus, introduced the speaker of the evening, A. C. Hesing, (Mr. Hesing who, being known to you all most advantageously, needs no further recommendation from me.)</p>
   <p>Mr. Hesing said, "Though art is not my field, I yet gladly follow the invitation of the Orpheus, because it is a noble German cause that shall be served. And a newcomer in German-American singing circles I am not! Thirty-one years ago, in Cincinnati, the city I then called home, I helped to found the first German singing society, the Cincinnati Liederkranz, which at the same time was the first German social society in Cincinnati. <pb facs="5418474_7_0974.jpg" n="2"/>Splendidly, since then, with the power of American Germandom there has developed German organized singing.</p>
   <p>As you know I have thrown the gauntlet to the Temperance movement, with the same utter disregard with which I have opposed the question of the fire limits the nativistic money bags - and that in the American camp itself. In order to gain this new aim, however, all Germans in Chicago must collaborate like one. Shame on every German, who tries to disturb this unity.</p>
   <p>We are called to ennoble, through our German attributes in a social as well as in a political respect, the whole life and being of our new fatherland.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0975.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>By defending our good right we at the same time render a great service to this country and its future.......The name Orpheus comes from the Greek singer whose voice tamed even the wildest beasts. Our Orpheus shall contribute through its work to the taming of two beasts whom we are challenging with firm resolution, namely, the beast, Knownothingism, and the beast, Temperance! The speaker frequently was interrupted by plaudits and closed amidst a storm of approbation.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
