<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-11-12">Nov. 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">Goethe Men's Chorus Celebrates its Silver Jubilee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0606</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0606.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1928-11-12">Nov. 12, 1928</date>.
<title level="a">GOETHE MEN'S CHORUS CELEBRATES ITS SILVER JUBILEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A cheerful crowd of 70c persons assembled to celebrate the 25th anniversary of the Goethe Men's Chorus.</p>
   <p>Wicker Park Hall, was festively decorated with flags and palms and about the stage a big lyre with a 25 in silver figures was displayed.</p>
   <p>The Festival concert began with the Tannhauser march, which was immediatley followed by a welcome song of the Goethe Men's Chorus. Miss Ella Reid, soprano soloist, then sang two songs, for which she was much applauded.</p>
   <p>President Heidemann presented her with a beautiful bouquet of Chrysanthemums. After a few songs and an orchestral number by Kaler Bela, Fritz Nitschke sang a Bass solo from the "Troubadour."</p>
   <p>President John G. Heidemann gave the festival speech, thanking the many guests for their appearance and expressing the hope, that the society will be able to celebrate its Golden Jubilee in another 25 years. Adolf Gill, then spoke in <pb facs="5418474_7_0607.jpg" n="2"/>the name of the United Men's Choruses of Chicago and presented a framed letter of congratulations to the society.</p>
   <p>A special honor availed Mr. Heidemann; he received from his society as a token of gratitude for his 15 years presidency a gold lyre ornamented with diamonds, which he pinned proudly on his chest.</p>
   <p>After the conclusion of the concert, dancing took place. All those present agreed that the festival was a great success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
