<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-03">Dec. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Harlem Men's Chorus in Forty-Fourth Anniversary Concert</title><title level="a" type="sub">Program under Direction of Reinhold Walter</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0400</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0400.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a </item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-03">Dec. 3, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">HARLEM MEN'S CHORUS IN FORTY-FOURTH ANNIVERSARY CONCERT</title><title level="a" type="sub">Program under Direction of Reinhold Walter</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Harlem Men's Chorus last night celebrated its forty-fourth anniversary with a musical program at the West Park Masonic Temple. The program was notable for its brevity, and for the prompt execution of the numbers. It bore eloquent witness to the striving of the men and women singers who are devoted to the German Song. The concert was held under the sponsorship of the Almira Ladies' chorus, and under the sole direction of Conductor Reinhold Walter. Both organizations have, in Herr Walter, a director of serious ambitions who is able to produce choral performances quite above the common level. Yesterday's concert gave proof that success may be had whenever a chorus puts itself completely under the spell of its leader.</p>
   <p>Beschmitt's song, "Ossian," with orchestral prelude, was sung a cappella by the Harlem Men's Chorus in an appealing manner, and brought forth hearty <pb facs="5418474_7_0401.jpg" n="2"/>applause. The solo part was in the capable hands of Adolf Schnaeble. Then followed the Almira Ladies' Chorus with Wengert's "Sonntagsfeier" and Waldmeister's "Senners Abendstaendchan," which latter was given with piano accompaniment. The latter song pleased the public because of its charm, and had to be repeated in part. A trumpet solo by the orchestra conductor, William Hebs, likewise called forth much stormy applause that the soloist had to consent to a few encores.</p>
   <p>Max Seitz, the gifted tenor, sang "Auf Fluegeln des Gesanges" and "Dear old pal of mine". After him came the Harlem Men's Chorus again, this time with the English song "The Old Spinning Wheel," by Hill, and "Zieh mit," by Angerer. The contrast between the two songs was so strong that it could scarcely escape any of the audience how inferior the average English song is, compared to the German, with respect to beauty of sound and musical effort. The climax of the concert came with the singing of the "Muelhe in Schwarzwald," by Eilerberg. It was sung by a mixed chorus, with orchestral accompaniment; the audience was highly elated, and was glad to have a partial repetition.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0402.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The president, Carl Brunns, welcomed the guests of the fest, and presented a scroll of honor to the singer, Engelbert Zentmer, for his twenty-five-year membership in the club. The president of the Almira Ladies' Chorus, Frau Amalie Ohlman, was presented with a bouquet by the vice-president, Frau Schultz. Herr A. C. Welrwein, president of the Northwest Saengerbund, expressed joy over the success of the fest, and urged the audience to participate in the Saar demonstration next Saturday. The beautiful fest came to an close with a gay dance.</p>
   <p>Chief credit for the success of the fest belongs to the fest president, Wilhelm Ranks, and the members of the committee: Wilhelm Meier, Karl Meyer, Adam Zeitz, and Ernst Marnudir.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
