<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-09-08">September 8th, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The German Theatre.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0279</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0279.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-09-08">September 8th, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">The German Theatre.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Before a large audience, which gathered at the Mc Vicker's Theatre to witness the first performance of the season, Mr. Emil Hochster, according to tradition, addressed the audience with a prologue in verse and promised to offer the best in art and artists. But, if the last night's performance should be an example of the new product of German art, then we beg the director to resort to plays which are not so modern.</p>
   <p>The "Men of Today", a comedy by Julius Rosen, revealed very little of his genius, which is so prominent in some of his other works.</p>
   <p>Therefore, it would be somewhat unjust to submit the artists to criticism. Of the new members of the company, who participated at last night's performance, we wish to mention Miss Reinhard and Mrs. Scholz-Rademacher, who, in our opinion, <pb facs="5418474_7_0280.jpg" n="2"/>will soon become the favorites of the audiences.</p>
   <p>Mr. Luhr, the new lover, has not been very impressive; he seemed awkward, his voice affected. Miss Heim and Miss Bayer, two beginners, have yet to learn much before they realize that they have missed their vocation. We dare say, that Mrs. Rolff may prove to be a capable member. Praise goes to Mr. Heinemann, who is well known to us, as a character impersonator, who changed expertly from the comic into the pathetic. Worthy mention goes also to Mr. Meier. Miss Wassmann was lovely to look at, and Messrs. Ravene and Rodenberg are old favorites. Mr. Klotz, a new artist, is very promising. The stage management was excellent. It would be well for the management, to take interest in the ladies costumes for modern conversation-plays require more preciseness in that respect, than what the German stage managers are accustomed to, to make a well rounded performance.</p>
   <p>Next Sunday"Sodom and Gomorrha" a moral sketch by Schonthal, will be given.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
