<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-05-02">May 2, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Singers Union to Arrange Jubilee.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0628</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0628.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III F</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-05-02">May 2, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">SINGERS UNION TO ARRANGE JUBILEE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nobody knows any more, where any when the German choral first sounded in America, but it is well known, that it belongs to the precious treasures, which were brought by the German immigrants, to their newly adopted Fatherland.</p>
   <p>For many decades, the German songs, in this country blossomed, if at all, only in the dark. It was not until 1835 that the first singing society, the "Men's Chorus of Philadelphia, was founded. But soon, the German singers of America were to get big support. The political refugees of 1830 and 1848 came, and brought a treasure of old and new melodies, along. Everywhere, societies were founded for the cultivation of German song, and in 1849 in Cincinnati, the first singing festival as held.</p>
   <p>The impression this festival made upon the Americans, was a divided one. Some could not find enough praise, while the others, especially the Puritans, condemned the festival, particularly since it had been held on a Sunday. Yes, a newspaper had the audacity to blame the singers for the appearance of the cholera in Cincinnati. It wrote: "These Dutch singers with their <pb facs="5418474_7_0629.jpg" n="2"/>intemperate jubilee, drinking sour wine, have brought the cholera upon us."</p>
   <p>In the course of this festival, the "German Choral Union of North America" was founded. But in other parts of the country there was also activity, and in recognition of the impossibility of holding a great mutual festival, attended by all choral societies, on account of the great distances in America, the "North-East Choral Union," the "pacific Singing Society", and the "North Pacific Choral Society," were founded.</p>
   <p>In the course of time, new societies, and new names were added. In 1866, in La Crosse, Wis., the "Union of Singers of the Northwest" was founded by seven societies, which will celebrate its 60th anniversary this summer in Peoria. These societies will do their utmost to celebrate the anniversary in a most festive manner. The festival administration of Peoria is fully confident of its success, because every single society is taking the greatest pains to contribute to a large success of the festival. With special pleasure the festival administration received the news, that the singing brothers of the "North-American Union of Singers", will participate at the festival. Their attendance will prove their not having forgotten the attendance of the North-West Union of Singers at the last singing festival of the North American Union of Singers in Chicago.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0630.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The following societies of Chicago and surroundings belong to the North American Union of Singers: Arion of the South Side, Baker's Singing Society, Burgenland Men's Chorus, Chicago Glee Club, Chicago Men's Chorus, Concordia Glee Club, Constantin Singing Society, German Military Singing Society, Excelsior Men's Chorus, Singing Club Fidelia, Singing Section of the War Veterans Societies of Town Lake, Singing Section of the German Charitable Union, Harugari Singing Club, Herder Choral Union, Glee Club Einigkeit, Richard Wagner Choral Society, Transylvanian-Saxonia Men's Chorus, SouthSide Choral Union, South-Hungarian Choral Society, Forward-Schiller, Waldeck Glee Club, West-side Choral Union, (all of Chicago, Illinois) and the Harmony and Harlem Men's Choruses, Forest Park, Illinois.</p>
   <p>The present union officials are: A. C. Wehrwein, president, Chicago, Ill; Albert Ross, vice-president, Forest Park, Ill.; Charles Sass, treasurer, Dubuque, Ia.; Otto Albrecht, Librarian, Davenport, Ia.; George H. J. Kieck, secretary, Milwaukee, Wis.; and F. A. Rehberg, conductor, Chicago, Ill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
