<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-05">Nov. 5, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Successful Song Recital of the Rheinische Gesangverein</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0440</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0440.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-05">Nov. 5, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SUCCESSFUL SONG RECITAL OF THE RHEINISCHE GESANGVEREIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We have become used, especially in the last two or three years, to expecting something special from the Rheinische Gesangverein (Rhenish Singing Society). It is well known that the chorus, consisting of about eighty active members, makes a serious effort to cultivate German song, and for this reason it is with great expectation that people go to the concerts which the Society gives from time to time. And yesterday's concert, held in the great hall of the Germania Clubhouse, which was filled to capacity, came up to expectations. The well-balanced program was carried out in a way which was a credit to the director, Jean Brodesser, as well as to the chorus. The two opening choruses, "Mein Rheinland" (My Rhineland), by Hansen, and "Untreue" (Unfaithfulness), by Gluck, gave evidence of the careful rehearsing the chorus had done during the six months that had passed since the spring concert. This first impression was strengthened when the chorus--it was necessary to change the order of the program--sang "Schwarzbraun Hanna" (Dark Brown Hanna), by M. Mueller, and "Die Goetterreiche" <pb facs="5418474_7_0441.jpg" n="2"/>(The Kingdoms of the Gods), by Bruckner. Both songs are new here, and were sung with expression and the correct shading. The same can be said of another composition, which has not been heard here very often, "Die Beiden Saerge" (The Two Coffins), by Hegar; and of the two final choruses, "Auf Dein Wohl, Du Rheinische Maid" (To Your Health, Rhenish Maiden), by Kahl, and "Waldeinsamkeit" (Forest Solitude), by Sendel. The applause was so great that the singers had to give an encore. For this they selected, "Innsbruck, Ich Muss Dich Lassen" (Innsbruck, I must leave thee), by Juengst. This was the conclusion of a concert which will long remain in the memory of its listeners.</p>
   <p>Three soloists shared in the success of yesterday's concert. Special mention should be made of the well-known German tenor, Frederick K. Mueller, who displayed great artistry in singing "Walters Preislied," from "Die Meistersinger"; as well as "Dein Ist Mein Ganzes Herz," by Lehar, and "Sangeslust." The singing of the last song, whose composer is none other than Director Brodesser, gave the guests the welcome opportunity to applaud both the singer and Mr. Brodesser.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0442.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Another soloist was the pianist, Arthur Lang, of whom the Society may well be proud, because the artist gave a perfect rendition of three difficult compositions, Chopin's "G Minor," Schumann's "Arabesque," and Liszt's "Liebestraveme." He, also, had to give an encore.</p>
   <p>The two artists, together with a member of the chorus, Mr. Walter Stern, also gave excellent renditions of the solos in the "Goetterreiche".....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
