<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-08-16">August 16, 1898</date><title level="a">The Germans of Chicago Honor Bismarck</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1555</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1555.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-08-16">August 16, 1898</date><title level="a">The Germans of Chicago Honor Bismarck</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A great solemnity prevailed last night at the Auditorium which was filled to its utmost capacity. Shortly after eight o'clock P: M rang out from the powerful organ in sonorous tones the Passacaglia in C Minor by Bach. The great organist, Professor W. Middelschulte played with full vigor and skill, obviously realizing the importance of the occasion. The organist also played the funeral march by Chopin.</p>
   <p>As soon as the last tunes of this touching composition faded away, the Chairman of the Committee, W. Vocke, held the opening speech:</p>
   <p>"The news of the death of Prince Bismarck has deeply touched the hearts of all Germans. Germany recognizes him as one of the greatest statesmen of all times. Through his efforts the Germans were united and reached a position of power and dignity among other nations..... This day is dedicated to the memory of the unforgetable and the greatest of all Germans of this century. Prince Bismarck.</p>
   <p>Following the speech of the chairman, Mr. Grosser gave a prologue, which he <pb facs="5418474_7_1556.jpg" n="2"/>had composed.</p>
   <p>Mr. H. Balatka, the director of the musical part of the celebration, had in his orchestra sixty of the best musicians of Chicago. The rendering of that marvelous musical composition, Beethoven's Funeral March, had a powerful effect. After this excellent performance the men's choir arose, consisting of nearly 400 singers, and being accompanied by the organ, sang the well-known "Prayer Before the Battle" by Moehring. This song made such a powerful impression upon the audience that a thundering applause broke loose. Due to the solemnity of the occasion, demonstrations of such nature were not indulged in at the beginning, but the masses became so enthused that one more song was rendered, namely, "The Watch on the Rhine".</p>
   <p>The chairman now proceeded to introduce the speaker of the evening, Professor Camillo von Klenze, of the Chicago University, a Swiss by birth:</p>
   <p>"A few days ago we received the sad news that Bismarck was dead. All of Germany was deeply moved and everywhere, where German hearts beat, the sad news made a deep impression. Even people of other nations felt the shock <pb facs="5418474_7_1557.jpg" n="3"/>Everyone realized that one of the most powerful minds of all times had passed away; one of those geniuses who accomplish in a few years what whole generations have tried to do in vain. He was one of those, who are loved and hated without limit; who, often misunderstood by friend and foe alike, have to travel their path in solitude, but whose glorious achievements make overpowering impression, similar to great natural phenomena.......Now the people stand at the bier of this greatest German of our time. The quarrel of the parties has ceased and a certain solemnity prevails. All his contemporaries stand as one man, looking into the face of that lofty Titan, representing for all the personification of German energy, German ability, and German loyalty. He has departed but he is not dead. Rendering his services to his time, he will live through all ages.</p>
   <p>Following the German speech, C. Samson rendered "Cantate" by Mozart, accompanied by the orchestra. Then the English speaker of the occasion, Mr. L. Mills, was introduced and he said among other things:</p>
   <p>"The home of a great man is not restricted to his native country or the place <pb facs="5418474_7_1558.jpg" n="4"/>he achieves his great deeds, but it extends over the whole world. The outstanding and uplifting accomplishments of his mind are a blessing for all nations. Outside his native country, the undying Bismarck had nowhere so many sincere admirers as among the people of the United States. We readily recognize him as the genius, who reconstructed and united a great nation.</p>
   <p>"The human race has produced only a few of those men, who, by the force of their genius and by their marvelous deeds, have united people of like interests and lifted them to the lofty heights of their historical traditions....</p>
   <p>"Abraham Lincoln was a true American but the influence of his character and his greatness made him the ideal of all nations in the hearts of the world. Mankind pays their heroes the highest tribute by claiming them as their very own.</p>
   <p>"In the spirit of this truth America now offers - their sympathies to the German people. We grieve with them because of their great loss, the loss of the most outstanding German of the century, who, in his personality, represented the highest characteristics of his people, and united the German tribes to one <pb facs="5418474_7_1559.jpg" n="5"/>nation. Being the most unique and constructive statesman of his time, if not of all times the patriotic hero and idol of his people, born to be a leader and to achieve, whose memory is the inheritance of all - this man of men - Bismarck.....</p>
   <p>"O Germany, you have lost your most gbrious son! In your great grief accept a wreath from the throbbing heart of this great republic to put it on his grave.</p>
   <p>"Powerful Bismarck, builder of an empire, you have achieved peace for your people and fame for your nation. and through the magnificence of your mind you have inflamed to greater enthusiasm the whole human race! Millions admire you with dignified solemnity! Coming generations will honor the memory of your marvelous achievements! "</p>
   <p>A most appropriate close to this unique festival furnished the orchestra by playing "Egmonts - Overture" by Beethoven. In the name of the large assembly a cablegram was sent to Bismarck's oldest son, expressing their sympathies.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
