<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-04-07">Apr. 7, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">German Theater</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0287</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0287.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-04-07">Apr. 7, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN THEATER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Der Letzte Brief" (The Last Letter) is a pleasant and amusing comedy, which at times takes on the aspect of a farce, due to the lively sequences in several scenes. We cannot imagine a better presentation than the one given yesterday at Hooley's Theater.</p>
   <p>The participants almost without exception, were admirably well chosen for the various roles, and the cast reflected the excellence of the training received from their director, as well as their own zeal in studying and rehearsing the play; all of these characteristics are essentials without which this presentation would never have been successful.</p>
   <p>"Der Letzte Brief" was produced by the Wurster Company less than a year ago and the plot need therefore not be given in detail. The action in relatively brief, being restricted to a limited amount of dialogue and number of scenes, and, as a result, it is fascinating. The language is fluent and appealing, <pb facs="5418474_7_0288.jpg" n="2"/>as may be expected of Heinrich Laube.....Miss Kuhn, as Susanne, pleased us immensely; she has never been better. Her characterization was highly skillful....her diction and deportment indicated the woman of the world, as well as an amiable character.</p>
   <p>Mr. Ravene was a brilliant foil for Miss Kuhn. His portrayal showed rare ability, which only a thorough mastery and complete understanding of the part would make possible. It was no easy task to commit to memory the heavy role assigned to him. The remainder of the cast also deserve congratulations.....</p>
   <p>It was an excellent performance, smooth in every respect, and the hearty laughter it evoked from the audience, combined with the public acclaim, are proof that the large crowd enjoyed itself thoroughly. Miss Kuhn and Mr. Ravene, aside from the author, were accorded the lion's share of the applause, and justifiably so.</p>
   <p>Future announcements:....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0289.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Concordia Theater</p>
   <p>"Die Nachtfalter von Chicago" (The Night Owls Of Chicago), written by the genial [Chicago] author and successful manager, Paul Loebel, was presented yesterday. To speak of the merit of the play would be somewhat unfair, when one considers the admirable performance; the author himself does not deny his comic vein as revealed in the role of Greynemeyer. Mr. and Mrs. Tietz sang beautifully. Miss Jantzen, as John, was charming, skillfully depicting the various moods [required by her part]. Mrs. Meyer, as Tine, Greynemeyer's wife, showed a true understanding of her role. The other members did their best in their unimportant parts.</p>
   <p>The theater was well filled, the title of the play undoubtedly doing its share to attract the people who expected a number of allusions to local matters, and the audience was not disappointed in its expectations.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0290.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Wahl's comedy, "Man Soll den Teufel Nicht an die Wand Malen" (One Should Not Paint the Devil on the Wall), Goerlitz's farce, "Eine Vollkommene Frau" (A Perfect Wife), and the short operetta "Aus Liebe Zur Kunst" (For The Love Of Art) were given at the Vorwaerts Turnhalle (Forward Gymnasium) yesterday. A fairly large crowd attended. Miss Nelson received enthusiastic applause for her singing during the intermissions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
