<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-09-10">Sept. 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Postlude to the Folksfest of the Schwaben Verein</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1132</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1132.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-09-10">Sept. 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">POSTLUDE TO THE FOLKSFEST OF THE SCHWABEN VEREIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>True to its custom of many years standing, the Schwaben Verein of Chicago organized a postlude to its recent Cannstatt Folksfest, so as to snow gratitude to the members of the committee who, by their co-operation or other work, contributed to the success of the fest. Such repetition of the rest was the more justified this year, as the recent Schwaben picnic again resulted in a considerable net profit, which, as is known, was given over to charitable purposes.</p>
   <p>The celebration took place on Saturday evening in the basement hall of the North Side Turnhalle, 820 North Clark Street, and was, as may be well imagined, a most pleasant affair. President Julius Klein opened the program with a brier address on the success of this year's Cannstatt Folksfest, and expressed the most sincere thanks of the organization to all who so willingly gave their services. He then invited the guests, among whom the fair sex was so well represented this year, to partake of a little supper (which tasted especially good because it was prepared by Swabian women) and to do justice to the invigorating drinks, furnished to bring forth pleasant reminiscences of the days of August 19 and 20 in Riverview Park. That this invitation was accepted <pb facs="5418474_7_1133.jpg" n="2"/>in the approved manner of the Swabians "fearless and faithful" was shown by the measly few trays which remained untouched, and which consisted largely of empty dishes and bottles.</p>
   <p>The management of the club, under the able leadership of its president, Julius Klein, Secretary Geo. Iberle, and the other officials, provided an elaborate program of entertainment, presenting first two songs by Inez Westen --"Trinklied" from the operetta "Die Kensche Susanna," followed by "Das braume Maidelein," by Leo Ascher. They were received with hearty applause, thanks to their excellent rendition.</p>
   <p>Next followed the "Buerzshaft," by Schiller, arranged in shadow pictures by Curt Benisch, and presented by Otto Haske, L. G. Scheib, Emil Baun, Anton Iberle, and Franzi Scheib; this number provoked unbounded mirth. As an encore, and as a special reminiscence of the Schwaben picnic, a newly composed "Schnitzelbank" was sung, under the direction of Curt Benisch, in which the entire festive audience participated.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1134.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Swabian Saengerbund, under the leadership of Kerr H. A. Rehberg, offered a number of songs, among them "Waldmorge", "Elslein von Caub," "Dorfreigen," "Ruedesheimer Wein," and "Am Rhein". These songs added to the enjoyment of the evening and brought well-earned applause.</p>
   <p>During the intermission, President Klein gave Honorary President William Janss special thanks, in the name of the club,for his services to the last Schwaben picnic. Mr. Janss responded with a short talk. The next speaker was Vice-President Wilhelm Reichert who, in a quite skillfully constructed poem, let the Cannstatt Folksfest "pass in review" again; then came a few remarks from the vice-president of the Swabian Saengerbund, Josef Beron, who pleaded for a large attendance at the German Day celebration next Sunday in the West Side Stadium.</p>
   <p>The rest of the evening was given over to gay dancing, for which Hartwig's orchestra (having previously supplied the supper music) played old and new melodies, until at last the lateness of the hour brought an end to the pleasant evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
