<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-30">Aug. 30, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">About the Swabian Festival</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Vox Populi)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1744</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1744.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-30">Aug. 30, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">ABOUT THE SWABIAN FESTIVAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Vox Populi)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the Editor of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung:</p>
   <p>In today's edition of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung appeared an article which gives the wrong impression of our association. To guard our reputation we consider it necessary to give a more detailed explanation to you and to the readers of the Illinois Staats-Zeitung. Indeed, we are fully aware of the sorrow affecting the entire nation, and we have the greatest sympathy for the misfortune which has befallen our leader. [President Garfield was near the brink of death at the time.]</p>
   <p>It certainly proves that we have great respect for him when one considers that the society voted 98 to 2 not to give any festival throughout the year if Garfield should die, and that we are willing to defray our organization's expenses out of our own pockets, approximately eighteen hundred dollars.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1745.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Furthermore, we should like to ask whether we aroused more disapproval than those other clubs which have held parades in the last eight weeks at a time when the President was as near death as he is now. It should also not be forgotten that the Schwabenverein was not prompted by greed when it held its festival, although your article led people to believe that profit was the motive for arranging the parade. We do not wish to be put in the same class with certain other associations. All our income, whether derived of monthly dues or realized as the surplus receipts of festival occasions, is used for charitable purposes.</p>
   <p>And if our American fellow citizens have taken offense, then we should like to mention the band wagons which were in evidence at all hours last week, advertising baseball clubs and so forth.</p>
   <p>With regard to the rabble which frequented the festival grounds and which, supposedly, was no recommendation for our activities, we were not so much to blame for it as the police, who were present in sufficient numbers. Instead of doing <pb facs="5418474_7_1746.jpg" n="3"/>their duty by expelling the undesirable element, the minions of the law insulted respectable guests and zealously watched Rinderer's lunch counters.</p>
   <p>That the Germans did not object to the affair was shown by the fact that most of our better citizens came to the festival. We therefore feel especially gratified. It may not be generally known that Mr. Assmus, the genial author of the Skizzebuechele, was also among those present.</p>
   <p>Respectfully,</p>
   <p>Joseph Schlenker,</p>
   <p>2230 Wentworth Avenue.</p>
   <p>Editor's reply: We are fully convinced that the majority of the Germans share our opinion and in no way feel elated about the Schwabenverein's parade of last Sunday, although it will generally be conceded that the society was in a predicament, since the committee in charge relied upon the parade to help advertise <pb facs="5418474_7_1747.jpg" n="4"/>the festival, and many members had made extensive preparations for the event and were anxious to display their splendid costumes while riding proudly, though not necessarily gracefully, on horseback. But this did not change the situation; a picturesque parade last Sunday was bound to invite criticism. The President's condition had never appeared so serious as it did last week. Chicago actually was in mourning, and the reports of last Sunday morning, though better than expected, were hardly sufficiently optimistic to warrant the sudden exhibition of a festival spirit or the organization of a picnic, and activities of that kind were bound to be regarded as showing lack of proper feeling. Other clubs which and had arranged Sunday parades were undoubtedly frowned upon, and the omission of such activities could only have benefited the Germans as far as the English-speaking contingent was concerned; but the parades of these other clubs did not follow immediately upon a day when our national leader hovered between life and death, whereas the Schwabenverein did hold its festivities at such a time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
