<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-09-10">Sept. 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Splendid Picnic of the Vereinigte Maennerchoere</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0495</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0495.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-09-10">Sept. 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SPLENDID PICNIC OF THE VEREINIGTE MAENNERCHOERE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Favored by the most wonderful late Summer weather, the Vereinigte Maennerchoere of Chicago yesterday had their picnic within that portion of the forest preserve which is on Dempster Road and Ferris Avenue. It constituted an excellent close to the Summer season.</p>
   <p>The members of the affiliated song organizations came in large numbers with their wives and children to spend a few hours outdoors in the midst of gay singers..... A wide variety of entertainment had been arranged for young and old; in the afternoon, a dance orchestra was featured. That a picnic of Maennerchoere could not be without German songs goes without saying. Soon gay songs could be heard coming from the various organizations, and the Vereinigte Maennerchoere, directed by H. A. Rehberg, often joined together to delight the picnic guests with a few songs. In short, the picnic was <pb facs="5418474_7_0496.jpg" n="2"/>exceedingly entertaining, with everyone feeling at home. The Vereinigte Maennerchoere may look back upon a splendid success and, being thus refreshed, may start the Winter season, which has much more work in store for them.</p>
   <p>Credit for the success of the entertainment belongs--aside from the beautiful weather, which was preceded by cloudy and cool days, and which for that reason was found the more pleasant--largely to the active arrangements committee which, before and during the picnic, did everything to provide the guests with a delightful day.</p>
   <p>In addition to Joe Keller, the president of the Vereinigte Maennerchoere, the committee consisted of the following: John Heidemann, chairman; Carl W. Berman, secretary; Carl Rathje, Hermann Schneidewind, Joseph Gies, E. M. Guntermann, Robert Boysen, Wilhelm Thuering, Wilhelm Stahl, Reinhold Seifert, Theodor Schenk, Rudolph Faller, Henry Heep, and Gustav Steinweg.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
