<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-10-28">Oct. 28, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Wiener-Waeldler Singers Celebrate Fifth Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0459</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0459.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-10-28">Oct. 28, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">WIENER-WAELDLER SINGERS CELEBRATE FIFTH ANNIVERSARY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As the only German Singing organization in the southern part of the city, the Wiener-Waeldler Singing Club cordially invites all friends and countrymen to its anniversary festival which takes place today in the Liberty Hall, 817 East 92nd Street.</p>
   <p>Conscious of having always done their duty as German singers, the members of the organization giving the festival indulge in the justified hope of being able to welcome a full house on this day. This the more so because all preparations for a varied and interesting program have been made.</p>
   <p>The concert is under the direction of the well-known conductor, Helmuth Steinmetz. In a humorous scene, "Ein Liebesabenteuer in der Sennheutte" <pb facs="5418474_7_0460.jpg" n="2"/>(a love affair in a cowherd's cottage), Miss Grethe Taborsky appears as a pretty dairy maid, Michael Geiger as the man from Berlin who knows his onions, and Mrs. Erna Loose as his jealous spouse. Even elsewhere, humor asserts itself in abundance. Of course,the best of care has been taken to give the guests good treatment.</p>
   <p>Special notice is given that the doors of the hall will be opened at 3 P.M. and that the program starts at 4 P.M. sharp. Admission fee at the ticket office is fifty cents, but presale tickets may be obtained at thirty-five cents at the Buerger Feuchtinger Hall, 5159 S. Ashland Avenue, at the South Side Ballroom, 302 West 47th Street, at Mr. Kolaritsch's, 4430 Wentworth Avenue, and from all members of the organization.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
