<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-08-01">Aug. 1, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Members of the Song Festival Committee Celebrate Closing Hours</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1418</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1418.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-08-01">Aug. 1, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">MEMBERS OF THE SONG FESTIVAL COMMITTEE CELEBRATE CLOSING HOURS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The final figures of the festival of the North American Singers Alliance held at the Coliseum here on June 11 - 14, are now available. The result was so epochal, that the members of the Festival committee decided to celebrate the event at a small social gathering. After all, it represents two years of diligent labors.</p>
   <p>The festivities were held at the Lincoln Turnhalle, and proceeded splendidly. Mr. Theodore Pilgram, who was so active in behalf of the great affair, was entrusted with the preparations for yesterday's meeting. At about eight P.M. members of old standing appeared with their companions. The hall was beautifully decorated with flowers..... A small orchestra played during the joyous repast. Ernst Kruetgen, the festival president, and his wife, were given the seat of honor. He nominated the first vice-president, George Landau as toast master, who performed his task with dignity. Several songs and solo numbers .... were given; among them the old, proved melody "Harmony Makes <pb facs="5418474_7_1419.jpg" n="2"/>us Strong."</p>
   <p>The Financial Success</p>
   <p>..... Treasurer Charles P. Kenning's report was jubilantly received. He showed a surplus of $12,456.91, an accomplishment which is probably unequalled in the history of German song festivals....</p>
   <p>Total income, including guarantee funds, sale of tickets, etc., $84,459.40.</p>
   <p>[A detailed expense account appears in the original. Translator]</p>
   <p>Cash sale of tickets: $14,549.</p>
   <p>Honorary tickets were sold for $47,098.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
