<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-30">July 30, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Summerfest of Hungarians a Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1170</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1170.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-07-30">July 30, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SUMMERFEST OF HUNGARIANS A SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Beneath the shade trees of Harm's Park, and favored by ideal weather, the Hungarian Nationals' Sick Aid Society of Chicago celebrated its annual summerfest. The organization's administration, in co-operation with representatives of various other groups, made the festival a success. The numerous visitors had a pleasant day and will, undoubtedly, remember it for a long time.</p>
   <p>Many families arrived around noon to eat, in the open, the food they had brought with them, or to recreate themselves in the dining room or in the veranda with the delicate viands prepared in the kitchen by the ladies of the organization. The bar had good wine and whisky on tap and those who wanted to refresh themselves on good ice cream or soft drinks were given a chance to do so.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1171.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the dance hall, music was furnished in the afternoon and evening. Quite a pleasure was it to sit in the Hungarian Csarda (pronounced tshardah-road-side ian), where genuine Hungarian Gipsy music could be enjoyed together with one's drinks. Other popular entertainments, varied in manner, were provided. Toward evening the singing section of the "Hungarians" entertained with songs.</p>
   <p>As is the custom among the Hungarians, youth was given the chief consideration yesterday. Following a procession through the park, preceded by the officers of the organization and by the band, every child received a nice present. Prior to this, President John Hess made special mention to the effect that the future of the organization lies with the youth. He said that when introducing the guests of honor by the president, and after he extended a hearty welcome to all the guests present.</p>
   <p>Following is a list of these who received distinctions: Joe Haschek, one of the founders and first grand president of the Hungarian Matienals' Sick Aid <pb facs="5418474_7_1172.jpg" n="3"/>Society; Martin Marshall, another founder and present president of Section One; Ludwig Gebert, secretary of the United German-Austro-fungarian Organizations (Mr. Mess is likewise the president of this organization); Mick Wagner, president of the Austrian Aid Society "Stock in Eisen"; "Papa" Anton Schoenherr, whom the president designated as the father of the "Hungarians"; Frau Aleanor Rovill, president of Branch Number two of the German-Hungarian Ladies' Society; the new director of the singing section of the "Hungarians"; Ottomar Gerasch; Mr. Gabriel Jung, and Mr. Carl Becker.</p>
   <p>The committee which in so exemplary fashion prepared and managed yesterday's entire arrangements was composed of the following members:</p>
   <p>John Mess, fest president; John Lauer, fest secretary; P. J. Pill, fest treasurer; J. Rinillong, J. Erich Lorn, J. Mathes, <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. Spranoff H. Mayer, A. Mildkatsch, M. Frauenhoffer, F. Kastimer, A. Schirmang, S. Weissmann, F. Pieschke, A. Schmalbach, J. Gebhardt, J. Andree, M. lansinger, J. Ortmann, <pb facs="5418474_7_1173.jpg" n="4"/>A. Berger, F. Schultz, N. Sieburg, A. Pahorny, F. Zorbo, F. Ellmer, J. Guldner, G. Hollstern, J. Schirmang, A. Hoffmann, P. Mondik, P. Kahles, M. Marschall. Frau Mayer, Frau Kupper, Frau Jung, Joe Schamber, J. Cuenther, N. Zimmerman, and A. Wagner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
