<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-12-29">Dec. 29, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A German Ladies and Children's Chorus Is to Be Organized for the World's Fair.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0842</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0842.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1890-12-29">Dec. 29, 1890</date>.
<title level="a">A GERMAN LADIES AND CHILDREN'S CHORUS IS TO BE ORGANIZED FOR THE WORLD'S FAIR.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last weeks Mr. Gabriel Katzenberger whose musical leadership and ability have been often proclaimed in our columns, is, diligently at work organizing a large children's chorus of 1,200 voices, likewise a ladies chorus of similar magnitude, which will be recruited from German clubs. It is intended to glorify the German Day during the World Exposition and to further the interests of the German song. Since a word, when sung makes an uneradicable impression upon a child's mind, it is obvious, that the German language finds considerable support when we sing German songs and for this reason alone, Mr. Katzenberger's plan deserves considerate attention and loyal support.</p>
   <p>At the last session of the great North American Singers Alliance in New Orleans, it has been proclaimed as a sacred duty, that all German clubs should promote German Singing instruction amongst the youth, and that more emphasis should be given this subject than heretofore. Mr. Katzenberger is convinced about the importance and necessity of this subject and so he has taken steps to organize this great juvenile <pb facs="5418474_7_0843.jpg" n="2"/>chorus. He intends to give instruction and rehearsals in the various Turnhalls of the city and promises to teach choral singing from the very elementary beginning to its highest branches. Thereby a rare opportunity will be given to all the students, to develop their musical sense of hearing, thought, and the sentiment for art, whilst those who later intend to be affiliated with a church choir or song club, will now have a chance to do the necessary advance work in Treffen (identification of tones by hearing, without seeing the note in print, transl.) and artistic choral singing.</p>
   <p>The plan of instruction provides for the following classes: The Elementary Class Musical primary instruction, also the rudiments of accords and the tone identification rythmic examples of all varieties and reading with pronunciation free from any dialect.</p>
   <p>The middle class: A brief recapitulation of the primary grade teaching plan. Continuation of accord knowledge, with the addition of the first principles of harmony; Ton-identification and accord exercises where greater difficulties are involved. Normal and complicated intervals in all keys in all keys, reversals of tone intervals, reading from the black board, requiring correct naming of the <pb facs="5418474_7_0844.jpg" n="3"/>accords as well as sound identification; copying of all exercises. Two and three voiced choral solfeggios in the restricted and free style with consideration of proper artistic shading (piano, de- and crescendo forte, fermato; sometimes tempo rubato is included in this category, tranel.) studies including duets and trios with text, with especial attention to a proper pronunciation and correct emphasis, (phrasing.)</p>
   <p>Upper class: Choral solfeggios in quartet form or arrangement, with and without accompaniment, (obligato) with proper regard for a preconceived recitation and expression of sentiment. ("The musical terms" dolce, con energia, con amore, scherzando, etc. are generally considered under this caption, Trans.)</p>
   <p>The conditions will be such, that even the poorest German child may participate. It is to be expected, that especially the German Lodges and Twin Clubs will be there, to support the venture and send the youngsters of seven to fourteen years to the classes.</p>
   <p>At the same time, Mr. Katzenberger is diligently at work, to start a large ladies chorus which will have its weekly rehearsals at some centrally located hall.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0845.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Every year a great concert is to be given at the auditorium and during the German days of the World's Fair the beautiful works by Reinecke, Abt, Freschhammer, Hummel, etc. will be produced. Also this effort would be a desirable achievement in the realm of song for the furtherance of Germanism in our city and it will be of great value for the future of German Choral singing in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
