<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-09-23">Sep. 23, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">61St Anniversary of the Senefelder Singing Society.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0598</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0598.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-09-23">Sep. 23, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">61ST ANNIVERSARY OF THE SENEFELDER SINGING SOCIETY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Senefelder Singing Society celebrated its 61st anniversary last Saturday in the Lincoln Turner Hall, under the leadership of the chairman of its amusement committee, Paul Bernan. A program of entertainment was followed by dancing. The stage was decorated with palms and flags of the society; the tables were adorned with fresh roses. Frey's orchestra supplied the concert and dance music. The chorus of 100 singers, under the leadership of the society's conductor, Karl Reckzeh, offered several songs, which were greatly applauded. Several humoristic dialogues were recited by Otto Reutert, which also were very much applauded.</p>
   <p>However, the principal number of the evening was the address of the president of the society, Hans Hamacher, who after welcoming the guests heartily, referred shortly to the history and present condition of the society, and also of the coming 25th anniversary celebration of Mr. Reckzeh, as conductor of the "Senefelder Singing Circle". He then spoke of the young generation of singers, and praised them as splendid people, who, he hoped, will help to celebrate the society's 100th anniversary, because, he said, <pb facs="5418474_7_0599.jpg" n="2"/>members of many years' standing of the Senefelder Circle, some of whom, in spite of their 50 years of membership, still participate every Friday night at the rehe rsals, are no rarity.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hamacher devoted a short time to the remembrance of the deceased co-founder of the society, Heinrich August Plautz; he then referred to the great number of the old, faithful, approved "song-brothers", who were able to be present and to take part in the 61st foundation festival. He mentioned, among others, "our old and faithful Jacob Becker, who a year after the foundation of the society, in 1869, joined the singers and who is now 89 years old today."</p>
   <p>Other old members of the society cited were: Carl Tadleben, a member for 54 years; Fred Schollenberger, 49 years; Hugo Bark, 47; Rudolf Fulda, 35; Peter Berns, 33; Ernst Pyritz, 32; Herman Wunderlich, 30; Christ Wassermann, 30; Fred Hess and Charles Rink, 29; and Henry Brandon, a member for 28 years. Twenty one have been members more than 20 years. Altogether there are at present 140 active members, and 140 passive members.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0600.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Mr. Hamacher then referred to the two gentlemen, William Reimer and Christ Prummenbaum, who will celebrate their silver jubilee as members of the society this year. A hearty applause rewarded the president for his splendid talk.</p>
   <p>The singers' eyes were shining, as afterwards conductor Reckzeh gathered them around him for the next song. They were proud and happy to be members of this outstanding singing society, which has existed for so many years: and all those who were present hoped, that it would continue for many more years.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
