<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-09-27">September 27th, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Deutsches Theater</title><title level="a" type="sub">(The German Theatre).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0255</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0255.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-09-27">September 27th, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Deutsches Theater</title><title level="a" type="sub">(The German Theatre).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The members of the Collmer Isenstein Theatre Company convinced us last night again, that every one is a real artist of the dramatic profession. The production was "Die Frau ohne Geist" ( The Narrow Minded Woman) a comedy in 4 acts by Hugo Burger. This work is very light,and only such artists as the ones, who participated at last night's performance, saved it from a fiasco.</p>
   <p>The narrow minded woman of the play, is really a lovable character that of a deeply loving and sentimental young woman. But the writer does not give enough of emphatic expression to such love, as to create a subject for a comedy; further more, it is quite a venture, to present to the audience, a young, beautiful, rich and educated girl, who for the love of her narrow-minded father, is determined to appear narrow-minded too.</p>
   <p>Miss Fiebach, who acted the principal character, that of Steffana, knows how to display poetic charm,such as the writer intended. She was rewarded, with <pb facs="5418474_7_0256.jpg" n="2"/>thunderous applause. Miss Trautmann's acting, as a member of high society was excellent. Miss Kaselowska as well as Mrs. Meyer have aided to the success of the evening. Mr. Richard in the part of Weiner showed again, that he is an actor of rare quality, as he is known already, to our audiences. Mr. Meyer's extra ordinary talent is not a new discovery. Messrs. Engel, Waldorf and Rodenberg helped to make the play a success.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
