<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1918-01-17">Jan. 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The German Song.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0746</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0746.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1918-01-17">Jan. 17, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN SONG.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With increased zeal the Chicago Singverein went to work to bring to the Chicago public concerts the very best, which could be produced from music consisting of the choral works of German composers. This is not only for the German-Americans of this city. In music lies a binding and conciliating power, therefore the Germans of Chicago consider it their profound duty to apply it. Music was one of their greatest talents, which they brought to America. Among all variations of music, the choral song was developed by the Germans to its highest standard. In the higher sense it is characteristically German. Not only because the German language is considered as fundamental, but because the German always expressed their feelings and sentiments in it. Upon German soil congregational church singing was originated. Student songs blossomed in the singing societies, with cultivated good fellowship. All these things, with their characteristics, were adopted into the life of other nationalities. In America they found full home rights, and cannot be separated, anymore, from national American life.</p>
   <p>Today we find all over America Glee Clubs, which are duplicates of German singing societies. At the last singers festival in Los Angeles, the pure English-American <pb facs="5418474_7_0747.jpg" n="2"/>singing societies were strongly applauded.</p>
   <p>In the hall of the University Club of Buffalo, several years ago, voices of the academic singers of Vienna and those of American universities were mixed, and they reveled in the cultivation of the chorals which united them, although they did not understand each others' language.</p>
   <p>The choral scoieties, which cultivate the choral songs, and which are Bead by an artistic society, like the Chicago Singverein, have endeavored to reach higher goals. They go further into the cultivation of German songs; they exercise this kind of music, which was neglected on account of chauvinistic reasons. This kind of animosity, in art, among nations should not occur, even during war. Nobody will be under suspicion of loving America less, by giving help to such artistic endeavors.</p>
   <p>Music will be the first intermediator through which peace and reconciliation among the war torn nations shall be accomplished.</p>
   <p>It is the incessant aim of the many singers of the Chicago Singverein, in spite of many objections, to prepare for this accomplishment.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0748.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In a short time all music loving elements of Chicago will be called together, for their next music festival, and, without doubt, nobody will stand aside unsympathetically, when they realize fully the reconciliatory power of melody. Then, the Chicago Singverein will have the glad conviction of having fulfilled its duty. The loss would be on the part of those who would show their unsympathetic attitude towards the cause that had as its aid to meet in a sphere, where hope was for all, for a much more beautiful and better future, in the development of the domestic harmony of America.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
