<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-07-24">July 24, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Festival of Germans from Baden.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1626</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1626.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-07-24">July 24, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">FESTIVAL OF GERMANS FROM BADEN.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After the convention of the Baden Central Association of North America and had ended its session, last Friday evening, the delegates from the 14 cities assembled once more for a glorious festival, which was given by the Baden Aid Society of Chicago in collaboration with the Baden Song Club.</p>
   <p>An extensive program was provided, commencing at 8. The goal was Oswald's Grove. The singers met at their club, 69 Larrabee Street, where the parade started with military precision, led by a marshal and adjutants, followed in order by a division of Hanau equestrians, a music corps, the United States and Baden flags displayed in an open cab, representatives of Baden in authentic costumes, riding in open coaches, out-of-town officials and delegates of the Baden Central Association, and other guests and club members in coaches...</p>
   <p>The parade of the Baden Aid Society started from the headquarters, 2701 Went-worth Avenue, at 11... Participation was good and the arrangements were a credit to the efforts of the committee.</p>
   <p>Upon arrival at the grove dinner was served, and at 3 o'clock the program commenced. The singers gave suitable selections, and Mr. C. Eichin made the <pb facs="5418474_7_1627.jpg" n="2"/>welcoming speech. This was followed by the theatrical play "Ritter Von Rodenstein" (Knight of Rodenstein).</p>
   <p>It was indeed a pleasure to behold these virile, tall figures in their native garb and listen to the sonorous voices which brought a gain the familiar folk songs of yore to our memory. "Das Lied Vom Rodenstein" was sung by the chorus, grouped on a small stage, the background showing the castle of Heidelberg. (Explanatory: The Rodenstein burg is a famous ruin near Reichelsheim, Germany.)</p>
   <p>The rest of the day was spent in dancing and genial conversation...</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
