<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-09-24">Sept. 24, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Celebration Following This Year's German Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1114</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1114.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-09-24">Sept. 24, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">CELEBRATION FOLLOWING THIS YEAR'S GERMAN DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday, after all participants in this year's German Day celebration were rested from the labors involved in its preparation, and when it was possible to draw some conclusions about the after-effects of this wonderful affair, the Ladies' Auxiliary for the German Day celebration gave a party in Lincoln Turner Hall, which it was hoped that all who had actively co-operated in the festival would attend. Although the attendance at the German Day celebration had not come up to expectations--considering the services of the Chairman, Mr. Gustav A. Brand, and of the officials and members of the committee, and their untiring efforts in the interest of Chicago's Germans--yet it was quite a satisfaction to Mr. Brand to hear many speakers acknowledge and praise the work that had been accomplished.</p>
   <p>The affair was opened by Mrs. Elizabeth Vautinek, second vice-president and president (sic) of the Ladies' Auxiliary for the German Day festival, who introduced the creator of this year's German Day festival. In his speech <pb facs="5418474_7_1115.jpg" n="2"/>Mr. Brand pointed out that this year's German Day celebration was a proof that determination and unity lead to success. He thanked all co-workers and the German people in general, for their active support. Other speakers were Fred Brumund, first vice-president of the German Day celebration; J. W. Kobalter, honorary president of the German Day Alliance....Mr. Brand responded briefly, and also thanked the German Press for their support.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
