<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-10-26">Oct. 26, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Golden Jubilee Concert of Vereinigte Maennerchoere</title><title level="a" type="sub">Distinguished Performances Celebrate Fifty Years of German Song</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0549</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0549.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-10-26">Oct. 26, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">GOLDEN JUBILEE CONCERT OF VEREINIGTE MAENNERCHOERE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Distinguished Performances Celebrate Fifty Years of German Song</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the most favorable conditions, the Jubilee Concert of the Vereinigte Maennerchoere (United Men's Choruses) was held yesterday evening at the Civic Opera House. The house was completely sold out; and long before the beginning of the concert there was a large crowd at the entrance of the Opera House.</p>
   <p>It was a bright, clear Sunday, a beautiful day, and the fine weather contributed to the festive mood. It was a pleasure to visit the singers backstage and to be infected with their joyous mood, to shake the hands of the festival committee members--offering a voiceless congratulation, for mere words were unnecessary.</p>
   <p>Gathered here were our true Germans, proudly displaying a gold leaf. Among <pb facs="5418474_7_0550.jpg" n="2"/>them, dressed in their Sunday clothes, were men of the laboring classes--they did not need formal attire. A tense silence prevailed in the auditorium--the audience expectantly awaited the lifting of the curtain. Suddenly, as the curtain rose, a shout of joy rose from the audience and Mr. [Karl] Reckzeh was greeted with loud applause. In his characteristic, informal manner he turned to the orchestra and gave the signal to begin. The audience immediately became silent and the orchestra began to play the Overture. It was not necessary to establish rapport; the singers were no strangers to the audience, they were members of the families of those who composed the audience, and who felt as one with the singers from the very start.</p>
   <p>Of course there were many among them who were not connected by family ties with the singers, but who came to celebrate, to enjoy German songs, and to honor the host of singers. The following well-known people were there: Mayor Cermak; Richard Barthold from St. Louis; Mr. and Mrs. Ernest Kruetgen; Consul General and Mrs. Berthold Singer; the Austrian Consul, General M. Girten; Mrs. Paul F. Mueller and daughter; Mr. and Mrs. Paul H. Mueller; Mr. and Mrs. Nick G. Mueller; Mr. and Mrs. A. C. E. Schmidt of the Hamburg- <pb facs="5418474_7_0551.jpg" n="3"/>American Line; Ludwig Plate of the North German Lloyd; Conductor H. A. Rehberg; Dr. I. Hollinger; I. Schlitte; M. Brisch; Mr. and Mrs. Leopold Saltiel; Mr. and Mrs. Schadler; and a number of others, some of whom sat in their own boxes, and others who sat with friends.</p>
   <p>At the conclusion of the fourth number, the president of the Vereinigte Maennerchoere, Joseph Keller, invited the president of the North American Saengerbund, Mr. O. Nuetzel from Louisville; and Messrs. I. Emme, A. Gill, C. F. Pegenan, and the festival president, Mr. Theo. Pilgram, to take places on the stage. Mr. Keller welcomed the audience in the name of the Vereinigte Maennerchoere and thanked them for the large attendance with which the Germans of the city had honored the singers, and which expressed the German people's appreciation of the efforts of the Chorus to perpetuate German songs. He then presented Mr. Nuetzel, the president of the North American Saengerbund, who welcomed his "dear brothers and friends of German songs" with the words, "Where men sing, you may settle in peace, because bad men do not sing".</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0552.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Unity and harmony are our aim," Mr. Nuetzel continued, "As evidence of harmony, I am presenting to the Vereinigte Maennerchoere, on this fiftieth anniversary, my heartiest best wishes as the president of the North American Saengerbund, and I hope that the Vereinigte Maennerchoere remain in existence for a long time, to grow, blossom, and prosper. The North American Saengerbund is proud of the Vereinigte Maennerchoere of Chicago."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
