<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-08">Oct. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Ladies' Choir Lyra Celebrates Thirtieth Anniversary</title><title level="a" type="sub">Choir as Well as Director H. A. Rehberg Could Celebrate this Day as Double Anniversary</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0487</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0487.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-08">Oct. 8, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">LADIES' CHOIR LYRA CELEBRATES THIRTIETH ANNIVERSARY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Choir as Well as Director H. A. Rehberg Could Celebrate this Day as Double Anniversary</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the occasion of the 30th anniversary of its existence, the Ladies' Choir Lyra sent out invitations to a concert and fest ball at the Social Turnhalle. The invitation was gladly accepted by friendly organizations and by the public in general, so that a sizable audience was present.</p>
   <p>The Ladies' Choir Lyra did everything in its power to promote the success of the fest in a worthy manner. The stage was impressively decorated with a basket of flowers, from which a lyre with the number 30 in silver emerged. On each side there were two more baskets containing red roses. As symbolized by the flowers, a special occasion was solemnized: the special joy over the accomplished work could be seen in the eyes of the members of the choir. After the festive strains of the overture to "Orpheus in der Unterwelt" were played by Bernie Hartwig's orchestra, the stately group of singers from the Ladies' Choir Lyra gathered on the stage to consecrate the day in song. From the succeeding songs, <pb facs="5418474_7_0488.jpg" n="2"/>it became clear that the organization is particularly effective in its singing when it stays in the realm of light music. Conducted by H. A. Rehberg the songs were perfect in word and sound. Hearty and sustained applause rewarded choir and director for their presentations.</p>
   <p>Later in the program, the president of the United Singers of Chicago and of the Singers' Bund of the Northwest, A. C. Wehrwein, had occasion to congratulate the choir on its thirtieth anniversary in the name of the Bund. Director H. A. Rehberg, who at the same time looked back over an active life of thirty years with the organization, was presented to the public by the president, Frau Mathilde Hager. In recognition of their laborious toil in the preparation of the fest, both the choir president and the past president, Frau Wilhelmina Schwarz, received bouquets.</p>
   <p>To a not inconsiderable degree responsible for the success of the event were the two daughters of the director, Irma and Esther Rehberg, who sang a number <pb facs="5418474_7_0489.jpg" n="3"/>of duets which were rewarded by the public with a storm of applause. The two singers have, in their voices, beautiful technical material, which they know how to put into the service of expressive singing. They reaped great rewards of applause with the first two songs! "Liebestraum," by Liszt and "Als die alte Mutter" by Dvorak. Two wreaths of flowers were given them by the president to express the thanks of the organization.</p>
   <p>Three well-trained male choirs--the Harmonie singing club, under Director Rekzeh, the Arion male choir of the North Side, and the Erinnerung singing society--placed themselves at the service of the cause, and offered songs whose rendition was a success technically, musically and in expression. The program was brought to a close with selections by a mass choir composed members of the United Ladies' Choirs of Chicago, directed by H. A. Rehberg. They sang the two folk songs "Santa Lucia" and "Lorelei" effectively, and with rich nuances. Besides the guest organizations already mentioned, there were also present the Swabian-Badensian Ladies' Club, and the Swabian Singers'Club. A smart ball concluded the anniversary fest, which was successful in every way.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0490.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The officers of the organization, and especially the ladies of the arrangements committee, deserve full credit for the success of the event. The committee consisted of the president of the festival, Wilhelmina Schwarz; the treasurer, Marie Wirth; the secretary, Frieda Beck; and the ticket treasurer, Marie Bendeich. The decorations, made by Frau Hedy Theiss, were in excellent taste.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
