<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-15">Aug. 15, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">The Old Settlers' Picnic</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1750</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1750.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1881-08-15">Aug. 15, 1881</date>.
<title level="a">THE OLD SETTLERS' PICNIC</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago's festival will be held next week. It originated seven years ago. Unfortunately Ogden's Grove had to be used for the occasion, since Chicago has no suitable large place, regardless of the city's millionaires. The place is sorely neglected by the present lessee and is dirty. But the committee on arrangements appointed by the Chicago Turngemeinde [Gymnastic Association] will do all in its power to make it fairly presentable.</p>
   <p>What the Old Settlers' Festival means to our residents need hardly be mentioned, since it recalls the past to those who spent their childhood days here, reminds them of their efforts and privations in former years, and helps also to convey and idea of the rapid growth of the community to those people who know Chicago only as a large city. The festival arrangements are destined to interest young and old, and special emphasis is placed on the old settlers, whose courage and diligence are the basis of Chicago's present greatness.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1751.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Festival Program</p>
   <p>The committee on arrangements of the Chicago Turngemeinde will leave the North Side Turner Hall at 1 P.M. and go to Ogden's Grove. At the festival grounds every old settler, man or woman, will be asked to sign his or her name on the record and will receive a silk ribbon showing the year of arrival in Chicago. Emil Hoechster will recite a poem by Emil Dietzsch which was especially written for the festival.</p>
   <p>In commemoration of the day gold medals will be awarded to the following persons:</p>
   <p>1) The German mother who had the most sons in the Union Army;</p>
   <p>2) The brewer who has longest been active in the brewery business in Chicago;</p>
   <p>3) The German foreman of a Chicago factory who has held his job longest;</p>
   <p>4) The typesetter who has been longest employed (sickness excepted) in Chicago print shops;</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1752.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>5) The woman whose membership admission to a Chicago Turnverein [Gymnastic Club] bears the oldest date; and</p>
   <p>6) The German midwife who has practiced longest in Chicago.</p>
   <p>A vote is to be taken to decide which woman has done most for the Chicago Deutsche Gesellschaft. Voting will be by ballot, each ballot costing twenty-five cents, and the proceeds will of course go to the Deutsche Gesellschaft. The winner will receive a suitable emblem.</p>
   <p>Popular games, singing, music, and dancing will provide entertainment, and the committee has spared no effort to make the festival fully as attractive as those of former years. In the evening brilliant illumination will be provided, consisting of calcium light, Chinese lanterns, and Bengal fire. [Translator's note: A bright, steady, intense, bluish light, formerly used for stage illumination abroad].</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
