<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-12">Nov. 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">The German Village.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Where During the World's Fair German Activities Will Concentrate.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1677</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1677.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1892-11-12">Nov. 12, 1892</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN VILLAGE.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Where During The World's Fair German Activities Will Concentrate.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Only a few more months, then the Germans, who respect their mother country and remember it gladly, will have an opportunity to realize a very pleasant dream. They will be able to imagine that they walk upon German soil, that they tarry upon German ground. They will be able to make themselves believe they are walking through one of those villages, which enrich our mother country with the poetic and the romantic.</p>
   <p>They will be able to hear genuine German sounds and words, without a mixture of the so-called Pennsylvania Dutch. Music from German Military Bands, in brilliant uniforms, will fascinate them. They will enjoy German wine, beer, and favored meals, and converse with German visitors. To speak German freely and sing German songs will be their delight and privilege.</p>
   <p>Anglo-Americans will observe this spectacle, but they will not be able to enjoy that sweet pleasure the Germans are favored with, because the latter's heart strings are tied to their homeland. By observing the Germans in their <pb facs="5418474_7_1678.jpg" n="2"/>activities, the Anglo-Americans will learn to respect them because here prevails genuine, honest, warm-hearted friendship and geniality. Hypocrites, bigots, and sneaks are strangers here, therefore the Know-Nothing, who despises the Germans as foreigners, has no place here....</p>
   <p>Our dream is not an empty one, but will soon be fully realized. The buildings of the village at the Midway Plaisance make splendid progress under the supervision of Mr. Belschner of Frankfurt. The framework for the Westphalian House, and a part of the castle with the chapel have been turned over to the roofers and bricklayers. Next month the architect, Mr. Hoffacker, of Berlin will arrive in Chicago... After the Westphalian House is completed, the House of the Black Forest, and the House of the Bavarian Alps will be constructed.</p>
   <p>Very active of late is C. B. Schmidt, the business agent of the concern incorporated under Ethnographical Exhibits. The required capital for the execution of their plans has been furnished by the German Bank, and the German National Bank of Berlin by subscription. They also have organized the previously mentioned company.</p>
   <p>The directors of the World's Fair were liberal enough to concede 175,000 square feet of space at the Midway Plaisance and contracts were closed <pb facs="5418474_7_1679.jpg" n="3"/>immediately with the architect C. Hoffacker, and the firm of Ph. Holtzmann of Frankfurt.</p>
   <p>We do not exaggerate in making the assertion that the German Village at the Midway Plaisance will greatly excel all other attractions there. This exhibit is not an idle one, but offers a wealth of things which are instructive as well as entertaining. It will teach the Nativists that the Germans are not so bad as is generally supposed. It will be a living demonstration of the fact that German songs, German entertainments, and German joviality and geniality are valuable treasures of the German people, of which it need not be ashamed.</p>
   <p>Upon the Germans themselves this exhibit will make a profound impression, and will refresh their memory in many respects. It will also enliven and restore their national pride. The desire will be aroused in the heart of every German to be of one accord with all who speak the German language.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
