<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-12-02">Dec. 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Song Club</title><title level="a" type="sub">Receipts Given to Charity; Crowded House</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0586</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0586.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-12-02">Dec. 2, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO SONG CLUB</title><title level="a" type="sub">Receipts Given to Charity; Crowded House</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The participants in yesterday's concert by the Chicago Singing Society, given at the Great Northern Hotel, were rewarded with generous acclaim by a grateful public. After all, the program provided unusual selections.</p>
   <p>The chorus, directed by Hans Marlow, who arranged the program, maintained its customary excellence, obviously intent upon preserving the enviable reputation attained under Boeppler's leadership. Thus, the individual numbers were highly successful. The folklore songs and the Swabian dance melodies probably proved <pb facs="5418474_7_0587.jpg" n="2"/>most appealing.</p>
   <p>The fourth number was dedicated to the memory of Boeppler. It was no dirge, but rather a jubilant song proclaiming death to be transitory and the spirit to be eternal.</p>
   <p>It was regrettable that Marlow's request to abstain from applause because of the solemn character of the selection was disregarded.</p>
   <p>The most conspicuous feature was undoubtedly the appearance of the soloists, Princess Tsianina and Harry Gillman. It is difficult to analyse the art of Princess Tsianina. It evokes the impression as though one were suddenly confronted with another language, even though the form adhered to customary precedents. Her sonorous <pb facs="5418474_7_0588.jpg" n="3"/>voice, of mezzo-soprano caliber, showed ingratiating qualities, bespeaking splendid schooling. One perceived, at random intervals, almost metallic sounds, which divested themselves of the conventional, reverting to aboriginal expressionism. In her "Canoe Song" this "recrudescence" especially manifested itself. The singer's arms showed that rowing has not been an unaccustomed activity in the past. Her "Flight from Civilization" bordered on the supernatural.</p>
   <p>When she added Franz's "In the Fall" (in German), the Indian song "Her Blanket" (in English), and "Vativinio" (in Italian), she was given well-nigh unending applause, which even increased in measure when the remarkable artist, seated at the piano, sang and played "The Waters of Minnetonka" and "Pale Moon."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0589.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Harry K. Gillman, violinist, attained the same artistic perfection. The "Faust Phantasy," by Winiawski, was fabulous in technique and rendition. His technique, brilliant in itself, proved most impressive in his first encore, a violin duet played in double stops. In a generous mood, he finally added "Fiebig's Poem."</p>
   <p>The accompaniment in the non a capella selections of the chorus was played by Miss Marie Stange in full conformance with her customary masterly manner.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
