<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1866-06-13">June 13, 1866</date>.
<title level="a">The Theater</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Robert and Bertram"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0365</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0365.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1866-06-13">June 13, 1866</date>.
<title level="a">THE THEATER</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Robert and Bertram"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sunday's performance, as well as yesterday's, was a complete success, and proves that the local German public knows how to appreciate a really good play.</p>
   <p>The house was overcrowded on Sunday, and the attendance on Monday was also very gratifying to the actors. On both evenings, the audience was kept in continual laughter, and the constant applause was sufficient assurance to the players that their efforts were successful.</p>
   <p>We must admit that, as far as comedy is concerned, we have never seen anything better or more comical than "Robert and Bertram". The play fairly teems with "queer" situations and funny remarks, and we do not hesitate to recommend it to all hypochondriacs as a remedy.</p>
   <p>The scenery is very good, the stage arrangements, decorations, and costumes <pb facs="5418474_7_0366.jpg" n="2"/>are everything one could desire, and, as for the performance itself, we do not hesitate to rate it as the best that we have seen in this country. The entire cast deserves unrestricted praise.</p>
   <p>The two "jolly vagabonds," Mr. Ahlfeldt and Mr. Pelost, are truly unsurpassable, and their natural wit kept the audience laughing continually. Mrs. Pelost played the part of Mrs. Ippelmeier, and Mrs. Yelguth enacted the role of Isidora Ippelmeier. Both actresses are to be commended for their marvelous performance. The Veilguth brothers also played their parts well and added no little to the success of the play. Mrs. Obernsdoerfer was truly charming in the role of Roessel. All in all, we must say that the Pelost Company is a well-trained group. There are no unnecessary interruptions in the performance, all the members have memorized their lines well, and everything is done smoothly.</p>
   <p>After such success, we do not have the least doubt that this comedy will draw a full house during the entire week, and we advise every lover of the theater, <pb facs="5418474_7_0367.jpg" n="3"/>and every one who wishes to spend a pleasant evening. To attend one of the performances at the German House during the current week.</p>
   <p>"Robert and Bertram" will be played every night this week, beginning at 8 P. M. Tickets are seventy-five cents for box seats and fifty cents for seats in the pit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
