<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-09-04">September 4th, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">The Goethe Festival. a Grand Mass Demonstration of Germanism.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1545</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1545.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1899-09-04">September 4th, 1899</date>.
<title level="a">THE GOETHE FESTIVAL. A GRAND MASS DEMONSTRATION OF GERMANISM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the Sunnyside Park a demonstration took place last night of Chicago's German-Americans, which was in every respect laudable and extraordinary. Over 15,000 German-Americans assembled to take part in the Goethe festival in commemoration of his birthday 150 years ago. The coordinated efforts of these great masses made a marvelous impression. Hardly anywhere else in the world, during these Goethe festivals have greater efforts been made by admirers of this prince of German poets and true mastery of living, than here at the shores of Lake Michigan. Indeed, this outstanding event of yesterday can be added to the landmarks of the German elements in the city's population.</p>
   <p>The Sunnyside Park was most fittingly decorated. A large platform was erected for the choirs and at both sides of it waved the flags of the different legations, <pb facs="5418474_7_1546.jpg" n="2"/>including the French, and of all the many German Clubs and Societies. Sayings and sentences of wisdom out of Goethe's work were attached to the trees in the park.</p>
   <p>At 3 O'clock P.M. the festival started officially. The orchestra rendered Beethoven's Egmont-Overture. Judge T. Brentano was then introduced as the first speaker and President of this festival event.</p>
   <p>"An American assembly never honored the memory of a more worthy and greater man. It is true that Americans celebrate the memory of their own heroes and great States men appropriately and enthusiastically, but at this occasion the Americans, as it were, step out of their boundaries, not to honor one of their great ones, but to offer tribute to a universal genius. Not only did he achieve political freedom for his nation, but he also created and promoted for all mankind the higher intellectual and moral freedom. This is the reason why this gigantic assembly, <pb facs="5418474_7_1547.jpg" n="3"/>consisting not only of German-Americans, but of Americans, is of such profound importance.</p>
   <p>"About a year age the German-Americans in Chicago commemorated the death of that titanic, iron statesman, Bismarck. His superhuman greatness achieved a united fatherland for the Germans, worthy of the high intellectual and moral rank, which they attained... But we can not imagine a German nation, accomplishing through their efforts such astounding progress, without such a poet and prophet with divine powers as Goethe, under whose influence it matured to its gigantic and glorious mission. We can not think of a such spiritual giants as Bismarck without the spiritual seed scattered by Goethe.</p>
   <p>"To pay the highest tribute of admiration and veneration to one of the greatest sons of Germany, if not the greatest, to J. W. von Goethe, are we gathered here. Goethe's own greatness, what he did in the and still is doing for his people and his importance and influence in the whole world other eminent and able speakers will proclaim; but I desire to remind you of the especially high significance Goethe has for our country, America.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1548.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"Political and moral liberty, which we enjoy, and of which we boast, is nothing else but self-control of the individual. It was Goethe who said of men in general: 'They all want to be masters, and none is master of himself.' Self-control, self-rule it is, what our people and government want to teach to the world.</p>
   <p>"Is it not self-control which increases and accentuates the dignity and value of personality? Is not through self-mastery that the true equality of men is obtained? Here we find the basic fundamentals of our constitution. Since Goethe stood upon this ground, on which we also stand, he can become, if rightly understood, our teacher in the contruction of our temple of liberty, beginning with the education of our youth, and continuing until the sovereignty of the individual citizen is complete. But in spite of the loftiness of his ideas and principles, Goethe was immensely practical and in this his mind is closely related to the minds of the American people and thereby becomes our high ideal. Everywhere he praises the deed, glorifies effort and diligence and the striving for practical aims, <pb facs="5418474_7_1549.jpg" n="5"/>without ever losing sight of the transcendental ideals. There is nothing hazy or indefinite about him; he is not "busy doing nothing," like most people, according his own words.</p>
   <p>"Because the real, practical life of all individuals constitutes the whole, thus operating together and for each other, we recognize in Goethe and in his writtings the complete realization of the American principle, 'one for all, and all for one.'</p>
   <p>"If we, as American citizens, and particularly as naturalized citizens, follow these few basic teachings of our own political doctrines and aims, them Goethe indeed has been a blessing to us.</p>
   <p>"Goethe is being considered more and more as the embodiment of the highest intellectual and moral ideals of the German nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1550.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>"Whatever may be slumbering in the bosom of future ages we do not know, but this present generation is not aware of a more complete and glorious realization of the highest idealism, than we find in Goethe, the prince of the poets. Who else in this wide world could more fittingly apply to himself the words of Faust:</p>
   <p>'Countless ages can not erase</p>
   <p>Traces of my terrestrail days.'"</p>
   <p>The official speeches were given by Mr. Max Eberhardt in German, and Congressman, Mr. H. S. Bontell in English.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
