<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-13">Aug. 13, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Cannstadter Festival.</title><title level="a" type="sub">German-American Historical Play Featured.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1618</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1618.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-13">Aug. 13, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE CANNSTADTER FESTIVAL.</title><title level="a" type="sub">German-American Historical Play Featured.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Swabians will give their 16th annual folk festival at Ogden's Grove today and next week, on Sunday the 20th, and on Monday, the 21st. The festivities this year will be held in honor of the World's Fair and its visitors... The main feature of the program will be an historical performance, the product of the genial Louis Kindt who functions in the dual role of author and director.</p>
   <p>The cast includes more than one hundred men and women. The play in four acts depicts the experiences and struggles of the early Swabians who settled on American soil. The main characters, Conrad Weiser, and his son-in-law, Muehlenberger, are genuine historical figures.</p>
   <p>Their names go back to the time when our adopted Fatherland was still a British Colonial possession. The first scene shows the arrival of the Swabians and of the Pfaelzer under the leadership of the senior Weiser, a native of Wuerttemberg. The environment is the Schohane Valley in New York state.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1619.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>They were employed by the English Government. The English governor of New York, Mr. Hunter, let them suffer from hunger and privations so they decided to settle in the Schohane Valley and eke out an independent existence among the Indians. The latter were exceptionally friendly.</p>
   <p>The second act shows the fight with the sheriff from Albany and a detachment of soldiers. The governor had maliciously deeded the land to a Dutch corporation, after the Germans succeeded in converting the wilderness into farms. Now they were to be evicted from their homes by means of military force.</p>
   <p>Mr. Weiser, the elder, even went to London to obtain justice for the German settlement, but the corporation won and the Germans, deprived of their possessions,sought a new home in the land of liberty, Pennsylvania, where the great Quaker, William Penn, had created a haven of refuge for all the oppressed.</p>
   <p>The third scene shows the exodus, and the fourth portrays the first festival in the thriving village, Wommelsdorf, which was founded by Weiser and his followers. Weiser's son was only a child when he came to America with his <pb facs="5418474_7_1620.jpg" n="3"/>father and while living among the Indians he learned their language thoroughly.</p>
   <p>He became famous in the political life of the Colonies, - New York, Pennsylvania, Maryland, Virginia, and particularly as mediator between the territories and the various Indian tribes. This then constitutes the historical backbone of the play and it provides a most timely addition to the Columbian festivities of the World's Fair.</p>
   <p>But the Swabians also will provide other entertainments. There will be acrobatics, concerts, a race, and marionette theater. Of special interest to those who appreciate choice vintages is the announcement that Neckar wine has been imported for this occasion - six barrels from the Stuttgart imperial cellars.</p>
   <p>There are also five barrels of Elfingen Riesling of 1886 vintage, and one barrel of red Mundelsheimer, anno 1889. These wines enjoy high repute in Swabia.... Let's go to the festival for a few hours of clean fun.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
