<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1918-10-13">Oct. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Proves its Patrictism</title><title level="a" type="sub">Liberty Loan Parade an Impressive Demonstration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1446</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1446.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1918-10-13">Oct. 13, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO PROVES ITS PATRICTISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">Liberty Loan Parade an Impressive Demonstration</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a colorful throng, made up of thirty-seven nationalities, Americans of German stock were also represented, though not quite to the extent that the promoters had hoped and expected. But if the German-speaking section of the parade was not outstanding in numbers, nor displayed as much pomp and glitter as did other sections, it must be said, on the other hand, that in its plain and quiet dignity it was a true reflection of German character, which dislikes noisy demonstrations to prove its merit. The contributions this section made, in the course of the parade, were to call to mind events and facts closely connected with the history of the new homeland, and glorious pages in the book which records the honors of German-America. Each selection symbolized an important period of American history and was prepared with German thoroughness and good taste. The result was a beautiful display from an artistic point of view. Foliage and color schemes gave a harmonizing and pleasing effect.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1447.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The noble and militant German-American patriot and clergyman, Peter Muehlenberg, pastor of Germantown, came to life again in the first tableau. He was pictured standing in his black, gold-lined pulpit before his enthusiastic congregation, on the memorable occasion when he delivered a fiery sermon favoring participation in the War of Independence of 1776. After the speech he throws off his black preacher's gown and with the words: "There is a time to pray and there is a time to fight!" stands before his audience in the uniform of an American colonel. This float was decorated with the American colors and also carried a silk flag showing the thirteen stars of the first states in the Union. Mr. Fritz Harder made an ideal Muehlenberg with his tall figure and expressive face. His congregation, men and women of Germantown, were a picturesque sight in their colonial costumes.</p>
   <p>"For Union--Against Slavery" was the motto of the second float, with a group taken from the time of 1861 when German-Americans responded in great numbers to the call of Abraham Lincoln, and joined the colors to fight for <pb facs="5418474_7_1448.jpg" n="3"/>the abolition of slavery and the preservation of the Union. Framed by oak leaves, the American colors, and the old black, red, and gold of German independence, were Father Abraham himself, Carl Schurz, and [General Franz] Sigel, surrounded by young turners, volunteers, women, girls, and freed negro slaves. The Stars and Stripes as well as the venerable and bullet-torn old flag of the Twenty-Fourth Illinois Volunteer Regiment, which is kept by the Chicago Turngemeinde were flying from this float. Lincoln was portrayed by Mr. Emil Heinrich, Schurz by Mr. Fred Roepenack, and Sigel by Mr. Arthur Clausen.</p>
   <p>These two displays were followed by a third tableau, called "1918-Answering the Call," in which Mrs. Floyd Garvick represented Minerva, to whom an old man handed all sorts of treasures from a chest, while War-Savings Stamps and Liberty Bonds were being bought eagerly and young citizens of German stock were joining the colors. This float was decorated with the national colors and with goldenrod. The three floats were arranged and prepared by <pb facs="5418474_7_1449.jpg" n="4"/>Dr. Walter J. Briggs, Wilhelm Ries, and Henry Schrott.</p>
   <p>Ahead of the German section marched the drum, fife, and bugle corps of the Social Turnverein, carrying the American flag and a sign which read: "Americans of German origin, for Liberty first, last and forever". Mr. John G. Blessing, first speaker of the Illinois Turnbezirk, was marshal of the detachment, and Mr. Adolf Georg, Jr., assisted him as deputy marshal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
