<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-09-08">Sept. 8, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">German Theater</title><title level="a" type="sub">First Performance of the Season</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0274</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0274.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-09-08">Sept. 8, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN THEATER</title><title level="a" type="sub">First Performance of the Season</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first German performance of the season was given at McVicker's theater yesterday evening. A crowded house greeted [Emil] Hoechster's company, and gave ample proof of the public's confidence in the German stock company. Judging from the first performance, Hoechster has organized a highly capable troupe.</p>
   <p>Above all, we must mention Miss Wassmann, whose performances of last winter are well remembered. She appeared in "Die Schoene Galathee" and "Fatinitza" several weeks ago, and so needs no introduction.</p>
   <p>Then there is Miss Reinhard, whose naturalness, youthful appearance, and stage experience greatly impressed the audience.</p>
   <p>Miss Hein also seems very promising; she reminds one of Miss Lindemann, who <pb facs="5418474_7_0275.jpg" n="2"/>became so popular here. At yesterday's performance, she was not entirely at ease, but that proved to be no handicap. Concerning Mrs. von Bayer, we cannot draw any conclusions at this time. Mrs. Scholz-Rademacher is undoubtedly an experienced actress, but she will encounter considerable difficulty here, since the public is accustomed to Mrs. Horn, who was a great favorite--and comparisons will, therefore, frequently be made. About Mrs. Rolff we must also defer an opinion.</p>
   <p>Among the gentlemen, we have Messrs. Ravene, Rodenberg, and Meyer, all well known. Mr. Luehr, the new leading man, seems to be very capable, and will appeal still more if he eliminates certain affectations in his speech. Mr. Klotz likewise is an experienced actor. By preference, he plays the parts of older gentlemen. Mr. Heinemann, the company's comedian, is an actor with a considerable knowledge of stage routine.</p>
   <p>We cannot say more of the company's members at this time. One must attribute this lack of comment on our part to the play which was given yesterday. The <pb facs="5418474_7_0276.jpg" n="3"/>performance enabled us to see the entire company, which was an advantage, but it also had this drawback--the actors could show off to full advantage because of the relatively small parts.</p>
   <p>Opening performances usually show deficiencies, and this production proved no exception. Aside from the greatly delayed start (and an oversight involving season ticket holders), the chief fault was in the choice of the play. Probably Mr. Hoechster could not find anything else in which to present a large company; also, the size of the theater was not taken into account by the actors, and so portions of the dialogue were inaudible. However, one would have been quite satisfied to have seen but a part of the cast, if the play itself had been better.</p>
   <p>The plot of the play is based on the attitudes of modern men--on their egotism in particular, and also their aversion to matrimony. The idea on which the play is based is good enough, but the play itself leaves much to be desired, since it shows a number of situations which are not approved by the better <pb facs="5418474_7_0277.jpg" n="4"/>class of people; besides, the outcome of the plot is obvious from the beginning. But the dialogue, as in all of Rosen's plays, is bright and pleasing and, in a few instances, even witty. This, then, is about all the praise that can be given.</p>
   <p>The performance, however, left nothing to be desired; the stage management did its share in presenting the play to the best advantage.</p>
   <p>Miss Reinhardt played the leading part, that of Karolina von Waldau, the young widow. Her elegant demeanor, expression, and other favorable attributes proved highly ingratiating.</p>
   <p>Mr. Luehr, the leading man, is an experienced actor, as we have mentioned. He has an affected way of speaking, but was well liked, and appears very promising. Mr. Ravene, as the young poet, Lenz, was excellent in every respect.....</p>
   <p>If a better play had been selected, we could have exclaimed, "This was the <pb facs="5418474_7_0278.jpg" n="5"/>best performance we ever saw!" But, nevertheless, we have the conviction that the German theatrical season will be very successful.</p>
   <p>The music between the acts was highly pleasing.</p>
   <p>Before the first curtain, Emil Hoechster recited a prologue, a lengthy poem by J. A. Seebaum, which won prolonged applause. [Prologue omitted in translation.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
