<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-07-06">July 6th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">World's Fair. the German House Enriched by a work of Art.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1636</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1636.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1893-07-06">July 6th, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">World's Fair. The German House Enriched By A work Of Art.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the German House, at the stairway to the Northern Gallery, an oil painting has been on display since the first of July well worth seeing by every visitor. The place is not very favorably selected, and the reason for it is that there is no empty space in the entire building. In spite of the poor light one notices at the first glance that here we have an art work of value. The painting carries the title "Grossvaters Geburtstag" (Grandfather's Birthday).-</p>
   <p>A young girl dressed in white has just entered grandfather's room and waits for his appearance, so she can hand him, together with the costomary congratulations, his photo which she holds in her hands and is decorating it with a wreath. The childish feature expresses impatience; the little one seems to be very anxious to meet the beloved grandfather and to enjoy herself over his surprise. The technical execution of the picture is well done. Not only for the main figure(the young girl) did the artist use great care, but also for her surroundings, the room furnishings, <pb facs="5418474_7_1637.jpg" n="2"/>producing an extraordinary favorable total effect. With particular skill a flower filled vase is executed. Also on the floor are flowers strewn about and it seems as if the fair maiden did plunder her whole little garden. On the wall hangs another picture, probably the girls's father's, so there are three generations represented.</p>
   <p>The painting is the work of the well-known Munich artist Adolph Pichler, a worthy pupil of Kaulbach. Other famous works of Pichler are : "Jacob's Tod" (Jacob's Death) property of the City of Munich;" Moses": "Deborah; "Maria and Jesus"; "Erster Verdienst" (The First Salary) etc.</p>
   <p>Owner of this canvas is Mr. Maximilian Morgenthau, a local well known business man. The price of this art work is $1500.00 but it is not for sale, it only was loaned to the German Commission by Mr. Morgenthau during the exposition, in order to decorate the interior of the German House. The purpose would be Much better served if, as aforesaid, the placing of the picture could be more carefully selected.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
