<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-03-09">Mar. 9, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Schiller Ladies' Society Celebrates Golden Jubilee</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1327</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1327.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-03-09">Mar. 9, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">SCHILLER LADIES' SOCIETY CELEBRATES GOLDEN JUBILEE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every society looks forward to its Golden Jubilee with great pleasure and expectation, making preparations that such day should be celebrated as an honor to its members. The Schiller Ladies' Society has done so and careful preparations have been seen everywhere.</p>
   <p>Although somewhat late as the announcer and conductor of the orchestra John S. Tansor declared, the program started at last with the sounds of the National Anthem. Miss Mary Tansor carried the National Flag into the room and placed it before the stage. Then followed the presentation of the officers by sister Ottilie Larsen. Here was shown the master hand of women.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1328.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A charming chorus of little girls in golden yellow dresses [yellow was the color of the day, and many members of the society were wearing it], carrying flower baskets, started the procession. The presentation and a short speech by Rosalie Ries, the President, followed. She spoke of the society's activity before, during, and after the war, and asked the women to join it. "Preserve your golden hearts," she added. Afterwards, presents were given her and the other officers.</p>
   <p>After Miss Ries's speech, the program continued with a recital by two small <pb facs="5418474_7_1329.jpg" n="3"/>children, Irene Klein and Rita Zimmermann. The festival orchestra played lively pieces under the direction of John Tansor, and the Schiller Singing Club, under Reinhold Walter's clever leadership, sang the "Day of the Lord," Wengert's "Morning Call," "Under the Lindentree," and "Student's Night Song." It is needless to say that these beautiful songs were greatly acclaimed. The president of the Singing Club was also asked to speak.</p>
   <p>DELIGHTFUL RECITALS</p>
   <p>The serious part of the program over, the audience prepared to listen to some jocular performances.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1330.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"The Musical Marriage," a humorous duet by Mr. and Mrs. Latkov, was exceedingly humorous and its song "Angra Pequena," evoked great merriment. Also, the Llewzler Brothers in "Two orderly people" were greatly applauded. A ball concluded the program.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
