<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-16">Jan. 16, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Busch Temple Theater</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Des Meeres und der Liebe Wellen," by Grillparzer</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0080</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0080.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-16">Jan. 16, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">BUSCH TEMPLE THEATER</title><title level="a" type="sub">"Des Meeres und der Liebe Wellen," by Grillparzer</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Des Meeres und der Liebe Wellen" (Waves of Love and of the Sea) a tragedy of love. And in none of the hundreds of German plays of this type is love stressed as much as it is in this work of Grillparzer....No other poet is better qualified to describe the happiness and sorrow of Hero and Leander.</p>
   <p>Miss Else Jannsen gave a superb performance as "Hero," the principal character of the drama. She gave a masterly portrayal of love, love in its incipient stages, in its development, its culmination, its bliss, its timidity, its courage, its hope against hope, its worries, and its self-accusations when it finds that all is lost. The audience showed its appreciation of her performance by hearty applause and by presenting her with bouquets and other gifts.</p>
   <p>In the drama "Hero" dominates to such an extent that the other actors have merely minor roles. Even "Leander," played by Richard Leusch, is of minor importance. He is a timid, bashful young man who avoids the members of the <pb facs="5418474_7_0081.jpg" n="2"/>other sex. Then he meets the beautiful "Hero" and falls in love with her. Now he is a different man. He is bold and ambitious, and his friend "Naukleros" finds it difficult to prevent him from committing foolish acts. His love knows no bounds. Twice he swims over the Hellespont in order to be near his adored one.</p>
   <p>August Stoye, who played the part of "Naukleros," has a somewhat peculiar conception of this role. He is humorous. Now, while humor may be permissible in some of William Shakespeare's serious plays, it is not at all becoming to the picture which Grillparzer portrays. His impersonation of "Naukleros"--as he conceived him--was very good.</p>
   <p>A further part of some importance was that of the "High Priest," the uncle of "Hero". It was played by Conrad Seidemann, who gave his character a quiet dignity and that relentless determination which proved fateful for the two lovers.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0082.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The other parts are small and unimportant. The lovable, cheerful, pert "Janthe" was played by Miss Hannah Waizenegger, the "Watchman of the Temple" by Jose Danner, and the "Parents" by Mrs Johanna Eisemann and Curt Benisch. The latter should be more quiet, and should stop rocking his head from side to side.</p>
   <p>Able directing by Conrad Seidemann contributed much to the success of the drama. The scenery, the illummination, and the costumes were excellent, and the performance was smooth and uninterrupted. (In two subsequent paragraphs the future performance of other plays is announced.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
