<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-10">Dec. 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Comrades' Night of the Stahlhelm a Complete Success</title><title level="a" type="sub">Front Line Fighters' Day Observed at Swiss Clubhouse</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1071</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1071.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-10">Dec. 10, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">COMRADES' NIGHT OF THE STAHLHELM A COMPLETE SUCCESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Front Line Fighters' Day Observed at Swiss Clubhouse</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago group of the Stahlhelm (Steel Helmet), a front line soldiers' bund, held its second great anniversary celebration Saturday night at the Swiss Clubhouse. The fest, not unlike that of last year, was arranged with a special eye to the fostering of comrade-like relations between the former members of the German army and the armies of the Allies, as well as the American veterans. And so, besides the Stahlhelm members and their families, there were present members of Chicago's military organizations, including many from the American Legion and the Veterans of Foreign Wars. That the great Saar demonstration was held on the same evening as the fest of the Stahlhelmers (who had engaged the rooms at the Swiss Clubhouse long before) is rather regrettable, because it was not possible to make arrangements to hold the party on another date. Yet, the great hall was quite well filled <pb facs="5418474_7_1072.jpg" n="2"/>when the official part of the program opened at 9:30 P.M.</p>
   <p>The program was conducted smartly under the leadership of N. Mueller of the local group. Quite a considerable part of the program was taken over by the Stahlhelm orchestra, under its conductor, Reinhold Pfaff, playing continously, to everybody's satisfaction.</p>
   <p>To emphasize especially the friendly relations between the former German and American front line fighters, the flag of the Stahlhelm was brought into the hall in a solemn procession together with the flag of the Lincoln Park Post of the American Legion, and all sang together "The Star-Spangled Banner, "and then the Deutschland song.</p>
   <p>The leader of the Milwaukee group, Heinz von Nobel, gave the welcoming address, and the Chicago group leader, N. Mueller--who, next month is to take office as the new district leader--gave the fest speech.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1073.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Beginning in German, and later changing to the language of this country he explained the purposes and aims of the Stahlhelm organization, laying special stress upon its readiness to foster good comrade-like relations with American veteran's organizations. In this connection, he extended a special and cordial welcome to the American comrades present, and thanked them for their attendance.</p>
   <p>After the official program was concluded, everybody stayed for the ball, and for a good drink. The host organization did everything in its power to treat the guests well and make them comfortable, so that the fest will certainly remain a pleasant memory for all who took part in it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
