<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-03-29">March 29, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The German Day.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1273</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1273.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-03-29">March 29, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN DAY.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Friday of this week, the meeting of the German Day Association will take place, at which definite decisions about this year's German Day are to be made. There have been extensive debates in the societies and the press, and in the course of previous weeks, in broader circles of our German population the conviction gained ground that the festival could only take place in the Exposition Building. It is pointed out that the management of the Exposition does not show the German Day Association very much courtesy. This is regrettable, and can not be censured strongly enough, but it does not change the fact that the Exposition is in Chicago and that the Germans of Chicago are in honor bound to arrange a German Day in the Exposition Building. The German Day Association, like other individuals and <pb facs="5418474_7_1274.jpg" n="2"/>organizations, is at present short of funds. But even this should not be an insurmountable obstacle.</p>
   <p>The World's Fair offers the visitors so many attractions that it is not necessary to have a large program in order to induce them to come. The celebration of the German Day should be sufficient inducement for men and women of German extraction to come in large numbers. Besides, it would be advisable to arrange some kind of out-door demonstration, by which the German Day would be conspicuous. This program could be carried out without large expenditures.</p>
   <p>Besides, the management of the World's Fair asked the German Day Association to acquire a large amount of admission cards. The undertaking should not be frustrated by this request. There is a way out and it must be found. It is unthinkable that the Germans of Chicago should not have a German Day celebration at the World's Fair this year, when in all probability thousands upon thousands of Germans and German-Americans will visit our city.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
