<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-08-18">Aug. 18, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">German Day Celebration</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1217</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1217.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-08-18">Aug. 18, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN DAY CELEBRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recent German Day celebration is now history. It seems fitting, therefore, to examine it critically and to analyse it because that is the only way to avoid making the same mistakes again, and to make German Day celebrations [more] successful in the future. The difficulties with which this year's German Day celebration was confronted, were solved very promptly and efficiently by the various committies. It had been decided to arrange a brief celebration, which would consist of several addresses and a few lieder, to be held on the Exposition grounds.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, this plan was not carried out. At the eleventh hour, the disastrous decision was made to hold the celebration in Soldier Field and to stage a long-drawn-out program. The fact was entirely overlooked that many thousands of German-Americans had come to Chicago primarily to see the World's <pb facs="5418474_7_1218.jpg" n="2"/>Fair and not to spend an entire afternoon at Soldier Field watching the German Day celebration.</p>
   <p>But since that was the way it was planned, Soldier Field presented an aspect of utter desolation. Those in charge of the celebration should have been warned by the unfortunate experiences others had had with Soldier Field on similar occasions. On Day 27, the Century of Progress Exposition was solemnly and officially opened. There was a huge parade; there were imposing opening ceremonies in Soldier Field, with the customary high dignitaries present, including the governor and the President's representative. The weather was splendid. In spite of all that, however, Soldier Field was empty. But on the fair grounds proper, there was a huge crowd of people.</p>
   <p>We cannot blame the German-American one bit for staying away from the [German] celebration. Who wants to listen to a lengthy program when a world exhibition is in progress next door, which offers a review of a whole century's activities? So much for this year's German Day celebration. Now a few words about German Day celebrations in general. If these celebrations are to be continued, their <pb facs="5418474_7_1219.jpg" n="3"/>programs must be completely changed. In the post, they have been boring; they never had the slightest touch of originality.</p>
   <p>The programs of the German Day celebrations are based on the assumption that all association and groups present, must also be given an opportunity to present themselves before the public. And so the turners must perform, the singers must sing, and the gymnasts must put on an exhibition. It's a good thing that the war veteran associations are not asked to demonstrate full maneuvers. When an occasional protest has been raised against this principle, the reply invariably was: If we don't give the societies an opportunity to show their stuff, they just won't participate all.</p>
   <p>This assertion is an insult to the societies. Most of the members of these organizations are not small and petty enough to refuse their co-operation unless they are given a chance to participate in the program. If the whole German colony in Chicago is approached in the right manner, they will give unanimous and enthusiastic support to German Day, and it will not be necessary <pb facs="5418474_7_1220.jpg" n="4"/>to reserve a place on the program for each society or group.</p>
   <p>The German Day celebrations have lost much of their attraction for the public because they do not have anything worth while to offer. It is the same thing year after year, which makes it monotonous. First of all the programs are much too long. The celebration should not take longer than two hours under any circumstances. It should consist of some musical numbers and a few brief speeches. The main feature should be appropriate to the occasion.</p>
   <p>With open-air affairs like that, the main point is to make the attractions appealing and interesting. The eye and the ear want to be entertained, and the main feature should, therefore, always be a swift-moving and colorful scene, which should, of course, include music and dancing. Then the spectators will not be tired and listless at the end, but [on the contrary], will visit the headquarters of the various societies in a happy frame of mind, and will join in some celebration afterwards. Unless the German Day celebrations change, they will have to forego their public character. After all, even the most <pb facs="5418474_7_1221.jpg" n="5"/>patient and faithful among the German-Americans does not relish the identical program year in and year out.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
