<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1919-11-02">Nov. 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Hearts of Gold</title><title level="a" type="sub">Bavarian Charity Affair a Great Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1443</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1443.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-11-02">Nov. 2, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">HEARTS OF GOLD</title><title level="a" type="sub">Bavarian Charity Affair a Great Success</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A large crowd dressed in its Sunday best--husky, blue-eyed men, buxom women, charming young girls, and healthy, rosy-cheeked youngsters all with the expectation of a good time, of music, singing, and dancing reflected in their faces-could be seen last night in the North Side Turner Hall, Where the Bavarian Aid Society held a great festival on behalf of suffering women and children in the old country. The promoters of the affair did not appeal in vain the Kind hearts of their compatriots. They came in such large numbers that the two halls could not accommodate them. Even the "socially elite" could not find seats, and before long even the vestibules were crowded. But that did not affect the joviality of those who came late. Nobody lost his festive spirit. Among the guests were also the officials of the German-American Aid Society.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1444.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>And the festival itself? Why, it was simply wonderful! The program committee had arranged a splendid entertainment to suit everyone, and they had engaged prominent performers who all did their best. It would take too much space to give a detailed account. As the highlights of the evening, however, we have to mention the "Hour Dance, Aurora," performed by Mrs. Schmidt and her ballet class; the biblical pantomime "Jephta's Daughter," by the same group; the wonderful songs (Lieder) sung by charming Resi Kranz and Resi Sterner, with piano accompaniment by Resi Buchner; the selections of the Liedertafel Freiheit (Liberty Glee Club), and the Singing Society Harmonie; the Bavarian folk dances [Schuhplattler, a kind of tap dance], by the clubs Edelweiss, Alpenrosen, and D'Wildschuetzen; the appealing recitals of the blind violinist, Franz Westengeier, and the selections of the Bavarian orchestra. They all captivated the audience and were rewarded by rousing applause.</p>
   <p>Mr. Joseph Moser, chairman, made the opening address, and Mr. Joseph Kestler gave the speech of the evening. In words that came from his heart and appealed to the hearts of his audience, the speaker explained that the purpose <pb facs="5418474_7_1445.jpg" n="3"/>of the affair was to alleviate as much as possible the war destitution in the old country. He then compared the past, the time of bloody war, with the present, which has brought disgrace and misery as well as peace for Germany. He drew a picture of the future in which the coming generation would be lacking in physical and spiritual stamina, their strength sapped by the hardships of war and the food shortage. After describing the services rendered their adopted country by the German element, he ended his speech, expressing the hope that peace and unity will be restored in Germany, with friendship and liberty the watchword.</p>
   <p>His words were received with deafening applause; they had fallen on fertile ground, and they opened hundreds of hearts and purses. Generous contributions to the fund for the destitute poured in. Individual gifts which amounted to more than one hundred dollars were contributed. The dancing continued until the early hours of the morning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
