<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-05-01">May 1, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">The Beginning of the World's Fair Today</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1665</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1665.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-05-01">May 1, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">THE BEGINNING OF THE WORLD'S FAIR TODAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Today begins the Columbia World's Fair in Chicago - a large exhibition which is to last for six months.</p>
   <p>Seventeen years ago the United States celebrated its one hundredth anniversary by means of the World's Fair in Philadelphia. Here, the development of the American industry was presented for the first time to an astonished world.</p>
   <p>Chicago is celebrating, beginning today, the four-hundredth anniversary of the discovery of America. It is also celebrating the gigantic development of this continent which started 400 years ago.</p>
   <p>Today, a World's Fair is opening, so grand and magnificent as no similar one has ever been witnessed by men before. At this exhibition the New World shall display the marvelous development it has attained in the <pb facs="5418474_7_1666.jpg" n="2"/>comparatively short time of a few hundred years. We speak from the standpoint of world history. At the same time the Old World will prove that it is still the mother of culture in the world.</p>
   <p>For quite a while it seemed that the World's Fair in Chicago would not bear the stamp of international culture - by being closed on Sundays - which would seem to put on the Fair rather the petty imprint of English zealotry. However, we can definitely say that the World's Fair will also be open Sundays, if not at the beginning, at least later.</p>
   <p>This Exposition will have a two-fold meaning and purpose for us, German-Americans. It will not only disclose to an amazed world what our adopted fatherland has achieved, chiefly by German labor, but it will also be an excellent opportunity for our old fatherland, Germany, as well as for German-Austria, to display its glorious achievements to the world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
