<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-09-19">Sep. 19, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">The German Day</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1409</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1409.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-09-19">Sep. 19, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN DAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago celebrates its German Day to-morrow.</p>
   <p>Originally these celebrations were held in memory of the arrival of the Krefeld Mennonites in America under the leadership of Franz Daniel Pastorius. In the course of years they have developed in many cities into big annual festivals celebrated by Americans of German descent, as in Chicago.</p>
   <p>The purpose of these celebrations is to give to men and women of German descent an opportunity at least once a year to acknowledge publicly and cheerfully that they are members of this race.</p>
   <p>Although they come from different parts of the great German Fatherland, and although their opinions are divided on religion and politics, yet they are all children of Mother Germania. They are all descended of one race, which can <pb facs="5418474_7_1410.jpg" n="2"/>look back upon an honorable and glorious history, and in the German Day celebration they remember and honor the great national union of their ancestors. With speeches and songs they proclaim loudly and proudly their everlasting gratitude for their descent from German forefathers.</p>
   <p>At the same time they do not forget their love for their adopted country, in which they have found a new home. They are fully aware of their duties to the new Fatherland and renew their oaths of loyalty to the country of their choice in the German Day celebration.</p>
   <p>This loyalty does not consist in the surrender of all moral and spiritual gifts and possessions bestowed upon them by Mother Germania but in the cultivation of these endowments and talents and the transmission of them to their fellow-citizens to the honor of the German name and the enrichment and cultivation of our national life. In this sense the German Day of Chicago is celebrated; therefore these festivals have always been brilliant events.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1411.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>It is the duty of all our fellow-citizens of German descent to participate willingly and cheerfully in our festivals.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
