<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-05">Dec. 5, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Lorelei Damenchor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0521</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0521.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-12-05">Dec. 5, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">LORELEI DAMENCHOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the direction of L. Lohmiller, the Lorelei Damenchor gave a concert yesterday afternoon in Prudential Hall; it was the first of its kind by the young organization, in existence only since February. That the ladies could sing as they did, after only a few months, justifies the assumption that they must have sung before. After hearing the program, we predict that, with careful training, these ladies will be able to give performances equaling those of their sister organizations. The four-part Evening Chorus from Kreutzer's "Nachlager von Granada" was beautifully rendered by voices which showed force and pleasing quality. The Lorelei ladies were aided in their two numbers by the singing section of the Deutscher Unterstuetzungsbund. The folk song "Muss i denn zum Stadtle hinaus" was especially enjoyable. M. Lohmiller orchestrated both numbers.</p>
   <p>A large number of friendly organizations participated in the exceptionally diversified program. The singing section of the Deutscher Unterstuetzungsbund had, earlier in the program, given proof of their abilities. The West Side Saengerkranz <pb facs="5418474_7_0522.jpg" n="2"/>and the Concordia Maennerchor directed by Mr. Lohmiller, also performed. Their rendition of "My Old Kentucky Home" made an excellent impression. The singing section of the Schwaben Athletic Club, long known for the fine quality of its youthful voices, joined with the Maennerchor and the Saengerkranz to conclude this part of the program with the "Soldiers' Chorus" from "Faust" accompanied by the orchestra; this rendition won enthusiastic applause. Director Reinhold Walter led the Independent Damenchor in the charming "Sonntagist's," which showed the choir's ability. Next on the program came the Polyhymmia Damenchor, under the direction of H. A. Rehberg, singing Lincke's "Gluewuermchen," in which number Mrs. Lammack's soprano obligato found extraordinary favor. Mr. Rehberg accompanied.</p>
   <p>Special joy was derived from the Vereinigte Damenchoere, who, directed and accompanied at the piano by Mr. Rehberg, gave two songs. The numbers were most favorably received.</p>
   <p>The program was also enriched by selections given by the North Side Mundharmonika <pb facs="5418474_7_0523.jpg" n="3"/>Club, which made a veritable hit; by the Harmonie Zither Club, directed by their president, A. Kuhnlein; by the appearance of the Gamsgebirg Schuhplattlerverein; by the piano solo by Regina Wittinger; by a tap dance delightfully executed by Shirley Kubeck; and, finally, by a fancy drill by the Harmonie Rebecca Lodge No. 2. While the gathering was enjoying all this, the hour became so late that those wanting to dance became anxious for the ball to start. Among the guest organizations, favorable mention should be made of the Baden-Schwaben Damenverein, No. 1.</p>
   <p>The festival committee was presided over by Mrs. M. Hillebrand. [Names of committee members omitted in translation.]</p>
   <p>Bardeleben's orchestra furnished the concert and dance music.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
