<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-12-06">Dec. 6, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">German Theatre in Mc Vickers.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0242</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0242.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-12-06">Dec. 6, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN THEATRE IN MC VICKERS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The bitter cold and the strong wind might have been the cause that the theatre was not very well attended last night. It seemed that the absent ones did not miss much. The evening was very discouraging for the public and actors. We have not so much cause to criticize the acting, but rather the singing, of this opera. In many salons of Chicago better singing can be heard than was done last night. "The Golden Cross," the excellent opera of the clever composer Brull, needs well-trained opera singers to be effective.</p>
   <p>We do not intend to hurt the feelings of anybody, but as regards the tenor Eisenbach, who has been praised so much by the management, we must state that it was audacious of this gentleman to appear active in an opera with such a voice. We doubt if he would find employment in a State Street Tingel Tangel (cheap musical entertainment). The chorus and orchestra were good. The second performance of the evening was much more pleasing and was entitled: "The Servants," a comedy by Bendix. It was shown here that the management disposes of very excellent actors, as better acting of this comedy was not possible and the best possible performance was given.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0243.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Well-deserved applause was accorded the players. The management should take its lesson about the direction of the plays to be enacted. Next Sunday, Schiller's "Wilhelm Tell" will be given as a benefit for Mr. Richard.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
