<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1891-03-23">Mar. 23, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">German Theatre</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0167</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0167.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1891-03-23">Mar. 23, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN THEATRE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Splendid performance of Moser's "The Hypochondriac". This drama, which was played yesterday by the German Theater Company under the management of Mr. Richard Welb and Wachsner, belongs to the plays which are always welcomed. The Theatre public was very pleased to see the play again and was greatly amused over the various misunderstandings in this real comedy, which caused much laughter and merriment over the many comical complications. We need not discuss the contents of the play as it is widely known. The performance in general was a masterpiece. The capitalist and hypochondriac Birkenstock, played by Mr. Ferdinand Welb, was represented in an excellent and perfect manner and created the chief interest of the public. Mrs. Markham, the wife of the hypochondriac, showed the highest ability for this difficult act. Also Miss Hedwig Lilia, representing their little daughter, was perfect in her role. Mr. Leon Wachsner, was the snobbish town counsellor, has not chosen quite the right role for himself; he exaggerated sometimes the character of his role. His domineering wife, Mrs. Richard, played her <pb facs="5418474_7_0168.jpg" n="2"/>role with great ability and effect.</p>
   <p>Their little daughter was well represented by Miss Clara Lippmann. The two lovers, the ambitious architect Reimann, and the jolly insurance agent Berger have been played very well by Messrs. Schmelzer and Bollmann. Of the small roles the following deserve our appreciation: The county official Pieper (Mr. Schubert), his wife Lina (Miss Albrecht), the county official Karner (Mr. Hortzheim), County official Hampel (Gschmeidler), and the Board of Health Physician Moll (Mr. Pechtel.)</p>
   <p>The management has been well done by Mr. Welb.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
