<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-10-22">Oct. 22, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Consecration of the Flag.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1543</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1543.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-10-22">Oct. 22, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">CONSECRATION OF THE FLAG.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>P. 6.. The Maximilian section, No. 2, of the Bavarian-American Society, of Cook County, Illinois, celebrated yesterday the consecration of the flag. From the balcony of the Freiheit Turner Hall where the celebration took place, flags were flown representing various divisions of the society.</p>
   <p>Every section of the organization appeared in a body. The fact that the hall proved too small, due to the unexpectedly large attendance, was most regrettable. Mayor Carter H. Harrison appeared as the guest of honor. Sitting on either side of the mayor were Pastor George D. Heldmann and Police Inspector Heidelmeier, honorary members of the society...</p>
   <p>Mr. G. Gleich, chairman of the flag committee, gave a short address of welcome. He was followed on the speaker's platform by Mr. Max Heidelmeier, Inspector of Police. He urged the assembly to maintain the German language and customs.</p>
   <p>The high point of the day was of course the consecration of the flag itself. This new symbol of unity was held on the stage by Miss Therese Kleiter, surrounded by the respective sections. After Miss Kleiter had appealed to <pb facs="5418474_7_1544.jpg" n="2"/>the members of the Maximilian section to remain loyal to the flag she handed it over to the flag-bearer, Ernst Kraft.</p>
   <p>Then Pastor George D. Heldmann stepped upon the platform. He spoke of the high culture of the Bavarians and of their extreme loyalty as Germans...He continued by saying that the blue color in the flag stands for loyalty, while the pure white symbolizes purity of intentions. The interwoven red indicates that the organization is not exclusively German but that it is a Bavarian-American Society. Pastor Heldmann was wildly acclaimed at the end of his speech....</p>
   <p>Heavy blue and white silk with gold fringe edging, was used as material for the flag. One side displays the Bavarian Coat of Arms while the picture of King Maximilian, the Second, decorates the other side....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
