<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-10">Oct. 10, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Harvest Festival of Rhine Organization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1310</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1310.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-10">Oct. 10, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">HARVEST FESTIVAL OF RHINE ORGANIZATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Wer kennt the Vaelker, nennt die Mamen, Die alle da zusammen kamen." (Who knows the peoples, gives the names of all who came here together.)</p>
   <p>Celebrating of festivals is what the people from the Rhine know best. Who had not known it from personal experience would have become aware of it last Saturday night when the singing section of the Rhine Organization celebrated its harvest celebration at the social Turnhalle.</p>
   <p>The young men who created this section know how to bring life into affairs affairs and make everybody comfortable at the same time. If we add that they spoke of Moselbluemchen and Bacharacher Glut (two brands of Rhine wine), one would be all but overcome by nostalgia. But the singers quickly sang it away. Under their esteemed director, Herr Brotesser, they greeted Father Rhine with his grapes, maidens, and bards, and sang songs of the sweet homeland and they sang so gaily that one's heart opened to them. One was in the midst <pb facs="5418474_7_1311.jpg" n="2"/>of his fellow countrymen, although away from the old homeland.</p>
   <p>The guests came and came and came, (sic) the space for dancing became narrow and narrower, and at ten o'clock the second hall had to be opened. But soon it became crowded there, too, when couples were enjoying the music of Mohr and his dance orchestra.</p>
   <p>The reporter was given no names of the committee in days, but he soon knew why. Long lines of tables were carried into the halls, the entire lodge was at work. Everyone was on the committee, no one hesitated to lend a hand.</p>
   <p>The president of the lodge, whose name the reporter must not reveal, welcomed the guests with rather whimsical words. But he mentioned the names of the Vienna and Hansa Football Clubs, the Swabian Athletic Club, the German Janitor Club, and the Senefeld Liederkranz, which, with its director, Herr Rekzek, and its president, Adolph Hambrock, came to return the visit <pb facs="5418474_7_1312.jpg" n="3"/>the Rhinelanders had made them at their anniversary. Of course, the Senefelders sang. And how they sang! They sang of the "dark brown maiden" and the Lueneburger Heide. And the beautiful harmony of the two male choruses was strengthened by the fact that the Rhinelanders' president, as a member of the Senefelder, was singing with the rest of them.</p>
   <p>Harmony was the keynote of the evening. That is why the event ran such a smooth course, just as though it had been held on the Rhine, in Coblenz, or Cologne. No doubt, it is beautiful everywhere on the Rhine!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
