<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-06-22">June 22, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Summer Festival of United Singers and Women's Choruses at the German Altenheim</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1931-06-22">June 22, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">SUMMER FESTIVAL OF UNITED SINGERS AND WOMEN'S CHORUSES AT THE GERMAN ALTENHEIM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United singers and the United women's choruses with their presidents, A. C. Wehrwein and Mrs. Ida Huch, respectively, arranged in the Louisenhain of the German Altenheim in Forest Park, their peoples and summer festival yesterday afternoon and evening.</p>
   <p>Those who attended admit that the festival was very successful. The president of the women's choruses, could only participate in the beginning of the festival, because other obligations, to her regret, prevented her from staying any length of time. So that President Wehrwein, had his hands full looking personally after the visitors. Shortly after 4:00 o'clock, he opened the festival with a hearty speech of welcome.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1320.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It gave Mr. Wehrwein a great pleasure to present to the large audience the Blue Island Liederkranz, who, with its women's section, under the leadership of H. Kornemann, were also present at the festival, in spite of the bad weather which prevailed at the time of their departure, with the singers of the district.</p>
   <p>With special pride did the festival leader present the Quartet, Harmony from Peoria. Messrs. Frank Rauen, Kurt Ahrens, August Hallermann and their director, Herman Meyer, an organization of selected singers in existence for only one and one-half years which enjoys an enviable reputation in Peoria. This was easy to understand, all those who had an opportunity yesterday to listen this quartet with its fine voices, had to admit unanimously, that it was excellent. The gentlemen were generous with their songs. Not only after their performance in the music pavilion, but again and again, sometimes here, sometimes there, they offered one of their songs, always earning rich applause, especially the song, Beim Kronewirt, pleased the audience very much.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
