<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-08">Apr. 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The Polyhymnia Singing Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0767</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0767.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-08">Apr. 8, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE POLYHYMNIA SINGING SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Polyhymnia, the goddess of lyric, must have been pleased yesterday because it was the day for the dedication of the new flag of the society bearing her name. The musical program was carefully selected by the very popular Mr. F. J. Beidel, conductor of the society, and it was designed to please even the most critical student of music. The program was opened with the "Song of Spring," by Schmidt, as the first offering of the Polyhymnia Singing Society, a most exact presentation indeed. The second number was entitled "In the Spring," by Fevra, a solo offering by Mr. W. Koch, for which he was enthusiastically applauded. Then followed a violin solo by Mr. Harry Diamond: and a song presented by the Harmonia Male Choir. After this Mr. August Behrens, the American national grand president of the lodge of the Sons of Hermann, delivered the festive address. "No more appropriate time could have been selected for the dedication of the new flag than during the Easter season with spring in the offing," he said. "The awakening of nature ought to have an inspiring effect upon the singers too, prompting them to shake off the lethargy,--if such is present,--and endow them with renewed <pb facs="5418474_7_0768.jpg" n="2"/>vigor and devotion for the cultivation of the song and the furtherance of their German mother tongue." The speaker then enumerated the attainments of the Germans in their adopted country. He also spoke of the decidedly widespread interest in the athletic field, in the culture of music, and of the achievements attained in industry as well as in agriculture. He implored the audience to continue the good work they have begun. "Above all," he said, "remain as a German true to yourself, because it is the best assurance of the respect of the native-born people." He requested the singers to sow the seed of musical appreciation in the hearts of our youth and, in conclusion, he expressed the hope that they will bring glory to the new flag when participating in the singing contest to be held in Buffalo.</p>
   <p>He then unfurled the flag under the loud acclaim of the audience. This act was accompanied by the singing of the "Song of the Flag" in which the singing societies Frohsinn, the Arion Male Choir, the Harmony Male Choir, and the Polyhymnia joined.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0769.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Polyhymnia Singing Society was founded five years ago and its steady growth is a credit to Mr. Carl Ebner, the society's ambitious president.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
