<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-10-02">Oct. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">Organizations and Their Social Activities Yesterday</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0758</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0758.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-10-02">Oct. 2, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">ORGANIZATIONS AND THEIR SOCIAL ACTIVITIES YESTERDAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The International Male Choir celebrated its 25th anniversary.</p>
   <p>The Hoerber Hall on 21st Street and Blue Island Avenue was crowded to capacity all during yesterday's celebration, which was arranged by the International Male Choir in commemoration of its 25th anniversary. Mr. Ludwig Rauch, the very able choir leader of the society, arranged an execellent concert program, in the presentation of which participated, besides the society's own male choir, the West Side Saengerkranz, the West Side Harmonie, the Schoenhofen Edelweiss Male Choir, the Liedertafel Einigkeit, the Concordia Male Choir, the singers of the Turner Society Eiche, the Society of German Warriors, the Union Male Choir, and the Society of German Male Singers of Kenosha, Wis., which appeared in its entireness. The concluding musical number on the program was "On the Altar of Truth," by A. Mohr, presented by a mass choir composed of members of seven societies. The force and the inspiration which was brought forth in this performance, won the singers great acclaim from the audience.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0759.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>An interesting sketch about the history of the International Male Choir was given in the festive speech, by Mr. Peter Schwab, the president of the association. He pointed out that when the organization was founded in 1886, courage and absolute belief in the principles for which one stood were required when one openly approved of the progressive aims of labor. The founders of the organization were Henry Betzel, A. Vavricka, Julius Glassner, Gustav Stange, Fritz Nebel, Henry Miller, Anton Hofmann, Wilhelm Kloss, and Gottlieb Schultz. Mr. Hugo Schmoll was the first conductor of the organization. He was succeeded by Hermann Bischop, who was responsible for the rapid growth of the membership of the association, which rose in the year 1888 to 200, with 40 active singers. Then came a change which almost necessitated the disruption of the organization; only four active members were left to carry on the work. Time and patience was required to withstand the strain, but it was worth the persistence, because it did make a magnificent comeback.</p>
   <p>The present vigor of our society raises our hopes for the continuation of its growth, until it will find the climax in the 50th anniversary celebration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
