<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-03-22">Mar. 22, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Swabian Singing Society's Concert.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0640</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0640.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-03-22">Mar. 22, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">SWABIAN SINGING SOCIETY'S CONCERT.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Although only a few of our great composers, came from beautiful Swabia, it was principally the noble folk song, especially men's singing which they always cultivated and still do. It was the Swabian Silcher, who gave the German people a number of beautiful folk songs and also one of them, who helped to elevate men's singing in the world, to the importance it possesses today. So, the Swabian Singing Society over there, whose festival the writer had the opportunity to attend for a day last year, is one of the most important in the fatherland on account of the number of its members and its performance.</p>
   <p>Its small cousin here in Chicago, has that in common with it, that it unites enjoyment of singing with endeavor. This was proven by the spring concert, which was given yesterday afternoon in Lincoln Turner Hall, which was, from <pb facs="5418474_7_0641.jpg" n="2"/>the artistic viewpoint and judging from the presence of such a large crowd undoubtedly also from the financial end, a great success.</p>
   <p>The singing society, as could be observed yesterday, is in excellent condition, having been increased by young blood; it was a pleasure to listen to the clear tenor voices. Also the bass and the baritone are well represented. Directed by an excellent conductor, it was only natural, that the chorus should rise to a superior performance. Well sung was "Rosmarin and Salbei-blattchen" by Silcher; also the "Farewell to the Forest" by Lange, in which Clemens Braun sang the baritone solo, and "Evening Peace on the Rhine," the last number. I liked best the song "Come Along" by Angerer, which, by its gay reproduction, pleased very much. "Homeless," by Becker, breathed pleasant feeling.</p>
   <p>The orchestra played a selection from "Blossom Time," beautifully, and it was noted that the large hall was in "Blossom Time" too, as the three <pb facs="5418474_7_0642.jpg" n="3"/>Rehberg girls made it so. Such a dainty sister-trio! And their performances? They almost placed the orchestra in the shade. That the youngest, Lillian, as a violincello player, has already achieved great things, was well known, but that she is already a great artist, came as a surprise. Nothing could be more beautiful, than her playing of Chopin's "Nocturne," more fluent, technically more perfect, than the "Spinning Song," by Popper.</p>
   <p>As an encore she played "O How Beautiful," by Kreisler, which she herself had transcribed from the violin to the violincello. Then came the second surprise, that her older sister, Irma, was almost as good a singer.</p>
   <p>Her performance of Wagner's "Dreams" proved, that she possessed a not very strong, but extremely flexible and effective voice, which, even in a higher pitch remained sympathetic and spoke of excellent training. Together with the third sister, Esther, who accompanied on the piano, she sang Massenet's <pb facs="5418474_7_0643.jpg" n="4"/>"Elegie," the most beautiful French song ever written, in a splendid manner with good diction, while the charming, seldom heard song, "Spring Flowers" by Reinecke, which sounds better with obligato violin than with violincello, was somewhat dragging. Touching was her singing of the simple "There Where My Mother Sung Me to Sleep" as a duet, in the course of which, even the little pianist revealed herself as the possessor of a fine alto voice.</p>
   <p>Mr. H. A. Rehberg can be congratulated not only as a conductor, but also as a happy father and to the success of the whole affair.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
