<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-19">Nov. 19, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Saengerbund Freiheit</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0416</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0416.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-19">Nov. 19, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">SAENGERBUND FREIHEIT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The concert given yesterday by the Saengerbund Freiheit at the Social Turnhalle had as its guiding motive the commemoration of the composer of the song of liberty and purpose, Josef Schen.</p>
   <p>The organization showed its reverence for one of the most outstanding protagonists of the socialist idea by giving three of the composer's best works. They were the "Lied der Arbeit", "An die Geduld", and the "Festgesang". The last was given at the close of the concert.</p>
   <p>The theme song was taken cognizance of also in the two numbers given by the ladies chorus composed of the Ferdinand La Salle Ladies' chorus and the singing section of the Ladies Sick-Aid Society Fortschritt. The ladies sang "O Freiheit,Loechstes Gut", by Lock and "Wahrheit, Freiheit, Recht"--the latter being based upon the melody of the familiar folk song "Aennchen <pb facs="5418474_7_0417.jpg" n="2"/>von Tharen".</p>
   <p>The remainder of the program consisted of folk songs and other songs, all of which were received with great applause by the audience.</p>
   <p>Director Karl Rekzeh took it upon himself to break through the pattern used at such concerts, and offered a program which, without any doubt, was found pleasing.</p>
   <p>The Saengerbund Freiheit and the Ladies Chorus were able to show what may be achieved by diligent practice. Both groups have good vocal material in their midst, and both show marks of good training.</p>
   <p>A much more magnificent effect was, meanwhile, achieved when the choruses sang together, "Es scheinen die Sternlein", "Was mein einst war", "Roeslein in Wald", and "Der Kaefer und die Blume", all were received with hearty <pb facs="5418474_7_0418.jpg" n="3"/>applause.</p>
   <p>The bass singer, Willard Andelin, was engaged to sing the solo parts; his wife took over the accompaniment on the piano. Much might be said about the art the well-known and popular singer uses in his singing. He was in an excellent mood. Profound silence prevailed when his voice rang out "In diesen heiligen Hallen", "Mephisto's Serenade", and Schubert's "Erlkoenig". The Mephisto laughter must have driven something of a shiver over the back of many a one. In a few words, Andelin explained the saga of the Erlkoenig to which he later gave an interpretation the like of which is seldom heard. He actually sang Schubert. Then, as an encore, came "Im tiefen Keller sitz' ich hier".</p>
   <p>The concert was followed by the usual ball. The hall proved too small to contain all the guests. Everywhere life was in full swing, and it was quite late when the last ones took their leave.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
