<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1891-07-13">July 13, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">Exceedingly Kind</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1702</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.F"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1702.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III F</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1891-07-13">July 13, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">EXCEEDINGLY KIND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Germans of Chicago have decided to celebrate "German Day" but to compare this day with the "St. Patricks Day" of the Irish, as is being done by the Daily News, can be prompted only by malicious intent. St. Patricks Day is not a historical day and has nothing whatsoever in common with any event important in the history of the United States. St. Patricks Day can be more fittingly compared to a German "Harvest Feast." As a rule there is much drunkenness and misdemeanors. Quite to the contrary, the "German Day" will be celebrated in commemoration of those courageous pioneers who established the first German Colony more than 200 years ago. This day shall remind the English and Irish Americans, that they have not been the only nation to build up and develop the United States.</p>
   <p>Another reason for the celebration of "German Day" is to convince the young generation of German-Americans that they can be just as proud of their forebears and kinsmen as other nations are. Above all, this day shall help to <pb facs="5418474_7_1703.jpg" n="2"/>stimulate the devotion of the German-Americans towards this country, for whose development German heads and hands have worked for hundreds of years. In this sense it shall be a genuine German-American holiday.</p>
   <p>The Germans are tired of being treated as of no account. They recognize the fact that others have no appreciation for the virtue of humility and contentment. They cannot be satisfied any more with empty phrases and they have decided to give a public demonstration of their power, as nothing else will attract the attention and admiration of the public effectively. Such a demonstration in Chicago would be of great benefit in many respects. Even the Germans would gain more self-confidence if they realize to the full extent their numerical strength. It is also certain that other nationalities will treat them with more respect after seeing a public demonstration of their legions.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1704.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>A year ago the Abendpost tried in vain to get the celebration of the "German Day" started. However, this year we have to same extent at least started the ball rolling, and should it be too late this season to properly prepare for a dignified celebration then it should be postponed. Nevertheless, the Daily News and similar institutions can depend upon our determination, that we refuse to accept or consider any of their plans as a substitute for the proposed great public demonstration.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
