<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-03">Feb. 3, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">German Theater</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-02-03">Feb. 3, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN THEATER</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The opening performance of the new German Stock Company was given at Hooley's Theater yesterday and....a large crowd was present. Only a few seats were vacant.....and standing room in the gallery was taken by several hundred people--quite sufficient proof that there still exists a strong demand for good German plays. The performance was not faultless, nor did we expect it. Mr. Hoechster had had insufficient time to arrange everything in as desirable a manner as possible. Besides, his leading man....deserted the Company, so the manager had to give the part, late on Saturday, to another gentleman....</p>
   <p>The play chosen for the occasion, "Children of the Times" by Felix Geber, also lacked certain salient features, and here we must emphasize that its chief fault is the entirely unmotivated, illogical plot. Not a soul comprehends why the leading lady does not marry the handsome and wealthy hussar lieutenant, but takes instead--"until death do us part"--the medicine man, <pb facs="5418474_7_0320.jpg" n="2"/>or better, the doctor.....There are....other instances....so contrary to expectations. The redeeming item consists in a fair measure of jokes interspersed in the unbearable, bombastic, long-winded speeches.</p>
   <p>In regard to the performance we must laud the excellent scenery, the costumes, and also the fact that the artists knew their parts thoroughly. About the performers themselves, the new members were given especial scrutiny by the public, and from what we overheard the impression has not reached the high level one might have wished for on an opening night.</p>
   <p>Miss Helene Kuhn, engaged to play leading parts....obliterated her youthful features with too much make-up. Her part, also, was not an auspicious one; though she has more than usual talent, and, given a favorable part, we feel convinced that she will prove of great appeal to our public. She is endowed with an ingratiating voice and deserves credit for perfect pronunciation.</p>
   <p>Regarding the qualifications and talent of Mrs. Sarner, we are likewise not <pb facs="5418474_7_0321.jpg" n="3"/>enabled to give definite criticisms after yesterday's appearance.</p>
   <p>Mr. Leon Scheerer in playing the unimportant role of the retired colonel gave proof of extensive stage experience.</p>
   <p>The lively acclaim accorded to Mrs. Horn immediately upon her appearance, showed definitely how the public appreciates the presence of the talented actress. She played the proud, aristocratic "Frau von Rhodenstein" in a very capable manner.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The omitted paragraphs contain comments about the lesser parts.]</p>
   <p>If, as we said before, the performance showed certain shortcomings and, therefore, could not be fully satisfactory, it is apparent, nevertheless, that Mr. Hoechster's prospects are good and that his intention to give us a good <pb facs="5418474_7_0322.jpg" n="4"/>German theater will be rewarded with success. It is, of course, a difficult problem to start a theater in midseason, and to organize a company quickly, especially one which will realize all the usual requirements. But apparently Mr. Hoechster is achieving this, and we hope he will be more successful next Sunday in selecting a play which will meet with greater approval, and in giving a more meritorious performance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
