<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-03-28">Mar. 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">The Plan of a German-American Exhibition Officially Abandoned Impossible to Raise Enough Money; Celebration of German Day at the Exposition.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1275</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1275.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-03-28">Mar. 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">THE PLAN OF A GERMAN-AMERICAN EXHIBITION OFFICIALLY ABANDONED IMPOSSIBLE TO RAISE ENOUGH MONEY; CELEBRATION OF GERMAN DAY AT THE EXPOSITION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At yesterday's meeting of the German group of the World's Fair, which took place, with Mr. Ernst Kruetgen presiding, at the Bismarck Hotel, it was decided to drop the plan of an exhibition within the framework of the "Epic of America" of the German-American section. This proposition was made by Dr. Otto L. Schmidt, president of the exhibition committee. Dr. Schmidt pointed out that it was impossible to raise sufficient money for the exhibition, therefore, it is best to abandon the plan, and to discharge the committee. A resolution to that end was, therefore, accepted.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1276.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is still possible, that through private enterprises, a German-American exposition can be arranged, but the prospects seem to be very poor. Mr. Reinhold Oeschler and Dr. W. Feichmann reported about their soliciting trip to the East and to St. Louis. On account of the depression and the situation caused by the bank holidays, these trips did not bring any results, although Dr. Teichmann succeeded in collecting a number of smaller contributions. The German group is now going to direct its attention to a worthy and imposing celebration of the German Day, which is planned for August 13th. Mr. Oeschler and Dr. Schmidt said that the leaders of the German-Americans of the East, declined to work together with this German group. Dr. Schmidt said he could find no explanation for their refusal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
