<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-29">Apr. 29, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">The German Theatre</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1017</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1017.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-29">Apr. 29, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN THEATRE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Otto Ernst, the illustrious playright, recorded great success last night when his delightful comedy, "Educator Flachsmann," was performed by the German Theatre company in Chicago. It was indeed a superb performance, well selected, with which to close the present season.</p>
   <p>Last night's production was an exhibition of brilliant accomplishments, which richly compensated us for some of the shortcomings of the past season, for which the company was to blame. If Otto Ernst had written nothing but "Educator Flachsmann", he would have endeared himself to theatre audiences. None but a pedagogue could have written a play like this one; none but a teacher in the German Reich is sufficiently informed of scenes in a school room.</p>
   <p>Otto Ernst was a teacher, but exchanged his career for that of a dramatist, becoming the most celebrated one of the present day. The <pb facs="5418474_7_1018.jpg" n="2"/>character, "Jan Flemming", is a self-portrayal of the playright, thus showing to the world what limitations teacher Ernst had to undergo. "Flemming" is the counterpart of the dramatist, besides, one does not have to be endowed with extraordinary brightness in order to recognize that every prominent character in the play is depicted from a living person. Names applied to the characters were fictitious, however, since Ernst was charitable, and did not wish to be too severe with the pedanic "Educational Cobblers." It may be said unhesitatingly that "Flachsmann" is especially appreciated for the realistic tendency of the play rather than for the brilliant dialogue which becomes classical at times, or for its delightfully refreshing and sparkling humor. Otto Ernst's satire is simply divine. Throughout the play, these "Cobblers" are brewing to the cracking of the whip. Neither is the great pedant, "Flachsmann", the empty head, the profligate, and crook spared from the well deserved disgrace, when he is finally unmasked. That a person who inspired Ernst with the material for the portray of the character, "Flachsmann", has lived, or still lives, is beyond doubt. Imagination alone could not have created this character. "Flachsmann" was too realistic for that........</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1019.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Exposing the school system was Ernst's chief object. The love scenes between "Flachsmann" and "Gisa", although poetical and very pleasing episodes, could have been easily ommitted....So much genuine enjoyment and hearty laughter as heard last night has seldom been heard in Powers Theatre....The dramatic architecture of this satire is a piece of art, glorifying the creator....The participating artists joined their forces to achieve an excellent success, and they did not fail.</p>
   <p>August Meyer-Eigen, the beneficiary of the evening, created a "Flachsmann" who would have evoked the plaudits of the playright. His impersonation of that character deserves unanimous praise. He excelled himself yesterday. The ovation, which was endless, spoke volumes. It expressed more than the attempts of a critic. Ewald Bach, our youthful hero, injected into the part of "Flemming", sufficient fire and emotion to make him an outstanding figure. This artist's highest ideal is art itself, to which he is devoted with every fibre of his being. This is, of course, the highest tribute we can pay this artist.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1020.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>And this is also the well deserved tribute to be paid to Mr. Meyer-Eigen, and Herman Werbke, for their characterization of "Prell", member of the School Board. Miss Else Haerting was simply adorable as "Gisa", the impersonation of which she was loudly applauded. The minor roles were also in hands of excellent artists.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
