<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-09-19">Sept. 19, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The German Theatre</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1013</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1013.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-09-19">Sept. 19, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN THEATRE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The comedy, "The Twin Sisters," was presented at the German theatre last night.</p>
   <p>Ludwig Fulda, author of "The Twin Sisters," wrote this delightful comedy in a poetical style, using the verse measure.....</p>
   <p>The writer demonstrated great capability when he wrote this work. The plot: In order to rekindle the vanishing love of her beloved husband, a young wife hides her own identity by masquerading as her twin sister. The charming psychological development, as well as the easy flow of the dialogue, the splendid humor, and the comical situations, were a source of great pleasure. Fulda enriched this comedy still more, by placing the acting in the colorful and carefree Italian Renaissance period. The elegantly construed verses of the dialogue are the work of a master.</p>
   <p>The principle feminine character, Giuditta, was interpreted by Violanda von Rooft, an artist of great ability and experience, She is <pb facs="5418474_7_1014.jpg" n="2"/>the possessor of a beautiful metallic speaking voice, shows an exceptional declamatory talent, and appears certain of herself at all times. She exhibited unusual talent by interpreting the grief of the neglected wife in act one, and then leaving this extreme, she gave a splendid portrayal of the jovial and exuberant spirit of the youthful twin sister. Her conception of the role was so convincing that an attempt to separate the artist from the figure of the author's creation, would have been difficult indeed. Playing opposite her was Ludwig Koppee, in the part of the bored landowner-husband and fiery lover of his supposed sister-in-law. With his pleasant voice and fine mimicry, he made a very good impression. The exceedingly entertaining figure of Count Parabosco was impersonated by Willy Schaff, who was cast perfectly in this role.....The role of the peasant simpleton, Beppo, an outstanding figure in the realm of character comedians, could not have been in better hands than those of Mr. Loewenfeld. Commendable also was the part of Lisa, played by Mrs. Emilie Schoenfeld.....</p>
   <p>The presentation of the "Twin Sisters" fully deserved the acclaim of the audience, which includes the orchestra under the direction of Mr. Ballmann.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
