<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-05-16">May 16, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">Die Gespenster (Ghosts).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0217</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0217.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-05-16">May 16, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">DIE GESPENSTER (GHOSTS).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ibsen's "Ghosts" had a warm reception in Chicago. It was our task a few days ago to go into details and into every phase of this play, on which occasion we defended the moral of the play and pointed out the great beauty of this work by Ibsen. Last night's first performance of "Ghosts" put us in a position to judge, whether this play produced the same effect when brought before our eyes by actor-artists, as it does upon every thinking individual when reading it. A deep gloom is cast upon this family tragedy from the beginning to the end without a single ray of sunshine to brighten it, ending in a breath taking tragedy which produced an almost harassing effect upon the audience. The author permits the sun to penetrate only after the horrid final act. When reading the book, one marvels at the daring of the writer in expressing his ideas; at the same time being filled with admiration for the man who so convincingly gave form to them and which produces quite a different effect when spoken by the actor. Ibsen's name will be known to generations to come; he had the courage to speak of things which in its secrecy bring harm and injury to families and nations, even to this day. He removed the veil of secrecy, exposing the horrible consequences. His name will be ranked with those of famous physicians, who work and fight for a healthy morale, condemning the world for its prejudices.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0218.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The part of Oswald as played by Mr. Mitterwurzer was perfect. He made a real study of the character and portrayed the scene of Oswald's insanity so realistically that he startled the audience by his movements. His art reached its height in the second act, while his death in the final act was nothing short of actual horror.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
