<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-09-26">Sept. 26, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">The German Theater</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Very Impressive Presentation of "Flop-House."</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1009</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1009.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1911-09-26">Sept. 26, 1911</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN THEATER</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Very Impressive Presentation of "Flop-House."</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The artistic staff of the German theatre company, as well as the audience who attended this performance last night have proven their ability of preparedness for excellent presentations. Exceedingly heavy demands are put upon the artists in Gorki's "The Flop-House"; therefore, the presentation of this extraordinary drama, can only be included in the repertoire of a theatre company, whose ensemble is composed of seasoned artists. The sombre unattractive scenery and costumes render the atmosphere much more critical towards the performers because not even the plot is sufficiently fascinating, and therefore heroic work on the part of the actors is required. The majority of the characters presented in this gripping drama are human derelicts, whose lives are of no consequence to themselves, the cynicism of which they have readily accepted. The author presented a very colorful group living in this "Flop-House," run by Kostylews and Wassilissa.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1010.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>That group consisted of an actor, a baron, a professional thief, a number of laborers, a women of loose character, and other women of questionable virtues. The majority of these human wrecks are seeking forgetfulness in the usual manner-indulgence in liquor. Gorki depicts the mental attitude towards the world as entertained by these men and women who philosophized on the possibilities which life offers, and what impression their plight has made upon the individual members of the human society. However, the author created in the pilgrim "Luka", a mild and understanding character, whose lot has thrown him together with these unfortunate people. Words of consolation and encouragement endeavoring to build up these wrecked lives as well as instilling lofty ideas on the philosphy of life, were the principles uttered by this apostle of reconciliation.</p>
   <p>This foregoing sketch may serve to clarify the difficult problems of the impersonators of the various roles. For effects, the actor must depend entirely upon his own inner resourcefulness. Furthermore, he must be able to impress the audience with the inner life of the character he portrays, if this great work should be understood and the <pb facs="5418474_7_1011.jpg" n="3"/>aim not be missed. The "Flop-House" was therefore an exhibition of outstanding ability by the ensemble of the German theatre, especially the accomplishments of the group of actors under the direction of Mr. Hanisch. Joseph Danner, in the impersonation of "Pilgrim Luka"; Ludwig Koppee, in the role of the demoralized actor; and Mrs. Jagemann in the part of "Anna," all of them proved their excellent dramatic talent, as did Mr. Vladimir Schamberg, the guest artist of the evening, in the role of "Pepel." Acknowledgment for the fine interpretation of their respective parts is due to Annie Bender, as "Natascha"; Mr. Marsano, as locksmith "Kletsch"; Mr. Wulff, as the cap-maker "Bubnow"; Paul Fasoli, as the carefree shoemaker "Alsoschka"; Mr. Loewenfeld, as "Kostylew"; Violenda von Rofft, as "Vassilissa"; Emilie Schoenfeld, as "Nastja"; Marie von Wegern, as "Kwaschnja," and director Hanisch in the role of the baron.</p>
   <p>The audience was so electrified by the play and its fine presentation as not to realize the lateness of the hour at the close of the production. We feel certain <pb facs="5418474_7_1012.jpg" n="4"/>that we voice the opinion of the public when suggesting that scenes of lesser importance should be omitted, as for instance, the greater part of Act IV, with the exception of the tale recited by the baron (Mr. Hanisch). Generous applause rewarded the artists.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
