<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-31">Oct. 31, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Forty-Ninth Anniversary of the South Side Arion Maennerchor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0449</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0449.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-31">Oct. 31, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">FORTY-NINTH ANNIVERSARY OF THE SOUTH SIDE ARION MAENNERCHOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Arion Maennerchor of the South Side last Sunday celebrated its forty-ninth anniversary with a concert, under the direction of Ludwig Lohmiller, in the West Englewood Masonic Temple. Mrs. William D. Peeso opened the program with an organ solo. A brief festival speech by the president, J. Georg Beier, was in the proper festival vein; he thanked all the guests for coming, and mentioned the golden jubilee which is to be held next year. Then the organization giving the festival sang "Kroent den Tag" and "Erinnerung" and received great applause. A baritone solo by Fritz Messthaler, which followed was likewise applauded. Then the organization giving the festival came onto the stage again and sang "Poeten auf der Alm," with Mrs. J. Georg Beier at the piano; this number brought honor to the singers and to the director.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0450.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Concordia Ladies' Singing Society and the Ladies Chorus Lorelei followed with the popular melody "Heimat" and with Schubert's "Lindenbaum," receiving great applause. Then the host organization sang the "Minnelied," by De La Hale and "Die Waldluft" by Tuellekrus. Youthful Marilyn, at the piano, played Paderewski's "Minuet" and Wely's "Monastery Bells". She was rewarded with rich applause and with flowers.</p>
   <p>A mass male chorus, composed of the Arion Maennerchor, Elmhurst Maennerchor, Junger Maennerchor, and Westseite Saengerkranz gave a singing march, "Hinaus". It was, accompanied by Frau Beier at the piano, an excellent treat to the ears.</p>
   <p>The final number on the program was an operetta in one act, arranged by the singers Fred Karper and Ludwig Lohmiller, under the title "Wiedersehn am Rhein". The stage represented the "Weingarten zur Rebenlaube" (Vineyard under the grape vine) and in this vineyard singers, as well as other people, <pb facs="5418474_7_0451.jpg" n="3"/>assembled for the gay harvest festival on the Rhine. The act was well done; special applause was given the individual songs of the singers, Fred Karper, Fritz Messthaler, and Georg Beier.</p>
   <p>The rest of the night was spent with music and dancing in the lower hall, for which the singers and Conductor Phillip Mohr provided splendid music. Kitchen and cellar took care of the bodily well-being of all guests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
