<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1934-09-16">Sept. 16, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Fest of Germans Completely Reshaped</title><title level="a" type="sub">Essentials of German Culture to be Displayed Every German Should Visit Fest Performance if Possible Motto: "Hie guet Deutschland allewege!" (Here and everywhere a toast to Germany)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1120</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1120.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-09-16">Sept. 16, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">FEST OF GERMANS COMPLETELY RESHAPED</title><title level="a" type="sub">Essentials of German Culture to be Displayed Every German Should Visit Fest Performance if Possible Motto: "Hie guet Deutschland allewege!" (Here and everywhere a toast to Germany)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An enormous amount of work has been done by the committee in making preparations for German Day; also by others who have volunteered their services to this great task.</p>
   <p>Numerous rehearsals were necessary to bring the fest show closer to the ideal visualized by its "father," Architect Gustave Brand, president of German Day. Endless patience was required to achieve all the desired effects for the eye of the onlooker--effects to last not only for a few hours, but to remain in his memory for a long, long time. Many a drop of sweat was shed, and many a sleepless night spent, to assemble all into a gigantic picture, which is to be designated as the outstanding feature of that which is nationally and characteristically German--how the German, in more than two thousand years has risen <pb facs="5418474_7_1121.jpg" n="2"/>from a dweller in virgin forests to a cultural height with so great a significance in the life of nations that even the most ignorant enemy cannot fail to acknowledge the change.</p>
   <p>Besides an enormous amount of work put into the fest show, Herr Brand likewise has succeeded in creating a proper mood for German Day. He has tirelessly visited the performances of organizations preparing to fulfill his ideal of German Day, seeking the most active co-operation. How far his efforts have been crowned with success will be shown today.</p>
   <p>In a like manner, the other members of the fest committee have endeavored to promote the success of German Day. The ladies' group has succeeded in contributing quite sizable sums to the "war chest" from the sale of flowers. The German element may show its gratitude to all who have given their services to this great cause by appearing in large numbers at the West Side Stadium today.</p>
   <p>But not only must all who have co-operated in preparing the fest show be assured<pb facs="5418474_7_1122.jpg" n="3"/>that their efforts are duly appreciated; it is up to us to demonstrate to other nationalities that the German element can do something great when so minded, and when working together. All this has nothing to do with politics. The celebration of German Day is no political show.</p>
   <p>It should make no difference what anybody's attitude is toward conditions in the old fatherland--whether he is or is not in harmony with the present form of government in Germany. It should further make little difference what any-one's political affiliations are, whether he is a Republican or a Democrat, or indeed whether he sides with any other party. All that sort of thing should be silenced today, as should the ever-present "bone of contention" among German-American organizations: differences of opinion and contrasts.</p>
   <p>We are all of the same tribe, no matter where or in what country our cradle may have stood; all of us represent German culture; we all are heirs to the <pb facs="5418474_7_1123.jpg" n="4"/>same tradition, which was a tradition when other nations (so bloated today) had no history at all, not even a face they could call their own. In some instances, some of these peoples hardly would have become nations, were it not for the German elements in them.</p>
   <p>There is only one thing for us to do on this day, and that is to acknowledge that we are proud of our German descent, that we are wiling to cultivate and to foster, in our lives, that which has been bequeathed to us by our ancestors: the German language and the German character.</p>
   <p>German Day should serve to remind us that all we see and hear at the fest show has its roots in a country which meets with enmity because it does not "crawl" to the cross," and refuses to moan and to cry, but will rather strive onward, resisting oppression in the hour of its greatest misfortunes; a country aiming at a place in the sun. German Day, on the other hand, should help us to contemplate, and to contrast all subsersive influences with those things which <pb facs="5418474_7_1124.jpg" n="5"/>are generally considered special German virtues: righteousness, sincerity and honesty.</p>
   <p>If we, as American citizens, intone the song "Deutschland, Deutschland ueber alles," then it is no boast at all, and is still less a negation of our oath as citizens. It is rather the vital expression of the fact that we have become aware of the value of what Germany has given us all, and of what we should bequeath to our children in so far as possible, since things German are, to us, more than just a hollow or meaningless phrase.</p>
   <p>There should be a common awareness in us all that it is right to say that, the better Germans we are at heart, the better citizens are we going to be in this land, and the better able we will be to discharge the great tasks which confront us. Making headway, with our German character enabling us to put the German brand upon many phases of American life, we can fulfill our duties as citizens in the truest sense of the word. This we can do only when we stand together; only together can we attain that high aim.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1125.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>We, as human beings, can never attain to the ideal. There is one thing, however, that we can do: At least on this one day, we can make a living thing of the motto quoted above: "Hie guet Deutschland allewege!"</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
