<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1910-02-15">February 15, 1910</date><title level="a">German Theater.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0108</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0108.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>DIE ABENDPOST</title>,
<date when="1910-02-15">February 15, 1910</date><title level="a">German Theater.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The Robbers," drama in 5 acts by Friedrich Schiller. In comparison to the rather unfortunate performance of the "Robbers" which was given four years ago at the Auditorium, yesterday's performance at Powers, was considerably better.</p>
   <p>The effect did not evaporate, as it did before, in too spacious surroundings, but the performance in itself, the selections for the various roles, the ensemble all bring in the balance and were an improvement over the previous presentation, All seats were sold again, and it is gratifying, to observe this eternally young drama, Schiller's first, inspite of its simplicity of action, with its fire and its roaring, foaming contents.</p>
   <p>This afternoon public is not yet infected with modernism, it came, unaffected and unprejudiced to the theater, but filled with reverence, for one of Schiller's works. A great achievement, an interesting character study was this Franz by M. Stiewe. In the first acts one might have wished a more quiet protrayal, less nervous vitality, since Franz's crimes are coldly premeditated. <pb facs="5418474_7_0109.jpg" n="2"/>the results of this scoundrels philosophy and not dictated by impulse. Possibly, in his final scene, a little more moderation might have been advantageous, but, regarded in its entirety, this Franz deserved much attention. Mr. Bolton gave a very satisfactory Karl who most capably showed the smoldering fire of this soul, yet preserved its benevolent character.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
