<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-21">Jan. 21, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Senefelder Song Club</title><title level="a" type="sub">Concert at the North Side is a Great Success. . .</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0776</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0776.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-21">Jan. 21, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">SENEFELDER SONG CLUB</title><title level="a" type="sub">Concert at the North Side is a Great Success. . .</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The hope that the Senefelder Liederkranz, through its entertainment would prove a financial success and increase the traveling fund for the forthcoming Buffalo Song Festival was more than realized. The large North Side Turnhall was crowded with an expectant, but patient multitude. At eight o'clock, many found difficulty in obtaining seats.</p>
   <p>The opening number was a delightful overture by Keler-Bela, followed by that sublime choral song, "Vom Rhein." Max Bruch's composition was a rare artistic treat. All the choral selections were given in such a masterful manner that they evoked almost unending applause. Two arias by Mary Carrington. . .were exceptional.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0777.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>A very presentable performance was given by young Arthur and Eugene Thomas, thirteen and fourteen years old, respectively. Their piano duet, "Birthday Music" by Bohm, reflects great credit upon the the thoroughness of their teacher, Mr. Kern, the Liederkranz director.</p>
   <p>The humorous quartet song "A Jovial Prison" by von Kron, in which Messrs. E. Pieritz, R. Braeutigam, F. Schollenberger, and William Dreuth excelled, was given generous acclaim.</p>
   <p>The choral selection, "Forest Whispers," by Schulz, and a splendid number, was given by the Liederkranz members. It has been also chosen as a number for the Buffalo Song Festival.</p>
   <p>In the second part of the program, we would like to place particular emphasis on Kemmerland's choral song, "The Four Seasons," a brilliant attainment of the society. This composition has not been heard in <pb facs="5418474_7_0778.jpg" n="3"/>Chicago heretofore, and its introduction is entirely attributable to the efforts of the club's president, Mr. Niederegger.</p>
   <p>Mr. Hieber's offering, "The Tambour-Major" by Andre, a humoristic song, earned unstinted applause, likewise did the duet of William Dreuth and Max Kleinert, which is also written in a jovial vein.</p>
   <p>The final number of the concert was the hilarious scene from the "City Musicians of Bremen" by Kreymann, which earned well sustained applause. Messrs. H. Scherzer, A. Talmer, F. Schulze, and H. Hieber played their roles excellently. Animals and a bird were portrayed.</p>
   <p>The highly successful concert proved a source of animation. It is no small wonder then that the majority remained for a protracted period to further enjoy the social amenities of the evening.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0779.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Yesterday's festival of the Senefelder Liederkranz proved anew that its popularity is bound to attract a huge throng. At the proposed masquerade on February the sixteenth, the Germans of our city will again appear in large numbers and we have ample assurance for that.</p>
   <p>The arrangement committee deserves much praise for its effective efforts in providing such a delightful entertainment. Jack Becker was the chairman appointed. Mr. Miederegger is the president of the society.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
