<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-29">Oct. 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Zither Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0452</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0452.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-29">Oct. 29, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO ZITHER CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>With its fall concert and the ball that followed it, the Chicago Zither Club yesterday once more achieved a new success, of which it may rightly be proud. Thanks to the popularity of the organization which lives up to what it promises, many lovers of good music from all parts of the city arrived at an early hour, so that shortly after the concert started there were only a few seats left in the great hall of the Lincoln Turnhalle. Truly, no one of the guests was disappointed.</p>
   <p>The program included a large selection of pearls of most beautiful music, so that everyone in the audience got something to his taste.</p>
   <p>As host, the Zither Club, led by its talented director, Joseph Waldherr, opened the program with three samples of what it could do and received hearty applause. Only further encores could satisfy the audience.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0453.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The succeeding numbers fared equally well. A double quartet of the Zither Club was heard later, and was given a fine ovation. So did the Chicago Mandolin Orchestra, led by its director, Paul Klein.</p>
   <p>The same may be said of the singing club Erinnerung, under the direction of its conductor. In short, the musical part of the program went along gaily and successfully, proving that the players are equal to difficult classical recitals.</p>
   <p>A gay ball followed the concert, and an excellent orchestra provided the music. Those who wanted to dance found ample opportunity to tire themselves out by dancing,especially when genuine German waltzes brought the right mood to them. An excellent kitchen took care of the bodily needs; also, there was a well-supplied bar. That the enjoyment of the occasion lasted until the early morning hours astounded nobody.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0454.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The festival committee, under whose direction the preparations were made, and which deserves the gratitude of the organization for the success of the festival, was composed of the following gentlemen and ladies: Festival president, Gabrie Jung; secretary, M. Blast; treasurer, O. Mackh; admission tickets, Frau M. Hafner; F. Rappold, W. Mackh, K. Woehrmann, V. Hafner, J. Holz, H. Schoelz, F. Maywald, W. Tegtmeier, Frieda Eichmann, and Miss S. Mackh.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
