<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-17">June 17, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">District Saengerfest of Arbeiter-Saengerbund a Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0381</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0381.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-06-17">June 17, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">DISTRICT SAENGERFEST OF ARBEITER-SAENGERBUND A SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In spite of the sultry weather, which was far from ideal for an entertainment in a closed room, there was a good attendance at the district Saengerfest of the West-of-the-Lakes Region of the Arbeiter-Saengerbund von Nordamerika (Workers' Singing Association of North America). It was held at the Vorwaerts Turnhalle, which was, thanks to the mobilization of their own numbers, filled to capacity. The musical program, led by the district director, Karl Reckzeh, merits unreserved praise. The kind of songs preferred by the Saengerbund is essentially different from the concert repertory that is generally offered. In the first place, it is characterized by political coloring.</p>
   <p>Viewed from a purely musical standpoint, the performance of the massed choirs and the singing of the mixed choir were a great success, as far ac director Reckzeh is concerned. He conducted the large body of singers with masterful skill, and knew how to draw out the beauty of the songs. All refinements of <pb facs="5418474_7_0382.jpg" n="2"/>choir singing were observed to the last detail. Especial emphasis was laid by the director upon good pronunciation; it was possible for the attentive listener to understand every word. The director was fortunate in having vocal material which was good and, in certain passages, actually excellent. The maennerchor sang "Kroent den Tag," by Kurz, and "Die nene Zeit," by Boese; the Franenchor sang "Wahrheit, Freiheit, Recht," by Funke, and "O Freiheit, hoechstes Gut," by Lock; the mixed choir sang "Die Macht der Musik," composed by the director, "Im Morgenrot," by Uthmann, and "Die Internationale," by Degeyter.</p>
   <p>Further interest was aroused by the appearance of two pianists, Alvena Reckzeh and Kathryn Anderson, who demonstrated a considerable measure of technical skill, and a sound concept of the spiritual values of the compositions. They gave, as piano duets, Beethoven's "Serenade," "Le Revuer," by Arensky, and "Malaguena," by Locdana. As accompanists of Reckzeh's choir composition "Die Macht der Musik," they demonstrated a delicate sensitivity and excellent taste. The solo part in the last-named composition was most ably handled by <pb facs="5418474_7_0383.jpg" n="3"/>the soprano singer, Else Nimtz.</p>
   <p>At the Saengerfest there were delegations from St. Louis, Milwaukee, Springfield, and Davenport. The secretary of the Bund, Carl Mayer, was given a banquet the preceding evening, in which the nine Chicago organizations affiliated with the Arbeiter-Saengerbund participated. The plans and arrangements for this successful Saengerfest lay in the hands of the chairman, Joe Kunst; the district secretary, F. Hesterling; the treasurer, Heinrich Hoffmann, and the financial secretary, Jean Wurska.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
