<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1924-06-15">June 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Great Folk Festival</title><title level="a" type="sub">Singers Meet at Riverview Park Cleveland to be Scene of Next Festival</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1420</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1420.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1924-06-15">June 15, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE GREAT FOLK FESTIVAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">Singers Meet at Riverview Park Cleveland to be Scene of Next Festival</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To reap the reward of the toil and labor of the festival days, to renew old acquaintances, and to make new ones, out-of-town and local singers met yesterday on the picnic grounds of Riverview Park. There were thousands present at the picnic grounds. There was jollity, hand shaking, questions, laughing and good-natured fun. Many a person found a good old friend quite unexpectedly, which gave occasion for an exchange of all kinds of opinions (sic). The picnic committee, headed by Mr. Pilgram, took care to provide plenty of music, food, and drink. Soon the singers of various societies started to sing gay songs. But youth was dancing in the beautiful dance hall to the beautiful strains of the Roth orchestra, and seemed never to get tired. Whenever a young couple wanted special entertainment, the adjoining Riverview Park offered opportunity aplenty for it.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1421.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Yesterday marked a conference of delegates of the North American Song Bund. After the minutes of the last conference in Louisville (1914) were read, the national treasurer reported about finances, showing a capital (sic) of $10,500. This report was favorably received, as the Bund, during the hard years of the war, had to struggle with many financial difficulties.</p>
   <p>Then the motion was made and carried that a few changes should be made in the constitution, to make it more in keeping with the present times. It was also proposed to bring back to life the former song periodical, "The German Song." This proposition was amended to read that all members of the Bund should subscribe to the paper and so assure its success.</p>
   <p>The Next Festival</p>
   <p>Two cities competed for the next festival, St. Louis and Cleveland. After a prolonged debate, Cleveland was unanimously chosen as the coming festival city. <pb facs="5418474_7_1422.jpg" n="3"/>Delegate Krueck, who spoke in the name of the city, expressed his thanks and gave it as his conviction that the coming song festival will not be behind the successful Chicago song festival, as Cleveland has a large new beautiful hall. And, as the speaker wittingly remarked, the festival may even turn out to be much more successful than this one, provided that a certain United States law suffers some modification; this would be quite desirable considering the eternally dry throats of singers.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
