<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-12-08">Dec. 8, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Pearls of Art.</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Chicago Singing Society's Concert.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0659</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0659.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-12-08">Dec. 8, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">PEARLS OF ART.</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Chicago Singing Society's Concert.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the opening of yesterday's concert of the Chicago Singing Society in the Medinah Temple, the old choral: "Only to God Above, Praise be Given", sounded like the bells of an old cathedral. In all the concerts which the Chicago Singing Society, under the conductor Wilhelm Boeppler, has given, we have heard nothing but good music. Yesterday's concert brought proof, that the society struggles to draw as close as possible to human perfection. Especially praise-worthy were the feminine voices. That was a genuine German chorus with frank, clear, ringing tone and excellent enunciation. But it should not be said that the male chorus was not excellent too.</p>
   <p>The Soloists.</p>
   <p>Miss Claire Dux was the celebrated soloist of yesterday's concert. Miss Dux fully deserved all the applause that was given her. Her voice was never as clear and full, her expression in tone and language never so deep and plausible, <pb facs="5418474_7_0660.jpg" n="2"/>as yesterday. She started her program with Schubert songs, which she interprets excellently. Her Gretchen at the Spinning Wheel" was charming, of soft tenderness, and her other Schubert songs were also works of art. She sang Agathe's Aria from "Freischutz" by Weber, with great fervor, which made a deep impression. All the modern songs which followed, were excellent, and the artist had to throw in several extra songs. She was accompanied on the piano by Mr. Bruno Seidler Winkler.</p>
   <p>Miss Lillian Rehberg, the young cello player, played first, from the Concerto in D Minor by Dvorak, the Adagio and Allegro. She has at her disposal a wonderful technique, which is the more surprising on account of her youth. She was accompanied on the piano by Miss Maria Stange.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
