<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-01">Apr. 1, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">Promising Indeed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0773</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0773.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-04-01">Apr. 1, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">PROMISING INDEED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The concert presented by the society, Eintracht, proved a decided success.</p>
   <p>Great things were expected of the newly founded singing society, Lieder Tafel Eintracht yesterday, when the association gave its first public concert. The general interest in this performance manifested itself early in the afternoon, when Schoenhoffen's Halle swarmed with eager music devotees.</p>
   <p>The carefully selected program was opened with the singing of Mozart's lovely composition, "Die Eintracht," [Harmony] with orchestral accompaniment. Outstanding <pb facs="5418474_7_0774.jpg" n="2"/>in the first part of the program was the brilliant performance of the "Voices from the Austrian Alps," by Weinwurm, the acclaim of which was shared by five participating male choirs and the soloist, Mr. Coninx. Exceedingly well received was the baritone, Mr. Fritz Mueller. He sang the "Recitative and Arioso" by Lortzing, and was compelled - by the persistent plaudits of the audience - to break the rules of the society and to please with an encore. A young Singer, Miss Helene Knochenmuss, whose exceptionally pleasing voice found much appreciation, concluded the first part of the program. It was her first public appearance, and judging her by yesterday's vocal solo, she will, with persistent study, achieve prominence.....</p>
   <p>Resuming the program, the Liedertafel Eintracht singing society exhibited the excellent training of its singers by presenting Bruch's composition, "Inn, Thou Beautiful...."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0775.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This newly founded singing society demonstrated at its first public appearance yesterday, that it already occupies a prominent place among the leading sister singing associations of our city....</p>
   <p>The executive officers of this organization are: Lorenz Mayer, president; Louis Coninx, vice-president; Alfred Neumann, secretary; Henry Meyer, secretary of finances; Ernst Fenske, treasurer; Oswin Nickol, archivist. Carl Linnemeyer, tramp-treasurer [sic]; Gustav Gundlach, conductor; and Lorenz Mayer, second conductor. Although this organization was founded as recently as January 31 of the current year, it already has a membership of fifty-four. The discontinuation of the singing section of the Aurora Turn Society on January 24 of this year, is directly responsible for the founding of the "Eintracht" association. Mr. Gundlach, who earned many laurels for the Aurora society during the eighteen years he was its conductor, has been engaged to lead the association toward their goal.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
