<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1891-03-16">March 16th, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">"Die Munchener"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0169</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0169.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1891-03-16">March 16th, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">"Die Munchener"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Enthusiastic reception of a first night performance. The Munich residents were greatly touched by the dramatic play which took place January 18th. The actors played to a full house and the audience gave them rousing cheers for the different parts they played. They met with a similar welcome by old friends of the "Grand Opera House." The play is built up in the old sacred commandment of obedience and piety in children. We find a true characterization of Bavarian life so that the public almost began to think that they lived among them sharing their joys and misery. What made it more susceptible was the nature of the play and the way in which it was acted. Everyone of the Munich players is an artist; there is no mistake about that and only the extent of their own will power makes one better than the other. The title roles were played by Miss Schoenschen and Mr. Swoboda, they represented the old peasants in such a way that everyone had to love them, the real affection they held for one another and their great love for their children and how they helped those in time of need won the hearts of the spectators who really felt they were living with them. Nr. Hospaner played the shoemaker in a capably dramatic way. The shoemaker who as a simple shoe repairer, married the energetic Maud (Miss Thaler) and later on in life rose to be a lordly official. Much praise must be given to M. Hospaner, The claypit builder was acted by Mr. Ernest and Miss Muller took the part of Wally.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
