<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-09-13">September 13th, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Deutsches Theater</title><title level="a" type="sub">(The German Theatre)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>CHICAGOER ARBEITER ZEITUNG</title>,
<date when="1880-09-13">September 13th, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">Deutsches Theater</title><title level="a" type="sub">(The German Theatre)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was quite refreshing to see a large audience gathered last night, at Mc Vicker's Theatre for the opening performance of this season, on which occasion the Collmer-Isenstein management presented the Putlitz play "Rolf Berndt".</p>
   <p>Rolf Berndt, the son of an merchant, returned home, after an absence of twelve years, only to find his father's business insolvent. To save his father's honor, he met the merchant's obligations. Such an unpleasant experience in his young life, made almost a recluse of him, without faith in anybody, and even his love for a young aristocratic widow could not penetrate into the depths of his soul, to bring forth the beautiful character, hidden there. Finally, through some daring situations the cloud of his gloomy life has been lifted, and he once more became a happy man. But around this treasure of a character, formed a group of persons, who have been taken from the so-called higher class of a small German town and therefore, not quite understood. Mr. Richard's acting in the part of Rolf Berndt showed us, that he is a seasoned actor with great experience, but who lacked warmth.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0262.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was a character difficult to impersonate, for which the audience showed him much appreciation. Miss Trautmann, acting the part of the woman, with whom Rolf fell in love, and herself deeply in love, was a splendid partner to Mr. Richard. She has personality, a clear voice and is perfect in dramatic art. Mrs. Hanno acted Rolf's mother very satisfactorily.</p>
   <p>Miss Fiebach in the part of Marianne, a young lovesick girl who has not learned to control herself, was in her element. She has the advantage of being known to the audiences through her previous engagement here, and was warmly received, when she made her appearance on the stage.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
