<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-19">Aug. 19, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Austrian Day</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1611</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-V.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-hungarian #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1611.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3) (Hungarian)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-19">Aug. 19, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">AUSTRIAN DAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5. 6 - Austrian Day was celebrated yesterday on the Exposition Grounds. This date was chosen because it coincides with the birthday of Franz Joseph, emperor of Austria and Hungary. The festival was a spectacular event which comprised three events, the parade, the celebration at the Choral Hall and at the Industrial Palace and finally the gathering at Old Vienna.</p>
   <p>The parade traversed the main business section...The weather was ideal. This was the first time that the Chicago Austrian and Hungarian clubs had united for a mass demonstration of such gigantic proportions, and one must grant that it was a huge success especially in view of the short advance notice.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1612.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The parade started on Wabash Ave., near the Auditorium. At its head was Mr. Ignatz Baum, festival marshal and chairman of the celebration committee.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, one of the most elaborate floats, the one which portrayed the Vindobona had an accident.... A wheel broke off and the horses shied. Consequently five lovely ladies had to display their gorgeous gala regalia in a hired back. There was no alternative...</p>
   <p>The advance guard of the parade consisted of a troupe of Chicago policemen, led by Lieut. Collins. Then followed the aforementioned marshal with his staff and the guests of honor, about 50 Germans who were exhibitors at the Fair. These gentlemen rode in gaily decorated cabs. Next in order came the division of "Allied Austrians and Bavarians," who are ethnologically related.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1613.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Austrian-Bavarian Ladies' Club members rode in pompous coaches decorated with ornate green embellishments... The Columbia Zither Club was also in this group. The next division was composed of men and comely girls from Tirol and Voralberg. A cavalcade of 25 Czikos ( Hungarian Cowboys) in their fantastic costumes, wide, white pants, red corset - shaped jacket with black cords, round hat with conspicuous band displaying the Hungarian colors, green, white, red , closed the parade.</p>
   <p>We express our appreciation for the generous participation of the Hungarian clubs, which supplied a surprisingly large contingent. This last division contained the Austrian-Hungarian Club. The Hungarian Aid Society, Hungarian Veterans, Hungarian Society, the Sarah Lodge of the Sisters of Humanity and the King David Lodge. Most of them rode in coaches.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1614.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The Austrian and Honved cavalry deserves to be mentioned. They maintained order throughout the parade. The festively decorated floats in their varied lines, as well as the allegorical and historical groups did much to enhance the color scheme..... At the Music Hall the main program was composed of speeches and music. Knights in armor flanked the American and Austrian flags, the crown and bust of the Austrian emperor were displayed on the stage and........a eulogy of Austrian accomplishments, was made by Dr. S. D. Sewards of New York....</p>
   <p>The next address was given by Dr. Henry Bak of Chicago. He said: "Today's celebration is watched with interest by our old fatherland. It will prove to Austria that we have not forgotten it, that it is still living in our hearts. Today we proclaim Austria's and Hungary's glory.... Our patriotism is genuine and intense. Such a faithful son also makes <pb facs="5418474_7_1615.jpg" n="5"/>a good citizen of America. We experience a constant yearning for the church steeples and the verdant hills of our homeland and for the trees shading the graves of our forefathers. This awakens in us a tender love for the land of our cradle, it makes us anxious to make sacrifices for our beloved fatherland."</p>
   <p>He then spoke of Austrian accomplishments, particularly of the exhibits at the Columbian Exposition. His closing remarks were: "Our beloved fatherland, and our new country - will always be dear to us. Hail Columbia is written on our banner, and 'Home, Sweet Home' will forever echo in our hearts."</p>
   <p>Mr. Hovarth was the Hungarian speaker....The festival ended amidst the melodious strains of Rubinstein's "Banquet." In Old Vienna at the Fair military music furnished the chief attraction. The Austrian National Hymn, and the German "Heil Dir, Im Siegerkranz," were played... Congratulatory telegrams were sent to the Emperor of Austria, this day being his birthday....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
