<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-02-03">Feb. 3, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">The German World - Exposition Ladies and Children's Chorus.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0836</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0836.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1891-02-03">Feb. 3, 1891</date>.
<title level="a">THE GERMAN WORLD - EXPOSITION LADIES AND CHILDREN'S CHORUS.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the past week the nine classes of the chorus materialized, as mentioned in the Illinois Staats Zeitung and in most of them instruction has actually begun. The classes were well patronized and great interest for the noble cause manifested itself everywhere. Many new applicants were accepted. The great benefits which will accrue to the German youth and to Germanism in general has convinced many intelligent, public spirited ladies to found committees in all parts of the city for the purpose of procuring talented ladies and gifted children to participate in the chorus. The success of these active committees will be reported by us from time be time. The ladies chorus will have its first meeting next Thursday evening in the Methodist Church block, corner south Clark and Washington streets. The ladies, and the various mixed choruses as well as church choirs will be there to form a unit.</p>
   <p>It is to be expected, that ladies who have had private instructions before, will appear in large numbers.</p>
   <p>Although applications will continue to be accepted for several weeks, it is advisable <pb facs="5418474_7_0837.jpg" n="2"/>to fill all the vacancies in the children's division as rapidly as possible, so that instruction will not be hampered. For the applicants of the 14th, 15th and 16th year group, a separate class will be started.</p>
   <p>In the following halls instruction will now be given regularly:</p>
   <p>Wednesday, 4 P. M., Aurora Turnhall, corner Milwaukee Avenue and West Huron Street, and Schumacher's Hall, at 4650 S. Ashland Avenue.</p>
   <p>Thursday, 4 P. M., Fortschritt Turnhall, 1824 Milwaukee Avenue and Apollo Hall, 250-52 Blue Island Avenue.</p>
   <p>Friday------------two halls are listed.</p>
   <p>Saturday-------five meeting places are mentioned.</p>
   <p>Applications will be accepted at all the aforementioned addresses and also by Mr. G. Katzenberger, 633 N. Clark Street. The admission cards are now available and <pb facs="5418474_7_0838.jpg" n="3"/>will be distributed to the registered members on Thursday. The choral exercises and songs are being printed and will be used during the instruction period this week.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
