<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-19">Oct. 19, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">Birthday Celebration</title><title level="a" type="sub">Vorwaerts-Schiller Maennerchor Honors Hermann Vogel, President for Many Years</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0525</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0525.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1932-10-19">Oct. 19, 1932</date>.
<title level="a">BIRTHDAY CELEBRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Vorwaerts-Schiller Maennerchor Honors Hermann Vogel, President for Many Years</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last Saturday the singers, with their wives and friends, came together to celebrate the sixty-third birthday of their president, Hermann Vogel, who is well known in German circles. The hall on 63rd Street and Racine Avenue proved to be almost too small to contain all who came to congratulate Mr. Vogel.</p>
   <p>In the name of all those present, Secretary Fritz Wegner offered Mr. Vogel the most cordial felicitations. He laid particular emphasis on the many years of devoted co-operation which Mr. Vogel gave to the fostering of the German lied in Chicago, especially to the building up of this organization and, in commemoration of this day, presented him with a beautiful meerschaum pipe. The recipient of this honor expressed his thanks in words fitting <pb facs="5418474_7_0526.jpg" n="2"/>the occasion and promised to continue doing his duty as in the past.</p>
   <p>Special satisfaction was occasioned by the presence of the president of the Vereinigten Saenger (United Singers) of Chicago and of the Saenger-bund of the Northwest, A. C. Wehrwein. He had been glad to come, he said, to extend cordial wishes to his old schoolmate and friend of many years standing, With whom he is united by a bond of common memories; and to spend a few gay hours in the circle of the singers of the Vorwaerts-Schiller Maennerchor. The singers could not refrain from making Mr. Wehrwein an honorary member. He expressed sincere gratitude for the distinction, explaining that it is so much more beautiful to give flowers to those still alive than to lay them later upon the grave of the deceased.</p>
   <p>Careful preparations had been made for the feeding of the guests, and many a gay melody was heard, alternating colorfully with humorous recitals until, at an advanced hour, the gathering broke up.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
