<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-18">Apr. 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">"Der Dritte,"</title><title level="a" type="sub">A Play in Three Acts by Albert Markwitz</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0065</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0065.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-18">Apr. 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">"DER DRITTE,"</title><title level="a" type="sub">A PLAY IN THREE ACTS by Albert Markwitz</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The first performance of the play "Der Dritte"(The Third) by Albert Markwitz was given yesterday evening at Bush Temple. The work bears evidence of diligent labor, and develops the idea that our present form of legitimate love and matrimony by which two people are bound together for life, or at least until one or the other procures a divorce, should be supplanted by a higher type. Under all circumstances, and irrespective of any legitimate ties, a woman should attach herself to that man whose nature, ability, and energy she has apparently been destined to develop to the highest degree. The advocate of this idea is well aware that our present moral standards strongly oppose his theory, for he says in the course of the play, that "a thousand years may elapse" before mankind attains such a degree of magnanimity. Perhaps more time will be required.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0066.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In treating his subject, Markwitz favors the man too much and does not give the woman sufficient consideration. The magnanimity of the two rivals who battle for the passive heroine is remarkable, indeed, even though it is far in advance of our time. But what can we say to a woman who is wedded to one man and then devotes herself to a second, or even a third man? One feels relieved when the curtain falls before further "affinities," whose "dormant powers" she feels herself qualified to awaken, appear. This woman who rushes from the arms of one to the embrace of another cannot command our respect. We are too old fashioned. If she had not attached herself to a second "lover," we might understand her conduct, for it may easily be explained, and even redound to her credit that she severed all intimate relations with the drunkard to whom she was legally married; and though it may be contrary to our moral standards when she looks about for a substitute, it is only human. But we are prone to suspect her when she casts the second one aside like a lemon which has lost its flavor, as soon as another impressive representative of the sex appears. Who can guarantee that a third, a fourth, a fifth, or even more may not follow?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0067.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The idea that only a woman can bring about the full development of a man's dormant powers is very pretty, indeed, and is true in some cases; it "sounds nice" to hear it said that when the woman meets this man she must consider it her life work to open the fountains of latent energies--and there may be something to that! But what if two or more men discover that their magnetic power, the so-called "great love," is inherent in one and the same woman, as has happened? Then the woman will have to alternate between the men, we suppose. It is, to say the least, questionable whether or not such "reasonable" parting and uniting on the part of lovers, or of people who think they are in love, will raise the morals of mankind to a higher level, as the author thinks. This idea is too remote from present views to make it acceptable.</p>
   <p>Markwitz took great pains in working out his theme, and he has done everything possible to make his idea acceptable. In fact, he went farther than was good for the play. The theoretical and philosophical discussions take up too much room and disrupt the limited action. The play could be made <pb facs="5418474_7_0068.jpg" n="4"/>more interesting if some parts were stricken out, others shortened, and superfluous scenes omitted. The subject matter is interesting and Markwitz approaches it in a very unusual way. Various scenes are unduly long, for instance the death scene in the third act. The last act, which presents the solution, contrasts strongly with the previous acts, even though the conclusion is peculiar.</p>
   <p>The author attempted to offset the seriousness of the play by the addition of byplays and several child scenes. He should have engaged Blumenthal and Kadelburg, if he wished to enliven the play, instead of inserting puns and jokes. They were out of place in this setting. Moreover, the omission of two or three acts would render the play stageworthy, for in its present form it will die because of its length and prolixity.</p>
   <p>As far as the performance itself is concerned, we wish to emphasize the fact that the roles should have been practiced more. Several of the actors did not completely master their parts and were dependent upon the prompter.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0069.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>It does not add to the pleasure of the public when major parts of dialogues are first whispered by the prompter and then repeated more loudly by the players; this procedure should be stopped. There were other deficiencies, also, which should receive the attention of the stage director. The actors were well chosen for their roles, excepting perhaps Max Juergens who played the part of the painter "Henkel". Juergens knew what was required of him and acted well, especially as far as "Henkel's" relations with "Ada" were concerned; but he did not look like an artist--he could just as well have taken the part of a traveling shoe salesman or that of a mailman. Mrs. Helene Koch had the thankless task of playing "Mrs. Ada," and it was not wholly her fault that she did not succeed, for the part was badly sketched--she did the best she could. Adolf Stoye did well as "Loser, the Pharmacist," the first "affinity" of "Mrs. Ada"; Jose Danner excelled as "Weixler" the drunkard and gambler. The others and their roles were: Hans Zoder as "Druggist's Apprentice"; Mrs. Johanna Eisemann as "Henkel's Housekeeper"; and Miss Hanna Waizenegger as "Mrs. Ada's Youthful Sister," a role in which she kicked over the traces several times. The scenes in which the children had <pb facs="5418474_7_0070.jpg" n="6"/>such long parts were not quite successful, because children in America are not good actors as a rule, and especially because the children spoke German with a foreign accent. As a result, the scenes had an unnatural and disturbing effect--the fewer the children, the better.</p>
   <p>At the end of the second act the author acceded to the wishes of the players and the curious audience and appeared on the stage. He was applauded by the audience in which apparently quite a number of his friends could be found.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
