<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title><date when="1888-04-09">April 9, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">Anniversary Festivities of the Social Turn Society</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1729</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1729.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter - Zeitung</title><date when="1888-04-09">April 9, 1888</date>.
<title level="a">ANNIVERSARY FESTIVITIES OF THE SOCIAL TURN SOCIETY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Those men who were responsible for the establishment of the Social Turn Society a year ago, can proudly look back on their accomplishment. Last night's anniversary celebration of this young society, held at the Northside Turner Hall had the appearance as if all the friends and admirers of these gymnastic societies kept its rendezvous and extended their hearty birthday greetings to the Social Society. Taking into consideration that the red banner flowed over the heads of the audience it was not at all surprising that the progressive turn societies as the Vorwarts Turn Society, Der Fortschritt and the Garfield Turn Societies were well represented. The Lincoln and the Chicago Turn societies took active part in the execution of the program, thus helping to make the evening a great success. Then turner Glog stepped on the speaker's platfrom and delivered a speech which did not fail to produce the expected effect: "Friends: That America, which is of most concern to this society is the platform of the turners of North America, which if necessary, the society is ready to defend. Our organization is not as progressive as it was expected to be, and it needs the strong support of its well wishers to help them win back the reputation of old. The heavy clouds which have <pb facs="5418474_7_1730.jpg" n="2"/>gathered on the political horizon of the Socialists, have become more threatening since the time of the sevenfold judicial murder of November last. Modern developments have reached a point, when a radical change of the social and political order, according to socialistic ideas, has become an important question of the present time. Disregard for this situation is dangerous and unworthy of an organization as that of the N. A. T. We have to take action! We can not remain neutral in a fight which divides modern society into two huge camps, capital and labor. Capital demands slaves, which a free man can never be, and with conditions as we know them, could there be even the slightest doubt to which of the belligerents the N. A. T. will give its aid? The North American Turners will have to decide in the near future whether the organization wishes to be known as a progressive and liberty loving organization. If so it will have to decide to work hand in hand and shoulder to shoulder with the progressive organizations of the country.</p>
   <p>We hope that it will not sink to the level of the American "Athletic and Sporting Societies" and share the viewpoint of the war societies, and be patriotic even to the extent of approving of murder. Finally, I wish to mention the unfriendly attitude of our press, which reminds me of Bebel's words "Whenever the liberal press has a word of praise for me, I am almost convinced that I did something which <pb facs="5418474_7_1731.jpg" n="3"/>I should not have done!" If the Illinois Staats-Zeitung ever prints anything in favor of the turn societies or any turner, one can take it for granted that some mistake has been made; and if the contrary is the case, we can be sure that we are on the right path.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
