<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-03-07">Mar. 7, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Carl Schurz Ceiebration.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1361</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-05">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1361.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-03-07">Mar. 7, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">CARL SCHURZ CEIEBRATION.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Independent German Women's Club Honors the Memory of the Well-Known Statesman. Personal Memories.</p>
   <p>A memorial celebration in honor of the 100th birthday of Carl Schurz was arranged yesterday, at the Palmer House, by the Independent German-American Women's Club.</p>
   <p>Mr. Leopold Saltial, the first speaker, honored the great German-American in the German language; Professor Julius Goebel, instructor of the German language at the University of Illinois followed, with the language of our country. Mr. Saltiel commented in a humorous - though sarcastic manner - on how absurd it is to celebrate, in the land of the free, the memory of a hero (who was a son of the beautiful Rhineland) for the cause of freedom, with a beverage prohibited hypocrites. He suggested the idea, that with men like Carl Schurz, among German-Americans of to-day, a cabinet consisting of only Anglo-Americans, would be incredible. People like Carl Schurz would not stigmatize a successful German-American, as title-hunter, whom <pb facs="5418474_7_1362.jpg" n="2"/>it dared not support.</p>
   <p>Professor Goebel praised, in the same vein, the courage and conviction, which could be found in Schurz. He spoke of the great talent and the love of a Schurz towards Mother Germania, as well as, towards the bride Columbia. His love of the German language did not blind him, therefore, he also mastered, like his mother tongue, the language of his adopted Fatherland so that he could reach the hearts of the Americans with his thoughts and ideals. His love of freedom made him loathe slavery; his integrity, the corrupt: his honesty and courage made it impossible for him to remain in the background, when he saw an injustice done.</p>
   <p>The speaker declared that Schurz never would have his name Anglicised, and that he always strove toward creating Unity.</p>
   <p>Prof. Goebel concluded his speech with Bismarck's words: "As a German I am proud of Schurz."</p>
   <p>Fitting well into the frame of festivity was a short address by the Chief <pb facs="5418474_7_1363.jpg" n="3"/>Clerk of the Municipal Court, James A. Kearns, who expressed himself, in reference to the German thoroughness, and declared his pleasure of having in his office a great percentage of employees who are of German descent.</p>
   <p>Mrs. Anna Schoedler admitted courageously that she owed her interest in politics only to Carl Schurz.</p>
   <p>A special surprise was given the audience when they were introduced to a former fellow student of Carl Schurz, Prof. Joseph Frank, who brought up the question of whether we could not produce more statesman of the same caliber, as that of Carl Schurz.</p>
   <p>At the conclusion, a short essay about Carl Schurz was offered by Miss Alice Wood, a student of Carl Schurz High School, which was gratefully received.</p>
   <p>Musical recitals by Mrs. Bishop, and a trio of the Bush Temple Conservatory of Music, completed the festivity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
