<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-07">Jan. 7, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">German Theater</title><title level="a" type="sub">"The Wholesale Merchant," Popular 3-Act Play by Walther and Stein</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0114</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0114.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1901-01-07">Jan. 7, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN THEATER</title><title level="a" type="sub">"The Wholesale Merchant," Popular 3-Act Play by Walther and Stein</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A howling success, indeed; that's the "Great Merchant"; it is colossal, hilarious. Who could not laugh yesterday, is hopeless. Walther and Stein are not endowed with intense dramatical talents, but they have abounding, limitless humor; splendid fellows who made something out of nothing, which is an art in itself.</p>
   <p>Yes, genuine humor! These chaps could be able to convert an old hat into a costume, and a dose of snuff into goose-liver pie. "The Whole-sale Merchant" is not a popular play nor a farce; it would be pre-sumptious to use either appellation. One might call it unadulterated nonsense whipped into a stage play in a most haphazard manner, but in spite of its hopeless array, it is drastically effective to die of <pb facs="5418474_7_0115.jpg" n="2"/>laughing, a scream! Walther and Stein need never attain greater literary accomplishments; they wished for laughter only, and will have it wherever and whenever "The Wholesale Merchant" appears. At present nearly anything sails under the banner of "popular play" or "farce," but neither applies to the "Wholesale Merchant." Therefore, our classification of the play should not evoke offense. We even assert the play surpasses Blumenthal and Kadelburg's "White Horse Tavern" as far as drollery is concerned, and the dramatical construction is superior.</p>
   <p>Only two figures support the play; the remainder fade into obscurity but produces contrast. The plot? With the best of intentions one can say no more than "It is desperately simple." But why talk of the plot. "Schneppke" and "Huber" have such elementary power to create convulsive laughter that the public cannot think of any intrinsic action, even if one were available.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0116.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The story revolves about the megalomaniacal "Schneppke," the heir, who intends to become a merchant prince and thereby also a rival of "Schwandorf," Councillor of Commerce, by whom he had been employed.</p>
   <p>Our financial wizard experiences heavy losses, due to his shrewd customers. He recognizes his folly and finds succor in the arms of his former employer. There is also the usual love affair. "Huber," the painter, is smitten; the object being the Councillor's daughter, "Franze." In this role Julius Donat is better than any of his former offerings. His Bavarian dialect was masterly, and he showed his stuff. This also applies to Theodore Pechtel. He, too, deserves unreserved acclaim for his impersonation of that nonsensical figure, "Schneppke." Pechtel is a comedian from head to foot. His impersonation was about the best which has been shown here. Both gentlemen were enthusiastically received and repeatedly recalled. A sold out house. Untarnished performance in every respect. All actors were given profound encomiums. Our muscles of risibility were <pb facs="5418474_7_0117.jpg" n="4"/>thoroughly exercised; our brain was not asked to solve abstruse problems. What more can you ask of the "Great Merchant"? That's sufficient, says Pfeffermann.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
