<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-06-11">June 11, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">Make German Day a Holiday! an Appeal to German Businessmen</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1659</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1659.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-06-11">June 11, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">MAKE GERMAN DAY A HOLIDAY! AN APPEAL TO GERMAN BUSINESSMEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is a twofold purpose in the celebration of German Day; first, to honor the German exhibitors who have made great sacrifices in order to contribute to the success of the Columbia World's Fair; and second, to demonstrate to the assembled delegates and representatives of all the nations of the earth the numerical strength and power of the German-Americans in Chicago.</p>
   <p>This can be achieved to a measurable degree, only if the Germans of Chicago take part in the parade and the festivities at the World's Fair.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1660.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But in order to make a full participation possible, it is necessary that the German businessmen, the storekeepers, manufacturers, and other employers, close their stores, shops, and factories on this day and grant their employees a holiday. German-American parents should co-operate by requesting to have their children excused from school, in order to make a holiday possible for the German school teachers. The stronger and the more imposing the Germans appear on German Day, the better it will promote the moral and business interests of Germanism.</p>
   <p>For this reason all German businessmen are urgently requested to make June 15 a holiday for themselves and their employees, so far as it is humanly possible.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1661.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>This appeal is signed by the Executive Committee, E. G. Kalle, chairman, Chas. H. Wacker, Harry Rubens, Max Stern, Frank Wenter, Wm. Vocke, Herman Pomy, Louis Kurz, Adolph Georg, J. F. Dewes; and also by the invitation and reception committee, H. Rubens, chairman, Dr. T. J. Bluthardt, Francis Lackner, Theod. Brentano, W. Michaelis, Joseph Brucker, J. Rosenthal, J. Goldzier, Geo. Schilling, W. Hesing, Peter Schuettler, and A. F. Stevenson.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
