<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-22">Oct. 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Radio Hour of the Saengerbund a Great Success</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0461</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0461.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-22">Oct. 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">RADIO HOUR OF THE SAENGERBUND A GREAT SUCCESS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As usual among the Schwabs, a cheerful sentiment prevailed at the variety night of the Swabian Saengerbund which took place Saturday night at the Lincoln Turner Hall, 1050 Diversey Parkway, and it was not surprising that, at the beginning of the performance, there was no seat available in the spacious hall; many of the late comers had to be satisfied with standing room.</p>
   <p>The Swabian singing bund gave its evening of entertainment the form of a radio hour in which, in quick succession, a program rich in variations was given, from beginning to end it held the audience in tension, bringing the performers rich, well-merited applause. After the singing of two German songs, "Die Rosenuhr" and "Das Echo", by the well-trained chorus of the organization, guided by their director, H. A. Rehberg, the program was unfolded as each number was announced separately and skillfully by Herr <pb facs="5418474_7_0462.jpg" n="2"/>Richard Moritz. Serious recitations, musical numbers by the radio orchestra of Bernie Hartwig, songs by the quartet, and various vocal solos succeeded one another. Numbers in the Swabian style were not lacking. They met with the special approval of the audience. Interspersed between the performances, came announcements about markets and sports, all in a humorous vein. All who participated in the program, members of the Swabian singing bund, did their best to guard the reputation enjoyed by the organization for its entertainments, and even to add to it. For the planning and execution of the program, the following gentlemen deserve special credit: Bernie Hartwig, Emil Baum, Max Diebold, and Anton Iberbe.</p>
   <p>The many-sided variety program was followed by a dance in the halls of the Lincoln Turner Hall. That the necessary refreshments were not missing is only natural. All in all, the Swabian Saengerbund has reason to look back with satisfaction upon the evening. The efforts of all participants, who gave their best, were well rewarded by the success of the evening. The <pb facs="5418474_7_0463.jpg" n="3"/>same applies to the members of the entertainment committee, who took care that the evening passed smoothly. The entertainment committee, which spared no labor or effort, was composed of these gentlemen: George Iberbe, chairman; Bernie Hartwig, Emil Baum, Richard Scheerle, Karl Hunold, Adolph Klockler, Ernst Degenfelder, and Anton Iberle.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
