<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-11-28">Nov. 28, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">Appreciation of Music.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0863</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0863.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II A 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1887-11-28">Nov. 28, 1887</date>.
<title level="a">APPRECIATION OF MUSIC.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There was not a vacant seat at last night's concert arranged by the "Orphans Singing Society at the "Turner" hall. Furthermore, professional musicians have hardly ever been so well represented at a concert, as was the case last night. The main attraction of last evening's program was the "Battle of the Hun's" by Zollner, executed by the male chorus with orchestral accompaniment. This composition will comprise the chief musical number to be played at the St. Louis song festival in the near future, therefore, much interest was displayed by professional musicians in the preparation of this extra-ordinary composition. Those who know the difficulties which have to be overcome when vocalizing this composition spoke of it as a daring undertaking for comparatively few rehearsals cannot bring about a rounded and smooth performance, But the "Orphans" male chorus stood the test splendidly and to the fullest satisfaction of those who doubted in their ability. This wonderful musical work has to be heard again before we should venture to say more about it. The beautiful and overpowering composition kept the listeners spellbound for over one hour. The "Orphans" male chorus gave an exhibition of fine musical <pb facs="5418474_7_0864.jpg" n="2"/>understanding and mastered the technical difficulties with ease. The supporting soloists were Miss Mathilde Wilde and Theodor Lammers, who were not at their best. The orchestra of thirty-five men, composed of Chicago's best musicians, worked in splendid harmony with the chorus. Miss Wilde, who appeared twice during the first part of the program, made a much more favorable impression than in the solo part in the "Battle of the Hun's", which requires an almost Wagnerian singer for the part. The same is true of Mr. Lammers, who has a pleasing voice for lighter music. The audience repaid the "Orphans" singers by thunderous outbursts of applause. The wish for a repetition of last night's concert was general. We are informed that this charitable singing society intends to repeat the concert, in the near future, for the benefit of the German hospital at the Central Music Hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
