<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-12-16">Dec. 16, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Bach Chorus Holds Well-Attended Pre-Christmas Festival</title><title level="a" type="sub">by F. W.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0584</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0584.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-12-16">Dec. 16, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO BACH CHORUS HOLDS WELL-ATTENDED PRE-CHRISTMAS FESTIVAL</title><title level="a" type="sub">by F. W.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>....The Chicago Bach Chorus, under the direction of Siegfried Prager, filled the audience in Orchestra Hall yesterday with reverence, and whoever was not already inspired by the Christmas spirit was surely made conscious of it.</p>
   <p>The Chorus and Boys' Choir, accompanied by a powerful organ and orchestra, gave, as the opening number, "Ein' feste Burg ist unser Gott". This was the first public presentation of the composition in Chicago, and many, in thought, repeated the words--"From the Great World Beyond I Came."</p>
   <p>Next came an a cappella selection, sung in perfect unison--"Thoughts of Advent"-- giving expression to the intense human longing for deliverance.....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0585.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>With well-defined motions, Conductor Prager directed the ensemble work of chorus and orchestra; the choir responded willingly, eagerly, giving its best.</p>
   <p>The "D-flat Major Fugue", played by Edwin Stanley with his usual mastery, served as a prelude to the concert.</p>
   <p>Mr. Prager led the Chicago Symphony Orchestra during the presentation of the "Brandenburg Concerto Number Three". It is to be regretted that the conductor could not be induced, despite persistent applause, to repeat even a part of the wonderful score. One longed to congratulate him and the musicians.</p>
   <p>After the choral offering, "The Heavens are Telling the Glories of God," the public remained seated, and the applause was so insistent that the director finally responded with an encore. It is my candid opinion that no one would have objected to an entire repetition of the program.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
