<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-26">Nov. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Concert of the Alpenlander Men's Chorus</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0407</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0407.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-26">Nov. 26, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERT OF THE ALPENLANDER MEN'S CHORUS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Notwithstanding the beautiful weather, and although many other organizations had greater fests of their own, the fourteenth annual fall concert of the Alpenlander Men's Chorus, held yesterday at the Lincoln Turner Hall, drew an exceedingly good attendance. A short time after the president of the organization, Herr Mathias Jeme, opened the festivities with an address, the great hall was filled to capacity, which shows how popular the organization is, in German circles.</p>
   <p>The guests were offered so much that they were all quite satisfied. The first part of the evening was filled with a particularly fine program; it was opened by the orchestra. The Alpenlander Men's Chorus next was heard in two charming folk songs, which released a great burst of applause. Miss Josephine Druml, a soprano with a beautiful and rich voice, then pleased the audience with an aria from "Samson et Dalila," and was forced by the applause to give an <pb facs="5418474_7_0408.jpg" n="2"/>encore.</p>
   <p>The La Salle Ladies' Chorus, under the direction of the talented conductor, Karl Reckzeh, sang a folk song and won so much applause that it seemed as though it would never end. The same hearty applause was accorded the Wiener-Waeldler Singing Club, which sang quite impressively under the direction of H. Steinmetz. Both groups had to give encores.</p>
   <p>Herr Joseph Lenz, a member of the Alpenlander Men's Chorus, delighted all present with his wonderful tenor voice. It may also be mentioned that Angelo Lippich, being an honorary member of the organization, was heard in a number of Viennese songs. The first part of the fest was concluded with a one-act play dealing with farm life in the mountains. Ludwig Steinacher, Frau R. Portenk, Frau J. Rahoy, Andy Pignet, Lukas Ranter, and Mathias Jeme acted in the play. It would not be right to forget to mention the director of the Alpenlander Men's Chorus, Herr Helmut Steinmetz, who conducted the program in an exceedingly skillful manner.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0409.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>After this treat for the ears, a gay ball occupied the latter part of the evening. An excellent orchestra played genuinely German dance music, thus giving all who wanted to dance ample opportunity to be entertained to their hearts' content. Excellent food and drinks were provided, and the festivities could thus hold out until the early morning hours in the best of moods.</p>
   <p>The fest committee, active in making a great success of the fest, was composed of the following: Fest president, Richard Portenk; fest secretary, Andy Pignet; fest treasurer, Joseph Heinhardt; Mathias Jeme, president of the Chorus; Lukas Ranter, secretary; Herman Scharm, Georg Krentzer, John Rahoy, Valentine Pfeifer, Konrad Schramm, Tony Glaser, Tony Mataskowith, Alex Berger, Fred Batscher, August Schubert, John Wolbart, and Fred Kader.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
