<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-07-04">July 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[The Theater]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0101</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0101.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-07-04">July 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[THE THEATER]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the third and final session of the yearly convention of the German-American Teachers Association, Prof. Oscar Burkhard of Marquette University gave the following address.</p>
   <p>The place the Anglo-Saxon race holds towards the theatre is a remnant of Puritanism. England and America are singular in this respect...</p>
   <p>The American theatre is almost exclusively a business enterprise, which offers only the temporary, and the repulsive, but not the enduring qualities. The American stage is an itinerant and a specialty stage, which excels only in specialities, the actors having been splendidly trained for his particular part.</p>
   <p>The theatre in Germany stands predominately on a higher artistic base, exerting a powerful influence on the social and intellectual life of the people, and is an expression of thought, feeling, strength, and solidarity. Such a theatre exists in almost every German city.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0102.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Two conditions aid the success of the theatre in Germany, the financial assistance of the city, and of the State government...</p>
   <p>The Stock Theatre Company signifies naturalness in control to virtuosity... It enables its drama to evaluate its worth and endeavors to educate the public in what is best and ideal, inflaming in a strong educational manner, the people, youth, and the schools.</p>
   <p>Although the establishment of such a national theatre is confronted with difficulties, yet the materialization of this idea is possible, by changing the attitude of the American people, and convincing the city and state governments, that the theatre is an educational institution and of national benefit. As a result we will have a national drama art. We must guard against the cinema theatres, who are not taking art seriously, but who exert a bad influence on public manners...</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
