<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-03">Mar. 3, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">"Paula"</title><title level="a" type="sub">Another Gala Performance of Hoechster's Theatrical Company</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0305</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.3.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-01">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0305.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II A 3 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1879-03-03">Mar. 3, 1879</date>.
<title level="a">"PAULA"</title><title level="a" type="sub">Another Gala Performance of Hoechster's Theatrical Company</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To give a just and adequate account of the performance presented by [Emil] Hoechster's company yesterday, would require considerably more time for reflection than is alloted to the reporter for a morning newspaper, and the reader will therefore not reproach the writer for his "scintillating generalities," a necessary outgrowth of the limited column space which prevents the inclusion of details.</p>
   <p>It almost seems as if Mr. Hoechster were one of those proteges of fortune, who are successfull in any venture. He promised the Germans a good German theater, and he redeemed his pledge far beyond expectations.</p>
   <p>When "Richelieu's First Duel" was given nine days ago, no one believed that the performance could be excelled, and whoever doubted the company's ability to <pb facs="5418474_7_0306.jpg" n="2"/>produce tragic works so profoundly impressive after the excellent presentation of comedies must now reproach himself for his premature judgment.</p>
   <p>No commendation can properly express the excellence of the presentation given yesterday. Verily, the play deserves the appellation of masterly. The story depicts in a virile, unforgettable manner the moral decadence in the upper strata of society which manifests itself in such magnitude throughout our mundane environment, and as a mirror of degeneracy, if names of characters were deleted, the text would readily adapt itself to all lands which claim to be imbued with the spirit of civilization.....</p>
   <p>The artists played their parts brilliantly. Most of the public's acclaim was showered upon Miss Kuhn because of the inherent nature of her part, for she depicted the villainess. Countess Hermine, and likewise because of her splendid declamation and magnificent acting. She gave a gruesome portrayal of the ruthless, unscrupulous, selfish woman who fears the loss of social prestige and subsequent degradation to poverty and resorts to flattery and threats to <pb facs="5418474_7_0307.jpg" n="3"/>maintain her position. Yet in compensation one must say that Miss Wassmann's passive delineation of her role, that of the saintly, innocent victim, was no less meritorious, convincing, and flawless. Miss Wassmann also proved herself a very capable actress in tragic presentations.</p>
   <p>Mr. Scherer as "Lorenz" gave an extraordinary presentation. His acting, his interpretation, and his mannerisms really corresponded to that of a misanthrope imbued with an insane longing for his dead daughter, and it is not an exaggeration to declare that no such characterization has ever been produced on our local German stage.....The performance was excellent and proves that Hoechster's stock company is fully qualified to present every type of play.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
