<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-11-12">November 12th, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">"Das Sangerfest"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(The Singer's Festival)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_0933</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-03">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_0933.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 1 c (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-11-12">November 12th, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">"Das Sangerfest"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(The Singer's Festival)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Central Committee of the North-American Singing Societies, arranged last night at Uhlich's Halle, corner North Clark and Kinzie Streets, a citizen's meeting, with the purpose of creating among the German population of Chicago, the necessary interest for the Song-Festival, which is to take place next year. This was especially expected, that business men, endowed with worldly goods would be present in a large number, but they have sadly disappointed us. The meeting was opened by Mr. Alfred Bucher, and Mr. William Floto, was elected chairman, and gave a sketch of the purpose of the Song Societies Festival. Mr. Oscar Schmidt was elected Secretary. In the name of the Central Committee Mr. Bucher proposed following:-To appoint a Finance Committee of 45 members, whose duty it would be, to supply the cash necessary, further, the appointment of a Press Committee whose work would be to induce the press to agitate for the forthcoming Festival, and the appointment of various other committees, whose duty would call them into action, shortly before the beginning of festivities, and finally a consultant committee of 15 members, <pb facs="5418474_7_0934.jpg" n="2"/>whose duty it should be, to make final decisions in all business matters. For the reason, that only a small number of persons have been present at this meeting, Mr. Harry Rubens proposed, to appoint a committee, for the arrangements of a second meeting, and induce every one, no matter in what capacity that he will be a participant at this festival, to be present at the meeting.</p>
   <p>After a short debate, Rubens' proposal was accepted, and the Chairman authorized to appoint a Committee. Acting upon the request of the Chairman, Mr. Hans Balatka, who is entrusted with the artistic management of the Song-Festival, gave a short sketch, as to the nature of this festival.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
