<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicagoer Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-12-06">Dec. 6, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">In the Aurora Gymnastic Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_7_1791</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-09">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-10-06">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_7_1791.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Arbeiter Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1880-12-06">Dec. 6, 1880</date>.
<title level="a">IN THE AURORA GYMNASTIC HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night an evening entertainment with dance was held, arranged by Messrs. Wolf, Leitner and Gloss.</p>
   <p>The program was exceptionally well chosen thanks to the cooperation of the entertainers; every seat in the large hall was taken and a great number of visitors had to remain standing. The playing and execution of the program in every respect was masterful. The gymnastic exercises on the horizontal bar, done by the members of the Aurora Club and the Chicago Gymnastic Club were excellent and brought much applause. Mr. Barthmann, the well known athlete, won the general admiration of the public by maniuplating the 200 pound heavy weights; also the famous club balancer, Mr. E. Leusch, showed such skill and endurance that the public applauded him widly. The zither entertainments by Messrs. Krause and Cabelli found much approval and had to be repeated before the public was satisfied. To be just, it must be stated that the most beautiful nuances of the zither play, and its soft <pb facs="5418474_7_1792.jpg" n="2"/>and agreeable vibrations were lost because of the poor acoustics of the hall. The climax of the evening was the balancing and gymnastics executed on two upright ladders by the gymnasts Leitner, Wolf and Ohnesorge with such swiftness and elegance, that the public rewarded them by an unlimited applause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
