<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-01-14">Jan. 14, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Intellectuals and the Masses of the Russian Colony</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-01-14">Jan. 14, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE INTELLECTUALS AND THE MASSES OF THE RUSSIAN COLONY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Very often one can hear complaints from us that the public is readily visiting beneficial entertainments and dances, but do not visit the evenings of finer entertainments and do not value good artists, singers, musicians and lecturers. All the fault is put on the masses, of which it is said that they are not cultured, that they are ignorant. There is a lot of sad and bitter truth in these complaints, but much of the blame for these faults of our masses is to be placed on our colony intellectuals and our progressive element. We do not speak the language of the masses; we do not come closely in touch with them; we do not try hard enough to understand the psythology of the masses. We, ourselves, spoil their tastes, we develop in them the love of showing off in polities, literature, and art. Pay attention to the undertakings of the colony. Each organization advertises, in American-like manner, its evenings with the words, "Grandiose Evening," "the famous artists," "a program unprecedented in the colony," and so forth. All advertisements, <pb facs="5423967_1_0373.jpg" n="2"/>handbills and notices regarding our undertakings are filled with such expressions. But how few of our undertakings are worthy of good criticism. A poor person from the masses visits one of the "grandiose evenings" with the "great artists" and "unprecedented program" and, not finding anything interesting, is disappointed. Next time he reads of a real grandiose evening with great artists and singers he will not go. He says, I know your grandiose and great evenings. Besides this he gets mixed up reading about something great and unprecedented; he does not know what is really grandiose and worthy of attention and what is not. Russia is justly proud of its authors, artists, composers, and folksongs, but in the colony there are seldom given artistic plays which can be understood by the people; seldom are better songs sung and worthwhile evenings arranged which harmonize with the soul of the common person. Our lecturers often speak in a language which is not understood by the masses, and often choose themes which do not touch their souls or agitate their minds. Our progressives, too, often change their opinion and go from one extreme to the other: from extreme <pb facs="5423967_1_0374.jpg" n="3"/>Bolshevism to White-Guardism, and from this to another extreme. They are excessively fractional and intolerant. All of this together creates confusion and bad taste. Judging strictly and justly, the Russian cultured classes have not much ground for complaining about the masses. In general, our masses are very sensitive. Upon learning of the famine in Russia, the "gray" masses sent much money to different committees and to Russia. The masses are lively in answering a call, and react to events in Russia. They readily fill the halls at all undertakings and generously spend money on them. At the present time many are willingly visiting the schools. The masses, in their own way, are fairly able to distinguish good artists, singers, musicians, journalists, and lecturers. Slowly, but surely, they will recognize the falsely risen celebrities, barkers, the false friends of the colony, the falsely sweet critics, praisers and covetous. It is understood that the masses understand with great difficulty the philosophy of Kant, Fichte, and Hegel, and do not understand much of the music of Wagner; do not know higher mathematics, and are not always able to analyze complicated theoretical <pb facs="5423967_1_0375.jpg" n="4"/>problems. On the other hand, our colonial masses do not stand any pretense in politics, literature and art. But with us, with rare exception, the masses are fed on incomprehensible and ununderstandable spiritual food. Is it the fault of the masses that they turn away from incomprehensibility and go to the show booths? The progressive part of the Russian colony, the proletarians and workers who are more educated, should get nearer to the masses. They should speak a language which is understood by the masses; they should penetrate into their psychology, experience, and ways of life. We all see how the masses are going to the pool rooms and saloons, but very few see how hard they are working and the conditions under which they live. Among our cultured, there are few who are sincerely devoted to the colony and the people. We have too many casual teachers and fugitives. The ground for work on cultural enlightenment is very favorable in the colony. But the work must be more ardent. The progressive elements of the colony must now use the old pass-words of <pb facs="5423967_1_0376.jpg" n="5"/>the progressive people of Russia, "To the people and near the people."</p>
   <p>Then backwardness, ignorance and bad manner will speedily begin to disappear.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
