<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1931-02-27">Feb. 27, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">A Father's Tragedy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0164</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.E.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.E.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0164.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-02-27">Feb. 27, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">A FATHER'S TRAGEDY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Fathers and mothers of my native Russia! Being deeply moved, I appeal to you in this article to pay immediate attention to this tragic question. Those who read these paragraphs should discuss this question with their friends. It is necessary to speak of this everywhere, discuss it and find a way out of this dangerous situation.</p>
   <p>One evening, on Jan. 31st, in Chicago, two sons of Russian colonists, F. Tureyko and Goncharevich, stopped a police car with the intention of robbery. The youthful robbers, who are still of school age, made a mistake and were severely punished. Mr. Tureyko's son was killed by a policeman and Mr. Goncharevic's son was seriously wounded.</p>
   <p>Since the time when the first Russian schools were founded in Chicago, Mr. F. Tureyko has been a very active worker in the educational field. He spent much time working for the Dostoyevsky Memorial School, and worked also for other schools. He attended many school conventions, participated on many committees, etc., and all this was done by F. Tureyko for the sake of his son, who is now gone, but who has left many bitter memories. Much energy and money was spent in order to make his son an honest man; but all the efforts of the father were <pb facs="5423967_1_0165.jpg" n="2"/>made in vain. His son chose the wrong road, and that road led young Tureyko toward the grave. This tragedy befell not only the father, but the mother as well. For days and nights, she sat crying, broken-hearted, lamenting the early death of her son.</p>
   <p>I chose for my article the title, "A Father's Tragedy", because of the following circumstances. During the last two or three months, F. Tureyko was stricken by many misfortunes. Some time ago he was badly injured by a car. Both of his legs were so badly injured that he was unable to walk for a long time. At the time he was in bed, his son left home, and six or seven weeks later the sick father received the terrible news of his son's death.</p>
   <p>Parents should endeavor to persuade the youth to stay at home as much as possible, in order that they may pay less attention to the unedifying influences outside. They should try and find the right kind of friends for them; and take them to scientific and useful lectures, even if they are given in the English language. Lectures are given frequently, usually on Sundays, by cultural, educational socieites, gratis, or for a very small admission charge. This will bring you and your children benefit; otherwise such tragedies as have befallen the families of F. Tureyko and Goncharevich will often occur in our Russian families.</p>
   <p>J. Raskatov.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
