<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Molodaya Rus (Young Russia)</title>,
<date when="1915-12-31">Dec. 31, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Machines and Men</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0436</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0436.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Moladaya Rus (Young Russia)</title>,
<date when="1915-12-31">Dec. 31, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">MACHINES AND MEN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Machines keep roaring, belts are hissing and whizzing; smoke, soot, and suffocating heat fill the workshop. Workers' faces are weary, but the movements of their hands are swift and rhythmical. Each one seems absorbed in profound thought, but is mechanically going on with his task. Only at rare moments, when for some reason the thud and wheeze of the machines subside, their movements slow up and their feet visibly give way under them; on their reflective faces weariness is written and, as if by common consent, from each one's breast a cough or a groan <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> Just like the soldiers who, accustomed to rigors of discipline and of necessity, keep marching on a sultry day over difficult sand roads, under the sounds of drums and group singing. Rumbling drums, rolling songs, and the foot of the soldier is <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in step with the others. Eyes blazing, chests thrust forward. But no sooner does the drumming cease than the soldier feels that his feet will not move; he has no more strength. A moment passes by and again the machines-drums are rumbling. And these iron inspirers say to the workingmen: <pb facs="5423967_1_0437.jpg" n="2"/>Boom.... boom.... boom..... We turned you into steel and iron. Be ye permeated with our sombre music, make your muscles into springs, and each movement of yours to fall in with the din. Keep turning and twisting together with the wheels, adapt your hand to our levers, become one of our component parts.... boom ... boom.... boom ...</p>
   <p>And the machines further say, You must become unfeeling, unthinking. You must forget everything which is alien to us machines. Never mind that in your souls is an unsubdued cry about an intense desire to live, to take in the glitter of the day and the glory of the fields; never mind that your heart is aching with the gloom of years spent aimlessly, aching with the impulse for freedom and with the despair over a <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> youth -pluck all this from your breasts and turn into machines. That our clang and scream may become your favorite music; a substitute for the song of the bird and the murmur of the stream; that our vibrating steel lustre may substitute the sun for you. Boom ..boom.. boom....</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0438.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Thus have machines been speaking to man from dawn to dawn day by day and year by year.</p>
   <p>But man's spirit will finally rebel against such steel palaver. Life, this multifarious, all-powerful queen, is luring the human soul by means of hosts of invisible threads. Like air and sunshine it forces its way into the dreary hones of the poor, and into the hovels of exhausted toilers, everywhere waking in them passionate desires and strivings. And there are no bounds to these desires in the human soul.</p>
   <p>In the rare free moments, away from filthy cellars and dark hovels - be that the unexpected glitter of the sun, the singing of birds, or the murmur of streams; or under the spell of a smile from wife or pale-faced child - man forgets the horrible, incessant machine lingo. The deep wrinkles are smoothed in those moments, and bliss comes to the weary soul of man.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0439.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>He repudiates the speech of steel and, seized with the joy and the wrath of life, he solemnly replies to the machines:</p>
   <p>Everything is in my power, everything is for me. I am your creator, you must wait on me...</p>
   <p>Never mind that I am chained to you like a slave - you shall not extinguish the living spirit in me. Beautiful and joyous is life! I am brimful with its joys and with struggles for it. Dead is your language - powerful and vital is the human soul!</p>
   <p>Otormsky.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
