<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-03-28">March 28, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">The Woman's Corner</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0332</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0332.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1925-03-28">March 28, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">THE WOMAN'S CORNER</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Women of the future, where are you?</p>
   <p>There are many Russian organizations in Chicago, elubs, circeles, school <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> etc. Thousands of Russians belong to these organizations. <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> of Russians ..... but not Russian women. Where are they - these <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> who received here in America equal rights? Why are the women <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> in organization such as the school societies, where they <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> with interests which are near to the heart of every <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> The answer is simple: The rights are there, but not the ability to <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> advantage of them. Society should take care that women can think, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> understand farther than the <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> limits of her family <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> one of us would but admit that the place of the housewife, <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> present conditions of life, is in the kitchen and the nursery. At the same time it is the place of the husband during the working <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> to be in the factory or the office. The question is, Would not the women <pb facs="5423967_1_0333.jpg" n="2"/>be a more conscious and sensible wife and mother if she would keep in touch with her social surroundings? Is not that why we hear so often about family dramas, different members of the family having so divergent interests as to have nothing to discuss in common when they get together. The man, against his will, has to go out to his comrades or to the club. The wife, being left all alone, bemoans her fate for being created a woman. When the woman will be a real companion to the husband, when she, together with him, will be able to take active part in the construction of the new fundamentals of life, only then would she be able to become a mother, an educator of the future useful citizens and not merely the dishwasher and laundress of the family, as it is often now the case. What is the role of women's organizations in the development of the social life of woman? Is their existence necessary?</p>
   <p>Would it not be simpler to further the joining by women of organizations already existing which consist largely of men? And this is undoubtedly the aim toward which we should strive. Nevertheless, long years of experience showed that only exceptional women have enough initiative <pb facs="5423967_1_0334.jpg" n="3"/>to be active workers in such organizations.</p>
   <p>The history of labor unions is full of such examples. Gradually when women are drawn into the work of the union, club, or society to which they belong, they gain confidence in their ability to lead the work of the organization, just as will their men comrades. Then they can enter on equal rights in these organizations. Thus we see that the organizations of women appear to be preparatory schools, a kind of step with the aid of which women climb up the platform of social life. The duty of every person (man or woman) is to help those who do not see yet the wide, clear height of the clearing horizons.</p>
   <p>Some day humanity will laugh at the conditions of life which called out the necessity of women's organizations, but now we must help with all our power toward their development.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
