<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-30">Mar. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Newspapers and Radio</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0422</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0422.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-30">Mar. 30, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">NEWSPAPERS AND RADIO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For several years, a relentless war has been going on between American newspapers and news agencies, on one side, and radio broadcasting companies, on the other. The goal of this war has been mastery of the air, or more exactly, the might to broadcast newspaper news over the radio.</p>
   <p>Powerful news agencies, such as the Associated Press and the United Press, have been leading the fight against radio stations because they fear competition. The radio listener, after listening to the news over the radio, will not buy a newspaper. The fight was a relentless one and ended in victory for the Associated Press and the members of this newsagency. A special control committee has been created and the rights of radio stations to broadcast news are strictly limited. As of March 1, 1934, the news broadcasts are limited to two a day, with no more than five minutes per broadcast. Each news item can contain no more than twenty words, and each broadcast no more than six hundred words. Besides, the news may be broadcast no earlier than nine <pb facs="5423967_1_0423.jpg" n="2"/>o'clock in the morning and no earlier than nine-thirty in the evening, that is, after the appearance of the morning and evening newspapers on the stands.</p>
   <p>The radio broadcasting companies did not accept this decision. The war continued. The fight against the strait-jacket rules and limitations was taken up by one large radio station in Boston. It refused to comply with the edict and organized a news agency of its own to gather news for transmission over the radio. The agency now functions in seven New England states and furnishes its service to eight stations.</p>
   <p>Thus it now happens that many radio stations broadcast the news irrespective of the conditions originally imposed.</p>
   <p>In their attempts to anticipate newspapers and get the news over ahead of them, the stations pay very little attention to the tastes of the radio listeners. To the latters' dismay, they very frequently interrupt musical programs and rush in with news about some sensational murder story. It is possible that <pb facs="5423967_1_0424.jpg" n="3"/>the fight will culminate in the newspapers' refusal to print the radio schedules.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
