<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>, (Russian Messenger),
<date when="1924-01-16">January 16, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Spiritual Needs of the Masses.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0369</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0369.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>RUSSKII VIESTNIK, (Russian Messenger)</title>,
<date when="1924-01-16">January 16, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE SPIRITUAL NEEDS OF THE MASSES.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Sunday, January 13th, in the Russian colony of Chicago, three big undertakings were arranged: the evening of the Independent School, the play "The Days of our Life", ("Day nashey shizni"), which was given by the Society of Technical Aid for Soviet Russia, and the Operetta, "The girl from Poltava" (Natalka Poltavka"), Besides this there were two lectures and gatherings. All the undertakings were crowded. The big West-Side Auditorium, at which the evening of the independent school took place, was packed with people which overcrowded the hall, lobbies and all corners. It was the same at Schoenhoffen Hall, where the Operetta, "The girl from Poltava", was given and at the hall of the Society of Technical Aid, where the play, "The days of our life", was presented. Almost all the people who visited those undertakings declared that if the halls were bigger, they would have been crowded in the same way. By the assurance of many who visited those undertakings it is clear that the arrangements at this time were much better than ever before.</p>
   <p>The opinions of most of the people, who visited the plays and the evening of the Independent School, are that the artists were well prepared and <pb facs="5423967_1_0370.jpg" n="2"/>that full order was observed. As it seems, the war against the unsucessful and poorly-prepared evenings and undertakings, which was started a few months ago, and which was supported by part of the colony, had its favorable effect. Besides this, the organizations have begun to think about how to provide the public with better spiritual food than before. The public, at the last meeting was well pleased by the efforts of the organization, and also visits the evenings, plays and lectures, more readily than before. In this change of the masses we see an evident confirmation of what we repeatedly have been writing in the paper. The masses of the Russian colony readily visit the evenings and other undertakings; if they can receive there the necessary satisfaction. The question about the extent to which the public visits the colony gatherings, depends to a great extent on the colony organizations. The more attractive those undertakings become, the more the public will attend them. On the contrary, the more superior, the poorer the attendance must be. We must make great efforts, in order to elevate the undertakings of the colony to the necessary heighth. Our masses are in great need of the inspiration; of good music, plays, operettas, lectures and so forth. If we will give them all this they certainly will gather in force at their meetings. One should keep in mind that our public has had very little chance to see and hear any thing good and its spiritual <pb facs="5423967_1_0371.jpg" n="3"/>hunger is particularly keen. We must satisfy this need to the best of our ability.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
