<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Staric, Yakov. <title>A History of the Industrial Workers of the World</title>. Chicago: Executive Committee, Russian Section, I. W. W.,
<date when="1921">1921</date>, pp. 183-4

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0472</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0472.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Staric, Yakov. <title>A History of the Industrial Workers of the World</title>. Chicago: Executive Committee, Russian Section, I. W. W.,
<date when="1921">1921</date>, pp. 183-4
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Union of Russian Workers was considered by the Industrialists a friendly organization. In like manner, the Industrial Workers of the World were regarded by the Union of Russian Workers as the standard bearers of the aims of the American workers. The mutual sympathy of both organizations led to the following:</p>
   <p>At the Cleveland convention of the Union of Russian Workers a resolution was passed, recommending that the members of the Union of Russian Workers join the Industrial Workers of the World, and vice versa.</p>
   <p>But the actual acquaintance of the Russian workers with the ideals of the Industrial Workers of the World began in the fall of 1915, when for the first time there appeared on the American continent a newspaper in the Russian language of the Industrial Workers of the World, Rabochaya Rietch.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0473.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The pioneering publishers of the newspaper, as well as the persons occupied with the dissemination of ideas of the Industrial Workers of the World among the Russian workers' colony, were comrades who lived in the East - in the field of decisive battles of the Industrial Workers of the World with the plutocrats, and who were aided by some syndicalists of the West.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
