<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-22">Feb. 22, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Right Versus Might</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0629</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0629.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-22">Feb. 22, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">RIGHT VERSUS MIGHT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since the World War and the revolutions in various countries a deep change has taken place in the consciences of people. Formerly morality played the leading role in human relationships but now morality is being supplanted by force. At present many people consider morality an antiquated prejudice and recognize law only insofar as it can yield them advantages of one kind or another, and if it does not yield such advantages, they disregard it altogether.</p>
   <p>This condition one can observe not only in the life of the people of any particular nationality but in international intercourse as well. Clear testimony to substantiate this is found in the fact that individuals, governments, and whole nations fail to fulfill their obligations or to observe any agreements or pacts. As a result, agreements signed only yesterday have today become scraps of paper.</p>
   <p>All this has brought it about that nobody believes anybody, and nobody attaches any importance to the promises given by anybody else or even by himself.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0630.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since the war, as we know, many international conferences have been called together, and numerous agreements have been signed, but they have all proved to be soap bubbles. At present also various agreements are being signed, and they again will turn out to be more bubbles. Public men and "statesmen" now openly defy morality and right and recognize only the law of might.</p>
   <p>Of all this the unavoidable inference is that humankind is degenerating spiritually and is approaching the moral status of the wild beast. People are reduced to this condition largely by certain dictators and by political parties which adhere to the Jesuit maxim:</p>
   <p>"The end always justifies the means."</p>
   <p>The chief enemies and despoilers of the old European culture founded on right and morality are of course the Bolsheviks and the Fascists. Both these parties destroy freedom,reject "decaying "liberalism, and substitute for them their bloody dictatorships. One may truly say that all past and present dictators, <pb facs="5423967_1_0631.jpg" n="3"/>as well as many politicians, adventurers, and demagogues should be in insane asylums, and yet, instead of that, they continue to play an important part in modern life and gradually reduce the people to the state of wild animals ready to cut one another's throats; and some of the European public men and writers are, it seems, not talking idly when they speak of the twilight of European culture. H. G. Wells, the well-known English novelist, has even gone so far as to describe the coming war and the shocking consequences of it, with the devastation and total ruin of civilization, and the people of Europe, those who survive turning into savages.</p>
   <p>However, we still cling to the hope that the impending catastrophe will be warded off by the concerted efforts of cultured and freedom-loving people.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
