<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-02-09">Feb. 9, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Plans and Deeds</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0359</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0359.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-02-09">Feb. 9, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">PLANS AND DEEDS</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As soon as a new organization appears in the Russian colony of America, it immediately sets forth 'grandiose' plans. Upon getting acquainted with these plans, one involuntarily thinks of the flight of a hawk, the swing upwards of an eagle - if the organization indeed would raise itself to the top. Alas! many of them soon let down their wings and, encountering impediments on the sinning earth, they, too, soon drop to the ground. Rude reality cuts under their wings.</p>
   <p>A new organization appears with all its comprehensive plans; the attention of the Russian coleny is attracted; plans are offered for many cultural institutions of 'grandiese' help to Russia and to the colony; money collections are proposed. In short, a revolution of its kind. Such organizations do not strive for small things, and they cannot reach the big things on account of the implacable laws of the existence of our coleny. And then the end ... We possess the good impulses, but are unable to fulfill them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0360.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>There are many such organizations in different cities of the United States. The Russian papers continually inform about their appearance or disappearance. In this lies our great woe. We have few schools, few libraries, few of our own corners where we could gather,and a small number of good teachers. Our organizations, with the exception of one or two, are weak. We have not a center where we may gather for protection in time of misfortune, sickness or insult. If each of these organizations would set out to fulfill one of these little deeds, giving up the carrying out of 'grandicse' plans, then we would be sooner stronger and richer. Again and again one has to repeat that our power is split and separated. We cannot unite or make a capable and unifying call to the colony; we cannot flow as a living stream into the monotonous life of our colony.</p>
   <p>If we put our will, if we make an energetic effort to accomplish little things, then we will find so many means, people, and possibilities that they will surpass all of our dreams. We will find a living answer to our call from all the colony; we will awaken it <pb facs="5423967_1_0361.jpg" n="3"/>to a life worthwhile, because when the members of the colony see and feel a necessity, they are always ready generously to give their work and money.</p>
   <p>It is the fault of the organizations that they cannot take advantage of it. So let us get busy with the little things: the schools, libraries, with strengthening useful organizations. We shall then be able to do a lot and be successful.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
