<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-01-09">Jan. 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">Necessity of Just Self-Criticism</title><title level="a" type="sub">(With reference to the article by A. G. Alekseev) by A. V. Kravchuk</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0263</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0263.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-01-09">Jan. 9, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">NECESSITY OF JUST SELF-CRITICISM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(With reference to the article by A. G. Alekseev) by A. V. Kravchuk</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"To know the universe enriching us, it is necessary first to know ourselves," said L. N. Tolstoy, the great writer and philosopher of Russia. A. G. Alekseev, in his article printed in Rassviet, on December 27, correctly stated: "The difficulty does not arise from the fact that we have several organizations instead of one, or because we have five or ten newspapers instead of one. The trouble lies within these organizations which do not have a wholesome social life because they do not fix our attention upon the great questions and problems of the contemporary era; because they do not invite us to participate actively in the workers movements."</p>
   <p>Really, the root of the evil is not accounted for by the great number of Russian newspapers or by the existence of several organizations, members of which, at almost every step, are workers. The evil lies within those who are trying <pb facs="5423967_1_0264.jpg" n="2"/>to create so many big organizations or newspapers. But the main root of evil lies in the ignorance of our leaders, and often in their betrayal of the Russian colony.</p>
   <p>It is understood that only one who was on an intellectually low level, would be permitted to state in public, at an assembly, such a phrase as: "We do not need Rubakin". For forty-five years N. Rubakin has worked for the enlightenment of the working people. Hundreds of thousands have received their education thanks to the system of N. Rubakin.</p>
   <p>The central committee of the organization, ROOV, Russkoe Ob'edinennoe Obshchestvo Vzaimopomoshchi (Russian Consolidated Mutual Aid Society) headed by N. Rubakin, intends to prepare a catalogue to assist self-education among the Russian people in America, but when at the assembly of the ROOV a report was submitted, showing what benefit the catalogue of N. Rubakin on self-enlightenment would bring, one of the delegates arose and asked: "Will we get <pb facs="5423967_1_0265.jpg" n="3"/>more money from it ? Naturally such an expression hurt those persons who participated eagerly and earnestly in cultural and educational activities for the benefit of the colony very deeply, because nobody thought of protesting or objecting to the question. But we have several such examples.</p>
   <p>The matter of foremost importance was pushed aside. The cultural and educational work has been crippled. The newspaper Rassviet, as the organ of the cultural and educational organizations, which defends and protests our interests, is read by only a few of all those who claim to be leaders. No projects, even though they may be vitally important, receive mass support, and very often expire.</p>
   <p>Therefore we need just self-criticism. But before we start to do anything we must first educate ourselves. We must learn to respect others, to discover sincerity in conversation, in debates, in books. We have considerable time <pb facs="5423967_1_0266.jpg" n="4"/>for this purpose, and no one will disturb us. Even though our material circumstances are not enviable, still in comparison with other countries, we have every opportunity to begin self-education. For one, the articles of A. G. Alekseev in which he touches many vital questions provocative to all of us, need very serious consideration.</p>
   <p>I, myself, do not quite agree with A. G. Alekseev in everything, but I absolutely support his practical opinion and judgment of life, and for this reason, I salute such an honest social worker as A. G. Alekseev.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
