<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title>,
<date when="1919-06-27">June 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Life and its Problems</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0456</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0456.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya, (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1919-06-27">June 27, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">LIFE AND ITS PROBLEMS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The World War created the all powerful Big Four.</p>
   <p>When Japan is invited to participate in discussions on international imperialism, then the Big Four is changed into the Big Five.</p>
   <p>While these Big Four or Big Five are bestowing lands, populated by millions of people, to crowned and uncrowned rulers, we here have in America at work, or about to be at work, the Laborers' Four. There are no kings, emperors, or millionaires among them. The one bad thing about them is that they are divided.</p>
   <p>Capitalist-Republicans can sit together at the same table with kings, lords, and barons, determining the fate of countries populated by many millions of people. Just so, the now divided workers' organizations could realize their ideals and solve their problems better, if they too learned to sit at one table.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0457.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Under the American Laborer's Four I mean organizations, which are fighting capitalism politically and economically.</p>
   <p>These organizations are: The Socialist party, The Socialist Labor party, Industrial Workers of the World, and The American Federation of Labor with its allied organizations.</p>
   <p>Let the reader not get frightened at the fact that I'm mentioning the conservative Federation of Labor. This purely labor organization is as yet not sufficiently revolutionary only because the revolutionary element fights shy of its ranks.</p>
   <p>If this is not a crime before the political and social revolution I don't know what is.</p>
   <p>The American Federation of Labor is almost virgin land for socialist- revolutionary activity. The heads of this enormous organization have <pb facs="5423967_1_0458.jpg" n="3"/> barricaded themselves with the capitalistic press.</p>
   <p>If you wish to know the truth, it is that capitalism in America finds more support in the American Federation of Labor than in anything else, and nothing is so precious to capitalism as the A. F. of L.</p>
   <p>The rational attitude towards this organization is not to ignore it, but to enter its ranks, and, having affiliated yourselves with the various other organizations, to declare a political war, through concerted action, on the capitalistic parties. And what a comfort it would be to greet an American Laborers' Four: The Socialist party, The Socialist Labor Party, The Industrial Workers of the World, The American Federation of Labor and its affiliates.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
