<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-01-11">Jan. 11, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Political Prisoners in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0665</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0665.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-01-11">Jan. 11, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">POLITICAL PRISONERS IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An old Russian adage says, "Make a fool kneel in prayer, and he will break his skull". The same can be said of those who are connected with the Novy Mir [Translator's note: A Bolshevik newspaper published in New York]. Those who are determining the policy of this Communist sheet obviously do not believe either in the world revolution or Socialism but, being obedient to those who hired them, live up to the demands made of them by the higherups, and in doing that quite often crack their skulls when the flunkeys get over-zealous.</p>
   <p>These political businessmen, orally and in print, carry on "a relentless fight against capitalism," but quite frequently they strike not their enemies but themselves.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0666.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Thus, for instance, in the latter part of December the Novy Mir printed a list of political prisoners in America compiled by the International Labor Defense. A sensible Bolshevik, using his common sense, would never make the list public,but the Bolshevik half-wits have not only printed the names and the charges against the men but, in their issue of December 23, wrote an editorial under the title "Prisoners of Capital".</p>
   <p>In printing the list, the Bolsheviks fighting capitalism only by word of mouth gave a good weapon into the hands of their enemy. This was done because the International Labor Defense, even though it frequently includes the names of those who have had nothing to do with political offenses, could find in capitalist America only ninety-three political prisoners. This number they find in a capitalist country, which, according to Bolshevik assertions, strive to strangle the labor movement.</p>
   <p>If the Bolsheviks from Novy Mir could prove that there are only ninety-three <pb facs="5423967_1_0667.jpg" n="3"/>political offenders in the U.S.S.R. and hundreds of thousands in capitalist America, they really could deliver a very painful blow to their enemies. But when political prisoners in the U.S.S.R. are counted by hundreds of thousands and in America there are only ninety-three, and the Bolsheviks of Novy Mir betray the fact, a good service is rendered to the capitalists. The list of political prisoners printed by the Bolsheviks acts like a boomerang; it cracks the skulls of Communist leaders of Novy Mir and not those of the capitalists.</p>
   <p>It is possible that the editorial offices of Novy Mir are occupied not by half-witted followers of Stalin, but by some members of his opposition group who deliberately try to hamstring Stalin and the Communist International in their "business" of inflaming a world revolution, for after reading such an "indictment" against capitalists even the most backward of readers of the Bolshevik paper may come to the conclusion that in their "Socialist fatherland" far worse repressions and outrages are practiced than in the <pb facs="5423967_1_0668.jpg" n="4"/>most reactionary capitalist countries, to say nothing of the United States.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
