<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-13">Apr. 13, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Decrease in Productiveness of Labor</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0608</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0608.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-13">Apr. 13, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">DECREASE IN PRODUCTIVENESS OF LABOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Soviet newspapers are full of reports to the effect that the new speedup system of production has failed to attain the results for which it was introduced, and that in many Soviet establishments the workers' productiveness is falling far short of the mark set by the new schedules. As a result of a survey made of the steel mills it became known that in twenty-two metallurgical plants covered by the study there had not been any noticeable increase in the productiveness of labor since the new quotas were put into effect. Of all the plants in the survey three mills showed an increase of 2.9 per cent; ten plants showed no improvement, and ten mills actually decreased their output from four to six per cent. The "decade of speedup" inaugurated in Leningrad <pb facs="5423967_1_0609.jpg" n="2"/>has so far yielded no results, and the productiveness of labor still remains at a low level. The same situation exists in the Donetz coal region, where miners have not shown any increase in production.</p>
   <p>This general lag in production has been followed by a mass discharge of technical personnel and officials by the overseeing committees of the Communist party for laxity in supervision and other faults. The managerial and supervising staffs are being accused of neglect of duty and of tampering with the new speedup system itself. From many places reports come that the new system of production is being discarded as not at all suitable or applicable. In other places it exists only on paper, and the work proceeds as of old. Thus we see that the results of the new speedup effort have proved lamentably small.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
