<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1922-09-06">Sept. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">Change of Season</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0066</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0066.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1922-09-06">Sept. 6, 1922</date>.
<title level="a">CHANGE OF SEASON</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Beautiful summer is gone. And gone is the season of languor and indolence.</p>
   <p>The bells of numerous Chicago schools imperiously proclaim that children get ready for school!</p>
   <p>Hundreds of thousands of children of all ages, some willingly, others unwillingly; have resumed their studies.</p>
   <p>Whistles, little boxes, balls, tops, all these were flung to one side. One cannot afford to think now of grasshoppers, butterflies, hikes to parks, or to be strolling about. One has to study now.</p>
   <p>It is time that also adults give thought to studies.</p>
   <p>All schools and all clubs were closed for the summer months. There were <pb facs="5423967_1_0067.jpg" n="2"/>no school session nor any other activity in the colony during the summer months, and the none-too-active life of our colony came to a complete standstill.</p>
   <p>Now, however, it is time to think of classes, lectures, affairs.</p>
   <p>Much could be said on this matter.</p>
   <p>Frankly speaking, only an insignificant number of Russians living in Chicago can speak English, while an overwhelming majority practically does not speak it at all.</p>
   <p>The fever about going to Russia has subsided for the time being. Why then not think seriously about attending classes in English? There are many. We have them in every section of the city. They are evening classes, and they are free.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0068.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Honest to God, they are a convenience, and by spending one hour an evening in school, one may learn to speak and write English to some extent in a few months.</p>
   <p>This is a great deal. Is not this better than wandering about in a strange land without a tongue, and, coming into a store, being obliged to point with your finger at the merchandise instead of calling for it by its name?</p>
   <p>However little one may learn, it will still come in handy, either here or in the event of going back home, also there. Besides, so many of us have lived here dozens of years but have not learned to speak a single word of English.</p>
   <p>So much for the English language.</p>
   <p>And now, how does it stand with us with regard to our own native <pb facs="5423967_1_0069.jpg" n="4"/>language?</p>
   <p>Are there not quite a few among us who cannot write their name correctly, and can read only by syllables, to say nothing about knowing the most elementary rules of the Russian language? The majority knows nothing of this.</p>
   <p>Why not attend the Russian schools?</p>
   <p>There are so many now.</p>
   <p>Would it not be better to know one's own language than not to know it?</p>
   <p>It would be well to think it over, so that all our endeavors for meetings and lectures be of greater benefit.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0070.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In the recent past all this has been done very poorly, carelessly, and at random.</p>
   <p>Soon autumn will come, and then winter. Let's work some.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
