<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1931-10-20">Oct. 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">"Help in the Name of Christ."</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0558</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.F.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0558.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-10-20">Oct. 20, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">"HELP IN THE NAME OF CHRIST."</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Hoover, in his radio speech the day before yesterday, at Old Point Comfort, Va., appealed to the kind-hearted Americans for Donations and aid to the millions of unemployed who are doomed to hunger and privation due to the economic and industrial crisis.</p>
   <p>The main point of the president's address could be summed up in the following words: "In the name of Christ, give a penny for the unemployed." At the time when millions of unemployed and their families were threatened by starvation, President Hoover could undertake no stronger action to relieve their destiny, than to appeal to the Christian feelings of the rich, who robbed those who at present are in need of aid...</p>
   <p>However, it is doubtful, whether with the old, long forgotten Christian doctrine, it will be possible to soften the hard-heartedness of the capitalists, whose entire meaning of life is based on making profits, and enriching themselves. In the United States there are many millionaires, but no one bears of any one of them, who, prompted by Christian impulse, would part with his millions and donate <pb facs="5423967_1_0559.jpg" n="2"/> them toward aiding the unemployed.</p>
   <p>The policy of the Hoover administration on the question of aiding the unemployed, leads, as is known, to entrusting such aid to individual charity, thus releasing the rich from the forced obligation of helping the poor. Some donated, but the poor received only the crumbs. And that did not measure up to the real needs of the unemployed.</p>
   <p>If Hoover really desired to help the unemployed, he should have compelled, by means of legislation, the very wealthy people to donate a certain sum of money towards a government insurance fund for the unemployed. Only in this manner would it be possible to force the rich to take a hand in helping the unemployed.</p>
   <p>The plea to be merciful will not affect them. The United States is a sufficiently rich country and therefore there is no need for the existence of hungry and needy people. If we happen to observe the contrary, then the blame for this should fall entirely on the rich class and the government who avoid the fulfillment of their duties under various pretenses.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
