<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-07-31">July 31, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">Crises and Unemployment, and the Means of Getting Rid of Them</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Written for a contest)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0562</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0562.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1931-07-31">July 31, 1931</date>.
<title level="a">CRISES AND UNEMPLOYMENT, AND THE MEANS OF GETTING RID OF THEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Written for a contest)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The contest organized by the editors of Rassviet for the writing of the best article on the subject, "Why do industrial crises and unemployment exist and by what means can they be liquidated?" is very timely indeed, and responds thoroughly to the social interests of the toiling people. We are living through a time when, aside from the revaluation of spiritual accomplishments, many of the material things are also being weighed and means are sought for the re-establishment of a very shaky social equilibrium. Ideas and spiritual aspirations of the people are thrown on one pan of the scale while material benefits and a full belly are put on the other, and the latter outweighs the former. For, no matter how great or good are the ideas in themselves, it must be admitted that material and economic phases of life are the basis of all the complex and multiform human existence.</p>
   <p>Properly speaking, the subject-matter of the theme should be divided into two parts, namely: crises and unemployment, on one side, and <pb facs="5423967_1_0563.jpg" n="2"/>means of getting rid of them, on the other. But due to the close organic connection between crises and unemployment joining them into one subject is permitted, the more so because the problem of crises and unemployment belongs to the class of "social ills," and for every ailment a certain course of treatment is always prescribed.</p>
   <p>Every social development must be viewed through the prism of cause and effect. Why do crises and unemployment occur? Let us attempt to find an answer to this question.... Quite slowly, but persistently and laboriously, the human mind worked at numerous inventions, which helped him gradually to overcome and conquer the blind forces of nature. Many generations of humans assiduously worked at the development and improvement of various means and approaches to handling manual tasks. And at present we have reached at last a stage of such perfection in life that mankind no longer should fear hunger and its unavoidable concomitants, sickness and death. Human inter-connection, inter-communication between different parts of the globe have been improved to such an extent that we , for instance, may obtain the best food from the most distant parts of the earth without any deterioration in the course of transportation. Besides, there is sufficiency, nay, abundance of victuals of every kind in every part <pb facs="5423967_1_0564.jpg" n="3"/>of the globe. And it would seem that none of us should suffer for lack of food. A cruel reality, however, decrees otherwise, for there are thirty-five million unemployed and hungry people at present. In the United States alone there are, according to the estimates made, around eight million unemployed, and as many people work only two or three days a week. And the number of people being thrown out of factories and mills grows hourly.</p>
   <p>The industrial crises and the unemployment that follows are not at all new developments in our social life. Prior to the development of machine production and modern technique the industrial slack was caused largely by two factors: abundance of manual labor (the supply exceeded the demand) and relative over-production, viz., abundance of the goods produced. At the present time to these two causes a third one is added, a factor of considerable significance, one that has a purely technical aspect. In other words, the introduction of new improved machinery, installed in many factories, works and workshops, is the third factor in working toward producing the present economic crisis.</p>
   <p>Being a technical one this crisis augurs grave consequences: continuous <pb facs="5423967_1_0565.jpg" n="4"/>improvements in the technical processes reduce the application of human labor to a minimum. The main causes are: over-abundance of workers, overproduction and technical improvements along with other contributory factors of lesser importance have produced the industrial crisis and concomitant unemployment.</p>
   <p>As social developments crises and unemployment occur periodically-almost every six or seven years, and each industrially developed country is faced with a difficult task of solving the problem: what means should be employed in order to put an end to the intolerable situation? The United States of America are not an exception in this case, for in this industrially highly developed country the crises are of quite frequent occurrence.</p>
   <p>After the crises of 1907-1914 came those of 1921-1928, and now we are living through the latest one and the most severe, which brought about mass unemployment among the American workers. During the last few years the American workers have produced such a mass of goods, such over-abundance of food stuffs that they will have to wait for a long time before the consumption of products reaches its minimum, in order <pb facs="5423967_1_0566.jpg" n="5"/>that they may again be put to work to be thrown out again on the street by a new impending crisis. The miserable, disastrous condition of the American workers is aggravated by the fact that the American government considers unemployment insurance for the workers as something unnecessary and even as an illegal measure. It is quite opposed to taking any kind of steps (except charity) to relieve the wide-spread unemployment as well as hunger, privations and sufferings of the people that go with it.</p>
   <p>Under such critical circumstances two questions confront us: What means should be employed to relieve the crisis and unemployment? And is it possible to get rid of these evils? .....</p>
   <p>We must produce less. We must reduce the working hours and increase the wages. While receiving higher pay workers will be able to buy more, for workers are not only producers, they are consumers as well. By reducing the hours of work we give for the unemployed a chance to get some employment. With the present degree of technical development workers work too many hours. Machines displace more and more human labor, and workers should gradually be relieved of hard work and given a chance to develop <pb facs="5423967_1_0567.jpg" n="6"/>mentally. This is required by the general interests of modern economic life: unemployment goes hand in hand with the development and improvement of technical processes. Simultaneously with technical development we must reduce the working hours. Together with this we must also strive to unite and organize the scattered forces of the unemployed. We must create powerful labor unions in such a way that they would permit workers to enjoy the right of being employed, carrying this right further, toward complete control over industry. This will give every worker opportunity to obtain employment, and, consequently, to be fed and sheltered.</p>
   <p>By producing less goods and by working fewer hours and alloting as far as possible, work to every one we may relieve the pressure of unemployment and alleviate the misery and suffering connected with it.....</p>
   <p>It is necessary at present for those unemployed to be well fed, shod, and in general to live in conditions fit for human beings; and the only correct and practical step in this direction is make several minimum demands connected with the everyday life of the workers demands for measures that could really help them. Let all those that are unemployed or <gap unit="words" extent="unk" reason="illegible"/> organize and by united <pb facs="5423967_1_0568.jpg" n="7"/>effort carry on a campaign for the granting of the following demands:</p>
   <p>Insurance from unemployment, the cost of such insurance to be covered by the government and the employers.</p>
   <p>Establishment of a 6-hour work-day and 30-hour week, without reduction in wages.</p>
   <p>Increase in wages. Supplying work to all those employed who are most in need of relief.</p>
   <p>Recognition of the workers' right to organize and strike.</p>
   <p>Only thus will it be possible to do away with the crisis and unemployment and to achieve a real improvement of the position of the working people. Loengrin.</p>
   <p>[Note: The Author of this article received the first prize in the contest. His article, in the judgment of the editors of Rassviet, was one of the <pb facs="5423967_1_0569.jpg" n="8"/>best on the subject of the "Crisis and Unemployment." Ten articles written on the same subject were submitted and published in the paper under their author's names. Loegrin's article has been abbreviated by half, but the essential parts of it have been preserved. All important and essential features were retained with all their clarity of the author's opinion and point of view of the problem involved. N. Korecki.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
