<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-04">Mar. 4, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Bootleg Trade Is Thriving</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0126</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0126.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-04">Mar. 4, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE BOOTLEG TRADE IS THRIVING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to official data, during the second half of last year Federal tax inspectors discovered about six thousand illegal stills within the continental territory of the United States. The total cost of the equipment found is appraised at $2,500,000. During the same period the customhouse and coast guard officials captured one airplane, more than 150 automobiles, and over 20 vessels engaged in illegal liquor traffic and smuggling.</p>
   <p>By repealing the "dry" law the United States government hoped to put an end to the illicit trade in alcoholic drinks and the contraband business connected with it. Receipts from taxes on alcoholic drinks have actually proved to be smaller than expected. And the smugglers are still thriving as before, even though their number has been considerably reduced. Americans prefer contraband goods because they are cheaper.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0127.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Recently, an article by D. Young on the activities of smugglers was featured in the New York Times. The picture presented by the author is as follows:</p>
   <p>In the Atlantic Ocean, in close proximity to the shores of Newfoundland, there are two tiny islands belonging to France--Saint Pierre and Miquelon--the nearest French possessions to the United States. During the time the "dry" law was in force in the United States, the island of Saint Pierre became an immense liquor storehouse; rum, wines, and whiskeys were transshipped in a continuous stream across the island and forwarded to the Atlantic seaboard of the United States. From its very inception this bootlegging trade was organized on a large scale, in true American style. Large syndicates were formed with solid financial backing and not without influential connections with the proper government agencies. These syndicates established quite imposing enterprises with well-known trade marks.</p>
   <p>Despite the repeal of the "dry" law these syndicates continue in existence. Today, just as before Repeal, coast guard cutters are busy every night in the bays, the ports, and even the small inlets in search of smugglers. From time to time <pb facs="5423967_1_0128.jpg" n="3"/>some small schooner falls into the hands of the inspectors. A great majority of the vessels carry on their traffic undetected, for the reason that the powerful bootleggers' syndicates have maintained their own well-organized counter-espionage along the coast. They have their own short-wave radio stations. The vessels loaded with contraband keep in constant touch with the lookouts on shore...and receive timely warnings of impending dangers. The bootleggers have their own code, while the revenue officers have theirs. Both sides endeavor to intercept each other's coded message transmitted over the radio.</p>
   <p>In conclusion, Young writes that even the concerted efforts of the revenue officials, the coast guard, and numerous other government agencies would not force the bootleggers to quit their illegal trade. Side by side with the contraband trade, the illicit manufacture of alcohol continues. Most of the consumers of this product are poor people, since the stuff is sold at a very low price. All this shows that the repeal of the "dry" law has not destroyed the bootlegger.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
