<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-03-03">Mar. 3, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">The Growth of Unemployment</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0527</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0527.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-03-03">Mar. 3, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">THE GROWTH OF UNEMPLOYMENT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to data recently provided by the American Federation of Labor the number of unemployed persons is again increasing. In January of the current year there were 12,626,000 idle persons. In comparison with December of last year the number of the unemployed had increased by 1,229,000 toward the end of January. In its statement the Federation declares that rise in unemployment is a seasonal development in January, but this year this increase is larger than it was last year and much larger than usual. For instance, last year in the same month the number of unemployed increased only 699,000, about half this year's increase.</p>
   <p>The Federation considers that the new rise in unemployment may partly be <pb facs="5423967_1_0528.jpg" n="2"/>explained by the lengthening of the work week that followed the abolition of N. R. A. From July through December the work week in the principal industries had been lengthened on the average by three hours. The other important factor tending to increase unemployment is the contraction that is taking place in production and trade. After the Christmas holidays this year the number of employees laid off was larger than last year by 50,000, and in farming it was 68,000 greater.</p>
   <p>One should also take note of the fact that out of 12,626,000 unemployed 3,672,000 men were engaged on public works in the month of January. They are included in the total of unemployed persons because public works give only temporary employment. This kind of work will be continued only as long as the funds appropriated for the purpose last. When the money has been spent, the Government will be confronted with the problem of finding new means to continue these jobs; [if it cannot continue them, it must] put the unemployed on direct <pb facs="5423967_1_0529.jpg" n="3"/>relief. Whatever is done, the Government will have to take care of the unemployed in some way if they do not find work in private enterprises.</p>
   <p>With the growth of unemployment the expense will increase of alleviating the condition of those who are idle. Even now Government expenditures for this purpose are reaching totals unprecedented in the history of this country. According to Mr. Staplin, head of the League of American Taxpayers, the expenditures of federal, State, and city governments now exceed the expenditures of the entire population of the country for food, clothing, and shelter, almost by 650 million dollars a year. In 1934 the country's population paid nearly ten billion dollars in taxes, and the expenditures of all governments exceeded fifteen billion dollars. The deficit was made up by borrowing money. As a result the indebtedness of the federal, State, and municipal governments grows from year to year.</p>
   <p>In the current year taxes will undoubtedly be raised still higher. The other <pb facs="5423967_1_0530.jpg" n="4"/>day President Roosevelt himself declared that in connection with the payment of veterans' bonuses alone the Congress will have to raise an additional billion and a half. Besides, money has to be found for unemployment relief and for the continuation of the public works programs. These expenditures also will force the Government to make the taxes still higher.</p>
   <p>All this indicates that economic conditions in the country continue to grow worse. By summer and fall, in connection with the approaching elections, conditions in all probability will grow worse still.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
