<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
      <title>Svobodnaya Rossiya</title>
      <date when="1923-10-18">October 18, 1923</date>
      <title level="a">Five Years</title>
     </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0064</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0064.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
     <title>Free Russia (Svobodnaya Rossiya)</title>
     <date when="1923-10-18">October 18, 1923</date>
     <title level="a">FIVE YEARS</title>
    </bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Five years have passed from the time that the residents of the south side energetically and devotedly, undertook the organization of their school. Work, effort, care and faith in the wonderful cultural enlightenment undertaking were not in varn. The south side school is worthy of the south side workers, and these workers deserve their school of which not only they, but all the local colony, can be proud. And there is really something of which to be proud. During the evening if you visit Morgan street, you no doubt will be interested in the very loud noise of children, from whence this exceptional apparition. There is heard a wonderful swan' like native Russian speech. And a thought is born in your mind, that there is a Russian school around. Yes this is right! A big red building. Just like a swarm of bees under the hum of the meledious sounds, so rushes the young generation after studies at the English school, again to its own native Russian school. But reader, we are going further, inside the school at the classes, where at 5:00 p.m. sharp, the studies are beginning. All around is silence. Why, you ask involuntarily? This was introduced here during the last year for exemplary discipline, thanks to which the studies are more successful. There are almost 200 children, but the order is excellent. Even the Americans, who visit rarely, are surprised with the able arrangement of this undertaking. Everybody here feels right, the students, who acquire knowledge and the parents, who after the days of hard work rush to the school <pb facs="5423967_1_0065.jpg" n="2"/>for conversation on the last events in politics, the news received from Russia, how the work is going, and on everything concerning the life of the workers. And one can feel that the south side school is the second family fire-place. New the south side school is occupying the first place, not only in Chicago but in the whole United States, because this school is a prepagator of culture and progress in its native language, both among young students and among adults. At the same time this school is also, in part, a People's House on the south side.</p>
   <p>Morozov.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
