<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1926-10-06">Oct. 6, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Concerning the Program of the American Federation of Labor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0444</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-12">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-09">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0444.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1926-10-06">Oct. 6, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">CONCERNING THE PROGRAM OF THE AMERICAN FEDERATION OF LABOR</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>This editorial contains a criticism, of the program of the A. F. of L., adopted by its 46th Annual Convention in Detroit. The only really new point in this program was practically the proclamation of a campaign in favor of the five hour day.</p>
   <p>As to the first aim of the A. F. of L., the struggle against the use of non-union labor, the editorial points out that this aim could hardly be achieved by the A. F. of L. as this organization could not hope to enlist all the American workmen. Its membership at that time, had, on the contrary, de-creased from about 5,000,000 to somewhat less than 3,000,000.</p>
   <p>As to the struggle against child labor, that also, though carried on for a long time, had not given any appreciable results. At the time the editorial <pb facs="5423967_1_0445.jpg" n="2"/>was written there were working in industrial enterprises over a million children under the age of fifteen. The struggle of the A. F. of L. is very commendable, but this organization fails to see that child labor can hardly be abolished by the efforts of any labor union while the parents of the children, owing to existing conditions, do not earn sufficient money to get a decent living.</p>
   <p>The third aim of the A. F. of L. is "to encourage the cooperation of workmen and employers" in an effort to lower the prices of the most necessary commodities. The author of the editorial remarks that the employers cannot be interested in the lowering of these prices, because as a class they are, on the contrary, interested in selling their goods at the highest price obtainable.</p>
   <p>The editorial also points out that the A. F. of L. justly denounce the activities of the communist dictatorship in Russia, as harmful to the interests of <pb facs="5423967_1_0446.jpg" n="3"/>the working class, yet fails to denounce the no less harmful activities of the fascist dictatorships.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
