<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1923-06-02">June 2, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">Indifference to Our Own</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0382</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0382.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I A 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Svobodnaya Rossiya (Free Russia)</title>,
<date when="1923-06-02">June 2, 1923</date>.
<title level="a">INDIFFERENCE TO OUR OWN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the old times in Russia there was a strong gravitation to everything foreign. There was a preference for everything from foreign countries. We even used to prefer matches from Sweden.</p>
   <p>As to our own, no matter how good it was, many regarded it with disdain; many did not value their own.</p>
   <p>During the last twenty years all this has been considerably changed. Russia has valued its own at its worth, and (has) begun to regard its science, art, and inventions with due respect.</p>
   <p>But the Russian-American colony has maintained this old custom. We are here extremely indifferent to all of our own. There were recently in Chicago many prominent representatives of Russian art - F. I. Shalyapin was here; the Art Theatre; the troupe of Mary Kusnietzov; the Russian <pb facs="5423967_1_0383.jpg" n="2"/>opera; the ballet of Pavlov and many famous violinists. Only an insignificant part of (the) Russian (colony) visited them; many had not even the desire to do it. But the American papers were full of enthusiastic praise of them. There are now many paintings of prominent Russian artists at the exhibition of paintings in the Art Museum on Michigan avenue, where admission is free. But how many of the Russians have visited the museum during the exhibition?. This indifference of the Russian colony to its own is amazing.</p>
   <p>We do not support our own; (we) are little proud of the fact that even strangers are praising us. We have become insufficiently patriotic here. Is it not the reason why we are in Chicago so poor in cultural institutions? Is it not the reason why we are so slow in cultural progress?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
