<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-02-04">Feb. 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Workers' Bankes</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0431</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0431.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title> (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-02-04">Feb. 4, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE WORKERS' BANKES</title>
<title level="a" type="sub">(Summary)</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>More than six billion dollars of all the savings in the American banks belong to the workers and unions. What use is that money to the workers? For what aims is this money used? Who is taking advantage of it and who controls it?</p>
   <p>The depositors are getting interest. Theoretically they get three per cent, but in practice - thanks to existing practices, such as non-payment of interest if the money is drawn even one day before the interest term - they get less than three per cent. The same worker, if the needs money and is able to put in a mortgage, pays to the bank 6%, 7%, and in some states, 8%. He often pays excessive commission and helps the bankers in the accumulation of big profits. But all this is not of such importance as the fact that the control of all that money is mostly in the hands of the banks, and this is of very little advantage to the working class.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0432.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The bank is a credit factory which produces and at the same time distributes credit. The banks also control credit. Who is taking advantage of this credit, the worker? Certainly not. Do you remember the house-building dispute in Chicago and all over the country? Who denied credit to the contractors who had employed union workers? During the war, when there was a great scarcity of workers, the foundry factories in Norfolk, Va., were forced to recognize the foundry unions. A short time after peace was declared the factory owners, feeling power, first withdrew the recognition of the unions and started to out wages. This was done by all factories but one, which had some directors (who were) former members of the unions and, therefore, friendly to the workers. All the factories closed up, trying to force the workers to surrender. The factory with union workers was the only one which kept on going and therefore it had enough orders to work twenty-four hours, thus giving a great deal of work to the striking workers. The union factory had a loan of $40,000 in one of the Norfolk banks. Due to the pressure of the factory owners' association, the bank demanded the immediate payment of the loan. The factory, not having the money on hand, would enter bankruptcy, and the <pb facs="5423967_1_0433.jpg" n="3"/>workers would be forced to surrender. But here - the first time in the history of the labor movement in America - there was carried out a very interesting and successful experiment. The machinists' union, seeing that the influence of credit (was being) used against the workers, thought: Why not use the credit for the interest of the workers? Why not loan $40,000 to the factory which is friendly to the workers?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
