<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. XII, Owned by: Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway Russkii Viestnik,
<date when="1918-12">Dec. 1918</date> (day not known).
<title level="a">"The Necessity for Sanitary-Hygienic Information."</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0387</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0387.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 3</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. XII, Owned by: Dr. H. R. Krasnow, 4601 N. Broadway Russkii Viestnik,
<date when="1918-12">Dec. 1918</date> (day not known).
<title level="a">"THE NECESSITY FOR SANITARY-HYGIENIC INFORMATION."</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>(A report read by Dr. Krasnow at the first Convention of Russian Cultural and Educational Organizations, held in Chicago, Dec. 27-28-29, 1918, under the auspices of the Chicago Russian People's University.)</p>
   <p>This report stresses in the main a flagrant need in the Russian People's Schools for elementary knowledge of the principles of sanitation and hygiene among Russians and Poles in Chicago, as a means of raising their very low standards of living.</p>
   <p>To demonstrate this urgent need Dr. Krasnow gave a vivid picture of how these immigrants live here:</p>
   <p>"The Russians live in the filthiest section of the city; in decayed, dilapidated, antediluvian houses which should have long been condemned and demolished. Nowhere in these houses will you find electric lighting, nor steamheat. Kerosene lamps light <pb facs="5423967_1_0388.jpg" n="2"/>these houses, gas light is the rare exception. Coal stoves heat these homes in the winter. Not a bath tub is to be found there, nor inside plumbing.</p>
   <p>The homes are generally of three or four rooms and in each of these houses dwell from twelve to twenty people. Very seldom does one find any more in furniture than beds, tables, and chairs. The rooms are half-dark, firstly because they are in back buildings, or in the rear portions of buildings. The windows are seldom cleaned. Fresh air is a very rare phonemenon in these dwellings. Fresh air currents cannot penetrate there for the simple reason that all around it is crowded, built-up; garbage is irregularly collected and generates heat in warm weather. </p>
   <p>In the winter it is even worse. On the one hand windows are never opened, and on the other hand, vapor forms because of the blasting stove inside the home, and the cold outside; then the cooking adds its own steam, and on top of it all comes tobacco smoke. The infinitesimal bit of air that could have forced its way through window crevices in kept out by packings of cotton or rags, in those crevices, 'so as to keep out the cold' ....As a result, according to very accurate statistical figures, 'the Russian--Polish section has the greatest percentage of consumptives, and is also marked for a very high degree of sicknesses of all kinds, and mortality." All this must be viewed as a direct result of ignorance and darkness among the greatest number of <pb facs="5423967_1_0389.jpg" n="3"/>Russian workingmen, who lack the A B C of information in hygiene or sanitation.</p>
   <p>As a rule the Russian turns to the doctor for help only after the disease has sunk its roots deeply, and has brought on complications from other diseases, and when the most experienced and skilful physician is helpless; when science can no longer combat the evils of nature.</p>
   <p>Most marked is the number of ailments, and the degree of mortality among children in the colony, and those who know how the plain Russian people violate all rules of care of children, will not wonder at it. Little children are seated at the table together with adults to eat the same foods with them, and are often treated to the same crude spirits. I have seen cases where mites of one or two years became intoxicated from these drinks and died from it.</p>
   <p>Dr. Krasnow closed his report with a forceful appeal to teach the pupils in the Russian schools the elements of hygiene, sanitation, anatomy and physiology.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
