<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russian Herald, (Russkii Viestnik)</title>,
<date when="1924-11-21">Nov. 21, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Russians in the Trade Unions</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0454</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0454.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russian Herald, (Russkii Viestnik)</title>,
<date when="1924-11-21">Nov. 21, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">RUSSIANS IN THE TRADE UNIONS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A few years ago there were some ignorant men among the Russian workmen in the city of Chicago, who were willing to go and work as strike-breakers. Complaints about such facts have been published time and again in our paper.</p>
   <p>During the last few years, however, the class-consciousness of the Russian workmen has grown very considerably. Now we hear very, very rarely about Russians working as strike-breakers.</p>
   <p>The Russian workmen are joining the trade unions in large numbers.</p>
   <p>In the unions of tailors, chauffeurs, metal workers, mattress-makers, window-washers, cabinet-makers and other workmen during the last years there are to be found many Russians.</p>
   <p>The writer of this article had the opportunity one of these days to talk to three Russians who are members of unions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0455.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"In the tailors' unions there are at present many Russians, and the employers will hardly succeed in luring any one of these Russian work-men to go and work in the open shops," said the tailor Boyko.</p>
   <p>"We have learned in America to value the power of trade unions: the union worker gets higher wages, he works in better conditions, and the employers treat him better," said F. Zamyatko, a metal worker.</p>
   <p>"We are not worse than any other workers and are not greenhorns any more; it is not so easy for the employers to fool us: we join the unions and invite our fellow workers to join also, as we see clearly that this is profitable," said Grigoriy Lushchev, an automobile mechanic who has come to Chicago recently from Colorado.</p>
   <p>One often listens to such answers now. In these there is perceptible anew spirit; new influences make themselves felt.</p>
   <p>S. Otormsky.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
