<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-27">Mar. 27, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Decrease in Unemployment</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0543</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.c"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0543.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-27">Mar. 27, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">DECREASE IN UNEMPLOYMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In March of 1933, there were 13,000,000 unemployed persons in the United States, and toward the end of February of the current year, the number of unemployed was reduced to 9,898,000 men. From January to the end of February of the current year, the number of unemployed was reduced by 242,000 men, or by two and four-tenths per cent. For the same period, the number of employed men and women has increased in almost every industry. Exceptions can be found only in commerce and transportation: in commercial enterprises, the number of unemployed increased by 11,000 and in transport, by 10,000.</p>
   <p>In the Chicago district, during February, the number of those unemployed increased by one and six-tenths per cent, and the total payroll, by two and a-half per cent. The most rapid revival in industry was noticed in the following Illinois cities: Aurora, Joliet, Peoria, and Rockford. Coming weeks are expected to bring further accelaration in industrial activity.</p>
   <p>Congress, as is well known, has passed a law appropriating four billion eight <pb facs="5423967_1_0544.jpg" n="2"/>hundred million for public works. Since amendments to the bill were introduced in both houses of Congress, it will take some time before the law will go into effect.</p>
   <p>According to proposals submitted by President Roosevelt, the public works are designed to give employment to three and one-half million men, which, it is expected, will automatically increase the number of employed in private industry by the same figure. Thus, when the public works get into full swing, the number of unemployed, it is hoped, will be reduced by more than three million men.</p>
   <p>Organized labor in the United States is, at the same time, carrying on for a thirty-hour week for the purpose of reducing unemployment still more. Recently the president of the American Federation of Labor, Mr. Green, made public "A Declaration by Organized Labor," basic proposals of which are as follows:</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0545.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>1. The establishment of the thirty-hour work week.</p>
   <p>2. University education for "unusual" workers' children.</p>
   <p>3. Social insurance, unemployment compensation, old age pensions, and sick benefits [for workers].</p>
   <p>4. A new system of credit and financing of industrial enterprises.</p>
   <p>5. Abolition of child labor.</p>
   <p>6. Abolition of company unions.</p>
   <p>7. Equal distribution of industrial profits through the medium of collective bargaining agreements.</p>
   <p>8. Advancement of workers' political movement.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0546.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>9. Guarantee of the right to strike.</p>
   <p>10. Imposition of heavier taxes on inheritances.</p>
   <p>Besides this, the American Federation of Labor demands the adoption of the Wagner Act providing for the settlement of workers' conflicts.</p>
   <p>From all this, we must conclude that in the near future the country will have a considerable spurt in industry, provided that these economic measures are not nullified by inflation.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
