<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Starik, Yacov. <title>A History of the Industrial Workers of the World</title> (Chicago, Executive Committee, Russian Section I. W. W.,
<date when="1921">1921</date>), pp. 188-190

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0466</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0466.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Starik, Yacov. <title>A History of the Industrial Workers of the World</title> (Chicago, Executive Committee, Russian Section I. W. W.,
<date when="1921">1921</date>), pp. 188-190
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The work of the Russian industrialists was so successful that it was decided to call a convention, which was in session from November 1922, 1919, in Chicago. At the convention the following were present: nine delegates from the sections of the Industrial Workers of the World, one delegate from the Union of Russian Workers, and one delegate from the colleagues of the publication Golos Truzenika, who represented about one thousand members of the various organizations.</p>
   <p>On the order of the day the convention had twenty-two questions.</p>
   <p>Some questions bore an organizational character; others, such as the question pertaining to the dictatorship of the proletariat, the attitude towards Soviet Russia, etc., were theoretical and took up a great part of the time at the convention.</p>
   <p>The convention approved the direction of the newspaper Golos Truzenika, <pb facs="5423967_1_0467.jpg" n="2"/>which was published three times a week, and decided to make it a daily at the first opportunity; to discontinue the monthly publication Trudo-vaya Misl. (Only seven copies of this were published, from May until November, 1919).</p>
   <p>There was also established an Executive of Russian Sections composed of each Section of the Industrial Workers of the World.</p>
   <p>The convention also took up the question regarding the departure to Russia of Russian workers living in America, as in the colony for several years a dire need was felt in obtaining such permission. Upon this question the convention passed the following resolution:</p>
   <p>"On the question of throwing open the border for a free departure to Russia, the first convention of the United Russian Sections of the Industrial Workers of the World deems it necessary to announce that neither petitions, delegations to those in power, nor street demonstrations will bring the needed results, for the simple reason that the <pb facs="5423967_1_0468.jpg" n="3"/>blockade against the Soviets is supported by governments which serve the interests of international capitalism, which in this case, as at all times, takes advantage of its economic powers.</p>
   <p>On this basis the convention arrives at the conclusion that only revolutionary action of the international proletariat will compel the capitalists of the world to stop intervention in Soviet Russia and open the borders.</p>
   <p>We, therefore, recommend propaganda and agitation on a large scale among all nationalities with a view of united economic pressure upon capitalists and powers.</p>
   <p>We emphatically call upon all Russian workers in the United States to join the great army of those organized in industry, so that through united effort the desired results may be accomplished."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
