<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material in possession of Dr. H. R. Krasnow</title>, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0486</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   <catRef target="#source-miscellaneous"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0486.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Miscellaneous Material in possession of Dr. H. R. Krasnow</title>, 4601 N. Broadway, Chicago, Ill.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To all Russian Workers</p>
   <p>To the entire Russian Colony in America.</p>
   <p>Comrades! The Chicago Newspaper Russian Viestnik-Rassviet is printed by strike-breakers. The bosses of the newspaper have categorically refused to grant the demands of the workers and to recognize the Union. For three days we have attempted to prove, that the workers have a right to be organized and work on union conditions. The bitterest enemies of the working class were forced to recognize this right of the workers, but the publishers of this newspaper, Russian Viestnik-Rassviet, on the headline of which it is said that the newspaper is an organ of "The Russian Professional Unions and Cultural-Educational Organizations", want to deprive the workers of this right.</p>
   <p>If the Russian professional unions exist in this country, and if any progressive organizations have anything in common with this newspaper, they will not tolerate this newspaper being printed by scabs, as it is done now.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0487.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The entire Russian colony of the United States and Canda, all Russian workers, all those who work for wages, should support the striking workers of the newspaper Russian Viestnik-Rassviet and the Chicago Typographical Union No. 16, under the leadership of which the strike is carried on.</p>
   <p>If you are with us and against the scabs, then help us win the strike. Accept the resolutions of the protest against the publishers, and out of sympathy to the union, inform all that there is a strike going on at this newspaper plant, and that scabs are being used. Send your protests to the publishers of the newspaper and a copy to us. Demand a union label on all typographical work.</p>
   <p>Fraternally yours,</p>
   <p>(Sig.) Chicago Typographical Union No. 16</p>
   <p>332 South LaSalle Street, Chicago, Ill.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
