<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-15">Apr. 15, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Russian Patriots Abroad</title><title level="a" type="sub">by I. Kovalev</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0602</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0602.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-04-15">Apr. 15, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">RUSSIAN PATRIOTS ABROAD</title><title level="a" type="sub">by I. Kovalev</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>When the Bolsheviks in Moscow saw that not only in the East but also in the West the military storm clouds were thickening, clouds from which a thunderbolt might strike Russia, they became pale in fear for their lives, and discarding their red neckties, they put on white ones and hurried to ask for the help of the bourgeoisie. Prior to that they had pretended to scorn the bourgeoisie and were ready to tear it to pieces without mercy, but now they choose to sit at the same table with the rich and to give their oaths in the name of all Russia that the Russian people will defend their interests to the last drop of their blood. Molotov has dressed his wife in czarist jewels and sent her to America to court the favor of American capitalists, whom he more than <pb facs="5423967_1_0603.jpg" n="2"/>once has threatened to destroy. There are no actions too evil, no offenses or frauds too grave, for the Bolsheviks to perpetrate. Could anybody expect any good of the people who only eighteen years ago were regarded as robbers and outlaws? Now they use their authority to continue their misdeeds. Only former chain-gang men could introduce eating from one common pot and going to work in gangs under the close watch of armed members of the secret police. Did not these highwaymen take the chain gangs as a model for their collective farm labor?</p>
   <p>What has become of the Russian revolution which was greeted so joyfully by the Russian people in its beginning, when to defend their freedom they fought off every interventionist? What was it all about? Was the revolution staged only to shoot down millions of people or to let them starve to death? Before the revolution the peasant felt himself an independent individual not subject <pb facs="5423967_1_0604.jpg" n="3"/>to anybody. Even though he had not much land, still the little which he had was his own. He was the boss on that patch of ground. He surveyed it with his eyes to its outer limit, which for centuries had remained unmoved. Not one blade of grass appeared on that soil without his knowing it. The peasant realized quite well that where there is property, there should also be a boss to see to it that the property was in good order, and that there was no waste in the business. But when Bolsheviks came into power, they took the land from the peasants by force, drove them on the collective farms, and made them tools of collective production altogether deprived of liberty of action, persons in whom free will was totally suppressed.</p>
   <p>But in case a war breaks out between Japan and Russia, the Bolsheviks will have to give rifles and other arms to the peasants to defend the country against the enemy. What will happen if after long years of suffering and servitude the armed peasants lose their patience and turn against their <pb facs="5423967_1_0605.jpg" n="4"/>oppressors? What will the Russian people in Russia do then, those who now profess that they will rise in defense of their fatherland? Will they join the Russian people, or will they with the Bolsheviks try to suppress the revolt against the hated oppressors?</p>
   <p>On several occasions I have spoken to the Russian people [in Russia] on this subject, and many of them have told me that they will help the Bolsheviks to suppress any revolt that may occur in time of war. In their opinion such a revolt would only play into the hands of foreign foes who by taking advantage of such a catastrophe would seize Russia and divide the country among themselves.</p>
   <p>Recently in New York a group was formed of representatives of various political factions, and this group has already drafted a tentative program of action for those who are inclined to defend Russia at any cost, irrespective of the government which happens to rule the country of their birth during the war. The platform contains an appeal directed to all the refugee elements of <pb facs="5423967_1_0606.jpg" n="5"/>of Russian extraction to join those who believe in defending Russia under any and all circumstances. In the discussion that took place at the first meeting of this group Mr. A. Pilipenko developed the thought that "in Russia Marxism is rapidly surrendering its position, and patriotic elemental force is sweeping away the last traces of Bolshevik internationalism". And if such is the case, Mr. Pilipenko thinks that even though the Bolsheviks may have killed our parents in a war with Japan, there should be no enmity toward them, and their government should by all means be supported in the war; we should all join the united front in the fatherland's defense, seeking the salvation of Russia.</p>
   <p>Considering all the past deceitful actions of the Bolsheviks, I do not quite agree with Mr. Pilipenko, for we all know what doom was meted out by the Bolsheviks to their honest revolutionary opponents who had saved them from certain defeat in the wars of foreign intervention. In conclusion I may say that I am not a defeatist. I am opposed both to the domestic <pb facs="5423967_1_0607.jpg" n="6"/>and to the foreign enemies of Russia, but when the time is opportune--in the case, for instance, of a war with Japan--I advise the Russian people to remove all the oppressors and the parasites of the Russian people in Russia in order to save Russia from graver catastrophes in the future.</p>
   <p>When all the dirt has been washed off, when all the murderers and workers of violence have been removed, only then may the Russian people begin to build up a happy life of justice and freedom. It is desirable that all believers in all-out defense and those who are conditionally opposed to such defense shall air their views on this important subject in Rassviet.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
