<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>,
<date when="1924-07-10">7/10/24</date>.
<title level="a">Around the Dollars of the Cooperative Restaurant.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0352</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0352.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russian Herald, (Russkii Viestnik)</title>,
<date when="1924-07-10">7/10/24</date>.
<title level="a">AROUND THE DOLLARS OF THE COOPERATIVE RESTAURANT.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Just a year ago there was held in Chicago, a convention of the Society for Technical Aid to Soviet Russia. This convention lasted two days. There has been even published in the Russian Herald, a report of its proceedings. At that time one could already see that this "highly useful institution" was fated to fail; one could foresee its doom and ultimate ruin.</p>
   <p>Yet this Society, the name of which had been changed to "Society for Technical Aid to the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics," (this change was the only important resolution passed by the convention) continues to exist. At least it is still in existence in Chicago. A circumstantial account of its activities during the period which has elapsed since the time of its last convention (especially during the first half of this year) will be given on the pages of our paper.</p>
   <p>We intend to point out here, only the boundless shamelessness which has been shown by the five members of this Society, (there may be more according to the list of members, but we know only of five in Chicago) in respect of the use of the money proceeding from the pockets of our workmen's colony.</p>
   <p>In today's issue of our paper the reader will find a report about the last session <pb facs="5423967_1_0353.jpg" n="2"/>held by the members of the cooperative restaurant.</p>
   <p>This restaurant is the only large Russian organization in Chicago of a purely economic character, absolutely non-political. The cooperative restaurant is the pride of the Russian workmen of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Its business is improving with every day. It can be said that financially it is in a brilliant state. Lately the amount of cash in the treasury has been steadily increasing and has reached the considerable sum of $5,200.00.</p>
   <p>And immediately the communist blusterers who are hunting the dollar began an attack on this lucrative business. One cannot deny to our bolsheviki a lot of stubborness and insistence in achieving their aims (and everybody knows what these aims are); besides, the New York communist paper gives definite instructions about the ways of destroying an organization - instructions, the effectiveness of which has been verified several times on a world-wide scale.</p>
   <p>And things began to happen.....</p>
   <p>Already, for six months this "S.T.A.U.S.S.R". (Notes Society for Technical Aid to the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics. D.S.) has been on the verge of death; it would be generous to keep silent about any of its activities, because the result of these activities is nil:</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0354.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Meanwhile the members of the "S.T.A.U.S.S.R." have no money to pay even the rent for the quarters the Society is occupying, and the owner suggests to these idle tenants to vacate the premises. And here is where the sly members of the Society desided to penetrate into the membership of the cooperative restaurant; for the restaurant possessed money.</p>
   <p>And they began to besiege the cooperators. Fortunately the majority of the members of the cooperative were not "greenhorns"; still after one or two sessions (interspered with stormy disputes and debates) they decided, in order to get rid of the importunities of the intruders, to assign for the payment of the rent for the quarters of the S.T.A.U.S.S.R., the sum of money lacking (with the reservation that the money would be provided only for the three summer-months). But immediately after this resolution had been passed the bolsheviki demanded $140.00 more of the money of the Cooperative and were given this money.</p>
   <p>But in the treasury of the cooperative there was $5,200.00.</p>
   <p>So another special meeting was called.</p>
   <p>At this meeting an address of the secretary of the communist paper to the cooperative was read requesting the cooperators to send delegates to a conference. </p>
   <p>But why a conference?</p>
   <p>"In order to serve better the colony with "our" paper, the Novy Mir (The New World)."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0355.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>(Editorial note:This paper is published in New York City.)</p>
   <p>What does this mean if we put it in plain words? This is what it means: "Assign to us your money; if you will not do it today, you will do it anyhow tomorrow. You have some money; we have not got any (i.e. -we do get money, but, don't you see, the Russian treasury has been considerably depleted, and we are short of money..) Capitulate without any fighting, for we shall get hold of your money anyhow".</p>
   <p>But the spirit of the cooperators was strong, and this first attack of the communists was repelled...</p>
   <p>Cooperators, never forget the words of our local ringleader of the communists, Shklar, who announced the following;-</p>
   <p>"Glory be to God" (this from a communist!) "we have already our own labor newspaper (he means that New York sheet!), a workmen's school is in process of formation (he means our Chicago Russian schools which this communist "nurse" wants to subvert), and we shall have our own workmen's restaurant" (meaning this very restaurant, created by the sweat and blood of hundreds of Russian workmen of Chicago!)....</p>
   <p>Cooperators, you have already hastily and thoughtlessly agreed to support the local S.T.A.U.S.S.R., which shallows every month $140.00 of your own hard-earned money.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0356.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Stop and do not go any farther towards the brink of a precipice.</p>
   <p>The robust Russian restaurant which you have created is in danger.</p>
   <p>Strive to open as soon as possible a second restaurant; do not accumulate any cash in your treasury, for only under such conditions will our home-grown international jackals not look with hungry eyes at your money. And, believe me, when the New York communist "Central Office" will have found out that there is no cash lying idle in your treasury, it will on the very next day lose all interest in the Chicago activities and in our local workmen's colony.</p>
   <p>Cooperators, hasten to invest your thousands of dollars in a useful enterprise..</p>
   <p>Open a second restaurant without any delay..</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
