<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-15">Mar. 15, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Education and Culture</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0050</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0050.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-15">Mar. 15, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">EDUCATION AND CULTURE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many of our people here in America think that education and culture mean one and the same thing, but this is not so. Education and culture are two different things, two different conceptions, although a close relation exists between them. A man may be educated, but at the same time he may be uncultured. Another man may possess very little education, and yet he may have culture. This is explained by the fact that one acquires education in schools and colleges and by self-training, but one absorbs culture from one's home, one's immediate family and the environment in which one lives. Culture is the result not of education but of proper bringing up.</p>
   <p>The reader of this article may ask which then is more important for a man to possess, education or culture. This question can be answered briefly: one is as important as the other, because both these qualities, like a mirror, reflect <pb facs="5423967_1_0051.jpg" n="2"/>the spiritual countenance of a man. We speak of a man with one healthy leg and one artificial one as an invalid. We can call a man who has education but who has no culture, or has culture but no education, a spiritual invalid.</p>
   <p>Education and culture are not bourgeois superstitions, not articles of luxury, but the two first necessities in our lives, and both should be in the possession of every man. Without education and without culture it would not be possible for one to accomplish anything, whether in the field of spiritual or esthetic values or in the betterment of one's material life. Every man needs education; he needs not only to be able to read and write, but also to have at least a superficial knowledge and understanding of scientific and social questions, and to be able to keep pace with his associates at the place where he works.</p>
   <p>Even the simplest work today requires some knowledge and training. Noted economists assert that in the near future, when mechanized labor reaches its peak, the illiterate or the poorly-educated workers will become superfluous and <pb facs="5423967_1_0052.jpg" n="3"/>unwanted. Even now we have many occupations in which it is necessary to have a highly trained mind, and a good knowledge of physics, chemistry, mathematics and other subjects.</p>
   <p>Education in itself, however, is not sufficient. A man must have culture, if he does not want to be avoided by other people. It is a well-known fact that nobody wants to talk with or listen to simpletons and boors, even when they may perhaps have a sound opinion or a good thought.</p>
   <p>A good example of the lack of education and culture are, for instance, the Russian Bolsheviks in America. They not only do not know how to write even a few words correctly, but they have not the remotest conception of that Bolshevism about which they talk so much everywhere they turn. They have not read Marx, Engels or Lenin, and even if they have read they do not understand, because of their very limited education. The wonder is how they can propagate ideas which they themselves cannot comprehend. Their lack of the very rudiments of education and their utter lack of culture are proverbial. It is not <pb facs="5423967_1_0053.jpg" n="4"/>by chance, obviously, that they got such names as boors, hoodlums and bumpkins. They show these characteristics wherever they may be. For this reason no self-respecting Russian desires to have any contact with them. All good people shun them like lepers.</p>
   <p>Every member of our Russian group in America should strive to give his children a good education and a good rearing. Then our children will not only be educated but will also have culture. Besides, every Russian adult in this country should use every opportunity to increase his own education and to broaden his culture.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
