<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. James Trushinsky</title>, Secretary of the Russian Cooperative Society, and Mr. Alexander Urieff, Manager of the Cooperative Restaurant.
(<date when="1936-11-16">Nov. 16, 1936</date>)

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0491</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.1.c.1"/>
   <catRef target="#source-interview"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0491.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 a</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Interview with Mr. James Trushinsky</title>, Secretary of the Russian Cooperative Society, and Mr. Alexander Urieff, Manager of the Cooperative Restaurant.
(<date when="1936-11-16">Nov. 16, 1936</date>)
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Some years ago the Russian Technical Aid Society was a club of Russian workers. All of them were single men and were compelled to take lodgings. They were thoroughly disgusted with their lot and homesick for real Russian food. They debated how to improve this situation and laid out constructive plans for the opening of a little restaurant at 1734 W. Division street.</p>
   <p>Each of the members of the Russian Technical Aid Society gave $25 as his share for a cooperative restaurant, which was opened shortly after.</p>
   <p>The Russian Technical Aid Society later changed its name to "Russian <pb facs="5423967_1_0492.jpg" n="2"/>Workers' Cooperative Society" (its present name), and now has 116 members. The organization has been granted a charter. They meet once a month to discuss the affairs of their organization and plan ways and means of aiding other organizations with which they are sympathetic.</p>
   <p>In 1922 the members of the Russian Workers' Cooperative Society decided to open a new restaurant (the Russian Cooperative Restaurant), now located at 1628 W. Division street. All members of the Russian Workers' Cooperative are shareholders in the Russian Cooperative Restaurant.</p>
   <p>The restaurant is under the management of Mr. Alexander Urieff. The financial standing of the Russian Cooperative Society has been sound during the years of the late depression and it is improving. The restaurant employs nineteen people, including the manager, and it is a strictly union affair.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0493.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>All profits from the Russian Cooperative Restaurant are used for the maintenance of club rooms at 1628 W. Division street (above the Cooperative Restaurant), for the purchase of Russian books - classics both old and new. A good deal of its money is used to support various Russian schools in Chicago. A very hospitable and homelike atmosphere prevails in the Russian Cooperative Restaurant, and it is patronized by 95 per cent of the workers in the Russian colony, and also by workers of other nationalities, tourists, etc.</p>
   <p>The Russian Cooperative Society, as well as the restaurant, has been for a good many years a great social factor in the lives of the Russians in Chicago. In their club rooms they conduct open forums, lectures, concerts. Their large library and reading rooms are open to the public at all times. The members of the Russian Cooperative Society are outstanding members of various left wing political parties.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0494.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>They spare no effort to help the workers culturally, educationally and socially.</p>
   <p>For years students from the Chicago universities, social workers, and all interested in the Russian colony and the mode of living of the Russian workers, have come to the Russian Cooperative Restaurant.</p>
   <p>In recent years tours, conducted for educational purposes under the auspices of the Works Progress Administration and the Chicago Recreation Commission, have included in their programs the Russian Cooperative Restaurant and its club rooms. They have listened to Russian music played by Russian musicians, songs by Russian singers, and have watched Russian dances.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0495.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The Russian Cooperative Society maintains meeting halls which are used by various Russian organizations without paying rent. Among the organizations taking advantage of the facilities offered by the meeting halls are a Russian choir, an orchestra, a dramatic group, branches of left wing parties, and fraternal organizations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
