<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1933-01-28">Jan. 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">All Is Quiet in Chicago</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0222</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-V.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0222.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>V A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1933-01-28">Jan. 28, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">ALL IS QUIET IN CHICAGO</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every Saturday a page of the Rassviet is devoted to the activities of the Russian Independent Society of Mutual Aid of Chicago. This page usually contains, among other articles, an editorial signed by the editorial group of the society. The editorial whose title appears above is devoted to the struggle between different social groups existing among the Chicago Russians, and it describes very accurately the state of affairs that existed in 1933, and which still remains practically the same at the present time. Therefore, there is given (here) a somewhat lengthy summary of this editorial, sometimes with verbatim quotations. Translator's note.</p>
   <p>"Leavitt Street," "Wood Street," and "Division Street," those are the names by which are designated the three chief Russian groups of Chicago. During the last twenty years these groups have been fighting each other. First a fight raged between "Leavitt Street" and " Division Street."</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0223.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then, after 1912, there arose a struggle between "Leavitt Street" and "Wood Street," which still persists.</p>
   <p>This continual struggle between the Russian groups has tired out the Russian residents of Chicago. Both geographically and as regards principles, the "Wood Street group" occupies an intermediate position between the two other groups. This may be one of the reasons why it has a much larger membership than the others. On Wood Street is located the center of the largest Russian society of mutual aid in the central states. Its membership in 1933 was about 1,500, while the Leavitt Street organization had 300 members, and the Division Street organization only 60 members. (Note: This group really comprises several organizations of different kinds. D. S.) Though this last group (Note: Consisting of Communists. D. S.) was small, it did its best to disrupt the other groups, but could not achieve (its purpose) and only caused a lot of trouble. Ultimately <pb facs="5423967_1_0224.jpg" n="3"/>even the members of this leftist group themselves began to doubt whether these destructive activities were really necessary and legitimate. They observed that both their group and the group they were fighting consisted of peasants from White Russia (Byelorussy), who had the same interests and needs, and that fighting and abusing each other could not possibly help them in any way; in fact, it could mean only a harmful waste of energy by both parties. They saw that more mutual understanding and tolerance was all that was wanted in order to enable them to cooperate in many useful undertakings and thus get much better results. (Note: Unfortunately, the leaders of the Communists could never agree with this reasonable standpoint and continued in their efforts to increase the antagonism existing between the three groups. D. S.)</p>
   <p>The authors of the editorial express the hope that in spite of that, in the future this deplorable state of affairs, injurious to the interests <pb facs="5423967_1_0225.jpg" n="4"/>of the Russian colony of Chicago as a whole, would be overcome and that Russians of all the three groups (the Leavitt Street group is the most conservative of the three) would be able to cooperate in such useful undertakings as the foundation of a Russian House of the People, the unification of all Russian schools, the organization of farms and cooperative stores, etc.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
