<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1927-10-13">Oct. 13, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The American Federation of Labor and Intemperance</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0112</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0112.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (2)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1927-10-13">Oct. 13, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE AMERICAN FEDERATION OF LABOR AND INTEMPERANCE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since prohibition was established in the United States, the American Federation of Labor at all its annual conventions has passed resolutions demanding the repeal of this law. The struggle against prohibition has become one of the features of the program of this labor organization. And this struggle is going on, not because the Volstead Act has not given satisfactory results, but simply because it interferes with the freedom of drinking beer and strong liquors.</p>
   <p>This attitude towards prohibition makes the American Federation of Labor quite a unique labor organization. Professing to stand for the interests of labor, it at the same time upholds the right of the workman to get drunk. The programs of labor organizations are concerned with the struggle of the working class for a higher standard of living, and with educational questions. Most labor organizations do not include into their programs the question of intemperance; yet, if in some of <pb facs="5423967_1_0113.jpg" n="2"/>these organizations this question is being discussed at meetings or conventions, the result is mostly the expression of a thoroughly negative attitude towards the excessive use of alcoholic beverages. Never has anybody been able to prove that the use of liquor is beneficial to the working class. On the contrary, it is well known that intemperance is the worst enemy of the workers. It brings with it poverty, disease, ignorance, brawls, fights, and dissolution of the family. All this is very well understood by all labor organizations except the American Federation of Labor. The leaders of the latter seem to wish not that the workers, after a hard day of labor, be able to read some good book or go to some instructive lecture, but that they be given ample opportunity to visit saloons and to leave there the money they have earned.</p>
   <p>The leaders of the American Federation of Labor and some of the members of this union maintain that after staying in the stifling atmosphere of a workroom, the worker wants to wet his throat with <pb facs="5423967_1_0114.jpg" n="3"/>beer in order to feel normal. This is entirely wrong. What the worker wants is fresh air, good food and some healthy drink; not beer and liquor. If a worker has to toil in the deadly atmosphere of an antisanitary workroom, no amount of beer or liquor will prevent him from getting sick. It will only endanger his health still more. It is the aim of all bona fide working organizations to shorten the day of labor, to protect the workers against dangerous machines and unsanitary conditions, and to raise their standard of living by enabling them to get higher wages. Drinking beer and whiskey certainly will not help to achieve that. Only dishonest politicians, who want to get popular at all costs, can encourage the workers to spend their money on drinking.</p>
   <p>The resolution of the convention of the American Federation of Labor also says that the present prohibition law has been proved to be unsatisfactory and (that it) has led to some dire result. With this part of the resolution we can agree, but the defects of the Volstead <pb facs="5423967_1_0115.jpg" n="4"/>Act do not prove at all that we should stand for the unlimited right of men to get drunk. Some an amendments may be necessary: one may even think that any law prohibiting or regulating the use of liquor would be useless, as it could never be strictly enforced. But even if one would take this attitude, it would not mean at all that one has to give up the fight against intemperance. Humanity cannot become healthy and happy as long as the craving for alcohol has not been overcome. Alcohol is one of the worst enemies of the working class, as it help to keep it in ignorance and subjection.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
