<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russian Herald, (Russkii Viestnik)</title>,
<date when="1924-11-01">Nov. 1, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">A Cultural Change in the Colony</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russian Herald, (Russkii Viestnik)</title>,
<date when="1924-11-01">Nov. 1, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">A CULTURAL CHANGE IN THE COLONY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The beginning of the fall season in the Russian colony has brought with it a revival of the activities of certain organizations.</p>
   <p>Without exaggerating one can say that this year we are witnessing in our colony an unusually energetic effort to intensify cultural and educational activities.</p>
   <p>With exceptional, almost unparalleled energy the colony has undertaken to increase the number of schools and to improve the teaching which the children are getting.</p>
   <p>In this year many more evening entertainments, concerts and theatrical performances are being arranged than last year and the year before last.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0060.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Many more lectures are given and many more papers on various subjects are read.</p>
   <p>Several new schools have been opened and several new organizations have been founded in this year.</p>
   <p>But the most important thing is that this year there is much more talk in our colony about the necessity of a more energetic cultural-educational work. And what is more, people do not only talk, but, as far as possible, try to do something. The pessimists who have become disappointed in the attempts of the colony to start some useful undertakings jeer at all such talk about a change for the better being observed in the colony.</p>
   <p>In reality only those who keep aloof from the life of the Russian colony do not notice this change.</p>
   <p>And yet it is not difficult to notice it. All that you want to do is just to go through the Chronicle of the life of the Russian colony in <pb facs="5423967_1_0061.jpg" n="3"/>our paper for the last year and compare it with this year's chronicle.</p>
   <p>It is also advisable to pay attention to the great number of advertisements of various entertainments, lectures, etc., that have been arranged in the colony.</p>
   <p>As it was before, we are still poor. We have yet a far way to go to be on a par with most of the other nationalities of the city of Chicago in respect of unification, organization and number of necessary institutions.</p>
   <p>But if in order to attain to all what the other nationalities have achieved we shall go on working as energetically as we are doing now we shall be able to achieve very much.</p>
   <p>We welcome the awakening of the colony for which we have been yearning a long time.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
