<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1926-08-12">August 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Editorial. Schools for Children.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0094</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0094.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 2 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III A (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet</title>,
<date when="1926-08-12">August 12, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Editorial. Schools for Children.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The schools for children are playing a great role in the Russian Colony. The work done by the schools is very vital and important. The future of it is secured. In spite of the considerable number of single men and women, there is a new generation growing up. The problem of the colony is to protect that new generation from the destructive influences from without. The problem is a quite difficult one. There is no other country where there is such a strong tendency toward assimilation of the different nationalities as in the United States. For example: the Jewish children in Russia, in most cases, spoke their native language, but here in America, they refuse to use their language, as is the case with the new generation of other nationalities. That means that the surrounding circumstances in America are stronger than they were in Russia. Another important fact is that the children of foreigners mechanically become Americans. From the day the child is born, there is a juridical barrier between him and his parents, and in order not to lose some of their authority over their children, the parents must also become American citizens.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0095.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>As far as the juridical side of the question is concerned, it cannot be helped. The only thing we can do is to take care that our children do not lose the signs of their origin. This problem is laid upon the schools for children. In what degree this problem would be fulfilled, depends upon the character and condition of the schools for children. So far, the schools are in their primary stage. They have not succeeded yet, in coming closer together, but this will probably soon be achieved. In cities like Chicago, New York and Detroit, where there are several schools for children, there arises the necessity of creating a Federation of Russian Schools for children in the United States and Canada. The idea about unifying the schools for children become more and more necessary and important, and probably before long we shall see local conferences of schools for children and later, of a general Colony Convention.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
