<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>, (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-10-27">Oct. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Russian Fakes in America</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0341</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0341.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>, (Russian Herald),
<date when="1924-10-27">Oct. 27, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">RUSSIAN FAKES IN AMERICA</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the olden times Russians used to say that it is always easy to find out whether a man is worthy of respect. Such a man does not boast and does not claim any dignity or any name to which he is not entitled.</p>
   <p>Faking is a thing unknown among honorable people. On the contrary, cheap men like to claim all kinds of titles, honorary appellations and even names of other persons, if it happens to be profitable, or even if it just flatters their self-love.</p>
   <p>A short time ago the writer of this editorial had a talk with an ex-colonel of the Russian army who has been holding an office which enabled him to know many military secrets.</p>
   <p>Among other things the colonel communicated to the writer the following fact: Once the colonel went to the co-operative restaurant, and a certain "professor V." was introduced to him.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0342.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"You are professor V.?" asked the colonel with astonishment.</p>
   <p>But instead of answering his question, the "professor" tried to escape, having recognized in the colonel his ex-chief, in whose regiment he had been serving, as a veterinarian.</p>
   <p>Yet in Chicago he is "a professor." The credulous public was trusting him and, until it was proved that he was a fake, people used to listen to the "professor's" wisecracks.</p>
   <p>Here is another case: An ex-officer of the Russian army visits the colonel and by way of introducing himself gives him a visiting card which says that the bearer of it has been occupying formerly three professorial chairs.</p>
   <p>"What do you know about that!" exclaimed the astonished colonel.</p>
   <p>This time there was no attempt to escape on the part of the visitor.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0343.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The "triple professor" just stopped distributing his high-faluting visiting cards.</p>
   <p>Not a very long time ago Chicago was honored by the visit of a well known "professor" of the Academy of the General Staff who, not being contented with the appellation of "professor," also assumed a much higher military grade than the one to which he was really entitled.</p>
   <p>However in this case also some misfortune happened. The colonel who knew all the "professor's" antecedents, disclosed the truth about him, and now the latter does not call himself a professor any more.</p>
   <p>And this is not all. There are many such fine gentlemen who arrogate other people's merits and even assume names of offices not belonging to them, and who are operating in Chicago and other American cities. And how many "princes," "counts," and "barons" there are, bearing phantastic names! How many "courtiers" who were treated by the tsar almost like "pals," how many "ministers" and "public men!"</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0344.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>When one hears about all these things one is aggrieved and, at times, fells ashamed.</p>
   <p>Gentlemen impostors! Don't you see that you cannot go on like that! Why should you deceive our simple-hearted, good-natured Russian colony!</p>
   <p>One can go a long way by telling lies, but such lies do not allow you to return when you would like to do so. The same thing is going to happen to you.</p>
   <p>If you have no pity for the uneducated simpletons, have pity at least for the real Russian intellectuals who exist in Chicago and try to start some useful activities! Impostors cannot disparage such persons, of course. Still they arouse in one's soul bitter, painful feelings.</p>
   <p>One should mind the fast that the Americans do not know us. If they should find out that on some occasion or other they have been cheated <pb facs="5423967_1_0345.jpg" n="5"/>by one of these "triple professors" or "ministers" and "friends" of the tsar, it may happen that they will not trust any other Russian, even when he is perfectly trustworthy. Many Russian scientists have been working and are working in American universities, Rostovtsev, Borodin, Petrunkevich, Tolmachev, the late Korf, Volkov, Struve, Maximov and others. All these men, while doing scientific work in American universities, have been doing at the same time another important work. They have been informing the Americans about what Russia really is and what useful men it has given to the universities of other countries.</p>
   <p>The reputation of such men will certainly not be injured by impostors. They are already known, but it is different with other perfectly trustworthy persons who are just beginning to become more or less prominent. Such persons can be harmed by the impostors, because the latter by their actions can arouse a feeling of distrust towards all Russians in general.</p>
   <p>It is necessary to fight the impostors, and this fighting must be done by the Russian-American intellectuals themselves. We shall help them.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0346.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>(Note: It is worth mentioning that the author of this editorial, A. P. Skopin-Shuysky, is himself a real Russian prince, though he has never insisted in America on his princely title. He is a very modest man: friendly, unobtrusive, honest, industrious, always openhearted.</p>
   <p>It is true that at the time when this editorial was written, there was among the new Russian immigrants an epidemic of using all kinds of bogus titles in order to gain greater notoriety and popularity in the Russian colony, which did not know the former status and descent of the newcomers. Such impostures were practiced in all large cities of the United States, where there were many new Russian immigrants.</p>
   <p>There was a campaign carried on, both by the Russian-American press and by spoken word against these impostors, until at last all such unwarranted use of titles and names of offices has been entirely dropped. The editor could not help feeling indignation when observing how such unhealthy conditions were disgracing the good name of the Russian colony. N. K.)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
