<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkii Viestnik</title>,
<date when="1924-07-26">7/26/24</date>.
<title level="a">The Crisis of the Colony.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(By G. Busko)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0349</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0349.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russian Herald, (Russkii Viestnik)</title>,
<date when="1924-07-26">7/26/24</date>.
<title level="a">THE CRISIS OF THE COLONY.</title><title level="a" type="sub">(By G. Busko)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During a year and a half, I have been observing the activities going on in the Russian colony of Chicago; I have been visiting lectures, meetings, theatrical performances, concerts and balls, and lately I have been to several picnics. I have also been reading at times in the Russian Herald that the colony is progressing and becoming more organized. It is true that if we compare the former and the present states of the Russian colony we see that the Russian organizations have achieved much as far as arranging good concerts and lectures goes.</p>
   <p>But as to progress and being organized, we have not only not made any advance, but have even gone back a long distance. This is especially noticeable at the present time; everywhere you see trouble, disputes and distrust; egoism has become so solidly engrained into the souls of the Russian immigrants that it seems to be hardly possible to dislodge it from them. I am sure that most of the Russian workmen are conscious of the fact that egoism is the greatest evil in man.</p>
   <p>But they cannot get rid of this evil because everyone of them wants for some reason to be respected, to be superior to others, to be regarded by others as a leader, etc.</p>
   <p>Even among the organizations each one believes itself to be better than the others and endeavors by all means to out-do the others; it happens even that one organization tries purposely to injure another on every occasion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0350.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>How long is this going to last? Could it be that we Russians shall never realize that our strength lies in unity? Could it be that these words will be forgotten by us or trodden down by our egoism, by our mean individualism and self-conceit, by our contemptible ago? Is it not time for us to realize that all this leads to the worst enslavement of ourselves?</p>
   <p>Wherever you go at present among the Russian immigrants you hear continually, such expressions as theses: "White guards!" - "Enemies of the people who have fled to Constantinople!" - "Commnunistic chatter-boxes,""Pseudo-communists", etc. Is all this to be reckoned as progress? Is there anything truly human in such abuse? What shall I call the shouting and disputing at the picnic of June 29th, in the "White Eagle Grove"" Whoever is in his right mind could explain all that was happening at the picnic of July 13th, in the "National Grove"?</p>
   <p>I shall not relate the details of what has been happening at these picnics, because most Russians know all about it. But it is so sad to witness such "progress", such a childish behavior.</p>
   <p>And yet we are not children, we are adults, and many of us claim to be educated persons, and some are intellectuals who have been graduated from colleges. But where is our intellectuality? What becomes of our education when we have to listen to an opponent or to a political enemy? How can such shouting and abuse be tolerated <pb facs="5423967_1_0351.jpg" n="3"/>by the public who has come to a picnic to enjoy contact with nature and to have some rest? When shall we learn to listen attentively not only to those who agree with us, but also to those who oppose us? Only then, shall we be able to dream about the unification of the whole Russian colony into one great family, were it only on the basis of mutual aid and education.  And how one would wish to see the whole Russian colony cooperating harmoniously for its own good and for the good of our native country which has been and is suffering so much! It is high time to cease quarrelling about all kinds of nonsense, whether it be party affairs or private affairs, and to get busy unifying ourselves on the basis of economic activities and enlightenment</p>
   <p>Enough of these disputes and petty quarrels, and of that calling each other of all kinds of nasty names.</p>
   <p>It is high time to get really busy!</p>
   <p>Gordey Busko.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
