<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            
Starik, Yakov. <title>A History of the Industrial Workers of the World</title>. Chicago: Executive Committee, Russian Section, I. W. W.,
<date when="1921">1921</date>, p. 182.
<title level="a">Industrial Workers of the World and the Russian Workers' Colony</title>

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0469</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0469.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
Starik, Yakov. <title>A History of the Industrial Workers of the World</title>. Chicago: Executive Committee, Russian Section, I. W. W.,
<date when="1921">1921</date>, p. 182.
<title level="a">INDUSTRIAL WORKERS OF THE WORLD AND THE RUSSIAN WORKERS' COLONY</title>
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The union of Russian workers (organized in 1907-08) was composed of political immigrants who did not know the English language and who lived for the interests of the revolutionary movement in Russia.</p>
   <p>Newspapers printed in Russian were not in existence, and it was necessary to be satisfied with newspapers from Russia.</p>
   <p>In the fall of 1907 appeared a newspaper, Russky Golos, (New York City), published by a former Socialist-Revolutionist, John Okuntsov, which gained the approval of the Russian colony. Immediately after its birth, this newspaper became the official organ of the Russian organizations, mainly, the Unions of Russian Workers. Consequently, Okuntsov became a typical businessman, and the direction of the newspaper changed in accordance with public opinion.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0470.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>At that time the Union of Russian Workers embraced all the immigrants. It was composed of anarchists, Social-Democrats, Socialist-Revolutionists, workers -all enemies of tsarism.</p>
   <p>A united front of this type would seem strange to a contemporary party worker, but considering the fact that the educational activities, aid and work of the Union of Russian Workers was all directed towards the overthrow of tsarism, it will become clear that this was possible.</p>
   <p>(This is included as background material on IWW movement among the Russians).</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
