<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. IX, 4601 N. Broadway, Chgo., Ill. Newspaper Clipping--Russko-Amerikanskoe Ekho, New York, No. 52
(<date when="1910">1909-10</date>)
<title level="a">Chicago: the Russian Unions and Circles</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0413</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0413.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Krasnow Scrapbooks</title>, Vol. IX, 4601 N. Broadway, Chgo., Ill. Newspaper Clipping--Russko-Amerikanskoe Ekho, New York, No. 52
(<date when="1910">1909-10</date>)
<title level="a">CHICAGO: THE RUSSIAN UNIONS AND CIRCLES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The Russian Colony in Chicago is not different from that in New York, there is the same lifelessness, the same chaos and emptiness.</p>
   <p>For the last five years the social life of the Russian Colony of Chicago has not moved forward a step, although more new immigrants arrive every year, and a number of new "unions" and "circles" quickly rise and decay. Often visiting Chicago, I received in answer to my question, "what is new?", the answer "everything is just the same." And that sameness has long been antiquated. New forms of organization and fresh strength to be devoted to the matter are necessary.</p>
   <p>In Chicago there are "on paper" dozens of Russian progressive organizations, and it is very curious that the same people are active in all of them. All these Chicago organizations might form one large, strong, progressive and lively organization.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0414.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Take, for example, the local "Russian Library" and the Russian Social-Economic Club, which are not only useful but directly necessary to the Chicago colony. In the meantime, the library has twelve (!) members and the club a few more. A library is needed by all immigrants, why then do not the remaining organization set about constructing a library? Why is it that there are altogether only a few dozen books in the library? Why is the that there are altogether only a few dozen books in the library? Why is the club open only several hours in the evening when all organizations should have a large roomy club, which would be open the whole day and in which there could be given frequent free concerts and lectures.</p>
   <p>The Society of Russian Students has all in all 25 members; of these 20 either cannot or do not wish to attend meetings, the five are, of course, not in a position to create anything. In the meantime these five or six energetic and devoted students could be of much use in a large organization.</p>
   <p>One "progressive organization," the Society of Russian Workers, has in its constitution the clause "except Jews." By this they first, unjustly insult the Jews, and second, offend every liberal man. And how much labor and energy <pb facs="5423967_1_0415.jpg" n="3"/>has the sympathetic and active Dr. Krasnow expended on the formation of the Russian branch of the "Arbeiter Ring" which provides for Russians in case of illness or accident, but up to the present his efforts have not been crowned with success.</p>
   <p>From one angle, the Russian Colony suffers from the fact that it is divided into small groups, from another angle, from the fact that it does not beliege in its own strength.</p>
   <p>The people of Chicago go with pleasure to listen to a tirescome lecture by a New York celebrity, and rarely goes to the useful and interesting lectures of their own Chicagoans.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
