<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-06">Feb. 6, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">New Form of "Patriotism"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0637</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0637.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1936-02-06">Feb. 6, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">NEW FORM OF "PATRIOTISM"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(An Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Izvestia [Translator's note: A Bolshevik paper published in Moscow] in its issue of January 17 gives space to a long speech delivered by the representative of the soviet trade union council, Mr. Lozovsky, at the session of the Central Executive Committee of the Communist party. The speech was directed mainly against the foreign press, which had called the Stakhanov movement [Translator's note: A speed-up system named after its initiator, a coal miner] a system of extreme exploitation hitherto unheard of and never before practiced anywhere, not even in capitalist countries.</p>
   <p>"Only one American bourgeois newspaper", declared the speaker, "found a more or less suitable term by which to designate the Stakhanov movement. It stated that it was the latest form of Russian patriotism. This is not badly put. The Stakhanov movement really was called into being by patriotism, <pb facs="5423967_1_0638.jpg" n="2"/>by love of country, love of the native land. There is no doubt as to that".</p>
   <p>This awakening of Russian patriotism Lozovsky considers as the justifiable and inevitable answer to the coalition formed by Japan and Germany.</p>
   <p>Whether any revival of patriotism in Soviet Russia is occurring is debatable, and moreover, the Bolsheviks understand patriotism in their own way; but to call Stakhanov's movement a particular form of patriotism is, of course, impossible.</p>
   <p>Stakhanov's movement is nothing else than an effort on the part of some workers to work harder and earn more. The same kind of patriotism is professed by workers in those capitalist enterprises where the piece-work system is established.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0639.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>To connect Stakhanov's movement with patriotism, socialism, or any other ideal is also impossible because the Bolsheviks themselves no longer believe in ideals of any kind.</p>
   <p>W. de Ormesson, the French Journalist, quite aptly remarked recently that "Soviet Russia finds itself now in the troughs of reaction. The reverse movement is applied in all spheres. The Bolsheviks now burn up what they used to revere and revere that which they used to burn."</p>
   <p>Followers of Stakhanov in their talk with Molotov, the Soviet premier, attributed their enthusiasm not to any lofty aspiration of the sort mentioned by Lozovsky but, putting it in a rather crude form, to the demands of the stomach. They said:</p>
   <p>"We work more strenuously and efficiently because each one of us works for himself. One who wants to earn more can do so".</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0640.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"If we consider", says de Ormesson, "that such tendencies among workers not only are not concealed but on the contrary are widely publicized by the Soviet authorities, it becomes clear how far along the road of bankruptcy the Soviet system and its doctrine have gone".</p>
   <p>Further on the Frenchman reveals to what gods the Bolsheviks at present bow down.</p>
   <p>"Daily", says he, "the Soviet papers render praise to the cult of country and army. The press advocates the preservation of family ties and calls upon parents to fulfill their duties to their children. Divorce is denounced as a social evil. The authorities in every possible way try to instill into the masses a sense of the value of individual effort. The return to the cult of individuality and rank is being accomplished at the rate of a hundred miles an hour. The state sets an example by gradually refusing to subsidize undertakings operated at a loss and by preaching <pb facs="5423967_1_0641.jpg" n="5"/>the doctrine of sound economy".</p>
   <p>And all this has nothing whatsoever to do with the kind of socialism to which the Bolsheviks formerly aspired, just as the Stakhanov movement has nothing to do with patriotism.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
