<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-07">Mar. 7, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">President Roosevelt's Suggestions</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0425</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0425.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-07">Mar. 7, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">PRESIDENT ROOSEVELT'S SUGGESTIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Roosevelt, in his speech last Monday relative to the functioning of the N. R. A. and delivered before a large assembly of manufacturers, made a number of good suggestions. Whether these suggestions will be realized is another matter. The President told the industrialists that the Government could not carry on its shoulders, as heretofore, the entire burden of supporting twenty million people (over eleven million on relief, over four million employed on public works projects, over one million war veterans, a great number of Government employees, and many others receiving Government aid).</p>
   <p>According to official figures, the N. R. A. program has decreased the number of unemployed by approximately two million men. But if we consider the total number of unemployed, this figure, however important, is quite insignificant. Thus, it is obvious that even up to this time the struggle to relieve the unemployment situation has been carried on at the expense of the Government <pb facs="5423967_1_0426.jpg" n="2"/>and not at the expense of industrialists and manufacturers. Now, according to the President's suggestion, the industrialists should take upon their shoulders, if not the whole, at least a part of the burden of unemployment. To make this possible, the President suggests that the manufacturers shorten working hours and increase the number of workers in their plants. The President, however, expressed himself in most decisive terms against the lowering of wages in connection with the reduction in the hours of the work day, a practice which has been prevalent in many industries, according to the President. The President declared that wages should be raised rather than lowered, even while the working time is reduced, as only then, in the President's opinion, will the purchasing power of the population increase. Such an increase in purchasing power will in turn stimulate all industry to higher production, and will make possible a general improvement in the economic life of the country. "The reduction of working time accompanied by the lowering of wages will not bring any benefits to the people," said the President. The President also stated that the workers should enjoy complete freedom in organizing their own unions and electing their own officers; otherwise they would be forced to accept the <pb facs="5423967_1_0427.jpg" n="3"/>unions sponsored by the employers.</p>
   <p>The industrialists who listened carefully to the President's speech applauded heartily, and then declared that they would support all of his measures intended to relieve the unemployment situation and the economic crisis. Only a few of them, the more conservative ones, were apparently not satisfied with the President's speech. They declared that the President's remarks and suggestions were directed not toward economic regeneration but toward economic ruin and the destruction of American industry.</p>
   <p>However, one cannot attach much significance to these loud expressions of enthusiasm on the part of the industrialists, for everyone is well aware that they actually do all they can to evade or break the laws and regulations intended to improve general conditions. There is no doubt that if Congress enacts any of the President's suggestions, many manufacturers will try to evade or get around them, as they do now with the N. R. A. codes. The near future will show how the manufacturers will follow the suggestions which they have so loudly applauded.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
