<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title>,
<date when="1928-08">Aug. 1928</date>.
<title level="a">"Learn English."</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0106</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0106.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 3</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russkoye Obozrenie</title>,
<date when="1928-08">Aug. 1928</date>.
<title level="a">"LEARN ENGLISH."</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 30.. If, on one of these beautiful days, you desire to travel around the world and visit all the countries, what language, do you think, will be most useful to you? English, unquestionably. In this language you will be understood wherever there are civilized inhabitants. This language is used in England and her colonies, Canada, Australia, South Africa, India, etc. English is speken in the United States, parts of China, and in the large cities of Japan.</p>
   <p>You will find people capable of speaking English in all corners of the world. The English language is the official language of the two wealthiest nations in the world: England and the United States. What this means can be seen from the following figures:</p>
   <p>Great Britain alone cooupies fifteen million square miles or about one-quarter of the surface of the globe, not including the seas and oceans. Its population totals 400 million people and almost all, if not speak the English language, at least understand it.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0107.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The territory of the United States covers over three million square miles, with a population of 118 million people. And all speak English. In other words, knowing the English language, you can travel freely in a territory having a population of 518 million. It is not necessary to discuss in lengthy detail the role the English language plays in the United States.</p>
   <p>Any Russian immigrant who has lived several years in the United States, without having learned to speak and write English, might relate of his failures and ill fortune, which happened to be his fate largely because of his lack of knowledge of the language of this country.</p>
   <p>It is very difficult for a Russian who does not know the English language to live in America. He is forced to accept the lowest labor; he is cheated and robbed by whoever pleases to do so. Besides this, the hundreds of insults and meckeries received by the "greenhorn," are not pleasant.</p>
   <p>In contrast, a Russian who speaks English feels entirely different and lives considerably better. He will not permit anyone to insult him; he will not be underpaid for his work, and no one will cheat and make a joke of him. On the whole, the Russian who speaks English is much better armed in the fight for his "bread and butter" than the "greenhorn" and "Silent" immigrant.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0108.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Yet it is not as difficult to learn the language as it seems to many. If you desire to learn something you will learn it. However, you must undertake the task in the right way with no fears such as: "I am old; it is too late; it will be difficult, etc." It is understood, that for the practical learning of the language, it is necessary to attend school. The correct accent and the acquaintance with English conversation could be much easier acquired in a school where there are capable teachers and where they speak excellent and correct English. It is not difficult to enroll. There are evening and day schools in every city in the United States and Canada, in which there are no tuition fees. Only willingness to learn on the part of the individual is required.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
