<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Extracts from Constitution of Russian Workers' Cooperative Association of Chicago.</title>
(As printed <date when="1925-07-17">July 17, 1925</date>.)

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0516</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-II.D.8"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0516.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 b</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 8</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Extracts from Constitution of Russian Workers' Cooperative Association of Chicago.</title>
(As printed <date when="1925-07-17">July 17, 1925</date>.)
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>These extracts show the general purpose and scope of the organization, its set up, etc. In the prologue the Cooperative is called a non-partisan organization. The original is in Russian and English. Title in Russian is Ustav-Russkogo Pabochego Kooperativnogo Obshchestva g. Chikago.</p>
   <p>Name: p.17</p>
   <p>Russian Workers' Cooperative Association: (Non-Partisan Organization) Organization to have a corporate seal with its name.</p>
   <p>CHAPTER I</p>
   <p>OBJECT AND PURPOSE</p>
   <p>a. To bring together Russian Workers on economic grounds or field.</p>
   <p>b. To organize workers cooperative restaurants, where all workers could procure nourishing food, prepared from fresh products and sold at reasonable prices.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0517.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>c. To organize cooperative stores, where workers may procure all necessities of life at reasonable prices.</p>
   <p>d. For education and cultural work - Russian Workers Cooperative Association will organize reading rooms, libraries, lectures, educational excursions, etc. and to assist those organized.</p>
   <p>e. Information Bureau - Will keep a list of all Russian organizations, schools, associations, social organizations, and names of local workers, etc.</p>
   <p>f. To keep records of activities of all Russian organizations, schools, etc.</p>
   <p>g. Also to keep records of all municipal, state and social institutions.</p>
   <p>h. Labor Bureau - To keep registrations of jobless workers, and send such person or persons to place or places of employment, where they are sure to procure work.</p>
   <p>i. Charitable Purpose - To assist Russian workers, in the United States and also if possible to assist Russian orphans in Russia and the United States.</p>
   <p>CHAPTER II</p>
   <p>COMPOSITION OF MEMBERSHIP</p>
   <p>a. Any person of good moral character, men not less than eighteen years of age, <pb facs="5423967_1_0518.jpg" n="3"/>may become a member of the "Russian Workers Cooperative Association", provided that he of she is not an employer.</p>
   <p>b. New applicant may be accepted at the general meeting, by a majority vote of members present, and must be recommended by two members of good standing of not less than three months membership in the Association.</p>
   <p>c. Membership dues must be paid before the new applicant is accepted, and in case of rejection, money to be refunded.</p>
   <p>d. All members must obey the constitution and rules and regulations of the Russian Workers Cooperative Association.</p>
   <p>CHAPTER III.</p>
   <p>RETIRING MEMBERS</p>
   <p>1. Any member may be discharged from the Russian Workers Cooperative Association by a majority of votes with two-thirds of all members present at the regular meeting, for the following reasons:</p>
   <p>a. For breach of Constitution or rules and regulations.</p>
   <p>b. For act or acts detrimental to any member, members or their family or <pb facs="5423967_1_0519.jpg" n="4"/>families.</p>
   <p>c. For mismanagement, concealment of the Association's property, money, or goods.</p>
   <p>d. For any act which will undermine the existence of the Russian Workers Cooperative Association.</p>
   <p>2. Discharged members may receive their membership dues after thirty days.</p>
   <p>3. Members who voluntarily resign from the Russian Workers Cooperative Association must inform the Russian Workers Cooperative Association at the regular meeting, showing the reason for the resignation. Resigned members will receive their dues from the Russian Workers Cooperative Association.</p>
   <p>4. Accepted reasons for leaving the Russian Workers Cooperative Association and exception thereto are as follows:</p>
   <p>a. Leaving the U. S. A. for a long period, or permanently.</p>
   <p>b. Leaving the State of Illinois for some remote state in the U. S. A.</p>
   <p>c. For some other reason recognized by the regular meeting of the Russian Cooperative Association.</p>
   <p>5. Resigned members applying for reinstatement will be accepted according <pb facs="5423967_1_0520.jpg" n="5"/>to the rules pertaining to the acceptance of new members.</p>
   <p>6. Members discharged will not be reinstated at any future time.</p>
   <p>CHAPTER IV</p>
   <p>MEETINGS.</p>
   <p>1. The meetings are divided into three classes:</p>
   <p>a. General</p>
   <p>b. Regular</p>
   <p>c. Special meetings.</p>
   <p>a. General meeting is called once every six months for the purpose of electing new directors, committees, choosing or appointing all other officers, managers,etc., and also to give a semi-annual account of the Association's activities, accounting of directors, committees, managers, and all other officer or officers responsible for the conduct of the Russian Workers Cooperative Association's business, and its financial standing.</p>
   <p>b. Regular meetings are called monthly for discussions of all current affairs of the Russian Workers Cooperative Association to hear reports, from the board of directors, various committees, various managers,etc., and also receiving new applications for membership and installing new members, etc.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0521.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>c. Special meetings are called by the Chairman of the Board of Directors or by the investigation or auditing committees, in cases requiring immediate attention.</p>
   <p>d. All meetings are considered in order when attended by one-half of all members. A special meeting requires an attendance of one-half of all membership. The second and each succeeding meeting called for discussion of the same subject requires any number of members, but not less than 10% of the membership.</p>
   <p>CHAPTER V.</p>
   <p>MANAGEMENT.</p>
   <p>1. The supreme executive power and the management is vested in the general membership meeting of the Russian Workers Cooperative Association.</p>
   <p>All decisions of general meetings are taken as final in all matters pertaining to employes and all members of the Russian Workers Cooperative Association.</p>
   <p>2. Board of Directors consists of ten members, elected at the general meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0522.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>OFFICERS.</p>
   <p>The Chairman of the Board of Directors, President, Vice-President, Recording and the Financial Secretaries, and other offices if necessary.</p>
   <p>3. All executives, managers, financial secretary, cashiers, messengers who are entrusted with money, real or personal property or anything of value must be bonded. The cost of bond is to be paid by the Russian Workers Cooperative Association.</p>
   <p>CHAPTER VII</p>
   <p>FINANCES OF THE ASSOCIATION.</p>
   <p>1. Means of the Russian Workers Cooperative Association consists of the following:</p>
   <p>a. Income from Commercial enterprises.</p>
   <p>b. From enterprises given by the Russian Workers Cooperative Association such as, Shows, concerts, picnics, etc.</p>
   <p>c. Membership entrance dues of $25.00 per member</p>
   <p>d. From voluntary donations to the Association by anyone.</p>
   <p>e. Membership dues of $25.00 is good during the life of a member and may be assigned by him to anyone with the approval of the Russian Workers Cooperative Association at the regular meeting.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0523.jpg" n="8"/>
   <p>f. $25.00 membership dues may be increased or decreased at the discretion of members.</p>
   <p>2. Members of the Russian Cooperative Association do not receive any profits or income from membership dues or from any enterprises.</p>
   <p>CHAPTER IX</p>
   <p>This constitution may be abridged, enlarged, or new constitution may be made with the consent of three-fourths of the total membership, but such change or new constitution must be in accordance with the charter granted to the Russian Workers Cooperative Association.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
