<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-20">July 20, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">An Example Worthy of Emulation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0037</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0037.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-20">July 20, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">AN EXAMPLE WORTHY OF EMULATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the Russian colony in Chicago there lives a very interesting family named Sharov. The Sharovs came here from Western Russia, province of Minok, more than twenty years ago. Like most Russians in America, Sharov first planned to stay in America for only several years, then to return to Russia with some money which would enable him to live a better life than he had been living before he left Russia. However, Sharov established a family in this country, and his life became more and more firmly engrafted into the American social texture and the American way of life. Then he knew that he was here for good, and he turned his attention to his children. He concentrated all his efforts on giving a good education to his three sons. Though of frail and delicate health, he worked hard as a laborer to save enough money to assure a continuous education to his three boys, who were good students and had a desire for knowledge. In his long years of <pb facs="5423967_1_0038.jpg" n="2"/>constant struggle and labor, his accomplishments were many. Sharov used to say that he would rather invest all his savings in the education of his children than keep them in the bank. His judgment proved to have been correct in more respects than one.</p>
   <p>Mr. Sharov's three sons are now graduates of the University of Illinois. The oldest, Basil, is a mining engineer. He was offered a position as instructor in one of the universities in Pennsylvania. Sharov's second son, Alexander, is a mechanical engineer. The third son, John, also is an engineer. Thus, a Russian peasant, himself hardly literate, was able to bring up and educate his children in spite of seemingly insurmountable difficulties and backbreaking hardships.</p>
   <p>These three young Russian-Americans are a splendid example for other Russian boys and girls to emulate. Their father should be a pattern for other Russian fathers to follow. Whenever parents notice in their children a desire for <pb facs="5423967_1_0039.jpg" n="3"/>knowledge, and when their children make good progress in school, they should spare no effort to enable their children to continue their studies and to complete their education in a higher institution of learning.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
