<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-05">Mar. 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">There Should Be No Strikes</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0479</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.2.a.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0479.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I D 2 a (4)</item>
     <item>I D 2 a (3)</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-03-05">Mar. 5, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THERE SHOULD BE NO STRIKES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Why do miners leave their work and go out on strike? Why do workers in general go out on strike? One may perhaps say that strikes are the result of petty squabbles, that workers strike because of their own foolishness. But this is not at all the case. Workers strike only when they are forced to. They strike only when they are forced by the mine owners to take some action, when they cannot food their families on what they earn, when the worker is treated like a beast of burden, when he is not considered a human being at all.</p>
   <p>During strikes, when workers leave their jobs and attempt to improve their standard of living, scores and often hundreds of thousands of workers join their ranks. The strikers' demands are just; they are directed at the owners of the mines and factories where the workers are employed. Their demands are not addressed to the city, state, or Federal administrations. The demands are usually of an economic character. They usually concern only employers of labor. Workers, as a rule, strive only to better their own conditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0480.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>In the strike struggle, unions appear as the vanguard of the fighting front. They play a very important role in the labor movement. Wherever the union is not recognized, the workers demand its recognition. Of course, the majority of the unions go through all the necessary legal formalities, but they do so because they attach no significance and importance to the procedure.</p>
   <p>Workers strike against factory owners, against mine owners, but the judicial and police authorities are called out against the workers. These say that workers should not strike. They claim that strikes are acts directed against the law. In order to sway public opinion and justify the actions of industrialists against workers, the mercenary press spreads false rumors during strikes to the effect that the strikers are really not the workers, that the workers do not want to strike, that they are compelled to strike by some agents--by agitators and propagandists--that these agents' final aim is not to win the strike, but to provoke revolution, to overthrow the capitalist system, to do away with the existing form of government. And the press claims that in order to prevent incipient revolt, it is necessary <pb facs="5423967_1_0481.jpg" n="3"/>to take appropriate and forceful action against the striking workers.</p>
   <p>This, approximately, is the way the striking tailors are being treated. The capitalists forget that the spirit of protest and indignation is generated by the injustices of the Social order and not by the agitators' propaganda. We see clearly that the capitalists themselves are their own gravediggers, and that their system will perish.</p>
   <p>Instead of recognizing the just demands of the workers, the capitalists try to make it appear that the workers' demands are not aimed at the improvement of their conditions, but at the destruction of the existing government. This is done despite the fact that the United States Constitution guarantees workers the right to strike. The same situation is taking place in connection with the strike conducted by the workers of the Gleen Alden Coal Company. The workers had declared a strike, and the company appealed to the courts for an injunction. The injunction was granted and this meant that the strikers had no right to picket the mine.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0482.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>On what ground did Judge Valentine outlaw the strike? He did it on the ground that the United Mine Workers' representatives declared in court that the miners' union had nothing to do with the strike declaration. But no matter what we think of the Anthracite Miners' Union, we cannot deny the fact that this Union still has power over a section of the coal miners and this is the Union which declared the strike.</p>
   <p>Everyone understands that an industrialist's profits are more if he pays less to his workers and makes them work longer hours, and for that reason alone it is easy to understand the motives which drive workers to strike for higher wages and shorter hours.</p>
   <p>The workers should unite in one big union of free and independent toilers, should join the ranks of the army of labor and hew a path toward a new social order under which there shall be no exploitation of man by man.</p>
   <p>Unemployed Miner</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
