<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Russian Herald, (Russkii Viestnik)</title>,
<date when="1924-04-12">4/12/24</date>.
<title level="a">The Life of Russians in the City of Chicago. the Children of the Russian Colony.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Russian Herald, (Russkii Viestnik)</title>,
<date when="1924-04-12">4/12/24</date>.
<title level="a">THE LIFE OF RUSSIANS IN THE CITY OF CHICAGO. THE CHILDREN OF THE RUSSIAN COLONY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The classes in the Russian schools are being assiduously attended by the children. If there were more schools, still more children would be visiting them.</p>
   <p>There are only seven or eight Russian schools for children in Chicago. The quarters they occupy are small and cannot by far accomodate all those who would like to study in these schools. Besides, some of these schools have been opened only recently and the Russian children have not yet got quite used to going to these schools.</p>
   <p>From talks with the teachers and the parents one gathers that the children like going to these Russian schools, are interested in the study of their parents' native language and of the customs, manners and history of the Russian people. The children study fairly well.</p>
   <p>But it is pretty hard for them to pursue these studies. At school and in the street the children hear only the English language spoken; at home they talk Russian, but their Russian language is not clear of foreign admixtures; finally, many of their school- and playmates speak Polish.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0063.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Thus, the children "get lost" in this maze of three languages. It is no easy matter for them to get out of this maze.</p>
   <p>In spite of that the children make considerable progress.</p>
   <p>The Russian schools are doing a great work in teaching these children the Russian language. Otherwise the children would grow up so that the native land of their fathers would be quite foreign to them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
