<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-03">June 3, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The Future of the Philippine Islands</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0711</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0711.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-03">June 3, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE FUTURE OF THE PHILIPPINE ISLANDS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In connection with the recent Philippine insurrection and the referendum on the question of independence for the Philippine Islands the British press devotes a great deal of attention to these Islands. The newspapers consider that the United States made a grave political error by according independence to them.</p>
   <p>The Manchester Guardian, for instance, writes:</p>
   <p>"Although relinquishment of control over an Asiatic people may be considered as an act of noble unselfishness, as a matter of fact this particular step is the result of the most arrogant and cynical conduct of the American sugar refiners. The latter are afraid of the competition from the Philippine Islands <pb facs="5423967_1_0712.jpg" n="2"/>and adopt trade reprisals which seriously threaten the future of the Philippines."</p>
   <p>Pointing to the tremendous growth of Japanese influence on the Philippine Islands, the author of the article quotes his conversation with one of the representatives of the Japanese government, who declared:</p>
   <p>"We want to penetrate the Philippine Islands for the purposes of trade. We shall not penetrate the Philippines for any other purpose as long as peace and order endure on the Islands. But if chaos prevails in the independent Philippines, it will be the duty of any civilized nation to show its hand and apply force."</p>
   <p>This means that if disorders break out in the independent Philippines, Japanese imperialists will not hesitate to send armed forces for the purpose of "re-establishing order" and in reality for seizure of the Islands. As far <pb facs="5423967_1_0713.jpg" n="3"/>as disorders are concerned they can be provoked by the Japanese imperialists themselves. Investigation of the recent insurrection on the Islands reveals that the disorders were inspired by the communists and bear all the earmarks of a communist revolt. The threads of the conspiracy were traced to Tokio. This connection is proved by the fact that the leading culprit of the rioters is at present in Japan in the capacity of "an honorable guest" and is being carefully guarded by the Japanese police.</p>
   <p>European and American communists are carrying on a criminal activity which is not confined to the Philippine Islands. As is well known from their own pronouncement, they continue a relentless struggle for the liberation of all Asiatic peoples from the domination of European and American imperialists, for their complete independence, and in reality they assist Japanese imperialists, for as soon as these peoples find themselves independent, they will immediately fall under the yoke of Japanese domination. If China should prove unable to offer any effective resistance to the Japanese aggressors then we should not even consider the possibility of any serious rebuff to the Japanese designs <pb facs="5423967_1_0714.jpg" n="4"/>from such countries as the Dutch possessions, Indo-China, the Philippines, or other colonial territories.</p>
   <p>This is well known to Englishmen, and that is why the Manchester Guardian writes:</p>
   <p>"The possibility of Japanese control over the Philippine Islands arouses anxiety among British subjects. They are apprehensive that Japanese domination over Manila will constitute a threat and a danger to Hong Kong, and that Japanese domination in the air and over the strategically important sea routes may influence the Chinese people to increase import duties on all foreign products except those of Japan. Englishmen are also worried lest the concessions made by the United States to the aspirations of Philippine nationalism may embolden analogous elements in British India and the Malay Islands, and lest such steps on the part of the United States may open the road for Japanese expansion toward the South and particularly in the direction of Australia".</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0715.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The communists know, of course, that small Asiatic countries cannot remain independent as long as Japanese imperialism exists, but they are not worried by this fact. They still cling to the slogan:</p>
   <p>"The worse it is, the better it is for us."</p>
   <p>They think that the sooner the Asiatic peoples fall under the yoke of a worse domination (that is under the Japanese yoke), the quicker those peoples will accept the communist faith.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
