<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-17">Mar. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Illiteracy</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0045</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-V.A.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0045.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>V A 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1934-03-17">Mar. 17, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">ILLITERACY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is now time to look with open eyes at the old Russian colony in America. The opinion prevails that the old Russian immigrants have made praiseworthy progress both individually and as a group during their stay in this country. This opinion, however, does not correspond with the facts. Illiteracy among the Russian group is still so overwhelming that it would be disastrous to try to hide this fact or to continue any self-deception. It is true that a part of our Russian group struggled hard against illiteracy and won the battle, but this part is so small that it cannot even be noticed in the large mass of our illiterate people. We have to look with the microscope in order to find those individuals among our old Russian immigrants who know how to read and write. The great majority of the old Russian immigrants have remained as untutored and ignorant as they were when they came to America more than a score of years ago. The cultural level of these people has not been raised to any marked degree. They occupy the lowest rung on the social ladder and will continue to hold this unenviable position so long as they remain unschooled and ignorant.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0046.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It is customary to put the blame for the ignorance of the people of a given country on the existing social order and on the system of government in that country, on the grounds that it does not provide sufficiently for the education of its citizens. It must be said that this is not the whole truth, as this idea in many cases does not conform to reality. In our times every country maintains schools which enable every man to learn how to read and write. Even czarist Russia, lagging behind in public education, had elementary schools in even the smallest provincial town and in many villages, and every man who really wanted to learn the rudiments of grammar and writing could do so.</p>
   <p>It was one thing for the Russian peasant to remain illiterate when he lived in a small town or in a village in Russia, where he could get by without any education whatsoever, but quite another thing when he found himself in America. City life in America is vastly different from the bucolic life of the Russian village. Here it is absolutely indispensable to know how to read and write; without this knowledge it is impossible to turn around or make a single step in any direction. Nevertheless, an overwhelming majority <pb facs="5423967_1_0047.jpg" n="3"/>of the Russians in America have not acquired a knowledge of reading and writing.</p>
   <p>Illiterate people cannot truly understand and appreciate the value of education, which opens the world to the eyes and to the mind. The illiterate man, no matter how much he may be endowed by nature, will never be able to develop his natural abilities. The ability to read and write is the foundation of all future development and future attainments of a person in any field of endeavor.</p>
   <p>The system of government, unfavorable social conditions and other reasons cannot be solely responsible for the ignorance of the people. Even with the best and most liberal system of education, there will be people who cannot read and write, if they have no desire to acquire that knowledge. This is exactly the position of the Russian immigrants in America. In every city in America, large or small, there are well-equipped American schools which offer everyone an opportunity to learn how to read and write the English language. But have we taken advantage of this opportunity? No. We have <pb facs="5423967_1_0048.jpg" n="4"/>fallen into the habit of thinking that we have done all we can, and usually we blame circumstances for all our failings, our shortcomings and our ignorance.</p>
   <p>In order to raise the educational and cultural level of our people, it is necessary that the people themselves, individually, make the greatest effort to improve their minds. No one can learn how to read and write without determination and personal effort. The illiterates are not only those who are absolutely unable to read and write, but also those who can read and write a little but who cannot speak correctly or write correctly. Almost all so-called literate people in our group are persons who stopped in the middle of the road<gap unit="chars" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>-between illiteracy and a creditable knowledge of the art of reading and writing.</p>
   <p>It is not difficult, when there is a will, to overcome illiteracy, this great handicap to a better life for so many of our people. In two years every man can acquire a complete knowledge of reading and writing by devoting to study only spare moments from his work and other activities. If our <pb facs="5423967_1_0049.jpg" n="5"/>Russian people would spend as much time in learning to read and write as they spend in drinking and playing cards, we would have no illiterates among our group. We also often hear the statement that it is too late now to begin such an arduous task. This is not true, as our group consists mostly of middle-aged people, and this period of a man's life is quite suitable for acquiring new knowledge. If a person has only enough interest and enough determination, the "too late" excuse will disappear.</p>
   <p>Leo Tolstoy once said that only education can raise the human race to its proper place in the universe, and free it from darkness and deep-rooted ignorance. And general enlightment can be achieved only after the complete overcoming of illiteracy. The art of reading and writing serves as a means of further development of our intellectual faculties.</p>
   <p>All you illiterates, strive now to acquire a knowledge of reading and writing. Our times require it.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
