<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-09">July 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">The American Communists Are Changing into Reformers</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5423967_1_0702</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-russian #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-01-29">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-29">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0702.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>RUSSIAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Rassviet (The Dawn)</title>,
<date when="1935-07-09">July 9, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">THE AMERICAN COMMUNISTS ARE CHANGING INTO REFORMERS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The American Communist party is being gradually transformed into a party of reformers. The right wing of the American Communist party differs strikingly in its slogans, its resolutions, and in the editorial articles of its press, from the orthodox Communist party and its leaders.</p>
   <p>It is difficult to explain the reason for this sharp variation between the two groups of the American Reds. Perhaps some of the American Communists have swung to the right because they have at last become convinced that communism in Russia has brought more slavery, and not liberation, to the workers of the Red Empire. Or it may be that they have turned reformers upon orders from Stalin, who, as everybody knows, has liquidated the Old Bolsheviks either by executions, prison sentences, or concentration camps in Siberia.</p>
   <pb facs="5423967_1_0703.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Red reformers do not speak in their press about world revolution, about the overthrow of the American government, and about changing the American economic system. They speak of peace and understanding between the Communists and Socialists in America, and of brotherhood with the American trade-unions. They even advocate the creation of a new workers' party, which would participate in the elections and bring about social changes in the country by means of the ballot box, without resort to violence. The people who do not know of and who do not notice the new trend in the American Communist party are the foreign-born American Communists, especially the Russian Communists in America. This can be ascribed to their ignorance in political matters, and, in part, to their insufficient knowledge of the English language and their inability to understand correctly what they read in the English-language newspapers. For this reason, they still cling to the old Communist slogans of world revolution, and are waiting for the day when America will become a communist dictatorship, when they will be made the commissars over one hundred and thirty million American people. These fools--these human dregs, as they often are--do not seem to realize that their Red leaders look down upon them <pb facs="5423967_1_0704.jpg" n="3"/>as upon cattle. And if these rustics and hoodlums are addressed by their leaders as "comrades," it is because they are needed to spread Red propaganda, and to contribute and collect money for various Red funds.</p>
   <p>No less than ninety per cent of all Russian Communists in America belong to this class of fools and rustics who follow blindly their clever leaders. The American Communists, for instance, no longer send their protests and demands to Washington, as they used to do; instead, the Russian United Front in New York (the Communist organization), continues this practice, as though it were a diplomatic post entitled to transact official business with the United States Government in Washington. In one of its recent "notes" to Washington, the Russian United Front demanded the removal of Admiral Sterling from his post in the United States Navy. Very frequent are its "notes" and protests to the United States Congress against this or that bill about to become law. It may be that the real purpose of all these "notes" and protests to Washington is publicity; but in any case, these fools from the Russian United Front, by their irresponsible actions and their crackpot behavior, <pb facs="5423967_1_0705.jpg" n="4"/>expose the entire Russian group in America to discredit and ridicule. If, however, they think that they will soon become commissars in the Communist United States, we should like to express our regrets, our pity, and our compassion for their disappointment. If this supposition is true, then we may be certain that they have not yet freed themselves from the Old Bolshevik illusions, and that they have not the slightest idea of what their leaders are doing and where, at this time, their hopes and their interests lie.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
