<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-03">Mar. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Way It's Done</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Editorial]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0725</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0725.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-03">Mar. 3, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE WAY IT'S DONE</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Editorial]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is hardly any doubt left among German-Americans that a certain portion of this miserable anti-German war propaganda, which is served them every day for breakfast, bears the unmistakable trade mark "Made in U.S.A." But the general public as a rule is not aware of the amount of callousness the American well poisoners employ in their contemptible calling. These worthy gentlemen figure that the memory of their readers for the details of their propaganda campaign paid for by British money for the greater glory of the Union Jack is a rather small one and that the poor dopes, after the truth has been revealed, do not recall the name of the author of the lie and that the interest in a rectification of a falsehood is superseded by interest in later "war news," equally phoney of course. By that time the excitement about the previous reports has completely died down. Usually this calculation pans out all right. And then we must not forget that, of all such malicious <pb facs="5418474_5_0726.jpg" n="2"/>falsehoods, calumnies, and lies, something is bound to stick, which was the purpose for publishing it.</p>
   <p>A certain portion of these amazing newspaper lies cannot camouflage their domestic origin. The French-made stories are usually distinguished by a certain degree of criticism and esprit. The English take European conditions into account, and make their lies fit into that framework, if possible. But the American newspaper writer gives free rein to his blooming imagination when producing war stories, and its wings carry him beyond all earthly bounds. This amazing ignorance regarding European geography, history and political, economic and social conditions is a great aid for the unlimited flight for his imagination. But without a certain degree of maliciousness some of the errors which can be found day after day in our English-language papers would even at that be impossible. Maliciousness and lack of good will, plus a deliberate or unconscious divergence from the avowed impartiality, are the reasons for many newspaper notices which, according to the temperament of a better informed reader, cause either a pitying smile or a fit of anger. Only <pb facs="5418474_5_0727.jpg" n="3"/>very few people are aware that many of these alleged "war dispatches" never did originate at the scene of military operations, but were simply clumsy fabrications by a penny-a-line reporter or a vituperative, vitriolic journalist, all doped out at a desk.</p>
   <p>In one of Chicago's most widely circulated papers a story recently appeared about a lady in Battle Creek, Michigan, who had received a letter from her daughter living in Germany, according to which Germany had plenty of food supplies. But the lady removed the stamp from the envelope and found written there, "We are starving." One reader of this paper became suspicious and wrote to the lady in Battle Creek, asking for more detailed information. The answer he received was placed at our disposal. The lady in question declared that the article was "absolutely false and lacked any foundation of fact." She had never received any mail from Germany, neither did she have any close relatives there. Her only child was only two years old and consequently incapable of writing any letters to the mother, which would be absurd anyway, since the youngster lived with her and could have asked for <pb facs="5418474_5_0728.jpg" n="4"/>anything it wanted by word of mouth, as children usually do. This reply needs no further comment.</p>
   <p>Not even the English would stoop to such clumsy attempts of duping the American public, although they are Germany's bitter enemies, while the Americans pretend to be "strictly neutral". However, the Chicago fake story which we have exposed here, could be traced to its origin in England. In its original form it was nothing but a harmless joke, designed to inject a little humor into the everyday life of the newspaper reader, to divert his thoughts from the tough future thats' facing England. In the English periodical The Argonaut we find the following humorous little story:</p>
   <p>"All letters which English soldiers send home pass the hands of the censor. One fellow, who had four or five letters reduced to nothing by the censor's blue pencil, decided to play a joke on this stern official, and wrote, at the end of his next letter: 'Please look underneath the stamp.' The letter was opened and read by the censor as usual. It took him quite awhile to remove <pb facs="5418474_5_0729.jpg" n="5"/>the stamp with the aid of steam, but you can imagine his disgust when he read the following words: 'Was it tough to get it off?'"</p>
   <p>This harmless joke was utilized by an American busybody, who put a little Yankee flavor in it and in order to make the product of his imagination more convincing, switched the scene to the United States, but cleverly enough not to Chicago itself, and did not hesitate one moment to use the name and address of the lady in Battle Creek for his phoney and slanderous story. The reading public can judge, from this example, how much credence can be put in some of the reports which are inspired by English-American journalists steeped in hatred for Germany.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
