<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-01">Aug. 1, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[Protest Meeting Wins Sanction of Local Groups]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1261</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1261.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-01">Aug. 1, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[PROTEST MEETING WINS SANCTION OF LOCAL GROUPS]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The appeal of the executive board of the local branch of the Deutscher Nationalbund is receiving an enthusiastic response from the various German societies, from many Germans who have no fraternal affiliation, and also from many Chicagoans who are not of German extraction, but who are friendly to the German cause. Thus the mass meeting which is to be held next Wednesday evening in the Auditorium should prove to be a very impressive and effective demonstration, and should show results in Chicago and in every other part of the United States where the English-language press spreads its falsehoods. The larger the attendance, the greater the moral effect will be, and it should not be necessary to remind the Teutons in Chicago that it is the sacred duty of every German in the city to come to this meeting and show the English-language press and those Chicagoans who share the attitude of that press that all the Germans in this city are supporting this movement.</p>
   <p>The Auditorium should not only be filled to capacity, but it should also be necessary to hold an open-air meeting to accomodate those who are unable to <pb facs="5418474_5_1262.jpg" n="2"/>gain admission to the building! If the threatening war is averted--and happily that is still possible--this fortunate turn of events should prevent no one from coming to the meeting; for, in this event, instead of serving as a protest, the assembly could become the joyful celebration of a great victory....</p>
   <p>Although the executive board of the Deutsch-Amerikanischer Nationalbund did not recommend that a general parade be held before the opening of the mass meeting, it would undoubtedly increase the moral effect of the demonstration if as many societies as possible gathered at some designated place in the farther end of the city and then marched to the Auditorium. Perhaps it would be best if one of the veterans' societies of the Turners would assume the leadership and make the necessary preparations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
