<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-03-11">March 11, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">Editorial about the great Commotion caused by the non-reelection of Charles Sumner as Chairman of the Foreign Relations Committee of the United States Senate.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1367</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1367.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1871-03-11">March 11, 1871</date>.
<title level="a">Editorial about the great Commotion caused by the non-reelection of Charles Sumner as Chairman of the Foreign Relations Committee of the United States Senate.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Sumner has made himself unpopular by his domineering manner. His opposition to the annexation of San Domingo is certainly not the main reason for his removal. Far more important is his attitude in the Alabama question.</p>
   <p>"The great speech which Mr. Sumner made about this topic, two years ago, was so bitterly hostile against England, it almost had the effect of a declaration of war. We then quite agreed with him because we never could sympathize with the idea of a payment of so many dollars and cents as an adequate restoration for the harm done the United States by England under the thin disguise of so-called neutrality. Meanwhile the attitude of the United States towards England has become conciliatory. A court of arbitration is going to make proposals that willcome, in the form of a treaty, before the Senate. Would it, then, be just and proper to leave the duty of reporting on it to a man who has supported a view so diagonally opposed to friendly arrangement? - - - Mr.Sumner is not a little child, who holds completely different opinions about the same issue in 1869 and in 1871. What he said about the relationship of England and the United States on May 1869, we hope was his <pb facs="5418474_5_1368.jpg" n="2"/>true conviction. But in that case, he is not the right man to take the lead when England and the United States compose their differences. Let us add, that in all probability in the future relations between the United States and Germany will be very important and that the attitude that Sumner has taken, toward the Franco-Prussian War (since Ledan), does not make him appear as the right man to manage these relations. Mr.Sumner, in the same way as Wendell Phillips, has described Germany's war against the mob republic of Paris as a barbarous crime. He has spoken against Germany, with such malice, that it would be demanding too much of Germans to expect that we should feel saddened by his fall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
