<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Daily Tribune</title>,
<date when="1914-11-07">Nov. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Irish Join in Protest with Germans. Plan Meeting to Condemn Shipping of Contraband.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0998</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0998.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Chicago Daily Tribune</title>,
<date when="1914-11-07">Nov. 7, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO IRISH JOIN IN PROTEST WITH GERMANS. Plan Meeting To Condemn Shipping Of Contraband.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4.. German and Irish citizens of Chicago will hold two large demonstrations December first in Orchestra Hall and the North Side Turner Hall in condemnation of the exportation of contraband articles of war from the United States to the belligerent nations of Europe.</p>
   <p>Among the Germans appointed to make arrangements for the meeting are Horace L. Brand, Editor, Illinois Staats Zeitung; <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/>. H. Hammell, Peter Ellert, H. Lueders, and Albert N. <gap unit="words" extent="1" reason="illegible"/> y. Irishmen identified with the movement are James T. Clarke, President of the "United Irish Societies" of Chicago; James O'Donnell Storen, Francis B. O'Gallagher P. H. O'Donnell, Judge Joseph E. Ryan, Michael Hartnett, Joseph Fogarty, Thomas P. Bonfield and James L. Devyer.</p>
   <p>It is the object of the demonstrations to urge the passage of laws for the promotion of peace by the prohibition of exportation from the United States of all contraband, except food stuffs. The meetings are called, "in the <pb facs="5418474_5_0999.jpg" n="2"/>Name of Mercy and Humanity," on the theory that to stop the supply of contraband will bring the war to an earlier close.</p>
   <p>Invitations to speak at the demonstrations have been sent to Hugo Muensterberg of Harvard University, Congressman Richard Bartholdt of St. Louis, Henry Vellmer of Davenport, Iowa; Senator George Charberlain of Oregon, Michael J. Ryan of Philadelphia, and James Larkin, the Irish labor leader of Dublin, who is now in New York.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
