<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-10-25">Oct. 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Is it Worth While?</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0453</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0453.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-10-25">Oct. 25, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">IS IT WORTH WHILE?</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The German American committee of Foreign Languages held a meeting under the chairmanship of E. G. Kussevuria. About forty men were present. The object of the meeting was to find ways and means for selling Liberty bonds. That work is well in hand and the result will be worthy of the cause. The cause is America's cause, and the result will be many subscriptions for bonds by German-Americans.</p>
   <p>One of the speakers stated that he was born in Germany and came to the United States twelve years ago. He is now a citizen here. He was in Sweden when America declared war upon the German government. He could have gone from Sweden to Germany. He took inventory of his assets, he held communion with himself, and analyzed his feelings. He decided to come back to the United States and stick with his adopted country.</p>
   <p>He arrived here with a new born feeling of freedom. He severed his racial ments and remained true to his oath of allegiance. His conscience was clear. He had done his duty, and in that knowledge he became strong. No longer a slave of <pb facs="5418474_5_0454.jpg" n="2"/>tradition, he is a freeman in the land of liberty. Every other citizen of the United States may be like this man. Without rancor toward Germany, with admiration, for many German characteristics and achievements, the American of German birth feels a new freedom. Is it not worth while to defend the cradle of Liberty; to maintain this country as the land of the Free?</p>
   <p>The German-American committee of the Foreign Language section of the Liberty Loan committee will be glad to assist you with advice upon request.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
