<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-01-28">Jan. 28, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Collection</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0624</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0624.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-01-28">Jan. 28, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE COLLECTION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We submit the fifty-fifth report of the treasurer. From January 13 to January 27 the fund had increased $2,521.05. The grand total yesterday at 12 P.M. was $353,657.10.</p>
   <p>During the session of the Executive Committee on January 26, the following resolution was proposed:</p>
   <p>"We deeply mourn the demise of our vice-president, F. W. Hess, who had been so intimately connected with our work since its very beginning. He always showed a great understanding for the aims of the Aid Society, and profound sympathy for its efforts. His departure affects all of us. As an expression of our sorrow let our secretary make a copy of these resolutions which shall be sent to the bereaved family."</p>
   <p>In recognition of the active support which the Hamburg-American Line gave the <pb facs="5418474_5_0625.jpg" n="2"/>Aid Society, by enabling it to use their premises gratuitously, the Executive Committee offered the following resolutions:</p>
   <p>"Be it resolved, that we herewith express our gratitude to Mr. A. C. E. Schmidt, representative of the Hamburg-American Line; that through his generosity his entire establishment was placed at our disposal; that we thank him for the splendid co-operation and interest his employees have shown in this worthy cause.</p>
   <p>"Be it further resolved, that these resolutions be entered in our minutes and that a copy thereof be sent to Mr. Schmidt."</p>
   <p>The American Consul-General at Ottawa, sends us very interesting news regarding the money we sent as a Christmas gift to the war prisoners in Canada. In the prison camp of Amherst tobacco was bought with the money, in conformity with the request of the inmates. In Kapus Kasing another prison camp, a huge celebration was held. The Commander, stationed at Spirit Lake, writes that <pb facs="5418474_5_0626.jpg" n="3"/>with the money he bought 1528 lbs. of geese, which were served as a holiday feast for the prisoners. The letters prove beyond a doubt that we were able to bring joy to these people, and that we have made the festival days more pleasant for them.</p>
   <p>Regarding the shipment of clothing, we have been notified that they arrived and were distributed among the various camps.</p>
   <p>An alliance of women known as the Ladies Aid, is now affiliated with us. Their main interest is gathering, packing, and sending clothing to the imprisoned. The headquarters are at 160 N. La Salle Street where the shipments originate. Whatever is received, such as wearing apparel, underwear, shoes, etc., will be carefully inspected and assorted; mended and repaired if necessary, and disinfected by the Board of Health. The collection of money for prisoners of war in Siberia, Canada, and other countries is also within the scope of the Ladies Aid. We expect great accomplishments from these capable <pb facs="5418474_5_0627.jpg" n="4"/>women who have dedicated themselves to our cause and we fully recognize the value of their support.</p>
   <p>German and Austro-Hungarian Aid Society. Charles H. Wacker, President; Oscar F. Mayer, Treasurer; Julius Goldzier, Secretary; Karl Eitel, Chairman of the Finance Committee.</p>
   <p>Stations where money will be accepted and collection lists distributed: Central, Hamburg-American Line, 150 W. Randolph St., Illinois Staats-Zeitung, 24 South Fifth Ave., Abendpost, 223 W. Washington St.</p>
   <p>[A list is contained which shows the amounts that range from twenty-five cents to one hundred dollars and were donated by individuals, firms, and clubs. The German Male Chorus, Kankakee, Ill., one hundred dollars; Edward Wedeles, one hundred dollars. These were the largest sums contributed. The second list contained an accounting of the one dollar remittances, the third shows fifty <pb facs="5418474_5_0628.jpg" n="5"/>cent donations, and the last shows twenty-five cent gifts. Separate paragraphs show items for the prisoners of war in Siberia, ranging from fifty cents up. Also $36.55, collected by Mr. Karl Antal for the Hungarian war prisoners in Siberia. German Defense Fund: Aid for German children $13.25 from Wheaton Ill., lowest amount one dollar. Collection boxes: Hamburg-American Line $20.24; German Imperial Consulate $9.53; Adolph Georg $10.25. Out of town items: Buffalo, N. Y., $20.00; Elgin, Ill., $10.00.Transl.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
