<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-10-04">Oct. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Citizens of German Origin, Especially, [Should Buy Liberty Bonds]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0317</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0317.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-10-04">Oct. 4, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">CITIZENS OF GERMAN ORIGIN, ESPECIALLY, [SHOULD BUY LIBERTY BONDS]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Liberty Loan campaign is in progress. Before October 19 Liberty Bonds to the amount of six billion dollars will--and must!--be absorbed by the American people. That means that every citizen, male or female, must reach into his cash register or pocket and must dig up as much money as possible; he must calculate how much of his anticipated income can be spared during the next few months and must purchase bonds accordingly, using the government installment plan.</p>
   <p>He must, for it is his simple duty to the state of which he is a part, and behind the duty there is force. A citizen can be compelled to do that which is his duty. If citizens should refuse to lend the state the money it needs <pb facs="5418474_5_0318.jpg" n="2"/>at good interest and with the best security in the world, the money will be appropriated in the form of taxes in return for which they will get nothing but tax receipts that may be used, at best, for lighting a pipe or a kitchen stove. In the last analysis, citizens are not doing a favor for the state so much as for themselves when they buy bonds quickly and to the best of their ability. Quickly to subscribe for the Fourth Liberty Loan is nothing but a duty to themselves and their loved ones; which the instinct of self-preservation and the natural desire to preserve their possessions demand.</p>
   <p>That is the way to look at duty, the duty of all citizens alike. He who looks at it the right way will subscribe for as much as he can.</p>
   <p>Men and women of German descent have recognized this duty more than others, because they are used to getting to the bottom of things and to thinking things out thoroughly and earnestly. They did their duty and are now doing it in every <pb facs="5418474_5_0319.jpg" n="3"/>respect, and they will do it again, and better; and, if that is not possible they will do it more willingly than ever before.</p>
   <p>When, formerly, they were asked to do their share, they acquiesced, for the most part, but often with a heavy heart. Sometimes complaint was made that the duties imposed on the American people would be doubly hard and painful for them to bear. This was in the nature of things, because at the beginning duty and sentiments were in a painful conflict, and their sense of duty had to win a victory over their natural sympathies for their native land.</p>
   <p>But today this no longer holds true. Reason and duty have gained the upper hand, banishing all doubt and painful indecision; and today, as German-Americans correctly size up the situation, their hearts should be filled only with courage, pride, and hope for the future.</p>
   <p>Today they have special reason for wishing full and quick success for the <pb facs="5418474_5_0320.jpg" n="4"/>Fourth Liberty Loan. What once was a plain or even painful duty should today be a privilege, a wonderful opportunity, and, as they serve their adopted country, they are also serving those to whom their heartfelt sympathies still belong, in spite of war and need; they are serving their blood relations over there, the German people; they are helping to gain victory for America--and the Fourth Liberty Loan is to insure America's victory!--a much-desired and just peace, and the liberation from unworthy subjection and oppression which Germany so richly deserves.</p>
   <p>Since President Wilson, a week ago in New York, told the world of America's war aims and peace hopes in clear and masterly language; since he declared that a league of all nations had to be established, and that all nations should get justice--full and absolute justice, regardless of whose interests were involved--and declared that within the league of nations no nation or group should be granted special privileges; that there should be no alliances or agreements between single nations directed against other powers--since the President of the United States has promulgated this wonderful message of peace and justice to all peoples of the world, no other element in the United States <pb facs="5418474_5_0321.jpg" n="5"/>has better reason for desiring a quick American victory than the German-Americans. They should be glad to do anything the government asks of them, in order to accomplish America's peace aims, with faithfulness and love for their adopted country and with pride in their own mighty America, fighting for justice and human rights--with faithfulness and love for the people of their own origin; for the German people, to whom justice and peace and liberty will come at last.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
