<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1862-07-31">July 31, 1862</date>.
<title level="a">Recruiting in Cook County</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1436</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1436.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1862-07-31">July 31, 1862</date>.
<title level="a">RECRUITING IN COOK COUNTY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The conference which General Fuller held yesterday with the various recruiting officers, the committees of the Board of Trade, the Mercantile Association, and the Young Men's Christian Association, can only serve to shatter the hope that Cook County's quota of regiments will be filled by voluntary enrollment. We are happy and proud to say that enlistments for service in Hecker's Regiment are an exception; otherwise, results were anything but encouraging. It has been definitely established that sixty-five persons who were authorized to do recruiting have been able to enlist a mere 390 men for service in our armed forces. In the face of this humiliating fact, it would be ridiculous to deny that despite the enthusiasm shown at the mass meetings, and despite the added inducements offered prospective recruits--such as additional bounties, pre-payment of wages, etc.--there can be no thought of providing the regiments that have been required of Cook County, and that conscription must be resorted <pb facs="5418474_5_1437.jpg" n="2"/>to--and the sooner the better.</p>
   <p>It cannot escape the unbiased and keen observer that men from the masses of the people cannot be persuaded, even by the great inducements offered, to risk life or limb for the special benefit and comfort of the wealthy class of citizens who stubbornly refuse to serve their country with their precious bodies, and who think that they have done their duty when they have contributed some of their paltry gold. The conviction is gaining ground in all circles that conscription is the only means of obtaining the soldiers which the Government has asked for, of distributing the burden and cost of the war equally among all classes, and, above all, of forcing the wealthy who are reluctant to enter combat service, who are heartless and unpatriotic, and, in some cases, even hostile, to do their full duty as citizens. If it were our duty to divide the city into districts for the purpose of ascertaining the military power of Chicago and of immediately furnishing the three thousand men required of Cook County, we would devote our attention exclusively to the area bounded by Michigan Avenue, Wabash Avenue, Lake Street, and <pb facs="5418474_5_1438.jpg" n="3"/>South Water Street, assuming that the other residents--the laborers and the tradesmen--have already sent many thousands of men to the battlefields!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
