<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-01-14">Jan. 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Time to Act Is Now</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0816</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0816.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-01-14">Jan. 14, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE TIME TO ACT IS NOW</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The [German] protest against the export of war materials was poorly presented, even though the intentions were good. It was not wide enough in scope. As a result of its having been made into a purely German-American affair, its success and the achievement of its purpose were jeopardized rather than helped.</p>
   <p>It would seem that German sentiments have for a time gained the upper hand over good judgment--certainly no disgrace for us Germans--but it also appears that sometimes the objective has become obscure. In this case one seems to have made a mistake by not playing up to their knowledge of American behavior. But then the position of the German-American element was not clearly defined.</p>
   <p>The identical national differences which led to war in Europe are also present and active over here. The Czechs and the Serbs conducted a very heated <pb facs="5418474_5_0817.jpg" n="2"/>agitation at the beginning of the war, but it did not last long. The most fanatical hotheads were cooled off with the argument that it would not be in the interests of their homelands to make such a noise and clamor.</p>
   <p>We Germans believe that we are within our rights in protesting by mass demonstrations against the malicious defamations of German character and the misrepresentation of Germany's motives. That was only natural; nothing else could be expected, and every American who believes in American principles has admitted, and still admits, that it is our inalienable right as German-born American citizens, to state our case.</p>
   <p>It is a difficult task to uproot the American prejudice against Germany, but the job has to be done, and the more dispassionately we Germans go about it, the more successful we will be. In doing this, we are rendering the best service to our blood brothers, fighting so gallantly over there, against a world of hate and malice. The German Government would hardly be pleased if we should widen the gap which already exists between America and Germany by resorting to noisy <pb facs="5418474_5_0818.jpg" n="3"/>and dashing methods. It is necessary to curb the emotions and to take a sober look into the future. And there are many things to be considered which would never occur to those who are only concerned with the present difficulties of our German compatriots. Sometimes we wish we could let our emotions dictate what we want to say, but that would be incompatible with our responsibility of which we must always be cognizant. If this sense of responsibility were lacking, the press would become worthless and detrimental to the common good. Frankly speaking, it would have been far better for us and for Germany's cause, if we had let time and circumstances work for us a little.</p>
   <p>In an analysis of the situation, it became obvious that some sort of conflict had to develop sooner or later between England and the United States. If the high office of Secretary of State had not been held by a miserable bungler [Bryan], this conflict would have arisen months ago. At that time this amateur was approached by commercial interests engaged in the export business. We are told that the result was negative. Bryan preferred to let the gentlemen be taken care of in the antechamber. He did not have the intestinal fortitude <pb facs="5418474_5_0819.jpg" n="4"/>to talk to them himself. The clash was inevitable--thanks to British tyranny at sea. It was all the more certain, as the British became more and more agressive in exercising their arbitrary control.</p>
   <p>If our protests are to have effect, their moral justification must be imparted to all. We German-Americans surely cannot have become so arrogant as to believe that we alone could guide Congress according to our desires. Justice and fair dealing, and above all, the very interest of our country must categorically demand the things we want done, if we care to obtain the additional co-operation of elements less friendly inclined toward us. This kind of protest is in the offing now. Unless the administration and Congress go to work and do the things that have to be done, public opinion may become a force to be reckoned with. In that case, the legislators will have missed a splendid opportunity and will have dug their political grave for 1916.</p>
   <p>The British reply to the American note is a farce. It is unsatisfactory, <pb facs="5418474_5_0820.jpg" n="5"/>evasive in every respect, and accuses our exporters of dishonesty and smuggling. The administration and the country cannot let the matter rest here. For the sake of international courtesy it would be wise to wait a week or so for the more comprehensive and final reply from the Britishers, but then action should be taken, and we mean drastic action.</p>
   <p>The time has come to use the weapon which the United States has kept in reserve for quite awhile, and which has become keener and more effective as the weeks and months passed by, in proportion as its application became more urgent with England's steadily mounting piracy. What has been anticipated for a long time will soon be a fact, namely, the demand for a universal embargo on exports; for the protection of American interest is imperative now. The time has arrived for the administration in Washington to declare that, since British tyranny at sea makes normal world trade impossible and England pays no heed to our justified complaints, and since every attempt to continue trade under these conditions would only lead to trouble and potential dangers, we deem it <pb facs="5418474_5_0821.jpg" n="6"/>advisable to forego any kind of export trade; therefore, and for other good reasons, we shall prohibit any and all exports!</p>
   <p>Now is the time to raise this demand, because it is absolutely justified by the necessity of protecting the vital interests of the United States. That we are going to prove!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
