<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-06">Aug. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Enthusiasm Soars to Staggering Heights</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1214</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1214.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-06">Aug. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">ENTHUSIASM SOARS TO STAGGERING HEIGHTS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In addition to the more than four thousand people who filled the Auditorium to hear various speakers express the indignation of the local Germans toward the American press, there were many thousands who could not gain admission to the hall, and who consequently held protest meetings in the open. This proved conclusively that the Germans of Chicago have now become fully aroused and have finally resolved to behave in a manner in keeping with their importance. This was evident when thousands of German men and women paraded to the publishing offices of the American newspapers and staged a demonstration concerning which the American press is wisely silent this morning. Anyone who watched the enthusiastic throng and the occurrences in and around the Auditorium will not forget last evening very soon.</p>
   <p>The crusade to the Auditorium began shortly before 7 P. M., and at 7:50 P. M. it had become necessary to close the doors. Three thousand reservists under the leadership of Lieutenants von Rottweiler, von Schuch, and von Holdhusen <pb facs="5418474_5_1215.jpg" n="2"/>met at the German Consulate and marched in military formation to the Auditorium. At Congress Street the command was given to march in parade formation. Pedestrians watched in awe and admiration, for they had never seen such maneuvers before. In the lobby of the Auditorium, where the reservists were waiting to be admitted to the hall, a great crowd gathered and began to give utterance to its feeling by singing "Deutschland, Deutschland, ueber alles," "Heil dir im Siegeskranz," "Die Wacht am Rhein," and by toasting the Emperors of Germany and Austria and President Wilson. The people standing in the street joined in the singing and toasting.</p>
   <p>At 7:50 P. M. the police closed the doors of the Auditorium and admitted only newspaper reporters. Shortly after 8 P. M. there were at least four thousand people in the lobby of the Auditorium and in the streets, waiting for admission to the Hall. Finally, the police convinced them that they could not possibly be admitted into the meeting. Hundreds of singers who were to have participated in the program could not be admitted, and hundreds of men and women who had tickets for reserved seats could not make use of them. It was impossible to <pb facs="5418474_5_1216.jpg" n="3"/>compute the great numbers of people who arrived on foot and in automobiles after 8 P. M., only to depart in disappointment.</p>
   <p>Groups formed everywhere in the vicinity of the Auditorium. Peddlers selling ribbons and German and Austrian flags did a flourishing business. Newsboys offered the latest extra of an English-language publication which announced, in large headlines, a mythical story of huge German losses. Their efforts were in vain, however, for the people placed no credence in this "news," and consequently sales were poor.</p>
   <p>The patriotism of the thousands who could not obtain admission to the hall, and their resentment toward the attitude of the American press were constrained to find some means of expression. Within a short time groups had formed and were holding impromptu meetings near the Auditorium. On Michigan Boulevard, Mr. Dietrich Heitmann of the Heitmann Lumber Company, 5852 South Ashland Avenue, collected a large number of listeners about him within a short time. In terse words he declared that the spirit of malice and hatred exuding from the <pb facs="5418474_5_1217.jpg" n="4"/>columns of the English-language publications clearly indicates that the time has come for social as well as political unity among the Germans in this country.</p>
   <p>"I can remember the time--it was before the Franco-Prussian War--" declared Mr. Heitmann, "when a mob broke the windows of the North Side Turnhalle; and if Germany should lose this war, matters would be much worse than they were at that time."</p>
   <p>Judge Michael F. Girten spoke in the lobby of the Auditorium. He emphasized the importance of Germany's cultural contributions and protested against the persecution tactics of the American press. Similar statements were made by A. Brueller, Reverend Friedrich Werhahn, Reverend Edmund Kayser, Reverend Wilhelm Breitenbach, Reverend Hans Jakobi, and Reverend C. Christian. The latter is a German-American who took the American press to task very severely and announced that he had reported to the German Consulate for voluntary service.</p>
   <p>A part of the large crowd that had come too late to be admitted to the meeting <pb facs="5418474_5_1218.jpg" n="5"/>went to Grant Park, where Hand's Band was giving its weekly concert. In a short time Germans had filled the space immediately before the band shell and had begun to sing "Die Wacht am Rhein." A serious disturbance would have ensued had not a very tactful Irish bluecoat restored quiet by requesting the bandmaster to play "Die Wacht am Rhein." The request was granted and many thousands of lusty voices sang this favorite German anthem. After the singing, the crowd gave three cheers for the policeman.</p>
   <p>The throng outside the Auditorium decided to parade through the city. In a few minutes more than five thousand had gathered in march formation. Headed by several young reservists of the German army, and amid loud hurrahs, they marched east on Adams Street. They were about to turn down Michigan Avenue when a South Park policeman stopped them and told them that they would obstruct all traffic if they continued down the middle of the street, but that he would not object if they proceeded down the sidewalk. This suggestion was followed, and they marched to the German Consulate in the best of order. There the enthusiastic crowd gave three cheers for both Emperors and sang "Die Wacht am Rhein." Under <pb facs="5418474_5_1219.jpg" n="6"/>the leadership of Fritz Klugel, Leo Langsam, and Gustav Meissner, three sergeants of the German reserves, the paraders wended their way to the headquarters of the Tribune, where they halted momentarily to express their "regard" with hisses and whistles of derision. Then they proceeded to the Austrian Consulate where they again gave three cheers for the two monarchs and sang the national anthem of Austria. After leaving the Consulate the crowd directed its course to the building of the Abendpost, and again loud cheers were the order. Here also "Die Wacht am Rhein" and other patriotic songs were sung. "On to the Hearst Building" was the cry, and they marched to Market and Madison Streets, pausing before the Hearst Building to boo loudly. Many of the thousands spectators joined in the booing. Across the street from the Hearst Building, "Die Wacht am Rhein" was sung again, and again three cheers were given for Germany and Austria. After staging similar demonstrations before the business offices of the Chicago Evening Post and the Chicago Journal, the crowd, which by this time had decreased to about one thousand, and which was accompanied by a similar number of spectators, continued on its course to the Auditorium where it arrived in time to greet the throng just departing from that building.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1220.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>This parade, which was composed of old men and women as well as young people, must be included among the most memorable events in the history of the German element in Chicago. The fact that the majority of the non-Germans who witnessed this demonstration revealed a very friendly attitude proves that the slanderous articles appearing in the American press are not taken at face value by the general public. Indeed, one young man, whose ancestors were not German, Mr. Edward Tinnigkeig, 2273 Rice Street, reported for service at the German Consulate.</p>
   <p>The Schlesischer Verein met after the mass meeting last night. This organization voted to contribute fifty dollars to the Red Cross, and requested that this sum be forwarded to the proper committee at once.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
