<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-02-17">February, 17, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial Comments on the Spanish War)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1319</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1319.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-02-17">February, 17, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">(Editorial Comments on the Spanish War)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Irresponsible War Whoops. The great misfortune which befell the American armored cruiser "Maine" in the harbor of Havana did not silence the American warwhoopers; it renewed their fury. While they pretend to be heartbroken over the loss of 260 capable sailors and a good ship, now they intend to risk thousands of human lives and the entire fleet. Without a vestige of evidence to prove their ascertions, they now accuse Spain of this cowardly criminal attack against the "Maine" and without awaiting the results of the investigation they now agitate for a war of vengeance. They are so blinded by their rage that they do not notice the monstrous inconsistencies in which they become entangled. First, they allege, that the "Maine" was blown up by one of the countless, concealed mines, which are supposed to be on the bottom of Havana harbor; on the other hand, they demand that the president send the entire fleet into the same hell hole. Now, if a single mine explosion is sufficient to destroy one of the best American warships and three quarters of its men, what would happen to the fleet, when hundreds of mines are exploded at once, and the torpedoes fly about like bullets during an Infantry battle! Evidently not a single man would remain who could relate the story of the great massacre to his countrymen. The largest and best division of our navy would be sunk with a single stroke. In honor to humanity, it must be said: there is not even a shadow of a doubt available for the assumption, that the Spanish Government caused the sinking of the "Maine". In close proximity to the American cruiser the Spanish <pb facs="5418474_5_1320.jpg" n="2"/>warship Alphonso XII lay at anchor, which surely would have been endangered, if a submarine mine is exploded right next to it. Besides immediately after the accident, the conduct of the Spanish sailors and Spanish authorities showed that the accident caused them genuine concern; they were prostrated. They not only displayed pure humane sympathy for the poor victims of the catastrophe but they also sensed what suspicions would be aroused. For the same reasons the Government of Madrid hastened to express its sorrow. It would have acted differently, had it desired a war with the United States. If there is such a possibility as a chance - explosion in the Havana harbor, as several experts at Washington and Brooklyn claim, then the "Maine" should not have been permitted to remain for three weeks in such a dangerous locality. For a mere friendly call, it was too long by far, and a demonstration was entirely unjustified, even if the Spaniards or a few fanatics were prepared to blow it up at any moment. The fury of the Jingos maybe explained in the fact that the unfortunate ship was sent there through their instigation or, - that they look upon its dispatch as a threatening attitude towards Spain. They know that they offended the Spanish national pride, and that Spanish fanaticism has been aroused. Instead of admitting their guilt, they continue to agitate wildly and passionately for war. The United States have played too long with the fire.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
