<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-24">Feb. 24, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The "Bloody Shirt" of Today</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0210</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0210.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-24">Feb. 24, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE "BLOODY SHIRT" OF TODAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the end of the Civil War, immediately after Lee had delivered his sword to General Grant, and ever since, the great and greatest of our country have loudly proclaimed, "Let us have peace".</p>
   <p>The resistance of the South was completely broken. The Confederate States had neither an army nor weapons. They could not gather a new army, nor could they furnish arms. They could not resume fighting. Military peace was established. When General Grant said, "Let us have peace," he could have had only civil peace in mind, a peace during which all hateful words and evil acts of war, which separated the people, are forgiven and forgotten. General Grant had reference to Lincoln's peace, "with malice toward none, with charity for all".</p>
   <p>That was the peace which the Nation needed in order to recuperate quickly <pb facs="5418474_5_0211.jpg" n="2"/>from the wounds which it suffered during the war; the peace which is necessary for, and conducive to, the welfare of all citizens; the peace of good, patriotic, intelligent, and progressive citizens. And they desired it.</p>
   <p>But there were low, wicked, and selfish men who profited and gained public attention from the war. They saw their opportunities end with the war. To them the "forgiving" and "forgetting" included in Lincoln's peace "with malice toward none, with charity for all," was synonymous with the removal of the ladder on which they had climbed to fame and riches. They feared that they would retrograde to their former humble financial and social status, should there be "malice toward none". And, mindful only of their petty selfish interests, they counteracted civil peace wherever and whenever they could.</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: The paragraph which has not been translated consists of one sentence, but evidently three or more lines have been omitted, making <pb facs="5418474_5_0212.jpg" n="3"/>it impossible to ascertain the author's intended meaning.]</p>
   <p>And thus the hatred between the South and the North was kept alive for several years to the detriment of the whole Nation--until common sense saw the light and the masses recognized the baseness of the war profiteers. Then the "bloody shirt" was condemned and "waving the bloody shirt" was taboo in decent society.</p>
   <p>The World War is ended. President Wilson is working for "malice toward none, and charity for all" as his great predecessor, Lincoln, did fifty-four years ago. And today, too, there are selfish people who want to have nothing to do with a "people's peace". They refuse to forgive and forget anything--if they have any right to an apology--and will not stop wartime hatred. Or they notice, as did their predecessors during the seventies of the past century, that their financial and social position is in danger, and they have neither the means nor arguments to fight their opponents successfully. In short, they have made a "bloody shirt" and are waving it in order to attain their ends, in utter disregard of the admonition, "Let <pb facs="5418474_5_0213.jpg" n="4"/>us have peace". They do not consider the great harm done to the nation in general.</p>
   <p>The cartoon in today's Chicago Tribune waves the "bloody shirt". It endeavors to create the impression that all Americans of German descent intend to vote for William Hale Thompson in the primaries. It shows a poster set over the entrance to a polling place, and the poster is inscribed, "Vote for Thompson," "Second Largest German City...." Other inscriptions read, "Disloyal element," "He was a good mayor for us...." It also shows Father Dearborn holding a piece of paper on which the result of the straw vote taken by the Tribune on February 25 is recorded, Thompson, 3,475; Judge Olson 3,131; Merriam, 1,546; and Father Dearborn points backwards to the "disloyal element" and says, "Vote for those of his opponents who show the greatest strength"--the "bloody shirt" of today.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
