<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-16">Feb. 16, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Abolition of Child Labor</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1592</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1592.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-02-16">Feb. 16, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE ABOLITION OF CHILD LABOR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The fight against the so-called amendment to abolish child labor was fought years ago. Now the fight is being renewed. In 1924 Congress adopted the amendment after a long debate. Soon thereafter it was rejected by more than twenty states, and thus was considered to be dead and buried. About a year ago agitation on behalf of the amendment was renewed, and it has already been ratified by a number of states, among them several which had previously rejected it.</p>
   <p>It is not surprising that interest in the amendment has revived. The government and the entire nation have started a systematic battle against the depression. The most important object of this battle is to secure work for the unemployed and thus to put them in the ranks of wage earners.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1593.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The first step necessary to accomplish this, naturally, is the elimination of children from competition with adults, and the best way to attain this end is to ratify the forgotten amendment to abolish child labor.</p>
   <p>The logic of this argument is so clear that neither unemployed nor employed persons can refute it. In addition, there is the human appeal. Is it not a disgrace to a civilized nation to expose defenseless youth to the brutal exploitation of greedy extortioners? Is it human to permit little children to work in sweatshops, factories, and on farms, and thus to stunt their growth physically and mentally? It is a disgrace, indeed, and therefore child labor should have been prohibited long ago. Nevertheless, serious objections are raised against ratifying the amendment.</p>
   <p>Actually, in name, it is not an amendment to abolish child labor. The amendment gives Congress authority to regulate or prohibit any activity of persons under eighteen years of age. According to law, children between <pb facs="5418474_5_1594.jpg" n="3"/>the ages of fourteen and eighteen are minors; but one cannot very well class them as children. It has long been a custom in all civilized countries to apprentice fourteen-year old boys. In Germany, technical schools were established for the purpose of giving apprentices an opportunity to continue their education. What is more, all apprentices were compelled to attend these schools. That was a very wise arrangement, for thus the physical and mental requirements of the young men were adequately provided for in every respect.</p>
   <p>It would be foolish to grant Congress power to forbid all persons up to eighteen years of age to participate in any and every activity. So great an authority would be too far-reaching. It would give our public officials the right to interfere with the private life of individuals and families in a manner that a nation having only an ounce of self-respect would never tolerate.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1595.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>'Tis true, the advocates of this amendment say that Congress will not exceed its powers; but that is a very weak argument.</p>
   <p>How about the Sixteenth Amendment which provided for the introduction of the income tax? When it was discussed, assurances were also given that Congress would not use the full authority that the amendment afforded, excepting in extreme cases, as for instance, during a war. And we know from experience just what happened. How about the Eighteenth Amendment which was adopted for the purpose of preventing people from misusing alcohol? It resulted in tyranny in brutal oppression and snooping, and will forever be a blot upon the history of America.</p>
   <p>What can young people from fourteen to eighteen years of age do, if they are not permitted to work? Very likely the sponsors of the amendment will say: "Let them study, so they may be better equipped for life." That is foolishness. There is too much studying in our country today, as matters <pb facs="5418474_5_1596.jpg" n="5"/>are; and thus we are rearing an academic proletariat that will prove to be very dangerous to our country.</p>
   <p>It is said: "If we refuse to build more schools, we will have to build more prisons." The contrary is true. Nobody has become a criminal through lack of knowledge; but many have been led to crime because they lacked an opportunity to apply the knowledge which they had acquired in schools, and were unable to adjust themselves to manual labor.</p>
   <p>Close scrutiny reveals that the fight against the depression is an effective argument against the ratification of the proposed child labor amendment. President Roosevelt said in an address regarding the aims and results of the N.R.A., "Child labor has been abolished." Well if that is so, why abolish it again through another amendment to the Constitution of the United States?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
