<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-01-05">January 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">American Journalism.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0840</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0840.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-01-05">January 5, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICAN JOURNALISM.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every decent citizen looks with contempt upon a certain local newspaper, which, by the way is called "The World's Greatest Newspaper," however, just great enough to create cheap and abhorrent sensationalism.</p>
   <p>We understand fully that every newspaper is justified in expressing its sympathy or antipathy to causes as it may see fit, but when a newspaper deliberately lowers itself to a point of vileness, then we are entitled to attack these lies in the strongest way we may see fit.</p>
   <p>We read that Herr Weil, the London correspondent of this "greatest newspaper in the world," conversed with the wife of a subordinate Serbian official. It is stated that she is the possessor of documentary evidence referring to the assassination of the Austrian duke and duchess, claiming that the Pan-Germans in Vienna were the originators of the murder plot, due to their antipathy towards the duke in regard to his Slavic inclinations. Therefore, the Serbs were absolved from all blame.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0841.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Taking the article under consideration again; the wife of a subordinate official has these extremely important documents in her possession, yet, neither England, Russia, or even Serbia are interested enough to demand them, apparently, on account of this woman's eagerness to present the American people with these documents. Of course they are much more important to the American people than they would be to England, Russia, or even Serbia.</p>
   <p>"The Greatest Newspaper in the World" had the audacity to point out and present such rot to its readers. "Shame" is not a word of nearly sufficient strength to express our disgust.</p>
   <p>Chicagoer Pressi.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
