<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-12-08">Dec. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">British War Aims</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0881</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0881.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-12-08">Dec. 8, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">BRITISH WAR AIMS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>England is willing to "sacrifice all," in order to defeat Germany. Her statesmen and diplomats are becoming more voluble than ever: They try to keep France and Russia in good humor to continue the war. That will give England time to take care of her "office details" and to grab the entire world market. When that is done, she will permit her Allies to think about peace. How secretly and tenaciously this objective is being pursued can be seen from a thousand instances, instances of such a brazen and violent nature that we are reminded of the era of pirates and buccaneers. England is not sincere if she claims to fight Prussian militarism or any other militarism. She is not even sincerely interested in Germany's economic ruin, because that would only strengthen the industrialism and trade of those nations which used to enjoy lively commercial intercourse with Germany. England's primary objective is <pb facs="5418474_5_0882.jpg" n="2"/>nothing less than the total ruin of the German merchant marine, and, of course, the German navy. Germany may go on manufacturing, but she should ship her goods in British vessels, use British trade connections and financial institutions. London would be the clearinghouse and Berlin only a branch office. England does not want any German territory, and she will hardly go out of her way to secure any for France or Russia. That would not be in England's interest, because Germany would recuperate and reconquer the lost territory. If she could be kept within her own boundaries, having no means of [overseas] transportation to get her products to the consumer, England could skim off the cream and take away the greater portion of her competitors' profits in the form of commissions and overhead expenditures. And that is what England's "fight against Prussian militarism" really amounts to. But there is many a bitter drop falling into this cup of hope, because this gigantic task is even harder to accomplish than Germany's military defeat. Although England is ideally equipped for such an enterprise, first, because she monopolizes the cables, and second, because she has the necessary ships, she will nevertheless fail in the end, <pb facs="5418474_5_0883.jpg" n="3"/>though initially successful, because she would have to make all other nations the slaves of the island kingdom at the same time. But the rest of the world will not put up with that, and no matter how strict the terms of trade imposed by England on the other nations, they would not be kept. As soon as these nations realized that they had only served English shopkeeper interests, they would unite with Germany against England. The present-day enmity between the Russians and the Germans and the French will make way for trade treaties directed against British monopoly. England's present allies will eventually turn against her, because England will abuse her present preferred position as the broker of the world, and will finally lose out. That is the inevitable and of any absolutism, be it political or economic.</p>
   <p>But, like the ostrich, we would be burying our heads in the sand if we thought that the English would find their "economic militarism" too expensive to continue. Huge fortunes are made in world trade and it pays to make sacrifices for its continuance. Once England has attained her objective, she will exact <pb facs="5418474_5_0884.jpg" n="4"/>her tribute from the nations, and the amount of this commission will be in direct proportion to the expenditures she made in order to close the deal. The Englishman looks at war expenditures as a capital investment. The larger the investment, the more interest the other nations will have to pay. It would not be the first time that England had figured it out that way. But in the end the collapse had to come just the same, and history proves the correctness of our theory.</p>
   <p>When the American colonies rebelled against the mother country, England had to expend ninety per cent of her entire national income for war purposes. In 1781 it was as high as ninety-four per cent. As the consequence of this Revolutionary War, England became involved in war with France and Spain, and finally with Holland. The shopkeepers sacrificed gladly during the six years between 1775 and 1782, but then they became very apprehensive. England's commerce suffered such tremendous damage that in 1782 Parliament adopted an address to the King, branding as the enemy of the throne and the people, anyone who <pb facs="5418474_5_0885.jpg" n="5"/>advocated continuance of the war. Whereupon peace negotiations with the United States were inaugurated. England declared herself defeated and recognized the independence of the United States. The economic setback had compelled the shopkeepers to tell the King to make peace. During the wars with Napoleon, England once more had to rally her entire financial resources. During the fourteen years between 1801 and 1814 England spent fourteen million marks [translator's note: Mark is the German monetary unit. In 1914 one pound equaled about twenty marks] for the navy, the army, and ordnance alone. In 1801, her population was only 16,227,000. Once again England faced economic ruin, and once again it was the shopkeepers not the dictators who urged the peace.</p>
   <p>The expenditures in the present war are incomparably higher, and although it must be admitted that England's financial resources are the equal of Germany's, if not greater, the day will surely arrive when the bill will seem somewhat large to the shopkeepers. They will find that the enterprise did not pay. As <pb facs="5418474_5_0886.jpg" n="6"/>soon as the shopkeepers have realized that, the war will stop, no matter how much the Asquiths, Churchills, Greys, and Georges are shooting off their mouths. To throw money away is not exactly a pastime the shopkeepers like to indulge in. Let us not be deceived, therefore. The best means to make the shopkeepers see reason is the diminishing buying power of their money and a rise in prices. The gigantic [domestic] loans, which are being floated, are flooding the money market with such a huge amount of false values that even the most financially sound state [nation] will have to peg the paper money--as Russia is doing now--if a greater portion of supplies has to be imported from abroad. While between 1780 and 1789 the regular price for wheat was fourteen shillings per quarter [translator's note: The quarter in this case is an English dry measure, equivalent to eight bushels or sixty-four gallons.] it rose to eighty-eight shillings between 1810 and 1819. The prices of other commodities increased in the same proportion.</p>
   <p>There is no lack of other examples which could show the British shopkeepers <pb facs="5418474_5_0887.jpg" n="7"/>where the ambition to world domination can lead; as in the instance of Spain. This country, through her power politics, has managed to sink from the position of a world empire to a third-rate power and her situation was once equally as favorable as England's. Therefore those timid souls who are overawed by the display of bravado in British diplomatic circles may be reminded that there are repercussions which may act like a boomerang. The blockade against Germany, for instance, has already completely paralyzed Russian trade.</p>
   <p>There may be only a few who have earnestly believed in the moral motives of the British Government. Unfortunately, we have to wait for the facts to materialize. Some firms engaged in international trade are already beginning to feel the pinch. The representatives of the American people, whether they like to or not, will have to make up their minds whether we are a British domain or an independent republic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
