<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-02">Aug. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Seroius and Dignified</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Attitude of Local Germans Towards the War</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1248</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1248.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1914-08-02">Aug. 2, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">SEROIUS AND DIGNIFIED</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Attitude of Local Germans Towards The War</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The dejection caused in their former country by Germany's declaration of war against Russia rests heavily upon the Germans of Chicago. Everyone is aware of the seriousness of the situation. Many have loved ones abroad, many have relatives there who will be called upon to sacrifice their lives in the service of their country, and all of them still have a warm spot in their hearts for their native land. Many are still citizens of the Reich and will be called to the colors, or will volunteer. It is no wonder then that the Germans in Chicago were in a serious and dignified mood. There was no demonstration of jingoism last evening; but wherever Germans assembled, dignified utterances of faith and strength in the justice of the German cause and nation were heard.</p>
   <p>In the following paragraphs, the reader is given a description of the general <pb facs="5418474_5_1249.jpg" n="2"/>spirit which prevailed in German circles, and which was made evident by the statements of prominent persons.</p>
   <p>The president of the Germania Maennercher, Mr. H. O. Lange, whom a reporter from the Abendpost, interviewed at the[Germania] Clubhouse, had this to say: "To take a firm stand with respect to the events which will come as the result of Germany's martial entanglements is now the chief duty of the Germans in Chicago. In my opinion, the customary entertainments of the German societies should be suspended as long as German soldiers are shedding their blood in battle with the enemy, and as long as the fate of the German Reich is hanging in the balance. We should forget all petty differences, and, if necessary, we should try to help Germany by collecting money and forwarding it.</p>
   <p>"Above all, the Germans of Chicago must make such an impressive demonstration against the hostile reports of the English-language newspapers that the <pb facs="5418474_5_1250.jpg" n="3"/>annoyances which we have suffered at the hands of the English-language press in recent times will not occur in the future. I am happy to learn that such a demonstration is to be made very soon. But I do not think that the contemplated mass meeting in the Auditorium will suffice. In addition, we should arrange a regular crusade of Germans to some centrally located park. We should see to it that hundreds of thousands of our people are present to join in our protest against the journalistic practices of the English-language press, and that the protest echoes and re-echoes in the offices of the editors and business managers of the English-language newspapers. I hope that this suggestion is followed; for my own part, I shall do all I can to make an open-air meeting possible."</p>
   <p>Mr. Ernest Kruetgen, president of the firm which bears his name, was also present at the Clubhouse. He was evidently very deeply moved by the report that war had been declared, and expressed himself thus to an inquiring reporter:</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1251.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"The hour has come when the Germans of Chicago will be severely tried. Perhaps the declaration of war, the results of which nobody can foresee, will prove to be a blessing in disguise for the local Germans, inasmuch as it may serve to unite us firmly. Like every other German who is worth his salt, I side with the German Reich, and, if necessary, I shall support it to the limit of my financial ability. At this time, we Germans should also throw our entire moral and political influence into the balance in behalf of our native land, which is very likely fighting for its very existence.</p>
   <p>"The Germans of Chicago should finally wake up and remind the English-language newspapers very forcefully that the Germans, whose blood helped cement this great Republic, are tired of being maligned by ignorant and malicious reporters as enemies of culture and suppressors of liberty. To achieve this end we should hold a mass meeting the like of which Chicago has never seen, and which will not only command respect in this city, but will also be an incentive for mass meetings everywhere in the Union; thus <pb facs="5418474_5_1252.jpg" n="5"/>they will serve to unite all the Germans in the United States. May our Deutschtum not be found wanting in this critical period of history."</p>
   <p>Reverend Rudolph A. John, pastor of St. Paul's Church, said: "I had hoped that war with its terrible results could be averted. The German nation showed remarkable patience. It is regrettable that in this enlightened age no other way of settling such national issues has been devised. Let us hope that this war will be of short duration, and that it will be followed by a lasting peace."</p>
   <p>Attorney Hans von Reinsperg declared: "Numerically we are, perhaps, weaker than the other Powers, especially if Italy, as it is reported, remains neutral. But I believe this is the time when Germany must strike. It has shown wonderful patience toward the attacks and persecutions to which it has been subjected. Our army is excellent and ready for action. The navy, too, is prepared to give a good account of itself. We are certainly <pb facs="5418474_5_1253.jpg" n="6"/>superior to the other Powers as far as ability is concerned. Perhaps our allied enemies have more ships than we have, but maybe our air force will make up for that difference. The purpose of this war is not to increase our territory, but to protect what we have--our country and our commercial interests--while our enemies are striking at the very core of our existence and are seeking commercial supremacy of the world. The German nation is aware of the duties assumed through treaties made with its confederates. Germany will keep the promises which it has made".</p>
   <p>Mr. Karl Roessler, manager of the Hotel Kaiserhof, told a reporter of the Abendpost that never before had he observed such a serious mood among Germans, and even among the English-speaking public.</p>
   <p>"Everything is remarkably quiet," said Mr. Roessler, "much more so than is usual during the evening, and my own people seem to be unable to grasp or to explain the present situation." He led the reporter to a table at which <pb facs="5418474_5_1254.jpg" n="7"/>a small group of men were sitting. Among them were a German reservist and a man who sent a telegram to Berlin yesterday afternoon, volunteering his services. Both are faced with the problem of getting to Germany. They feel that passage on a Holland or Red Star liner is the only solution to this problem.</p>
   <p>"No doubt your readers would be very interested if you could tell them how they can get to Germany safely and quickly," one of the men said. "German reservists will very likely be halted by the English or French, but I believe it possible to get to Germany by way of Holland."</p>
   <p>Thereupon these gentlemen began to discuss the war situation--the possibilities and results--and to weigh the advantages or disadvantages under which the various armed forces will have to fight. An employee of the hotel, a former German reservist who came here only a year ago, also participated in the discussion. One of the men could not understand England's conduct, <pb facs="5418474_5_1255.jpg" n="8"/>and this was the topic of spirited conversation. Another voiced the opinion that it is not England's object to destroy Germany,but that she is counting upon the continental Powers' becoming so weakened by war that she will derive great gains....</p>
   <p>The Hotel Bismarck, too, was unusually quiet. In the well-known Old Quincy Number Nine Room the reporter met Mr. Leopold Grand, the secretary of the Illinois Turnbezirk, and Mr. Louis Klemm, a prominent musician.</p>
   <p>Mr. Grand said: "We are all aware that the situation is very grave. Although we are Americans, we hope that Germany will be victorious, since she was forced to go to war. But I shudder to think of the blood which will be shed in this terrible conflict. These are trying times for Germany, surrounded as she is by enemies who are jealous of her unparalleled rise in industry, commerce, and all phases of economic life".</p>
   <p>Mr. Klemm proved to be an optimist. He laughingly confided to our reporter <pb facs="5418474_5_1256.jpg" n="9"/>that there can be no doubt whatever that Germany will win the war. In proof of his statement, he pointed to the remarkable preparations of Germany, to the splendid spirit among her soldiers, sailors, and officers, and, by contrast, to the many weaknesses of the French and Russians. As for England, Mr. Klemm was not disturbed in the least; he pointed out that Helgoland is so well fortified that any hostile fleet would shatter on this rock.</p>
   <p>When a reporter visited the German colony on the North Side, he heard many well-known German patriotic songs, special prominence being given to "Deutschland, Deutschland ueber alles". At Wurz'n Sepp [a restaurant where the guests are entertained by music], he found a gay throng which filled the place to capacity. The declaration of war was the chief topic of conversation, everybody maintaining with firm confidence that Germany would emerge victorius. The gay enthusiasm reached its climax when the orchestra played "Deutschland, Deutschland ueber alles," and Die Wacht am Rhein".</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1257.jpg" n="10"/>
   <p>The crowd arose and sang these songs. Deep silence followed the singing of these selections--an indication that local Germans also know that their former fatherland faces a very grave and serious situation. At the bar, German and Austrian reservists deliberated on ways and means of getting back to Europe....</p>
   <p>Anton Kercher, for many years President of the Veteranen der deutschen Armee told the reporter that he had not witnessed such enthusiasm since 1870. He said he hoped that it would show good results.</p>
   <p>In the Lincoln Turner Hall, the reporter also found a large crowd; and the declaration of war was again the chief topic of conversation. That Germany must win, that her endeavors must be successful, were the opinions voiced by everybody. Spirited patriots lauded the Kaiser. Leopold Ehrenwart, secretary of the Lincoln Turnverein, said that he had expected the declaration of war, and that he hoped the German armed forces would win. Carl Senft, <pb facs="5418474_5_1258.jpg" n="11"/>speaker of the Turnverein, made a similar statement. Paul Senft, president of the Harmonie Maennerchor, thought that the Germans deserved credit for promptly coming to the aid of their confederates. He hoped that they would be victorious.</p>
   <p>H. Von Oppen, director of Fidelia[a singing society], expressed satisfaction that the prevailing uncertainty was over at last.</p>
   <p>"Germany has a very difficult problem to solve," he said, "but I am confident that she is equal to the task, and that the righteous cause will prevail."</p>
   <p>Then the reporter went to the Social Turner Hall where he found enthusiastic representatives of the German element discussing matters pertaining to the war in a serious and dignified atmosphere. Of course everyone sided with Germany and wished her success.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1259.jpg" n="12"/>
   <p>Last night, the Chicago Board of Trade sent a request to President Wilson asking that he aid them in their endeavors to transport grain to Germany, by using his influence to have the shipping laws changed. The change involves a repeal of the present provision that none but American-built ships may fly the American flag, which would thus make it legal to use other ships to forward grain.</p>
   <p>It is reported that prices for meat will rise sharply in consequence of the war. The packers deny that they have received any orders from European nations, but, according to their statements, the demand will soon increase to such an extent that higher prices will be justified.</p>
   <p>Up to midnight, the German Consulate had received no official information concerning the declaration of war. Vice-Consul Baron von Reiswitz, who has been in charge since Consul-General Geissler has been on a leave of absence, told the Abendpost that as soon as he receives official notice of the <pb facs="5418474_5_1260.jpg" n="13"/>declaration of war, he will issue the call to service. No further information could be obtained, since official communications have been almost entirely disrupted.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
