<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-07-29">July 29, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Newly Patented Americanization Process</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1650</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1650.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I A 1 b</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-07-29">July 29, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE NEWLY PATENTED AMERICANIZATION PROCESS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Of late, hopeless Americanization ideas flutter about in hapless confusion. Heretofore, acceptance or rejection in naturalization matters depended upon a certain elementary knowledge of our American institutions, familiarity with the language and the general character of the immigrant. That was the proving ground. Insofar as our United States court in Chicago is concerned, a different view will prevail, according to Federal Judge Cliffe. The deciding factor in the future hinges upon the questions whether the applicant sends his children to the public schools; if he reads English newspapers regularly at home; and also if English is spoken in the family circle, etc. Judgment will be influenced, hereafter, if the suppliant is in the soft drink business. If so, then he cannot become a citizen, at least not in Judge Adam C. Cliffe's court in Chicago. "Because," says the jurist, "we already have too many whiskey dealers in this city."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1651.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We do not intend to argue about the truth of the last sentence, but the judicial logic is something else. No one, not even a federal judge, can classify anybody as a bootlegger, because adverse circumstances compel him to sell sodawater, ginger ale, or other non-alcoholic beverages. It would be contrary to our fundamental laws, if we adjudge a man guilty before having obtained a vestige of evidence. Applying the same principle, Judge Cliffe must condemn every man - ipso facto - because he owns a crow bar. It is regrettable that a federal judge indulges in such absurdities.</p>
   <p>The stipulation that a prospective citizen must send his children to a public school can merely be regarded as a clandestine thrust against parochial and community schools where other languages, German, Italian, French, etc., are taught, besides English. To propound such a rule is, after all, a rather serious transgression of parental rights, and if emanating from the judicial chair, must be doubly condemned. Insofar as the "most honorable judge of the federal court" is concerned, it is none of his business where the children <pb facs="5418474_5_1652.jpg" n="3"/>of future citizens go to school. What of it if they attend these institutions of learning in conformance to our statutes on compulsory education? As long as the separate states, that is, districts, recognize these schools, no federal judge has a right, even indirectly, to criticise them, or to interfere. Fortunately, we have not yet reached the stage where we are under Governmental supervision.</p>
   <p>And in regard to the question whether English is spoken within the confines of the home, and the reading of English newspapers, such an usurpation of private privileges, even if not directly decreed in the Constitution, must be firmly rejected, since these customs have been established by centuries of tradition. To complete the picture, the federal judge need only prescribe definite diets for the applicants, and prohibit certain entertainments; in short, use the Russian Tscheka as a controlling pattern prior to granting citizenship.</p>
   <p>Judge Cliffe should know that no one can be Americanized in that manner.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1653.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Americanization is vastly different from tyrannism, nor is it based on intimidation, and furthermore, it is not addicted to stupidity. Obviously, we are confronted with one of the obnoxious features bequeathed to us by a war psychosis. Guided by that heritage, we apply the most ludicrous, senseless methods, preferably some patented process, whereby we try to squeeze the new immigrant into the American mold under a given pressure, and in due conformity to the officially recorded compression formula. That system creates an army of hypocrites. The newly baked citizen who lied whenever he opened his mouth, affirming that he reads only English papers everyday, speaks English at home, bears the famous citation of Goetz of Berlichingen in his mind, or its much stronger Czechoslovakian and Italian equivalent, wherein the witness leaves the courtroom after clandestinely thumbing his nose at the highly intellectual judge. Or, does Mr. Cliffe intend to ascertain whether the affirmations of the supplicant are practiced in every day life? It would be desirable if the authorities who are involved in the naturalization process show a little confidence in the real America, not in their America, but in the Nation as it still lives <pb facs="5418474_5_1654.jpg" n="5"/>and acts. This genuine America still assimilates the great majority of the people who cross its shores. It does it better and more thoroughly than our judicial powers, because it works naturally. And this capacity can be assisted in a sensible manner, but to interfere aimlessly restricts the beneficient work and deteriorates the product.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
