<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-10-08">Oct. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[Yesterday's Mass Meeting On] the Northwest Side</title><title level="a" type="sub">Germans of that City District also Campaigning for 4th Liberty Loan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0571</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0571.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-10-08">Oct. 8, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[YESTERDAY'S MASS MEETING ON] THE NORTHWEST SIDE</title><title level="a" type="sub">Germans of that City District also Campaigning for 4th Liberty Loan</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Since America's entry into the world war eighteen months have passed and, in spite of ample proof to the contrary, insinuations accusing German-Americans of not being "one hundred percent loyal" can still be heard. It goes against the German character to make a virtue out of a duty and to ask for special recognition. The fact, that the casualty lists contain a high percentage of German names; the fact that the German element had topped all other nationalities with eighty million dollars when the Third Liberty Loan was subscribed, should suffice to silence all malicious slander. But in spite of that it becomes necessary for German-Americans occasionally to give up their reserve, which is still misinterpreted by some people. Such an occasion is afforded now while the campaign for the Fourth Liberty Loan is in full swing. Accordingly, the German Division for the promotion of the Fourth Liberty Loan called for a mass meeting of men and women of German descent, to take place at Wicker Park Hall last night. On this occasion speakers made it clear to the audience that it was not enough to do one's duty during these great times, but that the whole nation should be shown how this duty was discharged.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0572.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>.....Mr. Mueller greeted the assembly on behalf of the government, which also thanked the citizens of German descent for their support of the war measures. It is not the government's intention to suppress the German language, and the speaker expressed his satisfaction that the audience, by attending the meeting, had given proof that they were in full sympathy with their fellow citizens in their desire to fight for the democratic ideal, which would bring an early peace and liberty to all peoples in the world, including the German.</p>
   <p>Peter Scherer's Address</p>
   <p>.....The main speaker of the evening, Mr. Scherer, president of foreign language instruction in Indianapolis and chairman of the Foreign Language Division of the Liberty Loan Campaign Committee of Indiana, delivered the main speech of the evening.</p>
   <p>Speaking in English, he first of all pointed out that he had not come to explain the purpose of the organization. This had been made sufficiently clear by the press. Rather, he had accepted the invitation of the local German language committee</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
