<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-06">Apr. 6, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Our "Militarism"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0077</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0077.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1926-04-06">Apr. 6, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">OUR "MILITARISM"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to a report of the Chicago Tribune the Berliner Boersenzeitung (stock exchange paper) was compelled to point to the militarism which exists in the United States. The summer training camps for civilians are a particular cause of worry for the Berlin paper, because it writes that, in this manner, the United States will manage to submit its entire male strength to military training. The paper further sees a special proof for our cross militarism in the circumstance that the secretary of war has the desire to increase the standing army to 150,000 men.</p>
   <p>The military expert of the Berlin paper could have figured out, without much pain, what an enormous force this standing army of 150,000 men represents in a country of more than one hundred and ten million inhabitants. He could have found out that for every one thousand population there comes one <pb facs="5418474_5_0078.jpg" n="2"/>and one quarter soldier. In Germany proper the ratio is 1000 to 1.64, in France 1000 to 19.13 and even in England, with its mercenary army, there are 1000 to 5.43. However, there is some difference, as the American total do not include the militia of the individual states [national guard] and the reserve corps. The so-called army of the United States, consisting of the regular army, national guard, and organized reserves, has about 400,000 men, so that the relation per thousand population is increased to 3.5 soldiers. Even at that the United States is still at the bottom of the list of the great powers, ranging below Japan, which has 4.80 soldiers for each 1,000 of the population.</p>
   <p>Also, in other respects, our militarism is quite tame. Participation in courses of military education is, for instance, voluntary. Whoever does not want to play soldier for fourteen days may spend his vacation fishing. But whoever has military ambitions, but is not inclined to get his fling within the narrow confines of a strict discipline, has the opportunity to join all sorts of "armed" knight orders, in which he can live up to his <pb facs="5418474_5_0079.jpg" n="3"/>military instincts.</p>
   <p>But even insofar as our official militarism--the regular army--is concerned, it is with some blushing that the statement is made that, in point of skill, it is far from occupying first place. Our flying corps is of a rather problematic nature; our artillery and technical troups suffer from the policy of economy at the hands of the Government and Congress, as well as at the hands of all appropriations for military and fleet purposes, which enjoy no particular standing in the country's legislature. At any rate, it cannot compete with appropriations for prohibition, when it comes to being in good graces with the authorities. If we were dealing with our official militarism, without taking into consideration the economic and the co-ordinating forces of the country we could, if need be, easily engage in a conflict with Mexico, as long as our vivacious neighbor refrains from a union with Cuba.</p>
   <p>The Berlin paper may, therefore, sleep in peace as far as our militarism is concerned. The United States learned at least a small lesson from the last <pb facs="5418474_5_0080.jpg" n="4"/>war, that it is cheaper to train reserves in times of peace than to wait until war is declared. Any one in his sober senses cannot see, in this, a military threat.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
