<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-08-03">Aug. 3, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">Altgeld's Rage.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1295</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1295.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1900-08-03">Aug. 3, 1900</date>.
<title level="a">ALTGELD'S RAGE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 4.. The address delivered by Theodore Roosevelt, governor of the State of New York at St. Paul, enraged Altgeld to such an extent, that he indulged in sharp criticism of the governor. Following is an extract from Altgeld's utterances made in Toledo: "Words fail to properly characterize that man's (Roosevelt's) career. I will not even make an attempt. He is a man best qualified to defend the criminal desire for land possession.</p>
   <p>"He would not hesitate to defend violation of the president's duty. He is the type of man who would advocate a war of conquest, the burning of cities, the slaughtering of human beings, and who would kill freedom. The Democratic party will ignore and overlook those malicious attacks made by him."</p>
   <p>It is quite remarkable that Altgeld, who has the English language so well at his command, - in fact, he represents a living dictionary of abusive words and sarcastic remarks, - would declare that he is unable to characterize Roosevelt, as he would like to, because of the lack of words. This means only one thing, namely, that Roosevelt is less desirable than he could attempt to express.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1296.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The inconsistency of Altgeld is astonishing. He said that the Democratic party would disregard Roosevelt's speech; but no sooner was the address delivered than the high council of the party decided to reply. With that they entrusted former Governor Altgeld, whose every word is poison.</p>
   <p>"There are only two systems of government, the one is might, the other, the will of the people," said the former governor. Altgeld tried to prove that the Republican system was that of brutal force while the Democrats represent justice and liberty. Any child of school age could inform him to the contrary.</p>
   <p>Recent history discloses that might prevails over right in the Democratic South, the only hope of the Democratic party. Why did not Altgeld prefer to preach to the North Carolina Democrats against the horrible and unconstitutional treatment of Negroes?</p>
   <p>The South has adopted constitutional changes in every state, putting restrictions on the Negro mass votes. The colored people have only to recall the history of the Republican party, and what it has done and accomplished for the Negro race. This in itself is sufficient to establish confidence in the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1297.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But the past actions of the Democratic party, the treatment of the slaves who later became citizens of our country, has not been forgotten. The South still only tolerates the Negro. Must not the latter then regard the constitution with mockery? And is he wrong when he says to the Democratic party: "I do not believe you!"</p>
   <p>They wish to have the Democratic party known as the Democratic party of the just. But, Mr. Altgeld, - when and where has that taken place? Was it during your term as governor of Illinois, at the time you fought Cleveland like a jack-ass?</p>
   <p>Democracy has failed as a ruling party. The Democrats have not kept step with the times. The party's most prominent men are of an insignificant caliber, and this means you too, Mr. Altgeld. The destiny of this mighty nation must be entrusted to men of a different caliber.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
