<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-09-04">Sept. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Division of Europe.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1113</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1113.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-09-04">Sept. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE DIVISION OF EUROPE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Germany steadfastly declares that she has no intention to conquer any territory, and that she is only defending herself in a war which has been forced upon her, while her opponents cannot have the same clear conscience before the history of the world. France is eager to retake Alsace-Lorraine with the addition of the entire left bank of the Rhine, if she wins the war. Great Britain is fighting for the supremacy of her commerce and she also intends to take possession of the German Colonies in Africa to form a great British African Empire. Russia published its intentions even before the war, shortly after the assassination of the Austrian-Hungarian heir to the throne at Sarajevo. It was published in a Russian magazine controlled by the government and it was written by the pen of Prince Swiatopolk-Sciski. In this article, it is stated that the cardinal point of the war must be the dismemberment of middle Europe into a number of independent states competing with one another. The destruction of Germany and Austria-Hungary as governing states must be the main object in connection with the fall of the Hapsburg dynasty and the restitution of the former German federation. East Prussia, and all Polish territory in Prussia, and the province of Posen will have to be annexed by Russia. The greater part of Northern Saxony, which was ceded to Prussia by the Vienna treaty, must be returned to Saxony. The kingdom <pb facs="5418474_5_1114.jpg" n="2"/>of Hanover and the Electorate of Hessia must be reestablished. Finally, Schleswig-Holstein must be returned to Denmark. The main counter weight against Prussia must be a strong Bavaria, double its present size, to which must be added the German provinces of Lower Austria (Styria, Corinthia and Tyrol). This program of Prince Swiatopolk so cleverly worked out in all details before the war ever started concludes with the creation of a Bohemian-Moravian Kingdom, a Croatian Kingdom, and a division of Hungary in two parts, of which one will be given to Roumania. These are the ideal plans of the cabinets in London, France, and St. Petersburg, but as matters look at present, they might result somewhat differently.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
