<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-02-20">Feb. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Let Us Wait and Keep Our Poise</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0751</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0751.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-02-20">Feb. 20, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">LET US WAIT AND KEEP OUR POISE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As we have predicted in this column, the Chancellor of the Reich has replied to the State Department in Washington in a quiet but firm manner, that Germany did not embark on her submarine blockade, beginning February 4, in order to damage neutral shipping wilfully, but to counteract British methods. No neutral country can expect Germany to let her women and children be starved [by the British blockade] just so that neutral shipping can go on as usual. As we have frequently explained before, the responsibility for the German measure is, in the final analysis, the direct result of the foreign policy adopted by these neutral countries. Of the British, one could not expect anything else but that they would try to use all conceivable means to get hold of Germany's trade. They could be expected to violate all international regulations unscrupulously as long as the neutral nations did not protest. And they didn't! "His blood be upon them," said Pilate, when the mob in Jerusalem made him hand over an innocent Jesus instead of the criminal Barabbas.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0752.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>With infinite patience, Germany has watched Denmark send her food products to England, whose ships were plying German waters, carrying butter, eggs, and all good things to eat which Germany has an appetite for. Not one single boat was stopped on its way to England. And what are those scoundrels in Downing Street doing? It makes our blood boil when we read the arguments which that most perfidious of all [British] diplomats sent to the State Department, regarding the confiscation of a shipload of grain carried by the Dutch boat S. S. Wilhelmina. The protest of the United States was a legitimate one. Foodstuffs for the civil population are not contraband. Good care had been taken that the ship did not carry anything but foodstuffs, to eliminate any technical reason for its confiscation. And yet those scoundrels in London have confiscated the grain. The worthy successor of a Suffolk, who admonished his hordes in the War for Independence to kill the insolent revolutionaries with tomahawks and bowie knives, has this to say: "Of course we admit that grain is not countraband, if it is used for consumption by the civil population, but since even the civilians in Germany are an integral part of the military, the bread will finally find its way to the army anyhow." Listening to such interpretations of international <pb facs="5418474_5_0753.jpg" n="3"/>law, should Germany hesitate for one minute to sink anything that comes in front of her cannon or torpedo tubes? There is no more room here for sentimentality. Because of the rebellious spirit of the Belgian civil population towards the army of occupation, the good Saxons and Baravians stationed there are up against a tremendous job. In England these same Belgians would have been chased into the North Sea, if they would have tried stunts like that of the British military. The unbiased observer can easily guage German good nature by the insults it can take in Belgium and which are gleefully reported in Collier's magazine.</p>
   <p>It is unfortunate that the United States, by their own actions, have put themselves in a position where Germany, all peaceful intentions notwithstanding, has to tell them: "We are getting tired of the dry tone in your communications!" But it is a comedy the gods would enjoy, that Germany has to champion America's honor. Because what else can we call it, if Germany is about to punish England for her interference with neutral shipping? America will forever regret it if she gives in to England now. Every child knows what England is up to--she <pb facs="5418474_5_0754.jpg" n="4"/>wants to drive the United States into adopting warlike measures against Germany. These efforts are bound to be frustrated, because there is not the shadow of justification for a war against Germany, unless we admit the relationship with England as a valid reason. That is why it is inconceivable to us, how some German-Americans could declare with eagerness, to be willing to fight on the side of the United States against Germany. Let us first settle the question, which side is right! What happens then depends on the attitude of the governments. Certainly no right-thinking person would be in favor of Germany declaring war upon the United States, and vice versa. If these lamentable circumstances should cause difficulties for "our" trade, London would be the place to complain to.</p>
   <p>The warning, to confiscate ships interned in our harbors and to hold them for any eventual damage sustained by us [our merchant marine] would be technically legal, providing the ships belonged to the German Reich, but not if they belonged to private persons. In the latter case, Germany would have an equal right to confiscate anything belonging to American companies within her territory, like Standard Oil, International Harvester, and tobacco and meat interests.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0755.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>All this is nothing but conjecture, but loudmouthed jingoes in the pay of Northcliffe (Times, London) would like to bring matters to a head. To be sure, they won't have any luck in Washington, but just the same it won't do any harm to take some starch out of their rantings. It is up to us Germans to forestall a break with Germany. This is not only the duty of the little man any more, but merits the efforts of diplomatically trained heads.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
