<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-07-02">July 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">War for the Preservation of Democracy</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0432</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0432.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-07-02">July 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WAR FOR THE PRESERVATION OF DEMOCRACY</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>America is engaged in a War to defend and save Democracy. It fights for the principles of upholding, strengthening, and extending the democratic thought in foreign lands as well as in its own country. War for the democratic thought in foreign lands was strongly advocated by the president, and Congress approving it, declared War upon Germany on April 6, 1917. Germany provoked the conflict by her inexcusable actions--the U-boat war, the provocative incident of the Zimmermann letter, the submarine war note of January 31, etc. However, armed intervention was unavoidable, even without the aforementioned occurrences.</p>
   <p>America is waging its own internal war for the preservation of Democracy, which is, of course, of much longer duration.... War for the democratic thought in the meantime, is progressing abroad as well as at home. However, since America has not shown her real strength against her European adversary <pb facs="5418474_5_0433.jpg" n="2"/>so far, the Allies did not succed in recording any great success, but the War's effect upon foreign countries cannot be questioned.</p>
   <p>Democratic America, ridiculed by powerful and small nations alike for its military importance only a few years ago, is now the leader among nations. America has no	w the power to dictate, if it so chooses. Credit is due America alone,that the democratic thought became prevalent among all nations.</p>
   <p>What about our internal conditions? The immense progress which the democratic thought had already attained before 1913, the Progressive Income Tax, for instance, also the Banking and Coinage Law, the Farm Loan Act, etc., has had many other additions since April 1917. However, one generation would not have sufficed to bring about all these improvements if War had not added its moral support. The Nation's railroads and Express businesses are operated by the Government, and the continuance will eventually lead to Government ownership. The income tax barometer which, fortunately, climbed high, is also here to stay, so will tax upon profits, which tends to curb the unjust accumulation of great wealth in the future. . . . . All these indicate that in a democratic <pb facs="5418474_5_0434.jpg" n="3"/>country the Government is the law. It also expresses the success of the democratic thought against possession of enormous wealth and organized wholesale business, which were in the hands of autocrats until recently.</p>
   <p>Yes, great things have been accomplished. Just as this democratic republic has obtained the leadership and power among nations, whereby the democratic thought became a factor in world politics, so has it also affected the states in our country during the leadership of Woodrow Wilson.</p>
   <p>However, victory is till not complete, therefore, America's new Democracy has resolved to fight to the finish. The recently issued report by the Federal Trade Commission, waging a fight against well-established wholesale profiteering, will show to the Nation--through its eventual successful outcome--how important a part the war has played in behalf of America's own internal soundness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
