<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-10-18">Oct. 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[A Disgusting Spectacle]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter to the Editor) by C. A. Koenig.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0098</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0098.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-10-18">Oct. 18, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[A DISGUSTING SPECTACLE]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter to the Editor) by C. A. Koenig.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Two kinds of sentiments seem to remain constant and unchangeable in our countries after this war of nations--the noble, genuinely American sentiment on one side, and an eternally revengeful and unforgiving attitude on the other. Both are illustrated very distinctly here in Chicago on two different occasions. We visited a "War Relics Exhibition" at Clark and Madison Streets near the Morrison Hotel. It was very interesting, but the so-called "paintings" hanging on the walls all around could only be classified as the height of vileness and vulgarity. They were truly outrageous abominations. They were not, however, the work of an American. One can see very clearly the intention of unrelenting hatred and implacable enmity. German soldiers nailing children to barn doors; women with hands chopped off, surrounded by guffawing German <pb facs="5418474_5_0099.jpg" n="2"/>soldiers; women, children, and priests used by German soldiers as shields against bullets and many other such pictures, which the police would immediately confiscate, if--!</p>
   <p>We know that war is a bestial business and can make a beast out of man regardless of nationality. But the scenes which are on display in this exhibition of filth could hardly be verified by trustworthy witnesses. Hatred and thirst for revenge are to be kept alive by these pictures. We feel sorry that such infamous and positively un-American propaganda is still condoned at this time by the authorities.</p>
   <p>In sharp contrast to this are the travelogues which are now being given by Mr. Newman in Orchestra Hall. We attended his lecture on "Occupied Germany". The house was packed. Many a hothead probably expected to hear an anti-German propaganda speech and to see the type of pictures we have described above. But nothing of the kind! Mr. Newman spoke quite objectively, emphasized the highlights and shadows in a simple and often humoristic manner and talked with <pb facs="5418474_5_0100.jpg" n="3"/>admiration of the perseverence, industry and excellent discipline within the German occupied zone. The wonderful Rhineland is shown, German cities with beautiful bridges and buildings and romantic ruins and their traffic. Everything as it was before the War, with the exception of the numerous foreign soldiers everywhere. But nobody bothers them in the least. Mr. Newman mentioned particularly how well our American boys get along with the German population, although they always ask, "When do we go home?" A picture showing two American soldiers with two German girls who are working in a field would in itself make going to hear the talk worthwhile. Fraternizing with the enemy is strictly prohibited, but it was found out later that the two German girls, according to the soldiers, were not their enemies at all, but their sweethearts!</p>
   <p>Such purely objective pictures and lectures certainly contribute more to real peace among nations and reconstruction of the world, than that shameful exhibition on Clark Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
