<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-21">Feb. 21, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">School for the One-Armed</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0477</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.f"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0477.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 f</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-21">Feb. 21, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">SCHOOL FOR THE ONE-ARMED</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The principle of the German Aid to Invalids consists in making the injured soldier independent of his environment. The more the disabled man realizes and notes from personal experience that much can be accomplished with only a single hand, or even none, the easier it will be for him to disregard the loss of these members and yet feel as confident as a fully capable man.</p>
   <p>The schools for the one-armed, conducted by the German Red Cross, start the training of the injured soldiers at the morning rising hour. Under the supervision of a competent teacher, they are taught to dress themselves, wash, and make their beds. Even the breakfast becomes a subject for tuition, since eating, cutting bread, and meat with only one hand requires dexterity and it can only be acquired by practice.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0478.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The next subject is writing. Instruction therein is given by apt petty officers who lost their right arm. It is really astounding what a rapid progress the students make in writing and drawing with the left hand. Much time is given to carving and modeling, as such work is an excellent form of exercise to re-learn a trade or to re-acquire lost skill. Advice is also given on lock construction, door locks, carpentry, and gardening.</p>
   <p>A change of vocation, nevertheless, is necessary in many instances. Here also the School for the One-Armed, a branch of the German Red Cross, offers adequate tuition; and this war aid, just one of the many provisions, not only helps eliminate monotony during the convalescence period but it also banishes despair by recreating the ambition and joy to work, as well as that serenity of thought, a by-product derived from personal accomplishment, the true basis of self-reliance in man.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0479.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Nothing is more injurious to the war-crippled than compassion. "Spare us with your sympathy" is a shout often uttered by the brave. They do not like to be reminded constantly of their tragic sacrifices for the Fatherland, yet, well meaning words and kindred references to their condition invariably recall their loss. What we need now is sincere, active help. Friends of the German cause may send contributions to the German-Austro-Hungarian Aid Society, corner La Salle and Randolph Streets, at any time, and this association will forward them.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
