<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">An Appeal to German Americans</title><title level="a" type="sub">Campaign Funds for War Savings Stamps Committee Must Be Raised</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-14">Sept. 14, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">AN APPEAL TO GERMAN AMERICANS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Campaign Funds for War Savings Stamps Committee Must Be Raised</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Judge John Stelk, chairman of the German department of the Illinois Committee for War Savings Stamps, has sent letters to a number of well-known German-Americans in this city, calling their attention to the raising of a campaign fund for the War Savings Stamps Committee, in which they have fallen short of their duty, and pointing out that in case Americans of German descent should, against all expectations, not prove equal to their task, the fault would be their own. The letter reads as follows:</p>
   <p>"Although the indifference with which the appeal for contributions to the campaign fund for the War Savings Stamps Committee of Illinois was received seems to bear out the allegation that Americans of German descent feel lukewarm about the matter, I myself will not share this opinion before I have made another attempt.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0373.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"The strange thing is that people with limited means prove to be much more generous than the former spokesmen of the German-Americans who are known to enjoy wealth and influence.</p>
   <p>"In case the fifteen thousand dollars demanded by this department have to be raised, I shall need your assistance. Should you refuse it, the fault will be yours if the German department is not successful. I have been told by various sources that if Germans contribute to this purpose, they will do so only as Americans. But this is a false notion. On account of their birth or origin, they will always be regarded as German-Americans, and the same accusations will be made against them as against other Americans of German descent. Neither have they any reason to be ashamed of their blood, for the deeds of their fathers and forefathers have been written with indelible letters in the history of the United States.</p>
   <p>"All money invested in Liberty Bonds, War Savings Stamps, etc., will be paid back to the last penny, but in the present case, there will be no other reward than the feeling of having helped the government. Illinois is far behind <pb facs="5418474_5_0374.jpg" n="3"/>with her contributions, and the German department has no reason at all to be proud of its accomplishments.</p>
   <p>"It is the duty of all those who can help, to grant us their assistance and in this way to refute the accusations made against well-to-do German-Americans. Please lend us your help!"</p>
   <p>John Stelk</p>
   <p>Chairman of the German department of the War Savings Stamps Committee of Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
