<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-07-28">July 28, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">Reform and Uniform Suggestions</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1655</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1655.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I F 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1924-07-28">July 28, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">REFORM AND UNIFORM SUGGESTIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>United States Commissioner J. Frank Supplee .... discovered that his Prohibition agents are beset with difficulties because they lack uniforms. The gentlemen hit the nail on the head so to speak, and Chicago's "representatives of the desert" will gladly subscribe to that. After all, is it not rather annoying when these zealous and dutiful gentlemen are arrested by the local police, just after having succeeded in confiscating a load of beer? And that is precisely what happened to the decorous servants of our National aridity. They were arrested, including their truck, wherein fourteen and one-half barrels of beer rested so complacently. And when the minions of the law showed their shields, the police replied in a most impertinent and brutal manner that all of Chicago's beer runners carry such "tin tags." The Prohibition Agents implored their chief to send help, but before the re-enforcements arrived, they were exposed to the ridicule of a heartless crowd, <pb facs="5418474_5_1656.jpg" n="2"/>and the beer became warm.</p>
   <p>How differently matters would have been if the agents had only worn uniforms. The citizenry of our good city still remember the joyful and sorrowful episode when a number of prohibition officers were arrested in a negro cabaret. Of course, they had gone there on official business. They desired to observe how jungle liquor affects talented and temperamental sepia-hued dancers in order to use this evidence against the cabaret owners. The gentlemen were highly engrossed in their legal contemplations, and noted with profound satisfaction that the terpsichoreans executed a few movements of the Hula Hula and "danse du ventre" undoubtedly inspired by liberal imbibing of jungle distillate. Just then the police appeared and arrested the Prohibition agents. Such incidents are disagreeable. This is likely to spoil the pleasure which the brave men derive from their vocation. After all, they dedicated themselves to fight demon Rum.</p>
   <p>And, therefore, they should wear uniforms, so that their contemporaries and <pb facs="5418474_5_1657.jpg" n="3"/>co-citizens will be imbued with the proper respect, and this also prevents police interference in the future. Of course, their regalia should be symbolically suggestive. Here, we have a fertile field for imagination. How would the following design appeal? Clothing cut to conform to the military pattern, the color of delicate Pilzner beer? The cap should be embroidered with a wreath of grapes, which is both beautiful and designative, and as moonshine is not very suitable for pictorial reproduction, it might be advisable to use the "insignia of the copper coil" which converts the scofflaw vapor into liquid potentialities.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
