<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-10-30">October 30, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Peace on Earth.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1008</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1008.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-10-30">October 30, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">PEACE ON EARTH.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Wilson yesterday issued his Thanksgiving Proclamation and designated November 26th as the day of Thanksgiving. Like all of President Wilson's proclamations, this also is a masterpiece of composition. Whoever reads this document, without knowing the circumstances under which it was written, feels obliged to bend his knees before the author and to congratulate the nation for having at its head a man of clear thought, of deep perception, of statesmanlike wisdom, and imposing humanity. Under the searchlight, showing actual conditions, produced through truth, that document, we regret to say, assumes a different feature, a strongly reduced value. Whoever knows conditions and can judge events correctly, will, no doubt, enjoy the exquisite language of the document, but at the same time will put it aside with great regret. He will only have found words which soundlessly fade away, because they do not sprout from reality. The President calls special attention to the fact, that it was allotted to us, to live in honorable peace and to be able to help the sufferers. This assertion regrettably, is, only the delusion of a man, who is removed from actual life, and entangled in his own ideas. We certainly live in peace, but this peace cannot be called honorable. We live in peace, because we comprehend our duties wrongly. Had this country recognized its duty honestly, it should have made an end long <pb facs="5418474_5_1009.jpg" n="2"/>ago to the incendiarism in the neighbor Republic, even at the risk of war and should not have stood by with folded arms while the unfortunate Mexican people carry on an endless fratricidal war. To separate quarreling parties, is a more honorable task, than to let them thrash each other till utter exhaustion, and then to praise peace with eyes turned towards heaven. So speaks only down-right egotism, which only thinks of itself. Whoever, as man or nation, is placed in front of a mission, must fulfill this mission with the sacrifice of his or its own peace, and will be satisfied only after this mission has been fulfilled. And also in respect ot Japan, our peace can not be called an honorable one. We promised the Asiatic Sister Republic Neutrality, and when Japan, without compulsory reasons, and only driven by war lust, invaded Chinese territory, he tried to make believe, that this occurred, from military necessity, simply because it was more convenient and safer for us to live in an honorable peace. And also with the help which we grant to the sufferers and needy in Europe, we have no right to boast. It is not the all forgetting human feeling, which guides us by doing so. It is partly greediness, partly blind prejudice, against those who do not need our help.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
