<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-14">Jan. 14, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Dignity Is Missing!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0257</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0257.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-14">Jan. 14, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">DIGNITY IS MISSING!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The United States Senate has been, and on occasion still is, called the most dignified body in the world and it likes to hear it; so does the average citizen. He would like it better, however, if only his designation seemed justified to some extent.</p>
   <p>Consequently, the Senate watches over its dignity very jealously at times, and in outward manifestations, and quite often to the disadvantage of a good cause or a particular job which calls for quick action in the interest of the country and the people. By that we mean that courtesy rules and that regulations which protect the rights of members are observed with painful and exacting consciousness, even when the members talk balderdash; and the less sense their babblings make, the more ostentatiously this unlimited privilege of speech is emphasized. The idea probably is that the dignity <pb facs="5418474_5_0258.jpg" n="2"/>of the Senate is so great and sublime that even the curse of ridicule cannot touch it, and that the general dignity is even augmented--and appears in a brighter light--when individual members make themselves ridiculous. But the Senate may be wrong about this. The average citizen is quite direct in his thinking; he believes what he hears and sees and is inclined to judge by appearances. Every time a Senator talks poppycock, the respect which the people have for the Senate suffers. For the public argues in this way: The Senate as a whole is equal to the average mentality of its members and this average cannot be very great if instances of such low quality occur.</p>
   <p>Mind you, we refer only to nonsensical talk--not to malicious, "unpatriotic," and "un-American" oratory, which to many may seem not only in poor taste but also stupid; but then, again, may appear to others as politically smart and promoting a more or less desirable objective. What we mean here is just the idle talk, the purpose and aim of which would defy description. We refer to the kind of gossip, for instance, which Senator Myers of Montana dispensed yesterday when he said that Germany must not be admitted to the League of <pb facs="5418474_5_0259.jpg" n="3"/>Nations under any circumstances; that Germany "should be annihilated as a nation"; that the German leaders should be severly punished; that he did not have any patience with "false sentimentality". The Kaiser, he remarked, should be executed without due process of law, and Count Bernstorff, Von Papen, and Dernburg should be imprisoned for life. And to the question of Senator Poindexter, whether the Kaiser should be hanged or shot, Myers, the Senator from Montana, replied, with profound conviction in his voice, "Both!"</p>
   <p>We cannot expect too much from a Senator from Montana. Montana has not much room for choice, with its population of 460,000. That makes 230,000 for each Senator, about the number of people living in one of the larger Chicago wards. But even if little can be expected, Myers should not have talked the way he did, for what he said was nothing but unadulterated and unmitigated nonsense. It just did not make any sense, unless we assume that the Senator was trying, by his own behavior, to prove the correctness of Darwin's theory that man is descended from the higher apes. That, in turn, would be extremely stupid and malicious and unfair besides--unfair to the contemporary four-handed simians.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0260.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>We wonder where Myers originated, how he managed to get himself elected United States Senator, and what induced him, of all people, to call himself a Democrat.</p>
   <p>A. Myers, who claims to be a Democrat, says that the German nation should be exterminated and that the former German Kaiser should be both hanged and shot. He makes a long speech to that effect in the United States Senate--and the United States Senate claims to be the most dignified body in the world; and it would be all that if the people could bring it about; the most exalted and selected body on the globe!</p>
   <p>Too bad. Too bad for the dignity of the Senate, too bad for the good name "Democrat". Too bad that President Wilson and his loyal co-workers in the great task of the reconciliation of peoples and nations are helpless to stop this abuse.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
