<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-30">Apr. 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">The "Trial of an Emperor"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0132</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0132.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-30">Apr. 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">THE "TRIAL OF AN EMPEROR"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From Paris we have received information that Count Wilhelm von Hohenzollern, the former German Emperor, is to be prosecuted. He is to be tried before the "Big Five," because he allegedly offended against international morals and violated the sanctity of treaties. So the report goes. Such a trial is not a certainty. And neither is it probable. It is scarcely possible. For upon analysis of the facts of the alleged prosecution, one finds that the proposition is full of flaws, and that such a procedure would establish a precedent which might prove to be very "inconvenient" and dangerous in the future. And what was said about the people of Nuremberg in days of yore is still true today: "They hanged nobody until they had caught him"; and it is very doubtful, to say the least, that Holland would surrender Count Wilhelm von Hohenzollern. It is very possible that Paris expects, or even positively knows, that a request to deliver the former German Emperor <pb facs="5418474_5_0133.jpg" n="2"/>would not be honored, and that Paris is anticipating such an outcome. It is also possible that Paris is eager for such an outcome and that she proclaimed to all the world that the former Emperor would be prosecuted for his offenses against international morals and against the sanctity of treaties, in the hope of saving the faces of those who have laid all blame for the war upon the Kaiser, and have loudly demanded that he be punished. Although it may later be evident that it is impossible to prosecute and convict him, still the charge will stand; and the accusation will be reiterated and emphasized until all points of the accusation will be regarded as irrefutable, and in time, will be looked upon as true even by those who today are not convinced.</p>
   <p>The power of these unrefuted and therefore lasting accusations is generally known, and is feared so much that any innocent, self-respecting victim usually demands a trial, unless certain other factors, such as consideration for others,force him to suffer in silence. Every day we hear or read either that some officer or more or less prominent citizen demands that he be tried <pb facs="5418474_5_0134.jpg" n="3"/>for alleged offenses, or he uses all the legal means at his disposal to force people who accuse him or spread evil reports about him to prove the truth of their statements before a court. Why should not the former German Emperor, Count Wilhelm von Hohenzollern, do likewise?</p>
   <p>There may be various reasons why the case cannot be tried. It is certain that nothing of the kind has ever occurred in the history of the world. But many other things which have happened during the last five years, and are happening now, have never happened before; so this, too, could come to pass. If all objections and obstacles could be removed and the trial conducted in conformity with law and justice, and if provisions were made for an impartial trial with the accused given ample opportunity to present his side of the question before an unbiased tribunal--and thus before the opinion of the world--would that not be the best thing that could happen? Would it not serve the best interests of all humanity, especially those of the German people, who have suffered so much under the accusation that their leaders alone are responsible for the War and they (the German people) are just as blameworthy because they supported their leaders? Would it <pb facs="5418474_5_0135.jpg" n="4"/>not be best for the German Emperor, if he feels that he is innocent, or if he believes he can prove that he is only partly to blame, and that he per-haps made mistakes and thus helped to bring about the terrible massacre, but never intended to start a war?</p>
   <p>Assuming that a fair trial would be conducted before an international court, in which the United States would be represented, a layman would think that the former Emperor himself would demand a hearing, if not in order to justify himself, then out of consideration for the German people, who have endured so much, and who will continue to suffer for the sins of which he is accused.</p>
   <p>A fair trial would bring the truth to light, and we are all in need of the truth. We must all strive for the truth, if we hope for a better future. And a fair trial would reveal much that is of great interest; more perhaps than a certain person would like. Perhaps the former German Emperor, who <pb facs="5418474_5_0136.jpg" n="5"/>is now living in Holland as a refugee under the name "Count Wilhelm von Hohenzollern," would thwart his foremost enemies, by demanding a trial, or by voluntarily surrendering to a reliable court. Of course, in order to do this, the former Emperor must possess an absolute sense of innocence and confidence in the justice of his cause.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
