<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-09-14">Sept. 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A New Attack in Sight</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0069</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0069.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1933-09-14">Sept. 14, 1933</date>.
<title level="a">A NEW ATTACK IN SIGHT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Roosevelt certainly performed one of his greatest services when he put a stop to the raids on the Federal Treasury. It was not easy for him to put through the bills for the reduction of veterans' pensions, and he was able to accomplish this only because he exerted on Congress all the influence he possessed. But anyone who believes that the question of the veterans' pension has been decided for good is wrong. The professional pension hunters do not give up.</p>
   <p>By the new laws Congress has done away with, or checked, only the worst abuses and scandals in the pension system, but among the leaders of the veterans there are some who have a different idea. When the American Legion of New Jersey held its convention a few days ago, one of their leaders declared that the veterans "had been nailed on the cross" by the Administration. This <pb facs="5418474_5_0070.jpg" n="2"/>patriot also declared: "You cannot endure that any longer. You will be told that you are to keep yourselves aloof from politics. That you cannot do."</p>
   <p>The man is right. Anyone who wishes to live without working, anyone who wants something from the Government, must go into politics. The manufacturers have done it for generations, the farmers for decades, the steamship companies, the railroads--all went into politics to win advantages and privileges which did not rightfully belong to them. About forty years ago James Tanner, the most successful pension politician in history, gave the G. A. R. the same advice. The veterans of the Civil War followed his advice, and the result was that the Federal Treasury paid out billions of dollars.</p>
   <p>One can probably assume that the great mass of the veterans want nothing to do with this policy, but, after all, they are only human, and the human motive is always decisive. Who can resist the temptation to get something for nothing? And how does the definition of the word "democracy" go? A democracy is that form of government in which every citizen wants something from the government.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
