<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-23">Apr. 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Victory Liberty Loan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0152</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0152.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-23">Apr. 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">VICTORY LIBERTY LOAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the German Societies of Chicago!</p>
   <p>The Foreign-Language Division of the Victory Liberty Loan Organization will hold a parade on Sunday afternoon, April 27. This parade will consist of floats, and will start at the Municipal Pier, proceeding south on Michigan Avenue to "Victory Theater" which has been erected in Grant Park. A mass meeting will be held there, and each nationality will be presented with a white flag containing a gold star which will symbolize the expression of gratitude on the part of the American Government for the patriotic sacrifices which were made during the War.</p>
   <p>The relatives of those in the parade from the various nationalities will not march, but will view it from reserved positions. The flag-bearers of the Societies, and of the various nationalities will meet at two o'clock at the Art Institute, Adams Street and Michigan Avenue, and will follow the floats <pb facs="5418474_5_0153.jpg" n="2"/>to the "Victory Theater". This is the first distinctive demonstration of its kind which the several nationalities will make, apart from their participation in the other groups of the Organization. The motto is: "Americans All". It is up to you to give the Germans first place among the foreign-language groups; they are entitled to it. If all of you appear for this demonstration, Chicago will see that no nationality is so strongly represented, nor has rendered so valuable a service. Every one of you has willingly made sacrifices in contributing money. Thousands of Americans of German origin have shed their blood for their country, and thousands have met a hero's death in conflict. You will do honor to them and to yourselves, if you participate in this all-American demonstration in corpore.</p>
   <p>The place of assembly of the German Societies will be indicated by an American and a black-gold flag, and will be made known through the press.</p>
   <p>Victory Liberty Loan Organization, Foreign-Language Division,</p>
   <p>Henry Zander, Chairman of the German Division;</p>
   <p>Felix J. Streykmans, Federal Reserve Director.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
