<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-14">Aug. 14, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Yiddish Press and the War</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1158</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-jewish #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1158.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C (Jewish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-14">Aug. 14, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE YIDDISH PRESS AND THE WAR</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Relatively few of our readers know that in the United States there are a number of newspapers, periodicals, and weeklies which are published in Yiddish and which have tremendous influence on their hundreds of thousands of readers. Most of these publications have a socialistic flavor which conforms to the radical political convictions of their readers, who are mostly Russian immigrants of Jewish faith. The two Yiddish dailies with the largest circulation are the Tageblatt and the Wahrheit. Their editorial policy is authoritative for most of the other yiddish newspapers, therefore it was interesting to observe which attitude they would adopt towards the European war. All doubts were removed when two flaming articles appeared, both of which put the two dailies unconditionally on the German side.</p>
   <p>The article closest to the point appeared in the Tageblatt, from which the <pb facs="5418474_5_1159.jpg" n="2"/>following excerpts are given:</p>
   <p>"What have the Russians, Poles, Bulgarians, Serbs ever done for civilization? They have invented nothing, have built no political systems, nor have they given us any new ideas. Everything these races possess they have taken away from others. Their own specialties are to arrange massacres, to torture and crucify innocent people,and to be wantonly cruel.</p>
   <p>"We all know the bestiality of the Russians. The Serbs betrayed their brutal character when a few years ago they invaded the bedroom of their royal couple and slaughtered them, in order to put the present King Peter on the throne. The atrocities committed by the Bulgarians during the last Balkan wars are familiar to us through the reports of the commission which has investigated these bestialities.</p>
   <p>"Such is the character of that lowly, ignorant, barbaric, and sinister race which has declared war on the civilized nations of Europe in order to gain control over <pb facs="5418474_5_1160.jpg" n="3"/>them. That is the race which, under the despotism of the Russian Czars, has been clamoring for the way to Constantinople for centuries.</p>
   <p>"No greater calamity could befall the world--not only Europe, but the whole civilized world--than for this race to become victorious. A victory of the Slavs means the death blow to education, democracy, liberty, and free thought.</p>
   <p>"A victory of the Slavs means the nullification of all the progress which Europe has made during the last four hundred years, and it would also mean that the forward march of civilization would be halted for a long time to come.</p>
   <p>"What a horrible and disgraceful spectacle it is to see a free France help Russia spread Slavic barbarism over Europe! And to have to watch England, the 'Mother of Parliaments,' herself a nation of Teutonic stock, attack Germany in order to help the savage Slavs destroy the progress of mankind. Out of fear of Germany, these two countries, representing culture, education, and progress, have decided to bring about a catastrophe for civilization."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
