<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-18">Mar. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Flour Shipments Via Parcel Post</title><title level="a" type="sub">Various Kinds of Food Packages a Beginning the Sentimental Value of the Idea</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0712</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0712.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-03-18">Mar. 18, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">FLOUR SHIPMENTS VIA PARCEL POST</title><title level="a" type="sub">Various Kinds of Food Packages A Beginning The Sentimental Value of the Idea</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As reported yesterday, a large and responsible Chicago business firm has agreed to take over and manage the shipment of parcel post packages containing flour and other kinds of foodstuffs to Germany and Austria-Hungary. Several kinds of packages have been put up and given a number, so all that is necessary is to mention the number of the package desired to be sent.</p>
   <p>Below is a list of various types of parcels:</p>
   <p>#1. 10 lbs. of best quality wheat flour .................$1.90</p>
   <p>#2. 5 lbs. of best quality wheat flour; . . ................</p>
   <p>5 lbs. of ham.........................................................$2.20</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0713.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>#3. 5 lbs. of flour;</p>
   <p>2 ½ lbs. of bacon .........................$2.00</p>
   <p>#4. 5 lbs. of flour;</p>
   <p>3 packages of macaroni;</p>
   <p>3 packages of spaghetti....................$2.00</p>
   <p>#5. 5 lbs. of flour;</p>
   <p>3 lbs. of rice;</p>
   <p>2 lbs. of noodles.............................$2.00</p>
   <p>#6. 5 lbs. of flour;</p>
   <p>1 quart of preserves;</p>
   <p>1 can of peanut butter.......................$2.00</p>
   <p>#7. 5 lbs. of crackers;</p>
   <p>1 quart of best quality preserves.................$2.00</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0714.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>These prices include postage, wrappings, and all other expenses.</p>
   <p>We should like to add that the quality is uniformly good and the price is held as low as possible under the circumstances.</p>
   <p>The above price quotations do not include insurance, since it was generally assumed that it would not be necessary, parcel post service being considered absolutely dependable. But anybody who wants to, can have his parcel insured by paying ten cents extra to Uncle Sam.</p>
   <p>The business concern in question does not care to have its name mentioned in the paper, but will issue an individual receipt for each order given.</p>
   <p>The idea to send flour and other foodstuffs "over there" via parcel post, has undoubtedly met with great favor among the public, because it originated with the public, as it were. If we are not mistaken, hundreds, or even thousands, <pb facs="5418474_5_0715.jpg" n="4"/>of such parcels will be mailed within the next few days. The people know very well that this scheme does not pay from a business point of view, since the shipping expenses are all out of proportion and then, too, it would be impossible to feed the German people in this way or to avert a food shortage, if that were in the offing. But people realize that the sentimental value of these gifts more than makes up for the lack of commercial success of the experiment and may even yield a "plus", although not in dollars and cents. If we can interpret the general attitude correctly, the few pennies of extra expense do not matter at all in view of the fact that dear relatives and friends will be made happy, just as we would be happy if we'd unexpectedly receive a nice food package from America's west coast. People feel that these gifts will be welcomed by rich and poor alike, who have to do without such foods for the time being, even though there is no actual starvation, and because these parcels are a token of brotherly love and remembrance. These manifestations of an ardent effort on the part of German men and women in America, to make their brothers and sisters in the old country happy, demonstrate again the unity of all the Deutschtum (things German) to its enemies everywhere in the world.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0716.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This seems to be the basic idea behind those parcel post shipments--to make the folks over there happy during these hard times; a messenger of love and loyalty.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
