<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-08-06">August 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Deliberate Friendliness of America.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0656</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0656.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-08-06">August 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">DELIBERATE FRIENDLINESS OF AMERICA.</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the title "Deliberate Unfriendliness," we have just concluded a series of articles, in which we, on the grounds of actual events, brought proof that our government has planned its, unfriendly attitude toward Germany. On the other hand, it would certainly pay, in another series of articles, to prove how honestly Germany tried, even in the most critical moments, to prove to the United States its honest friendship. And in spite of its honest friendship, Germany has never made any claims against the United States. It has not even asked that the Republic should cease to assist Germany's enemies.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0657.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Germany wanted to finish its fight alone without foreign help; it only desired not to be interfered with by others. But the United States did not accede even to this modest wish. The government permitted American citizens, to travel on ships carrying contraband of war and demanded from the German war administration, that in consideration of the Americans on board. Germany should cut her own throat, and allow munitions landed at the seat of war.</p>
   <p>But even this unjust challenging demand could not exhaust the patience, the friendliness of Germany, toward the United States. And this friendliness found a renewed expression lately. While England took harmless American citizens off neutral ships and placed them in jails, Germany, on the other hand, gave an American citizen who was guilty of treason, upon request of the American Government, his freedom.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0658.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The man in question is Harris L. Wilson of Portland, Oregon, who was an official in the American consulate in Berlin. This Wilson certified at the consulate that an Englishman who spied in Germany was an American citizen. The Britisher, therefore, with the help of the consul, was enabled to leave Germany. When the truth came to light, Wilson escaped, but was arrested on the Danish frontier and returned to Berlin, where, naturally, a severe punishment awaited him. Then the American Government interfered, in spite of the fact that we forfeited every claim to consideration on the part of the German Government. The German Government proved itself magnanimous, even in this case, and gave the political criminal his freedom, and he returned to this country. The pro-British newspapers, which would like to see us German citizens decapitated, because we are making use of our right to express our opinion freely, do not find it worth while to even mention the liberation of this American traitor. They obviously want to prevent German barbarians from appearing in a favorable light before the world.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
