<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-11-06">Nov. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">German Friends and German Enemies</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1000</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1000.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1914-11-06">Nov. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN FRIENDS AND GERMAN ENEMIES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>While they are trying to indoctrinate the Germans of Chicago with the infamous doctrine that while supplying the Allies with war materials, which brings in dollars and cents, every German should rejoice that Germany's enemies receive the means from "neutral" America to continue the war, there is one dyed-in-the-wool Democratic newspaper, of a different opinion. The "New Yorker Staats Zeitung," which in all political questions followed the Democratic Party through thick and thin wrote an editorial about the annihilating defeat which the Democrats suffered in the State as well as in the city of New York, and concluded with the remarkable essay: The Administration in Washington, for their often criticized deportment in the neutrality question, deserve a box on the ear, there is no doubt, that many voters of German descent, who were Democratically inclined, will withhold their votes from the Democratic candidate for Governor. Are they going to deduct the consequences from this <pb facs="5418474_5_1001.jpg" n="2"/>lesson in the Federal capitol, Not only in the capitol, but also in editorial offices of some German Newspapers, the lesson should be taught, that the spirit of liberty, the spirit of respectability, cannot be disgraced for party considerations. And especially, in the editorial offices of German newspapers, where they latelyseem to side with those, whose object, it appears to be to put on the hypocritcal mask, to cover their partiality, should take cognizance of the fact, that only frankness will lead to the goal, and that with distortions they only hurt themselves.</p>
   <p>There is not one German in this country, who wants to cause economical damage to the Republic, for the simple reason of merely justifying his German sympathies. But no German can, conscientiously, support a Government, which first falls on its knees to pray to the Almighty to finish the war, and in the next moment, for vile profit taking sanctions the prolongation of the war. Against such methods, the population of this country, showed its attitude last Tuesday, when, in some parts of the country, it simply swept <pb facs="5418474_5_1002.jpg" n="3"/>away the Democrats, even after President Wilson's announcement, that he would consider the results of the election as an expression of confidence or as a vote of censure towards him personally. And we hope that the assertion of the New Yorker Staats Zeitung, that German Democrats, owing to the Government's attitude, were voting against the Democratic Party, is correct. Everywhere in the country, the Germans, regardless of their party affiliations should oppose energetically a policy, which after having first caused the economic ruin of the country, drives it now in to moral bankruptcy.</p>
   <p>The defeat of the present administration, is felt to be a deliverance by the business world, and already a fresher wave of air is fluttering through our commercial life. But this defeat has been received with even greater satisfaction by those citizens, who can not defend themselves with a policy of miserable hypocrisy and helplessness.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
