<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Chicago Tribune</title>,
<date when="1914-08-04">Aug. 4, 1914</date>, p.5
<title level="a">Loyalty to U. S. Comes First Assert Germans Resolutions Adopted at Meeting Deplore Existence of War,But Hold Allegiance Is Here.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1225</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1225.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Chicago Daily Tribune</title>,
<date when="1914-08-04">Aug. 4, 1914</date>, p.5
<title level="a">LOYALTY TO U. S. COMES FIRST ASSERT GERMANS RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED AT MEETING DEPLORE EXISTENCE OF WAR,BUT HOLD ALLEGIANCE IS HERE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At an organization meeting held at the Germania Club last night it was voted to present the following resolution to a huge mass meeting of Germans and Austrians by birth and descent later in the week:</p>
   <p>"Those here assembled, American citizens of German and Austro-Hungarian parentage and descent having met for the purpose of giving vote to their sentiments relative to the war now in progress between the countries from which they come and other European nations, have embodied their thoughts in the following resolutions. "We deplore the existence of a state of war in this enlightened age, and fervently hope that it may end speedly and that peace and the pursuit of happiness may soon be restored to all the people of Europe.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1226.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"We American citizen by birth or by adoption, can take no active part in this struggle. Our allegiance now as at all times, belongs to the United States, our own country, for which now, as in the past we are ready to sacrifice our possessions and our lives. Come what may, we are loyal Americans, now and forever.</p>
   <p>"We declare however, that our love for and our attachment to our adopted country does not prevent us from extending sympathy and affection to the people of Germany and Austro-Hungary, with whom we are allied by ties of blood and fellowship.</p>
   <p>"We pledge ourselves, one and all of those who have come here, and to the best of our abilities we will attempt to alleviate the sufferings of those who in our Mother lands are burdened with the horrors of war.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
