<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-12-31">Dec. 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Where We Stand.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0445</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0445.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-12-31">Dec. 31, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">WHERE WE STAND.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>What Henry Vollmer said, Saturday, about the attitude of the German-Americans in these serious times will be repeated by generations as their patriotic creed. This was expressed by August Lueders and Charles W. Wurster to a reporter of the Staats Zeitung. As Mr. Vollmer declared: "The 311 names of members of the German Club, or their sons and members of their families, are a testimonial that the love and loyalty to the country, which either by choice or by birth became their home, and which they have proved through sacrifice of their lives and chattels, has not cooled. It belongs to the proud conviction of the German that he never hesitates where duty calls, and that he even, with a bleeding heart, fulfills it faithfully. Mr. Vollmer has, with great understanding, placed his finger on the wound, from which the German-Americans are bleeding today; the uncertainty and the hatred which from certain quarters has been instigated against the Americans of German birth. It the patriotic feeling of some Germans is not expressed in public the reason of it lies in the unmerited enmity, which they meet with in certain circles. Their hearts are true without any insincerity. Mr. Vollmer tried in his speech to open the eyes of many people and persuade them to reflect upon the question. He said: "The past as well as the present in the history of the United States speaks a very clear language. The lists of the volunteers, the participants in the Liberty <pb facs="5418474_5_0446.jpg" n="2"/>Loans, the collections for the Y. M. C. A. and the Red Cross are pronounced documents for the patriotism of the German-American, who through deeds, with few words, proves how and where we stand." The admonition of Mr. Vollmer, that all national sentiment, natural feeling, private views, etc., must cease and our property, blood and highest honor have to be dedicated to the country that received us and offered us protection and freedom, found a loud echo last Saturday among those present. Also his assertion that our loyalty cannot be questioned when we, our sons, brothers, and beloved ones prove it to the country. That which we defend ourselves against and which we raise our voice against, are those hateful, fanatical elements who try to carry on the war with lies. They are not satisfied to sling mud at the loyal citizens of German descent, no, they even attack the dead.</p>
   <p>Repeatedly the words of Mr. Vollmer, with which he denied the justification and truth of the reports about German cruelties, found an echo in the hearts of the thousands of his listeners. These insults against our ancestors, we are unable to tolerate. We refuse to believe even the tenth part of the reports, and therefore we reject them. Also against the fanatics who try to age war against art and literature, Mr. Vollmer raised his voice. "They fight against Wagner's music, against Schiller's literature, and Luther's philosophy", declared the speaker. "Every citizen of German descent," said Mr. Vollmer, "should not only do his share, but even <pb facs="5418474_5_0447.jpg" n="3"/>more. Send your sons into the fight with the admonition to sacrifice more than the next man, and prove their forefathers did not deserve such slanderous attacks."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
