<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-21">Feb. 21, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Why a War against Germany?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0480</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0480.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-21">Feb. 21, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">WHY A WAR AGAINST GERMANY?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>[Summary: Congressional meeting, Saturday 19th. Senator James Hamilton Lewis' speech described as a memorable event. At first the great hall was well-nigh empty, but before the Senator had finished, floor and gallery were crowded. He was given much acclaim, and at the conclusion his colleagues congratulated him. Reports state his speech made a profound, far-reaching impression. Transl.]</p>
   <p>Lewis' questions are justified. Why a war against Germany? What new sources for campaign funds are opened thereby to our Republican friends? What interests prompted them to seek a conflict with Germany?</p>
   <p>A war now after a Republican Administration left us without a fleet or <pb facs="5418474_5_0481.jpg" n="2"/>army and unable to defend ourselves for twenty-four hours, i.e., if the assertions of our Republican friends are correct.</p>
   <p>Why the agitation against Germany? Why the intense animosity towards Wilson's policy now, at the very instant when it seemed as if the sordid Lusitania question was definitely settled, and an understanding had been reached with Germany about submarine warfare; and the road would be clear, at last, to emphasize our demands and prosecute our claims against England?</p>
   <p>Why the war propaganda now? And, above all, why have the Republicans tried so assiduously at the beginning of the war to convince us that the Republic is prostrate and not capable of conducting a war for even twenty-four hours?</p>
   <p>Just a few words about the last query. At the time when Root, Lodge, <pb facs="5418474_5_0482.jpg" n="3"/>Gardner and associates proved the defenselessness of our Republic, we were not confronted with a Lusitania and U-boat problem; during that period no one thought about the possibility of becoming embroiled in a German war. Then it was manifestly the order of the day, that we must meekly submit to England's and her Allies' transgressions; to do otherwise would be suicidal. Eventually came the Lusitania catastrophe and ever since an impending fight with the Teutons is being painted in lurid colors and preached about promiscuously. Now the great struggle with the Huns resolves itself into an uncomprising insistence, because one feels fully assured that Wilson and the Democratic Congress are unequivocally opposed to any such intercession and thus the belief prevails that it is possible now to depict our administration as a weak, spineless entity, and convince the public accordingly. The present idea consists in proclaiming us to be incapable of protecting our interests, the ideals of the Nation; to be fear-imbued and cowardly.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0483.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The animadversion about apprehension and unwillingness to risk a war, and possibly actually becoming involved, will probably be admitted by most of our citizens. But the majority will think about a war with England, as that only would be justified, hence expectable; and then comes the introspection that our submissiveness towards England is one of the Republican accomplishments, bequeathed to us by that party's successive rule of sixteen years, during which it refrained from giving us an adequate defense-and to-day it is dominated in its entirety by the pro-British interests, which is so overwhelmingly proven by its efforts to engulf us in a German war, for the sake of beloved England.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
