<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-25">Feb. 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">"The People Are Masters"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0206</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0206.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-02-25">Feb. 25, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">"THE PEOPLE ARE MASTERS"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In his address at Boston President Wilson said nothing new about the plan for a league of nations, or about the ways and means by which he hopes to carry out his plans and attain his objects. But he let it be known in a very impressive and emphatic manner that he confidently adheres to his principles, and that America must remain true to the ideals for which she entered the war.</p>
   <p>He said, "The achievement in which I take greatest pride consists therein, that our great country and nation has gained the confidence of the whole world.</p>
   <p>"Now American ideals have performed the miracle that all nations of Europe are filled with the hope and the confidence that we have entered upon the threshold of a new time; a time when the nations will understand one another; <pb facs="5418474_5_0207.jpg" n="2"/>when they will assist one another in every just cause; when the nations will combine their moral and physical strength to maintain justice. What would be the result should America fail, should America disappoint the world at this moment? I believe that I am not offending any other great nation when I say that the hopes of the world are set on America, and that the results would be unspeakable if we do not prove that we are worthy of this trust. People would not only be bitterly disappointed; they would also despair? All countries would again become hostile camps; the delegates to the peace conference would return home with bowed heads, would be ashamed because of the knowledge that they had failed; for they received orders not to come home until they had done more than merely sign a peace pact. The nations of the world have decided to accomplish something great, and they will not be diverted from their purpose. And when I speak of the nations, I speak of the people who constitute the nations. They (the people) are masters and will see to it that if their present governments do not do their will other governments will!"</p>
   <p>"The people"--more precisely, the masses of the people--"are masters." Anyone who has followed the course of recent events with some diligence will have no <pb facs="5418474_5_0208.jpg" n="3"/>doubts on that score. He will also be convinced that the people expect more than a mere peace pact from the delegates to the peace conference; that they demand a permanent peace; that they desire a peace secured and guaranteed by a general league of nations in line with President Wilson's plan--according to this plan, because nothing better could be conceived or proposed.</p>
   <p>Anyone who has paid attention to current events and to the voice of the people --the masses of the people--knew long ago that the masses everywhere are coveting more, more of everything that is desirable: more freedom, more wages for work, and more of the goods of this world.</p>
   <p>They are indeed masters and have resolved to force their governments to grant more, or to overthrow these governments and to replace them by administrations that will be obedient to their (the people's) will. Lloyd George, the Premier of Great Britain, admitted this. Presenting a Government proposal to Parliament, he declared that the United Kingdom faces a civil war and that the ruling body of the country must do everything possible to avert the evil. Perhaps the situation of all other nations is not as serious; not in all countries <pb facs="5418474_5_0209.jpg" n="4"/>do the masses know how to assert their power as well as the common people of England; there may be nations whose "governed" are not masters. Everywhere the masses have come to know their power, and everywhere there is a desire for improvement of conditions.</p>
   <p>Everywhere nations predominantly desire the security of peace through united power, because the nations know that the welfare of the masses depends on a sure and permanent peace. The interests of the nations demand a league of nations which assures a just and lasting peace. This is, therefore, the hope of all nations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
