<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-05-06">May 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">What Is Needed</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0689</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0689.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-05-06">May 6, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT IS NEEDED</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Reports from Germany leave us doubt that the friendly attitude toward the United States, which was manifest throughout the Reich during the first months of the war, has undergone a decided change, and that our blood brothers across the ocean today hate Uncle Sam almost as much as the actual enemy whom they oppose in bloody battle. We German-Americans are familiar with the circumstances which have brought about this lamentable rift in the friendly relations between the two nations. We have sharply opposed a policy which, as we knew beforehand, could only have evil effects on the peaceful economic relations between Germany and the Union. But, unfortunately, we were not powerful enough to make our influence felt in places of authority.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0690.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It would lead us too far to appraise the reasons for this lack of influence. We all know them and there is no use crying over spilled milk. What has been done cannot be remedied, but it should teach us a lesson for the future. The prejudice of a large majority of our people, and the questionable attitude of our government toward the belligerents, we were unable to correct to any noticeable extent. But the war will probably have such tremendous effects on the future economic relations among all trade-pursuing nations that we German-Americans should get ready, even today, to pave the way for a resumption of friendly economic and political relations with Germany. We owe it to our old fatherland, to our adopted country, and to ourselves as well, because only in case we German-Americans represent an economic force will we be able to gain the political influence in the United States to which our [German] race is entitled.</p>
   <p>England's express purpose in the present war is the destruction of German trade, and she stops at nothing to accomplish this objective. German trade <pb facs="5418474_5_0691.jpg" n="3"/>is to be replaced by British trade wherever that is possible. For this purpose, numerous permanent organizations have been established in England and France which, with the aid of the respective governments, go after their assignment in the most unscrupulous manner. To be prepared for this contemplated blow by the enemy, namely, the elimination of Germany as a commercial nation, is the duty of Germans all over the world, but particularly here in the United States. We have to find means, therefore, to prevent this planned curtailment of trade relations between the German Reich and Austria-Hungary on one side and the United States on the other. We must create an organization which is capable of counteracting British commercial intrigues and connivances and of frustrating the efforts of the anti-German forces.</p>
   <p>How such a vital and influential agency could be created, and the thankful task it could perform, was recently outlined by F. F. Matenaers in a series of expertly written articles published in the Abendpost. These treatises, which caused quite a sensation when first published and which met with wide- <pb facs="5418474_5_0692.jpg" n="4"/>spread approval, have now been combined in pamphlet form under the title, "Wakening Call to the Deutschtum in America and to all Loyal Americans." The worthwhile suggestions of the author, which are the results of his critical studies of the alienation between Germany and the United States, of British intrigues, and of the unfortunate political and economic weakness of the German-American element, merit universal attention, not only by German-Americans, but by all those who regard a disturbance of trade relations between the United States and Germany as detrimental to established interests. The "German-American Economic Alliance," as the author conceives it, should include the entire United States, and should work hand in hand with an organization in Germany set up for similar purposes. The time for the establishment of such an alliance is at hand. Prominent German-Americans of all professions and walks of life--industry, agriculture, commerce, trade, science, and arts--should immediately get together for this purpose. "We have to get busy without delay and start organizing", writes Matenaers," in order to plan the right steps to guarantee permanently the prosperity of our country and to safeguard its economic security, at the same time fulfilling an honorable <pb facs="5418474_5_0693.jpg" n="5"/>duty toward our blood brothers in Europe, who have been put under such tremendous pressure by the present Anglo-American ruling class in their momentous struggle for the German principle and for German equality." The near future will demonstrate whether the well-meaning suggestions of the author, who hit the nail on the head, have fallen on fertile soil, or whether we German-Americans will continue to wear German Michael's [allegoric figure] nightcap with equanimity, while the old country has discarded it a long time ago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
