<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-12-29">Dec. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">Reconstruction of the World.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0448</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0448.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-12-29">Dec. 29, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">RECONSTRUCTION OF THE WORLD.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is a movement in progress in Chicago, which has as its purpose the reconstruction of the French cities after the war. The proposition is made, that every large city in America should accept a sponsorship for the reconstruction of a French city which has been destroyed in the war. The idea is worthy of recommendation and praise. It originated in Germany, when the desire for the destroyed cities and towns in East Prussia to be rebuilt was not carried out by the State, but by the citizens. This proved a success. It is one of the cases, where psychology plays such a prominent part. Many persons are ready to help their fellow creatures, many are willing to give according to their ability, and probably even more, but is always depends on how a matter is laid before them. Not only personal ambition, the desire to be known as a benefactor plays a role in such case, but the connection of a natural wish to help and to give is so strongly developed in humans, that it spurs the fervour exceedingly. Pittsburgh has done so much for its god child, that Chicago cannot lag behind. Cincinnati has, in a very short time, supplied its French city with the means to rebuild. St. Louis <pb facs="5418474_5_0449.jpg" n="2"/>must do it in even less time. And they will produce more result than all public appeals to sentiment. This might, from an ethical standpoint, be very valuable. But the awakening of ambition is practical and effective, and that is the main object. That it should be French cities, which are made the objects of such activities is easily understandable. From the beginning of the war the French enjoyed the greatest sympathy, a sympathy, which even in Germany was not denied to France against whom enmity was never strongly felt. The old friendship of the two countries, the historical recollections of the help, which they accorded to the young American Republic, and the historical and cultural importance of the cities hard hit by the war, fully explain this sympathy. It, no doubt, will lead to the success of the movement. The reconstruction of the world after the big war is a matter which should be dear to the heart of all nations. To destroy all traces which the war left is one of the great problems inherited by humanity. Whatever can be done for its fulfillment is urgently recommended. The war has given America has often been mentioned, very much, which is worth the sacrifice made for it. If we <pb facs="5418474_5_0450.jpg" n="3"/>add to this the activity for reconstruction of French cities, not only will the historical debt of gratitude be repaid to France, but America will be erecting for itself a monument, visible from a great distance, which will act at all times as a memorial. It will prove that the "splendid isolation" of the past has made room for an active co-operation through collaboration on the great and beautiful problem of the unity of nations.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
