<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-11-17">Nov. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[The Tribune and its Correspondents] Letter to the Editor</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0968</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0968.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-11-17">Nov. 17, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">[THE TRIBUNE AND ITS CORRESPONDENTS] Letter to the Editor</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Dear Editor: What would be the reaction of an Englishman, living in a neutral country, to a newspaper account of a letter, found on the person of an English war prisoner and written by his wife, in which this English woman, probably a mother herself, admonishes her husband not to spare women and children in this war?</p>
   <p>Well, my dear German fellow citizens, the Chicago Daily Tribune of November 12 published just such a story of a German soldier, in an article entitled, "King Albert of Belgium, the Hero of All Europe". A female namesake of the President of the United States [Wilson] made this fantastic claim. Although any German newspaper would reject material of this kind, and brand the story as a shameless lie, regardless of whether the subject happened to be an English, French, Japanese, Hottentot, or even a Belgian soldier's wife, the "World's <pb facs="5418474_5_0969.jpg" n="2"/>Greatest Newspaper" publishes the story as a special news report from a correspondent.</p>
   <p>How would an Englishman react if one of his countrymen deserted and joined the German side, and later, as a correspondent in a neutral country defamed the land of his fathers in the most despicable manner?</p>
   <p>Well, a native German, named Friedrich Wilhelm Weil--he has changed it to Frederic William Wile--is engaged in this apparently lucrative business; he is writing for the Chicago Tribune. The above mentioned issue contains one of his daily fabrications. Among other things he says that the morale of the German soldiers was not nearly as high as was generally believed. According to him, the soldiers sold and traded their uniforms for civilian clothes, in order to escape to Holland. Mr. "Wile" also makes the startling discovery that the Germans were using special incendiary bullets in Belgium, as part of the German culture which they had imported to Belgium. Mr. Wile <pb facs="5418474_5_0970.jpg" n="3"/>considers this discovery no less important than the one made by his colleague, James O'Donnell Bennett, this white raven among Anglo-American war correspondents, who described the horrible mutilations caused by the dum-dum bullets used by the English and French. And how this famous Mr. Wile has obtained for the Tribune a "Psychology of War" of the "Eminent Author and Humanitarian, and profoundest observer among comtemporary English writers". [Translator's note: Words in quotation marks appear in English in the original text.] The upshot of it all is that the German motto; might is right, attributed, by the way, to the German Reichs-Chancellor Von Bethmann-Hollweg, was responsible for this war and was the only reason why Belgium's neutrality was violated, which in turn brought about England's participation in the war. And although the Tribune as a rule thinks very little of the military and political utterances of poets, scientists, and artists, it nevertheless publishes in full these extremely biased opinions of this great novelist and miserable historian.</p>
   <p>I am asking again, What would an Englishman do in such a case?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0971.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>What are we doing? What we have always done--nothing. Shall we be good boys and behave like good citizens while the others humiliate us and make fools of us?</p>
   <p>Well, a number of German-Americans and I will do at least one little thing, and it is the least we can possibly do for the sake of our German heritage. After having sent a friendly warning to the Tribune, and after having received a courteous reply emphasizing "impartiality" and stating that Mr. Wile was of German descent as far as they knew, we [German-Americans] pledged ourselves not to buy the Tribune any more as long as this German renegade and that other mud slinger are employed as correspondents by that paper.</p>
   <p>Yours truly.</p>
   <p>[signed] Hermann Brandall,</p>
   <p>Chairman of the Kaufmaennischer Verein</p>
   <p>[Commerce Club] of Chicago.</p>
   <p>1840 West Monroe Street.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
