<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1936-01-06">Jan. 6, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Roosevelt's Message</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0036</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0036.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1936-01-06">Jan. 6, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">ROOSEVELT'S MESSAGE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The President broke several traditions when he presented his message to Congress. He delivered the message in person, simultaneously broadcasting it over the radio for the people to hear. He offered no detailed report on the nation's general condition but mentioned briefly that an improvement in economic conditions was manifest everywhere. On the other hand, he used the strongest possible terms in speaking of those who cast aspersions upon him and who resort to frothy virulence.</p>
   <p>In unmistakable words he reminded us that in the years following the great war a very small group of bankers and commercial and industrial leaders grabbed economic control of the nation.</p>
   <p>When our economic order failed under their incapable, shortsighted, and selfish <pb facs="5418474_5_0037.jpg" n="2"/>rule, they temporarily abdicated their leadership, he stated, but now they are attempting to regain power. For this reason, they are waging a merciless fight against the Administration, in which they are supported by their "political puppets," as Roosevelt calls them.</p>
   <p>The underlying dishonesty and mendacity of this onslaught were plainly set forth by Roosevelt, who had submitted a long list of questions to his opponents. Thus far, not a single answer has been forthcoming. In other words: They have merely criticized his measures in the most derogatory manner, but they have not been able to offer definite solutions for the country's problems. Thus Roosevelt disproved with tremendous effectiveness and irrefutable logic the claims of his adversaries who oppose the measures he has adopted for the New Deal.</p>
   <p>The greater part of his speech involved foreign affairs, and here, too, he broke with tradition, because he discussed foreign policy at the beginning of his address. He defended the democratic form of government and emphasized <pb facs="5418474_5_0038.jpg" n="3"/>that it is to be regarded as an assurance of peace, whereas the autocratically governed countries threaten world peace continually. From the comments of the press, it is generally assumed that the President alluded to Italy and Japan.</p>
   <p>In the case of these two countries Roosevelt's assertion is justified. But if he generalizes and declares that democracy always assures peace and autocracies lean toward war, then history does not corroborate his contention.</p>
   <p>One need only consider the autocratic Germany of today to recognize that the German government has succeeded in maintaining peace at a national sacrifice. Our own country is young in comparison with most European nations. But if we are honest, we cannot deny that our democracy has always had a deeply in-grained propensity to resort to arms. Our Mexican conflict was a pure war of conquest, and no less a man than Lincoln, a Congressman at the time, told the incumbent President that he was guilty of homicide. The Spanish-American War was deliberately provoked, and our participation in the World War was <pb facs="5418474_5_0039.jpg" n="4"/>absolutely inexcusable, as nearly everybody admits today.</p>
   <p>There is a great omission in the President's philosophical dissertations on history. He considers the form of government as the essential and deciding factor in the foreign affairs of a country. He completely overlooks the fact that economic reasons, as history amply testifies, usually are responsible for wars.....</p>
   <p>His message then considered the impending neutrality legislation. The President explained that neutrality laws are designed in the interest of peace, and that two policies must be considered: first, warring nations must be prevented from obtaining arms, munitions, and other military supplies from the United States; and second, they must not be permitted to buy larger quantities of material of a general nature--which may be used for war purposes--than they obtained in time of peace.</p>
   <p>Perhaps Roosevelt intended through his remarks to induce other nations to <pb facs="5418474_5_0040.jpg" n="5"/>follow our precedent and, by adopting similar laws, to seek to avoid wars or--shorten them. If he should succeed, a new epoch in international relations would be established which might prove valuable in maintaining peace. But the prospects are well-nigh nil. Through such measures the present causes of war cannot be eradicated; and these must be removed if peace is to be assured.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
