<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-02">June 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Combating the Registration of Noncitizens</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Immigrant Protective League Appeals to the People of the State</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1508</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1508.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1935-06-02">June 2, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">COMBATING THE REGISTRATION OF NONCITIZENS</title><title level="a" type="sub">The Immigrant Protective League Appeals to the People of the State</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Immigrant Protective League protests, with a special circular against two bills purporting to bring about the registering of all immigrants who for one reason or another have not yet become citizens. Sponsors of the bill are Assemblymen Sinnett, from downstate, and Charles H. Weber from the sixth senatorial district, former county commissioner.</p>
   <p>What is to be done with these bills is still undecided. It is scarcely to be assumed that they will be debated at this legislative session. Yet, the League would like to apprise the people of the state of the planned measures and to combat them emphatically.</p>
   <p>On various occasions, attempts have been made in Congress to elevate the registration of aliens to the dignity of a law, but nothing ever came of it.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1509.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Then the State of Michigan introduced such a law in the year 1931. On December 9, 1931, this law was declared unconstitutional by the federal court.</p>
   <p>The Sinnett-Weber bills provide that even minor children may be deported from Illinois. Noncitizens could only obtain work if no American is able to fill the position in question. All noncitizens who are compelled to ask for public aid must be deported.</p>
   <p>The League takes the view that those provisions are as an insult to humaneness.</p>
   <p>By this, the noncitizen is exposed to every suspicion, every assault, and every oppression. It would lead to retaliations in other countries, and many pacts would be endangered. Registration of noncitizens would be admissible if the citizens were likewise registered.</p>
   <p>Even citizens would then also run the risk of being treated as noncitizens, for only in extremely few cases could they show their birth certificates.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1510.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The latter system has not long been in use, and still not in every state.</p>
   <p>The bills are intended to create the impression that it is quite easy to become a citizen. Its sponsors themselves know that it is difficult, that there are many immigrants who, through no fault of theirs cannot become citizens.</p>
   <p>The worst thing would be to force these people to become citizens. What would be the outcome can be easily imagined.</p>
   <p>Judged from the administrative point of view, it would be quite difficult to execute such a law. The Sinnett bill provides that the sheriffs of the counties should be made to take over the job of registration. The Weber bill provides the same for the county clerks. Registration should take place every ninety days.</p>
   <p>The bills are so much in contrast to the Constitution that the sharpest <pb facs="5418474_5_1511.jpg" n="4"/>opposition to them is needed. The noncitizens have immigrated to escape forms of government that put too much compulsion on them. Now they are to be subjected to a compulsion much worse than before. This is political tyranny.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
