<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-05">Mar. 5, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Good Luck!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0198</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0198.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-05">Mar. 5, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">GOOD LUCK!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last night President Wilson addressed the nation--and the whole world--from the Metropolitan Opera House in New York, before about five thousand men and women. A close observer says, "He looked pale and gray. His hair has turned completely white. His posture is not as erect as it formerly was. America wears out her men very quickly."</p>
   <p>If, as this report indicates, the President appeared to be "worn out," his hearers were soon convinced by what he said, and by the manner in which he said it, that he has aged and is worn somewhat, only physically--not mentally; that the great burden of work and worry which he assumed has affected his body, but not his mental powers or his courage or his "anger" or his confidence that he will be victorious.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0199.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>He spoke as one ready to give battle. His address, from beginning to end, breathed battle. What he said indicated that he is unalterably resolved to abide by his original plan, that his attention and effort is firmly fixed on his goal, that nothing can cause him to waver or to deviate from his course as he has outlined it. His address contains no extenuating phrases, no compromising statements. It is a challenge to, and an attack upon, all those who oppose his plans for a league of nations and a lasting peace.</p>
   <p>Alluding to the well-known song "Over There", the President began his address by saying, "I will not come back until everything is over over there". That was his answer to the Republicans who tried to force him to renounce his second trip to Europe, or to persuade him to return home very soon--prematurely if possible. To indicate how firm his resolve is, he repeated in the middle of his address: "I will not come back until everything is over over there".</p>
   <p>His confidence also is firm. <pb facs="5418474_5_0200.jpg" n="3"/>"The first thing that I will tell the people on the other side of the ocean is that an overwhelming majority of the American people is in favor of a league of nations. I know that this is true"....We also know it. And then the clear perception: "And I want to issue this solemn warning--not as a threat, for the forces of the earth do not threaten, they work. The floods of the earth do not announce beforehand that they are coming; they swell and rise in their majesty and overwhelming power and swallow all who stand in their way. The heart of the world is now awake, and the heart of the world must be satisfied."</p>
   <p>He concluded his address by saying: "The day will come when Americans will remember with joyful spirits and swelling pride that they were privileged to make the sacrifice necessary to unite their power and their moral strength with the cause of justice for men of every race and place.</p>
   <p>"May God grant us the strength and discernment to do this wisely. May He grant us the privilege to know that we did it without any thought of the cost--just because we are Americans who love freedom and doing right.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0201.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"May God grant that America, a free, strong, proud America, may, in years to come, gladly, proudly, and with good conscience look back upon the role which it is playing today and upon the role which it will play in the conclusion of peace and in establishing and organizing a league of nations."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
