<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-02-07">Feb. 7, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[Sumner's Revenge]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1357</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1357.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1872-02-07">Feb. 7, 1872</date>.
<title level="a">[SUMNER'S REVENGE]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Under the heading "Sumner's Revenge" writes the Democratic Cincinnatier Volksfreund:</p>
   <p>"In Sumner's motion for the appointment of a committee for the investigation of the arms traffic lies a truly satanic malice against the Grant administration. Just now while the administration is accusing England before the Geneva court of arbitration to have acted unneutrally by giving indirect support to the rebellion - Sumner is hurling the same accusation against the Grant administration based on the French arms traffic. The administration thereby is brought into a very disagreeable position both before the court of arbitration and in England. This no doubt corresponds to Sumner's main purpose - while the denunciation of Grant to the German element is no more than secondary. It is a powerful blow against Grant, but a patriotic way of acting it is not."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1358.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>What the Volksfreund says about Sumner is as a matter of course, true also of Schurz......Every German American citizen who regards the United States as his adopted fatherland understands that without difficulty........At the time when the shady traffic took place Mr. Schurz did not open his mouth in the Senate of the United States, though hundreds of meetings of German-born citizens asked him for it..........Herr Schurz, however, wanted to create no enmity (apparently refers to the resignation of Jussen).</p>
   <p>However, we would be eager to know why Mr. Schurz now thinks the time more favorable to stir up the arms traffic. Does he do so now as a German, or an American citizen?</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1359.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The idea to put a weapon into the hand of the most malicious enemy of our adopted fatherland through his public discussion would make us think twice... At the moment when the decision of the court of arbitration in Geneva has become very doubtful anyway, the speeches made by Messrs. Sumner and Schurz are arms sent to England, there to serve against the United States...</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
