<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-09">Apr. 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Down with Prices!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0163</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0163.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-09">Apr. 9, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">DOWN WITH PRICES!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is reported from Texas that during the past few days more than two thousand employees of Fort Worth Packers have been dismissed, because the demand for meat has diminished as the result of the unexpected, quick conclusion of the War. When hostilities ceased and meat consumption suddenly declined, refrigerators everywhere in the Country were filled to capacity with products consigned to the war zone, and all plants of the packing industry were operating at full force. Apparently, the meat barons have not yet thought about creating a greater demand for their products in the home markets by reducing prices.</p>
   <p>Everybody in our Country thinks that wholesalers of meat cheated the public to an extent which was inexcusable, even during wartime. The report from an investigation which was made by a Congressional committee reveals <pb facs="5418474_5_0164.jpg" n="2"/>astonishing, pertinent facts, which cannot be invalidated by any explanations or denials which the packers may offer. If these facts needed confirmation, it could be amply supplied by the circumstance that nothing has been done to make the enormous surplus of meat accessible to our people by reductions in prices which would be commensurate to conditions which will be prevalent after the conclusion of peace. Instead the wholesalers continue to store their products and endeavor to maintain the severely-felt high prices, by decreasing production. When merchants or manufacturers have a surplus of goods, they must, necessarily, be considerate of consumers in order to increase sales; in many cases they forego a part or all of their profit in order to dispose of the surplus and thus obtain money with which they may purchase new supplies. Apparently this procedure is preferable to dismissing employees and shutting down business, merely for the purpose of forcing consumers to pay unjustifiably high prices for goods or to do without them. It is reported from Kansas City, also, that many packing-house employees are being laid off. This action by the packers seems to be convincing evidence that they constitute a monopoly, and that they <pb facs="5418474_5_0165.jpg" n="3"/>ruthlessly utilize the monopoly to their own advantage and that they are not, as they say, competitors in an open market where "equality of all" is the basic principle. But to close industrial plants, to decrease production, and to dismiss workers is also very reprehensible, when considered from other viewpoints. This is true now, especially when hundreds of thousands of our khaki-clad boys justly demand that the opportunities which they should have to gain employment must not be diminished by profit-hungry food hoarders. Such contemptible action ought be possible only when governments and people are unable to stop them legally.</p>
   <p>There can be no doubt that the high war prices, which are demanded for all goods, will soon have to drop; though perhaps not to the prewar level, yet sufficiently to permit the American people to return to a way of living which is in keeping with their customs. It should not be very difficult to prosecute certain industrial and commercial combines, which are adding exploitation and artificial shortage to the heavy war burden, under our <pb facs="5418474_5_0166.jpg" n="4"/>Antitrust Law. The American people have shown a remarkable patience in very trying conditions, but this patience, too, is limited as the "profit hogs" will find out to their sorrow. In view of the numerous protests, the next Congress will have to give its attention to the efforts being made to maintain the high prices which are desired only by relatively few persons and firms. It is high time that production and selling be given free sway. And as far as the distribution of foods in Europe and the United States is concerned, we advocate following the old proverb "charity begins at home".</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
