<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1863-10-27">Oct. 27, 1863</date>.
<title level="a">Jeff Davis' Peace Conditions</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1407</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1407.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1863-10-27">Oct. 27, 1863</date>.
<title level="a">JEFF DAVIS' PEACE CONDITIONS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Richmond Enquirer, Jeff Davis' newspaper, sets forth the following as the conditions under which the Confederates will make peace with the United States: acknowledgement of the independence of the Confederate States; withdrawal of Union troops from every foot of Confederate soil, including Kentucky and Missouri; withdrawal of troops from Maryland and an open election in that state on the question of remaining in the Union or joining the Southern Confederacy; cession so the Confederacy of all territories lying west of the Confederate States; a fair compromise in regard to national indebtedness and public lands, and equal participation by the Confederacy in the advantages accruing from agreements with foreign nations; surrender of a proportionate part of the navy to the Confederates.</p>
   <p>Indeed, The Richmond Enquirer even designates these monstrous conditions as <pb facs="5418474_5_1408.jpg" n="2"/>the minimum demand of the South and promises that the South, should it win the war, will force the North to pay the whole war debt of the South. We doubt very much if the majority of the people of the Southern States will accede to these impudent demands, but these demands show that the leaders of the Jeff Davis party are very determined men.</p>
   <p>It is hardly necessary to say that the North can never accept these conditions. Withdrawal of our armed forces from Kentucky, Tennessee, Mississippi, Louisiana, Arkansas, Missouri, Texas, North Carolina, South Carolina, Virginia, and Maryland; cession to the South of all territories west of the Southern States, that is, of the territories of Utah, Colorado, Nevada, New Mexico, Arizona, and the Indian Territory, the division of our navy between the North and the South; and, finally, payment of a part of the Southern debt: in short, complete subjection to the South--these are conditions to which even many of the Copperheads would object, not to speak of loyal Unionists.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1409.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>However, the Davis party rules those parts of the South that are still in its power with an iron hand, and it will abide by its program; that is, to use the words of the Enquirer, "they are firmly resolved not to rest until either the Confederacy or the Union has been destroyed". So the life-and-death struggle goes on.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
