<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1919-12-21">Dec. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">America, Hflp Us!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0090</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0090.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-12-21">Dec. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">AMERICA, HFLP US!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Leopold Neumann, president of the Oesterreichische-Ungarische Hilfe, [Austro-Hungarian Aid (Society)], has issued an appeal, the general tenor of which we reproduce below:</p>
   <p>"If our brothers and sisters in America do not come to our assistance, we will surely starve!', so writes an old friend of mine from Viennna. 'If you don't come to our aid right now with foodstuffs and provisions, all of German-Austria and German-Hungary will become one great cemetery!', so reads a distress call from an old school chum in Gratz [Austria]. From Budapest [Hungary] and Temesvar [Rumania], from Marburg in beautiful Stvria, from Stuhlweissenburg [Hungary] and Agram [Yugoslavia], wherever Germans live, in Austria or Hungary, we hear this call for bread, both from old and young. Babies are dying in their mothers' arms, old people are committing suicide.....</p>
   <p>"Are Americans of German descent going to stand idly by and let this happen? <pb facs="5418474_5_0091.jpg" n="2"/>Shall the curse of millions of people be called down upon those over here, who go to bed with full stomachs and leave those in despair and agony, who still live on the same soil where their own cradle once stood?</p>
   <p>"German-America has a duty to perform by giving immediate aid; otherwise history will be the judge some day. How humanely and nobly has Germany acted, even though prostrate herself! A cable report says that the present people's government in Germany has decided to turn over fifty grams of the weekly bread ration to Austria, to prevent general starvation in the districts of German-Austria and German-Hungary. But how about the German element over here? Why don't they get busy and help? Why is it that of 350 German men's and women's clubs only ten have sent a contribution of about ten dollars to the Oesterreichische and Ungarische Hilfe?</p>
   <p>"If children are starving in China, money is collected here--and it should be--to save unfortunate human beings from dying. Are the Germans in Austria and Hungary, who are only the victims of the wrong policy of their former autocratic <pb facs="5418474_5_0092.jpg" n="3"/>governments, worth less than Chinese children:</p>
   <p>"Shall ten million Germans in Austria and Hungary starve, because the French desire for revenge and ambitious diplomats have condemned them to death?</p>
   <p>"America is feeding the children of Vienna, Gratz and Budapest. In the British Parliament, upon his return from Austria, Sir Willis declared on December 6: 'In Vienna, streetcar traffic is impeded because there is one funeral procession after the other, and all these hearses contain the bodies of children!'</p>
   <p>"In the face of these gruesome reports, is the German element of America going to remain quiet and inactive?</p>
   <p>"Fellow citizens of German stock and blood, awaken!</p>
   <p>"As American citizens of German descent, let us not disappoint the last hope of those unfortunates in the old country. Help, and help quickly, no matter <pb facs="5418474_5_0093.jpg" n="4"/>how small the gift, so we can send bread to the hungry.</p>
   <p>"Forget the frontier posts in the old country and help where help is needed most!</p>
   <p>"America is rightly termed the great melting pot of the world. Show that you are worthy citizens of this country, that you are the best, the noblest elements of this league of nationalities."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
