<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-28">Nov. 28, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Hercules at the Cross-Roads</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1559</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1559.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-28">Nov. 28, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">HERCULES AT THE CROSS-ROADS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not unlike the ceiling in a torture chamber, the problem of providing means to continue aid for the unemployed is screwed down upon the administration. Whether or not they like to do it, they have to do it. The cessation of that aid would, without a doubt, lead to grave and serious disturbances in public and private life. There are more than mere signs that there is quite a quantity of "inflammable matter" among the unemployed. An explosion must be avoided.</p>
   <p>On the other hand, it can not be denied that any additional tax load on the population will lead to nothing but a further diminution of the public's purchasing power. People are restricting their purchases more and more; the demand for goods is becoming smaller, and the result is restricted production, hand in hand with which goes increased unemployment.</p>
   <p>The efforts of petitioners has succeeded in biting off another eighteen million <pb facs="5418474_5_1560.jpg" n="2"/>dollar chunk from the Federal government for Illinois. This sum is supposed to suffice for December and the first half of January. After that, the state will have to provide at least three million dollars monthly, otherwise the Federal government will shut its purse, and the state must then see for itself how it can feed the unemployed.</p>
   <p>The governor now intends to urge the legislature [to action]. There is no further mention of the surplus derived from the sales tax and other state incomes. What is to be done with it remains obscure. It might seem advisable to make at least some use of that surplus, which has almost become a legend. It seems, however, that above the door of that sanctuary there is a sign that reads "Taboo".</p>
   <p>The legislature must see what can be done. It has broad shoulders. Does it not interpret and express the will of the people? It is convenient, in such situations, to let others do the thinking for you and, what is more important, take over responsibility for you. The legislature can do nothing but enact new <pb facs="5418474_5_1561.jpg" n="3"/>taxes. In such manner do we uphold the fairy tale that the administration does all in its power to keep taxes down.</p>
   <p>Nor does the legislature have to be squeamish about it, for there are still a number of things which, for no explainable reason, have remained untaxed. Taxation of these would produce handsome sums. People just do not like to renounce habits that have become a pleasure to them, such as smoking, card playing, and the like.</p>
   <p>In the beginning there will be protests, even complaints, but man can adjust himself to almost anything. Is it not serving a good purpose? Politically, not much damage will be done, for "the poor people can not help themselves" (sic).</p>
   <p>It is astonishing that they worry only about how to secure the necessary money, but they do not give a thought to whether it might not be advisable to alter the system of distribution. All assaults upon the system have so far been victoriously repulsed. It seems that they believe that they have created the <pb facs="5418474_5_1562.jpg" n="4"/>"ne plus ultra," and the monster so created is defended tooth and nail. In contrast stands, however, the effort of three separate commissions, which have been at work for some time to investigate the entire Situation. They no longer seem to be able to answer so many complaints by a wave of the hand, for such commissions are but acting as lightning rods and scapegoats of appeasement. What they intend to do later on can already be foreseen today: nothing. Time will have to do it for them.</p>
   <p>If increased burdens have to be carried, care should be taken that the system of distribution [of relief funds] be altered in such a way that the money comes under government control. The legislature has the power to do that, too.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
