<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1909-11-09">November 9, 1909</date><title level="a">The Navy Race</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1288</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1288.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1909-11-09">November 9, 1909</date><title level="a">The Navy Race</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It has already been proven in ancient times that the sea strength of a country is not alone dependent on the number and the size of their war ships. The Athenians, with their easy and light movable rowing boats, defeated the great Persian sea-fleet. About a hundred years later, the Attic fleet, which was the master of the Mediterranean Sea was destroyed in the port of Syracuse, because the Syracusans had smaller ships which could move quicker in the narrow port. The Romans conquered the Carthagenians on account of their newly-invented grapling hooks. The Danish-English King Kurt conquered the Norwegian Vikings by building towers on their ships, behind which they fought their enemies. In more modern times, the Dutch and the English conquered much stronger fleets by their superior art of seamanship, and not always by their numerical strength. Notwithstanding, the Navy Department in Washington seems worried that Germany in the last year had taken second place as a sea power, and has surpassed France and the United States of America as it has increased its tonnage from 693,599 to 820,682. In the same period Great Britain has boosted its tonnage from 1,871,176 tons to 2,005,873 tons, whilst the tonnage of the United States has only increased from 770,500 to 785,000 tons.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1289.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Not mentioned in the report, is, that the French have specialized in submarines and that Great Britain has specialized in building much bigger warships. Their latest Super-Dreadnoughts have a tonnage of 26,350 tons and a velocity of 28 miles per hour. Their armaments are much heavier than the newest German warships. Nobody can say beforehand what will be the practical result of these monsters, or if they will ever have an opportunity to show their effectiveness. The race among the sea powers is limited to their construction bureaus, and the means of their taxpayers. The report of the Washington Navy Department therefore, must be considered more as information to the public that we have ceded the second place in the Naval race to another power.</p>
   <p>As Congress has refused on various occasions to have four ships built at a time, the intervention of public opinion is looked for. We do not think that the American public has much cause to worry or to take part in the silly race of the European naval powers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
