<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-01-26">Jan. 26, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">Physicians' Expedition</title><title level="a" type="sub">Well-known Chicago Surgeon Added to the Third Expedition</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0635</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.A.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0635.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-01-26">Jan. 26, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">PHYSICIANS' EXPEDITION</title><title level="a" type="sub">Well-known Chicago Surgeon Added to the Third Expedition</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>According to a statement by the American Doctors Expedition Committee, Inc., the Third Expedition will depart for Germany and Austria within two or three weeks. The doctors and nurses will start on their trans-Atlantic journey as soon as necessary preparations have been made; such as, buying equipment, securing passports, etc.</p>
   <p>Again the committee has been successful in obtaining an eminent surgeon to head its expedition. This will be fulfilled by H. M. Richter, 44-year-old <pb facs="5418474_5_0636.jpg" n="2"/>surgeon, of the Wesley Memorial Hospital, Cook County Hospital and Extraordinarius of Surgery at the Medical Faculty in Northwestern University, Chicago.</p>
   <p>Dr. Richter will select most of his assistants and nurses from the ranks of his co-workers, who are familiar with his methods, and others from persons recommended by the New York Committee of Physicians, which functions in an advisory capacity.</p>
   <p>Conforming with his principles that the best is none to good for the German and Austrian wounded, particular care will be exercised to make certain that the participants and materials are first-class, in accordance <pb facs="5418474_5_0637.jpg" n="3"/>with the preceding expeditions.</p>
   <p>It is said that the British authorities have rescinded the embargo on hospital supplies to the Central powers. On January 18 a large shipment of bandage material, medicaments, and other necessary items for war hospitals, was transported to Germany aboard the S. S. "Nieuw Amsterdam," to augment the supplies of the two expeditions now active in Germany. The equipment for the third expedition will be procured as quickly as possible so that it will arrive in Germany promptly and be available for Dr. Richter's force.</p>
   <p>Three expeditions having been definitely established, it is up to us to provide for their support, so that they may continue their service, <pb facs="5418474_5_0638.jpg" n="4"/>during and after the war, among the German and Austrian wounded. It is obvious that no assistance is more deserving than this. Donations for this important work may be sent to the German Legation in Washington, but mention specifically that the contribution is for the Physicians expedition.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
