<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-10">Feb. 10, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">War Sufferers in Chicago</title><title level="a" type="sub">The German Labor Aid Can Sing a Song about It</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0587</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0587.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-02-10">Feb. 10, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">WAR SUFFERERS IN CHICAGO</title><title level="a" type="sub">The German Labor Aid Can Sing A Song About It</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ignace Paderewski, his wife, and his friends succeeded in collecting about $40,000 for the war-stricken Poles.</p>
   <p>Here in Chicago, hundreds of German, Austrian, and Hungarian workers, who gave up their jobs when the factories were converted into arsenals are suffering as a result of the war. Such men deserve special consideration.</p>
   <p>The secretary of the All-American Alliance has taken action on the matter. He has found profitable employment for a large number of compatriots, particularly mechanics, in companies which do not manufacture war supplies. For others he created work. His office, in Room 76, 154 W. Randolph Street, was converted into a shop where soldiers, cavalrymen, infantrymen and other leaden troops peacefully emerge from their molds. A group of eight equestrians and a group <pb facs="5418474_5_0588.jpg" n="2"/>of four soldiers on foot, costs fifty cents.</p>
   <p>Posters of Washington and Lincoln are in preparation, and the pictures of Hindenburg and Mackensen have found a ready sale.</p>
   <p>Assistants and sales people, who will be willing to work gratuitously for this cause, which after all has been created as an exclusive industry for war sufferers, are still in demand. In fact, they are urgently needed. A few German women of Chicago have shouldered burdens beyond their strength. At this time help, especially financia-, is of utmost importance for this worthy cause adopted by the Chicago Labor Aid. Therefore, the distress call is: Volunteers to the front, help, give a hand, have a heart!</p>
   <p>Contributions will be gratefully acknowledged by M. Niven, 154 West Randolph Street, Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
