<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-10-01">Oct. 1, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">Resolutions of Socialer Arbeiterverein</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1451</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1451.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>III D</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1861-10-01">Oct. 1, 1861</date>.
<title level="a">RESOLUTIONS OF SOCIALER ARBEITERVEREIN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In a meeting held September 28, 1861, the Socialer Arbeiterverein of the Tenth Ward passed the following resolution:</p>
   <p>Whereas, It is absolutely necessary that we wage a forceful war and use every means at our disposal if our efforts are to be successful; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, Slavery, the cause of the War now raging in our Republic, must be eradicated, and to that end the Southern Rebels must be conquered; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, The Germans in our free country look upon the procedure described in the proclamation of General John Fremont as the only correct way of suppressing the rebellion, and have been encouraged by that proclamation to continue war operations and to report for military duties in large numbers; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, President Lincoln's mutilation of General Fremont's proclamation has <pb facs="5418474_5_1452.jpg" n="2"/>discouraged not only many Germans, but also a great number of Americans who came from countries other than Germany, and has retarded the enlistment of volunteers; therefore be it</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we fully indorse the resolutions adopted in public meetings at Coldwater, Michigan; Davenport, Iowa; Cottage Hill, Illinois; Racine, Wisconsin; etc.; be it further</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we consider President Lincoln's act of multilation to be treason against our country; be it further</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we urge all existing societies and organizations, especially those which have a German membership, to inform General Fremont of their attitude and encourage him by continuing to follow his principles, for in no other way can victory be attained, the country saved, and rebellion, treason, and slavery extirpated; and be it further</p>
   <p>Resolved, That these resolutions be published in all local English and German <pb facs="5418474_5_1453.jpg" n="3"/>language newspapers, and that a copy be sent to President Abraham Lincoln and General John Fremont.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
