<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-23">Apr. 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A Word to the Wise</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0147</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0147.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-23">Apr. 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">A WORD TO THE WISE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>By six o'clock yesterday evening Chicago had subscribed for about twenty-three million dollars' worth of Victory Loan bonds, and its quota was for $189,000,000. That is not exactly bad for the first two days, nor can it be called expecially good. One who is familiar with the nature of this Loan will probably express mild surprise that a much greater amount has not already been subscribed, for he will know that not only are these United States bonds the safest investment in this wide world and that they yield an interest which is high, considering the absolute security of the Loan and the extraordinarily favorable terms of payment, but also that the great financial institutions of our country--banks, and dealers in securities, etc.--are able and willing to purchase the entire issue, should the public show no inclination to avail itself of the good opportunity, or is slow to do so.</p>
   <p>Doubting Thomases will say that if capitalists and banks rate this fifth <pb facs="5418474_5_0148.jpg" n="2"/>Victory Loan so highly, why have they failed to purchase as many bonds as they possibly could during the first few days of the sale, inasmuch as they are not accustomed to give the public any special consideration, nor to step back modestly and unselfishly so that the well-known "little man" might have a chance to make a profit. Well, it is conceded that great financiers and financial corporations do not suffer from too great an unselfishness, and also that they are not especially considerate of the welfare of others, unless their own welfare is involved. However, it is certain that successful financial operations require a certain ability to see ahead, and that men who manage large financial institutions are wont to look a little beyond the tips of their noses; and, it is certain that they must, and do, view the entire economic situation and are guided in great enterprises by the answer to this question: How will the general financial conditions and, therewith, the entire economic structure of the country be affected? Nor is this procedure followed in the interest of public welfare, but it emanates from the selfish consideration that their prosperity, in the final analysis, depends upon general prosperity, and <pb facs="5418474_5_0149.jpg" n="3"/>that it is necessary to forego immediate advantages for the purpose of securing permanent and greater profits in the future. The banks could easily buy the whole issue--they have $4,500,000,000 and could collect the four and three-fourths per cent interest, while paying two or three per cent interest to their clients on the money which the latter will use to buy Victory Loan bonds; or they could sell all or a part of the bonds, or even hold them four or five years and then exchange them for three and three-fourths per cent tax-free bonds which would immediately, or very soon, be far above par.</p>
   <p>Before the War, when our country was not as wealthy as it is today, four per cent bonds sold at 130. Three per cent tax-free bonds were sold above par before any human being could say how many more billions the Government would need.</p>
   <p>The Victory Loan will be the last Liberty Loan, and even with this and the other five Loans, our national debt will not amount to more than about <pb facs="5418474_5_0150.jpg" n="4"/>one half of the annual income of our country. Europe owes us more than ten billion dollars, or about one half of our whole debt.</p>
   <p>There can be no doubt that this loan is an absolutely safe and profitable investment, but it should be explained just why banks, etc., did not immediately "grab" the Loan, although they could have done so, and are not in the habit of acting unselfishly when profitable transactions may be made. Their restraint in this instance has its roots in the fact that, if they subscribed for the whole issue, their reserve would be severely strained and as a consequence, there would be only a small amount available for business purposes. Interest rates would greatly increase, and the interest on short-time commercial notes, which fortunately dropped from six to five and one-half per cent recently, would rise again and make it difficult for businessmen to obtain the money necessary to finance the transition to peacetime activity and the repair and alteration of industrial plants. That again would result in retarding the reconstruction and readjustment of our entire economic system, to the detriment of business, including banking, and of our whole Nation.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0151.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>The banks, too, will definitely subscribe to a share of the issue within the time specified for that purpose; however, the fewer bonds they buy the better it will be for all of us.</p>
   <p>The more the "little fellow," the laborer, the small businessman and small manufacturer, avail themselves of this excellent opportunity to invest the money they have on hand, or the savings and profits which they will make during the coming seven months, the quicker reconstruction will proceed, and the sooner will come the time of great economic prosperity, for which we all long and, from which we will all benefit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
