<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-09-18">Sept. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">England Rules the Waves</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1084</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1084.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-09-18">Sept. 18, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">ENGLAND RULES THE WAVES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The great war was started by England. Great Britain believed that her supremacy on the high seas was threatened by the growing German merchant marine and by the German navy. The "English" [i.e., pro-British, not English-language] press of America approves of this war. Germany stands condemned and the Allies are praised as the fighters for progress and civilization, because the independence of the continental European nations is said to be threatened by Prussian-German militarism; because it is alleged that Germany was aspiring to military supremacy on land.</p>
   <p>The truth is of course, that Germany armed and built up her military might because she saw herself surrounded by enemies who made no bones about their evil intentions; the truth is that the German Reich was led merely by the instinct of self-preservation to prepare herself as much as possible for the <pb facs="5418474_5_1085.jpg" n="2"/>eventual challenge. But even if it were true that Germany wanted military hegemony over the continent, America would still not be justified in indicting her. Because Germany would not be asking for any more on land than England had asked for and claimed on the high seas. England is today supreme on the seas, and the same people who brand Germany's alleged military aspirations on land as an infamous and heinous crime recognize British supremacy on the high seas as a matter of course. These people talk and act as if Great Britain had an inherent right to world domination, and in their opinion any attempt to challenge this "right" would be tantamount to sacrilege or would be a proper object of ridicule.</p>
   <p>The so-called American newspapers published in the English language act and write in this same vein, and American citizens, who profess to be good and "loyal" Americans, are climbing all over themselves to echo the American press, in spite of the fact that this great Republic would have nothing to fear from Germany's military supremacy on the European continent, while Great Britain's mastery of the sea infringes upon America's rights and tends to make this <pb facs="5418474_5_1086.jpg" n="3"/>nation, to an ever-increasing degree, a vassal of England. England rules the sea with her merchant marine and her navy, and she is determined not to tolerate any rival, either in world trade or in naval strength. At present, she is engaged in smashing Germany with the aid of France, Russia, and Japan because Germany seemed to be a dangerous rival on the sea. Similarly, and with no scruples about the methods she employs, England would try to keep any other power from competing with her in world trade. And as far as the United States is concerned, England seems determined to suppress at the very beginning any attempt to revive American commerce.</p>
   <p>Those who are not yet convinced of this despite all that has happened thus far should certainly have all their doubts removed now that England is even protesting against America's purchase of German steamers at present in American ports--steamers which are badly needed for American overseas trade. Then there is England's disregard for international law, her disregard for ships flying a neutral flag. These violations of international law go on all the time. Take the case of the steamers "Rotterdam" and "Rhyndam" of the Holland-America Line.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1087.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Consider the Brazilian government's order, instigated by England, which refused to grant the American-owned tramp steamer "Robert Dollar" permission to fly the American flag instead of the British flag in the harbor of Rio de Janeiro.</p>
   <p>The United States today is completely dependent on England as far as sea trade is concerned, and the dear cousin and pal of Uncle Sam is determined to keep the latter in this state of dependency and even to increase British domination over him. England is not only America's most powerful, shrewd, and ruthless enemy, but also the only potential enemy this Republic has. Without England's aid and support, Japan would be powerless against us; without England's constant agitation there would be no Japanese enmity to speak of.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
