<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-20">Nov. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">Social Welfare</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1632</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1632.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1929-11-20">Nov. 20, 1929</date>.
<title level="a">SOCIAL WELFARE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Hoover invited representatives of industry, commerce, finance and labor to a conference in Washington. At this meeting steps are to be taken to prevent a depression and continue our national prosperity. The President feels that through the present crazy speculations, money has been withdrawn from industry. The crash in the Stock Exchange liberated tremendous sums which are now available for other purposes, and the President desires that leaders in industry, commerce, and high finance should now be magnanimous and use this accumulated capital for productive purposes. In this manner, he hopes to infuse new blood into our social body and thus obviate a crisis which is now quite evident <pb facs="5418474_5_1633.jpg" n="2"/>due to the financial disaster.</p>
   <p>The President's procedure is undoubtedly rational. How far his expectations may be realized, is unascertainable at present. During his campaign, Mr. Hoover made the mysterious declaration that he intends to abolish poverty. Surely, this assertion was not to be taken verbally. He probably intended to convey the thought of trying to prevent depressions. He probably had no inkling at that time that upon his initiation this opportunity would present itself.</p>
   <p>There are two obstacles to this plan, first, our social life depends in a great measure upon building activity, and during the last ten years we have built entirely too much, especially apartment houses, factories, and office buildings, so that in this branch one may <pb facs="5418474_5_1634.jpg" n="3"/>scarcely expect an increased output; the contrary, in fact, is the case.</p>
   <p>The second hurdle results from our deferred payment system. Under normal conditions, manufacturers and merchants can increase consumption artificially by lowering the sales price and being content with moderate profits, but this is only possible when the market is capable of absorbing the products.</p>
   <p>In America, this ability has been systematically reduced. All luxury articles, such as automobiles, musical instruments, jewelry, fur coats, furniture, vacuum cleaners, sewing and washing machines, and so on, have been sold on the installment plan by high-pressure salesmen. The public,-- most of us,-- pay for months and in many cases for years. Consequently, our purchasing power has been greatly <pb facs="5418474_5_1635.jpg" n="4"/>diminished, and, considering these circumstances, it appears almost impossible to increase consumption, a factor upon which depends our production.</p>
   <p>Opposed to this, we know that most industrial enterprises are in an exceptionally good and sound financial condition. Some firms paid off their bonded indebtedness entirely, or reduced it considerably within the last years. They are, therefore, fully able to rebuild their plants and make improvements which have been contemplated for future years. The largest builder and employer in the land is probably the Federal Government. Its financial position is excellent, and by providing necessary work much can be done to eliminate a depression.</p>
   <p>No superfluous or useless work need be resorted to, to distribute <pb facs="5418474_5_1636.jpg" n="5"/>money to the unemployed. The building of Boulder Dam and the flood control of the Mississippi are, for instance, absolutely profitable enterprises. This has been conceded long ago, and here veritable armies of laborers can find work and numerous industries can secure large contracts.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, most states, counties, and cities cannot emulate the government. They follow the precept of most of the inhabitants. They mortgaged the future and spent the money. Apparently, the citizens are not willing to continue in that vein. Chicago and Cook County rejected all bond issues, save one, during the last election. On the same day, similar local elections were in progress in many cities and counties of Ohio. Almost all their bond issues found definite opposition. Only Cincinnati approved them.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1637.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>From this side, then, no far-reaching vitalization of our building industry can be expected. In judging economic conditions, we must consider, first of all, that the repercussions of the financial crash will probably be of short duration so far as business activity is concerned.</p>
   <p>The Christmas sales will undoubtedly suffer, but if President Hoover's conference accepts his plans, and the government comes to the rescue with the needed work, then a prompt return to normalcy is well within the range of probability.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
