<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-03-26">Mar. 26, 1917</date>.
    <title level="a"/></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0458</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0458.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-03-26">Mar. 26, 1917</date>.
    <title level="a"><gap unit="words" extent="8"/></title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In certain circles known as German haters, the members endeavor to represent the Germans of this country, whether citizens or not, as dangerous to America in case war should break out between the United States and Germany. We, who know the Germans of America better than all those haters combined, repudiate this suspicion as one of the most cowardly acts which could have ever been invented by the brains of a brazen scoundrel.</p>
   <p>The crooks of those circles from which such suspicions emanate are accusing us of the crime they themselves committed, in the interest of a foreign power, against our fatherland. We do not have to enter into the matter much closer. Every politically mature person knows whom and what we mean, and the future will confirm how justifiable our warnings were against those pseudo-patriots and those war like adventurers for whom there was no necessity at all. And from the midst of those pharisees and hypocrites came lately, the inciting lies that the German-Americans were lukewarm towards the promotion of universal military service. This caused <pb facs="5418474_5_0459.jpg" n="2"/>surprise, because the militarily trained Germans have special interest in this institution, for the purpose of defending our country.</p>
   <p>There is not a German in America, who does not love this country as much as he hates those who want to lead it into massacre and trouble. And, because all Germans love America, for that reason they support every measure which is fitted to increase the military strength of our country. Because the competent, militarily and politically ripe Germans of America have noticed for a long time, that dangers are threatening our country, against which we are not sufficiently armed. Every politically experienced man in America knows that in the south as well as in the far east war clouds are gathering against the United States. The Mexican question is still as unsolved, as at the time when the bandit Villa was "persona grata" in Washington. Mr. Wilson does not seem to have much luck with his Mexican friends. For years Villa was his choice. Then the picture changed suddenly to Carranza, Villa's enemy who became Washington's favorite. Now, if signs do not deceive, we again are standing before a change, a change which seems to be more wonderful than the previous one. It says that Carranza has fallen in disgrace and that in all probability, Villa again appears to be the coming man in Washington.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
