<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-07-20">July 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">The Tribune Attacks the Illinois Staats Zeitung.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0455</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0455.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1917-07-20">July 20, 1917</date>.
<title level="a">THE TRIBUNE ATTACKS THE ILLINOIS STAATS ZEITUNG.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The following editorial was printed July 19th, 1917 in the Chicago Tribune:</p>
   <p>We reproduce it because it criticises our editorial entitled "Canada" printed July 17th, in the Illinois Staats Zeitung. We champion the very best interests of the United States over and above those of every other nation, including Great Britain and Germany. The tendency of some American newspapers to prefer the interests of Great Britain to those of our own country we deplore and condemn. America first, last, and all the time is our slogan.</p>
   <p>The German-American Press.</p>
   <p>"In view of the attitude of a large section of the German-American press, it is worth while to consider what would happen if a newspaper printed in Germany carried on a campaign of abuse directed at Germany's allies. The question answers itself. The paper would be suppressed and the editor would be put in jail. The German newspapers printed in the United States have mostly carefully avoided making any open attack on our government. But they have consistently abused and berated Great <pb facs="5418474_5_0456.jpg" n="2"/>Britain, they have pictured her as a monster doomed to destruction by the forces of "Kultur", and they have printed articles to show she is on the verge of financial collapse. In a lesser degree these papers have published similar attacks on our other allies. The war reviews written by their editors are based on their opinion that Germany is bound to win. If this kind of jounalism is not designed to give aid and comfort to the enemy, we are at a loss to understand what its purpose is. It is perhaps more vicious in its effect because of the insidious method necessarily employed to avoid prosecution.</p>
   <p>The character of this propaganda is well issustrated in a recent editorial on Canada appearing in the Illinois Staats Zeitung. In this editorial it is suggested that England perhaps will be unable to pay her war debts, and, we ought to be able to make a deal to get Canada in return for cancelling Great Britain's financial obligation to us.</p>
   <p>This assumption is unfriendly to Great Britain. They involve the disintegration of the British Empire. In this war we have made common cause with England and the Allied Nations. To foster the disintegration of England is to seek to undermine <pb facs="5418474_5_0457.jpg" n="3"/>our own cause. It is exactly parallel to the idea of a German newspaper trying to disintegrate Austria-Hungary.</p>
   <p>The German-American newspapers continue to publish because of our easy American tolerance. But we are becoming quickly disillusioned as to their loyalty to the United States and its cause."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
