<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-04-23">April 23, 1898</date><title level="a">Still Not Satisfied</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial Spanish War)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1310</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1310.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-04-23">April 23, 1898</date><title level="a">Still Not Satisfied</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial Spanish War)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After the Jingoes compelled the President to discontinue all further efforts for negotiations with Spain and start the first war of sympathy in the world's history, they now complain about his procrastination and slowness. According to their view, the fleet should have commenced the bombardment of Havana yesterday and the Spanish fortifications should have been destroyed in 24 hours. They are very indignant that the President "did nothing", except order a blockade of Cuba's north coast and declare coal to be contraband. Does he perhaps fear the Dons? they exclaim, "or does he believe, that the American people only authorized him to organize soup kitchens for the Reconcentrados?" Such expressions show plainer, than all the war lies of the yellow press, that the Jingos did not have any sympathy with the starving Cubans but created the war only to satisfy their furious craving for something sensational. As a counter measure, the President is more likely trying to minimize the spilling of blood, as well as the attendant horrors of war, to the lowest possible point. Instead of allowing the city of Havana to become a mass of ruins, he evidently first intends to show Spain the futility of their resistance. The latter, however, declared triumphantly, that the American navy is not large enough to blockade the entire Island, whereupon he adds, that the blockade is to be restricted to a hundred and fifty mile strip on the north coast and the Cienfuegos (100 fires) harbor of the <pb facs="5418474_5_1311.jpg" n="2"/>south coast. In all the other Cuban districts the Rebels are so strong, according to the reports of our Consuls, that the rebels could take possession of every harbor, if they did not have to fear the Spanish fleet. If the latter is kept in check, then if human predictions are at all reliable, the Spaniards will be driven back, into their fortifications. Then it will be comparatively easy to cut off their supplies and re-enforcements, and, if besides they are attacked by the Rebels in the rear then their position must be just about hopeless. They will be in a trap, similar to the French at the battle of Sedam, and if they are not insame, they'll capitulate.</p>
   <p>Of course, the Abendpost does not claim that this is the President's war plan, or that of his advisors, but it comes to these apparently logical conclusions after considering the first war movements. They indicate, as we said before, that he does not intend to increase Cuban misery, if there is a possible way to avoid it. Just as he declared in his message to Congress, he is not concerned to degrade the Spaniards, but he wishes to prevent a devastation of the entire Island and he intends to create peace and order again. If he had been given a free hand, then the entire war might have been prevented, since lately, the Spanish Government <pb facs="5418474_5_1312.jpg" n="3"/>offered one concession after another. The Jingoes, however, who consider themselves the only patriots, were pressing for a war and are even now, not satisfied, because no blood has been spilled. They accused the President of cowardice, when he attempted to reach his goal by diplomatic negotiations; now they berate his indecision because he does not intend to disembark 100,000 Americans immediately on the unhealthy Island, so that they may throttle the throats of the Spaniards. They want to see blood, yes, very much blood. And that is called patriotism!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
