<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-10-20">Oct. 20, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">A National Problem</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1642</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.E.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1642.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>II E 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1925-10-20">Oct. 20, 1925</date>.
<title level="a">A NATIONAL PROBLEM</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Whoever, on any old day, wanders through the business section of Chicago, must needs arrive at the conclusion that regulation of traffic is a complete failure. This condition is one which Chicago has in common with almost all the large cities in America, not only with cities of more than a million residents, but with all cities of two hundred thousand and less.</p>
   <p>According to official statistics published in the national capital, more than a third of all arrests made in 1924 in one hundred and seventy of the larger cities of the country were for offenses against traffic regulations. In the thirty largest cities, with more than 175,000 residents, the number amounted to about forty per cent.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1643.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Of all the cities, Grand Rapids, Michigan, heads the list of arrests for offenses against traffic regulations. In that city, with scarcely 150,000 residents, 36,613 arrests were made, of which 32,662 were for traffic violations. This case may easily be interpreted as abnormal and could perhaps be explained by local circumstances. In Los Angeles the percentage was sixty-five, in Detroit and Cincinnati more than sixty. In contrast to these numbers, they were scarcely more than nine per cent in Philadelphia and San Francisco, while Buffalo showed a little more than ten per cent. Of the total number of arrests made in Chicago, thirty per cent were for traffic violations; in New York they amounted to forty per cent.</p>
   <p>In the thirty of the largest cities of the country, with a total population of 22,386,140, according to the census bureau [1924], 1,952,646 persons were arrested, and of these, 731,580 were traffic violators. These numbers make it clear that the police, as far as it is within their power, seek strictly to carry out the traffic ordinances. They further make it clear that these <pb facs="5418474_5_1644.jpg" n="3"/>ordinances are absolutely abortive and ineffective.</p>
   <p>Since 1907, the number of arrests for these offenses has steadily and rapidly kept increasing, Before 1907, there were scarcely any arrests for this cause, as at that time automobiles were still rare and traffic regulations were not needed. This further proves that the persons arrested for having violated these ordinances are guilty only technically, but not morally. Traffic has grown to such dimensions that it simply cannot be managed any more.</p>
   <p>The grounds for it are quite apparent. They consist above all and almost exclusively in that the streets of our cities are overcrowded with automobiles. All efforts to regulate traffic by methods now in use have proven to be of no avail; withess the enormous number of arrests and the enormous number of traffic accidents. For years the problem has occupied numerous cities, but no solution has been found up to now.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1645.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>But it must be found sooner or later if America's cities do not stop short in their development. Proper traffic rules constitute an indispensable condition for the growth of cities. Up until now man has always succeeded in solving every problem that was solvable. He will solve this problem also; only it is up to us Americans to approach its solution with methods hitherto untried.</p>
   <p>There are, for instance, no tangible results to be expected from the activities of the competent committee in our state legislature. This committee has been traveling over Europe for a few months now. They visited Vienna, Edinburgh, Rome, Dublin, and the battlefields of France which, places, all combined, do not have as many automobiles as one single Chicago ward. It is also doubtful whether the gentlemen will obtain valuable inspirations for the solution of the traffic problem from the Venetian gondoliers, whose voices are so gifted. In such a manner, not even with political methods can this problem be solved. It must be solved by experts, by engineers, and the less politicians butt in, the better.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
