<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-30">Mar. 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Will High Prices Remain?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1683</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1683.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-03-30">Mar. 30, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">WILL HIGH PRICES REMAIN?</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the present time the world's industry and commerce are in a perilous condition. Manufacturers and merchants are living from hand to mouth. Industrialists and businessmen seem to be unwilling to risk an increase in either production or purchases, and private consumers are very careful to buy only what they need at the moment. Everybody knows the reason for this peculiar condition, for everybody is waiting for the inevitable drop in prices. No one wants to pay exorbitant prices now only to become angry later because he was not patient enough to wait a week or two, when he could have purchased the same articles for much less money. A man who needs a suit of clothes now defers his purchase from one day to another, hoping silently that he can obtain a better bargain tomorrow or the day after tomorrow. Building activity is apparently at a standstill; for contractors argue: "If we begin to build now when prices for materials and labor are so <pb facs="5418474_5_1684.jpg" n="2"/>high, we may find ourselves confronted with the unpleasant necessity of having to sell the finished product at cost price or even less, should the present prices return to their normal level."</p>
   <p>It is not difficult to understand this general attitude because we are wont to look upon high prices as an unwelcome result of war, and we believe that they will drop to their normal level, or at least nearly that when the war is ended. This deduction appears to be logical but it is not unconditionally so. For we have no real assurance that prices will decrease as much as is generally expected. Indeed, some economists even state that a general decrease in prices is highly improbable. They say that in a few instances there is a special reason why abnormally high prices should be lowered, but that on the average the high price levels attained during the war will remain. They assert that the world is now experiencing a price revolution similar to that which occurred in Europe during the sixteenth century, when a great amount of gold and silver was purchased from the New World. They also declare that the prices for copper and steel will decline, since they <pb facs="5418474_5_1685.jpg" n="3"/>were raised to unusual heights by the abnormal demand for them during the war. They state that the price condition of wheat is similar to that of copper and steel in that a drop in the prices of these war commodities would be followed by a decline in the price of wheat, which is also a war commodity. Despite all this a general decline from present price-levels is not to be looked for because there are no reasons for a general reduction. The gold which various governments have stored in vaults will not be more widely circulated because people have become accustomed to the use of currency and checks. Our superfluous gold will not be exported; it is more likely that Europe will export gold to our country.</p>
   <p>The economists say that there is no reason to believe that the American market will be flooded with European goods, or that Europe will dispose of her obligations to us by sending us manufactured products in lieu of money, because prices have risen in Europe more rapidly than they did in America....</p>
   <p>During the next twelve months we should find out whether or not these economists are right. The average citizen will find it difficult to adjust <pb facs="5418474_5_1686.jpg" n="4"/>himself to their ideas. He clings to the principle of "what goes up, must come down". But he fails to take into consideration the fact that a decline in prices is not feasible unless wages decline at the same time, and that workers will strenuously oppose any reduction in pay....When prices are low business stagnates. The question is, which is preferable, high prices or a poor market?</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
