<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1919-03-23">Mar. 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Civil Service in Danger</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1694</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1694.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1919-03-23">Mar. 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">CIVIL SERVICE IN DANGER</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The civil service bill which gives discharged sailors and soldiers preference in civil service examinations, and which has been advanced to the third and final reading in the State Legislature, must be considered one of many attacks which have been made on this institution. Some veterans of the Spanish-American War have claimed such preference for years, but it may be said to their credit that only a small number of them asked for the favor, the majority advocating the principle of equality.</p>
   <p>The civil service law was enacted to give all citizens of this country, irrespective of rank, station, origin, or religion, equal opportunity to participate in the public examinations. Impartially established merit, and nothing else, should be decisive in filling any public position, and obviously must serve as a basis for any proposed improvement of the <pb facs="5418474_5_1695.jpg" n="2"/>system. Civil service, in the true sense of the word, is possible only if all those who take part in examinations are placed on the same level, and the position in question is awarded to the man or woman whose name heads the list of candidates. Preference is nepotism, not proof of ability. The gratitude which is due former soldiers and sailors should not mislead us into introducing class distinctions into civil service and into making officials of people who would not be able to compete with other civilians.</p>
   <p>Civil service does not exist in state or city merely to reward meritorious work performed in the army or navy or in any profession or occupation. Its purpose is to foster intelligent action, ability, and honesty in the handling of state or municipal affairs. They who are chosen on the basis of their public examination for public service, should be required to submit only their qualifications and should not be asked to prove that their claims to the respect and good will of their fellow citizens are valid. Veterans, irrespective of their age, can successfully write the examinations, or they cannot. If they can, they need no preference. If <pb facs="5418474_5_1696.jpg" n="3"/>they cannot, they should receive no preference. The bill which is now up for consideration in Springfield, seems to have had its origin in a few "office-hungry" soldiers. It is being supported by legislators principally under the false supposition that they are doing a patriotic duty. It would be regrettable and contrary to public interest, should this additional burden be placed on civil service, which is already reeling and tottering.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
