<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-21">Nov. 21, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">The Wolf in Sheep's Clothing</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1566</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1566.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I F 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-11-21">Nov. 21, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">THE WOLF IN SHEEP'S CLOTHING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In order to comply with the Governor's whim, the state legislature convened in special session to pass the bill authorizing the collection of the sales tax beginning June 30 of next year. The bill does not state the length of time during which the tax is to be collected. To take some of the sting out of the sales tax, the Governor wishes to disclaim the land tax for 1935, just as he did for 1934. This action will somewhat lighten the burdens of the plagued taxpayer. The state administration indicates that it intends to keep at least one of the 1932 campaign promises. To say the least, this makes a good impression.</p>
   <p>In the meantime it seems that the business tax is an important source of revenue, notwithstanding the depression and the resulting curtailed purchasing power of the general population. It brings the state administration an <pb facs="5418474_5_1567.jpg" n="2"/>additional annual income of twelve million dollars. Another advantage of the business tax is that the assessments are collected monthly, and there is no long period of waiting as is characteristic of the land tax. This circumstance cannot be too highly appreciated in view of the prevailing scarcity of money.</p>
   <p>The legislature has made no disposition of the surplus income, and we do not venture to guess at its eventual disposal. The Governor fought tooth and nail against the use of even a part of the sales taxes for special purpose, such as aid to the unemployed or subventions to the school districts. For this purpose taxes on gasoline had to be employed. Be that as it may, the question is: How far will the disclaiming of the land taxes on the part of the state actually benefit the taxpayer?</p>
   <p>Let us assume that a building lot has, in accordance with the equalization factor, a taxing value of $2,000. As the state's claim is fifty cents for every $100, the state is to get $10 in taxes. At the present sales tax <pb facs="5418474_5_1568.jpg" n="3"/>rate, the same landowner would have to spend a mere $500 for his vital needs and the tax he must pay is equal to the assessment on the lot valued at $2,000. Even though the sales tax is paid by the merchant, it is included in the selling price and the consumer actually pays the tax.</p>
   <p>The situation might have become even worse for the buyer if the suggestion made by the Illinois Association of Commerce had been complied with. This suggestion advocated a fixed tax on amounts as low as twenty-five cents. More money has already come in than was expected. According to the familiar adage, "Little drops of water....make the mighty ocean," even more income could be realized. This would, of course, benefit the administration, but not the people. One consolation remains for the landowner, namely, that all have to pay the sales tax, even those who are otherwise exempt. This, however, does not increase the amount in his cash register which, after all, is his chief concern.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
