<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1914-11-29">Nov. 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Germany as Liberator of the American People</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0935</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0935.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1914-11-29">Nov. 29, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">GERMANY AS LIBERATOR OF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The present war will bring about a more or less thorough emancipation of the world from British domination and guardianship," writes Dr. Paul Rohrbach in the Sueddeutsche Zeitung [Native German paper]. This refers not only to international power politics, but also to the news service. Germany is learning right now by practical experience what this lie system of British news reporting can mean. But next to the Germans, the North Americans are the ones who suffer most, as anyone knows who reads the transatlantic news reports transmitted to this country.</p>
   <p>This absolute dependence on the British cables is as damaging as can be, not only for ourselves, but also from the American point of view. England controls all the transatlantic cables and, by this means, exercises a sort of guardianship over the world. Any time England so wishes, the whole world <pb facs="5418474_5_0936.jpg" n="2"/>will either get news reports of purely purely British origin and sentiment, or none at all. England, through her cable service, dictates to all the newspapers in the world what they are to publish. She is not in the least concerned with South American or Chinese interests, for example, but considers only her own interests, in so far as this cable service is concerned. Every news item of economic or political importance is first filtered through the sponge of her own selfish interests. The nations in general do not at all realize to what extent they have become England's hirelings in this respect.</p>
   <p>Even in America [U. S. A.] there is only a tiny group of people who are aware that the American people are looking at world events, not from the prospective of their own interests, but from the British point of view. The entire transatlantic cable service, dealing with European affairs, has a decidedly British tone. The European correspondents of the great American daily news-papers are oftentimes Englishmen, and even the Americans among them are mainly dependent on English sources for their news dispatches, because they know only the English language. Then too, most news reporting does not even originate <pb facs="5418474_5_0937.jpg" n="3"/>on the European continent, but is doctored up in London to promote British interests, not American. During the first two or three weeks of this war the American newspapers, with hardly an exception, contained nothing but news which breathed hatred and enmity for Germany. The reaction of the majority of the American people was marked. Not only were Americans convinced that the Germans were in the wrong, but they also believed that Germany was being licked by her enemies consistently, from the first day of the war on. Only weeks later, when German newspapers reached these shores, and a large number of Americans came home from Germany, could a change in attitude be observed.</p>
   <p>If you look at it objectively, is it not simply incredible, and unworthy of the United States that during such a tremendous event as this World War a nation of one hundred million people--a world power--should be completely at the mercy of alien British news reporting? If the Americans had had a translantic cable connection of their own, if they had had an independent news service <pb facs="5418474_5_0938.jpg" n="4"/>not subservient to British interests, if they had not been conditioned for decades by British reports on Germany and other European countries dressed up to serve British interests and their own, Americans would be able now to form a correct picture of the causes and aspects of present events abroad. As it is, they are groping in the dark. We have never heard of such colossal insolence in all the world as that of the English who, from their official government communiques down to the wildest press agency, tell all America fake stories about the origin of this war, in the same way that a crooked horse dealer would try to soft soap a yokel. The Americans would learn a good lesson for the future. If they realized how unworthy and damaging it is for them to be heplessly dependent on British transatlantic cable monopoly. America, immersed in a cloud of lying propaganda, caught in a trap laid by a gang of demagogues, presents a grotesque aspect. And if Americans ever rediscover their self-respect and dignity in this matter, by demanding to read the truth from overseas rather than falsified reports, they themselves will gain by it even more than Germany would. One good thing about German victories is <pb facs="5418474_5_0939.jpg" n="5"/>that they cannot be successfully lied away. But it would be nice for Americans to obtain the facts immediately, instead of first being led around by the nose for a couple of weeks.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
