<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-10-01">Oct. 1, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">Protest--But with Moderation! Editor-in-Chief of the Amerikanische Turnzeitung Sounds Warning</title><title level="a" type="sub">Germany and America</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-10-01">Oct. 1, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">PROTEST--BUT WITH MODERATION! Editor-in-Chief of the Amerikanische Turnzeitung Sounds Warning</title><title level="a" type="sub">Germany and America</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"Let us be moderate in our protests against the anti-German attitude which has become prevalent here in America since the outbreak of the war in Europe; let us not become victims of hysteria, and let us be careful not to create the impression that we are a segregated part of the American people and thus antagonize the Anglo-Americans against us "--this was the essence of the warning which Martin L. Bunge of Milwaukee, editor in chief of the Amerikanische Turnzeitung, gave hundreds of Germans who had gathered last night at the North Side Turner Hall in response to an invitation from the Committee on Intellectual Interests of the [Chicago] Turngemeinde. The subject of Mr. Bunge's talk was "The Political Relations between Germany and the United States, a Historical Review".</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1060.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Before the lecture began, Chairman Kusswurm talked about the importance of "mental" training and pointed out that the turners had advocated such laws as abolition of child labor, direct election of United States Senators, etc. long before anyone dreamed that such laws would ever be enacted.</p>
   <p>The Turner Maennerchor, conducted by Julius Remke, gave a splendid rendition of "Gebet waehrend der Schlacht" and "Das Deutsche Lied" Frau Mathilde Kahler, who had promised her co-operation, sang the aria "Kennst Du das Land" from the opera "Mignon" and also a melodramatic ditty called "Mei Bua is ma aanzige Freid," which, since it described the feelings of a young girl whose sweetheart is about to go to war, met with great applause.</p>
   <p>International Ethics</p>
   <p>Mr. Bunge was then introduced to the audience. He began his lecture by <pb facs="5418474_5_1061.jpg" n="3"/>saying that he was going to keep himself strictly to the topic under discussion, namely, the political relations of the Republic of the United States with Germany. The speaker emphasized, right at the beginning, that during these times, when patriotic sentiments [for the old country] were rekindled among hyphenated Americans, special care should be exercised not to condemn a whole nation on general grounds. The political world situation should be judged from a viewpoint of "international ethics" and one should bear in mind that decent people are to be found everywhere. The German blood, said the speaker, is not any better than that of other nations, but German culture should be honored and respected.</p>
   <p>In broad outlines, the speaker then presented a historical review of the relations between two countries. He declared that the German princes at the time the young transatlantic Republic was born were nothing but a gang of unscrupulous scoundrels. The only exception was the king of Prussia, <pb facs="5418474_5_1062.jpg" n="4"/>Frederick the Great, who at that time was at the height of his power and glory, and who sent his general Von Steuben to America to make soldiers out of the Americans.</p>
   <p>But Frederick the Great aided [America] not only by sending Steuben; he did equally as much by immediately recognizing the new-born nation, a fact which should receive more space and emphasis in American school and history books. The speaker then touched upon the tariff treaties negotiated between the two countries in the early forties, which engendered the enmity of England, and he described in detail how Prussia's attitude during the Civil War, unlike that of France and England, had helped America immeasurably by strengthening her credit in Europe. He then gave some details of the important services which the American Ambassador in Paris, Washburn, had rendered in 1870-71 to many Germans who had been expelled ( ausgewiesen). After the speaker briefly mentioned the Samoa incident, and tried to explain the questionable attitude of the German fleet before Manila Harbor during the Spanish-American War, an attitude which caused an anti-German outburst in <pb facs="5418474_5_1063.jpg" n="5"/>the Anglo-American press, he concluded his historical review by expressing the hope that in the future, should Germany win the war, both countries, as the greatest powers in the world, might work for permanent peace on this globe. Mr. Bunge then urged the audience always to remember that they were Americans first, and Germans second, and to do nothing that would bring them in conflict with their Anglo-American fellow citizens.</p>
   <p>Although there was considerable applause, it was nevertheless evident that the audience was more pleased with the historical facts presented to them than with the speaker's personal opinions.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
