<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-05-24">May 24, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">Radio Programs</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1512</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.B.3.b"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1512.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 3 b</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-05-24">May 24, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">RADIO PROGRAMS</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Last April, Anning S. Prall, the chairman of the Federal Communications Commission, issued a warning concerning objectionable radio programs. He especially emphasized the importance of greater care in the choice of children's programs. His demand was certainly justified, and he made a good impression by not asking for new laws to provide censorship over radio programs. He believed that the existing laws would suffice to bring about the desired changes in programs, since the Federal Communications Commission has the right to refuse to renew licenses.</p>
   <p>His way of doing things seems productive of the desired results. The Columbia Broadcasting System is the first major network to issue new regulations for radio programs to satisfy the wishes of the Federal Communications Commission. These regulations, of course, cannot change the contracts already in effect.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1513.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since, however, the last of the existing contracts will terminate in March, 1936, all objectionable programs should be eliminated by that time. But it must be made certain that, when business is poor, the Columbia Broadcasting Station shall not be tempted to weaken, or to ignore one or the other of its rules for the sake of lucrative contracts.</p>
   <p>First, a very laudable limitation is provided for the commercial part of the program. This part should not exceed fifteen per cent of the total time until 6 P.M., or ten per cent after 6 P.M. One single exception is permitted in programs of fifteen minutes' duration; their advertising time is extended by forty seconds. They also want to curb the practice of rapid talking to get more commercial announcements into the time allotted for advertising.</p>
   <p>The second point deals with children's programs. The Columbia Broadcasting System decided to engage the services of a recognized child psychologist, who is to form a committee of persons versed in the field. They will examine the children's programs to be broadcast, and will also assist in selecting the <pb facs="5418474_5_1514.jpg" n="3"/>proper material. This is intended to assure that the so-called blood-and-thunder programs will be granted no time over the radio.</p>
   <p>Glorification of gangsters and racketeers is especially to be avoided; cruelty, lust for gain, and egotism should be presented as unworthy of emulation. Care should also be taken to avoid strengthening children in disobeying their parents, or showing disrespect or impoliteness to older persons, even if the scene is supposed to be humorous. These rules will undoubtedly have a very favorable effect upon the rearing of children, especially if correctly applied.</p>
   <p>The Columbia Broadcasting System goes a step farther by refusing to sign contracts with firms whose products make reference to parts or functions of the body that are unfit topics for social conversation. Under these rules, for instance, remedies for the regulation of the bowels, depilatories, aids for combating bad breath, and similar things could not be exploited.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1515.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>It is to hoped that other radio stations and networks will follow the example of the Columbia Broadcasting Station.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
