<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-17">Apr. 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Much Adc about Nothing</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0159</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0159.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-17">Apr. 17, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">MUCH ADC ABOUT NOTHING</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Easter Monday, 1919, the sale of the Victory Loan will begin. Everywhere in our city and country preparations are being made with rapidity and persistency--very special preparations. Not only are committees being organized, speakers being engaged, and advertisements written and published, but triumphal arches are being erected, great parades and mass meetings arranged, etc. The sale campaign is to be ushered in, here in Chicago, by a loud, awe-inspiring, and somewhat fantastic demonstration. At one minute after midnight the electric current which lights the thousands of bulbs totaling about one billion candle power will be turned on. They will illuminate the "Victory Forum" which has been built to advertise the Victory Loan campaign. The whistles of the factories in the city and the sirens of the boats in the harbor are to be sounded; the church bells are to be tolled, and large bombs are to be exploded in order to <pb facs="5418474_5_0160.jpg" n="2"/>inform the citizens of Chicago that the campaign for the Victory Loan has begun. It is expected that Chicago will--what?</p>
   <p>The total amount of the Victory Loan was set at $4,500,000,000. Chicago's quota is $180,000,000. That is the sum which Chicago is asked to lend to the Government, so that the latter may be able to defray the unpaid balances for armaments, the cost of demobilization, and the necessary expenditures which must be made in connection with the readjustment of the country to peacetime conditions. The Government is not asking that the Loan be made gratis, but it will issue promissory notes, secured by the assets of the whole nation, and bearing interest at the rate of 41/2 per cent per year.</p>
   <p>Is that the reason for these elaborate preparations, the great exertions, the advertisements, the din and clamor, and the enthusiastic appeals to the sense of duty and patriotism of our fellow citizens? The average Frenchman would probably say: "Tant de bruit pour une omelette" (much ado about nothing). The <pb facs="5418474_5_0161.jpg" n="3"/>American, more mature, might be tempted to say: "Methinks thou protests too much." The latter has had very many sad experiences with "gilt-edged" stock and "bomb-proof" bonds, which glib promoters had to offer. He is reminded most vividly of this by the manner in which Uncle Sam is offering the Victory Loan. The Frenchman, however, is used to purchasing government securities, and he is good at figures. He knows that the "gold notes" of Uncle Sam at 4g per cent interest are a good investment, in fact, the best investment anybody can possibly make. He would be right in thinking that these bonds could easily be disposed of, and that so much ado about nothing is entirely unnecessary.....</p>
   <p>Well, the "how" is merely incidental, at all events. There may be people who can be awakened to the knowledge of their duty toward the state and themselves only by bells, whistles, and bombs, and who can be made to realize the benefits of purchasing those bonds in no other way.</p>
   <p>The main thing is that these securities be disposed of quickly: that Chicago subscribe to its quota; that the so-called "little man" participate especially, for <pb facs="5418474_5_0162.jpg" n="4"/>it will be a long time before such an opportunity presents itself to him again. Above all, men and women of German origin must avail themselves fully of this opportunity, for the benefit of the state of which they are a part, as well as for their own benefits.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
