<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-09">Sept. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Fight against the German Language</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0383</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0383.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-09">Sept. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE FIGHT AGAINST THE GERMAN LANGUAGE</title><title level="a">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At a meeting of a local German women's lodge held not so long ago, an American-born member, both of whose parents were German, rose from her seat and demanded for "patriotic" reasons that henceforth all proceedings should be conducted in the "American" rather than in the German language. Before the proposal was permitted to come up for discussion, the president of the organization asked for the privilege of making a reply. She answered the "patriot" in the following words:</p>
   <p>"When you joined our lodge, you knew that it was a German organization in the sense that German was its 'business' language. This does not imply that the members consider themselves Germans or that they should conduct themselves as Germans, and it does not mean that they are asked to neglect <pb facs="5418474_5_0384.jpg" n="2"/>their duties toward their new country in any way in order to favor the interests of Germany. It merely means that the language employed in this lodge is the language which is best familiar to the members, simply because it is their native tongue. Patriotism does not manifest itself in words, but in deeds. One can urge on people to heroic deeds for their adopted country in the German language, and by the same token one can advocate high treason in English. The German women belonging to our organization have given their sons to the Army and Navy; they have lent their daughters to the Red Cross to nurse the wounded; they have invested their own and their husbands' money in Liberty bonds, war-savings stamps, and thrift stamps; and they have knitted and sewed clothing to preserve the health and promote the well-being of our boys in khaki. Are these things not to be considered simply because these women desire to cling to their native tongue--a desire which is after all only human--and thus continue a practice to which they have an unquestionable right?</p>
   <p>"President Wilson has declared that we are at war not with the German people, <pb facs="5418474_5_0385.jpg" n="3"/>nor with German art and science, nor even with the German language, but solely with the autocracy that is ruling Germany. In Germany the saying is: 'The Kaiser's word is above reproach!' For us in the United States, the saying should be: 'The integrity of a President's word should not be impugned!' As long as the Federal Government does not forbid the use of the German language in the United States, we shall speak German here and nothing but German, which, I hope, will be spoken here for many generations to come."</p>
   <p>And this--we almost said, manly--speech sealed the fate of the proposal advocating the use of the English language.</p>
   <p>We could not help thinking of this incident as we read an announcement published by the American Defense Society, which tells of the success the Society is having in its "defense" against the German language, although "attack" would seem to be a more appropriate word. "Fourteen states," the report goes <pb facs="5418474_5_0386.jpg" n="4"/>on to say, "have forbidden the teaching of German in all of their schools, and in sixteen other states a campaign is in progress to bring about a similar ban. In many cities in the latter group of states, German-language instruction has already been dropped, but the states themselves have as yet taken no action on the matter. The Defense Society is now endeavoring to get these states to act." The following states are singled out as worthy of commendation: Alabama, California,...., Utah, and West Virginia. The states in which a vigorous campaign is being waged include Arizona, Arkansas,...., Virginia, and Wisconsin. The following large cities have "dropped German-language instruction entirely or in part": New York, Philadelphia,...., Quakerstown, Pennsylvania, and Glen Cove, Long Island.</p>
   <p>There is much food for thought in the various aspects of the systematic action conducted by the Defense Society. However, we leave it to our readers to draw their own conclusions. We are not motivated by self-interest when we point out once more that, in the light of present conditions, the <pb facs="5418474_5_0387.jpg" n="5"/>continued existence of the German-language press is vitally bound up with the fate of the German language in the United States.</p>
   <p>German-Americans, do your duty!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
