<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-01-04">January 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Announcement</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0842</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0842.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-01-04">January 4, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">ANNOUNCEMENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Every association in the United States is urgently requested to quote and adopt the following resolutions:</p>
   <p>The - - - - - - - - - -</p>
   <p>of - - - - - - - - - - -</p>
   <p>with a membership of - - - - citizens of Chicago, on the - - day of - - 1914, adopted the following resolutions:</p>
   <p>Whereas, ten nations of the old world are now waging the greatest war of mankind and are not only exhausting their own resources but are also drawing immense supplies and munitions of war from the United States of America, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, the armament amd supplies that are being furnished by the United States tend to increase the military conflagration of Europe, multiply the loss of life, already appalling, and cause the destruction of property that is bringing nations to desolation, and assist in the prolongation and continuance of this most dreadful of all wars, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, we, as a people, from our hearts lift our voices in prayer for peace <pb facs="5418474_5_0843.jpg" n="2"/>while, as a Nation, we are aiding in war, and augmenting the struggle by emptying our private arsenals and war supplies onto the battlefields of Europe, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, our Government has proclaimed strict neutrality and thereby given assurance to American citizens of all races and to the belligerent powers themselves, that we shall give aid and support to none, and by our acts, as a Nation break no bonds of friendship with the countries with whom we are at peace, and create no discord among our citizens hereby discriminating against their fatherland, yet when we offer military supplies and equipments to any nations that choose to buy, it is with the full knowledge that for one hundred years England by her supremacy on the sea, is the master of all contraband goods transported by water, and that she and her friends alone can benefit by our unholy commerce, and we are pursuing that course which diverts so far from strict neutrality that we injure our ancient friends, excepting the employment of armed force alone, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, this country has recognized the right of our government to with hold war supplies from contending armies when she laid an embargo upon munitions of war when the feeble armies of Mexico were arrayed against each other, nevertheless, she now offers her limitless supplies to the mightiest armies that were <pb facs="5418474_5_0844.jpg" n="3"/>ever assembled in battle array; and</p>
   <p>Whereas, the United States is disloyal to itself when it promotes a foreign war by furnishing the sinews of war, while the nation is prostrate commercially and waiting for the dawn of peace to return to her former prosperity and achievement.</p>
   <p>Therefore be it resolved, that we, the above named society, hereby declare that it is the imperative duty of the Congress of the United States to pass the necessary law forthwith that will enable the President of the United States to lay an embargo upon all contraband of war, saving and excepting foodstuffs alone, and thereby withdraw from the contending powers all aid and assistance of this Republic.</p>
   <p>Be it further resolved, that we are in strict sympathy with the Christian endeavor of this nation to appeal to the God of nations that peace may come and reject as hypocrisy and national sacrilege the commercial spirit of the country that is answering our supplications for peace by sending the instruments of destruction and death to the serried armies arrayed in struggle through the empires of Europe.</p>
   <p>And be it further resolved, that we, as joint races, who have sought the shelter <pb facs="5418474_5_0845.jpg" n="4"/>of the American flag and have contributed our full share to American peace, American Christianity and American civilization, that we call upon all Americans to join with us in enforcing thatstrict American neutrality that will give aid and comfort to none of the contending powers and that will withhold American resources from promoting destruction and slaughter among the friendly nations of Europe.</p>
   <p>We, the President and Secretary of the above named society attest the above by our signatures.</p>
   <p>Every society is requested after adopting the resolutions to copy some three times and have them certified by the President and Secretary, where upon the Illinois Staats Zeitung will mail one of each to the representative of the district in which the society is located.</p>
   <p>By request copies of these resolutions will be delivered free of charge.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
