<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-07-24">July 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Note to Germany.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0659</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0659.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-07-24">July 24, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE NOTE TO GERMANY.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>As we stated yesterday before we saw the text of the latest note to Germany, that it appeared as if our Government had a secret understanding with England to intentionally provoke Germany, to disregard all intentions and necessities of German warfare, and to cause a rupture by force. The text of the note is now before us and its tenor justifies assumption of yesterday. Germany cannot accept such a tone and, to our painful regret, will find only one way to answer same; the severance of diplomatic relations. We, as well as the German Government, know that such a step only realizes the united wishes of Washington and London, and places the German-Americans in a very awkward position, but every fair thinking person will understand and appreciate fully that Germany, in spite of the hostile attitude of its (America's) press, and in spite of the unneutral neutrality of its Government, offered the United States the broadest possible ground for an accord, and for the prevention of <pb facs="5418474_5_0660.jpg" n="2"/>every danger to traveling Americans. Every fair thinking person will understand and appreciate that Germany must consider also her own dignity and the necessity with which it is faced in this bloody struggle.</p>
   <p>And if Mr. Wilson asserts the German answer is totally unsatisfactory, because it does not remove the differences existing between the two governments; if, further, the president in his submitted note thinks that he and his government can deal only with the English Government in British questions, then the German Government will deny this Government, with perfect justification, the right, in regard to the safety of British ships, to negotiate with Germany or to make claims against it in the form of threats. And the German Government, in view of the insulting remark that humanity and justice demand the cessation of submarine warfare, if neutral life and interests are endangered - no doubt will reply <pb facs="5418474_5_0661.jpg" n="3"/>that President Wilson forfeited the right to demand in the name of humanity and justice, as long as he cannot see the inhumanity and injustice of the one-sided supply of arms and the reasons that compelled Germany to resort to the submarine war. Furthermore, Germany could point out that Americans who take passage on a hostile vessel, according to the law enacted during the Civil War, lost every right to be considered neutrals and be treated as such. And on the part of our Government a malicious intent is noticeable in the headstrong demand to spare hostile ships, because Americans are on same. It is much easier for Americans to keep off such ships than it is for Germans, to allow vessels, carrying arms to be used against her, to proceed unmolested. The note reveals that President Wilson wants to cause a rupture with Germany at all events. Our great apostle of peace shows himself in his true light. But he should first ask us, the people of the United States, whether we are willing to be forced into war.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0662.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The President's latest note is unworthy of this republic and we trust that Germany will bear no grudge against the American people for the want of tact by their government - which must be considered as only temporary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
