<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-07-13">July 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">The Undivided People.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0663</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0663.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-07-13">July 13, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">THE UNDIVIDED PEOPLE.</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Tribune, in its edition of yesterday showed a picture of the President reading the Anglo-American newspapers, according to the Tribune's comprehension, laying his finger on the pulse of the nation. If the President is able to hear the voices of the American nation from these papers, he actually has good reason to suppose, that the American people are undivided. Undivided in their hatred against Germany, undivided in the desire to see the German nation reprimanded by the American government. But in the same manner by which President Wilson obtained his high office through a minority of the American people and which he executes to the dissatisfaction of the majority, in the same way do the Anglo-American newspapers represent a vanishing minority of the American people.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0664.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The millions of petitions, which have been submitted to the President, since his pursuit of an Anglophile policy; the complaints of the cotton growers and the wholesalers originate from the people and prove audibly and emphatically, that the President has no undivided nation behind him, and, that it is not only the un-American German-Americans who assert that the government's policy does not fulfill the requirements of neutrality and causes moral and economic loss to the country.</p>
   <p>The President should also listen to those voices, which proclaim another truth rather than the newspapers. And if he could count the voices he would come to know, that the editorials of the Anglo-American papers, which have been dipped in poison, are originating from paid hirelings and not from the hearts of the American people.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0665.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Prof. Edward Meyer of Berlin published a letter received from W. G. McNeill, who lives in Richmond, Va. This letter sounds entirely different, from the Anglo-American inciting articles. It runs as follows: "The Germans should not forget, that besides a hostile American press and a number of malevolent Americans, a large number of Americans, especially former students of German universities, congratulate Germany upon the success of its tactics. It is possible, that Germany's American friends have made political, diplomatic mistakes, but they must be satisfied with the strong hope of a final victory. They are praying earnestly, that a united, determined, courageous and trusting Germany, should endure till the oceans are freed by the Germans. Like in olden times with the religion this gigantic task, at present, is a fight for the solving of the inevitable." And another American, John Van Kloak, writes from Ridley Park, Pa., that 50 to 75 per cent of the people of the United States, share the opinion of the editorial of the German press of May 18th, on the case of the Lusitania. Germany may believe the assurance, that millions and millions of Americans, in spite <pb facs="5418474_5_0666.jpg" n="4"/>of the demeanor of their press, sympathize with Germany.</p>
   <p>The letter closes as follows: "Let our newspapers fume. Go forward, and beat your enemies." The writer of the letter maintains, that there flows no German blood in his veins, because his ancestors were of Dutch-English descent and settled in America in 1637. And Hannis Taylor, former American Ambassador to Spain, and later special adviser to the State Department in Washington, a real authority in international law, writes: "We should not allow illusions to deceive us. Germany stands with its back to the wall. It fights for its life, and, therefore, it could not comply with our demands in regard to the submarine war, even if the same were unlawful, except we compel England, and we are unable to compel her, to change her method of unlawful blockade in a way which would unable Germany to make concessions."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0667.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Who is so blind, that he cannot see that the way to peace can only be opened through such an action? We cannot expect a friendly agreement with Germany, if we do not compel England, to yield, and this can only be accomplished by an action on the part of the American Congress......</p>
   <p>Hannis Taylor is one of those Americans, who are not descended from barbarians. And it might also be supposed that William Jennings Bryan, in spite of his many faults, can still be counted among the true Americans and that his word has, even now, as much weight as that of the clandestine Anglo-American editors. And Mr. Bryan, said in a speech he made in Los Angeles, yesterday, in regard to the German answer: "The majority of the American people, as far as I can judge their feelings, has only an interest for one thing and that is that American interests should be protected and that neutrality should be observed.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0668.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Every individual may have an opinion about the inhumanity of the drowning or starving of non-combatants but it is not our (a neutral nation) business to regulate the methods which warring parties apply to each other.........</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
