<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-10-11">October 11, 1898</date><title level="a">Militarism and Disarmament</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1303</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1303.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-10-11">October 11, 1898</date><title level="a">Militarism and Disarmament</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The proposal to disarm made by the Czar, the ruler of all the Russians, just a few weeks ago, already ceased to be a subject for public discussion. Once in a while only one can find an article in a newspaper about the peace problem and disarmament. Even those reports, which are expected as soon as the appointed commissions will meet and discuss the problem of disarmament, will hardly become the general and important topic for open discussions and conversations. Since one cannot and will not believe, that the beautiful words of the Czar can be practically realized, the consultations of the peace commissions will meet with academic interest only.</p>
   <p>If the Czar was sincere in his proposals, it must hurt him to see the cool and distrustful reception of his peace plans. Perhaps, he expected hopeful and joyful rousing shouts from the oppressed masses of militaristic Europe, and enthusiastic support from democratic countries, but nothing of this was manifested. Large and enthusiastic mass manifestations - neither in his own country, nor in Germany, France, Italy etc. - took place. Both the large republic of the United States and the small one of Switzerland failed to support him. This exceptionally cool reception of the Czar's humane proposal admits several interpretations. Either the people do not trust him - they do not believe in the sincerity and earnestness of his nice <pb facs="5418474_5_1304.jpg" n="2"/>phrases - or they think it impossible to carry his plans out, or else they do not care for disarmament and peace.</p>
   <p>Perhaps, the last of the three mentioned reasons for the cool reception of the Czars peace proposal is the decisive one, though only few would confess the truth of it. If the nations really possessed a burning desire for general disarmament and world peace, as one should assume and the friends of peace believe, then they would have felt joy over the words of the Czar, which would have culminated in manifestations of great exultations, in spite of critical reflections and remarks. A powerful and mighty, "we will it" would have thundered through the nations. Probably objections of the Governments would have been drowned in the categorical demand of the people, "You must find ways and means to carry out such lofty plans." The silent reception of the Czar's message of world-peace is sufficient evidence of the nations disbelief, or that their desire for disarmament is not very urgent and intense.</p>
   <p>The individual as well as a nation both are the product of their environment. Germans may oppose militarism and the great burdens of armaments, yet they are proud of their military fame and the empire's position of power. Even Germans separated from their home country for a generation like to read about the <pb facs="5418474_5_1305.jpg" n="3"/>powerful and well disciplined army. Militaristic plays belong to the greatest amusements of the people. The army enjoys a favorable position in the life of the nation, and this position the people themselves have granted. England gets intoxicated about the heroic actions of its soldiers, and the Frenchmen are idolaters in their glorification of the army. The French would not renounce their famous army for any consideration.</p>
   <p>One can justly assert, that next to the republic of France the great republic of the United States would be the least willing, to accept the proposals of the Czar, because the idea of militarism has become more popular since we obtained easy victories over Spain, and the desire for military adventures is aroused.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
