<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-02">Nov. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">For the Congress!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0520</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-danish #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0520.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>IV (Danish)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-02">Nov. 2, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">FOR THE CONGRESS!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Sixty-Sixth Congress, which is to be elected next Tuesday, will be chiefly a Congress of reconstruction. That means that its first and foremost duty will be to put the country back on a peace basis--to take care, by wise legislation, that the transition from war to peace takes place without any heavy economic losses or disturbances and to insure that the country enjoys prosperity under the new conditions which the war has brought about.</p>
   <p>As regards the Senate, we must add that it will be called upon to conclude the peace, inasmuch as it will have to negotiate the peace terms and give its final approval.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0521.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Since we desire an American and truly democratic peace--the sort of peace President Wilson is seeking--and a peace which guarantees fullest justice to all peoples, we are in favor of Senator James Hamilton Lewis, whose re-election by the citizens of Illinois is requested by President Wilson, because he can depend on him completely in any problem involving war or peace. We urgently recommend that all readers of the Abendpost and citizens of German descent give their votes to Senator Lewis in the senatorial elections.</p>
   <p>The recommendations for the House of Representatives, which can be found elsewhere, were based chiefly on the anticipated attitude of the respective candidates regarding the peace policy of the President, and also on their character and general qualifications for that high office.</p>
   <p>Party politics did not influence our selections. These considerations were only incidental and were decisive in only one case.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0522.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>In the Seventh Congressional District, in which the present Representatives, Mr. Niels Juul and Mr. Frank M. Padden, are candidates for the House of Representatives, it was hard to make a decision. Mr. Juul has earned a good reputation as a conscientious and capable legislator, and can also be considered to have a sound attitude on the questions of war and peace aims, whereas his opponent, Padden, is by comparison a political novice and has yet to earn a name for himself. However, our government is a party government. In important national questions the policy sponsored by the party in power is authoritative and obligatory for those members of Congress who are members of the party; few would dare to oppose the party orders on important issues; still less could they manage to retain any appreciable influence if they chose such a course. Because Mr. Padden pledged his unconditioned and unreserved support for the President's policies for peace and reconstruction, he became our final choice.</p>
   <p>To the voters of the Ninth Congressional District we highly recommend <pb facs="5418474_5_0523.jpg" n="4"/>Mr. Fred S. Britten for re-election. For Mr. Britten, although a Republican, stands squarely behind the President's peace policy. Mr. James H. Poage, his Democratic opponent, seems to be inclined toward the policy of the Lodges and Roosevelts, etc.. The National Security League published the copy of a questionnaire which was filled out by Britten and Poage. The ninth question of the League's questionnaire was: "Is the candidate willing to pledge his advocacy of a peace with victory--i.e. a forceful continuation of the war, until Germany, Austria-Hungary, and Turkey yield to the demands of the Allies?"</p>
   <p>To this question Mr. Poage replied: "I am for a peace with victory. We and our Allies will determine the terms of peace."</p>
   <p>Mr. Britten replied: "I am for a forceful continuation of the war until Germany, Austria-Hungary, and Turkey give in to the demands of the Government of the United States."</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0524.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>This makes Britten our man. For by his answer he puts himself behind the President and unconditionally favors an American peace; whereas Mr. Poage talks about our Allies and thereby puts himself in opposition to the President, who recognizes only temporary allies.</p>
   <p>All voters of the Ninth Congressional District who desire an early, just, and American peace, should vote for James H. Lewis and Fred S. Britten, regardless of whether they are or were Republicans or Democrats or otherwise.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
