<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-09">Dec. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Three Cheers for Investigation!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0278</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0278.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-12-09">Dec. 9, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THREE CHEERS FOR INVESTIGATION!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Federal Secret Service continues to keep under strictest surveillance all those who are suspected of being "pro-German," and does not hesitate to make raids and arrests if any accusations are made, or special suspicions reported, by anybody against anybody.</p>
   <p>This is as it should be. For so far there is only an armistice--no peace has been declared--and a prompt investigation by the proper authorities is the best and only protection a suspected citizen has against injustice. Only by such an investigation can he be cleared of the suspicions voiced against him. Only by such an investigation can he be safeguarded from the violence of ill-advised or malicious persons or a "patriotic" mob.</p>
   <p>The specially appointed Senate committee entrusted with the investigation of <pb facs="5418474_5_0279.jpg" n="2"/>"German propaganda" is doing its job eagerly and diligently. The Department of Justice is furnishing all the material it has in its possession (all reports of the Secret Service, documents, letters, memoranda, etc., which its agents could get hold of). This is not only proper, for the Senate has the absolute right to demand from the Department of Justice any and all such material, but it is also gratifying and a good thing--good for the people and the country; good for all suspected and distrusted elements; and good also for those immediately involved. It promises to bring the truth to light and give every one what is his due. Those who have been found guilty of grave illegal acts will be punished, but this punishment they deserve. Others will be cleared of a suspicion that arose from nothing more than their giving free expression to their opinions and sentiments at a time when America was still officially neutral. The whole country and all the people will know the full extent of the "German propaganda" and will know for certain that grave suspicions which may arise in the future are untrue and unfounded. There will be confidence in the untiring watchfulness of the government; there will be peace <pb facs="5418474_5_0280.jpg" n="3"/>and security.</p>
   <p>That means a great deal. The investigation pays big dividends. It will also satisfy and reconcile those who are now convinced that it is not so much the desire to inform and enlighten, to bring the full truth to light and to do everybody justice, which motivates this investigation, but rather hatred and a mania for persecution. But there is something still better to look forward to. "Sauce for the goose is sauce for the gander." Though this motto seems temporarily relegated to the background, the American people still believe in it and always come back to it. Almost always an investigation is the cause of further investigations--the other side will be investigated, too.</p>
   <p>This is the case at present. While the investigation of "German propaganda" is still pending, an investigation of the National Security League, and other similar organizations, by a House committee is as good as decided upon. The favorable reception, in the House of Representative Frear's proposal to this <pb facs="5418474_5_0281.jpg" n="4"/>effect we owe, undoubtedly, to the Senate investigation. Thanks to this the House investigation will be conducted as thoroughly as the public interest requires. Thanks to the great publicity which the "revelations" of the Senate investigation will receive, we can hope that the results of the House investigation (of the Security League, etc.) will also be brought to the public's attention.</p>
   <p>And quite a great deal may be learned by the American public which will be to their advantage to know, even if they may not be so delighted to hear it. Besides the fact that these unscrupulous organizations have attempted to intimidate the Representatives of the people and have tried to beat them in the elections by using illegal means if they did not give in to their wishes, we may also learn that the rabid patriotism so brazenly displayed was, in most cases, nothing but despicable hypocrisy, petty selfishness, and yellow envy. And this investigation may lead to further investigations, which probably will bring to light quite interesting things, the existence of which <pb facs="5418474_5_0282.jpg" n="5"/>we have long suspected. All this will be welcomed by the loyal, hundred-per-cent Americans, though at first it will make them sick.</p>
   <p>Three cheers for this investigation and for those which we hope will follow! For the investigation will bring out the truth.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
