<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1916-04-22">Apr. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">We Caught Them Napping This Time</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0466</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0466.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Scandia</title>,
<date when="1916-04-22">Apr. 22, 1916</date>.
<title level="a">WE CAUGHT THEM NAPPING THIS TIME</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Scandia has received a letter from Horace L. Brand, president of the Illinois Publishing Company and editor of the German paper Illinois Staats-Zeitung.</p>
   <p>He begs the foreign-language newspaper readers to petition the President to stop the war. The letter is reprinted below:</p>
   <p>"I submit to you that the publishers of the United States have it in their power to end the war in three or at the most in six months.</p>
   <p>"Let the publishers of all the daily, weekly, Sunday, and monthly papers in the United States demand that their readers petition Congress, petition the State Department, and petition the President to take immediate steps <pb facs="5418474_5_0467.jpg" n="2"/>to have the United States send an ultimatum to the Central Powers to cease fighting within one month, stating that otherwise the United. States will declare war upon Germany and join with the Allies in order to crush her; and simultaneously with the demand on the Central Powers an ultimatum should be sent by the United States to the Allies to cease fighting within one month [with the statement that] otherwise the United States will declare the complete inhibition of all commerce between them and the United States, to continue both in the case of the Central Powers and in that of the Allies as long as the fighting shall go on. Furthermore [let the United States include] with each ultimatum the additional demand that each belligerent shall send duly accredited representatives to the United States with full authority to discuss the terms upon which peace will be declared by all the belligerents; [and let it be demanded that] the representative of the United States shall act as chairman of the Convention of the peace envoys.</p>
   <p>"I believe that the above plan would bring so many petitions into Washington <pb facs="5418474_5_0468.jpg" n="3"/>that the administration and the legislative branch of our government would soon find ways and means by which the United States might send the ultimatum hereinbefore described.</p>
   <p>"The peremptory demands of the United States, if backed by the threat of drastic action, would be granted by each group of belligerents. An armistice would result. Within the period of the armistice the peace envoys would debate the terms of peace--calmly, sanely, coolly, weighing all the factors, all the evidence, and all the cost. [The realization of the] horror and the suffering of war would dispel the hatred, the fear, the distorted ideas about grandeur and heroism and national wealth, the greed, and the jealousy.</p>
   <p>The threat of the United States would hold all belligerents in check. Fighting would not be resumed. Within three to six months peace terms would be agreed upon.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0469.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>"I verily believe that this plan, dangerous though it may seem, would succeed without injury to a single American or to any American property."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
