<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1862-11-04">Nov. 4, 1862</date>.
<title level="a">What We Want</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1417</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1417.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I J</item>
     <item>I E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1862-11-04">Nov. 4, 1862</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT WE WANT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We want the National Government to use every means at its disposal to suppress the armed Rebellion against the unity, peace, happiness, and liberty of the country.</p>
   <p>We wish to place the entire power of the nation, our property and life, at the disposal of the President and the Government, to support them in their arduous and responsible task.</p>
   <p>We desire to present a recurrence of such violent shocks to our national life for all time to come, by eradicating the root of the evil, slavery--a curse to our country and a shameful stain upon the glorious escutcheon of the United States.</p>
   <p>Therefore, we heartily approve of the President's Emancipation Proclamation, <pb facs="5418474_5_1418.jpg" n="2"/>not only because it is a necessary, effective, and forceful military measure, which will do more than anything else to quell the Rebellion, but also because it is a meritorious act which atones for the cruel crime of slavery--a crime that is contrary to every law of morality and humanity.</p>
   <p>We want the Rebels, the rebellious Southerners, to bear a proportionate part of the cost and burden of the war which they caused, and, to that end, we want the Confiscation Act which Congress passed, rigidly enforced, and the proceeds used to decrease the burden of taxation in the North and to lighten the economic pressure in the Union States.</p>
   <p>We do not want large numbers of emancipated slaves to come to the North and compete with our white workers and, perhaps, force wages to a lower level.</p>
   <p>For that reason we desire that the Emancipation Proclamation be put into practice; for we are convinced that the liberated Negro will remain in the South where the warm climate is conducive to his health and well being, if his human rights are <pb facs="5418474_5_1419.jpg" n="3"/>respected in the Southern States, if an appropriate place in society is assigned to him, and if honest and adequate efforts are made to educate him, to elevate him mentally and morally, and thus to render him a useful member of the human family.</p>
   <p>For the same reason we wish to prevent mass migration of Negro refugees through the enforcement of the Emancipation Proclamation, aided by a more rigorous prosecution of the war, under generals who really fight, who seek and defeat the enemy, who utilize the advantages which they gain, who hold conquered areas, and who protect against cruel and revengeful masters those Negroes who are devoted to the Union.</p>
   <p>To that end we want in Congress men like Arnold who was tireless in his endeavors in behalf of the enactment of the great salutary measure, and like the War-Democrat Jackson who wholeheartedly endorsed the emancipation and confiscation policy of the President and unreservedly supported Lincoln's administration.</p>
   <p>We want men in the State Legislature who are ready to support the State <pb facs="5418474_5_1420.jpg" n="4"/>administration in its commendable efforts to promote the welfare and reputation of our great patriotic State, and to care for our brave soldiers on the battlefield or in the hospital, men who have obligated themselves to preserve and further the interests of the workingman by sponsoring and passing a lien law for the purpose of protecting the workingman's property....</p>
   <p>That is what we want, and that is what that people want.</p>
   <p>And today we shall make our wants known at the polls.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
