<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-05">Sept. 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">Our Foreign-Born and the Third Liberty Loan</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0389</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <!-- 5418474_5_0388 omitted, duplicate of 5418474_5_0389 -->
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0389.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-09-05">Sept. 5, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">OUR FOREIGN-BORN AND THE THIRD LIBERTY LOAN</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Below is a compilation of the amounts which Americans of foreign birth or immediate foreign origin have subscribed to the Third Liberty Loan. The tabulations are in order of nationalities and states. These subscriptions have either been reported directly to the Treasury Department, or indirectly through the foreign-speaking departments of the Federal Reserve Districts.</p>
   <p>These figures represent about fifty-five per cent of the total amount subscribed by that part of the population. Forty-five per cent have not been reported for various reasons. This proportion is based on a conservative estimate, which is based, in turn, on the general result of the campaign in all parts of the United States.</p>
   <p>The total amount of the subscriptions of Americans of foreign birth or origin to the Third Liberty Loan can therefore be safely estimated as reaching 741,437,000 dollars. Since the grand total of subscriptions to the Third <pb facs="5418474_5_0390.jpg" n="2"/>Liberty Loan is 4,176,516,850 dollars, it can be seen that Americans of foreign origin--although on the whole they do not belong to the "wealthy classes" but rather to the "toiling masses"--have contributed seventeen and three-fourths per cent of the total amount.</p>
   <p>Tests taken at random, with the aid of detailed reports for thirty-eight different nationalities in all sections of the United States, reveal the fact that ten thousand individual subscriptions amounted to a little over one-hundred and five dollars per person.</p>
   <p>If this average is taken as a base, it is plain that those 741,437,000 dollars subscribed by Americans of foreign birth or origin, were contributed by 7,061,305 individual subscribers.</p>
   <p>Since the total number of individual subscriptions to the Third Liberty Loan is about seventeen millions, it follows, therefore, that the share of Americans of foreign birth or origin is about forty-one and one-half per cent. [A table follows showing the amounts which various nationalities have subscribed. The Germans are credited with $87,295,000.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
