<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1924-09-10">Sept. 10, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">The Necessity of Defense</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0085</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0085.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1924-09-10">Sept. 10, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">THE NECESSITY OF DEFENSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>There is not the slightest doubt that the United States needs a certain measure of national defense, because the fortunate geographical position of the country even if it is the best protection, is not sufficient.</p>
   <p>This necessary measure for the country's defense has been in very bad shape for decades; yes, it is even a tradition in the United States to arm only when serious causes arise. How costly such near sighted policies are, was shown in the Civil War. Also in the Spanish-American War to say nothing about the World War and the squandered billions. Short shift should be made with this tradition, because in a case of emergency it costs not only thousands of valuable human lives but it also unnecessarily demands great sacrifices from the country.</p>
   <p>Apart from the fact, that the United States in spite of its size and political position, does not play any role in the world, it must also be said that even its navy is unable to protect its extensive coastline in case of war. Then we must add to their burden the Panama Canal, the West Indian islands belonging to us, etc. The existing coast fortifications are scarcely sufficient for the protection <pb facs="5418474_5_0086.jpg" n="2"/>of the larger harbor entrances of the country. Protection against air raids scarcely exists, although this branch of defense is the most important. Even if we overlook the fact that the United States has no large army, serious thinking Americans must be alarmed by the absence of adequate coast protection by the navy, and of aerial defense by flyers. A glance at the map of the United States will convince even a layman, of the necessity of increasing our defense.</p>
   <p>Every one who is not imbued with the idea of world peace, and the phantasy of no more wars, must admit the necessity of protecting ourselves. Every sensible person should clearly see the path we have to take to realize the fulfillment of this necessity. If we consider what the aims of the National defense days are, it must be admitted, that the day belongs to that category of enterprises which remind one of cleaning weeks, 'better babies' days, and similar days, which have become the fashion in the last few years.</p>
   <p>As soon as the parade ends, the defense day is forgotton. What was attained? Naturally nothing, because a parade of hundreds of thousands does not build any aeroplanes, procure cannons, neither does it make submarines swim after having been treacherously sunk. The only thing that will be attained, is the expression <pb facs="5418474_5_0087.jpg" n="3"/>of the often documented spirit; "We can lick the whole world", a spirit which does not fit into a sensible and effective defense preparation. The United States imperatively needs a defense program, in order to put the country in a suitable defensive position, but they have no use for a noisy arming program, which could only serve for offensive purposes, if the noise was at all necessary.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
