<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-28">Aug. 28, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">German Veterans of Town of Lake.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1322</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1322.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1893-08-28">Aug. 28, 1893</date>.
<title level="a">GERMAN VETERANS OF TOWN OF LAKE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>p. 5 - The summer festival of the German veterans which was given yesterday under the leadership of the president, Ernst Reichardt was a huge success, thanks to the committee members. The imposing parade, which started at 11 A. M. at Ashland Hall, Ashland Avenue and 47th Street, under the command of the Veterans' Festival Marshal, Mr. Reichardt, revealed that this association, organized in 1886, was very popular even among the Americans of the Lake Town District. The parade was augmented by the following clubs and associations: General Edward Hatch Post #713 G. A. R.; General Edw. Hatch Camp #383; and all the members of the two Union Soldiers' Clubs, dressed in regular field uniform; the Association of German Companions <pb facs="5418474_5_1323.jpg" n="2"/>at Arms (Waffengenossen), Concord Council #41, Plattdeutsche Gilde Uhland No. 17, (Low-German Guild Uhland), the Sick-Benefit Club of Arnoldsville, the Bavarian Club, in National costumes, Hope Lodge #23, Order of Hermannsoehne, of the Town of Lake, the Gymnastic Clubs "Teutonia" and "Cleveland," also of the Town of Lake, the Song Club "Concordia," the veterans clubs of Chicago and South Chicago, the former represented by delegates. Particular recognition must be accorded to the American Veterans Associations which turned out in large numbers and made this parade a memorable success.</p>
   <p>The Bavarian Club furnished a splendid allegorical float and the crowd evidently appreciated it for it met with enthusiastic acclaim. The leaders of the parade were the aforesaid festival marshal, his adjutants, O. Liebetraut and G. Rickert, as well as the association's physician, <pb facs="5418474_5_1324.jpg" n="3"/>Dr. Schmidt, all on horseback. Ex-territorial dignitaries....from Texas and other states, rode in gala coaches as the guests of honor.... As a humoristic finale, very appropriate because of the oppressive heat, - the club's physician requisitioned the association's ambulance to follow the panting procession....</p>
   <p>Prof. Dillenberger's recently organized band, 50 men in uniform, and Prof. Bode's military band played marches....At the Park there was much gaiety, which characterizes all such German functions.......Julius Valentine, secretary of the Association of German Veterans made a speech in English, in which he thanked the Americans for their participation. He further assured his audience that if the occasion should arise, the Germans would fight shoulder to shoulder with their American fellow soldiers....</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1325.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>The most popular man, as ascertained by a secret vote, was Mr. Richard Meissner. He had a majority of several hundred votes and was given the gold medal.... The question of who was the most decorated and heroic soldier could not be settled soon enough to allow us to publish the name of the winner in this issue.....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
