<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-12-31">Dec. 31,1916</date>.
<title level="a">The Honor of the United States</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0460</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0460.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1916-12-31">Dec. 31,1916</date>.
<title level="a">THE HONOR OF THE UNITED STATES</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>President Wilson has changed his views about preparedness. His campaign speeches are different now. It must be admitted that they evoke popular approval, because they are more appropriate than his former talks, which revolved around the four monosyllabic words, "Too proud to fight".</p>
   <p>Whether his opponent, Roosevelt, with his copious supply of condemnatory phrases about cowardice, suddenly changed Wilson's ideas. or if the change is attributable to England's growing impertinence toward the United States, is immaterial. Possibly both have done their share. That Germany is not at fault is proven by its conciliatory responses to the unusual demands of the United States.</p>
   <p>President Wilson, in his speech at Cleveland on Saturday evening, declared that the public had imposed a double duty upon him, (1.) to keep the United States out <pb facs="5418474_5_0461.jpg" n="2"/>of the war, and (2.) to defend the honor of the United States. Possibly the hour may come, perhaps tomorrow, when these ideals cannot both be maintained at the same time; then honor must rule above all.</p>
   <p>These were splendid words, and more manly than "too proud to fight", but the deeds which might give emphasis to them have not been forthcoming. There has been a return to a policy of threats, threats invariably directed against one power only--Germany, a nation which even subconsciously has no intentions of besmirching our honor. The only governments which impose upon us are those of England, France, and Mexico. Will energetic steps be taken against these three miscreants?</p>
   <p>It should be unnecessary to ask what one understands by the honor of the United States. But in this age of slogans--just consider "neutrality" and "humanity"-- terms are stretched and twisted to an extent which confuses a rational mind and makes one doubt the proper functioning of his mentality. Take, for example, <pb facs="5418474_5_0462.jpg" n="3"/>Secretary of State Lansing's statement. On the subject of Americans murdered in Mexico he concluded that it behooves us to consider whether our countrymen were killed on land or water. We also have the recent assertion of a prominent solon who declared it does not bother him if his mail is confiscated; it does not, in his opinion, justify a war. These examples might be multiplied indefinitely, making selections from both the governing and the governed classes, to show the confusion which prevails even among those who boast of being first-class patriots.</p>
   <p>The revered, medieval belief evidently still exists that the flag represents the honor of the country. If not, then what prompts our schoolma'ms to induce flag waving among the tiny patriots? Is it to be regarded as merely an exercise in physical culture? Whosoever desecrates the flag insults the land. The flag is the highest symbol, wherefore the prudent English regiments keep it safely at home, to preclude the possibility of becoming imbued with too much enthusiasm and supermundane courage, upon seeing it. In American wars, <pb facs="5418474_5_0463.jpg" n="4"/>however, Old Glory always fluttered in the wind ahead of the charging troops. But nowadays the flag question here takes on an English aspect. We remain comatose if the Star-Spangled Banner of an American merchant vessel is torn down by uncouth, piratical British fists, but we show excitement and write reams of paper if a ship displaying the Union Jack is sunk by a German submarine.</p>
   <p>A private individual, like that Southern congressman, may well remain indifferent if his letters are stolen. But if the United States Mail is tampered with on the high seas, and even pilfered while the sacks are in transit to neutral ports, it is indeed a different matter from the honor of one man; it is then an affront to the nation.</p>
   <p>If an American soldier, in uniform, is deliberately removed by a French cruiser in the West Indies, there has occurred a flagrant disregard of our honor, because the American uniform is also symbolic. Yet such a viewpoint seems to be unknown here, as was illustrated by Judge Tracy P. Madden, of Yonkers, New York.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0464.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>In meting out punishment to a chicken thief, the judge offered the thief the alternative of joining the marine forces or going to jail. Secretary of the Navy Daniels, it is said, wrote an indignant letter to the crazy judge, telling him in no uncertain terms that the Navy was not to be used as a dumping ground for chicken thieves and other such people. But this disregard of the American emblem is by no means an exceptional case. Much ado has been made about the deplorable fact that in many circles civil attire is preferred even to the officers' regalia. Such practices as these do not support the present powerful preparedness propaganda.</p>
   <p>The most detestable and abominable vilification of a nation's honor's is the misuse of its hallowed flag, to perform clandestine murder, as in the Baralong case. If the Secretary of State dismisses this incident with an indifferent shrug and insinuates that it is strategy, then he will prove that a basic change has crept into our timeworn conceptions of the traditional Washingtonian era--that the beliefs of former leaders, like Lincoln, are outmoded.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0465.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>Do we regard it as honorable today, to use extreme measures against a friendly nation that does not care to be inveigled into further animosities, as it is already surrounded by a world of enemies and is in the throes of a life-and-death struggle? If we do not, then why rehash the apparently long-forgotten Lusitania affair? However, the Republic's most relentless foe and a bitter enemy since its birth, the kingdom that now ruthlessly destroys American commerce, treats the Stars and Stripes with contempt, robs governmental mail, etc., is treated with deference--nay, with resignation akin to fear.</p>
   <p>This is not the American way--at best it is English. May the President, who believes American honor is being sullied, express himself more explicitly in the future.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
