<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-04">Aug. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">The Rush Continues</title><title level="a" type="sub">Hundreds of Germans and Austrians Report</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1231</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1231.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-04">Aug. 4, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">THE RUSH CONTINUES</title><title level="a" type="sub">Hundreds of Germans and Austrians Report</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The war spirit in the German and Austrian sections of the city has not abated in the least. Men are still rushing to the places where they can report for service to their country. And it is especially remarkable that both young and old men are declaring their willingness to face the enemy--men whose term of service has hardly begun, and men who are already beyond the age limit. More than three hundred of the latter class alone registered at the German Consulate yesterday.</p>
   <p>Though the transportation problem has not yet been solved, it may be safely assumed that a large part of the armies which will undertake the trip to the old country at their own expense in order to comply with the mobilization order will sail from New York City, August 11, on the "Rotterdam". Reserve officers of the German as well as the Austrian army are included. The "Rotterdam" is the second largest ship of the Holland Line, and since Holland is friendly to the German nation, and since there is uninterrupted railroad service between <pb facs="5418474_5_1232.jpg" n="2"/>the two countries, the "American" armies should reach their destination without any delay. The plan to travel via Norway would not be as favorable, because the port of Bergen, where Norwegian ships unload, has no direct railroad connection with Drontheim, where trains leave for Germany; also, the trip from Bergen via water requires two days, and thus entails a considerable loss of time, aside from being more expensive.</p>
   <p>Today a reporter from the Abendpost discussed the question of safe travel on a ship of the Holland Line--that is, if there were any danger that such a ship would be captured and the German passengers be made prisoners of war, in case England declared war against Germany while the ship is enroute. According to international law, such a ship may not be taken if it leaves a neutral port prior to the declaration of war, and is not due at its destination until after the declaration of war. Then again, during the last war between America and England--more than one hundred years ago--the international rule was established that men may not be regarded as contraband. However, it was pointed out at the Austrian Consulate that rules are made only to be broken, that this is true also of international laws, but that, on the whole, the trip on the <pb facs="5418474_5_1233.jpg" n="3"/>"Rotterdam" would be the safest.</p>
   <p>An unexpectedly large number of men have presented themselves at the German Consulate during the last two days. After a comparatively quiet morning seven hundred reported for duty, and today the number of those eager to serve under German colors had exceeded sixty before 10 o'clock this morning. The present staff at the Consulate was unable to do all the work of interviewing the men and registering those eligible and willing to report for duty. Reinhard Scheunemann, secretary of the Consulate, who had left Chicago, was called back to assist with the work. And the pressure at the Austrian Consulate is even greater.</p>
   <p>Hermann Brandau, chairman of the Chicago district of the "1858'ers", worldwide organization of young businessmen founded in Hamburg in 1858, has invited his departing fellow members to a farewell party which is to be held at the Kaiserhof Hotel on August 6. It is likely that the entire local branch of the society will be present, since all of the members have decided to offer their <pb facs="5418474_5_1234.jpg" n="4"/>lives in defense of their country.</p>
   <p>Meeting at Germania Maennerchor Clubhouse</p>
   <p>Last evening, at the request of several very prominent Chicago Germans, a meeting was held at the Germania Maennerchor Clubhouse, to discuss the questions: How can the Germans of this city best show their sympathy for the German nation, which is fighting for its very existense? And how can they express their willingness to help the innocent victims of this war?</p>
   <p>It was decided that the first step would be to attend the massmeeting in which resolutions would be drawn up against the hostile attitude displayed by the English-language press, and to persuade as many others as possible to join in the proceedings.</p>
   <p>A committee consisting of Dr. O. L. Schmidt, Mr. A. B. Steffens, Dr. George Schmauch, Mr. Charles A. Wacker, Mr. Julius Goldzier, Mr. Arthur Hercz, <pb facs="5418474_5_1235.jpg" n="5"/>Mr. Theodore Kuehl, Mr. Carl Eitel, Mr. Leo Austrian, Mr. E. J. Kruetgen, Reverend H. O. Lange, and Mr. B. Balogh was elected to confer with the two committees in charge of the massmeeting with regard to some future meeting of Germans on a much larger scale. Such a meeting, as was pointed out by those assembled in the Germania Maennerchor Clubhouse, would through the great number of those who would attend and the great influence which they have, serve as a "backbone" for the German cause, and would provide the impetus for similar meetings wherever Germans are found.</p>
   <p>The establishment of a Red Cross fund was also discussed, and further steps toward its realization were left to the committee.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
