<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-05-07">May 7, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">On the Proposed Old-Age Pension</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1516</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1516.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1935-05-07">May 7, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">ON THE PROPOSED OLD-AGE PENSION</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The newspapers are giving a great deal of attention to the impending social legislation, and particularly the proposed old-age pension. The positions that they take on this question are as different as the interests which they represent. A few oppose the bills for the singular reason that they cannot see why the younger wage earners should have to contribute to the old-age pension fund. There is no point in paying any attention to these people, for they do not wish to give the aged any real claim to a pension, but instead offer them Government charity. It is clear that this Government charity would, in any case, be paid for by the taxpayer. One of the aims of the social legislation, however, is just this: to give the old people a legal claim to a pension.</p>
   <p>The only possibility of giving such a claim a real and moral basis is for people to contribute toward the establishment and maintenance of a pension <pb facs="5418474_5_1517.jpg" n="2"/>fund during the period when they are young and able to work. A person who has made these payments regularly has a legal claim to an old-age pension. It is insurance like any other. The only difference lies in the fact that it is compulsory insurance, but it must be compulsory in order to include all the workers and to make the whole thing a success. If the workers had to shoulder the whole cost of the pension the payments they would have to make would be very large. To avoid this, the employers, who reap no direct benefit from the arrangement, are to contribute one half of the necessary amount, leaving only one half for the workers to pay. Old-age insurance is handled in a similar fashion in Germany. There the worker pays one third, the employer one third, and the Government the remaining third.</p>
   <p>It cannot be denied that the proposed old-age insurance, in its present form, reveals a few serious defects. These defects do not seem very conspicuous, because Americans lack practical experience in these matters, and perhaps also because the states' fear of a possible encroachment upon their rights by the Federal Government may still prove an insurmountable obstacle. In former <pb facs="5418474_5_1518.jpg" n="3"/>times the Democratic party prided itself on being the protector of states' rights. Today there is not much left of this old principle. Perhaps it could no longer be maintained in the age of electricity, the automobile, the airplane, and radio. But the states guard the surviving remnant of their sovereignty even more jealously. With careful consideration for this independence of the states the plan provides that the pension legislation is to be enacted by the individual states. They can draw up the laws to suit themselves without worrying about the corresponding laws of the other states. By the prospective federal law the Federal Government accepts only one obligation, to double the pensions provided by the individual states, with a maximum contribution, however, of fifteen dollars per month.</p>
   <p>Thus there will be forty-eight different old-age pension laws each of which contains different provisions, and some of which provide for a certain period of residence in the state before a person is entitled to an old-age pension. Several states which already have old-age pensions require that the applicant shall have been a resident in the state for five, ten, or even fifteen years, <pb facs="5418474_5_1519.jpg" n="4"/>before he is entitled to a pension. In view of the tendency of our people to move around, and the great interchange of population between states, such requirements work great hardship. They also imply that the recipient of an old-age pension must continue to reside in the same state if he does not wish to forfeit his claim at least temporarily.</p>
   <p>Such laws are not suited to the modern age of the railroad, the automobile, and the airplane. Unquestionably it would be better if the administration of the old-age insurance were located in one central place, and if this central administration were responsible for the payment of the pension to all those entitled to it, all over the country. Then the residence requirements for old-age pensions might be eliminated, and the recipients of pensions would be able to move about without endangering their claims to a pension. Sooner or later the law must be changed in this way. Why wouldn't it be better to do this in the beginning and have an efficient procedure right from the start? This would have the further advantage of putting the pension system beyond the reach of greedy state politicians, and of keeping the recipients of the pensions themselves free of the patronage of corrupt politicians.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
