<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-23">Jan. 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[Case] Continued Until Friday</title><title level="a" type="sub">Socialists Not Yet Sentenced</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0251</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0251.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-01-23">Jan. 23, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">[CASE] CONTINUED UNTIL FRIDAY</title><title level="a" type="sub">Socialists Not Yet Sentenced</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The five Socialists, Victor L. Berger, Adolf Germer, William F. Kruse, J. Louis Engdahl, and Irwin Saint John Tucker, who were recently found guilty of conspiracy in connection with war activities by a jury in Federal Court, appeared before Judge Landis today. Their attorneys, Seymour Stedman, Swan Johnson, Cochems and Cunea, were to present arguments for a new trial; but Attorney Stedman asked for a continuance, and the hearing was postponed until 10 o'clock Saturday morning. He assured the Court that he would have the necessary documents for an appeal to the Appellate Court prepared by that time. He appears to be sure that Judge Landis will sentence his client, after refusing to grant a new trial. In that case, an immediate appeal will be made.</p>
   <p>The five who were pronounced guilty, especially Berger and Tucker, were evidently in good spirits, and Berger spoke of Karl Haessler, former Rhodes scholar and university teacher. Haessler appeared as a witness for the <pb facs="5418474_5_0252.jpg" n="2"/>defendants in the trial of the Socialists, and he is now serving a sentence of twelve years in the penitentiary at Leavenworth for refusing to serve as a soldier during the war because of conscientious objections. Berger said he hoped that Haessler, and many others who were sentenced for the same reason, would soon be set at liberty. He declared that as soon as Haessler was again at liberty he would be employed on the editorial staff of the Milwaukee Leader; Haessler had worked for that publication previously.</p>
   <p>Tucker has in his possession a number of copies of poems which he had written, and they were to be had for the asking. He said that upon being sentenced he will send a copy of his poems to Judge Landis. Tucker wrote them during his trial....</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
