<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1934-11-16">Nov. 16, 1934</date>,
<title level="a">The Bleeding Heart of Peace.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0061</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0061.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1934-11-16">Nov. 16, 1934</date>,
<title level="a">THE BLEEDING HEART OF PEACE.</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We do not dare to doubt the sincerity of the President's and his Secretary of State's sentiment. Both have declared repeatedly that they want strictly to observe this country's neutrality. They have continually repeated that they were ready to make any sacrifice in order to restore peace in Europe. Before such assurances, we must respectfully and humbly doff our hats; especially if we consider that the President has laid special emphasis on his oral assurances, or has he not displayed his feelings for neutrality, when he refused to see Mister Horace L. Brand, who wanted to bring him a petition of 10,000 German Americans? It must have hurt the President terribly to have been compelled to receive the representative of the best citizens of this country. But it is the obvious proof of his neutrality that he acted like that, and he brought the same proof, when he criticized Congressman Barthold, because he dared to open his mouth and speak in friendly terms about the Germans and even promised him an official censure. And we can understand, how the President's neutral heart was bleeding when Congressman Gardner in the House of Representatives stormed against Germany and Senator Burton loosed speech in Cleveland, which dripped <pb facs="5418474_5_0062.jpg" n="2"/>with hatred towards Germany. And we fully approve that he passed over these anti-German speeches in benevolent silence. He did not want to give them any further publicity. For the same reason, and only for the same reason, did he allow that noisy woman from London, Mrs. Parkhurst, to yell in Washington and allowed the English writers, to incite America towards a war against Germany. His neutral soul was bleeding, and his heart of peace writhed in pain, although the otherwise talkative lips remained closed. The whole misery of humanity, must have gripped the noble minded President in view of the fact that his people, whom he wanted to lead to the clean heights of statesmanly and human ideals, prefers to dance around the golden calf and instead of to the all bountiful Jehovah to bring sacrifices to the heathenish Baal. Tears stream through the answering telegram which Secretary of State addressed to the Oshkosh citizens. The citizens of Oshkosh, Wisconsin notified the President that a train loaded with arms and ammunition passed through Oshkosh on its way to Canada, and Secretary of State Bryan saw himself compelled to inform the Oshkosh citizens, who seem to have peculiar views about neutrality, and do not seem to appreciate the rise of American trade, but instead believe in the President and his high ideals, that if the cannons and other war materials were sold in the United <pb facs="5418474_5_0063.jpg" n="3"/>States by regular commercial treaty and had also been shipped, a breach of neutrality had not occurred. We want to make an end to the embarrassment, and the suffering connected with it for the President. The deplorable, because helpless position, of the mighty friend of peace in the White House, cuts deeply into our heart. And if only to make an end to this shameless derision of the President's wishes and to help him to realize his dreams about a genuine neutrality, have we arranged a mass-meeting to be held December first, in the course of which a resolution be adopted will request congress to create a law, that during the continuance of the European war, the export of all war materials should be prohibited. Only with such a law, only with such a means of power in his hands, will the President be able to realize his peace ideals. Is there a friend of peace, can there be a friend of Wilson, who would not welcome this movement with joy, and would not go heart and hand with it? In the interest and for the purpose of promoting the true neutrality of Mr. Wilson's advocated peace efforts, we request all German newspapers, particularly our Chicago colleague, the Abendpost to reprint the above article. The bleeding peace heart of the President shall be healed, the neutrality of the United States shall, in the noble sense of Wilson, be guaranteed.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
