<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-10-30">Oct. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[Vote for Democratic Candidates]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter to the Editor by Karl Schmidt)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0530</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.F.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0530.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-10-30">Oct. 30, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">[VOTE FOR DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATES]</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Letter to the Editor by Karl Schmidt)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Permit me to make a little contribution to the present election campaign. I am interested in it only so far as the Americans with German blood in their veins are concerned. Anyone who is familiar with American history will know that whenever the German element met with enmity and was persecuted, the Democratic party came to its aid and held a protecting hand over the despised Germans. I just want to remind you of the so-called Know-Nothing times. I could cite innumerable other cases in which it was always the Democratic party which acted as protector of the foreign-born part of our population.</p>
   <p>The Republican party is, in its basic conception, a party of zealots, of single-track world reformers and hypocritical money worshippers. Frequently the great Lincoln is dragged into the present election campaign; nothing suited the Republican party in 1866 better than his assassination, for Lincoln was the only obstacle which prevented the party leaders of that time from carrying <pb facs="5418474_5_0531.jpg" n="2"/>through their program of revenge and the subjugation of the conquered South. I have lived in the South for many years and have become familiar with its inhabitants. I have enjoyed their full confidence, and many a time the older people of the South have told me about the unspeakable indignities which they had to suffer--and by whom?--by the Republican party. All of them agreed that the war itself did not hold nearly as much terror and hardship as the period after it was ended. There is no room here to go into details about that horrible period.</p>
   <p>All I want to do here is to draw a comparison between then and today: President Wilson is asking the people to elect leaders who are completely sympathetic with his program for the time after the war, the reconstruction period. President Wilson is, in his heart, a friend of the German people, animated by friendly intentions, a man of high ideals, and a humanitarian. Only under his leadership, surrounded by men of like attitude, will the postwar period be bearable for the German-American element. All the infamous measures against the German-Americans did not originate with the President but with the Republican <pb facs="5418474_5_0532.jpg" n="3"/>minority in Congress for whose support President Wilson wanted to show himself grateful. A member of the House has told me so himself. I could say many things more in this connection but I have to close.</p>
   <p>The German element would only betray itself if it gave as much as one vote to the national representatives of the Republican party. Be on the alert!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
