<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-09-27">September 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">In Which Camp Does America Find Itself?</title><title level="a" type="sub">Editorial.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0645</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0645.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1915-09-27">September 27, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">IN WHICH CAMP DOES AMERICA FIND ITSELF?</title><title level="a" type="sub">EDITORIAL.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Chicago Daily Tribune, in its Sunday edition, published an article dealing with the foreign press. Under "foreign language newspapers" are understood all those printed in a language other than English.</p>
   <p>Such publications are considered foreign in America. That is a great injustice! <pb facs="5418474_5_0646.jpg" n="2"/>For none reflects the true picture of this republic better than the "foreign language newspapers". The contrary may be said of the newspapers printed in the English language.</p>
   <p>Germans and Hungarians, Poles and Czechs, Italian and French, Serbs and Roumanians, Russians and Greeks, will never disown their motherland, nor will they renounce their native language. They all want to become Americans, Americans in the highest sense. They want to be Americans in spite of their clinging to the mother tongue and to national habits, but they decline to become English.</p>
   <p>The English speaking newspapers of this country, have brought sufficient proof of their inability to liberate themselves from British tradition less thoroughly than, for instance, the German language newspapers to free themselves from German traditions.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0647.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The assertion that only newspapers printed in the English language are American is exaggerated. It is not the language in which a newspaper is printed, but the spirit that runs through its lines, that makes it American, therefore, most of the so-called American newspapers have not given the right interpretation to public sentiment, they were the least American. - The Tribune expresses surprise over the influence of the non-English newspapers during these critical times, although "The World's Greatest Newspaper" regrets that this influence did not always favor America and American interests.</p>
   <p>The accusation of the Tribune is justified regarding those foreign newspapers which were willing to be taken in tow by the Anglo-American newspapers, and, therefore, gave their services to English, French, and Russian interests and pursued a foreign policy in America. The German press of this country, especially the Illinois Staats Zeitung, has proved in the last thirteen <pb facs="5418474_5_0648.jpg" n="4"/>months, that not for a moment has it abandoned its American principles, even if such principles were to the disadvantage of Germany, therefore, the complaints against the Germany newspapers are becoming louder every day. The writers are afraid of the compelling truth which appears in the columns of the German newspapers; they are afraid of enlightenment, which strives to have this country ruled by American statesmen and in a truly American sense. They are afraid, that the German press may end the British rule of our government and that it may force our government to take less instruction from London and, rather, pay more attention to the will of the American people.</p>
   <p>The German press welcomed the proclamation of the neutrality of the President, while the hatred for Germany and the friendliness toward England, celebrated terrible orgies. Again it was the German press, which, in the sense of <pb facs="5418474_5_0649.jpg" n="5"/>George Washington, warned against foreign alliances, while the Anglo-American papers tried to pave the way for an American-English military alliance.</p>
   <p>It also was the German press which in the name of humanity and in the spirit of a true neutrality, tried to find legal ways to bring an embargo on arms, etc; while the Anglo-American papers fed its readers daily with English inspired articles.</p>
   <p>The Anglo-American newspapers, which even today, are unable to see that they endanger the best interests of this country when they, in direct contradiction to the word and the spirit of our constitution, are encouraging the President to create conditions on his own responsibility, which are dangerous for this country, now, and for the future.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0650.jpg" n="6"/>
   <p>The Tribune is right with its estimate of the surprising influence of the "foreign newspapers". This influence, as far as German newspapers are concerned, will grow. The more harm intended by the raging Anglo-American newspapers, so much more will truth related by the German newspapers be published.</p>
   <p>The people will learn where true Americanism is to be found, an Americanism which does not brag, but which is in earnest work for the truth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
