<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-22">Dec. 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A Costly Plan</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1526</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.D.2.c"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-24">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1526.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I H</item>
     <item>I D 2 c</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1934-12-22">Dec. 22, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">A COSTLY PLAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The special commission appointed last summer by President Roosevelt for the mustering of national resources to fight the present depression and to prevent depressions in the future, has summed up its work in a program which will be submitted to Congress at its next session. It would take a period of twenty to thirty years and the enormous sum of over one hundred billion dollars to complete the program. It provides for public works, the clearing of great areas of land which is now idle, the building up of the national forests, the elimination or at least the lessening of the dangers of floods, and similar large-scale projects which would provide years of remunerative work for thousands of unemployed. The authorities estimate that to carry out this program would entail an annual expenditure of from three and one-half to five billion dollars. These expenditures would be covered by a new reserve fund. According to the estimate of the authorities this fund would have to be set, provisionally, <pb facs="5418474_5_1527.jpg" n="2"/>at about ten billion dollars.</p>
   <p>It is scarcely to be expected that Congress will adopt this program in the form proposed. A sort of long-time insurance against unemployment will naturally be very attractive to the representatives of the people--for political reasons, if for no other. But if this insurance involves the expenditure of sums of which the average person can scarcely have an idea, it is, after all, a risky matter to vote for a project whose costs, in one form or another, will, in the long run, have to be borne by the taxpayer.</p>
   <p>The expenditures of our Federal Government are now far larger than its revenue. But if they are increased by several billions annually the burden of future deficits must finally lead to a financial catastrophe compared with which the ill-famed crash of 1929 was mere child's play.</p>
   <p>Secretary of Labor Frances Perkins is of the opinion that the costs of the program would be more than balanced by the fact that it would ensure lasting and remunerative employment "for every healthy man in the United States".</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1528.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>But as long as these costs are continually being placed upon the shoulders of the majority of the taxpayers, the danger exists that even their strength and willingness to carry this burden any longer will fail. What then?</p>
   <p>The commission was seriously endeavoring to fulfill its task. Whether the results of its work can be regarded as a specific remedy is still a question. The proposed plan has good features, but also bad ones, and the latter seem to be important enough to make it necessary for us to consider thoroughly all the details of the program before coming to a decision.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
