<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Sonntagpost</title>,
<date when="1934-10-28">Oct. 28, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Organization of German World War Veterans</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0059</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0059.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Sonntagpost (Sunday Edition of Abendpost)</title>,
<date when="1934-10-28">Oct. 28, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">ORGANIZATION OF GERMAN WORLD WAR VETERANS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From the Organization of World War Veterans the following appeal has been received by the Sonntagpost with the request to publish it. It speaks for itself:</p>
   <p>"Since 1928 there has existed in Chicago an organization of former World War veterans. All German participants in the World War, insofar as they saw action at the front or at least in the area of operations and there served their old fatherland, can be accepted. Enrollment is free, and takes place at the meeting of members who assemble every second Thursday of the month at 8 P.M., and every fourth Sunday of the month at 3 P.M. in the organization hall, Northwest Hall, corner North and Western Avenues.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the organization is to unite all former front warriors from the German army of the World War, to foster good comradeship, to aid in the <pb facs="5418474_5_0060.jpg" n="2"/>procurement of work, and to hold unconventional family evenings with dancing following the members' meeting on every fourth Sunday of the month at the hall of the organization. The monthly fee is rather low so as to make it easy for every comrade to join the organization.</p>
   <p>All comradesnot yet in the organization are asked to apply for further information to the business manager of the organization, Secretary Comrade Carl Eggert, 1936 Cornelia Avenue, or to call on one of the meetings named and be enrolled.</p>
   <p>With the salute of comradeship: Organization of German World War Veterans of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Carl Eggert, Secretary.</p>
   <p>The next meeting will be held Thursday, November 8, at the Northwest Hall.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
