<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-11-20">Nov. 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">British Shopkeepers Have Little to Cheer About</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0956</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0956.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-11-20">Nov. 20, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">BRITISH SHOPKEEPERS HAVE LITTLE TO CHEER ABOUT</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The British Lion has already lost a goodly number of teeth. It is only that one half of all the English officers now fighting in France--probably half of all officers Britain has altogether--have been killed, but even the British navy has "suffered heavy losses" although, as the First Lord of the Admiralty, Winston Churchill, confessed in Commons yesterday, the navy has not yet been engaged in a sea battle. This most arrogant of all arrogant Britons once coined the word "luxury fleet" when referring to the German navy. Judging by the complaints over their losses, the luxury, i.e., the expensiveness, seems to be indulged in by Britain. Even the Anglo-American press is beginning to realize that the prestige of the British navy has suffered a heavy blow, since until now it has not achieved anything outstanding. The British navy so far has lost 222 officers and 3455 enlisted men as casualties; 37 officers and 428 men are reported wounded, and 5 officers and one man are missing. These figures do not <pb facs="5418474_5_0957.jpg" n="2"/>include the losses sustained at Antwerp and during the sea battle off the Chilean coast, otherwise the number of casualties would have been increased by 1875. In addition to this confession of the loud-mouthed Admiralty chief [Churchill], there is another item. The battleship Canopus has disappeared without a trace. Since the sea battle off Chile Mr. Churchill has not had any news from this warship.</p>
   <p>Under such circumstances it is no wonder that the British cabinet is getting panicky. The Chancellor of the Exchequer had to admit in Commons that Great Britain's war expenditures would reach $2,250,000,000 for the first year; this is more than twice as much as the cost of the four-year campaign in Africa. The Chancellor announced a war loan of one and one-quarter billion and new taxes to raise another billion. In return for that, the British cannot point to one single success, but they have an abundance of fear, which they are trying to hide by adopting the "most un-christian" measures. To <pb facs="5418474_5_0958.jpg" n="3"/>accuse of espionage and to incarcerate persons with German-sounding names is the lowest and most despicable form of vengeance for the great disappointments which the shopkeepers have suffered through German efficiency and alertness. The whole civilized world will laugh at the story that fifty thousand German spies, or persons suspected to be spies, have been at large in England, and that only fourteen thousand of them have been arrested. The [British] Government is just trying to cover up their own inefficiency, that's all. The German Government had to resort to retaliatory measures. It is not that the Englishmen now living in Germany constitute a menace. Let them observe and hear all they can and report to London; it will do no harm. But in order to secure humane treatment for the Germans now languishing in English prison camps, the German authorities were compelled to arrest all Englishmen found at large on German soil. But the Germans will never forget the respect that is due human beings; the world may be assured of that.</p>
   <p>But this will not appease England's fury. The worst disappointment for these <pb facs="5418474_5_0959.jpg" n="4"/>scummy shopkeepers is the fact that the blockade directed against Germany hurts their own people as much as it does the Germans. That is why we see these arbitrary procedures against neutral shipping. With Turkey's entry into the war, the Russian grain supply is cut off, and if the Turks are successful in their attempts to occupy the Suez Canal, the island kingdom will really be in a fix. Perhaps their shopkeeper spirit would have restrained the [British] government from plunging into this war if they had not been so fully and firmly convinced that they could wrest Germany's entire world trade away from her within a few short weeks. This wonderful prospect was dangled in front of the shopkeepers as bait to make them "enthusiastic" about this war. In the ministries, this fairy tale was honestly and implicitly believed! But by now it has become obvious that a portion of the British textile industry cannot be maintained with-out German dye products, that chemical supplies are almost depleted, and that they cannot be replaced. Instead of taking over Germany's export trade as they expected, the customers of German export houses are telling these Britishers that the war has to come to an end sometime, and that then they would buy from the Germans again anyway. That's bitter medicine! The British shopkeepers really <pb facs="5418474_5_0960.jpg" n="5"/>would have gone to some lengths to steal the German trade. But it seems that in business, too, an unethical operator is despised: he who would fire his competitors warehouses in order to get his customers. But that is not beneath the British!</p>
   <p>Shopkeeper ambitions started to sprout over here too. But they have wilted just as they did in London. A Mr. William Dawson even wrote a book giving all necessary advice how to "catch" the German market. The instructions were not meant for the "Yanks," it is true, but the latter believed that what was good for the Britons was good for them also. But their hopes were soon dashed. The inexperience and the clumsy methods of the English, as well as those of the American shopkeepers, amaze us. Even the London Times had to call the whole thing off. They write as follows:</p>
   <p>"There is much talk about the opportunities, created by the war, to take over the German market. The territories which we will occupy with the help of our fleet, <pb facs="5418474_5_0961.jpg" n="6"/>will not remain in our hands once normal conditions have been restored. Germany has built up her trade honestly, by the knowledge, hard work, and intelligence of her business pioneers. Only by employing the same qualities could we hope to conquer and keep those markets." That's sensibly spoken! But the "shopkeeper-government" thought it could burn down its neighbors storage houses and then inherit his customers!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
