<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-11">Nov. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">What Otto C. Butz Has to Say [About the Armistice]</title><title level="a" type="sub">America's Triumph</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0499</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0499.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1918-11-11">Nov. 11, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">WHAT OTTO C. BUTZ HAS TO SAY [ABOUT THE ARMISTICE]</title><title level="a" type="sub">America's Triumph</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"As an American of German descent," said Otto C. Butz, president of the Friends of German Democracy, to a representative of the Abendpost this morning, "I am profoundly happy about the successful conclusion of the war. America's triumph means also the beginning of a new and greater development for the German people. I hope that Germany's change into a democratic state will be made in an orderly fashion. That is in harmony with the spirit of the German people. I believe that it would perhaps be best for the German people if a regency were established during the period of transition, until they get accustomed to the new order of things. As far as I know the Germans, a very liberal-minded monarchy with a liberal constitution would be the most suitable form of government for them. But perhaps the German people are ready right now to demonstrate that they desire and are able to govern themselves.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0500.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>"Solf's remark [Translator's note: Dr. Solf, a member of the German Cabinet at that time] that the Reichstag so far had very little to say about the government, and the frank statement of Prince Max von Baden [Translator's note: Prince Max v. Baden, Chancellor of the Reich at that time] that Germany will realize now that might is not right, demonstrate that America has assumed a perfectly correct point of view in this war. These statements also justify all that Americans of German descent, in agreement with the American people, have wished for the German people--those desires which now have been fulfilled.</p>
   <p>"The relations between Americans of German descent and their fellow citizens of other origins will soon be as friendly again as before, and no objections will be raised against the use of the German language in the press, the theater, etc., provided that it is used in a completely American way. Only that which could be interpreted as a separation of Americans of German <pb facs="5418474_5_0501.jpg" n="3"/>descent from their fellow citizens will be looked upon askance, but no fault will be found with anything that is done in the true American spirit.</p>
   <p>"I should like to impress on all my fellow citizens of German origin," Mr. Butz concluded, "the necessity of quickly restoring the former friendly relations and of promoting this objective, the necessity of active and organized participation in all American activities. It will be learned that Americans of German descent are always willing to co-operate whole-heartedly when the interests of their country, America, are involved, and that they do not consider politics from the standpoint of commercial self-interest."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
