<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-04-25">April 25, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">The Recruiting Drum Booms. Military Associations Grow Like Mushrooms. the German Americans Commerce to Be Active.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1307</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.D"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1307.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III D</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-04-25">April 25, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">THE RECRUITING DRUM BOOMS. MILITARY ASSOCIATIONS GROW LIKE MUSHROOMS. THE GERMAN AMERICANS COMMERCE TO BE ACTIVE.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>During the last few days, when the last vestige of hope for the preservation of peace was destroyed, the war enthusiasm of the American people mounted everywhere, ever upward like a magnificent brilliant flame, and as is to be expected, here in Chicago, preparations go forward with determination. For President Mc Kinley's first request, a contingent of 125,000 men is desired. Illinois is only required to procure six regiments and two battalions, i. e. about 8000 men, but it is expected that more troops will be needed later. Therefore the recruiting drum is beaten everywhere and the war loving youth gathers around the flags.</p>
   <p>In German-American circles, little interest has been shown, in regard to the Cuban venture, but since the die is case, the Germans are now eager to prove that if the necessity varies they are just as patriotic as the English-Americans. The Chicago Turn Association, one of the oldest and strongest organizations in the city issued a call to all its members and <pb facs="5418474_5_1308.jpg" n="2"/>especially those who are capable of bearing arms, to be present at the Northside Turnerhall mass-meeting, next Wednesday evening. There, the gentlemen Julius Goldzier, Harry Rubens, Emil Hoechster, Wilhelm Vocke, Theodore Brentano, Philipp Stein and others will speak on questions of the day, as they intend to start a German regiment that very evening. The recruiting will be under the leadership of Turner Emil Bloch, who tasted plenty of powder in the Franco-Prussion War; whilst here, he has been a member of the State militia, which made him familiar with our army methods. Captain Hotaling of the Logan Hussars, informed the Abendpost that he soon hopes to have his German squadron ready. On Friday, after his First notice appeared in this paper, 15 men responded, among them several cavalry men who have seen actual service. The German Press of the City also sent a representative to the war-contingent of the State, the reporter R. Liebrecht. He entered the cavalry division of the militia ten days ago, and Gov. Tanner promoted him to a lieutenantcy today. Even the veteran Wilhelm Reisenegger of the City Map Department, cannot find rest in this war tumult; Like Weiland the gruesome hero, who feels that the battle calls him. A counterpart to Hagan who found Volker, his friend; so also this Bavarian hero procured a comrade at arms, the aristocratic Karl V. Wolfskeel. These two, together with Mr. H. Aigner, <pb facs="5418474_5_1309.jpg" n="3"/>O. Klapper, Leopold Wormser and other former members of the German army, asked the Governor for authority to organize a German sharp shooters battalion. Their recruiting office will be opened in a few days. County Secretary Knopf, supported by his political friends wants to raise a volunteer regiment from the 13th, 14th, 15th, and 16th wards. For this purpose a meeting has been called for Wednesday evening at Wicker Park Hall. The 7th regiment of the militia is composed of the Irish-Americans and is ready to a man; it expects to a among the first to be called to the front, by Governor Tanner. At the regimental quarters, corner wabash and 12th Street, a departure festival will be held, tomorrow, Tuesday evening. Ex-Judge Prendergast's children will present the regiment with flags which their father procured for it. He will deliver the festive address, speeches are expected also from such well-known men as Ex-Governor Altgeld, Judge Brentano, General Fitz Simons, John F. Finerty and others.</p>
   <p>A list of Clubs(English, Irish, American) and names are appended of those who are helping financially and otherwise in raising and maintaining regiments.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
