<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1870-08-06">Aug. 6, 1870</date>.
<title level="a">Mass Meeting in Farwell Hall</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1393</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1393.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Illinois Staats-Zeitung</title>,
<date when="1870-08-06">Aug. 6, 1870</date>.
<title level="a">MASS MEETING IN FARWELL HALL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Persuant to an appeal published in the Illinois Staats-Zeitung yesterday, a large number of Germans assembled in Farwell Hall to express their sympathies in respect to the late events of the War. Despite torrential rains the large hall was well filled by 8:30 P. M. There was little time to decorate the hall appropriately, since the meeting was impromptu but the enthusiam displayed by the assembly made up for the lack of pomp and show.</p>
   <p>Mr. Claussenius called the meeting to order after the band had played "Heil Dir Im Siegerkranz" as effectively as was possible while 1800 to 2000 people gave vent to their feelings by thunderous applause. The enthusiasm evoked by the national song was a worthy introduction to the program.</p>
   <p>Mr. Claussenius stated that he had been requested by the executive board <pb facs="5418474_5_1394.jpg" n="2"/>of the Young Ladies' Society [? for the Aid of Factory Workers] and by the finance committee to call a mass meeting of German citizens of Chicago as soon as the first battle between Germany and France had been fought.</p>
   <p>"That battle has now taken place," he said, "and the Germans were the victors. Although it was not an important or a decisive victory, to us who anxiously followed every move made by our brothers on the Rhine, the news of this victory was prophetic--glad news which has awakened in us the glad hope and confidence that Germany will ultimately win the War. And our purpose in meeting is to give expression to these sentiments. Mr. Claussenius then made a motion to elect a chairman.</p>
   <p>Caspar Butz was unanimously chosen. He took the chair and made an address <pb facs="5418474_5_1395.jpg" n="3"/>that was very favorably received and loudly applauded. The text of Mr. Butz' speech follows:</p>
   <p>"On that memorable and glorious day--memorable and glorious because of the important steps we then took--on July 17, when we last met in the North Side Turner Hall, the mantle of the prophet seemed to have fallen upon me, as I read the message of German victory in your enraptured eyes. Germany has shown that she is not unworthy of the words of praise that we uttered then and the enthusiasm which all of us displayed; she has lived up to the expectations of her sons who are scattered over the entire world. 'Tis true, the victory was not a decisive one: the battle which will force the French back into Paris must still be fought. But it was a victory, a victory which created in us the living hope, the firm conviction that our former fatherland will finally <pb facs="5418474_5_1396.jpg" n="4"/>overcome her old foe, France--a victory that has dispelled from our hearts all uncertainity, all doubt in regard to the outcome of the War.</p>
   <p>"Germany has entered upon a dangerous and difficult course. Every report from our former country assures us that the Germans are well aware of the importance and the seriousness of the war which has been forced upon them. However, the joy of great confidence is tempered with that serious mood, and the certainty of ultimate victory with the knowledge of the importance of the conflict. Though the way lead over many rocks, through fire, bloodshed, death, and destruction, that it will end in victory, unity, and freedom for Germany is the hope, the firm conviction, of millions of Germans here and abroad.</p>
   <p>"The two centuries during which we, the slaves of Europe, sat within and performed the mental work of the world, have passed. Having conquered the world of thought, Germany now enters the material world to assume her position <pb facs="5418474_5_1397.jpg" n="5"/>among the nations of the earth. She has given the world enough men of great intellect, and now she is ready to enforce her demand for the material things of which she was unjustly deprived some centuries ago. In order to regain possession of the land which France plundered she is demanding that this stolen property be returned, not by uttering 'highfaluting' phrases, but, as becomes the nation founded by Frederick the Great, by resorting to cannon and bayonet.</p>
   <p>"This War is not only a battle against the Corsican who usurped the throne of France; it has a greater and much wider and deeper significance. Through the thunder of the battle on the Rhine we hear the voice of a united, greater Germany, and the blood streaming from the wounds of thousands of brave men is the bloody baptism through which Germany will be regenerated, will become free, will be united. Do not be deceived, my fellow citizens; that is the real significance of this terrible conflict.</p>
   <p>"However, since blood has begun to flow, let us not forget to perform the <pb facs="5418474_5_1398.jpg" n="6"/>grave duty which we once assumed. We vowed that we would care for the widows and orphans of the brave soldiers who sacrifice their lives fighting for the cause of Germany, and we shall keep that vow.</p>
   <p>For a long time there was doubt that war would break out. The Battle of Weissenburg has removed every possible doubt. That is the only importance which the news of this Battle has for some; but the majority of our great American nation received the news as the glad realization of a most cherished wish. The American people are on our side; they sympathize with the Germans, although they are aware that the latter are ruled by a king; they hope that the men who are fighting under the red and white flag will emerge victorious; Americans feel instinctively that liberty, civilization, and human progress depend upon the outcome of this War, and they value these essentials very highly.</p>
   <p>"Why should we care, even if a few people do deny what the whole world admits? <pb facs="5418474_5_1399.jpg" n="7"/>A few days ago some Danish citizens of our city held a meeting in which they expressed great fear that their beloved Scandinavia would be endangered if Prussia wins the War. Well, one cannot blame them, if their recollection of what happened at Dueppel prevents them from forgetting old grudges. But I appeal to you people from Schleswick-Holstein. You know that an effort is being made to bring Schleswick-Holstein under Danish jurisdiction again. Now, although I did not come from Schleswick-Holstein, but from Westphalia, for twenty-five years I sang 'Schleswig-Holstein. Meerumschlungen' [Schleswick-Holstein Surrounded by the Sea]; for twenty-five years I have shared the hopes of the people of Schleswick-Holstein that these two duchies would not be separated. They were German and they will remain German, an inseparable part of a united, great Germany!"</p>
   <p>After this address had been made Mr. George Schneider was elected vice-president, and Mr. C. F. Jung secretary. Vaas' Orchestra then played "Schleswig-Holstein <pb facs="5418474_5_1400.jpg" n="8"/>Meerumschlungen".</p>
   <p>[Translator's note: Reverend Hartmann, Mr. H. Michalis, Mr. Emil Dietsch, Mr. George Schneider, and Mr. E. C. Salomon also spoke at this meeting, however, they added no new ideas, but merely repeated thoughts which had been expressed by the first speaker, Caspar Butz. Therefore I did not translate their speeches.]</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
