<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-05-11">May 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">Truth Will Triumph</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Editorial]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0674</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0674.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1915-05-11">May 11, 1915</date>.
<title level="a">TRUTH WILL TRIUMPH</title><title level="a" type="sub">[Editorial]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Nobody will deny that the relations between the United States and Germany have been rather strained for months. It seems unlikely, however, that the Lusitania catastrophe will precipitate a complete break. The English [language] press of the country is trying hard, though, to arouse public opinion against Germany to a fever pitch. But it won't work. Chances are that after the first storm of indignation has blown over, common sense and an appreciation of justice will gain the upper hand, and the public will judge the entire situation from a more correct point of view than has so far been the case. In deciding the question of guilt, points and facts will be discussed, which previously were not generally known or were not considered important enough to bother with, or were forgotten in the rapid succession of events. The public will get a closer, more co-ordinated picture than the one they received during the first hectic days following the disaster.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0675.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The statement which the German Foreign Office has issued through the German ambassador in Washington will also help a lot. Of this statement it can be said that it did not lack clarity and succinctness. In brief words it expresses the profound regrets of the German Government for the great loss of American lives in connection with the sinking of the Lusitania, and then immediately goes to the root of all the trouble America has been putting up with, and places the responsibility where it belongs. "The responsibility," the German note says, "lies with the British Government which, by its policy of starving the German civil population, has forced Germany to adopt retaliatory measures". And that is it. That is the point which must be emphasized and must always be remembered. Because England, by instituting a war of starvation against Germany and cutting of all neutral trade not only from Germany but from Germany's neutral neighbors as well, was the first one to violate all international conventions. She arbitrarily vitiated all international rules and regulations. After England had done this and the neutral powers tolerated these procedures, Germany could not be expected to live up to certain other international agreements also found on the same page, for the benefit of her <pb facs="5418474_5_0676.jpg" n="3"/>enemies and to the detriment of herself.</p>
   <p>This is the most important thing we have to keep in mind. Everything else is secondary, convincing as it may be for the illumination of England's guilt and responsibility. And whatever we may hear about America's duty to preserve her dignity and prestige by demanding satisfaction from Germany, it is only half the truth or a distortion of it. For instance the English [American] press of our country, with all the signs of jubilant anticipation has repeatedly demanded that President Wilson should take some action against Germany and do so at once, because he had said that for every American life that was lost, the United States would demand the strictest accounting; now, in view of this mass murder committed by the sinking of the Lusitania, the President had to make good his word. But the matter is not as simple as that, because in the American note, which one has reference to, it says: "....if the commanders of German naval vessels should act on the assumption that the flag of the United States was used in bad faith, and should [in consequence] destroy an American ship or American lives, the United States <pb facs="5418474_5_0677.jpg" n="4"/>would find it hard (etc.) ... in that case the United States would be compelled to hold the German Government to strictest accountability...."</p>
   <p>In that case - that means if an American vessel or American lives should be destroyed on the assumption that the American flag was used with intent of fraud and an enemy ship was hiding behind it. Since the Lusitania was obviously a British vessel, it cannot be argued that the President should act on his promise, if lives were lost because of the sinking of this boat.</p>
   <p>Indeed, there is no reason whatever for anxiety and apprehension on account of this Lusitania case. The English [language] press will not succeed in inciting and hoodwinking the people by their yelling. And if they should, there would still be President Wilson, who will not let himself be influenced by these demagogic vaporings, but will keep the country at peace at all costs.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
