<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-06">Aug. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">"We, German Citizens of Chicago"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1211</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1211.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1914-08-06">Aug. 6, 1914</date>.
<title level="a">"WE, GERMAN CITIZENS OF CHICAGO"</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Chicago's German citizenry has spoken. In a dignified and inspiring mass meeting, held last night, Chicago's Germans made the cause of the German people their own. They expressed their sympathy and pledged all possible support to the German Reich and the German people, now fighting so desperately for their honor, for their "place in the sun," and for their very existence. Chicago Germans protested solemnly and energetically against a biased and unjust description and interpretation of the causes of this war, at the same time appealing to the American sense of justice and the American love of "fair play". They asked the Anglo-American public, whose good will they value, and the English language press, first to make sure and then to judge, and not to provoke controversies in America thoughtlessly. Being good American citizens, the Germans of Chicago appealed to the patriotism of their non-German fellow citizens, warning them that any degradation of German civilization <pb facs="5418474_5_1212.jpg" n="2"/>and culture, any defamation of the German nationality, which has contributed so much to the preservation and glory of the United States, would only result in evil consequences. As good American citizens and true sons of Germany, the Germans of Chicago expressed their gratitude to the President of the United States for having offered his services as a mediator in an effort to restore peace.</p>
   <p>It was an inspiring and impressive demonstration, of which the German citizens of our city can be proud. It will find a response wherever there are Germans in America, and they are everywhere. It will make an impression and bring good results. The words that were uttered here in Chicago yesterday will resound like a German bugle call throughout the country, and the voice of German-America will be heard. Yesterday's words will be taken to heart, and what German Chicago started last night will benefit the German citizens throughout this great republic.</p>
   <p>The German citizens of Chicago can be proud of their action, and Chicago can <pb facs="5418474_5_1213.jpg" n="3"/>be proud of its German citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
