<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1918-09-20">Sept. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">The Fourth Liberty Loan</title><title level="a" type="sub">Important Meeting of the German Department Called</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0343</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0343.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title><date when="1918-09-20">Sept. 20, 1918</date>.
<title level="a">THE FOURTH LIBERTY LOAN</title><title level="a" type="sub">Important Meeting Of The German Department Called</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Mr. Paul F. Mueller, chairman of the German Department of the Seventh (Federal Reserve) District for the floating of the Fourth Liberty Loan, has called a committee meeting for September 23 at 8 P.M., at the North Side Turner Hall. It is of the greatest importance that not only present members of the committee but as many volunteers as possible attend this meeting. The purpose is to complete the organization of the German Department, so that the work of floating the Fourth Liberty Loan on September 28 can start according to schedule.</p>
   <p>As reported, four vice-presidents have been elected for the Chicago committee, who have divided the wards of the city among themselves, thereby establishing North-Side, South-Side, Northwest-Side and Southwest-Side districts. At the next meeting a fifth vice-president will be present, who has taken over the suburbs, which,as everybody knows, have a large population of citizens of German descent.</p>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0344.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Each vice-president will appoint a captain for each ward assigned to him. The captain, in turn, will name a lieutenant for each precinct. These lieutenants will have the important duty of making sure, during the daily checkup, that every citizen of German descent gets full credit for each bond that he has purchased. But in order to facilitate this accounting, it is urged that there be enough volunteers to co-operate in a house-to-house campaign. For each ward, from two to five such volunteer salesmen are needed, depending on the number of residents of German descent in the ward. It is not necessary, but desirable, that these men be residents of their respective wards and that they have a large circle of acquaintances.</p>
   <p>It is expected that everybody who can spare the time, and has the inclination to do this kind of work, will be at the Turner Hall next Monday (September 23). These volunteers will not only do a patriotic deed for their country, but they will also fulfill a high duty to themselves and their fellow citizens of like origin. The more actively they show their loyalty, i.e., by not only purchasing <pb facs="5418474_5_0345.jpg" n="3"/>Liberty Bonds but also by making effective propaganda for their sale, the quicker the last traces of the suspicion will be dissipated which unscrupulous persons have instigated against citizens of German descent. It is useless to try to find out who is to blame for these conditions or whether or not the prejudice was justified. It is not a theory but a fact which must be faced. Such a situation can only be remedied by forceful and decisive counteraction. Every volunteer for the purchase of Liberty Bonds will help to attain this great and important objective.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
