<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-03-14">March 14, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Malicious Lies (Editorial about the Spanish War).</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_1316</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
                    
                    
                </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-23">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_1316.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Die Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1898-03-14">March 14, 1898</date>.
<title level="a">Malicious Lies (Editorial about the Spanish War).</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The President of the United States appears to be in a very communicative mood. Every newspaper reporter who calls on him or only reaches the ante-chamber becomes the confidant of all his secret plans and thoughts, so that every "large" newspaper can inform its readers, and explain exactly just what will happen. It is very remarkable however, that no two similar predictions can be found. Although they all drew wisdom from the same fountain, the news-gatherers give opinions which are so contradictory, that even the most gullible person has no confidence in their writings. Yes, they even dispute their own statements, since they do not adhere to them for two days in succession. For example, if one of the confidants declares today, in a manner that admits of no doubt, that the declaration of war against Spain is an absolute certainty, he will, on the following morning give detailed proof, that only fools can believe in the possibility of conflict. In both cases however he quotes the President with whom he is as familiar, as if they had been herding pigs in the past. As a matter of fact, the President quietly and patiently awaits the report of the Investigation Committee, which had the wreck of the "Maine" inspected by divers and upon their findings it is to be decided whether the unfortunate explosion was a matter of chance or if it may be attributed to crime. Although almost all reporters declare, that the explosion was on the outside, this is not definitely established by any means. If their assumption is correct, then the question still remains, whether the Spanish Government can be accused of official negligence, <pb facs="5418474_5_1317.jpg" n="2"/>which would make it responsible for the mishap. According to the view of the "Jingos" this is of course, immaterial, but the United States of America will hardly wish to create a precedent, which at some future time may be very disagreeable. If they take the stand that a government is responsible for every crime and under all conditions, when it is perpetrated within its boundaries by its citizens or strangers against foreigners, then they cannot ignore the demands which may be made against the United States on the strength of the foregoing sentence. If a crime has been committed and the Spanish Government is innocent, then one can request only the International "satisfaction", which it would give, without doubt. Even then, there would be no cause for war. The explosion then, will hardly lead to war. Whether the United States will have to end the Cuban war of desolation for other reasons, is a question which deserves serious consideration. If the "European Concert" considered itself justified in preventing Turkey from totally annihilating Greece, then the right of the United States of America cannot be denied, if it intends to prohibit the desolation of the island Cuba. If it is shown that the Spaniards are incapable of creating peace, without exterminating the population of the Island and its resources, then the interference of the United States may become a necessity. We are not only concerned with important commercial interests but it is evident that a prolonged war creates the inevitable epidemics which gravely on danger the American population. Of course, it is not the duty of the United States to support every real or alleged war of liberation but it cannot be claimed that is should look on indifferently, if within a few miles of its <pb facs="5418474_5_1318.jpg" n="3"/>shores an entire people are eradicated and a thriving country is turned into a desert and epidemic hatchery. If the neighbor's conduct endangers one's own home, then the right of interference cannot be denied. Of course, such an interference need not necessarily be a declaration of war. In spite of the rancous fury of the Spanish Jingos, it is unlikely that the Spanish people will devote their entire strength to a lost cause, and if one soothes their national sensitivity somewhat, then, perhaps it can be argued into desisting of its own accord. Whoopers do not want to know anything about a peaceful settlement of the difficulty and accuse our Government of cowardice, because it desires to reach its goal by negotiations, but their constant ranting has just about exhausted them and daily it becomes more difficult to mislead the public to a display of anger. The war must be prevented, as long as it can be prevented.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
