<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-21">Apr. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">Of Course!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5418474_5_0154</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-german"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-german #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-10-02">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-09-21">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5418474_5_0154.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>GERMAN</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Abendpost</title>,
<date when="1919-04-21">Apr. 21, 1919</date>.
<title level="a">OF COURSE!</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Editorial)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The sale of the Victory Loan is under way, and it is expected that the press, expecially the foreign-language press, and above all the German press, will do its best to explain the advantages of the Victory Loan and to recommend that everyone buy as many as possible.</p>
   <p>The American raccoon chooses the fork of a large tree as a place to sleep; he presses close to the trunk, and cannot be easily seen. Therefore hunters take keen-nosed dogs on "coon hunts," and the dogs bark when they smell a "coon". But when the trees grow close together it often happens that the dogs are sidetracked in some manner, and stand and bark before a tree in which there is no "coon". And thus the American proverb "barking up the wrong tree" originated. It implies that somebody is wrongly suspected, or that someone's endeavors are centered on the wrong goal.</p>
   <p>Americans of German descent will be reminded of this proverb when they are <pb facs="5418474_5_0155.jpg" n="2"/>informed that German newspapers have been requested to put forth special efforts to induce their subscribers to purchase Liberty bonds; for the proverb certainly applies to this situation. It may be advisable to use ballyhoo to call the attention of the general public to the significance and the value of the Victory Loan; and it may be necessary to use the foreign-language press to inform those among us who speak a foreign language, and are more or less foreign, of the extraordinary value of the Victory Loan, and to appeal to their patriotism. But when such methods are used in dealing with our citizens of German descent, and especially when the German press is requested to apply such tactics--well, that is "barking up the wrong tree".</p>
   <p>For, if actual tests can be taken into consideration, then American citizens of German parentage can claim to be the most loyal and most patriotic of all Americans, because their patriotism and loyalty have been subjected to the severest tests that man can devise--tests which no other so-called foreign element has been forced to undergo. But they have emerged victorious, refined, and strengthened; now they can well say that to preach to them, <pb facs="5418474_5_0156.jpg" n="3"/>especially, about the value of the Loan as an investment, or about their duty as citizens, is just as useless as carrying coals to Newcastle, or scattering sand on the seashore.</p>
   <p>One of the Victory Loan posters--it is very pretty, and the best one of all--shows a worker in overalls, thrusting his hand into his pocket and saying, "Sure, we'll finish the job". That poster illustrates our position. "Of course we'll finish the job!" American citizens of German descent, women as well as men, purchased liberally of the first two Loan issues, more of the third, and much more of the fourth. And they will buy more Victory Loan bonds, for they are better informed on their status, and on their duty to their country and to themselves; they know better now than they did six or twelve months ago, what they must do to improve their condition, and they know that the Loan which is being offered for sale now is better than any other investment.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
