<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Filipino Bulletin</title>,
Vol. I, No. 7, <date when="1934-04-07">April 7, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Quezon Stops at Center to Greet Crowds National Idol Returns Home in Blaze of Merited Glory</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Luis S. Quianio</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0444</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0444.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Filipino Bulletin</title>,
Vol. I, No. 7, <date when="1934-04-07">April 7, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">QUEZON STOPS AT CENTER TO GREET CROWDS NATIONAL IDOL RETURNS HOME IN BLAZE OF MERITED GLORY</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Luis S. Quianio</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Filipino Community of Chicago paused for a brief spell Wednesday, April 4th, and paid its respects to Senate-President Manuel L. Quezon and members of the independence mission. It was a great day for Filipinos in the city for the presence of the national idol even for only ten minutes made them realize that the long-sought and much-coveted independence has really come. They cheered the aging man who had to be carried through the winding steps of the Filipino Community Center, 837 N. La Salle St., up to the office and thence to the chapel.</p>
   <p>Thousands Keep Vigil</p>
   <p>The thousands of Filipinos, who kept the vigil at the early hours of the morning watching the coming of the conquering hero, stood at <pb facs="5427330_0445.jpg" n="2"/>attention and bareheaded as Quezon was ushered in to face the barage of photographers. He concealed his breaking health with smiles and in a few chosen words he addressed the anxious spectators. "My countrymen," he said, "I do not have much time to spare, but I am with you in heart and spirit."</p>
   <p>This was the laconic message, as laconic as Ceasar's message across the Alps, "I came, I saw, I conquered." History has repeated itself. For Quezon also came, saw and conquered. He got the Tydings-McDuffie Act.</p>
   <p>Arrived Early</p>
   <p>The Quezon entourage stopped only one hour and thirty-five minutes in Chicago. Arriving on the Liberty Limited at 8:25 A.M., the missioners were again on their way at 10:00 A.M. That was the first stop from Washington, and the trip is one long stretch from Chicago to Vancouver, and from Vancouver to Manila.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0446.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Quezon's Party</p>
   <p>With President Quezon were Senator and Mrs. Elpidio Quirino, and Antonio Quirino, brother of the senator; Rafael Alunan, former secretary of the department of finance and now president of the Philippine Sugar Planter's Association; Isauro Gabaldon, former resident commissioner and president of the Philippine Civic Union, and Representative Nieto of Cagayan, Quezon's personal bodyguard.</p>
   <p>Antonio A. Gonzales, director of the Filipino Community Center, and Mrs. Gonzales were host and hostess during the day. It was Gonzales who led the community's reception committee to the union depot and brought the party to the Center where a breakfast was to have been served but limited time prevented its execution.</p>
   <p>F. A. C. Queens</p>
   <p>The two queens of the Filipino Association of Chicago, Misses Pearl Nasberg and Vida Illiot stayed behind to receive the party at the Community Center.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0447.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>They were in charge of the breakfast arrangements as well as decorating the hall.</p>
   <p>The reception committee that met the missioners at the depot were Mr. and Mrs. Antonio Gonzales, Quintin A. Yumul, president of the Filipino Association of Chicago; Jose M. Albertson, president of the Pampaugan Circle; Lino D.Onagan, president of the Ilocos Nortenean Association; Rafael M. de Leon, former president of the same organization; Simeon Biason, retiring vice-president of the United Pangasinanes; Dr. Isidoro L. P. De Vera, president of Balagtas Club, and Mrs. De Vera; Anastasio D. Joven, president of the Ilocos Sur Club; Dr. Baltazar G. Raz, Dr. Serapion B. Ledesma, Dr. F. Hicaro, instructor in the Chicago Medical College; Larry Laureano, president of the Big V; Mrs. D. Onagan, social chairman of the United Ladies Club, Dr. and Mrs. Jose Zialcita Cailles, Baldomero T. Olivera, and Euginio M. Estacion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
