<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 10, <date when="1935-06-23">June 23, 1935</date><title level="a">The Phi Alpha Gamma Fraternity Filipino American Graduates</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Tiofilo D. Suratos</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0039</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0039.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 10, <date when="1935-06-23">June 23, 1935</date><title level="a">THE PHI ALPHA GAMMA FRATERNITY FILIPINO AMERICAN GRADUATES</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Tiofilo D. Suratos</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>An old adage avers that "a tree is known by its fruits." So man is known by his achievements or accomplishments. Introspectively, one might suggest, we are what we are now because of what we have been! To have achieved the award of a Diploma, the testimonial evidence, for proficiency in scholastic endeavors, and to be robed with the Toga, the symbol of matured wisdom, would mean the culmination of elemental factors--ambition, earnestness, struggle, sacrifice and perseverance---put together into one determined effort to succeed in betterment for oneself.</p>
   <p>The symbols Diploma and Toga, however, do not guarantee the assurance of success to its possessor in his future. To have had them is achievement enough to make one feel proud of himself for having "got there." The prejudiced <pb facs="5427330_0040.jpg" n="2"/>opinion against many Filipino college graduates, because of the fact that most of them have not, as yet, done or shown better results in the struggle for a living than those who have not passed thru the gates of a high institution of learning is simply borne of envy and jealousy. Let those who deny due credit to the college men show evidence of their own worth!</p>
   <p>The small number of Filipino graduates in Chicago have organized themselves into a brotherhood known as the Phi Alpha Gamma Fraternity. It is incorporated under the state laws of Illinois. It has for its primary purpose "Research Work" by its members. As yet, this scope of activity remains dormant. The Fraternity also awaits proper development to establish contacts before it creates its placement bureau. For the time being, it is functioning only socially, having its regular business meeting once a month, giving occasionally a lecture. The Fraternity has invited well known speakers and Foreign diplomats as its guest speakers.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0041.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Phi Alpha Gamma is going into the third year of its life and has just elected its new officers. It is the hope and the wish of every member of the Fraternity to have greater activity under the leadership of the new officers who are: Mr. B.V. De Vera, President; Mr. F. R. Villa, Vice-president; and Mr. M.M. Vergara, Secretary-Treasurer. The new officers are to be inaugurated in conjunction with the reception of the June graduates. The official members and the whole Fraternity seek the encouragement of their friends and public. The combined inaugural and reception will be a Social Dine and Dance at the International House, July 6, 1935.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
