<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 10, <date when="1935-06-23">June 23, 1935</date><title level="a">The Necessity of a Fixed Stand</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0442</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0442.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 10, <date when="1935-06-23">June 23, 1935</date><title level="a">THE NECESSITY OF A FIXED STAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The outburst of the Philippine Revolution was a result of a well defined and fixed stand taken by our people to liberate our country from the misdeeds and injustices done them by the Spanish administration. Although it was not enough for us to realize what they have achieves, still we can cherish and appreciate their meager accomplishments as a preliminary guide and incentive for us to fully realize our dream and aspiration for our country and people.</p>
   <p>The passage of the Jones Law in 1916 by the United States Congress pointed very clearly the road of fulfilling the coveted desires of our early leaders, and ever since very few of our leaders have worked vigorously to finish the job. The real cause for this is the lack of a well defined and fixed objective by which to guide our leaders. A minor reason is the egoistic motive of our leaders in putting first party interest, which is disastrous to our national cause.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0443.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Unless we will be able to cope with the situation in order to arrive at a definite objective, our party interest might rain everything. I hope this will not remain long as a picture of our political situation for our future generation, and I am wishing that all of our political and social leaders would ride together towards independence so as to end all uneasiness toward the problem and devote our time to education, economic and social reconstruction and towards a greater and more enduring Phillippine Republic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
