<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 15, <date when="1935-09">Sept. 1935</date><title level="a">Let's Be Prepared for Our Future Task</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0438</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.A.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0438.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>II A 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 15, <date when="1935-09">Sept. 1935</date><title level="a">LET'S BE PREPARED FOR OUR FUTURE TASK</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Very soon we will be a free and independent country. To be free is a great task. It demands the highest possible contentment in every sphere of life for all of us.</p>
   <p>To gaze at the moon does not make us astronomers. We have to do more than gazing to be astronomers: -we must spend several years of study of the heavenly bodies, through a series of strenuous training. Likewise, if we want to become good builders of our Philippine Republic we must train and prepare ourselves for the task.</p>
   <p>Do not believe in the common belief of our people that we have too many doctors, lawyers, teachers, politicians, etc. The real fact is that we have too many bookish people in every field of activity, but we have not yet produced the quality of men to rank with Edison, Newton, Lincoln, or Gladstone, etc. It takes years of labor in a suitable environment to produce such men. Now is the right time to prepare ourselves for any task that we could do for our future country. Great men of the nations in every age have given themselves to an undying devotion of love for their own native land. They have succeeded. They <pb facs="5427330_0439.jpg" n="2"/>have been immortalized, and the people of other parts of the globe held them up as examples in shaping the destiny of their countries. They have succeeded, and have reaped the noble contributions of the ages.</p>
   <p>If the other peoples of the generations before us have been greatly benefited by the experience of other people and were willing to take time to study to examine facts to construct something of their own, I think that we, too, should take time to prepare ourselves, before taking the saddle of responsibility for our people and country.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
