<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VII, No. 17, <date when="1936-08-15">Aug. 15, 1936</date><title level="a">Editorials Clubs No Longer Hold Weekly Social Dances</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0277</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-IV"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0277.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VII, No. 17, <date when="1936-08-15">Aug. 15, 1936</date><title level="a">EDITORIALS CLUBS NO LONGER HOLD WEEKLY SOCIAL DANCES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The campaign of the Associated Filipino Press and the Oriental Press against the practices of Filipino provincial clubs holding social dances practically once a week, seems to be heeded by the public, and nowadays one hardly notices any club or group of persons enthused over the prospect of holding expensive social dances in the loop which would obviously be a complete social and financial "flop".</p>
   <p>Height of Ambition</p>
   <p>In previous years or months, the height of ambition of any newly elected President of a club was to hold under the color of inaugural dances, impressive <pb facs="5427330_0278.jpg" n="2"/>and pompous social whirls, merely for the satisfaction of his false pride and vanity. He willingly appropriated much of his hard-earned cash for ballroom rental, orchestra and very little for publicity. Deficits were always, in many respects, the result. In him was quite apparent the stamp of the "social climber" and "sucker". He did not care how much he had to spend, as long as he was called "Senior President." Today, it is quite different. He realizes now that honey does not grow on trees.</p>
   <p>Those who used to pay $10 to taxi-dancers to have them for partners at social affairs will never commit the same folly again. They are now more thrifty than they used to be so that they can improve their economic situation. They no longer find romance and thrills in such affairs because the practices became common and ordinary.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0279.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Realizing, undoubtedly, the wisdom of the campaigns of the Filipino publications, as against the practices of previous years holding its international dinners in the swankiest hotels in town, Director Antonio A. Gonzales, of the Filipino Community Center, held the most recent international dinner right in the Filipino Community Center's Chapel. It was well attended by religious leaders in the city, representatives of foreign nations, and the press, and as a result, there was manifested amongst the diners a true fellowship which had never been equalled in past years. Financially, too, it was a success.</p>
   <p>Dr. Francisco M. Duerme, President of the Zambales Club of Chicago, in his official message to his members, too, emphasized the fact that as far as he was concerned, under his administration he would exercise and follow a more constructive and economical way of running the organization; furthermore, <pb facs="5427330_0280.jpg" n="4"/>he would discourage the holding of common and ordinary social dances.</p>
   <p>Generally speaking, it is apparent, today, that many farsighted group leaders of the Filipinos in Chicago will do away with wasteful practices and will direct their attentions and concentrate their energies upon policies which will eventually elevate the moral standing and well being of their fellow citizens.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
