<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 18, <date when="1935-10">Oct. 1935</date><title level="a">"Post Officials Were Installed"</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0399</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0399.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>THE PHILIPPINE MESSENGER</title>,
Vol. II, No. 18, <date when="1935-10">Oct. 1935</date><title level="a">"Post Officials Were Installed"</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Filipino Veterans of the World War, now in Chicago, who members of the Tomas Claudio Post No. 509, American Legion, Department of Illinois, installed their officers for the ensuing year, with a colorful program last Sunday evening, Oct. 13, 1935, at the Sky Ball Room of the Majestic Hotel.</p>
   <p>Commander J. R. Murphy of the Department of Illinois and his Senior Vice-Commander, Matt Murphy of Chicago Police Post, were introduced to the audience by Comrade Alex Arriva, Past Commander of the Van Buren Post, who at the request of Commander A. H. Dadoly of Tomas Claudio Post, took the chair and acted as Master of Ceremonies.</p>
   <p>Commander Sid Hilzman, of the Cook County Council, represented his County Legionaires. The Sixth District was represented by Commander, Wm. Collins, Sr., Vice-Commander Frank Prete; Adjutant, C. H. Gustafson; and Finance Officer, Louis Rosset.</p>
   <p>Other Posts of the Sixth District were represented by Harold A. Taylor Post No. 47: Al Mulcasek, Commander; Frank Prete, Past Commander.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0400.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Lincoln Park No. 481 was represented by Gus Kupic, Past Commander; R. E. Hickey; R. Aylward; Joe Bell; Joe Auer; Christ Ernest; and John Smide. Medill-Tribune Post No. 348 was represented by Frank Nessinger, Commander.</p>
   <p>Van Buren Post No. 401 was represented by Ben Kaufman, Past Commander; Alex Arriva, Past Commander; Al Stols, Past Commander; and a few more.</p>
   <p>Allied Post No. 226 by John Mikolajczak, Past Commander; Paul Capouski, Commander.</p>
   <p>Pioneer Post No. 768 by Phil Sullivan. Pulaski Post No. 86 by Louis Rosset, Past Commander. The Sixth District Auxillary was represented by Sussana Mindak, President; Helen Cipowski, Sergeant at Arms. Mrs. Agnes Mikol of the Allied Unit was with the Ladies of the Sixth District.</p>
   <p>The Commander of the Sixth District installed the officers of Tomas Claudio Post for the ensuing year. The following members were sworn into their respective offices with a brief speech by Commander Collins regarding their duties which they were about to perform: Jose Leonidas, Commander; S. Urbi, Sr. Vice- <pb facs="5427330_0401.jpg" n="3"/>Commander; S. del Rosario, Jr., Vice-Commander; T. Devera, Adjutant; B. C. Cas, Chaplin; C. de la Cruz, Sergeant-at-Arms.</p>
   <p>After the installation the dance followed and lasted till 1 o'clock Monday morning. Every Guest had his share of a real good time during the evening.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
