<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. III, No. 12, <date when="1936-06-07">June 7, 1936</date><title level="a">Our Community Today</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0106</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.B.2.g"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0106.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. III, No. 12, <date when="1936-06-07">June 7, 1936</date><title level="a">OUR COMMUNITY TODAY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The present Filipino Community in Chicago as compared to that of some years ago is very different. The difference is that every Filipino has lost his confidence. More emphasis is placed on politics rather than on education. The Community, at present, lacks the spirit of co-operation and appreciation of the Community Center which stresses education. The Community Center which has been the Mecca of all Filipinos in America has less attraction of late to draw the crowd. The Center is conducting many social activities with the aid of the various clubs, to foster education in general.</p>
   <p>Members of the Big V. house (which has become the palace of the Visayans in the near North Side at Dearborn Street) have been trying hard to keep up this monarchial residence. Every Saturday night a big entertainment is at the club house.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0107.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The 212 Club is also endeavoring to gain the confidential patronage of the local Filipinos. Bunco and dancing are always the main events housed at the club house. One of the latest innovations among the club activities is being fostered by the 212 Social Club. It has placed more emphasis on education rather than on pleasure. Lectures, illustration of current pictures and discussion of economic statistics are examples of its activities. No one can afford to miss them, yet response to them is not very encouraging.</p>
   <p>The recent social dances held at the Morrison Hotel sponsored by the Filipino Bulletin and the F.A.C., Ladies Auxiliary respectively are clear evidences of lack of cooperation on the part of our Filipino Public. I think the Annual Picnic will bring back that Oriental vigor, enthusiasm and hilarity because the change of atmosphere and surroundings is the most fitting background for the revitalization of the Community spirit.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
