<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. III, No. 8, <date when="1936-04-05">April 5, 1936</date><title level="a">A Toast to Dr. Placido Nebres</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0451</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0451.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. III, No. 8, <date when="1936-04-05">April 5, 1936</date><title level="a">A TOAST TO DR. PLACIDO NEBRES</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Within a few days, Dr. Placido Nebres is leaving Chicago, for the Philippines. The desire to see his folks and friends has actuated the Dr. to make this decision. After obtaining his degree, which was calculated to enable him to render better and greater service to his newly inaugurated Philippine Commonwealth, he will pack his belongings here and sail for the homeland.</p>
   <p>Dr. Nebres will be remembered here in Chicago, as a man, with a generous heart, few words, and plenty of action. He always minded his own business, earned his livelihood honestly, and upheld the traditions handed down to him by our heroes. He may be remembered, also, as a man with great tenacity of purpose and veracity of action.</p>
   <p>A story is current among his fellow-workers which runs thus: "Mr. Nebres, why do you work so hard?"</p>
   <p>"I want to give an equivalent labor for my wages."</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0452.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>While dining in a restaurant with some friends, who were inclined to talk about nothing, Dr. Nebres made this remark: "Better save your breath, brother, and close your mouth, so that you can preserve your energy and keep the germs from entering into your mouth." Whereupon, only sensible things were spoken from then on throughout the dinner.</p>
   <p>I heard Dr. Nebres say, while engaged in a round table discussion: "There is plenty of room on the top."</p>
   <p>Indeed, there is plenty of room on the top but only for those who are qualified to be on the top.</p>
   <p>When I asked Dr. Nebres why he did not associate with people more than he did, he answered, "I know how to do my duty to society. I converse with the great masters first." If I did not know Dr. Nebres as well as I do, I would say that he was conceited, but I agree with him that a mind, trained for reflection and deep meditation, needs plenty of time to commune with those whose life has been devoted to the discovery of more important things than just mere talk.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0453.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>There was a time when the Filipino Association of Chicago, Inc., was in dire need of finances. A meeting of the leaders was called upon to find ways and means to raise money. Dr. Nebres was among those who attended this meeting. An impassioned debate ensued and continued, for hours and hours, but Dr. Nebress already gave his cash. Cash was the purpose of the meeting, not arguments and Dr. Nebres was equaled to the task.</p>
   <p>It is commonly observable among people that men who have achieved nothing in life are inclined to pomposity and bragging. We have even in our Filipino community many instances of college graduates bragging about their diplomas as an indication of what they are supposed to know. Upon conversing with them, however, one will find such answers as, "I don't remember that" or, "It has been such a long time since I read that," or, if they attempt to answer, the answer is vague, if not misleading, leaving the inquirer in the dark.</p>
   <p>I have yet to discover Dr. Nebres engaging in such shallow vanities. Truth will out and Dr. Nebres has such simple ways. Great minds do not herald their accomplishments by a striking of cymbals. They will come on top,not by social trickery, but by wisdom.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0454.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>A great loss will be felt by the Filipino community, here in Chicago, due to the departure of Mr. Nebres, but a personality will be added to the honor and glory of the "Rajah Matanda" and the heroes of our Philippine revolution. More power to you, Dr. Nebres! Your ideals have performed their task here. They will always serve as an example for many of us here in Chicago.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
