<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VI, No. 5, <date when="1935-05-05">May 5, 1935</date><title level="a">Uprising Report Is Bunk Merely to Arouse Prejudice to Withhold Independence</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0132</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.C"/>
    <!--                        <catRef target="#grp-americans #code-I.C"/>
    -->
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0132.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C (Americans)</item>
     <item>I E</item>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I G</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VI, No. 5, <date when="1935-05-05">May 5, 1935</date><title level="a">UPRISING REPORT IS BUNK MERELY TO AROUSE PREJUDICE TO WITHHOLD INDEPENDENCE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In the opinion of the great majority of the Filipinos in Chicago, the "Philippine Uprising" which was reported by the Hearst newspaper in the most sensational fashion for which they are quite famous is nothing else but bunk.</p>
   <p>The greater masses of Filipinos, throughout the United States, from coast to coast, are of the above general opinion. All Filipino publications in America deny such reports, and the "Associated Filipino Press" wishes to be on record as one among them that brings to the American Public reports devoid of sensational colors and prejudices.</p>
   <p>We believe that the incident in Loguna Province, which was hurriedly flashed to the Hearst papers in America by A.P. correspondents, at Manila, was nothing else than minor labor trouble which brewed up amongst the "reds" in that particular section.</p>
   <p>Such incidents are similar to the many that occur these days all over the United States.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0133.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Such announcements that have no foundation should not be taken seriously. Let us all fully realize that there are always two sides to an issue.</p>
   <p>Granting that the reported uprising was projected against the New Commonwealth's governmental system, how could it be true when the people have not, as yet, finally voted upon the passage of Commonwealth constitution?</p>
   <p>The Filipino people have been taught how to sacrifice for liberty and independence. Inherent in their race are the qualities and characteristics of valor, courage, patience, and tolerance.</p>
   <p>For over three centuries they have struggled hard and fought bitterly endless and numberless battles, shedding their blood on the battle fields, in defense of their mother country.</p>
   <p>Under the American Flag they have learned that the greatest value of love and of country requires the education of the masses. Under the American tutelage, they have learned the true meaning of cooperation, within reason. Their loyalty to America has won for them the friendship of the American people.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0134.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Filipino people cannot afford to lose the respect and confidence of this great Republic. Neither are they willing to give up the blessings of liberty and independence which they are now about to enjoy as a result of the recent enactment in Congress.</p>
   <p>Such reports of uprisings in the Philippines arouse animosity, and to impress the American people that the granting of Philippine Independence by America, as passed by Congress, and approved by the President, was a mistake. The American people will know that such reports are false and that they have not made a mistake in taking the initial step towards granting the Philippines their independence.</p>
   <p>Francisco A. Lopez.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
