<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VI, No. 2, <date when="1934-12-30">Dec. 30, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">Pangasinanes Club Attracts the Biggest Crowd at the Sherman Hotel</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0343</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0343.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>I C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VI, No. 2, <date when="1934-12-30">Dec. 30, 1934</date>.
<title level="a">PANGASINANES CLUB ATTRACTS THE BIGGEST CROWD AT THE SHERMAN HOTEL</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Community Luminaries Present; F. A. C. Leaders Scored in Announcements; Times Editor Deeply Impressed by Courteous Attention of U. P. C. Officers and Members. By F. A. Lopez, Editor, Associated Filipino Press.</p>
   <p>The biggest crowd that a Filipino organization has ever attracted was during the Thanksgiving Dance of the United Pangasinanes Club held at Sherman Hotel, Dec. 2nd.</p>
   <p>From 8:30 P. M. until late in the evening, people in gorgeous attire, continually came in. It was interesting to stand for a moment in the lobby just to watch the throng of people getting into the hotel elevators.</p>
   <p>Impressed By Courtesy.</p>
   <p>The representatives of the Press were not required to pay admission. It was considered that such action set an example to all organizations which were ignorant of the privileges of the Press as a "public commodity".</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0344.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The courtesy of the U. P. C. officers and members, their unabated popularity, unity and cooperation, are considered the best factors that drew such a large crowd to its social affair.</p>
   <p>Luminaries of the community were there to grace the glorious evening. Among them were:- Mr. and Mrs. P. F. Manaais; Miss Selma Meyers, who was the Rizal Day Queen last year; Miss Vida Elliot; D. T. Duga, President of the Big V. Club; F. R. Umipig, President of the Zambales Club and Chief Executive of the Associated Filipino Clubs of Chicago; Mr. Jaramilia, President of the Postal Club; Q. A. Yumul, Contest Manager of the F. A. C. Queen Contest; Mr. and Mrs. Antonio A. Gonzales, Gen. Director of Filipino Center; Ernesto Ilustre, popular newspaperman; Jose B. Totaan, Associated Editor of the Times; Mr. B. Guinsatao Tobias, President of the Nueva Viscaya Club; and Julio Lorenzana, President of the F. A. C.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
