<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 21, <date when="1935-11-17">Nov. 17, 1935</date><title level="a">"Much We Have Yet to Learn"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0431</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0431.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>THE PHILIPPINE MESSENGER</title>,
Vol. II, No. 21, <date when="1935-11-17">Nov. 17, 1935</date><title level="a">"Much We Have Yet To Learn"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>We heard it said before, that the propriety of our action or speech must depend upon the proper identification of the nature of our purpose with respect to circumstance time and place. We often find ourselves to be doing or saying something, which, although right at a certain time and place, is entirely wrong or vulgar at other times and places. But how are we to know what should be right and proper? Our common sense should give us the right warning.</p>
   <p>The celebration of the Inauguration of the Philippine Commonwealth under the auspices of the Associated Clubs and the Filipino Association of Chicago, while it was a sound and patriotic purpose, failed to get the whole-hearted support of all Filipinos in this city, and had incurred a lot of criticism. Why? Because it was pre-mature. It did not satisfy the requirements of proper time. The motive behind the celebration given in such haste became a mooted question.</p>
   <p>What were the results of the affair? Just listen to the remarks of those who attended. Some said we had committed a grave social error that cause the <pb facs="5427330_0432.jpg" n="2"/>sudden and abrupt walking out of the consul from Spain and his wife. Others say the performance was very poor and the whole affair was a "flop". The faltering introduction of the Filipino Club presidents was not only unnecessary on such an occasion, but it showed the utter lack of good judgment because, while there were so many "chieftains" present, there were no members or followers to fill up the many vacant chairs and tables at the banquet. The clumsy way in which guests introduced showed cramped preparations and lack of poise.</p>
   <p>Did we gain anything good by the stubborn pretention of a minority at such a celebration of so national an import? Except for personal elation of a few, we gained only a blot of social error. We yet have much to learn and we can only learn not by the way of swelled arrogance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
