<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 12, <date when="1935-07-21">July 21, 1935</date><title level="a">Lend Your Support to Big V Clubhouse</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0286</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0286.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I C (Filipinos)</item>
     <item>I H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 12, <date when="1935-07-21">July 21, 1935</date><title level="a">LEND YOUR SUPPORT TO BIG V CLUBHOUSE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The F.A.C. Clubhouse had collapsed in 1932. The Filipino Town, another house for Filipinos, was opened last year by Filipino Brothers but it did not last long. Monagers of these two institutions gave reason that because insufficient funds, these two clubhouses had to close. However, the opening of the Big V Club, Inc., another Clubhouse, this year, at 1500 N. Dearborn Street gives us evidence for optimism.</p>
   <p>The Big V Clubhouse is entirely supported and managed by Filipinos. If the Big V Clubhouse loses its present character of stability, Filipinos alone are to blame. Believe it or not, our own race is going to be affected if this club fails. Our past leaders say that they have failed in their undertakings because of financial difficulty. They forget to tell us, however, that the management of the business is as important as the money. I think that it was the former rather than the latter which caused our club house failures. I can assure you that the Big V leaders are conscious of this fact and I have no doubt that they are not going to repeat the failures of their predecessors in the Filipino club world.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0287.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>If the Big V leaders are going to offer us all the benefits of their clubhouse we must disregard our petty prejudices and jealousies and join hands with them in stabilizing a Clubhouse which is dedicated to the honor of our own race. You alone, are the ones to answer this problem. It is no time for you to be selfish in rendering your service, your cents, and your share, to make your own race more honorable and more dignified by supporting and maintaining a Filipino Clubhouse that will be a credit to your race.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
