<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>.
Vol. II, No. 16, <date when="1936-09">Sept. 1936</date>.
<title level="a">"Megellan's Conqueror Is Honored"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0358</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0358.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>THE PHILIPPINE MESSENGER</title>.
Vol. II, No. 16, <date when="1936-09">Sept. 1936</date>.
<title level="a">"Megellan's Conqueror Is Honored"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Long live the memory of King Lapulapu of Mactan! Long live the memory of the man who paralyzed Spain's Imperialistic Policy!</p>
   <p>The Cebu Club of Chicago, under the leadership of Mac Hinoguin, led the way for the national celebration of Lapulapu Day at the Palmer House, on Sunday, Sept. 22. It was a great experiment. Money was spent lavishly in souvenir programs, stage entertainment, radio orchestra, etc. The whole Community turned out in a grand style. In part Mac Hinoguin explained the meaning of the occasion thus:</p>
   <p>"In this era of constant change nothing is certain anymore. New philosophies have arisen to augment the doubts wrought by the old ones. Peace is no longer peace; nations are always at odds with one another, fighting for peace. Uneasiness, suspicion, and hypocrisy predominate. The octopus of imperialsim with its perennial tentacles stands ready to strangle the world once again. Diplomats and scientists are in a hopeless chaos.</p>
   <p>The common man, who, by pure common sense or instinct, acts without the <pb facs="5427330_0359.jpg" n="2"/>cloak of hypocrisy and greed seems to solve our problems much more successfully. Beneath the tomb of Lapulapu lies the great lesson of nationality. We, who have followed his footsteps, can well afford to dedicate this day to his memory and to those who in the service of righteousness left all that was dear to them, to endure hardship, to face danger and their own lives that others after them might live in freedom. We who come after must see to it that their names are not forgotten."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
