<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 23, <date when="1935-12-15">Dec. 15, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">"Rizal and Filipino Unity in Chicago"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0365</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0365.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>THE PHILIPPINE MESSENGER</title>,
Vol. II, No. 23, <date when="1935-12-15">Dec. 15, 1935</date>.
<title level="a">"Rizal and Filipino Unity in Chicago"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Let us have one united Rizal Day celebration this year!</p>
   <p>I am nobody, just a humble citizen, and I am appealing to my fellow citizens, men and women, to reason together in the interest of a greater glory and prestige for our country.</p>
   <p>In observing Rizal Day, our only National Holiday of consequence, it is our aim to show to the races of mankind that we have a nationality and an individuality of our own. We want, also, to show that we are a united people not only in political aspirations but also in blood and ideals.</p>
   <p>Rizal Day is an occasion that calls for reverence, solemnity and sincerity. It is the day of all days dedicated to patriotism and love of country. Rizal sacrificed all, even his own life, in order to bring unity of his people.</p>
   <p>What we are doing in Chicago is a perversal of the aims and ideals of Rizal. Our community demands that we get together for the common cause and and the common good. Patriotism is measured in terms of principles.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0366.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Is there a way out of this Rizal Day mess? I ask this question in all sincerity. Perhaps, it is asking too much from my countrymen to do some real thinking.</p>
   <p>Let us all come down to an agreement. It may be a change for the better. Let a committee from the community-at-large handle the affair with the Filipino Association and the Associated Clubs and other unattached clubs breaking it up.</p>
   <p>What Apolinario Mabini said: (Dr. Jose Rizal follower)</p>
   <p>"I realize that the logic of events has led me to grevious conclusions; but I aspire to be a critic and ought to be faithful to the truth. Having written these memoirs with the sole object of seeking from the past the lessons most useful for the present and the future, I have tried to be impartial. Likewise, I have tried to criticize the facts, not definite persons....I am convinced that I have related the events as I saw them, and I saw them happen."</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
