<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VIII, No. 18, <date when="1936-10-01">Oct. 1, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Contests of Queens Declamation and Oratory End Soon Press Sponsors Voting</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0354</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.B.1.e"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0354.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 e</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VIII, No. 18, <date when="1936-10-01">Oct. 1, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">CONTESTS OF QUEENS DECLAMATION AND ORATORY END SOON PRESS SPONSORS VOTING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Associated Filipino and Oriental Press, under the auspices of the Filipino Association of Chicago, is conducting a Queen Contest, Oratorical Contest and a Declamation Contest all of which close December 20.</p>
   <p>In order to enter the Queen Contest, the entrants must have one hundred votes. The Press will print a ballot in every issue until the close of the contest. This ballot must be used for all voting.</p>
   <p>Any one can vote and any girl can enter. Send all votes to the office of this paper. The girl receiving the most votes will become the Queen of Rizal Day, the two next highest will be Miss Philippines and Miss America, respectively.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0355.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>December 20 (or about) Last Day</p>
   <p>The candidates will be officially presented at the Commonwealth Day banquet on Sunday, November 15. The Queen and her two Princesses, Miss Philippines and Miss America, are to be chosen on or about December 20, entrants will be admitted.</p>
   <p>Themes to be Limited</p>
   <p>Themes for the Oratorical Contest are to be limited to the subjects "Rizal As a Doctor," "Rizal As a Writer," and "Rizal As a National Hero." Each article must deal with one of these topics only. The speeches must also be original. If the editors find that any material has been copied from any published matter the writer will be disqualified. The talk should not be longer than five thousand words or fifteen minutes. All articles may be submitted to F. R. Villar, Contest Editor, in care of this paper. The Filipino Association of Chicago will award medals to the three who submit the best themes.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0356.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>The Declamation Contest will be on "The Last Farewell of Rizal." Both the Oratorical contest and the Declamation contest close December 20.</p>
   <p>Rules Governing the Contest</p>
   <p>1. The one who gets the highest vote in the final count will be declared the Queen of 1936, Rizal Day.</p>
   <p>2. Anybody is entitled to vote for his favorite candidate by using the coupon printed on the Associated Oriental Press.</p>
   <p>3. Mail your coupons to the Contest Manager, care of Associated Oriental Press, suite 615, 166 West Jackson Blvd.</p>
   <p>4. Ballot boxes will be opened only before the presence of the authorized representatives of the different candidates.</p>
   <p>5. Ballots will be counted before we go to the press - once every two weeks.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0357.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>6. The final day for the Queen contest will be on or about December 20, 1936.</p>
   <p>7. A grand ball will be held on December 20, 1936, for the benefit of the different candidates.</p>
   <p>8. Write the name of your candidate plainly.</p>
   <p>9. The chairman of the Queen contest is the Advertising Manager of the Associated Oriental Press, assisted by Mr. Rustico de Guzman.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
