<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VI, No. 2, <date when="1934-12-30">Dec. 30, 1934</date><title level="a">F.A.C. and Associated Clubs Pick Up Rizal Day Orators</title><title level="a" type="sub">Judges Find Orators with Extraordinary Talents Almost Impossible to Pick Ranking Contestants</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0374</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0374.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VI, No. 2, <date when="1934-12-30">Dec. 30, 1934</date><title level="a">F.A.C. AND ASSOCIATED CLUBS PICK UP RIZAL DAY ORATORS</title><title level="a" type="sub">Judges Find Orators With Extraordinary Talents Almost Impossible to Pick Ranking Contestants</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Filipino Gibbons Society Hall and the Filipino Chapel were the center of activity of the 1934 oratorical contests, at which orators were selected to speak on the subject "The Life and Works of Dr. Jose Rizal," Dec. 30, proximo.</p>
   <p>At Gibbons Hall, 1122 South Wabash Avenue, at 3:00 P.M., Sunday, Dec. 16, Mariano Cejalvo, was adjudged first place winner. He is to deliver the Rizal Day oration at the banquet and dance given under the auspices of the F.A.C., at the La Salle Hotel.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0375.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>G. Maglaya, 1933 Gibbons Society medal holder, was second; Martinez and Menor tied for third place honors.</p>
   <p>The Judges were: J. Churchhill; O.F. Taylor, Northwestern University (College of Law); and Miss Erna Layman, Yankton College, South Dakota.</p>
   <p>Out of the four contestants, Velez won the "first place" honor. He will be the Rizal Day orator under the banner of the Associated Filipino Clubs, which will sponsor the Rizal Day Literary Program and Dance, at the Steuben Club, Randolph and Wells streets, free to the public, on Dec. 30, 1934.</p>
   <p>The contest held at the Filipino Chapel, was one of the most exciting oratorical contests that has ever been held in the City of Chicago.</p>
   <p>Tambis was second, Pulmano third. The judges: Dr. F. Duerme, chairman; Attorneys, M. Moreno and Calderon.</p>
   <p>In both places, big crowds of people were present, including the partakers of the previous year's contests.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
