<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 16, <date when="1936-09">Sept. 1936</date><title level="a">Filipinos Must Prepare</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Daniel Dancel</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0150</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.F.5"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.A.1.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0150.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 5</item>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 16, <date when="1936-09">Sept. 1936</date><title level="a">FILIPINOS MUST PREPARE</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Daniel Dancel</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Within the next ten years, according to the Tyding-McDuffie Act, unless something unforeseen happens, the Philippines shall be granted their freedom. They shall then assume the role as one among the Independent Nations. Although our country is already in the making, we are, nevertheless, totally unaware of our gigantic task of nationhood.</p>
   <p>However, before independence comes, it is high time for us, the youths of our country, to be well prepared. It is important, therefore, that we train and discipline ourselves in the art and science of true citizenship. We must acquaint ourselves with the provisions embodied in the constitution of the Commonwealth. It is wise, also, to know and study the historic past of our country and people, thereby we can learn their success and failures. From the past, we may derive the greatest good for the benefit of ourselves and our children.</p>
   <p>We must realize that the destiny of a nation, whether it be great or small, independent or not, lies in the hands of youth. Our country is no exception. We learned from our past history that the "youths of yesterday" have done their best in shaping our future. Now our turn has come.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0151.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Senate President Quezon, in his message, inspires us to have the thought of our country uppermost. Now the acceptance of the Tyding-McCuffie Act, by the American government, has brought us face to face with vital issues. Now is our chance to scrutinize ourselves whether we have the capability to offer service to our country.</p>
   <p>Right here in Chicago is the best place for us to exercise and to prove whether we have the ability for leadership. Chicago is the only city in the Union such priviliges can be enjoyed. Here we have a miniature Philippines; we have a junior House of Representatives, a prototype of the Congress of the Philippines, wherein we could practice and learn the art and science of government.</p>
   <p>Let those who have shown themselves worthy, those who worked hard and succeeded while they were abroad or here with us adjust the pattern of our life. If we let go our chance now, if we don't advance in education we can never hope to fit ourselves for the task of taking up the responsibilities of the future new Philippine Common wealth.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
