<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Associated Oriental Press</title>,
Vol. VII, No. 22, <date when="1936-12-20">Dec. 20, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Filipino Center at Stake Gonzales on Trip West - Mrs. Akers Take Reiga Aspirants Seek Position</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0264</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.D.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0264.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Associated Oriental Press</title>,
Vol. VII, No. 22, <date when="1936-12-20">Dec. 20, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">FILIPINO CENTER AT STAKE GONZALES ON TRIP WEST - MRS. AKERS TAKE REIGA ASPIRANTS SEEK POSITION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A long and painful series of controversies between the Filipino groups and Antonio Gonzales, Director of the Filipino Community Center, culminated temporarily last week when Gonzales left for California on a leave of absence. Whether or not this unexpected decision was due to the consensus of opinion against the management of the Center, or whether this is just a pleasure trip, is not known.</p>
   <p>Mrs. David Akers, Associate Director of the Center, has now resumed the rigid task of Directorship. She emphasizes, however, that she will assume this position only until such time when the Filipinos of Chicago will find a suitable man to qualify as director of the Community Center or until the return of Antonio Gonzales.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0265.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Meanwhile the Center is being renovated and remodeled so that it will be attractive to visitors and kept on a standing level with other charitable institutions.</p>
   <p>The Filipino Community Center is a charitable institution supported by Americans interested in Filipino philanthropy, for the housing and maintenance of Filipino indigents. The chief contributors are Messers. Walter L. Templeton, George A. Chritton, Harold H. Rockwell and Mrs. George Wilson.</p>
   <p>All Filipino clubs and group leaders appear to be in a "semi-suspense" frame of mind and are discussing at their meetings the possibility of replacing another Filipino as director of the Center in the event Antonio Gonzales quits his position. Applications for the position are already pouring in by aspiring Filipinos who are urging the Board of Directors to consider their records and achievements as soon as the position is vacated.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
