<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VIII, No. 6, <date when="1937-04-11">April 11, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">Apology to the Board</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0262</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.D.6"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0262.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 6</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VIII, No. 6, <date when="1937-04-11">April 11, 1937</date>.
<title level="a">APOLOGY TO THE BOARD</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To the members of the Board:</p>
   <p>The Filipino people, I am sure, are a grateful people, and they are grateful to you for all the nice things you have done for the Filipinos. Whether they be at home or abroad, they will at all times keep in their hearts the memory of a fine fellowship with you, and the true American hospitality you have shown to them all.</p>
   <p>We, the Filipinos, do not know how to minimize your work in the Center. We realize the full value of what you have done for us, and all the many things that you intend to do for our good. We are sorry that the true meaning of what Mr. Thompson said at the meeting on your behalf was grossly misinterpreted and inhumanly published in a "thrash sheet" circulated in your beautiful city. That article, we assure you, does not constitute the intelligent interpretation of the thinking element of Filipinos in our humble community. It was a distorted misinterpretation <pb facs="5427330_0263.jpg" n="2"/>of facts brought unfortunately by a biased, disgruntled, bogus, peak-headed writer, who was a defeated candidate for appointment to the directorship of the Center. Harboring a grudge when he was not appointed, and under the influence of an unruly instinct, he resorted to writing such an insidious article.</p>
   <p>In our ways of thinking, he was not a sport. The majority of Filipinos, especially those in Chicago, know how to use "sportsmanship" in the right place and at the right time.</p>
   <p>When the Filipinos go back to their native land, we say in all sincerity, that they would go home with the best impressions of American homes and American institution!</p>
   <p>Again, we thank you for all that you have done!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
