<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl>
            

        </bibl>
     <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>, Vol. VI, No. 5,
<date when="1935-05-05">May 5, 1935</date><title level="a">Chicago Filipinos Speend More Than Two Million Dollars Yearly</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0298</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.B.1.c.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.B.1.c.3"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.A.1.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.D.1.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.K"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0298.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (2)</item>
     <item>II B 1 c (3)</item>
     <item>I A 1 a</item>
     <item>I B 1</item>
     <item>I D 1 b</item>
     <item>I K</item>
     <item>I B 3 a</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl>
</bibl>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>, Vol. VI, No. 5,
<date when="1935-05-05">May 5, 1935</date><title level="a">CHICAGO FILIPINOS SPEEND MORE THAN TWO MILLION DOLLARS YEARLY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Compiled very roughly, but conservatively. (Editor's Note: This is a result of a six months' close study, and personal observation, made by the Editor of the Press. While he does not claim accuracy over this report, he maintains, however, the opinion that his estimates come nearest to actuality than any of general scope so far published.)</p>
   <p>Look at the social calendar, of the 5,500 Filipinos marooned in Chicago, compiled by social experts or by the N.R.A. big bosses.</p>
   <p>Monthly Inaugural Dance.</p>
   <p>Reading, we see that social affairs of the community are compiled as far as February of 1936, however, mid-week activities are not mentioned. These social affairs are mostly inaugural dances of provincial clubs, and are booked practically every Sunday, at high class and expensive hotels, such as Drake, Palmer House, La Salle, Morrison, Congress, Sherman, etc., the provincial <pb facs="5427330_0299.jpg" n="2"/>clubs paying an approximate rent of $75.00 per night for each affair given. In my opinion, if a part of heaven is found in Chicago and God allows J.P. Morgan's descendants, or Andrew Mellon's proteges to hold social affairs in it, the Filipino leaders will break their necks and legs in their haste to rent such a place for their weekly affairs.</p>
   <p>Rough Statistical Estimate</p>
   <p>There are 5,500 Filipinos in Chicago. They hold social dances almost every week. One half of this number really are socially minded; they buy nice suits and pay their room rent. Some work in domestic places with free room, free board, and with "starving wages." Very few go to poolrooms and most are quite ambitious. There are many able to proceed to school rooms. Some are in business, while thousands want to be politicians.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0300.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Over 3,500 have hair cuts twice a week. A high class barber shop is being operated successfully by a Filipino on South Dearborn street. Some amateur barbers cut hair in dingy rooms, just to take care of their friends. Quite a number play horses, sicoy-sicoy, (Chinese game), and their loses in these pastimes, run quite high yearly. Some also take chances in buying smuggled sweepstakes tickets.</p>
   <p>A good number of artful romeos, (due to the lack of Filipino girls) lavish plenty on queridas, (sweethearts to you, if I may call them by that name, although I am not sure if this name is the appropriate one, for some of them have wings and fly from arm to arm as fast as the tick-tock of a clock.)</p>
   <p>More than 2,000 Filipinos use the phone, and most of them call their sweethearts three times a week, some every day. Some also buy flowers for their girl friends, not to mention the insignificant portion that buy dresses and shoes for the object of their affections.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0301.jpg" n="4"/>
   <p>Three thousands ride the "L" or street cars; some drive their own cars, spend much for garages, repairs, oil and gas, and incidently must also buy city and state licenses and pay taxes. An average of $25, every year, is spent by each of the 2,500 for jewelry (lowest estimate), and a good number of the Filipino population buy radios, furniture, and other articles which modern living demands.</p>
   <p>I leave to your imagination, the amount of money the dance hall enthusiasts spend, every year, for their fun and frolic, and that which they appropriate regularly before and after leaving the dance hall, to chop suey establishments.</p>
   <p>Because Orientals eat nourishing food, you will see in your roughly written statistics, how great the amount will be. Now how much do you think is left to spend for newspapers? And how much for contributions to churches?</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0302.jpg" n="5"/>
   <p>Now let's Get Down to Brass Tacks</p>
   <p>An average of 250 Filipinos attend the weekly dances at $1.00 admission, which means that they spend $25 per week, or $1,000 per month, that is $12,000 a year for that purpose. 125 (average) bring along their partners and each is sure to spend, roughly estimated, for taxi cabs, flowers, shoes, dresses, etc., $10, which means that 125 spend $1,250 per week or $5,000 per month, or in a year---$60,000 for this purpose.</p>
   <p>At least 3,000 buy three suits a year, at a nominal cost of $45 a suit, that is, each spends $135 each year, and the 3,000 buyers spend $405,000 a year for suits. Jewelry: An average of $25 (very conservative estimate) worth of jewels are bought by each of the 3,000 Filipinos or $75,000 is spent for jewelry every year.</p>
   <p>For Chirstmas gifts to blonds and brunettes, and also to the adorables left behind (P. I.) $10,000. Shoes, socks, underwear, shirts, hats, neckties, <pb facs="5427330_0303.jpg" n="6"/>belts, pajamas, bathrobes, overcoats, topcoats, powder, pomade, combs, shows, etc., $25,000.</p>
   <p>Room rent: 3,000 (average) pay room rent, the rest work in domestic places and have free room and board. On the average each pays about $4 a week for rent. Hence, $12,000 a month, or $48,000 is paid for rent by the 3,000 Filipinos. Food: An average of $25 per month for each of the 4,000 or $100,000 per month, or, $1,200,000 a year is spent for food.</p>
   <p>Phone calls for dates, parties, and for sweethearts, or business calls by 2,000 Filipinos each averaging 10 calls per month or 50 cents per month, or $12,000 a year for phone calls. Street cars, taxi cabs, telegrams, postage stamps and money orders-----$2,000.</p>
   <p>Billiards: about 1,000 shoot pool in a year, at an average of 80 cents per week, or $3,200 per month, or $38,000.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0304.jpg" n="7"/>
   <p>Barbers: Fifty cents for every two weeks, or $1.00 per month, and the 3,500 spend $3,500 per month, or in a year----$42,000.</p>
   <p>Sicoy-Sicoy, (Chinese game) Horse Races, Sweepstake Tickets, and other games of chance----$10,000.</p>
   <p>Dance Halls ("Universal banking corporation") of at least 500 night life enthusiasts, who are there night after night take up as accounts receivable an average of $5 per month, and such Banks have no windows marked. In other words 500 Filipinos spend $2,500 per month, or $30,000 per year for ball room dancing.</p>
   <p>Laundry, dry cleaning, pressing: at least each spends $1.50 per week, 3,000 Filipinos spend for this purpose $18,000 per month, or $216,000 a year. Schooling, tuition fees, text books, stationery, transportation, etc.-----$2,000. Rizal Day celebrations queen contests, banquets, picnics, monthly dues for club membership, etc.--$1,000. Total yearly expenditure by Filipinos of Chicago $2,026,400.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
