<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Associated Oriental Press</title>,
Vol. VII, No. 22, <date when="1936-12-20">Dec. 20, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Filipinos in States Hold Commonwealth Celebration</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Diosdado M. Yap Special Washington Correspondent</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0346</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.3.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.B.1.d"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0346.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 1 d</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Associated Oriental Press</title>,
Vol. VII, No. 22, <date when="1936-12-20">Dec. 20, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">FILIPINOS IN STATES HOLD COMMONWEALTH CELEBRATION</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Diosdado M. Yap SPECIAL WASHINGTON CORRESPONDENT</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Throughout the United States Filipino organizations have held social literary programs on the occasion of the first anniversary of the Commonwealth of the Philippines, Nov. 15, 1936. These celebrations no longer deal on the subject of independence but largely on the various aspects of future problems that the baby nation of the world will face in the next nine years of its probationary period.</p>
   <p>In the nation's capital, the Filipino community held a social-literary program with Atty. William A. Roberts of the People's Counsel as the principal speaker. Hardly a single government official was present at this celebration, not even a member of the Commissioner's office.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0347.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Other parts consisted of short remarks and musical selections by the community orchestra.</p>
   <p>Paredes, Jr., Sepaks</p>
   <p>New York Filipinos held two celebrations, one at the Astor Hotel at which place a dinner was given and the other at the Plaza Hall in Brooklyn. Quintin Paredes, Jr., was the principal speaker at the Plaza celebration. Similar celebrations were held in Chicago, Los Angeles, San Francisco, San Diego, Salinas, Seattle, Stockton, New Orleans and Philadelphia.</p>
   <p>On the eve of this historic day, the Commissioner's office issued a statement addressed to all the Filipinos in the United States in which it is strongly recommended that every Filipino must act as a committee of one to educate the American people to the necessity of continuing the trade reciprocity between the two countries. It is further recommended that <pb facs="5427330_0348.jpg" n="3"/>every Filipino must study the various activities taking place in the Islands in order that he can intelligently and reliably inform the American people of the truth of the various tasks and programs undertaken by the baby nation.</p>
   <p>Speaking of the Quezon administration the statement pointed out that "the Quezon deal needs the undivided support and co-operation of every Filipino everywhere." President Quezon has done his best to live up to the expectations of the people and stated that in order that he may carry successfully his constructive program of less politics out more government, the undivided support of every Filipino citizen wherever he may be is vitally needed.</p>
   <p>Governor-elect Frank Murphy did not issue any statement on the occasion of the anniversary of the Commonwealth. However, he has indicated that he will visit the Islands before taking his oath in Michigan by the first of January. It is also authoritatively stated in official quarters here that President Roosevelt may visit the Islands next year.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
