<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. 3, No. 9, <date when="1936-04">April, 1936</date><title level="a">Debate: "Resolved, That American Occupation of the Philippines has Been a Blessing to the Filipinos"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0111</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.B.2.g"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0111.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>II B 2 g</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>THE PHILIPPINE MESSENGER</title>,
Vol. 3, No. 9, <date when="1936-04">April, 1936</date><title level="a">Debate: "Resolved, That American Occupation of the Philippines has Been a Blessing to the Filipinos"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Filipino Community Center- Chicago. March 26, 1936</p>
   <p>(Conclusion, and part of the Rebuttal Speech for the Affirmative) by Miguel E. Alejado.</p>
   <p>Honorable Judges, Worthy Opponents, Ladies and Gentlemen:</p>
   <p>I have lucidly proved to you tonight that politically, socially, and economically, American Occupation of the Philippines has been a blessing: politically, because it had divorced the Church and the State, and had planted Democracy: socially, because it had secured and preserved for all the equal right to life, liberty, and property; and economically, simply because it had raised Philippine standards of living to unprecendented levels, actually unequalled anywhere else throughout the entire Eastern Hemisphere.</p>
   <p>Upon this bulwark of solid reasoning you have witnessed tonight the seemingly apparent ship-wreck of the Negative side; and likewise, perhaps how in <pb facs="5427330_0112.jpg" n="2"/>the oxygen of the inexorable reality which the Affirmative has presented...all of the Negative's fantastic theories about "originality"....and the utterly vain lamentations for the so-called lost Filipino freedom of individual and inner self-expression have thoroughly crumbled to pieces and have been reduced to more idle vapourings--thus rendered absolutely devoid of any validity.</p>
   <p>Now, my friends, I have outlined before you tonight some of the positive accomplishments which American Occupation has wrought for us. The outline may appear prosaic, as it is a tale of "common things;" but upon scrutiny, it will be found to include most of the factors which minister not merely to the material but also to the mental and moral progress and uplift of our people. Through American Occupation we, as a people, have come in contact with the best that American leadership has to offer, thereby enabling us to enjoy the glorious blessings which are indispensable to a vital and genuinely progressive national life....to secure and enjoy that which other nations and peoples had to struggle and fight for with their pen and blood. Through the superior guidance of gracious America we have thus been enabled to enjoy untrammelled the most hard-earned, most precious, and richest heritage of mankind with the least possible price and sacrifice on our part.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0113.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Is not American Occupation, therefore, a blessing? In all candidness, I again declare that it is; and he who, in this true light, could still dare affirm that it isn't, could only be either mentally blind, or else sadly dishonest.</p>
   <p>I need those who decry American Occupation...in the name of justice and common decency, again to consider the positive achievements which I have outlined tonight and then, in the light of History and Natural law set up those fantastic theories by blind idealists of what the outcome would have been if American Occupation had not been.</p>
   <p>Idealism is a beautiful thing...as a theme it lends itself to oratory and public acclaim; like emotion it is good, but not enough; and when the vital and serious issue of national well-being is envolved it is well to use a little common sense.</p>
   <p>Here ends the arguments of tonight's debate; and God forbid that my utterances have been to disparage our noble forefathers in their poor and unfortunate way. Far from it. As a pure-blooded Filipino myslef, I praise their glories, and my heart bleeds with every solemn memory of their bitter miseries. Notwithstanding, these, however, facts are facts, and for our purpose it is, always fair <pb facs="5427330_0114.jpg" n="4"/>that credit and honor should be given where they are due. For those in whose heart and minds still lingers the darksome doubt as to the ingenuousness of benevolent America, the answer is not far to seek--and if remember we must, then let us remember that as with individuals, so it is with nations: "By their fruits, ye shall know them."</p>
   <p>(Decision: Four to One in favor of Affirmative)</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
