<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 14, <date when="1935-08-25">Aug. 25, 1935</date><title level="a">Gonsalez' Membership Is Pending</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0385</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.4"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0385.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 4</item>
     <item>I B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 14, <date when="1935-08-25">Aug. 25, 1935</date><title level="a">GONSALEZ' MEMBERSHIP IS PENDING</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Director Antonio Gonsalez of the Filipino Community Center, who was once a member of the Filipino Association of Chicago, but who was expelled at one time from the latter for certain reasons, again applied for membership. Three months have elapsed since he had handed his membership fee in and yet whenever he attends the monthly meetings he speaks as a guest during the deliberations.</p>
   <p>Former colleagues of his, who were responsible for his expulsion from the organization, are opposed to his joining the group again. Director Gonsalez demanded an explanation for such a drastic attitude taken by his trustworthy associates, but they remained silent. It is their contention that Gonsalez, himself, ought to know by now why he is not permitted to join the Association anymore.</p>
   <p>The public, which is not informed of the history of the hatred between the old and loyal supporters of the F.A.C., might as well be told that in previous years Director Antonio Gonsalez took active part in controversies which brought about a division within the National Organization. In fact, <pb facs="5427330_0386.jpg" n="2"/>he played the leading role in bringing about the formation of the recently organized Filipino Associated Clubs, which have caused the power of the F.A.C. to decline in the Community.</p>
   <p>Since the F.A.C. had been deeply wounded indirectly as a consequence of Antonio Gonsalez's actions in the past, the member of the F.A.C. feel that his application for active membership is not welcome.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
