<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VI, No. 2, <date when="1934-12-30">Dec. 30, 1934</date><title level="a">Rizal Day to Be Better Observed by Filipinos of America Colorful Celebrations Are Planned from Coast to Coast</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0372</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.3.a"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0372.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 a</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VI, No. 2, <date when="1934-12-30">Dec. 30, 1934</date><title level="a">RIZAL DAY TO BE BETTER OBSERVED BY FILIPINOS OF AMERICA COLORFUL CELEBRATIONS ARE PLANNED FROM COAST TO COAST</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The 1934 Rizal Day will be well observed by all Filipinos of America and their friends. The National Holiday will be more pompous, more impressive and more colorful, than in the past years according to reports received at our Press Office.</p>
   <p>In Los Angeles, the Rizal Day Program Committees are determined to render Literary-Musical Programs, which will be unique and unequalled by presentations made in the past years. The Joint Rizal Day Commemoration, under the auspices of the Caballeros de Dimas Alang (Fraternal Society), with all the efforts of the Filipinos publications, will feature a Grand Reception and Ball, athletic competition, queen contests, etc.</p>
   <p>In New York City, under the auspices of the different Filipino organizations, headed, of course, by the Filipino Students' Association, a big program, at the International House, in commemoration of the 38th anniversary of the death of the most illustrious son of the Philippines, Dr. Jose Rizal, will take place. In Philadelphia, Washington, D.C., Seattle, Kansas City, and <pb facs="5427330_0373.jpg" n="2"/>practically in all principal cities in the United States, Rizal Day will be celebrated in an appropriated manner by Filipino communities of those cities, respectively.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
