<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 20, <date when="1935-11-03">Nov. 3, 1935</date><title level="a">"Michael Igoe to Address Banquet"</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0433</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0433.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>THE PHILIPPINE MESSENGER</title>,
Vol. II, No. 20, <date when="1935-11-03">Nov. 3, 1935</date><title level="a">"Michael Igoe to Address Banquet"</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>For the first time in many years 5,500 Filipinos in Chicago are united for a national celebration. Other Philippine organizations throughout the United States contemplated elaborate Commonwealth Inauguration programs. The Filipino Association and the Associated Clubs, in Chicago, united their efforts to stage an inauguration of the Philippine Commonwealth here on Sunday, November 3, at the Sherman Hotel, in the form of a banquet and dance.</p>
   <p>The Hon. Michael Igoe, present United States District Attorney of Illinois and formerly representative at large to the United States Congress will be the guest speaker at the banquet. Igoe was one of those who supported the Tydings-McDuffie Act which provides for the independence of the Philippines after a ten year transition period. It is expected that the District Attorney, a sympathizer of the Filipino cause, will give a hint as to the future policies of the United States toward the Philippines.</p>
   <p>According to German Maglaya, president of the Filipino Association, and Jose Albertson, chief executive of the Associated Filipino Clubs, invitations <pb facs="5427330_0434.jpg" n="2"/>have been extended to consuls of many countries. Included are the consuls of Spain, Mexico, Honduras, China and Puerto Rico. These consuls are expected to attend the banquet and dance.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
