<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
<date when="1936-04">Apr. 1936</date>.
<title level="a">[Dishonesty in Filipino Association]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0153</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.F.6"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.F.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0153.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I F 6</item>
     <item>I F 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
<date when="1936-04">Apr. 1936</date>.
<title level="a">[DISHONESTY IN FILIPINO ASSOCIATION]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Filipino Association of Chicago, Inc., has been in existence for many years. The Association was once a credit to the Filipino name. We all know the reason why it failed. Dishonesty in the handling of funds undermined the noble structure and with crumbling of its finances, the integrity of the club went down.</p>
   <p>The F. A. C. needs a leader who loves his country, proud of the Filipino name and, above all, revere the Almighty God. Francisco P. Gonzales is that type of leader. He is a very capable officer as shown in the manner in which he discharged his duties as president of the United Pangasinanes, Inc., and prior to this, as auditor and treasurer. He is sociable and believes more in action than in words. He is opposed to the buying of votes, because he sincerely believes that the F. A. C. will never progress if candidates buy votes to get into office.</p>
   <p>He is noted for his honesty in handling funds and in his dealings with members of our community. He has received many knocks but was never knocked <pb facs="5427330_0154.jpg" n="2"/>down, and always takes every knock with a smile. He is a very able man. Rest your trust and confidence in him, support him and you will have at the helm of the F. A. C. an energetic and level-headed leader.</p>
   <p>Vote to elect Gonzales for President of the F. A. C. Teofilo D. Suratos</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
