<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. III, No. 12, <date when="1936-06-07">June 7, 1936</date><title level="a">Editorials We Must Preserve the Virtue of the Brown Race</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Quintin J. Yaranon</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0104</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0104.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. III, No. 12, <date when="1936-06-07">June 7, 1936</date><title level="a">EDITORIALS WE MUST PRESERVE THE VIRTUE OF THE BROWN RACE</title><title level="a" type="sub">By Quintin J. Yaranon</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Filipino Community is the hamlet of a law abiding, peaceful and intelligent people. But it will be a disgrace if the brown race is to be known as a group of thoughtless and unappreciative living souls.</p>
   <p>We abide by the law; we live in peace; we act intelligently and thoughtfully; and we like and love America. We have a country to serve; we have law and order to watch; we can do whatever we please but it must be measured by the authority of what is right and is justice. An infectious germ is never welcome in any community, it destroys society.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0105.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>We must curb the current bad precedents made by our fellow countrymen. We must curb those of our race who insult the fair sex, those who are jealous of their more successful brothers, those who fight in public places, and those who steal. We must not let ourselves be chopped down to humiliation. As members of the majority, we are conscious of the fact that these undesirable parasites and crooks are destined to live in the "Big House". We are the mirror of ourselves. We can see how good or how bad we are when we are among the intellectuals.</p>
   <p>We Filipinos, as a group, must have far visioned plans to righteousness and justice. We must further conceive that only men of genius superbly equipped by nature could contribute to the progress of mankind.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
