<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>The Philippine Messenger</title>,
Vol. II, No. 22, <date when="1935-12-01">Dec. 1, 1935</date><title level="a">"An Eventful Night" by Mrs. M. M. Westing</title>.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0429</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.H"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-III.B.2"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0429.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
     <item>III B 2</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>THE PHILIPPINE MESSENGER</title>,
Vol. II, No. 22, <date when="1935-12-01">Dec. 1, 1935</date><title level="a">"An Eventful Night" By Mrs. M. M. Westing</title>.
</bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On November 17th, the United Ladies Club of Chicago, an organization composed of the wives of Filipinos, had a grand celebration of our Philippine Commonwealth at the Brevoort Hotel.</p>
   <p>The program was very short yet it was very interesting and very educational. Mrs. Fortunato Samonte, who acted as toastmaster, for the occasion, introduced Mrs. Guinn Gonzales, the president of the Club, delivered her welcome address in a very short paragraph, but she gave more emphasis and thought on the significance of the day. She said in closing, "We want to thank you all for your attendance tonight in making the Inauguration of the Philippine Commonwealth a great success."</p>
   <p>Mr. Antonio Gonzales emphasized also the need of a graver responsibility by every Filipino at such a time when the Philippines are about to become free and independent, and he also called the attention of the audience to the Honorable President Franklin D. Roosevelt, one of the greatest men of this Republic, <pb facs="5427330_0430.jpg" n="2"/>whose life will always be remembered by every Filipino, because he helped in fulfilling the dream of every Filipino patriot that some day the Philippines will be a free nation.</p>
   <p>The singing of the Philippine Anthem had added a new fervor for love of country, and the cheering by the crowd for a grand and more prosperous country awakened the rest of the crowd, who were very busy making arrangements for their dates, and the march showed a line of happy people filled with the spirit of the occasion.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
