<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VII, No. 17, <date when="1936-09-15">Sept. 15, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">Reflections of Our Readers</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0241</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.D.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.D.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.D.9"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0241.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 2</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
     <item>II D 9</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VII, No. 17, <date when="1936-09-15">Sept. 15, 1936</date>.
<title level="a">REFLECTIONS OF OUR READERS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Not long ago a society was organized by men of different professions and nationalities. The purpose of the Society is to promote a more friendly relationship and better understanding between the Orientals and people of other nationalities, and only thru mutual assistance and cooperation of its members can the Society protect their interests.</p>
   <p>The Oriental Aid Society, Inc., is intended to adjust and relieve the unfortunate situation of the people from the Orient. It aims further to lessen unemployment and sickness of the Oriental people and above all to offer them protection in case of accident or natural death.</p>
   <p>I wish to express my gratefulness to the unbiased sincerity of the founder or founders of the said organization. It is just timely that the Occidental and the Oriental should meet in common understanding in promoting a closer relationship by trying to help one another in all difficulties whatsoever. It is just fitting not to eradicate racial prejudice by establishing or creating means by which these two peoples could find a way out of the intricate characteristics of both.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0242.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Friendship, good will and peace among people of the world can be acquired only thru mutual understanding.</p>
   <p>It is my sincere desire that all Orientals thruout the United States and their friends who are sympathetic to the Oriental cause, join the Society so that the aims of the Society can be achieved.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
