<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VI, No. 5, <date when="1935-05-05">May 5, 1935</date><title level="a">The Press Is Not under the Associated Club</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5427330_0199</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-filipino #code-II.B.2.d.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2010-02-24">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2010-02-18">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5427330_0199.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>FILIPINO</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II B 2 d (1)</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Associated Filipino Press</title>,
Vol. VI, No. 5, <date when="1935-05-05">May 5, 1935</date><title level="a">THE PRESS IS NOT UNDER THE ASSOCIATED CLUB</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>"The reason why I haven't used the Associated Filipino Press during my administration," said Julio Lorenzana to the editor of the Press, "is because the Press is connected with the Associated Filipino Clubs, and its policies are under the whims of the big bosses of those clubs."</p>
   <p>For the information of the Filipinos in Chicago and the entire friends of the Press, throughout the country, the editor and publisher of the Associated Filipino Press wish to announce the following:</p>
   <p>"The Associated Filipino Press never has been and never will be under any particular club or group of clubs. It was not subservient to any particular person or group of persons, in Los Angles, New York, or Chicago, ever since its inseption.</p>
   <p>"As editor and publisher, I shape my writings and will continue to shape them, to further the interests and progress of the Filipino Community in Chicago. This is my policy for the last six years."</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0200.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The Code of Ethics of Our Press: "The foundation of our work is sincerity. We are honest in our purposes and in our writings. The dishonest thinker has no place on our staff.</p>
   <p>"By study and inquiry and observation, we constantly aim to improve ourselves, so that our writings may be more authentic, and of greater perspective and more conducive to the social good. Our employees are reasonably equipped to carry out their ideals. We are accordingly, the enemies of superficiality and pretense.</p>
   <p>"We maintain and fight for the liberty of the press, but we do so in such a way that we will not make utterances that show privilege. We do not make unjust attack on anyone. Within reason, we protect the rights of individuals. We deal with all persons alike. Mercy and kindness are legitimate considerations in journalism, and therefore, we will try to so conduct our publication, or direct our writings that justice, kindness and mercy will be exemplified in our work.</p>
   <pb facs="5427330_0201.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>"Believing that the best interest of society requires intellectual freedom in journalism, we will resist outside control in every phase of our practice. We will rise above partisanship, in our writings and publications, supporting parties and issues only so far as we sincerely believe them to be for the public interest.</p>
   <p>"We desire to be abreast of the best thought of the time. We endeavor to keep our writings in our publication free from unrefinement except so far as we may sincerely believe publication of such sordid details to be for the social good.</p>
   <p>"We will discourage and bar from our advertising spaces material which, in our belief, is intended to deceive our readers.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
