<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-06-15">June 15, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A Short History of the Douglas Park Christian Reformed Congregation</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0138</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0138.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-06-15">June 15, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">A SHORT HISTORY OF THE DOUGLAS PARK CHRISTIAN REFORMED CONGREGATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>In another part of this paper you will find the report that the cornerstone of the new Douglas Park Christian Reformed Church building, will be laid on Saturday June 18. We give herewith a short History of this congregation. Many of the members, who formerly belonged to the First Christian Reformed Church on 14th street, moved further West. The distance made the organization of a new congregation imperative. On April 19, 1899, this congregation was organized. A Committee appointed by the Classis, helped in the work. The brothers, R. Tinge, R. Dykhuis, and H. Bulthuis, were chosen as elders on that occasion. As deacons were chosen the brothers F. Brands, M. Hoekstra, and G. Slager. The consistory was officially installed by the Rev. Jriemersma. The first meeting place was in a store on 1732 West 12th Street, where services were held until September 24th, 1900. On September 17, 1899, the first Pastor, the Rev. F. Welandt, was installed in office, by the Rev. K. Kuiper. The congregation was incorporated by the State of Illinois on October 16, 1899. On March 5, 1900, ground was broken to commence building of a Church. On September 27, 1900 this building was occupied and put in use by the congregation. The Rev. Welandt preached a sermon at the dedication according to Genesis 28:17.... Since it's organization, the congregation has expanded from 21 to 81 families. The Rev. Welandt served the congregation for more than five years with visible blessing. On December 17, 1905, Rev. 1. de Leeuw <pb facs="5420781_2_0139.jpg" n="2"/>was installed in his official capacity, by Rev. I. Fles. Eagerly and industriously, the Rev. de Leeuw worked among the congregation for a period of five years. The Rev. Manni, shortly thereafter accepted the call, and on August 21, 1910, he was officially connected with the congregation. Rev. Manni also worked with visible blessings among the congregation. After six years of service this servant of the Lord, also left our congregation. In 1917, the Rev. J. O. Vos came to us and after 10 years of labor, richly blessed, he left the congregation on 1926.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
