<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1913-02-07">Feb. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">Colonization</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0062</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0062.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1913-02-07">Feb. 7, 1913</date>.
<title level="a">COLONIZATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>To The Editor of Onze Toekomst:</p>
   <p>Please allow me some space for this letter in your paper.</p>
   <p>The readers remember that during the year 1912 the undersigned gave, when in charge of the Chicago-Section of the General Netherlands' League, a reading on the subject of colonization.</p>
   <p>Later on, these articles were published in the weekly Onze Toekomst. From different sides assurances of agreement were received. But, as it so often happens, there was nothing more heard about the affair. Later on the silence was broken again by Mr. S. E., who in the same manner wrote an article on this subject in Onze Toekomst, Since then however, nothing more was heard, and it seemed as if this matter had come to an end. This, however was not the case. For a long time people were working on the matter, and at present things have come to such a pass that they must be laid before the public.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0063.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It was Mr. J. Berghuis, well known by our Dutch people, who started the event again. More than three months ago Mr. Berghuis asked me to assist him in the placing of a Dutch settlement in one of the States of our Union or in neighboring Canada, in other words, to set up together an agency for a new settlement.</p>
   <p>Upon this I gave a negative answer, but, because he insisted, I promised to take the matter into consideration and assured him I would let him know about it in a couple of days. And that happened. I told him that I had determined to participate in the matter if we worked for the purpose mentioned in the article about this cause.</p>
   <p>Naturally some difficulties were connected with this event. With this purpose in view each offers of Land Companies were rejected. It was also impossible to avoid some expense. Yet these difficulties were not insurmountable, and at present we have come to the point where we can offer the public a plan and also a proposition.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0064.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Friday evening, February 14th, all people interested are invited to come together in Soustek's Hall, at the corner of Laflin and 18th Streets, where all information can be obtained and definite precautions taken. However, I hope to give more definite information about the enterprise in another number of Onze Toekomst.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
