<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1921-05-13">May 13, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">Support for Widows, Fatherless Children and Families in Need.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0042</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.D.10"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0042.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1921-05-13">May 13, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">SUPPORT FOR WIDOWS, FATHERLESS CHILDREN AND FAMILIES IN NEED.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>From an examination of the statistics of the juvenile Court of Cook County, it appears that very few Dutch mothers, who are widows or whose husbands are unable to work, make use in Chicago of the support offered by the State of Illinois in such emergencies. For this reason a short announcement about this can be of service. Evidently in this State many Dutch widows with children do not know of the monetary assistance which they have a right to expect. Naturally each case is conditional. In June, 1913, the following law was enacted:</p>
   <p>A law to care partially for mothers, whose husbands are dead or are forever unable to work on account of bodily or spiritual blemishes, when such mothers have children below the age of 14, and are citizens of the United States of America and inhabitants of the county in which application for help is made... It was indeed interesting to look over the statistics. But it was remarkable how few Dutch ask for help of the County. Some of the other nationalities were represented in large numbers in the statistics of Charity.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
