<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1908-12-25">Dec. 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">Christian Celebration</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0122</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.B.3.b"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.B.4"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0122.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 3 b</item>
     <item>I B 4</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1908-12-25">Dec. 25, 1908</date>.
<title level="a">CHRISTIAN CELEBRATION</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It is remarkable how little attention generally is given to the literal meaning of Christmas, although the celebration of that day is universal among all nations.</p>
   <p>In many cases the celebration of the day, ends in sinful and insipid amusements, while they forget, "The Child of Bethlehem".</p>
   <p>Especially in our country, where people are observing or having Christmas mingled with St. Nicholas, in consequence that Christ, whose birthday we are celebrating is lowered to an imaginary Santa-Claus.</p>
   <p>There is no harm in giving presents and in fixing up a Christmas tree, but people are taking a risk by seeing in these worthless things of high value, through which Christmas is loosing altogether its religious meaning.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0123.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>But in spite of all, this day of rejoicing is for the Christ worshippers a feast of excellence, the feast of all feast, the birth of God's word becoming flesh, from whom the Evangelist testifies: "Thus God has loved the world, and has given his only, begotten son, so he, who believes in Christ, is not doomed, but shall have eternal life".</p>
   <p>It is not the birthday of a human being, but the Son of God, "Jesus Christ".</p>
   <p>For that reason Christmas is not an ordinary holiday. It is not for the follower of Christ, another free day, which is spent with eating and drinking, with giving and receiving of presents, which cause false flattery and thanksgivings, but a day when the Light of the world appears through all ages, in spite of resistance and persecution of Satan and his companions, has brought enlightment to the nations of the earth, and has showed to be a light of enlightment to the heathens, and to the gloriousness of the people of "Israel".</p>
   <p>The coming of Christ in the flesh is the most important event in the history of humanity.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0124.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>His arrival was preached by the poets,, sang by the angels, but nevertheless, misunderstood by all, because it is the miracle of miracles. God became man, as any of us, "born from a woman, origined under the law".</p>
   <p>A Christmas without Christ, is a world wothout light, a life wothout hope. It is just for that reason, why the Satan does everything, that is in his power to take away Christmas gospel from the Christmas celebration, and to put something else in its place. That is why the multitude of those, who hate the Cross of Christ, are doing their best to forget the real meaning of the day, and to show us misery and depravity. Naturally, people are still singing, "The Child in the manger", but does everybody mean "The Saviour, who is Christ the Lord", as was announced,by the Angels?</p>
   <p>The history of Christmas is so simple, and beautiful. "Glory to God in the highest heavens, peace to the people on earth!" But is not that story simple, the way it is told by the Evangelist, without any affectation, without any idea of fear over sensibilities? Simple, beautiful, but majestic.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
