<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Year Book of the Holland Society of Chicago</title>, 1897, 1898, 1899, 1900 Published by direction of the Board of Trustees, Compiled by the Secretary B. T. Van Alen,
<date when="1901-03">March, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">A Resolution Made by the Holland Society of Chicago</title>. p. 69.

        </bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0077</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.B.1"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0077.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 1</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Year Book of The Holland Society of Chicago</title>, 1897,1898,1899,1900 Published by direction of the Board of Trustees, Compiled by the Secretary B. T. Van Alen,
<date when="1901-03">March, 1901</date>.
<title level="a">A RESOLUTION MADE BY THE HOLLAND SOCIETY OF CHICAGO. p. 69.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Our ancestors in little Holland resisted for eighty years the efforts of Spain to conquer them. By force of arms they pursued that resistance, backed by indomitable Dutch courage and perseverance. It is fitting for us assembled here tonight, as descendants of those Dutchmen, to suitably express in this public manner our sympathy for a people who, today, that same Spain is endeavoring to destroy. I present, Mr. Toastmaster, in response to the sentiment, the following pre-amble and resolutions:</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0078.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Whereas, The chivalry of Spain has written itself in characters of treachery, rapine, fire, and blood into the history of every people and every land where the Spaniard's ruthless arms have penetrated, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, The descendants of the Netherlands have imperishable memories of Alva and the heroes born of the eighty years war, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, The conquest by Spain has been invariably followed by the infamy of mal-administration, and</p>
   <p>Whereas, The savagery of Spain's treatment of Cubans, followed by the destruction of the battle-ship, Maine, and its noble crew while reposing in that friendly harbor, has placed her outside the pale of civilized apology or immunity,</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0079.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Therefore, Be It Resolved, That we, the descendants of the Holland heroes of eighty years war, hereby approve the course of the Government of the United States in declaring that Cuba must be free and that Spanish tyranny and savagery must depart from the Western hemisphere, and,</p>
   <p>Resolved, That we respectfully urge upon President Roosevelt and Congress that no compromise nor delay be permitted to stay the execution of the full measure of the reparation for our sailors slaughtered, and,</p>
   <p>Resolved, That while peace becomes a nation, the war is holy that conquers despotism, so peace may reign.</p>
   <p>That resolution was seconded and, with great enthusiasm, was adopted unanimously.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
