<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-03-04">Mar. 4, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">An Old Noble Family</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0288</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0288.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-03-04">Mar. 4, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">AN OLD NOBLE FAMILY</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Many of our readers will learn with pleasure that Dr. L. J. Heldring, of 1509 North Clark Street, son of Mr. John Heldring, well and favorably known to our countrymen, has fallen heir to one of the oldest noble titles in the Netherlands, namely, that of Baron Fabricius van Henkelam.</p>
   <p>Dr. Heldring inherits this title from his mother, Baroness Johanna Wilhelmina Fabricius van Henkelam, only daughter of Albert C. L. Baron Fabricius and Baroness Wichren van Heemstad, who has assigned to her son all her titles of nobility in order that her name and those of her celebrated ancestors may not sink with her into the grave.</p>
   <p>The family of Fabricius is really one of the oldest and most celebrated in the Netherlands. The line springs from Arent Meindertzoon Fabricius of Haarlem, one of the oldest among the defenders of Ostend in the Spanish siege from 1601 to 1604. After the fall of Ostend Fabricius was honored by the states of <pb facs="5420781_2_0289.jpg" n="2"/>Holland and Belgium with a silver chalice in token of their gratitude for his faithful services.</p>
   <p>Fabricius was born in 1547. In 1583 he was sheriff of Haarlem and filled the judgeship in 1588. After 1595 he became mayor of Haarlem, and from 1604 to 1607, and again from 1618 to 1622, he was a member of the States General of Holland and West Friesland.</p>
   <p>The above-mentioned silver chalice is still in the so-called Fabricius Chamber of the City Hall of Haarlem, where paintings, documents, weapons, and other curiosities of the Fabricius family are also on exhibition. These things were presented to the city of Haarlem by Baron J. C. W. Fabricius in 1883. The cover of the chalice is inlaid with a view of the besieged fortress, showing the position of the batteries, and the camp of the Spaniards.</p>
   <p>As is known, the line of the Heldrings is also one of the oldest Dutch families. We know that Dr. Heldring's father is a son of the famous founder of Heldring's <pb facs="5420781_2_0290.jpg" n="3"/>Institutes, Dr. O. G. Heldring of Zetten. And this Dr. Heldring was the great-grandson of a certain Captain Heldring who as commandant of the royal guards accompanied Prince William the Third on his voyage to England when William became king of England.</p>
   <p>Heldring's Institutes are still the refuge of hundreds of deserted, neglected, or fallen children and women, although their founder died in 1876 and had to leave his field of activity to others.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
