<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1906-04-13">April 13, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Chicago Division of the General Dutch League</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0107</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.B.2.a"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0107.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II B 2 a</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1906-04-13">April 13, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">CHICAGO DIVISION OF THE GENERAL DUTCH LEAGUE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>At the last held executive meeting,of the Chicago division of the General Dutch League, the program was decided upon for the coming meeting Tuesday evening, in the Church of the First Christian Reformed Congregation on 14th Street. Of this meeting you will find an announcement in this number of Onze Toekomst. We can add nothing to this except to state, that everyone who is interested in the well-being of our people, here and in the Netherlands and in all corners of the world, is energetically invited, not to let this opportunity pass by. Let us as Dutchmen support the well-being and prosperity of our people, especially where this is so closely connected with the wellbeing of this land, our newly accepted Fatherland. At this executive meeting it was also decided to establish a respectable Dutch library, the details to be worked out later. This work was started by a gift of $50.00, which was our division's share of a donation to the General Dutch League of $500.00, by H. M. Queen Wilhelmina, for the purpose to spend among the Netherlanders who live abroad, in this case those who live in Chicago. The library will be named "The Queen Wilhelmina Library", in her honor. The adminstration hesitated somewhat to make the above mentioned decision, not knowing whether the attendance would be sufficient to justify the establishment of such a library. We are happy nevertheless that this decision was made, because nothing else could serve better to teach our people Dutch grammar, knowledge and wisdom of all descriptions, as a respectable gathering of Dutch literature.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
