<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1921-02-25">Feb. 25, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">[Dutch Immigrants' Contributions to America]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0259</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.G"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.A.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.J"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0259.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III G</item>
     <item>II A 2</item>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>I C</item>
     <item>I J</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1921-02-25">Feb. 25, 1921</date>.
<title level="a">[DUTCH IMMIGRANTS' CONTRIBUTIONS TO AMERICA]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The Netherlands immigrants contributions to America. For a practical showing we start with the mention of the contributions, which the Netherland element, planted here by immigration, has made to America. The contributions, which The Netherlands, the low land by the North Sea, has made not alone to America but to the entire civilized world are very important and not very easy to understand. The Netherlands of course is one of the first culture lands of the world and has in its glorious history benefitted the entire human race with spritual, educational, political and artistic ideals. So much so, that not any territory no matter in what part of the world, has stayed strange to the Netherlands ' influence. The Netherlands' civilization has made itself felt over the entire world. But the influences of this hotbed of western civilization by the North Sea, the candle of freedom lit by the undaunted culture people of The Netherlands, are naturally not to be made one with the contributions which the sons of these people in foreign lands and especially those made in America.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0260.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The largest contribution to America by the Dutch emigrants, is the true religion planted here, especially The Christian Reformed Church. This spiritual contribution that our Christian people brought here and kept up, is of inestimable value to the spiritual life of America... In the creative contributions of the Dutch emigrants we call attention to the pioneer work in the establishment of Pella and Orange City, Iowa. Holland and Zeeland in Michigan. Roseland and Englewood in Illinois and other later scattered settlements in Iowa, Dakota, Minnesota, Wisconsin and other midwestern states.</p>
   <p>The oyster fishery on the coast of Long Island at Layville was brought over by Zeewish fishers and the American bluepoint was developed by Dutchmen. The diamond cutting and the jewelers trade were in a large measure developed by Amsterdam immigrants. The cigar and tobacco industry in the east in a large measure was developed by Netherlands emigrants. The seed and flowerbulb raising of greatest American dealers and growers are developed by Holland emigrants. In Kalamazoo the celery <gap unit="sheet" extent="1" reason="missing"/></p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
