<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-07-15">July 15, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Excursion to Winnie, Texas</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0067</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.A"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.L"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0067.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
     <item>I L</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-07-15">July 15, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">EXCURSION TO WINNIE, TEXAS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The special excursion of Hollanders to Winnie, Texas, under the conduct of the Theodore F. Roch Land Company, the founders of the Dutch settlement at that place, left Chicago on July 7, as previously announced, and proved a success.</p>
   <p>The excursion consisted principally of Hollanders of Michigan and Wisconsin, although some came from the far West, for instance, from Washington, and met the other excursionists at Winnie. And all who went to Winnie and visited the new Dutch colony of the Theodore F. Roch Land Company were so much pleased with the farms there that they all, to the last man, bought land with the intention of settling there themselves in the near future.</p>
   <p>Thus far about sixty Dutch families have bought land at Winnie, Texas. Already several families have settled on the land, and others are preparing to do so. A Dutch colony will surely be organized as soon as possible. Mr. Theodore F. Roch has already donated fifteen acres of land on which to erect a church and <pb facs="5420781_2_0068.jpg" n="2"/>a clergyman's residence, and he has promised besides a tidy sum of money for the construction of the church.</p>
   <p>All industrious Hollanders who are on the lookout for a good place to settle are welcome at Winnie, Texas. The Dutch settlers have asked the Roch Land Company to organize another excursion, which the Company has promised to do. This special Dutch excursion will leave Chicago on next Tuesday, August 2. If you are interested in a new country and a place in which to settle and better yourself, then go on this excursion.</p>
   <p>The excursion rate is very low.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
