<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-04-30">Apr. 30, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Support a Charter Member Fellow Members of Zelfhulp!</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0046</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.D.1"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0046.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>II D 1</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onzetoekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-04-30">Apr. 30, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">SUPPORT A CHARTER MEMBER Fellow Members of Zelfhulp!</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On the last annual meeting of Zelfhulp in Mandel Hall a discussion was started by Mr. J. Berghuis and Mr. P. Van Wanroy, concerning the support of Mr. R. Stuivenga, the man who organized Zelfhulp. One proposed a donation from the treasury and the other a collection. Nothing became of either proposal and until now I have heard no more of it. Meanwhile the man is in dire need. Now the time has come to do something to keep the wolf from the door.</p>
   <p>He has been helped for two weeks, but that has become now an impossibility for only a couple of members who themselves possess nothing, to continue doing so. When it is discussed at a meeting, one says it is not possible and the other it is against the law. I can not see it. There is so much that is against the law and yet happens.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0047.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Supposing we go to work and give each collector a decent list, and this is presented to the members for a small yearly donation, I must be very much mistaken in our fellow-members, if any one had the heart to say no. I have spoken to our collector about this and he is ready to do this.</p>
   <p>Now something else that amounts practically to the same thing. We have, I believe, a membership of between 10,000 and 12,000 and a capitol of approximately $110,000. Now if every member donates the small sum of 5c a year, would any one ever miss that? That would amount to the sum of five to six hundred dollars. It would be an honor for Zelfhulp and its members and each and every member would be proud to do his bit. We could proclaim this before the world. And the old man in his poor and lonesome home would utter a prayer of thanksgiving and say: I have not organized Zelfhulp in vain.</p>
   <p>And last but not least, while writing this it is Easter, the feast of resurrection and new life. Now if this feast shall be of any value to us, then we must, clasp our hands together and put all doubts aside.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0048.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>For doing well, no one has ever been sorry. Life is so short and we travel together, we must help one another. The great master, whose resurrection is being celebrated by the entire civilized world, went before us and in him and through him unity will be maintained, to you Mr. Editor goes my thanks in advance for the publication of this article.</p>
   <p>Yours very truly,</p>
   <p>W. Beerthuis</p>
   <p>317 Cortland Street,</p>
   <p>Chicago, Illinois.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
