<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-03-02">March 2, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">The Martin Luther Film</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0140</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.E"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.B.2.e"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.E.3"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0140.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III E</item>
     <item>II B 2 e</item>
     <item>II E 3</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-03-02">March 2, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">THE MARTIN LUTHER FILM</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>On Friday, March 4th the "Young men's Society of the First Christian Reformed Church"will present for your approval an eight reel motion picture entitled, "Martin Luther, His Life and Time". A most remarkable picture, showing in detail the life of the great reformer and the age in which he lived. Conditions in the Roman Church during the period of the Reformation are portrayed. The student, Martin Luther, finds the Bible in the library of the University of Erfurt, 1502. Martin Luther vowing to become a monk during a thunderstorm, July 2, 1505. The young monk Luther in the Augustinian Cloister at Erfurt, 1506. Luther's first view of the eternal city as he approached Rome, October, 1511. Luther, nailing the ninety-five thesis upon the door of the Castle Church at Wittenberg, October 31st, 1517. Disputation between Luther and Eck in Leipzig, July 5th, 1519. Luther before Emperor Charles V at the Diet of Worms, on the evening of April 18th, 1521. Luther preaches beneath a linden tree in the village of Mohra on the morning of May 4th, 1521. Luther's marriage with Catharina Von Bora on, June 13th, 1525. These and many other phases of Luthers life are portrayed. Truly this is a picture that must be seen to be appreciated. Don't fail to see it at Orchestra Hall, Friday, 8:15 P M....</p>
   <p>Endorsement of picture by Dr. Clarence Bouma. The committee received the following <pb facs="5420781_2_0141.jpg" n="2"/>letter from Dr. Clarence Bouma dated February 2nd, 1927: "Replying to your recent letter in which you request my endorsemnet, if possible, of your proposed plan to present the film entitled "Martin Luther, his Life and Time" under your own auspices, and for the benefit of the Chicago Christian High School, allow me to say the following. From my lecture on "The Movies" delivered on various occasions you may know, that I am the sworn foe of the corrupting influence exerted by the present - day moving picture theatre. The average moving picture theatre is, in my opinion, a positively demoralizing influence, and ought not to be patronized and supported by Christian people. The art of moto-photography, however, which the moving picture houses are using almost invariably, today for their corrupting and debasing purposes, is in itself an art which, under proper limitation and judicious control, can and ought to be used for the highest educational purposes. Any attempt to produce films, which are truly clean, educational and inspiring, and to present such films under proper auspices to the Christian public, ought to be welcomed and deserves our support. Now without a moment passing upon all its details, I consider the Luther film, produced under Christian auspices in Germany, a splendid help to our Christian public to cultivate love for, and appreciation of, the great work of God accomplished through the heroic reformer of Wittenberg. I heartily endorse your plan to present this film under your own auspices and am convinced you are in this way furnishing clean, instructive and inspiring entertainment to the Christian public, which ought with <pb facs="5420781_2_0142.jpg" n="3"/>increased determination, to turn its back upon the present day moving picture theatre with its worldly, demoralizing influence.</p>
   <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
   <p>Clarence Bouma.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
