<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1926-01-13">January 13, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">Dedication of the Church Building of the Christian Reformed Congregation at 72nd and Peoria Streets, Englewood, Chicago.</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0151</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0151.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1926-01-13">January 13, 1926</date>.
<title level="a">DEDICATION OF THE CHURCH BUILDING OF THE CHRISTIAN REFORMED CONGREGATION AT 72ND AND PEORIA STREETS, ENGLEWOOD, CHICAGO.</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>After the dedication of the church had been postponed several times the building was finally turned over and the dedication ceremonies could proceed. The consistory had prepared a good program for this event. The building was filled to more than its capacity, (not only) on both evenings. An interested crowd listened to the speakers, singers, and so forth. Two of the former pastors of the congregation, Rev. J. R. Brink and Rev. H. J. Kuiper, were present and spoka. The Rev. Brink made a speech on "The Church and Its Vicinity," and the Rev. Kuiper talked on "The Job of the Church." The collection, taken on this occasion, amounted to about $360. Sunday morning and evening the Rev. Tuuk spoke before a large crowd in the new church.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0152.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>It gives a royal impression, and is finished beautifully inside as well as out. Mr. Ecklund, the architect, can be proud of his work. The auditorium has approximately 550 seats and the balcony 170 seats. In the basement is a large hall, library, catechism room, consistory room, kitchen, and so forth. In the tower, on the corner, hangs a bell, a gift of the Men's Society. The floor in the auditorium is covered with carpet donated by the Ladies Society, while the beautiful pulpit furniture was given by the Young Ladies Federation. The entire building is a gain to the community.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
