<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1907-03-01">March 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Annual Celebration "Eendracht Maakt Maght."</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Unity Makes Strength)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0104</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-II.D.10"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-I.G"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0104.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>II D 10</item>
     <item>I G</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1907-03-01">March 1, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">ANNUAL CELEBRATION "EENDRACHT MAAKT MAGHT."</title><title level="a" type="sub">(UNITY MAKES STRENGTH)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>It was on February 3, 13 years ago, that eleven men gathered to discuss the establishment of a society. These eleven men knew what they wanted and their meeting and perseverance was the medium for organizing the society, Emm. In remembrance of this event, Emm held its 13th annual meeting on February 23rd. During its existence, it collected a small contribution of 10 cents per week, the society has accumulated a treasury amounting to over $1,500 at present. It has not only been able to acquire a treasury but has shown itself at all times to be helpful to the membership and also to those Hollanders who were not members and who proved their need. During the Boer war this society, was in the front in supporting the Boers financially in their great struggle with England. That Emm, during all that time has survived and has been successful, is not only proof that it is not composed of disreputable persons, but that it is founded upon good principles, and that the executives and the members know how to cooperate. On the occasion of its 13th anniversary Emm celebrated by having a feast in the beautiful Sibuse Hall on 12th Street last Saturday. This great auditorium was more than filled by the members and those generally interested. This feast was a great success, and the feast-committee has shown that they were fully able to carry out the task assigned to them.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0105.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The orchestra consisted partly of members, and in a short while there is a p possibility that they will have their own orchestra. The feast was very successful and it was proven again that the beautiful saying "Eendracht maakt macht" is not just a hollow sound.</p>
   <p>C. B. Koopseer.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
