<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-10-26">Oct. 26, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">[Immanuel Church]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0136</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.C"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0136.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1927-10-26">Oct. 26, 1927</date>.
<title level="a">[IMMANUEL CHURCH]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>A colorful mixed choir of 50 voices sang for the second time in the Immanuel Church in Roseland, October 20th. This Church in my opinion is one of the simplest and yet the most useful and stately churches in this entire region. It is a "near cross" building with the side walls built high, supplied with three windows in good proportion. Above the entrance is a gallery and the entrance is covered and supplied with two rooms in it's wings. Entering you look from a height down to the speaker's platform, which is so situated that the speaker is visable from the seats, 800 in number, at all times. Behind the platform form is the beautiful organ, which surpasses any other church organ in sweetness of sound and in harmony of tone. The organ was installed by C. Jellema. This organ was masterfully played by the organist of the choir in accompainment to many beautiful songs. The first song; "Joy and Peace shall dwell in Thee" was the outstanding song of the evening. "Ride O King", "I Long to be a Christian" and "Nearer My God to Thee", were almost as beautiful. The solo, duets and quartettes, which were delivered in between, were also extremely good as was"Jerusalem" which was sung by the director of the choir. There was soul, feeling, life and strength in those songs and I am certain that no one in the over crowded church went home dissatisfied. The meeting was led by the Rev. Muelenburg of South Holland, while the Rev. Alshuis of Englewood made the opening prayer, and at closing gave the <pb facs="5420781_2_0137.jpg" n="2"/>blessing. The Rev. Muelenburg opened with a request to sing "Sail On, Sail On" which wonderfully inspiring and touching, flowed through the building from a thousand voices accompained by the powerful organ. Mr. Ettema, son of Mr. and Mrs. C. Ettema, is the organist who leads the song services on Sunday.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
