<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1906-03-23">March 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">Rev. W. Greve</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0310</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-IV"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0310.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>IV</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1906-03-23">March 23, 1906</date>.
<title level="a">REV. W. GREVE</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Monday noon, the last remains of the 70 year old minister, the Rev. William Greve, were entrusted to the earth in Mount Greenwood cemetary. He was known by nearly every Dutchman in Chicago, loved by many, and honored by everyone who knew him. It was a solemn moment. The 74 year old widow was the only one of the relations who was present at the interment. But what the couple missed on blood relations, was well compensated for by the large number of friends they had made. The church of the 71st Street congregation, where the funeral services were held, was filled by those interested in rendering to the Rev. Greve their last respects. The services at the home were led by the Rev. Poppen, one of the most trusted friends of the deceased, and at the church speeches were made in the order given by the Pastors Van Dellen, Breen, Einink, Kuiper and Van Uliet, while at the grave the Rev. Van Dellin leddin prayer. The Rev. Grave was born January 16, 1836, in the county of Bentheim, where his father, Willem Greve, was a gardener. Mr. Greve, the father, was financially able to give his children a good education, and they were taught in a school with the Bible, which at that time in Bentheim was the public school. From his childhood the young William felt a longing to study for the ministry, a longing which resulted in his conversion to God. His conversion and the manner of living he assumed through that, were the cause of his being cast aside by the family. Yes, even despised and banished.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0311.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>Although his father was a religious man, true conversion was for him a strange business. The attempts made by the young man to become a minister were fruitless. This was the reason that he resolved to try his luck in the "New World". He journied to Cincinnati, where he had preached the gospel many tines before private or public gatherings, until, at last, the now deceased Rev. D. J. Van der Werp, provided funds for his education in the ministry. In 1869 he became a preacher. He served the following congregations in order, Chicago, Cincinnati, Passaic, N. J., Borculo, Mich, and Grandville Avenue, Grand Rapids, Mich. In both of the first mentioned congregations he served twice. Later, after a well earned rest, he served the congregation at Hull, Iowa. He was a man who wanted and had to work for, the cause of the gospel. The ministry was his life. This was also the reason he made so many friends. His most beloved place was Chicago. When he obtained his diploma, he first moved to Pella - Iowa, but his longing for Chicago was too great, He sold his possessions in Pella and went to live in this city, in restful Englewood, where he spent his last days. In the last few weeks of his life he suffered greatly from asthma and Brights disease which made an end to his life, may his remains rest in peace.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
