<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1924-02-20">Feb. 20, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[Chicago Knickerbocker Club]</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0085</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.B.2"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0085.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III B 2</item>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1924-02-20">Feb. 20, 1924</date>.
<title level="a">[CHICAGO KNICKERBOCKER CLUB]</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>The recently organized society of Netherlanders, so by descent or by birth, called the Chicago Knickerbocker Club, met last week Thursday, at noon, at a plentifully supplied table at the Illinois Athletic Club, where the members were the guest of F. Posthuma, vice consul of the Netherlands. The host was well satisfied with the attendance, because, as he said, of the twenty-two invited, twenty-three were present. Prof. E. D. Dimment, president of Hope College at Holland, Michigan was present as a guest of honor. Vice Consul Posthuma is thought to have found his number (23) because of the remarks he made after the speech of the guest of honor. After the partaking of the well selected food, the program of activities was handled in a most businesslike way. The new organization shall be known as the _________________________ Chicago Knickerbocker Society. The By-Laws, proposed by a committee, were adopted with few changes.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0086.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>The principles of the society are: The cultivation of mutual pleasure, the immortalization of the folklore, the keeping alive and propagation of the principles and qualities of the Dutch people. Further, the society hopes to give its support to Dutch art and other institutions in Chicago as, for example, the Holland Old People's Home, and so forth. Officers chosen were: President, Gelmer Vuiper; secretary-treasurer, D. J. H. Hospers; delegate-at-large, J. J. Van Pernis. In closing, a speech was made by Consul General John Vennema.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
