<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-09-17">Sept. 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">Union Day at Columbia Park</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Address by Reverend S. S. Vander Heide)</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0224</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.C"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.E"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0224.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III C</item>
     <item>III E</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1909-09-17">Sept. 17, 1909</date>.
<title level="a">UNION DAY AT COLUMBIA PARK</title><title level="a" type="sub">(Address by Reverend S. S. Vander Heide)</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Honorable President, dear friends:</p>
   <p>In order to grow, a society of young men or young women requires co-operation among its members; for a house divided against itself cannot exist. Thus the ideals and the purpose of a society must provide inspiration to all its members. Young men and women who share the same ideals organize a society in order to attain them. This aspiration is responsible for the existence of the reformed boys' and girls' societies. Such societies must necessarily devote themselves to the study of reformed principles. But what are the reformed principles? We can define them as "The thoughts of our God, as revealed in His word." God's word teaches us the meaning of life and how we must always walk in His holy presence. Reformed principles give us thus an appraisal of life and of the world. Reformed principles must gain more and more ground, and for that reason they should be studied and examined. Guided by those <pb facs="5420781_2_0225.jpg" n="2"/>principles our youth will be able to brave the storms of life. We are happy, therefore, to have in our midst a union of reformed boys' societies. I am glad to say a few words about that union. "In union there is strength" says an old Dutch proverb. The reformed families of this community have grasped the importance of this saying and have put it into practice in their own lives. The different societies have banded together in one union of young people, in order to face the difficulties of life together. Such a union, to be profitable, should have frequent meetings. In these meetings the principles common to all should be discussed.</p>
   <p>Young reformed men and women who love and confess the Lord live by the covenant of grace. But this covenant of grace also imposes obligations. He in whom Christ is living must produce fruits. Boys and girls, live up to your vocation, be true to the covenant of your God, even amidst the temptations of life!</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
