<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-05-06">May 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">Roosevelt in Holland</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0285</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.H"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0285.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III H</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1910-05-06">May 6, 1910</date>.
<title level="a">ROOSEVELT IN HOLLAND</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>Ex-President Theodore Roosevelt spent last Sunday in Holland, the home of his ancestors. We have not enough space to describe the visit in detail, but we cannot omit some information regarding that occasion.</p>
   <p>Mr. and Mrs. Roosevelt left Brussels Saturday morning, April 30, at 8 A.M., accompanied by their daughter Ethel and their son Kermit, who made the trip through East Africa with their parents. They took an extra train to Arnhem, and were enthusiastically welcomed by the people at every stop.</p>
   <p>From Arnhem they went by auto to "Het Loo" where the party was welcomed by Prince Hendrick, and later was invited to dinner by the Queen. This was the occasion of Princess Juliana's birthday, and Mr. Roosevelt had already sent her a congratulatory message.</p>
   <p>We cannot fail to observe how ridiculous the American papers sometimes are in reporting such news. Walter Wellman, in a special report to the Record Herald, <pb facs="5420781_2_0286.jpg" n="2"/>calls the palace of the Queen "het Helloo Palace". Mr. Roosevelt spoke in the Dutch Reformed Church, and of this Mr. Wellman writes that Reverend Bosserain welcomed the party, and that Mr. Roosevelt said he was very sorry he could not speak Dutch, but notwithstanding recited a little Dutch poem, the first line of which goes: "Tripput, trapput, trunket". What this means we do not know.</p>
   <p>We could recall other absurd statements. For instance, Wellman calls Baron van Swinderen, Minister of Foreign Affairs, "Minister Schwinderen". But it is better that we simply say that the citizens of Holland have satisfactorily demonstrated that they sincerely appreciated the visit of Mr. Roosevelt and his party.</p>
   <p>Besides "Het Loo" and Amsterdam, Mr. Roosevelt visited The Hague, Delft, Haarlem, and other places. At Haarlem he visited the flower exhibit, in Amsterdam the National Museum, at Delft the grave of William of Orange, and on the way to Scheveningen the "Huis ten Bosch" (House in the Forest), where the first Peace Congress was held.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0287.jpg" n="3"/>
   <p>Monday night, at 9 P.M., the party left Amsterdam for Copenhagen.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
