<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/flps0.2.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1907-09-06">Sept. 6, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">Immigration and Wage Standards</title></bibl>
    </title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois</pubPlace>
    <address>
     <addrLine>60 West Walton</addrLine>
     <addrLine>Chicago, IL 60610</addrLine>
     <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
     <addrLine>http://www.newberry.org</addrLine>
    </address>
    <idno>5420781_2_0071</idno>
   </publicationStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>Transcribed from digital images contributed to the Internet
                    Archive by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl><title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey</title>, <date>1936-1941</date>, 
                    <sponsor>Works Projects Administration</sponsor>, 
                    <sponsor>Chicago Public Library Omnibus Project</sponsor></bibl>
    <bibl>
     <title>Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey [microform]</title>
     <sponsor>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</sponsor>
     <sponsor>Internet Archive</sponsor>
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schema/flpstaxonomy.xml">
    <xi:fallback>Taxonomy file not found.</xi:fallback>
   </xi:include>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <textClass>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch"/>
    <catRef target="#grp-dutch #code-III.A"/>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2009-12-26">Automated conversion to expanded header.</change>
   <change when="2009-12-15">Initial TEI transcription from PanGeo Partners, Inc.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0071.jpg" n="1"/>
   <div type="group">
    <list>
     <item>DUTCH</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="codes">
    <list>
     <item>III A</item>
    </list>
   </div>
   <div type="citation">
    <bibl><title>Onze Toekomst</title>,
<date when="1907-09-06">Sept. 6, 1907</date>.
<title level="a">IMMIGRATION AND WAGE STANDARDS</title></bibl>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <p>One of our newspapers writes in a leading article, that immigration is increasing more than is desirable and warns the American laborer against the danger of lowered wage standards to be brought about through the daily increase of strangers.</p>
   <p>That some uneducated politicians or leaders or labor unions speak in this manner, is understandable, but that a correspondent should hold such an opinion is hardly imaginable.</p>
   <p>What is really the truth?</p>
   <p>In the last couple of years the wage-standard has become higher even after immigration increased. In 1907 more than 1,250,000 strangers settled in the United States of America and at the same time the wage-standard increased more than 10%. Instead of lowering the wage-standard, these hundreds of thousands of immigrants are giving more work to the people.</p>
   <pb facs="5420781_2_0072.jpg" n="2"/>
   <p>These immigrants have to be fed, dressed, and lodged. This all costs money. This money comes into circulation and increases salaries and wage-standards. Besides, America has such rich resources for living, that at present we cannot speak of over population. On the contrary we need European labor to help bring these resources into development.</p>
   <p>According to an official budget our agricultural income for this year totaled six and one-half billions of dollars, and our mines and forests together totaled two billion. Our factories produce an annual income of twelve billion, railroads two billion. The owners of our factories and railroads are paying to their laborers this year the enormous sum of three and one half billion dollars. Briefly, this country is so rich that the influx of immigrants can only cause more progress.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
